<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Extract of a letter from M. Humboldt to M. Blumenbach, containing new Experiments on the Irritation caused by the Metals with respect to their different Impressions on the Organs of Animals</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:42</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">I.48</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1796-Neue_Versuche_ueber-6</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1796-Neue_Versuche_ueber-1.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1796-Neue_Versuche_ueber-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1796-Neue_Versuche_ueber-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1796-Neue_Versuche_ueber-4.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1796-Neue_Versuche_ueber-5.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1796-Neue_Versuche_ueber-6.xml" type="self"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Extract of a letter from M. Humboldt to M. Blumenbach, containing new Experiments on the Irritation caused by the Metals with respect to their different Impressions on the Organs of Animals</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1842</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Annals of Electricity, Magnetism, and Chemistry; and guardian of experimental science&lt;/i&gt; 9:54 (Dezember 1842), S. 522–526.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="522" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Extract of a Letter from</hi> M. <hi rendition="#k">
                        <persName key="humboldt_av"/>Humboldt</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">to</hi> M. <hi rendition="#k">
                        <persName key="blumenbach_jf">Blumenbach</persName>,</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">con-<lb break="no"/>taining new Experiments on the Irritation caused by the Metals<lb break="yes"/>with respect to their different Impressions on the Organs of Animals.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">From <persName key="gren_fag">Gren&#x2019;s</persName> &#x201C;Journal of Natural Philosophy.&#x201D;</note>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. <hi rendition="#k">
                        <persName key="humboldt_av"/>Humboldt</hi> is one of the philosophers who has made the<lb break="yes"/>most numerous observations on the phenomenon discovered by Gal-<lb break="no"/>vani, concerning the irritability produced by the contact of different<lb break="yes"/>metals with the parts of animals in which the principle of life is ap-<lb break="no"/>parently extinguished. As long ago as the year 1795, he observed<lb break="yes"/>that the animal irritability was augmented by the oxygenated muri-<lb break="no"/>atic acid. Not having discontinued his attention to this object, the<lb break="yes"/>perusal of the physiological writings of <persName key="reil_jc">Reil</persName>, and his correspondence<lb break="yes"/>with <persName key="scarpa_a" >Scarpa</persName> and <persName key="volta_agv"/>Volta, afforded him indications for new enquiries,<lb break="yes"/>of which he has occasionally had the courage to make himself the<lb break="yes"/>subject.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In a conversation,&#x201D; says he, &#x201C;with M. <persName key="scarpa_a">Scarpa</persName>, at <placeName key="pavia" >Pavia</placeName>, on the<lb break="yes"/>effects which <persName key="galvani_la">galvani</persName>sm produced upon myself, nothing surprised<lb break="yes"/>him more than the appearance of a lymphatic and serous humour on<lb break="yes"/>my back. &#x2018;What can be the nature,&#x2019; said he, &#x2018;of this stimulant,<lb break="yes"/>which in a few instants changes the nature of the vessels to such a<lb break="yes"/>degree as to cause them to prepare humours, which, the instant they<lb break="yes" />touch <choice>
                        <sic>they</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial"/>
                    </choice> epidermis, excite inflammation, and mark their course<lb break="yes" />by a redness which lasts for whole hours?&#x2019;&#x201D; M. <persName key="humboldt_av"/>Humboldt pro-<lb break="no"/>mised to repeat the experiment; and the account he gives of the<lb break="yes"/>facts constitutes one of the most interesting articles in his letter.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>For this purpose he caused two blistering plasters to be applied<lb break="yes" />on the deltoid muscle of both shoulders. When the left blister was<lb break="yes"/>opened, a liquor flowed out which left no other appearance on the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="523" facs="#f0002"/> skin than a slight varnish, which disappeared by washing. The<lb break="yes"/>wound was afterwards left to dry up: this precaution was necessary,<lb break="yes"/>in order that the acrid humour which the <persName key="galvani_la">galvani</persName>c irritation would<lb break="yes"/>produce might not be attributed to the idiosyncrisis of the vessels.<lb break="yes"/>This painful operation was scarcely commenced on the wound, by<lb break="yes"/>the application of zinc and silver, before the serous humour was<lb break="yes"/>discharged in abundance: its colour became visibly dark in a few<lb break="yes"/>seconds, and left on the parts of the skin where it passed, traces of<lb break="yes"/>a brown inflamed red. This humour having descended towards the<lb break="yes"/>pit of the stomach, and stopped there, caused a redness of more<lb break="yes"/>than an inch in surface. The humour, when traced along the<lb break="yes"/>epidermis, left stains, which after having been washed, appeared of<lb break="yes"/>a blueish red. The inflamed places having been imprudently<lb break="yes"/>washed with cold water, increased so much in colour and extent,<lb break="yes"/>that M. <persName key="humboldt_av"/>Humboldt, as well as his physician Dr. <choice>
                        <sic>Schalleru</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">
                            <persName key="schallern_v">Schallern</persName>
                        </corr>
                    </choice>, who as-<lb break="no"/>sisted at these experiments, entertained some apprehension for the<lb break="yes"/>consequences.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. <persName key="humboldt_av"/>Humboldt has not undertaken to determine the nature of the<lb break="yes"/>fluid which produces such astonishing effects; but he applies him-<lb break="no"/>self to circumscribe the phenomena in the real circumstances which<lb break="yes"/>produce them. He judiciously varies the preparations, and carefully<lb break="yes"/>notes all the results; being persuaded that the cause of <persName key="galvani_la">galvani</persName>sm<lb break="yes"/>cannot be explored with success, but by observing the proportions<lb break="yes"/>in which the chain of metals either irritates or has no effect: and<lb break="yes"/>to extend still more this vast field of observation, he employs various<lb break="yes"/>means to raise or diminish the irritable capacity of the animal<lb break="yes"/>organs.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>What is the sensation which the <persName key="galvani_la">galvani</persName>c irritation produces?<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="humboldt_av"/>Humboldt has discussed this question. &#x201C;No one,&#x201D; says he,<lb break="yes" />&#x201C;can speak more decidedly on this subject than myself, having made<lb break="yes"/>several experiments on my own person, the seat of which, in some<lb break="yes"/>instances, was the socket of a tooth which I had caused to be ex-<lb break="no"/>tracted; in others, certain wounds which I made in my hand; and<lb break="yes"/>in others, the excoriations produced by four blistering plasters.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>The following is his answer:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The <persName key="galvani_la">galvani</persName>c irritation is always painful, and the more so in pro-<lb break="no"/>portion as the irritated part is more injured, and the time of irritation<lb break="yes"/>more prolonged. The first strokes are felt but slightly; the five<lb break="yes"/>or six following are much more sensible, and even scarcely to be<lb break="yes"/>endured, until the irritated nerve becomes insensible from continued<lb break="yes"/>stimulus. The sensation does not at all resemble that which is<lb break="yes"/>caused by the electric commotion and the electric bath; it is a pe-<lb break="no"/>culiar kind of pain, which is neither sharp, pungent, penetrating,<lb break="yes"/>nor by intermissions, like that which is caused by the electric fluid.<lb break="yes" />We may distinguish a violent stroke, a regular pressure, accom-<lb break="no" />panied by an unintermitting glow, which is incomparably more<lb break="yes" />active when the wound is covered with a plate of silver, and irritated<lb break="yes"/>by a rod of zinc, than when the plate of zinc is placed on the wound,<lb break="yes"/>and the silver pincers are used to establish the communication.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="524" facs="#f0003"/>
                <p>When the communication is made by the contact of the epider-<lb break="no"/>mis, it produces no effect; it appears to insulate like glass, when<lb break="yes" />interposed between the wound and the metal; but if the skin be<lb break="yes" />removed, by making two wounds at eight inches distance, and a<lb break="yes" />plate of zinc be placed on one of them, and on the other a leg of a<lb break="yes"/>frog prepared, this last is seen to contract itself when it communi-<lb break="no"/>cates with the zinc by the silver wire, which proves that the gal-<lb break="no"/>vanic fluid there passes beneath the epidermis.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This fluid produced in some circumstances a very sensible acid<lb break="yes" />taste. The two wounds of M. <persName key="humboldt_av"/>Humboldt having been covered, one<lb break="yes"/>with silver, the other with zinc, an iron wire of several feet in<lb break="yes"/>length, attached to the zinc, was conveyed between his upper lip<lb break="yes"/>and the spongy substance of the teeth, and thence to the tongue of<lb break="yes"/>another person. When the iron wire was made to touch the silver,<lb break="yes"/>a strong contraction of the scapular muscle took place, and at the<lb break="yes"/>same instant the person whose tongue formed part of the chain of<lb break="yes"/>communication perceived the sensation of acidity. There are also<lb break="yes"/>cases in which the fluid acts on the organs of taste without pro-<lb break="no"/>ducing any sensible effect on the organs of motion: such is that<lb break="yes"/>where the epidermis serves as the conductor from zinc to the frog;<lb break="yes"/>for there is not then any contraction, but merely an acid taste on<lb break="yes"/>the tongue.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The author, having learned from M. <persName key="volta_agv"/>Volta that he employed the<lb break="yes"/>solution of potash <hi rendition="#i">(oleum tartari per deliquium)</hi>, in order to augment<lb break="yes"/>the conducting power, availed himself successfully of this means<lb break="yes"/>to raise the capacity of the animal organs. He moistened one of<lb break="yes"/>his wounds with this liquor, which produced little pain; but the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="galvani_la">galvani</persName>c irritation was more violent, and accompanied with more<lb break="yes"/>heat; sparks appeared and disappeared before his eyes; the tongue<lb break="yes"/>moistened with the same, distinctly perceived the acid sensation,<lb break="yes"/>although the communication was established only between zinc and<lb break="yes"/>zinc. The thigh of the frog, moistened with the alkaline solution<lb break="yes"/>and laid upon a plate of glass, without touching either metal or car-<lb break="no"/>bonic matter, fell of itself into violent convulsions, the antagonist<lb break="yes"/>muscles of the legs and toes being incessantly agitated. Irritability<lb break="yes"/>has been re-established by this application in the animal parts, where<lb break="yes"/>it had been extinguished by warm solutions of the oxide of arsenic.<lb break="yes"/>Lastly, the irritation (which does not commonly take place when the<lb break="yes"/>nerve and the muscle are armed with the same metal, the different<lb break="yes"/>metals being between the coatings), becomes manifest after this<lb break="yes"/>preparation; which seems to indicate that the alkali not only irri-<lb break="no"/>tates the nerve, but likewise adds to its irritability.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The author applied this method to amphibious animals, which he<lb break="yes" />roused from their winter sleep, and in which he perceived a pecu-<lb break="no"/>liar symptom of irritability.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These observations led him to distinguish two states of the animal<lb break="yes" />organ. The first, of irritability naturally or artificially raised or<lb break="yes"/>excited; the second, irritability in a less degree. These two states,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="525" facs="#f0004"/> which he calls <hi rendition="#i">positive</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">negative</hi>, are merely, as he remarks, dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent degrees, and not phenomena absolutely distinct from each<lb break="yes"/>other.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In individuals naturally sensible, the effects produced by alkaline<lb break="yes"/>solutions, by the oxygenated muriatic acid, by the solution of oxide<lb break="yes"/>of arsenic, are very rarely of the same intensity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the case of increased irritability, muscular motions are observed<lb break="yes"/>without metal or carbonic matter. They may be obtained with<lb break="yes"/>metals, though without communication between the nerve and the<lb break="yes"/>muscle; that is to say, without the regular connection or chain.<lb break="yes"/>They may be also obtained by forming the chain of similar metals.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Let the crural nerve of an animal naturally tenacious of life be<lb break="yes" />placed upon glass. Let a small piece of fresh muscular flesh be<lb break="yes" />fixed on a stick of sealing-wax, and then brought into contact with<lb break="yes"/>the crural muscle. The result will be a violent convulsion at the<lb break="yes"/>instant when the chain of communication is completed. The same<lb break="yes"/>thing happens if, instead of the small piece of muscular flesh, a de-<lb break="no"/>tached piece of the crural nerve be fixed on the stick of sealing-wax.<lb break="yes"/>The connection is therefore formed of two things, nerve and mus-<lb break="no"/>cular fibre. How in this simple case can the fluid which passes from<lb break="yes"/>the nerve into the muscle cause it to be contracted? M. <persName key="humboldt_av"/>Humboldt<lb break="yes"/>thinks that it becomes stimulant, merely because it returns from the<lb break="yes"/>nerve into the nerve by a foreign animal matter; that is to say, not<lb break="yes"/>organically connected with the nerve.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The disparity of the metals forming the chain has hitherto ap-<lb break="no" />peared as a necessary condition to produce <persName key="galvani_la" >galvani</persName>c irritation. This<lb break="yes"/>hypothesis, however, is overturned by the experiments of M. <persName key="humboldt_av"/>Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt. If it be true that, in the state of less irritability, there is<lb break="yes"/>very rarely contraction with similar metals (as <persName key="volta_agv"/>Volta affirms, con-<lb break="no"/>trary to Aldini), this circumstance becomes indifferent in the case of<lb break="yes" />increased irritability. M. <persName key="humboldt_av"/>Humboldt put into a china cup some<lb break="yes"/>mercury exactly purified; he placed the whole near a warm stove,<lb break="yes"/>in order that the entire mass might assume an equal temperature:<lb break="yes"/>the surface was clear, without the appearance of oxidation, humidity,<lb break="yes"/>or dust. A thigh of a frog, prepared in such a manner that a crural<lb break="yes"/>nerve and a bundle of muscular fibres of the same length hung<lb break="yes"/>down separately, was suspended by two silken threads above the<lb break="yes"/>mercury. When the nerve alone touched the surface of the metal,<lb break="yes"/>no irritation was manifested; but as soon as the muscular bundle<lb break="yes"/>and the nerve touched the mercury together, they fell into convul-<lb break="no"/>sions so brisk that the skin was extended as in an attack of tetanus.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We ought not to be surprised at the precaution here taken by M.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="humboldt_av"/>Humboldt to heat the mercury. This is required in consequence of<lb break="yes"/>the opinion which he announces, that the parity of the metals does<lb break="yes"/>not depend on the homogeneity of their chemical constituent parts,<lb break="yes"/>but of their heat, polish, hardness, and force.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Gold, placed between two armatures of zinc, produces irritation<lb break="yes" />only when the gold is moistened by some volatile fluid, or by the<lb break="yes"/>moisture of respiration.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="526" facs="#f0005"/>
                <p>Lastly, M. <persName key="humboldt_av"/>Humboldt has attempted to include all the cases in<lb break="yes"/>the following formula:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>1. In the State of Increased Irritability.</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <list>
                        <item>Positive cases. <list rendition="#leftBraced">
                                <item>Frog&#x2014;muscular flesh.</item>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <item>Frog&#x2014;zinc&#x2014;zinc.</item>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <item>Frog&#x2014;zinc&#x2014;muscular flesh&#x2014;silver.</item>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <item>Frog&#x2014;zinc&#x2014;silver&#x2014;zinc.</item>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <item>Frog&#x2014;muscular flesh&#x2014;silver&#x2014;zinc.</item>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <item>Frog&#x2014;zinc&#x2014;muscular flesh&#x2014;silver&#x2014;muscular<lb break="yes" />flesh&#x2014;zinc.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>2. In the State of Diminished Irritability.</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <list>
                        <item>Positive cases. <list rendition="#leftBraced">
                                <item>Frog&#x2014;zinc&#x2014;silver.</item>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <item>Frog&#x2014;zinc&#x2014;muscular flesh&#x2014;silver&#x2014;zinc.</item>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <item>Frog&#x2014;zinc&#x2014;muscular flesh&#x2014;silver&#x2014;muscular<lb break="yes" />flesh&#x2014;silver&#x2014;zinc.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>Negative cases. <list rendition="#leftBraced">
                                <item>Frog&#x2014;zinc&#x2014;zinc.</item>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <item>Frog&#x2014;zinc&#x2014;muscular flesh&#x2014;silver.</item>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <item>Frog&#x2014;zinc&#x2014;muscular flesh&#x2014;silver&#x2014;zinc.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>M. <persName key="humboldt_av"/>Humboldt finished this letter by some observations which he<lb break="yes"/>has collected in the course of his experiments on the <hi rendition="#i">sthenic</hi> or<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">asthenic</hi> virtue of chemical agents; that is to say, their energy or<lb break="yes"/>their inefficacy to produce irritation. Alkalis appear to be to the sen-<lb break="no"/>sible fibres what acids are to muscular groups. The muriatic acid<lb break="yes"/>augments the irritability of the muscle while it extinguishes that<lb break="yes"/>of the nerves, which does not re-appear even after the acid has been<lb break="yes" />saturated with alkali.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>By continuing to bathe the nerve with an alkaline solution, an<lb break="yes" />entire atony is at length produced by excess of irritation; but if a<lb break="yes"/>few drops of muriatic acid be left on the part, the irritability is re-<lb break="maybe"/>established.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A thigh of a frog, irritated even to total relaxation by a warm<lb break="yes"/>solution of oxide of arsenic, has exhibited new convulsions after<lb break="yes"/>having been immersed for two minutes in a solution of potash.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The sthenic virtue of the oxygenated muriatic acid is not less<lb break="yes" />remarkable. Thighs of frogs naturally flaccid, and weakened still<lb break="yes"/>more by the <persName key="galvani_la">galvani</persName>c process for seven hours, which afforded no<lb break="yes"/>sign of motion when silver served as a conductor between zinc and<lb break="yes"/>the nerve, exhibited violent contractions when the nerve was mois-<lb break="no" />tened with oxygenated muriatic acid. The author refers to this<lb break="yes"/>subject the experiment which he published in 1793, in his <hi rendition="#i">Flora<lb break="yes"/>
                            <placeName key="freiberg"/>Fribergensis</hi>, by which it is ascertained that ordinary muriatic acid<lb break="yes"/>retards the germination of plants, but that oxygenated muriatic acid<lb break="yes"/>had caused a plant to germinate in seven hours, which required<lb break="yes"/>thirty-eight in pure water in order to arrive at the same develop-<lb break="no"/>ment. This fact appears to him to indicate some relation between<lb break="yes"/>the vegetable and animal organization.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 