<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Sketch of a Geological Delineation of South America</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:43</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">II.8</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1801-Esquisse_d_un-4</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1801-Esquisse_d_un-1.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1801-Esquisse_d_un-2.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1801-Esquisse_d_un-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1801-Esquisse_d_un-4.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1801-Esquisse_d_un-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1801-Esquisse_d_un-6.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Sketch of a Geological Delineation of South America</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1804</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Philosophical Magazine&lt;/i&gt; 17:68 (Januar 1804), S. 347–357; 18:69 (Februar 1804), S. 26–36; 18:70 (März 1804), S. 172–179, Tafel.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="347" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Sketch of a Geological Delineation of South Ame-<lb break="no"/>rica. By</hi>
                    <persName key="humboldt_av">F. A. <hi rendition="#k">Von Humboldt</hi>
                    </persName>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">This sketch is an extract from a paper transmitted by M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Von<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt</persName> from <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>, together with a geological collection, to<lb break="yes"/>the directors of the cabinet of natural history at Madrid. It was sent<lb break="yes"/>also by M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Von Humboldt</persName> to <persName key="lametherie_jcd">Delametherie</persName>, and inserted by him in the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Journal de Physique,</hi> vol. 53. p. 30.</note>.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#in">S</hi>ince</hi> I sent to Madrid the two first sketches of a geolo-<lb break="no"/>gical delineation of <placeName key="suedamerika" >South America</placeName>, from the Caraccas and<lb break="yes"/>Nueva Valencia, I have travelled 1200 miles, and described<lb break="yes"/>a square between Caribe, Portocabello, Pimichin, and Es-<lb break="no"/>meralda, a space comprehending above 59000 square miles,<lb break="yes"/>for I am not acquainted with the land between the moun-<lb break="no"/>tain Parea and Portocabello, and between the northern<lb break="yes"/>coast and the valley of the Black river. In consequence of<lb break="yes"/>the great circumference of this district, I must content my-<lb break="no"/>self with delineating it in a general manner, and to avoid<lb break="yes"/>details, with describing the construction of the earth, the<lb break="yes"/>declivity of the land, the direction and inclination of the<lb break="yes"/>mountains, their relative ages, their similarity with the<lb break="yes"/>formation of those in Europe. These are the circumstances<lb break="yes"/>most necessary to be known in this science. We must<lb break="yes"/>proceed in mineralogy as in geography; we are acquainted<lb break="yes"/>with stones, but not with mountains; we know the mate-<lb break="no"/>rials, but we are ignorant of the whole of which they form<lb break="yes"/>component parts. I wish I may be able, amidst the variety<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">of</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="348" facs="#f0002"/> of the objects which occupy my attention during my tra-<lb break="no"/>vels, to throw any light on the structure of the earth.<lb break="yes"/>The laborious journeys which, for eight years, I have made<lb break="yes"/>through Europe, had no other object; and if I have the<lb break="yes"/>good fortune to return to Europe, and to recover my geo-<lb break="no"/>logical manuscripts which I left behind me in France and<lb break="yes"/>Germany, I shall venture to give a sketch of the structure<lb break="yes"/>of the earth. What I have long said, that the direction<lb break="yes"/>and inclination, the rising and falling of the primitive<lb break="yes"/>strata, the angles which they form, with the meridian of<lb break="yes"/>the place, and with the axis of the earth, are independent<lb break="yes"/>of the direction and depression of the mountains; that they<lb break="yes"/>depend on laws, and that they observe a general parallelism<lb break="yes"/>which can be founded only in the motion and rotation of<lb break="yes"/>the earth. What <persName key="freiesleben_jc" >Freiesleben</persName>, <persName key="buch_lv">Von Buch</persName> and <persName key="gruner_01">Gruner</persName> have<lb break="yes"/>proved better than I will be found confirmed, namely, that<lb break="yes"/>the succession of the alluvial strata, which was considered<lb break="yes"/>as a peculiarity of certain provinces, such as Thuringia and<lb break="yes" />Derbyshire, takes place generally, and that there appears<lb break="yes"/>an identity in the order of the strata (see Plate IX.); from<lb break="yes"/>which there is reason to conclude that the same deposition<lb break="yes"/>has been effected at the same time over the whole surface of<lb break="yes"/>the earth. All these ideas are of the greatest importance,<lb break="yes"/>not only to the philosopher, who endeavours to elevate<lb break="yes"/>himself to general principles, but also to the miner, who<lb break="yes"/>must conceive in his mind what he has not before his eyes,<lb break="yes"/>and guide himself by analogy deduced from actual ex-<lb break="no"/>perience.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Before I describe the situation of the mountains which I<lb break="yes"/>have observed from the coast to the province of Venezuela,<lb break="yes"/>I shall give a general view of the form of this continent.<lb break="yes"/>Unfortunately there are no early observations to serve as a<lb break="yes"/>ground for this description. For half a century past many<lb break="yes"/>accidental observations respecting this land have been col-<lb break="no"/>lected, but not a single idea relating to its geology has been<lb break="yes"/>made known. The great genius of <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condamine</persName>, the zeal<lb break="yes"/>of Don <persName key="juanysantacilia_j">George Juan de Ulloa</persName>, would certainly not have<lb break="yes"/>left us in the dark on this subject, had mineralogy been<lb break="yes"/>more cultivated at the time when they wrote. All that<lb break="yes"/>could then be done was to measure and to take levels. As<lb break="yes"/>they were employed on the high cordillera of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>,<lb break="yes"/>which extends north and south from Zitara, as far as Cape<lb break="yes"/>Pilar, and beheld with wonder the immense height of the<lb break="yes"/>mountains, they forgot that <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName> exhibits other<lb break="yes"/>cordilleras, which extend east and west parallel to the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="aequator">equator</placeName>, and which, on account of their height, deserve as<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">much</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="349" facs="#f0003"/> much the attention of naturalists as the Carpathians, Cau-<lb break="no"/>casus, the <placeName key="walliseralpen">Alps of the Valais</placeName>, and the Pyrenees. The<lb break="yes"/>whole immense tract on the west side of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>, which<lb break="yes"/>extends obliquely to the coast of Guiana and Brasil, is de-<lb break="no"/>scribed as a low plain, exposed to the inundation of the<lb break="yes"/>rivers. As only a few <persName key="franzvonassisi" >Franciscan</persName> missionaries and a few<lb break="yes"/>soldiers have been able to penetrate over the cataracts to<lb break="yes"/>Rio Negro, the inhabitants of the coast of Caracas ima-<lb break="no"/>gine that the immense plains (the Llanos de Calabozo, del<lb break="yes"/>Guarico, and de <placeName key="apure">Apure</placeName>) which they see to the south, be-<lb break="no"/>yond the valleys of <placeName key="aragua">Aragua</placeName>, extend without interruption to<lb break="yes"/>the Pampas of Buenos-Ayres, and to the country of the<lb break="yes"/>Patagonians; but the extent of these plains is far from<lb break="yes"/>being so great; they are not uninterrupted plains, they are<lb break="yes"/>rather phenomena of the same kind as those presented by<lb break="yes"/>Canada and Yucatan, the Island of St. Domingo, the north<lb break="yes"/>of Sierra de St. Martha, <placeName key="barcelona" >the province of Barcelona</placeName>, and the<lb break="yes"/>land between Monte-Video and Mendoza, New Holland,<lb break="yes"/>the eastern part of Hungary, and the country of Hanover.<lb break="yes"/>They are separated from each other by the cordilleras, and<lb break="yes"/>are as far from lying in the same plane as the <choice>
                        <sic>desarts</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">deserts</corr>
                    </choice> of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="afrika">Africa</placeName>, and the steppes of Tartary, which rise by grada-<lb break="no"/>tions, according to the distance from the sea coast.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When one considers the irruptions which the North Sea,<lb break="yes"/>the Mediterranean, &amp;c. have made into the old world, the<lb break="yes" />direction of its cordilleras appears not to be very different<lb break="yes" />from that of those in the <placeName key="amerika">new world</placeName>, as most naturalists<lb break="yes"/>have asserted. We are acquainted also with the traces of<lb break="yes"/>several high chains of mountains which extend from north<lb break="yes"/>to south, and run out from those which extend east and<lb break="yes"/>west. The garnet and micaceous schistus of Norway,<lb break="yes"/>Scotland, Wales, Brittany, the province of Gallicia, Alem-<lb break="no"/>tego, Cape Bogador, (I have found the same with granite<lb break="yes"/>on Teneriff,) the upper part of Guinea, Congo, and the<lb break="yes"/>Table Mountain, as also the original mountains of Oren-<lb break="no"/>burg, Caucasus, Lebanon, of <placeName key="abessinien" >Abyssinia</placeName> and Madagascar,<lb break="yes"/>seem at first to have formed nothing else than two large<lb break="yes"/>cordilleras parallel to the meridian.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the <placeName key="amerika">new world</placeName> these cordilleras run parallel to the<lb break="yes"/>meridian from Cape Pilar to the north of California beyond<lb break="yes"/>Nootka and Prince William&#x2019;s sound towards the <placeName key="allegheny">Aleganhey<lb break="yes" />mountains</placeName>, which were discovered in 1792 by Mr. <persName key="stewart_01">Stewart</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>on his journey to the sources of the Missoury, the northern<lb break="yes"/>part of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>, which is inhabited by Indians nearly as<lb break="yes"/>much civilized as the Peruvians were fifteen hundred years<lb break="yes"/>ago. From this cordillera proceed ramifications of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">original</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="350" facs="#f0004"/> original mountains which extend from west to east. With<lb break="yes"/>those of <placeName key="nordamerika">North America</placeName> I am not acquainted, but it appears<lb break="yes"/>that some exist in Canada under the latitude of 50° and<lb break="yes"/>42° north latitude, as in the destroyed continent of the<lb break="yes"/>Gulph of Mexico under 19° and 22°, as is proved by the<lb break="yes"/>mountains of Cuba and Saint Domingo. In South Ame-<lb break="no"/>rica there are three chains of original mountains which run<lb break="yes"/>parallel to the <placeName key="aequator">equator</placeName>: the chain of the coast under 9° and<lb break="yes"/>10°; that chain which is in the great cataracts of Autures<lb break="yes"/>(in latitude 5° 39&#x2032;) is between latitude 3° and 7°; and that<lb break="yes"/>in Maipure in 5° 12&#x2032; 50&#x2033;, which I therefore call the chain<lb break="yes"/>of the cataracts or that of Parime, and the chain of Che-<lb break="no"/>quitos under 15° and 20° south latitude.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These chains in the old continent on this side of the<lb break="yes"/>western ocean can be traced, and it is seen how the original<lb break="yes"/>mountains of Fernambouc, Minas, La Bahia, and Janeiro,<lb break="yes"/>correspond, under the same latitude, to those of Congo, as<lb break="yes"/>the immense <placeName key="amazonasregion">plains near the river Amazon</placeName> lie opposite to<lb break="yes"/>the plains of Lower Guinea, the cordillera of the cataracts<lb break="yes"/>opposite to those of Upper Guinea, and the Llanos of the<lb break="yes"/>Mississippi, since the irruption of the Gulph of Mexico, a<lb break="yes"/>property of the sea, opposite to the Desart of Serah. This<lb break="yes"/>view will appear to be less hazarded when one reflects in<lb break="yes"/>what manner the old continent has been separated from the<lb break="yes"/>new one by the force of the water. The form of the coasts,<lb break="yes"/>and the salient and re-entering angles of <placeName key="amerika">America</placeName>, <placeName key="afrika" >Africa</placeName>,<lb break="yes"/>and Europe, are a sufficient proof of this catastrophe. What<lb break="yes"/>we call the <placeName key="atlantik" >Atlantic ocean</placeName> is nothing else than a valley<lb break="yes" />scooped out by the sea. The pyramidal form of all the<lb break="yes" />continents with their summits turned southwards, the great<lb break="yes" />flattening of the earth at the south pole, and other ph&#x00E6;no-<lb break="no"/>mena, observed by Dr. <persName key="forster_jr" >Forster</persName>, seem to show that the in-<lb break="no"/>flux of the water was from the south. On the coast of<lb break="yes"/>Brasil, from Rio Janiero to Fernambouc, it found resist-<lb break="no"/>ance, and taking a direction from the latitude of 50° north<lb break="yes"/>towards the north-east, where it scooped out the Gulf of<lb break="yes"/>Guinea near Loango<choice>
                        <sic/>
                        <corr type="editorial">,</corr>
                    </choice>
                    <placeName key="benin">Benin</placeName> and Minc, it was obliged by<lb break="yes"/>the mountains of Upper Guinea to direct itself north-west,<lb break="yes"/>and separated, to the latitude of 23° north, the coast of Gui-<lb break="no"/>nea from Mexico and Florida. The force of the waters was<lb break="yes"/>still broken by the cordillera of the United States of Ame-<lb break="no"/>rica, and once more turned towards the north-east, and<lb break="yes"/>seems to have spared less the western coast of Europe than<lb break="yes"/>the northern of <placeName key="amerika" >America</placeName>. The least breadth of this channel<lb break="yes"/>is at the Brasils and Greenland; but, agreeably to the geo-<lb break="no" />graphical history of plants and animals, it seems to have<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">been</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="351" facs="#f0005"/> been formed at a time when the organic creation had not<lb break="yes"/>been properly expanded. It would be of great importance<lb break="yes"/>to geology if a sea voyage were undertaken, at the expense<lb break="yes"/>of some government, to examine the rising and depression<lb break="yes"/>and the relative situation of the mountains to the salient<lb break="yes"/>and re-entering angles of <placeName key="amerika" >America</placeName> and <placeName key="afrika">Africa</placeName>. The same<lb break="yes"/>analogy would be found here as is observed in the English<lb break="yes"/>Channel, in the Sound, the Straits of Gibraltar, and the<lb break="yes"/>Hellespont; small creeks which are as new as the secondary<lb break="yes"/>formation of the chalk rocks of Jura, of Pappenheim, La<lb break="yes"/>Mancha, Marseilles, Derbyshire, and Suez, which have all<lb break="yes"/>been produced at the same time by precipitation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Of the three cordilleras of primitive mountains which<lb break="yes"/>traverse <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName> from west to east, the most north-<lb break="no"/>ern, that of Venezuela, is the highest, but the narrowest.<lb break="yes"/>The real chain of the <placeName key="anden" >Andes</placeName> extends from the large plain<lb break="yes"/>of Quito, through Popayan and Choco, to the western side<lb break="yes"/>of the river <placeName key="atrato">Atrato</placeName> (or Rio San Juan), between the valley<lb break="yes"/>of Tatabé, in the provinces of Zitara and Biruguete, to-<lb break="no"/>wards the isthmus, where it forms a mountainous district<lb break="yes"/>of not more than two or three hundred toises in height on<lb break="yes"/>the bank of the Chagre. From these <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> arises the cor-<lb break="no"/>dillera on the coast of Venezuela. Rows of mountains<lb break="yes"/>higher, but forming groups less regular, extend on the<lb break="yes"/>east side of the <placeName key="atrato">Rio Atrato</placeName> under the name of the Sierra de<lb break="yes"/>Abibé and the Montes de Cauca, through the high savan-<lb break="no"/>nahs of Jolu towards Magdalen river and the province of<lb break="yes"/>St. Martha. The cordillera of the coast contracts itself like<lb break="yes"/>that of the Gulph of Mexico, approaches nearer to Cape<lb break="yes"/>Vela, and then proceeds first from south-south-west to<lb break="yes"/>north-north-east, and then from west to east to the ridge<lb break="yes"/>of Paria, or rather to the Punta de la Galera in the Island<lb break="yes"/>of Trinidad. Its greatest height is found at that place<lb break="yes"/>where it has the name of Sierra de Nevada de St. Martha in<lb break="yes"/>latitude 10° 2&#x2032;, and of Sierra Nevada de Merida in latitude<lb break="yes"/>8° 30&#x2032;; the former is about 5000 the latter 5400 Spanish<lb break="yes"/>ells (<hi rendition="#i">varas</hi>), or 2350 toises in height. The Paramo de la<lb break="yes"/>Rosa and de Macuchi, and also the mountain of Merida,<lb break="yes"/>are continually covered with snow: boiling water (with<lb break="yes"/>hydrogenated sulphur) issues from their sides, and they<lb break="yes"/>exceed in height the Peak of Teneriff, and are, perhaps,<lb break="yes"/>equal to Mont Blanc, which has been more accurately mea-<lb break="no"/>sured. These colossal masses and St. Martha stand almost<lb break="yes"/>insulated, being surrounded by few high ridges. To the<lb break="yes"/>west of Santa Fé, or as far as the Sierra of Zuindiu, no<lb break="yes"/>snow-clad peaks are seen, and the Sierra Nevada de Merida<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">stands</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="352" facs="#f0006"/> stands at the edge of the plain of Caracas, which is scarcely<lb break="yes"/>forty toises above the level of the sea. Mont Blanc, which<lb break="yes"/>terminates the high ridge of the <placeName key="alpen">Alps</placeName>, exhibits the same<lb break="yes" />ph&#x00E6;nomenon. The altitude of the highest mountains,<lb break="yes" />however, is so very small in proportion to the magnitude<lb break="yes"/>of the earth that it would appear that very small local causes<lb break="yes" />ought to have accumulated more matter in these points.<lb break="yes"/>That part of the cordillera of the coast which lies to the<lb break="yes"/>west of Maracaybo-Sees, and joins the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>, has large<lb break="yes"/>valleys extending from north to south, such as that of Mag-<lb break="no"/>dalena, of Cauca, of Saint George, of Sinu, and <placeName key="atrato">Atrato</placeName>.<lb break="yes"/>They are very long and narrow, but covered with wood.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On the other hand, that part of the cordillera which ex-<lb break="no"/>tends from Merida to Trinidad incloses three valleys lying<lb break="yes"/>east and west, which show by certain signs, like Bohemia,<lb break="yes"/>or the Haslithal of Swisserland, that they have formerly<lb break="yes"/>been lakes the water of which has evaporated or run off by<lb break="yes"/>opening for itself a passage. These three valleys are in-<lb break="no"/>closed by the two parallel rows of mountains into which<lb break="yes"/>the cordillera of the coast divides itself, from Cape Vela to<lb break="yes"/>Cape Codera; the northern row is a continuation of Saint<lb break="yes"/>Martha, the southern a prolongation of Sierra Nevada de<lb break="yes"/>Merida. The first extends through Burburuta, Rincon del<lb break="yes"/>Diablo; through the Sierras de Mariara, the mountain<lb break="yes"/>Aguasnegras, Monte de Arila, and the Silla de Caracas, to<lb break="yes"/>Cape Codera. The second from three to four miles more<lb break="yes"/>to the south extends through Guigui, La Palma, the high<lb break="yes"/>summits of Guairaima, Tiara, Guiripa, and the Savana de<lb break="yes"/>Ocumare, as far as the mouths of the Tuy. These two<lb break="yes"/>chains unite with two arms which run from north to south,<lb break="yes"/>like, as it were, dykes, by which these old lakes were con-<lb break="no"/>fined within their boundaries. These dykes are, on the west<lb break="yes"/>the mountains of Carora, <choice>
                        <sic>Tonto</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Torito</corr>
                    </choice>, Saint Maria, Saint Phi-<lb break="no"/>lips, and <placeName key="aroa">Aroa</placeName>; they separate the Llanos de Monai from<lb break="yes"/>the valleys of <placeName key="aragua">Aragua</placeName>: on the east they are the naked sum-<lb break="no"/>mits of Los Teques, Coquiza, Buena Vista, and <placeName key="altosdespedro">the Altos<lb break="yes"/>de S. Pedro</placeName>, by which the valley of <placeName key="aragua" >Aragua</placeName> or the sources<lb break="yes"/>of the Tuy (for there is only one valley between the bottom<lb break="yes"/>of Coquiza or the Hacienda de Brisenno to Valencia) from<lb break="yes"/>the valley of Caracas. On the east from Cape Codera the<lb break="yes"/>greater part of the cordillera of the coast of Venezuela was<lb break="yes"/>destroyed and laid under water by the great catastrophe<lb break="yes"/>which formed the Gulph of Mexico. The rest of it is di-<lb break="no"/>stinguished in the high mountain peaks of the Island of<lb break="yes"/>Margaretha (Macanao and the Valle S. Juan) and in the<lb break="yes"/>cordillera of the Isthmus of <placeName key="araya" >Araya</placeName>, which contains the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">micaceous</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="353" facs="#f0007"/> micaceous schistous mountains of Maniguares, Chuparipari,<lb break="yes"/>Distilador, Cerro-Grande, the mountain of St. Joseph and of<lb break="yes"/>Paria: the remainder I have accurately examined, and found<lb break="yes"/>in them the same structure, the same direction, and the same<lb break="yes"/>inclination of the strata. The three hollows, or valleys of<lb break="yes"/>Caracas, <placeName key="aragua">Aragua</placeName>, and Monai, are remarkable on this ac-<lb break="no"/>count, that the level of them is above the surface of the<lb break="yes"/>sea; they become lower by gradations, and the highest step<lb break="yes"/>is the eastern, which may serve as a proof that they were<lb break="yes"/>formed at an earlier period than the Llanos, whose decli-<lb break="no"/>vity proceeds from east to west, like the whole continent<lb break="yes"/>of <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>. By repeated barometric measurement<lb break="yes"/>I found the height of the valleys of Caracas to be 416<lb break="yes"/>toises, of <placeName key="aragua">Aragua</placeName> 212 toises, above the surface of the sea;<lb break="yes"/>the Llanos of Monai, the western bason, appears to have<lb break="yes"/>an elevation of no more than 80 or 100 toises. The valley<lb break="yes"/>of Caracas has once been a lake, which formed for itself<lb break="yes"/>an efflux through the Quebrada de Tipe, Catia, and Rio<lb break="yes"/>Mamon; the bason of <placeName key="aragua" >Aragua</placeName> appears, on the other hand,<lb break="yes"/>to have become dry by gradual evaporation; for the remains<lb break="yes"/>of the old water (loaded with muriate of lime) are still seen<lb break="yes"/>in the lake of Valencia, which becomes less every year, and<lb break="yes"/>discovers islands which are known under the name of Apa-<lb break="no"/>recidas. The height of the cordillera of the coast is com-<lb break="no"/>monly from 600 to 800 toises; the highest peaks, Sierra<lb break="yes"/>de Nevada de Merida and the Silla de Caracas, (to which<lb break="yes"/>we undertook a laborious journey with our instruments)<lb break="yes"/>are 2350 and 1316 toises in height. To the west they al-<lb break="no"/>ways become lower, and the height of Cape Codera is only<lb break="yes"/>176 toises. The Macanao, on the island Margaretha,<lb break="yes"/>which I measured trigonometrically, is not more in height<lb break="yes"/>than 342 toises; but this speedy depression takes place only<lb break="yes"/>in the primitive mountains of the cordillera. On the<lb break="yes"/>eastern coast secondary accumulations of lime rise from<lb break="yes"/>Cape Unare to a more considerable height than the gneis<lb break="yes"/>and micaceous schistus; these calcareous rocks, which are<lb break="yes"/>covered with sandstone of a calcareous base, and which<lb break="yes"/>accompany the cordillera of the coast in its southern decli-<lb break="no"/>vity, are very low on the side towards Cura, but rise in a<lb break="yes"/>mass towards the eastern extremity of the continent.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In Bergantin they are 702 toises high, in Coccollard 392,<lb break="yes"/>in Cucurucho du Tuminiquiri (the highest summits of the<lb break="yes"/>province of Cumana) 976 toises, and the pyramid of the<lb break="yes"/>Guacharo rises above 820 toises: from Cape Unare they<lb break="yes"/>form a separate ridge of mountains, in which the original<lb break="yes"/>ridge totally disappears; they are connected also with the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">micaceous</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="354" facs="#f0008"/> micaceous schistous cordillera of Maniquare and Paria only<lb break="yes"/>by the Cerro de Meapire, which, analogous to the branches<lb break="yes"/>of Torito and los Teques, which separate the basons of<lb break="yes"/>Monai, <placeName key="aragua">Aragua</placeName>, and Caracas, extends north and south<lb break="yes"/>from Guacharo and Catouaro, to the mountain Paria, and<lb break="yes"/>separates the valley of Cariaco (the dried up bank of the<lb break="yes"/>Gulph of Cariaco) from the valley of St. Boniface, which<lb break="yes"/>formerly belonged to the Golfo Triste. It will be seen<lb break="yes"/>hereafter, that the accumulation of calcareous formation<lb break="yes"/>on the eastern part of the coast of this country seems to<lb break="yes"/>have been more exposed to earthquakes; and that the Cerro<lb break="yes"/>de Meapire, at the time of the irruption of the Gulph of<lb break="yes"/>Cariaco, and the Golfo Triste, prevented the water from<lb break="yes"/>converting the land of <placeName key="araya" >Araya</placeName> and the ridge of Paria into an<lb break="yes" />island.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The declivity of the cordillera of the coast of Venezuela<lb break="yes"/>is gentler towards the south than towards the north, which<lb break="yes"/>is particularly striking when one descends from the heights<lb break="yes"/>of Guigue, through St. Juan, Parapara, and Ortiz towards<lb break="yes"/>the Mera de Paja, which belongs to the great Llano de<lb break="yes"/>Calabozo. The northern declivity is every where very<lb break="yes"/>steep, and there is scarcely found, Mont Blanc excepted,<lb break="yes"/>above Courmayeur, a more frighful precipice than the per-<lb break="no"/>pendicular wall of Silla de Caracas, beyond Caravalledo,<lb break="yes"/>which rises to the height of 1300 toises. An accurate mea-<lb break="no"/>surement of this wall of rock was of great importance to<lb break="yes"/>navigators, as they could find its distance from the coast<lb break="yes"/>only by taking the angle of its elevation: its longitude,<lb break="yes"/>therefore, of 60° 37&#x2032; 32&#x2033; west from Paris, will enable them<lb break="yes"/>to discover it.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The phenomenon of a more gentle declivity towards the<lb break="yes"/>south seems to contradict the observations made in other<lb break="yes"/>cordilleras of the earth, as it is asserted that they all decline<lb break="yes"/>more abruptly towards the south and west. This contra-<lb break="no"/>diction, however, is only apparent as the northern part of<lb break="yes"/>the cordillera, during the great catastrophe which produced<lb break="yes"/>the Gulph of Mexico, was torn away by the force of the<lb break="yes"/>water; and therefore the northern declivity might at that<lb break="yes"/>time be gentler than the southern.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If the form of the coast be considered, it appears to be<lb break="yes"/>pretty regularly indented. The headlands of Tres Puntas,<lb break="yes"/>Codera, S. Roman, and Chichibacoa, on the west, from<lb break="yes"/>Cabo de la Vela, form a row of promontories, the western<lb break="yes"/>of which runs more to the north than the eastern. To the<lb break="yes"/>windward of each of these capes a creek has been formed;<lb break="yes"/>and one cannot help seeing, in this singular formation, the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">action</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="355" facs="#f0009"/> action of the tropical currents, which may be called the<lb break="yes"/>currents of the earth&#x2019;s rotation; an action which shows it-<lb break="no"/>self also in the direction of the coast from Cuba, St. Do-<lb break="no"/>mingo, Porto Rico, Yucatan, and Honduras, as in the se-<lb break="no"/>ries of the windward islands Grenada, Orchila, Rocca, <placeName key="aves">Aves</placeName>,<lb break="yes"/>Buenos-Ayres, Cura&#x00E7;oa, and <placeName key="aroma">Aruba</placeName>, the ruins of the cor-<lb break="no"/>dillera from Cape Chichibacoa, which are all parallel to<lb break="yes"/>the <placeName key="aequator">equator</placeName>. It was this headland of Chichibacoa, not-<lb break="no"/>withstanding its inconsiderable height, which by its resist-<lb break="no"/>ance to the influx, preserved the kingdom of New Grenada<lb break="yes"/>from losing so much land as the general government of<lb break="yes"/>Caracas.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The second original cordillera of <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>, which<lb break="yes"/>I have called the cordillera of the Cataracts of Orinoco, is<lb break="yes"/>yet very little known. During the journey which we made<lb break="yes"/>on the Black River, to the borders of <placeName key="bara">the Great Bara</placeName>, we<lb break="yes" />travelled more than 200 leagues, first from north to south,<lb break="yes" />from Cerro de Uruana to <placeName key="atabapo">Atabapo</placeName> and Tuamini; then from<lb break="yes"/>west to east, from the mouths of the Ventuari to Vulcan<lb break="yes"/>de Duida, which I have found to be in latitude 3° 13&#x2032; 26&#x2033;,<lb break="yes"/>and longitude 60° 34&#x2032; 7&#x2033; west from Paris. Since the jour-<lb break="no"/>ney of Messrs. <persName key="jturiaga_01">Ituriaga</persName> and <persName key="solanoybote_j" >Solano</persName>, a passage over these<lb break="yes"/>cordilleras, which may be called also Parima or Dorado<lb break="yes"/>(golden), a name which has occasioned so much misfortune<lb break="yes"/>in <placeName key="amerika" >America</placeName>, and so much ridicule in Europe, has been pos-<lb break="no"/>sible; but as all the European settlements on the <placeName key="altoorinoco">Alto<lb break="yes"/>Orinoco</placeName>, and the Rio Negro (Black River), contain at<lb break="yes"/>this time no more than 400 Indian families, and as the<lb break="yes"/>way from Esmeralde to Erevato and Caura has been totally<lb break="yes"/>lost, our researches in a land so little civilized, presented<lb break="yes"/>more difficulties than <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condamine</persName> experienced during his<lb break="yes"/>tedious navigation on the <placeName key="amazonas">river Amazon</placeName>, the banks of which<lb break="yes"/>for many years have been inhabited.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The cordillera of the Cataracts or of Parima separates<lb break="yes"/>itself from the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> of Quito and Popayan, in the longi-<lb break="no"/>tude of from 3° to 6°. It extends from west to east from<lb break="yes"/>Paramo de Tuquillo and St. Martin, or the sources of the<lb break="yes"/>Guaviare, the theatre of the gallant deeds of Philip de Urre,<lb break="yes"/>and the old residence of the Orneguas, through Morocote,<lb break="yes"/>Piramena, and Macuco, stretching through the country of<lb break="yes"/>the Indians of Guajibos, Sagi, Dagueres, and Poigraves,<lb break="yes"/>according to the direction of the great rivers Meta, Vichada,<lb break="yes"/>Zama, Guaviare, and Ymerida, in the longitude of 70° west<lb break="yes"/>from Paris, between the high summits of Uniama and Cu-<lb break="no"/>navami. They form the Raudals of <placeName key="atures" >Atures</placeName> and Maypuré,<lb break="yes"/>tremendous waterfalls, which afford the only passage by<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">which</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="356" facs="#f0010"/> which one can penetrate into the interior of the land in the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="amazonasregion">valley of the River Amazons</placeName>.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These cordilleras of the Cataracts rise from the longitude<lb break="yes"/>of 70°, and spread out in such a manner that they compre-<lb break="no"/>hend the whole immense tract of country between the rivers<lb break="yes"/>Caura, Erevato, Cavony, Paraguamusi, Ventuari, Jao, Pa-<lb break="no"/>damo, and Manariche, and then ascend south towards the<lb break="yes"/>sources of the Pasimona, Cachevayneris, and Cababury,<lb break="yes"/>towards the forests, where the Portugueze, penetrating into<lb break="yes"/>the Spanish district, collect the best sarsaparilla known<lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">Smilax Sarsaparilla,</hi>
                    <persName key="linne_cv">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Linn.</hi>
                    </persName>). In this district the cordilleras<lb break="yes"/>of the Cataracts are above 120 miles in breadth. Their<lb break="yes"/>continuation more towards the east, between the longitude<lb break="yes"/>of 68° and 60° west from Paris is little known. I pro-<lb break="no"/>ceeded with astronomical instruments only, as far as Rio<lb break="yes"/>Guapo, which discharges itself into the Orinoco, opposite<lb break="yes"/>the Cerro de la Cauclilla, in longitude 68° 33&#x2032; west from<lb break="yes"/>Paris. The Indians of Catarapeni and Maquiritares, who<lb break="yes"/>reside in the small mission of Esmeralde came fifteen miles<lb break="yes"/>further east over the mountains Guanaja and Yamariquin<lb break="yes"/>to the Canno Chiguire; but neither the Europeans, nor In-<lb break="no"/>dians with whom Europeans have had any intercourse, are<lb break="yes"/>acquainted with this source of the Orinoco, which is here<lb break="yes"/>called Canno Paragua, and is scarcely 150 or 200 toises in<lb break="yes"/>breadth, whereas at <placeName key="bocadeapure">Boca de Apuré</placeName>, in latitude 7° 32&#x2032; 20&#x2033;,<lb break="yes"/>it is 4632 toises, as I myself found. The wildness of the<lb break="yes"/>Indians of Guaicas, who are only four feet in height, but<lb break="yes"/>who are a very white and warlike people, and particularly the<lb break="yes"/>savage state of the Guajaribos, greater men-eaters than any<lb break="yes"/>of the other nations which we visited, prevent any one from<lb break="yes"/>penetrating over the small cataracts (Raudal de Guajaribos)<lb break="yes"/>east from Chiguire, unless a military expedition were un-<lb break="no"/>dertaken on purpose. But by the wonderful journey<lb break="yes"/>undertaken by D. <persName key="santosdelapuente_adl">Antonio Santos</persName>, who married Onotho,<lb break="yes"/>and who dressed sometimes as a Carib, and sometimes as<lb break="yes"/>a Macacy, whose languages he spoke, from Orinoco (the<lb break="yes"/>mouth of the Rio Caronis) to the small lake Parima and<lb break="yes"/>the river Amazon, we have obtained information respect-<lb break="no"/>ing the continuation of the cordillera of the Cataracts.<lb break="yes"/>Under the latitude of from 4° to 5° and longitude 63°, it<lb break="yes"/>becomes so narrow that it is scarcely 60 miles in breadth.<lb break="yes"/>It assumes here the name of Cerrania de Quimiropaca and<lb break="yes"/>Pacaraimo, and forms a chain of not very high ridges, by<lb break="yes"/>which the waters were divided. The water of the northern<lb break="yes"/>declivity, the Nocapray, Paraguamuci, <placeName key="benamo" >Benamo</placeName>, and Ma-<lb break="no"/>zurini, flow towards the Orinoco and Rio Esquibo; the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">waters</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="357" facs="#f0011"/> waters of the southern, the Rio Cururicana, Parime, Madari,<lb break="yes"/>and Mao, pour themselves into the <placeName key="amazonas">River Amazon</placeName>. Some<lb break="yes"/>degrees further towards the east, the cordillera again extends<lb break="yes"/>in breadth as it ascends southwards towards the Canno Pa-<lb break="no"/>rara along the Mao. It is here that the Dutch give to the<lb break="yes"/>Cerro d&#x2019;Ucuamo, the magnificent name of the Gold-<lb break="no"/>Mountain, or Dorado, because it consists of a very shining<lb break="yes"/>micaceous schistus, a fossil which has brought into celebrity<lb break="yes"/>the small island of Ypamucena in the lake of Parima.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On the east from Rio Esquibo, or on the other side of<lb break="yes"/>the land of the Aturajo Indians the cordillera turns south-<lb break="maybe"/>east as it unites with the garnet mountains of the Dutch<lb break="yes"/>and French Guiana, which are inhabited by a mixture of<lb break="yes"/>Negroes and Caribs, and give an origin to the rivers Ber-<lb break="no"/>bice, Surinam, Marony, <placeName key="aprouage">Aprouague</placeName>, and Oyapock. The<lb break="yes"/>last mentioned ridge of mountains extends very much: its<lb break="yes"/>gneis appears at <placeName key="baxoorinoco">Baxo Orinoco</placeName>, in latitude 8° 20&#x2032;, between<lb break="yes"/>the mouths of the Upata and <placeName key="acquire">Acquire</placeName>, and in latitude<lb break="yes"/>2° 14&#x2032; on the north side of the <placeName key="amazonas">river Amazon</placeName>, in the moun-<lb break="no"/>tains of Fripoupon and Maya.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Such is the form of the great cordilleras of the Cataracts,<lb break="yes"/>which are inhabited by a great number of uncivilized<lb break="yes"/>savages, little known to the Europeans. I must here ob-<lb break="no"/>serve, that in this description I have followed my own<lb break="yes"/>observations only, and the notices we obtained from the<lb break="yes"/>Indians, as also the observations of D. <persName key="santosdelapuente_adl">Antonio Santos</persName>, and<lb break="yes"/>the companions of his journey, who dictated to their<lb break="yes"/>friends. The maps of this part of the continent are en-<lb break="no"/>tirely false, and the map added to the history of the Evir-<lb break="no"/>coco by P. <persName key="caulin_a">Caulin</persName>, a work in other respects meritorious, is<lb break="yes"/>by our last observations some degrees more wrong in longi-<lb break="no"/>tude and latitude than the map published thirty years be-<lb break="no"/>fore by <persName key="anville_jbbd" >d&#x2019;Anville</persName>. All the Indian names in it also are mu-<lb break="no"/>tilated, and mountains and rivers are delineated where none<lb break="yes"/>exist; a defect the more pardonable as the author was never<lb break="yes"/>beyond the waterfalls of Orinoco, nor at the Rio Negro.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">[To be continued.]</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <pb n="26" facs="#f0012"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Sketch of a Geological Delineation of <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>.<lb break="yes"/>By</hi>
                    <persName key="humboldt_av">F. A. <hi rendition="#k">Von Humboldt.</hi>
                    </persName>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">[Continued from our last volume, p. 357.]</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>he</hi> cordillera of Parima never reaches to the same height<lb break="yes"/>as the Sierra Nevada in the province of Caraccas, which is<lb break="yes"/>2350 toises. Their highest summit seems to be the Cerro<lb break="yes"/>de la Esmeralda, or the mountain Duida, which, by trigo-<lb break="no"/>nometrical measurement, I found to be 1323 toises above<lb break="yes"/>the surface of the sea, which is the height also of the Ca-<lb break="no"/>nigou. This mountain is situated in a delightful plain co-<lb break="no"/>vered with ananas and palms: the monstrous mass which<lb break="yes"/>it exhibits towards the Mission and the rivers Canu-canuma<lb break="yes"/>and Tamatama, and the flames it vomits up towards the<lb break="yes"/>end of the rainy season, give it a romantic and majestic ap-<lb break="no"/>pearance. No Indian is able to clamber up to the top of<lb break="yes"/>this mountain and the rocks of its summit without a week&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>labour, because the luxuriance of vegetation in this climate<lb break="yes"/>impedes the progress of travelling. Next to the Duida, the<lb break="yes"/>Maraguaca, more towards the east of the river Simirimóni,<lb break="yes"/>and the high cordillera of Cunarami and Calitamini, which<lb break="yes"/>at Maypuré and St. Barbara is known under the false name<lb break="yes"/>of Sipapo, are the highest summits of the chain; they are<lb break="yes"/>from 1000 to 1100 toises in height. The common height<lb break="yes"/>of the cordillera, however, does not exceed 600 toises, and<lb break="yes"/>sometimes it is less, as the part situated between the left<lb break="yes"/>bank of the Cassiguiaré, an arm of the Orinoco which<lb break="yes"/>connects together the Rio Negro and the <placeName key="amazonas">river Amazon</placeName>,<lb break="yes"/>and the sources of the cataracts and Piramena between Ca-<lb break="no"/>richana and Morocote, is destroyed, and still exhibits insu-<lb break="no"/>lated rocks rising from the ground. The cause of this de-<lb break="no"/>struction seems to have been an eruption of water from the<lb break="yes"/>bason of the <placeName key="amazonas">Amazon river</placeName> towards the bason of Calabozo<lb break="yes"/>and <placeName key="baxoorinoco">Baxo-orinoco</placeName>, which differ in height about 160 toises.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The geological chart of this district which I have con-<lb break="no"/>structed represents an immense valley which unites the<lb break="yes"/>Llanos of the Rio Negro, Cassiguiaré, and <placeName key="amazonasregion">Amazon</placeName>, with<lb break="yes"/>those of the province of Caraccas, <placeName key="barcelona">Barcelona</placeName>, and Cumana;<lb break="yes"/>a valley which sinks down towards the north, and is inter-<lb break="no"/>sected by a large series of single rocks which show the di-<lb break="no"/>rection of the old cordillera on the banks of the Guaviare<lb break="yes"/>and Nuta in the province of Cassemora. The eastern ex-<lb break="no"/>tremity of this valley is the lowest part of it, and therefore<lb break="yes"/>the remains of the water of the Orinoco cut out for itself a<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">bed</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="27" facs="#f0013"/> bed in this place. This cordillera has two remarkable<lb break="yes"/>properties. In the first place, as has been remarked in<lb break="yes"/>other ridges, the southern declivity is much steeper than<lb break="yes"/>the northern: the high summits of Caravami, Jao, of the<lb break="yes"/>volcano of Duida, Maraguaca, &amp;c., all lie towards the<lb break="yes"/>south, and are there cut into perpendicular precipices. In<lb break="yes"/>the second place, this cordillera does not seem to contain a<lb break="yes"/>single rock of alluvial mountains, and consequently has bor-<lb break="no"/>rowed nothing from the organized kingdom. On our pas-<lb break="no"/>sage over this ridge we observed nothing but granite, gnieis,<lb break="yes"/>micaceous schist, and hornblend schist; nowhere a covering<lb break="yes"/>of sand-stone or alluvial chalk, which on the cordillera of<lb break="yes"/>Venezuela on the coast rises to the height of 976 toises<lb break="yes"/>above the level of the sea. Had the proximity of the <placeName key="aequator">equator</placeName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and the rotation of the earth any influence on this ph&#x00E6;no-<lb break="no"/>menon?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The third chain of original mountains, the cordillera of<lb break="yes" />Chiquitos, is known only from the accounts of some per-<lb break="no"/>sons who have resided at Buenos-Ayres and travelled<lb break="yes"/>through the Pampas. It unites the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> of Peru and<lb break="yes"/>Chili with the ridges of Brasil and Paraguay as it stretches<lb break="yes"/>from La Paz, Potosi, and Tucuman, through the provinces<lb break="yes"/>of Maxos, Chiquitos, and Chaco, towards the government<lb break="yes"/>of the Mines and of St. Paul in Brasil. Their highest sum-<lb break="no"/>mits seem to be situated between the latitude of 15° and 20°<lb break="yes"/>south, as the streams between the <placeName key="amazonas" >rivers Amazon</placeName> and La<lb break="yes"/>Plata divide themselves at that height.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Between the three cordilleras, the direction of which we<lb break="yes"/>have hitherto followed, lie three broad and deep valleys.<lb break="yes"/>1st, The valley between the south side of the cordillera of<lb break="yes"/>Venezuela, on the coast, and the cordillera of the Cataracts,<lb break="yes"/>or the valley of Orinoco and <placeName key="apure">Apuré</placeName>, between latitude 8°<lb break="yes"/>and 10°. 2d, The valley of the rivers Negro and <placeName key="amazonasregion">Amazon</placeName>,<lb break="yes"/>bordered by the Parima ridge and the cordillera of Chiqui-<lb break="no"/>tos, between latitude 3° north and 10° south. 3d, The val-<lb break="no"/>ley of Pampas of Buenos-Ayres, which extends from Saint<lb break="yes"/>Cruz of Sierra to Cape Virgin, between 19° and 52° south<lb break="yes"/>latitude. The first and second valley are in some measure<lb break="yes"/>united by the destruction of a part of the Parima cordillera.<lb break="yes"/>I do not know whether this be the case also with the Pampas<lb break="yes"/>and <placeName key="amazonasregion">valley of the Amazon</placeName>; it, however, appears that it is<lb break="yes" />not, though the Llanos of Monso form a sort of canal which<lb break="yes" />descends from north-west to south-east. All these immense<lb break="yes" />valleys or plains are entirely open towards the east, as they<lb break="yes" />run out into a low sandy coast: towards the west they are<lb break="yes"/>shut by the chain of the high <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>. There are some creeks<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">(<hi rendition="#i">anses</hi>)</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="28" facs="#f0014"/> (<hi rendition="#i">anses</hi>) which proceed from east to west in the direction of<lb break="yes"/>the tropical current, and on that account extend further<lb break="yes"/>into the land the broader the continent is. The valleys of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="apure">Apuré</placeName> and Orinoco are closed by the ridge which extends<lb break="yes"/>from Pampelona to Merida in longitude 73°, and the val-<lb break="no"/>ley of Pampas in longitude 70°: they both fall together a<lb break="yes"/>little towards the east, and seem to be covered by one and<lb break="yes"/>the same formation of alluvial strata.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <persName key="tralles_01">Tralles</persName> says, that in Swisserland there is more reason to<lb break="yes"/>wonder at the depth of the lakes than at the height of the<lb break="yes"/>mountains: I will venture to make a similar observation in<lb break="yes"/>regard to the <hi rendition="#i">Llanos</hi> or plains of <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>. How<lb break="yes"/>astonishing it is to see a continent which in its inte-<lb break="no"/>rior parts several hundred miles from the coast, and in the<lb break="yes"/>neighbourhood of mountains 3000 toises in height, is ele-<lb break="no"/>vated scarcely fifty toises above the surface of the sea! If<lb break="yes"/>the flux in these places should rise to as great a height as<lb break="yes"/>at St. Malo and Bristol, and if more motion should be<lb break="yes"/>communicated to the ocean by earthquakes, the greater<lb break="yes"/>part of these valleys would be laid under water. The<lb break="yes"/>highest Llano which I have measured is that between the<lb break="yes"/>rivers Ymirida, Temi, Pimichia, Cassiguiaré, and Guiainia<lb break="yes"/>(Rio Negro); it is 180 toises in height; but it sinks down<lb break="yes"/>towards <placeName key="atures">Atures</placeName> in the north, as towards the <placeName key="amazonas">river Amazon</placeName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>in the south. The valley of Orinoco and <placeName key="apure" >Apuré</placeName> is still<lb break="yes"/>much lower than that of Cassiguiare and Calabozo in the<lb break="yes"/>middle of the Llano where I made observations, in latitude<lb break="yes"/>8° 56&#x2032; 56&#x2033; and longitude 70° 9&#x2032; west from Paris. At <placeName key="angostura">An-<lb break="no" />gostura</placeName>, the capital of Guyana, latitude 8° 8&#x2032; 24&#x2033;, longitude<lb break="yes"/>66°, it is only 33 toises, and eighty miles from the coast<lb break="yes"/>scarcely eight toises above the level of the sea. The plains<lb break="yes"/>of Lombardy, in Europe, have the greatest resemblance to<lb break="yes"/>the Llanos on account of their small elevation. Pavia is<lb break="yes"/>only 34, and Cremona 24 toises in height; the other plains<lb break="yes"/>of Europe have a much greater elevation. In Saxony and<lb break="yes"/>Lower Silesia the plains are only from 87 to 120 toises<lb break="yes"/>in height; those of <placeName key="bayern" >Bavaria</placeName> and Swabia are from 230 to<lb break="yes"/>250. The declivity of the Llanos of <placeName key="amerika">America</placeName> is so gentle,<lb break="yes"/>their inequalities are so imperceptible, that no large river<lb break="yes"/>flows to either side. The Orinoco appears in the longitude<lb break="yes"/>of about 70°, as if about to discharge itself in the sea towards<lb break="yes"/>Portobello; but at Cabrouta it turns to the east without the<lb break="yes"/>least obstacle being discovered either there or at <placeName key="sanfernandodeatabapo">St. Fernando<lb break="yes"/>de Atabapo</placeName>, in latitude 7° 55&#x2032; 8&#x2033;, to oppose its course. In<lb break="yes"/>the large valley of Rio Negro, and of the <placeName key="amazonasregion">Amazon river</placeName>, is<lb break="yes"/>a tract of land, in 2° or 3° north latitude, of not less than<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">1600</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="29" facs="#f0015"/> 1600 square miles, which is bordered by the large rivers<lb break="yes"/>Atabasso, Cassiguiaré, Guiainia, and Orinoco, and repre-<lb break="no"/>sents a parallelogram, in which the water flows on the four<lb break="yes"/>opposite sides in opposite directions. In regard to the Ori-<lb break="no"/>noco, I found a fall of 151 toises in the distance of 70 miles<lb break="yes"/>from the mouth of Guaviare to the <placeName key="apure">Apuré</placeName>; but from the<lb break="yes"/>capital to the sea not more than eight toises. La Conda-<lb break="no"/>mine observed the same thing in regard to the river Ama-<lb break="no"/>zon, from the narrow pass of Paucis to Para, where it runs<lb break="yes"/>through a district of 240 miles, but falls not more than 14<lb break="yes"/>toises. It is not improbable that there might have been<lb break="yes"/>on the north side of the cordillera of the coast of Venezuela<lb break="yes"/>a plain as much lower than the plain of Orinoco as the plain<lb break="yes"/>of Rio Negro is higher than that of Orinoco, and on this<lb break="yes"/>account the former plain was covered by the water of the<lb break="yes"/>bay.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The two Llanos or plains which lie at the opposite ex-<lb break="no"/>tremities of <placeName key="amerika">America</placeName> exhibit a striking difference from that<lb break="yes"/>which lies between them, namely, the vale of the <placeName key="amazonas">river<lb break="yes"/>Amazon</placeName>. The latter is covered by so impenetrable forests<lb break="yes"/>that rivers alone can force a passage through them, and that<lb break="yes"/>scarcely any other animals but such as frequent trees can<lb break="yes"/>live in that district; so much is vegetation favoured by the<lb break="yes"/>continual rains under the <placeName key="aequator">equator</placeName>. The case is quite dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent with the plains of Orinoco and Pampas; they are<lb break="yes"/>level valleys covered with herbs, and savannahs which con-<lb break="no"/>tain only a few scattered palm-trees. The same heat, the<lb break="yes"/>same want of water, and the same ph&#x00E6;nomena of refrac-<lb break="no"/>tion, that is to say, the inverted image of objects seen float-<lb break="no"/>ing in the atmosphere, are observed here as in the deserts<lb break="yes"/>of<placeName key="afrika">Africa</placeName>and Arabia. But plains so perfect are nowhere<lb break="yes"/>else to be found; for the Mesa de Pavone and the Mesa de<lb break="yes"/>Guanipa in 800 square miles contain no eminence of eight<lb break="yes"/>or ten inches in height. The plains of Lower Hungary,<lb break="yes"/>on the west of Presburgh, have the greatest resemblance to<lb break="yes"/>them; for the flat land of La Mancha, Champagne, Westpha-<lb break="no"/>lia, Brandenburgh, and Poland, is hilly when compared with<lb break="yes"/>the Llanos of <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>. Nothing but a long stagna-<lb break="no"/>tion of water could have produced so horizontal a bottom.<lb break="yes"/>Traces of old cities are found here, but seldom are any seen<lb break="yes"/>which rise like castles (La Piedra Guanan, longitude 69° 3&#x2032;,<lb break="yes"/>latitude 1° 59&#x2032; 48&#x2033;) in the Llano of Cassiguiaré and of Rio<lb break="yes" />Negro. But from St. Borja to the mouth of the Black river<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condamine</persName> observed no eminence; and the Llano of Ori-<lb break="no"/>noco is also without islands. As the Morros of San Juan<lb break="yes"/>belong to the southern declivity of the cordillera of Vene-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">zuola,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="30" facs="#f0016"/> zuola, an impetuous current of water must have swept every<lb break="yes"/>thing along with it; and the present sea presents large spaces<lb break="yes"/>without islands: instead of islands there are in the Llanos<lb break="yes"/>whole uninterrupted portions of from 200 to 300 square<lb break="yes"/>miles of surface which rise from two to five feet above the<lb break="yes"/>plain, and which are called <hi rendition="#i" >mesas</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">bancos</hi>; which is as<lb break="yes" />much as to say, that they were shoals or sand-banks in the<lb break="yes" />antient sea. I must here observe, that the middle of the<lb break="yes"/>plain of Orinoco is the most beautiful and levellest part of<lb break="yes"/>it. The bottom of this immense bason rises up and becomes<lb break="yes"/>unequal at the edge; the plains therefore which one tra-<lb break="no"/>verses between Guyana and <placeName key="barcelona">Barcelona</placeName> are less perfect and<lb break="yes"/>level than those of Calabozo and Uritucu.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This remarkable difference which we found between the<lb break="yes"/>cordillera of Venezuola and that of the Cataracts, which is<lb break="yes"/>that the latter consist of alluvial mountains entirely bare, is<lb break="yes"/>observed between the northern Llano of the Orinoco and that<lb break="yes"/>of the Rio Negro and <placeName key="amazonas">river Amazon</placeName>. In the former, the<lb break="yes"/>original mountains are every where covered with compact<lb break="yes"/>limestone, gypsum, and sandstone: in the latter the gra-<lb break="no"/>nite every where appears. The more one approaches the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="aequator">equator</placeName> the thinner is the stratum of sand which covers the<lb break="yes"/>crust of earth on the original mountains: in a land where<lb break="yes"/>vegetation is so luxuriant, there is seen in the middle of fo-<lb break="no"/>rests spaces of 40,000 square toises scarcely covered with<lb break="yes"/>a few lichens, and which do not rise two inches above the<lb break="yes"/>rest of the surface. Will the same be discovered in <placeName key="afrika">Africa</placeName>?<lb break="yes"/>for it is only in <placeName key="amerika">America</placeName> and <placeName key="afrika" >Africa</placeName> that there is land under<lb break="yes"/>the <placeName key="aequator">equator</placeName>.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Having taken a view of the direction of the mountains<lb break="yes"/>and valleys, or the form of the inequalities of the earth, let<lb break="yes"/>us now turn our attention to objects of more importance<lb break="yes"/>which have been less examined, namely, the rising and fall-<lb break="no"/>ing of the strata of the original mountains which form<lb break="yes"/>this part of the earth I have traversed. I have been con-<lb break="no"/>vinced since 1792 that the rising of the original mountains<lb break="yes"/>follows a general law, and that, making allowance for those<lb break="yes"/>inequalities which may have been produced by trifling local<lb break="yes"/>causes, and particularly veins and strata in mines, or by very<lb break="yes"/>old valleys, the stratified coarse-grained granite, the foli-<lb break="no"/>ated granite, and particularly the micaceous schist and ar-<lb break="no"/>gillaceous schist, rise in the league 3<formula notation="TeX">\frac{4}{8}</formula> by the miner&#x2019;s com-<lb break="no"/>pass, as they form with the meridian of the place an angle<lb break="yes"/>of 52<formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{2}</formula>°. The falling of the strata is towards the north-<lb break="maybe"/>west; that is to say, they fall parallel with a body that<lb break="yes"/>might be thrown in the same direction, or the aperture of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="31" facs="#f0017"/> the angle of inclination (less than 90°) which it makes with<lb break="yes"/>the earth&#x2019;s axis stands towards the north-east. The rising is<lb break="yes"/>more constant than the falling, especially in the simple moun-<lb break="no"/>tains (argillaceous schist, hornblend schist), or in the com-<lb break="no"/>pound mountains with fewer crystallized grains, such as the<lb break="yes"/>micaceous schist. In granite (it is, however, found very re-<lb break="no"/>gularly stratified rising in the league 3 &#x2014; 4, and falling to-<lb break="no"/>wards the north on the Schneekopfe, the Ochsenkopfe, the<lb break="yes"/>Siebengebirge, and the Pyrenees,) and in the gnieis the at-<lb break="no"/>traction of the crystallized mixed parts to each other seems<lb break="yes"/>to have prevented the regular stratification; therefore more<lb break="yes"/>coincidence is found among the micaceous and argillaceous<lb break="yes"/>schist, and these first led me to the idea of the law of rising<lb break="yes"/>during my tour to the Fichtelberg and the Thuringian fo-<lb break="no"/>rest. Since that time I have examined with great care<lb break="yes"/>the angle of the strata of other original mountains in other<lb break="yes"/>parts of Germany, in Swisserland, Italy, the southern<lb break="yes"/>parts of France, and the Pyrenees, and lately in Gallicia.<lb break="yes"/>Mr. <persName key="freiesleben_jc" >Freiesleben</persName>, whose labours have been of so much ser-<lb break="no"/>vice to geology, assisted me in this examination; and we<lb break="yes"/>were astonished at the uniformity in the rising and falling<lb break="yes"/>of the mountains which we found at each step on one of<lb break="yes"/>the highest cordilleras of the earth, the <placeName key="savoyeralpen">Alps of Savoy</placeName>, the<lb break="yes"/>Valais, and the Milanese.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>An examination of this ph&#x00E6;nomenon, and of the identity<lb break="yes"/>of the strata, was one of the principal objects when I under-<lb break="no"/>took a voyage to <placeName key="amerika">America</placeName>. A measurement of the angles<lb break="yes"/>which I have hitherto made on the cordillera of Venezuola<lb break="yes"/>and Parima gave again the result of my observations in<lb break="yes"/>Europe in the chain of the micaceous schist mountains of<lb break="yes"/>Cavaralleda as far as Rio Mamon; on the Silla de Caracas at<lb break="yes"/>the height of 1000 toises; of the Rincon del Diablo, on<lb break="yes"/>mount Guigue; in the islands in the beautiful lake of Va-<lb break="no"/>lencia, which has almost the same elevation as the lake of<lb break="yes"/>Geneva, at the boundaries of the isthmus of Maniguaré and<lb break="yes"/>Chupariparu; on the hornblend schist which appears unco-<lb break="no"/>vered in the streets of the capital of Guyana, and also in the<lb break="yes"/>Cataracts, and on the stratified granite at the foot of the<lb break="yes"/>Duida. Every where the strata form an angle of 50° with<lb break="yes"/>the meridian (in the league 3 &#x2014; 4 by the Saxon compass) as<lb break="yes"/>they rise from the north-east to south-west, and fall about<lb break="yes"/>from 60 to 80 towards the north-west.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This great coincidence in the old and <placeName key="amerika">new world</placeName> must<lb break="yes"/>excite serious considerations. It exhibits a very important<lb break="yes"/>geological fact. After so many observations which I have<lb break="yes"/>made in places so far distant from each other, it can no<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">longer</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="32" facs="#f0018"/> longer be believed that the rising of the strata follows the<lb break="yes"/>direction of the cordillera, and that the falling follows the<lb break="yes"/>declivity of the mountains. The profile of many of the<lb break="yes"/>mountains, particularly a section of the mountains, such as<lb break="yes"/>that of Genoa through the Bochetta, and of St. Gothard as<lb break="yes"/>far as Franconia in Germany, which I intend to publish at<lb break="yes"/>a proper time, proves exactly the contrary. The rising and<lb break="yes"/>declivity of the cordillera, the form of the small inequali-<lb break="no"/>ties of the earth, seem to be newer ph&#x00E6;nomena. A stream<lb break="yes"/>might scoop out a valley in this or in that direction; might<lb break="yes"/>tear asunder a part of the cordillera, and give it apparently<lb break="yes"/>one direction or another. The strata of the original moun-<lb break="no"/>tains appear, amidst all these angles of rising and falling<lb break="yes"/>observed at present, to have existed before these changes at<lb break="yes"/>the surface of the earth. They are the same at the summit<lb break="yes"/>of the <placeName key="alpen">Alps</placeName>, and in the mines into which we descend.<lb break="yes"/>When one travels for 15 miles over strata of argillaceous<lb break="yes"/>schist, which are inclined parallel to each other, at an an-<lb break="no"/>gle of 70° towards the north-west, one can no longer be-<lb break="no"/>lieve that they are deranged strata, which once stood hori-<lb break="no"/>zontal. We must suppose mountains that were once 15<lb break="yes"/>miles in height, and that the whole mass had an uniform<lb break="yes"/>fall, and then reflect on the space which such a mass would<lb break="yes"/>occupy: and one must remember the strata on the heights<lb break="yes"/>of Genoa, or on the heights of Bochetta, or on St. Maurice,<lb break="yes"/>which are exactly parallel; and on the strata of the Fich-<lb break="no"/>telberg of Gallicia, the Silla de Caracas of Robolo on the<lb break="yes"/>isthmus of <placeName key="araya">Araya</placeName> of Cassiguiare, in the neighbourhood of<lb break="yes"/>the <placeName key="aequator">equator</placeName>. One must allow that this coincidence gives<lb break="yes"/>evidence of a cause which has acted at a very early period,<lb break="yes"/>and in a general manner; a cause which must have arisen<lb break="yes"/>from the first attraction by which matter was forced toge-<lb break="no"/>ther to form a spherical planet.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This grand cause does not exclude local causes, by which<lb break="yes" />individual smaller parts of matter were determined to ar-<lb break="no"/>range themselves in this or in that manner, according to<lb break="yes"/>the laws of crystallization. <persName key="lametherie_jcd">Delametherie</persName> has made an in-<lb break="no"/>genious remark on this subject: he shows the influence of<lb break="yes"/>a large mountain (as a small nucleus) on the neighbouring<lb break="yes"/>small mountains. One must not forget that, besides the<lb break="yes"/>general attraction towards the centre, all matters exercise a<lb break="yes"/>mutual attraction on each other.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The crust of the earth, for I will venture to speak only<lb break="yes"/>of this part, must be the result of an immense action of<lb break="yes"/>powers of attraction of affinities, which determined, put<lb break="yes"/>in equilibrium, and modified each other. M. <persName key="klugel_01">Klugel</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">thought</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="33" facs="#f0019"/> thought he found, by calculation, that the great flattening<lb break="yes"/>of the earth must be on the west side of the north pole.<lb break="yes"/>Has the axis of rotation been changed? What will be the<lb break="yes"/>inclination of the strata in the southern hemisphere? We<lb break="yes"/>are not acquainted with the cause; let us rather continue to<lb break="yes"/>examine the ph&#x00E6;nomena.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This falling of the strata of the original mountains in<lb break="yes"/>the cordillera of Venezuola has a great and melancholy<lb break="yes"/>influence on the fertility of the provinces of Caracas, Cu-<lb break="no"/>mana, and <placeName key="barcelona">Barcelona</placeName>; the water which filtres through at<lb break="yes"/>the summit of the mountain flows down according to the<lb break="yes"/>direction of the strata, and for this reason there is great<lb break="yes"/>want of water in the whole large district which lies on the<lb break="yes"/>south side of the cordillera, and therefore so many springs<lb break="yes"/>and small streams burst forth on the northern declivity,<lb break="yes"/>which, by this great quantity of moisture, and the super-<lb break="no"/>abundance of wood, which shelters it almost the whole day<lb break="yes"/>from the sun&#x2019;s rays, is rendered as unhealthful as it is fruit-<lb break="no"/>ful.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The alluvial mountains which I have hitherto observed<lb break="yes"/>are almost under the same circumstances as in Europe. The<lb break="yes"/>oldest seem to have experienced the action of the same<lb break="yes"/>causes which determined the strata of the original moun-<lb break="no"/>tains, as they rise in the league 3&#x2014;4, or as the seamen ex-<lb break="no"/>press it, N. 50 E. They often fall towards the south-east,<lb break="yes"/>as in the <placeName key="alpen">Alps</placeName> of Bern, the Valais, Tyrol, and Steyermark;<lb break="yes"/>but the greater part of them, and particularly the newest,<lb break="yes"/>which where I have been are the most numerous, follow<lb break="yes"/>no certain law; their strata often lie horizontally, or rise<lb break="yes"/>towards the edge of the large dried-up basons, which in<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="amerika">America</placeName> are called Llanos, and in<placeName key="afrika">Africa</placeName>Deserts.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName> says that in Peru and Quito he observed<lb break="yes"/>no petrifactions. The cordillera of Quito, however, is not<lb break="yes"/>like that of Parima, naked granite, for at Cuen&#x00E7;a, and on<lb break="yes"/>the south side, there is gypsum and alluvial chalk. <persName key="buffon_gllcd">Buffon</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>dwells much, in his <hi rendition="#i">Epoques de la Nature</hi>, on the question<lb break="yes"/>whether <placeName key="southamerika">South America</placeName> contains petrifactions? I have<lb break="yes"/>found an immense quantity of them in calcareous alluvial<lb break="yes"/>sandstone which covers the northern and southern decli-<lb break="no"/>vity of the coast of Venezuola, from the summit of St.<lb break="yes"/>Bernandin, and <placeName key="altosdeconoma">the Altos de Conoma</placeName>, to the Cerro de Mea-<lb break="no"/>piré, or the headland of Puria and Trinidad. The same<lb break="yes"/>stratum is found also in Tobago, Guadaloupe, and St. Do-<lb break="no"/>mingo. An immense quantity of sea and land shells,<lb break="yes"/>which in Europe are seldom found mixed together, cellu-<lb break="no"/>lari&#x00E6;, madrepores, cerallines, and astroites, are found in-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">terspersed</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="34" facs="#f0020"/> terspersed in this sandstone. The shells themselves are half<lb break="yes"/>broken: whole rocks consist merely of such remains re-<lb break="no"/>duced to powder. My fellow-traveller, <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName>, discovered<lb break="yes"/>in them shells of the genus Pinna, Venus, and Ostrea, of<lb break="yes"/>which living specimens are still met with on that coast; an<lb break="yes"/>observation of great importance to geology. Every thing<lb break="yes"/>shows that this stratum, which I have seen only at the di-<lb break="no"/>stance of nine or ten miles from the present coast, is of very<lb break="yes"/>modern origin, and that the fluid in which it was produced<lb break="yes"/>had been in a state of violent motion. The petrified shells<lb break="yes"/>in a much older stratum of compact limestone are scarcer<lb break="yes"/>and much differently stratified: they are anomia, terebratu-<lb break="no"/>lites, &amp;c. placed together in families, and in such a manner<lb break="yes"/>that it is seen that they have lived (as those of Mount<lb break="yes"/>Salive, the Heinberg near Göttingen, of Jena, and Geneva)<lb break="yes"/>on the spot where they are now found petrified. They are<lb break="yes"/>not interspersed throughout the whole mass of the lime-<lb break="no"/>stone; they are only peculiar to certain strata. Many rocks<lb break="yes"/>may be examined without finding any of these petrifactions;<lb break="yes"/>but where found they are in great quantity, and present<lb break="yes"/>themselves chiefly on great heights; peculiarities which<lb break="yes"/>they have in common with the shells found in the lime-<lb break="no"/>stone of the high <placeName key="alpen" >Alps</placeName> of Swisserland and Salzburg, which<lb break="yes"/>is identic with the hardened marl of Thuringia, a limestone<lb break="yes"/>which lies above the very old sandstone.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I must observe also, that, besides the new sandstone<lb break="yes"/>stratum with a calcareous base, of which I have already<lb break="yes"/>spoken, the petrifactions do not often occur; and I was<lb break="yes"/>particularly astonished to find no single belemnites or am-<lb break="no"/>monites which are so common in all the mountains of<lb break="yes"/>Europe. The Llano of Orinoco, and that even of Rio<lb break="yes"/>Negro, are covered with a coarse grained breccia (<hi rendition="#i">nagel-<lb break="no"/>fluhe)</hi> which contains no petrified shells, and perhaps covers<lb break="yes"/>the other alluvial strata with petrifactions. But this breccia<lb break="yes"/>contains on the other hand petrified trunks of trees, which<lb break="yes"/>are sometimes found of the length of a toise, and of the<lb break="yes"/>diameter of two feet. They seem to belong to a kind of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="malpighi_m">Malphigia</persName>.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The sandstone which contains all kinds of marine ani-<lb break="no"/>mals (the quarry of Punta del Barrigon near <placeName key="araya">Araya</placeName> is of this<lb break="yes"/>sort) never exceeds the height of from 30 to 40 toises. In<lb break="yes"/>several places it forms the bottom of the Gulph of Mexico<lb break="yes"/>(Cabo Blanco, <placeName key="puntaaraya">Punta Araya</placeName>). In the compact limestone I<lb break="yes"/>never saw petrified shells above the height of 800 toises;<lb break="yes"/>but other very new testimonies prove the residence of the<lb break="yes"/>water at much greater heights. Slate found on the Silla de<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">Caracas,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="35" facs="#f0021"/> Caracas, at the height of 1130 toises, proves that the water<lb break="yes"/>once, as on the Bonhomme in Savoy, formed this aperture<lb break="yes"/>between the two peaks or pyramids of the <placeName key="avila">Avila</placeName>, an aper-<lb break="no"/>ture which is much older than the five counted in the cor-<lb break="no"/>dillera of the coast, namely, those of Rio Neveri, Unare,<lb break="yes"/>Tuy, Mamon, and Guyaca. Among the mountains of the<lb break="yes"/>province of Cumana, there are very singular valleys of a<lb break="yes"/>perfect circular form, which seem to be dried up lakes. Of<lb break="yes"/>this kind are the valleys of Cumanacoa and St. Augustine,<lb break="yes"/>507 toises in depth, which are celebrated for the refreshing<lb break="yes"/>coolness which travellers experience in them.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When the modern action of water is considered, two op-<lb break="no"/>posite effects are observed: one recollects a very distant<lb break="yes"/>epoch, when the irruption of the sea formed the Gulph of<lb break="yes"/>Cariaco and the Golfo Triste; separated Trinidad and Mar-<lb break="no"/>garetha from the main land, and convulsed the coast of<lb break="yes"/>Mochima and Santa Fé, where the islands of la Boracha,<lb break="yes"/>Picua, and Caracas, form a heap of ruins. The sea then<lb break="yes"/>attacked the land; but the contest did not long continue:<lb break="yes"/>the ocean again begins to draw back. The islands Coche<lb break="yes"/>and Cuagua are shoals which emerged from the water; the<lb break="yes"/>large plain of Salado, lying in Cumana, belongs to the Bay<lb break="yes"/>of Cariaco, and is only 5<formula notation="TeX" >\frac{1}{2}</formula> toises above the level of the sea.<lb break="yes" />The hill on which the castle of St. Antonio is situated was<lb break="yes"/>an island in this gulph, as an arm of the sea passed to the<lb break="yes"/>north of Tatoraqual through the Charas towards Punta De-<lb break="no"/>legada, as is proved by a multitude of unaltered shells. It<lb break="yes"/>is observed here and at <placeName key="barcelona">Barcelona</placeName> that the sea is daily<lb break="yes"/>retiring: in the harbour of <placeName key="barcelona" >Barcelona</placeName> it has lost in 20 years<lb break="yes"/>above 900 toises. Is this decrease of the sea in the Gulph<lb break="yes"/>of Mexico general, or is it the case here, as in the Mediter-<lb break="no"/>ranean Sea, that it gains in one point and loses in another?<lb break="yes"/>This retreat of the sea must not be confounded with an-<lb break="no"/>other real ph&#x00E6;nomenon easy to be explained, namely, the<lb break="yes"/>decrease of fresh water, of rain, and of the rivers in this<lb break="yes"/>continent. The Orinoco, as we see it at present, is no<lb break="yes"/>longer the shadow of what it was 1000 years ago, accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to the evidence of the traces which the water has left<lb break="yes"/>on both banks at the height of 70 or 80 toises. These traces<lb break="yes"/>have long attracted the notice of learned Europeans who<lb break="yes"/>have seen the <placeName key="barraguan" >Barraguan</placeName>, the Cueva de <placeName key="ataruipe">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Atarnipe</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">Ataruipe</corr>
                        </choice>
                    </placeName> (the bury-<lb break="no"/>ing place of the <placeName key="atures" >Atures</placeName> Indians, who formed a kind of<lb break="yes"/>mummies), the Cerro Cuma, the Daminari, the Keri, Oco,<lb break="yes"/>and Ouivitari, the bottom of which at present is scarcely<lb break="yes"/>covered by the foam of the Cataracts of Maypuré. These<lb break="yes"/>traces remind the Indians of a great inundation, during<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">which</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="36" facs="#f0022"/> which many persons saved themselves on rafts of Agave,<lb break="yes"/>and afterwards cut out inscriptions and hieroglyphics, with<lb break="yes"/>which the granite of Urnana, of Incaramada, and the banks<lb break="yes"/>of Cassiquiaré, are seen covered, but of which no one at<lb break="yes"/>present has the key. This tradition, common among the<lb break="yes"/>Indians of Erovato and of Parima, shows great analogy with<lb break="yes"/>the mythology of the antients. People think they read the<lb break="yes"/>history of <persName key="deukalion">Deucalion</persName>, and <persName key="pauw_cd">Pauw</persName> would find the remembrance<lb break="yes"/>of this flood not uninteresting.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">[To be concluded in our next.]</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <pb n="172" facs="#f0023"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Sketch of a Geological Delineation of South Ame-<lb break="no"/>rica. By</hi>
                    <persName key="humboldt_av">F. A. <hi rendition="#k">Von Humboldt.</hi>
                    </persName>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">[Concluded from p. 36.]</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#in">H</hi>aving</hi> already given a cursory view of the general ap-<lb break="no"/>pearance which the mountains of <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName> exhibit to<lb break="yes"/>the eye of the geologist, I shall now enumerate the different<lb break="yes"/>kinds of mountains which I have hitherto discovered in that<lb break="yes"/>country, beginning with the oldest.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#c">I. <hi rendition="#i">Primitive Mountains.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Granite.</hi>&#x2014;The whole cordillera of Parima, and particu-<lb break="no"/>larly the neighbourhood of the volcanoes of Duida and Mar-<lb break="no"/>cielago, consist of granite, which does not form a transition<lb break="yes"/>into gneiss. In the cordillera of the coast it is almost every<lb break="yes"/>where covered and mixed with gneiss and micaceous schist.<lb break="yes"/>I saw it disposed in strata of from two to three feet in thick-<lb break="no"/>ness, exceedingly regular, declining from three to four per<lb break="yes"/>league, towards the north-west between Valencia and Porto-<lb break="no"/>cabello. I found it on the Rincon del Diablo south-east<lb break="yes"/>from Portocabello, with large and beautiful crystals of feld-<lb break="no"/>spar an inch and a half in diameter, like the large grained<lb break="yes"/>granite on the high summits of the Schneegebirg and the<lb break="yes"/>Fichtelberg, those of Scotland and Chamouni. It is here<lb break="yes"/>split into regular prisms; and I saw it on Calavera du Cerro<lb break="yes"/>de Mariana beyond Cura, and on the Silla de Caracas,<lb break="yes"/>in this prismatic form, which the learned mineralogist<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="karsten_dlg" >Karsten</persName> observed on the Schneekoppe in Silesia. The<lb break="yes"/>northern part of Germany, and the lands on the <placeName key="baltikum">Baltic</placeName> in<lb break="yes"/>Europe, but not the plain to the south of the Fichtelberg<lb break="yes"/>in Swabia and <placeName key="bayern">Bavaria</placeName>, are full of monstrous blocks of gra-<lb break="no"/>nite which have rolled down from the heights. In neither<lb break="yes"/>of the llanos of <placeName key="suedamerika" >South America</placeName>, that of Orinoco, and that<lb break="yes"/>of the <placeName key="amazonasregion">Amazon river</placeName>, did we find any such masses, and no<lb break="yes"/>fragments of primitive mountains. The granite mountains<lb break="yes"/>of Los Mariches near Caracas, and those of Torrito be-<lb break="no"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">tween</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="173" facs="#f0024"/> tween Valencia and St. Carlos, and that of Sierra Neveda<lb break="yes"/>de Merida, contain, like that of St. Gothard, fissures which<lb break="yes"/>are covered with very beautiful and large rock crystals.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The granite is covered with gneiss and micaceous schist,<lb break="yes" />particularly on the cordillera of the coast of Venezuela.<lb break="yes" />Gneiss is abundant in particular from Cape Chichibocoa to<lb break="yes" />Cape Codera in the Tequez, Cocuiza, and the mountain<lb break="yes"/>
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Guigne</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">Guigue</corr>
                        </choice>, as well as in the islands of the Lake of Valencia,<lb break="yes" />where I found (on Cape Blanc, opposite to Guacara,) blackish<lb break="yes"/>quartz in the gneiss which passes into Lydian stone, or<lb break="yes"/>rather into the schistous state of <persName key="werner_ag">Werner</persName>. The Macanao<lb break="yes"/>on Margaret&#x2019;s island, and the whole cordillera on the isth-<lb break="no"/>mus of Cariaco, is nothing else than micaceous schist full<lb break="yes"/>of red garnets; and at Maniquarez it is combined with a<lb break="yes"/>little cyanite. Green garnets are intermixed with the gneiss<lb break="yes"/>of the mountain <placeName key="avila" >Avila</placeName>. In the gneiss of the rock Cala-<lb break="no" />micari in Cassiquiare, and in the granite of Las Trincheras<lb break="yes" />near Valencia, I saw round masses, from three to four<lb break="yes" />inches in diameter, interspersed, which consisted of finer<lb break="yes" />grained granite, yellow feldspar, a great deal of quartz, and<lb break="yes"/>scarcely any mica. Is this old granite contained in some<lb break="yes"/>of later formation, or are these masses, which have the ap-<lb break="no"/>pearance of accumulations, merely the effect of attraction,<lb break="yes"/>which here and there made the particles to approach nearer<lb break="yes"/>to each other, but at the same time that the whole moun-<lb break="no"/>tain was formed? This ph&#x00E6;nomenon of one kind of gra-<lb break="no"/>nite interspersed in the other is observed also in Silesia, at<lb break="yes"/>Wunsiedel, on the Fichtelberg, in Chamouni, on St. Ber-<lb break="no"/>nard, on the Escurial, and in Galicia. Nature is uniform<lb break="yes"/>in her natural productions, even to the small variations in<lb break="yes"/>proportions.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The micaceous schist passes into talc schist in the cor-<lb break="no" />dillera of the coast, on the mountain Capaya, and on the<lb break="yes" />Quebrada Secca, in the valley del Tuy. In the cordillera<lb break="yes" />of Parima talc is found in very large shining masses, and<lb break="yes" />this has contributed so much to the celebrity of the Do-<lb break="no" />rado, or Cerro Ucucuamo, between the river Esquivo and<lb break="yes" />Mao, in the island Pumacena. The bright fiery appearance<lb break="yes" />exhibited sometimes by the truncated pyramids of the large<lb break="yes" />Cerro Calitamini, near Cunavami, at sun-setting, seems also<lb break="yes" />to proceed from a stratum of talcy schist cut perpendicu-<lb break="no" />larly towards the west.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Small idols of nephrite, which I saw brought from Ero-<lb break="no"/>vato, show that to the south of Raudal de Mura there are<lb break="yes"/>nephrite rocks in gneiss like those I found at the bottom of<lb break="yes"/>St. Gothard, near Ursern. This formation was repeated by<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">nature</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="174" facs="#f0025"/> nature in the land of the Tupinambaros Indians. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Con-<lb break="no"/>damine</persName> discovered this variation of the hard nephrite, which<lb break="yes"/>is known under the name of the Amazon stone.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The granite, gneiss, and micaceous schist, contain here,<lb break="yes"/>as in Europe, strata of chlorite schist arranged under each<lb break="yes" />other in the sea at Cape Blanc west from Guayra. Very<lb break="yes"/>pure and beautiful hornblend schist is found in the streets of<lb break="yes" />Guyana; and, still more south, in the cordillera of Parima,<lb break="yes" />feldspar effloresces into porcelain earth in the Silla de Ca-<lb break="no"/>racas; strata of quartz, with magnetic iron-stone, is found<lb break="yes"/>at the sources of the Cutuche, near Caracas; grained folia-<lb break="no"/>ceous, primitive limestone, without tremolite, but with a<lb break="yes"/>great deal of sulphureous pyrites and sparry iron-stone, on<lb break="yes"/>the Quebrada de Topo on the road from Caracas to Guayra.<lb break="yes"/>This limestone is entirely wanting in the cordillera of Pa-<lb break="no"/>rima, where it has been sought for many years. Zeichen<lb break="yes"/>schist, a kind of carbonaceous iron, and pretty pure gra-<lb break="no"/>phite, are found in the Quebrada de Tocume near Chacao,<lb break="yes"/>in the Quebrada Secca near Tuy, and north from the La-<lb break="no"/>guna Chica; on the difficult road which leads across the<lb break="yes"/>isthmus of Cariaco to Chiparipara, there are found veins<lb break="yes"/>of quartz, which contain auriferous sulphureous pyrites<lb break="yes"/>and antimony, native gold, gray silver ore, mountain blue,<lb break="yes"/>malachite, &amp;c.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The copper ore of <placeName key="aroa">Aroa</placeName> is the only kind here taken from<lb break="yes"/>the earth: sixty or seventy slaves obtain yearly 1500 quin-<lb break="no"/>tals at most of refined copper. The quintal is sold for<lb break="yes"/>twelve piastres. The valley in which this ore is dug up is<lb break="yes"/>less unhealthful than the valleys near the sea where the<lb break="yes"/>Indians wash gold; namely, Urama, Maron, and <placeName key="alpagoton">Alpago-<lb break="no"/>ton</placeName>, where the air appears to be poisonous, as is the case<lb break="yes"/>in the fertile valley of Cararinas between Nirgua and Rio<lb break="yes"/>Jaracuy. The gold is dispersed throughout the whole pro-<lb break="no"/>vince, particularly in the strata of quartz at <placeName key="baruta" >Baruta</placeName>, Catia,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Guigne</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">Guigue</corr>
                        </choice>, Quebrada del Oro near Tuy, and on the Cerro de<lb break="yes" />Chacao, and Real de Santa Barbara near St. John, where<lb break="yes"/>I found barytic spar, the only instance I ever met with in<lb break="yes" />this country. All the rivers of the province of Characas,<lb break="yes" />wash down gold. It however does not thence follow that<lb break="yes" />this province is rich, and contains veins of gold not yet<lb break="yes" />discovered: the gold may be interspersed in whole masses<lb break="yes" />of granite; and I am acquainted with no high granite cor-<lb break="no" />dillera, either here or in Europe, the rivers of which do<lb break="yes" />not wash down gold. The Cerro Duida of Esmeralda in<lb break="yes" />Dorado, the Quebrada du Tigre near Encaramada, and the<lb break="yes" />Cerros de Amoco, the Real de S. Barbaro near St. John,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="175" facs="#f0026"/> the Quebrada de Catia, the alum ore of Chuparuparu, some<lb break="yes"/>traces of iron ore in the llano of St. Sebastian, and par-<lb break="no"/>ticularly the <placeName key="aroa" >Aroa</placeName> abundant in copper, seem to call for the<lb break="yes"/>industry of the miners.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Argillaceous schist is very scarce: it covers the micace-<lb break="no"/>ous schist on the southern declivity of Venezuela, in the<lb break="yes" />neighbourhood of the Llanos, in the Quebradas de Malparo,<lb break="yes" />and Piedra Azul: there is blue argillaceous schist, with<lb break="yes" />veins of quartz, on the isthmus of Cariaco, near Chupa-<lb break="no" />ruparu, in the Distillador Arroyo du Robola, and also on<lb break="yes" />Macanao. In the four last-mentioned places there are<lb break="yes"/>found in the argillaceous schist alum and vitriolic schist, in<lb break="yes" />strata of two or three feet in thickness, which effloresce<lb break="yes" />sulphate of alumine, or natural alum, with which the Indi-<lb break="no" />ans of Guayqueries carry on a little trade.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Serpentine is found on the cordillera of Venezuela above<lb break="yes" />micaceous schist, on the surface of Villa de Cura, at the<lb break="yes" />height of 245 toises; between the Cerro de Piedras Negras<lb break="yes" />and the Rio Tucutunemo, here and there green olivin mixed<lb break="yes" />with glimmer, without garnets, schillerspath, or hornblend,<lb break="yes" />but with veins of bluish lardstone.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Grunstein (green rock), original trapp, an intimate union<lb break="yes"/>of hornblend and feldspar, sometimes intermixed with sul-<lb break="no" />phureous pyrites and quartz, often confounded with ba-<lb break="no" />saltes, and very little known in Europe, is found in strata<lb break="yes" />of two fathoms in thickness, or balls of from three to four<lb break="yes" />feet in diameter, composed of concentric strata united with<lb break="yes" />micaceous schist or original argillaceous schist, in several<lb break="yes"/>places of the northern and southern declivity of the cordil-<lb break="no"/>lera of the mountain <placeName key="avila" >Avila</placeName>, in the sea near Cape Blanc, in<lb break="yes"/>a real vein which traverses the strata of gneiss, but inter-<lb break="no" />mixed with newer granite, which fills up the vein between<lb break="yes"/>
                        <placeName key="antimano">Antimano</placeName> and Carapa near Caracas. The gray stone con-<lb break="no"/>tains here red garnets which I have never seen in Europe.<lb break="yes"/>I have sent specimens of them to Madrid in the first box<lb break="yes"/>which I transmitted to the captain-general of Caracas.</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>II. <hi rendition="#i">Kind of Mountains which form the Transition from<lb break="yes"/>Primitive to Alluvial Mountains. Formation of the<lb break="yes"/>Transition of <persName key="werner_ag" >Werner</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>This formation is found in particular to the north of the<lb break="yes" />Parima cordillera, opposite to Caccara, and in large masses<lb break="yes" />on the southern declivity of the Venezuela cordillera. Be-<lb break="no" />tween the llanos and Morros of S. Juan, between the Villa<lb break="yes" />de Gura and Parapara, between longitude 9° 33&#x2032; and 9° 55&#x2032;,<lb break="yes"/>one seems to enter a land of basaltes, on descending from<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="176" facs="#f0027"/> the height of 300 to 63 toises above the level of the sea.<lb break="yes"/>Every thing reminds one here of the mountains of Bilin<lb break="yes"/>in Bohemia, or of Vienza in Italy. The primitive ser-<lb break="no"/>pentin on the banks of the Tucutunemo, which like that of<lb break="yes"/>Silesia contains copper veins, becomes gradually mixed<lb break="yes"/>with feldspar and hornblend, and makes the transition into<lb break="yes"/>trapp or grunstein. This trapp is found in stratified masses<lb break="yes"/>declining 70° towards the north, or in balls with concen-<lb break="no"/>tric strata, which, interspersed in calcareous clay, form<lb break="yes"/>pyramidal hills; sometimes the transition argillaceous<lb break="yes"/>schist of <persName key="werner_ag" >Werner</persName> is interspersed in green and very heavy<lb break="yes"/>argillaceous schist, which consists of hornblend and argil-<lb break="no"/>laceous schist intimately mixed together. The same argil-<lb break="no"/>laceous schist makes a transition near the Quebrada de<lb break="yes"/>Piedras Azules into the primitive argillaceous schist above<lb break="yes"/>which it lies. The trapp or grunstein contains also foliace-<lb break="no"/>ous olivin, crystallized in pyramids of four faces, a fossil<lb break="yes"/>which M. <persName key="freiesleben_jc" >Friesleben</persName> discovered on our tour into Bohemia,<lb break="yes"/>and deseribed in the Mineralogical Journal of Freyberg,<lb break="yes"/>augite with a shelly fracture, leucite in dodecaedra, the<lb break="yes"/>sides of the holes and cavities of which are covered with<lb break="yes"/>green earth like that of Verona, and a substance which<lb break="yes"/>has the splendour of mother-of-pearl, and which I consi-<lb break="no"/>der as zeolite. All these interspersed fossils increase to-<lb break="no"/>wards Parapara, and the trapp there forms real amygdalite.<lb break="yes"/>Above this amygdalite, near the hill Florez, at the entrance<lb break="yes"/>into the large valley of Orinoco, lies that remarkable stone<lb break="yes"/>which is scarce in Europe, and which <persName key="werner_ag">Werner</persName> describes<lb break="yes" />under the name of porphyry schist. The hornschist of<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="charpentier_jfwv">Charpentier</persName>, a kind of rock which accompanies basaltes,<lb break="yes"/>forms groups of irregular columns, and by the impression<lb break="yes"/>of the ferns which it contains in the middle of the moun-<lb break="no"/>tains, as discovered by M. <persName key="reuss_01">Reuss</persName>, proves that it is not of<lb break="yes"/>volcanic origin. The porphyry schist of Parapara is a green<lb break="yes"/>mass of sonorous stone, which is very hard, acute angled,<lb break="yes"/>and has transparent fragments on the edges: it strikes fire<lb break="yes"/>with steel, and contains vitreous feldspar. I did not ex-<lb break="no"/>pect to find this stone again in <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>; it however<lb break="yes" />does not form here such groups of grotesque appearance as<lb break="yes" />in Bohemia, and on mount Eugoneide in the Venetian ter-<lb break="no" />ritories, where I have seen it.</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#c">III. <hi rendition="#i">Alluvial Mountains</hi>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>These secondary formations, which are of later origin<lb break="yes"/>than the organic bodies of the earth, follow each other in<lb break="yes"/>the order of their relative age, as in the plains of Europe,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">and</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="177" facs="#f0028"/> and as has been mentioned by that excellent geologist M.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="buch_lv">Von Buch</persName>, in his Mineralogical Description of the County<lb break="yes"/>of Glatz in Silesia, a small work, which contains valuable<lb break="yes"/>ideas and interesting observations.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I found here two formations of compact limestone. The<lb break="yes"/>one makes a transition into the small grained and imper-<lb break="no"/>ceptibly foliaceous limestone, and is identic with the lime-<lb break="no"/>stone of the high <placeName key="alpen">Alps</placeName>; the other is compact, exceedingly<lb break="yes"/>homogeneous, with several petrifactions of shells, and ana-<lb break="no"/>logous to the limestone of Jura, Pappenheim, Gibraltar,<lb break="yes"/>Verona, Dalmatia, and Suez; a formation of foliaceous<lb break="yes"/>gypsum, and another mixed with clay, containing common<lb break="yes"/>salt and rock oil. The saline clay which I always found<lb break="yes"/>accompanied with rock salt in the Tyrol, Steyermark, and<lb break="yes"/>Salzbourg in Swisserland; marl schist stratified in lime-<lb break="no"/>stone of the <placeName key="alpen" >Alps</placeName>, and two formations of sandstone, one<lb break="yes" />of which is older and almost without petrifactions, some-<lb break="no" />times small and large-grained sandstone of the llanos, and<lb break="yes" />the other full of the remains of marine animals, which<lb break="yes" />forms the transition into the compact limestone.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The blue limestone of the <placeName key="alpen">Alps</placeName>, with white veins of cal-<lb break="no"/>careous spar, is found on the micaceous schist lying upon<lb break="yes"/>the Quebrada Secca near Tuy to the east from the Punta<lb break="yes"/>Delgada, on the road from Cumana, on the Impossible<lb break="yes"/>towards Bordones, on the island of Trinidad, and on the<lb break="yes"/>mountain Paria. This limestone contains here, as in Swis-<lb break="no"/>serland, three formations arranged under each other:&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>1st, Repeated strata of black marl schist; marl schist, or<lb break="yes"/>cupreous schist of Thuringia, mixed with pyrites, and earth<lb break="yes"/>pitch on the Cuchivana near Cumanacoa. This clay con-<lb break="no"/>tains carbon, and absorbs the oxygen of the atmospheric<lb break="yes"/>air. 2d, Saline clay mixed with rock salt and crystallized<lb break="yes"/>gypsum, in which the salt pits of <placeName key="araga">Araga</placeName>, Pozuelas, and<lb break="yes" />Margaret&#x2019;s Island are placed. 3d, Small-grained sand-<lb break="no" />stone, with a calcareous base, almost without petrifactions<lb break="yes" />of shells, always penetrated by water, and sometimes with<lb break="yes" />brown strata of ferruginous earth on the Cocollard, Tamir-<lb break="no" />quiri. I am not certain whether the last-mentioned stone<lb break="yes" />lies on the limestone, or is not sometimes covered by it.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>This limestone serves as the base for a newer one. It is<lb break="yes" />exceedingly white and compact, full of holes (Cueva del<lb break="yes" />Guacharo, in which thousands of birds reside, and among<lb break="yes" />which is a new genus of Caprimulgus, from which a kind<lb break="yes"/>of fat much used in the country is obtained, Cueva del<lb break="yes"/>S. Juan, Cueva del Cuchivano); sometimes porous like<lb break="yes"/>the Franconian, and forms grotesque rocks (Morros de<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">S. Juan</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="178" facs="#f0029"/> S. Juan, de S. Sebastian). It contains strata of black<lb break="yes"/>hornstone, which passes into siliceous schist or Lydian<lb break="yes"/>stone (Morro de <placeName key="barcelona" >Barcelona</placeName>) and Egyptian jasper to the<lb break="yes"/>south of Curataquiche. Over this compact limestone is<lb break="yes"/>placed, as on Jura, very beautiful alabaster in large masses<lb break="yes"/>at Soro, in Golfo Triste. All this gypsum contains sulphur<lb break="yes"/>as well as the gypsum of Bex and Kretzetzow, and in the<lb break="yes"/>Carpathians. This formation of limestone, with black<lb break="yes"/>hornstone and gypsum, seems also to occur in the <placeName key="amazonasregion">valley<lb break="yes"/>of the Amazon</placeName> and Rio Negro, where they were found by<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">la Condamine</persName> near Cuen&#x00E7;a, between Racam and Guyausi,<lb break="yes"/>on the east side of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>This limestone and gypsum (the latter in the <placeName key="llanodebarcelona">llano of<lb break="yes"/>Barcelona</placeName> near Cachipé) are often covered in the valleys of<lb break="yes"/>Orinoco, and the <placeName key="amazonasregion">Amazon river</placeName>, by a conglomeration or<lb break="yes"/>sandstone, with large strata, in which the remains of lime-<lb break="no"/>stone, quartz, Lydian stone, all of greater antiquity than<lb break="yes"/>the sandstone itself, occur. This conglomeration, breccia,<lb break="yes"/>which has a similarity to that of <placeName key="aranjuez">Aranjuez</placeName>, Salzburg, &amp;c.,<lb break="yes"/>is extended over more than 18000 square miles in the<lb break="yes"/>llanos. It contains strata with small grains and traces of<lb break="yes"/>brown and red iron ore. I have never seen petrifactions<lb break="yes"/>in it.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The sandstone full of shells and coral, without any traces<lb break="yes"/>of crocodiles in a country which unfortunately contains so<lb break="yes" />many, and which passes into limestone, but on closer ex-<lb break="no" />amination is intermixed with grains of quartz, is of newer<lb break="yes" />formation, and always nearer the coasts: <placeName key="puntaaraya">P. Araya</placeName>, Cabo<lb break="yes"/>Blanco, Castillo, S. Antonio de Cumana.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It may perhaps be expected that I should close this de-<lb break="no" />scription with an enumeration of the volcanie productions<lb break="yes" />of this country, which has been convulsed by the most<lb break="yes" />terrible earthquakes, the high summits of which (Duida),<lb break="yes" />and lately some of its caverns (Cueva du Cuchivano), vomit<lb break="yes" />forth flames, where boiling springs are thrown up from<lb break="yes" />Golfo Triste to the Sierra Nevada de Merida (the springs<lb break="yes" />of Triachevar I found to be 72°&#x00B7;3 of <persName key="reaumur_rafd" >Reaumur</persName>), where, on<lb break="yes"/>the coast of Paria, near Cumacator, there is an air volcano,<lb break="yes"/>the noise of which is heard at a great distance, and sul-<lb break="no"/>phureous pits in several places as at Guadaloupe&#x2014;a coun-<lb break="no"/>try where, in the extent of several square miles, the whole<lb break="yes"/>surface is undermined and hollow (Tierra Hueca de Cari-<lb break="no"/>aco), where, in the year 1766, the earth, after being agi-<lb break="no"/>tated eleven months by violent shocks, opened on all sides,<lb break="yes"/>and poured forth sulphureous water and bitumen; and<lb break="yes"/>where, in the midst of the driest plains in the Mera de<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">Guanipa</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="179" facs="#f0030"/> Guanipa and du Cary, flames burst from the earth. But<lb break="yes"/>nature discharges me from this task. The effects of<lb break="yes"/>the volcanoes in this part of the world are very different<lb break="yes"/>from those seen in Europe. Great and melancholy in their<lb break="yes"/>consequences, they change the rocks which are exposed to<lb break="yes"/>their action. The immense revolution of Pelileo and Ton-<lb break="no"/>guragua de Zuito has not only covered the earth with<lb break="yes"/>lava, but with clayey mud, deposited by the sulphureous<lb break="yes"/>water which spouted from the earth. The sulphureous<lb break="yes"/>gypsum, the mixture of sulphureous pyrites in all the<lb break="yes"/>rocks, even in granite, the bituminous saline clay, the<lb break="yes"/>rock oil, or asphaltum, which every where floats on the water<lb break="yes"/>or lies on the ground, the immeasurable quantity of rain-<lb break="no"/>water, and the lakes which penetrate into the earth heated<lb break="yes"/>by the sun, the aqueous vapours and immense quantities of<lb break="yes"/>hydrogen gas every where disengaged, seem to be the prin-<lb break="no"/>cipal causes which contribute to produce these volcanic<lb break="yes"/>effects.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The sulphureous pits of Guadaloupe, of Montmisene,<lb break="yes"/>St. Christopher de l&#x2019;Oualiban, St. Lucia, and Montserrat,<lb break="yes" />are in all probability connected with those on the coast of<lb break="yes" />Paria. These volcanoes, however, belong rather to the pro-<lb break="no" />vince of natural philosophy than of mineralogy; and I must<lb break="yes" />visit other countries before I can venture to form any opi-<lb break="no" />nion on so difficult a subject. May Heaven avert from the<lb break="yes" />eastern side of New Andalusia such a catastrophe as that<lb break="yes" />which has convulsed the plains of Pelileo!</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back>
          <div type="editorial">
            <head>Abbildungen</head>
            <figure facs="1801-Esquisse_d_un-4.jpg"/>
          </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI> 