<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023299100">
                        <surname>Clark</surname>
                        <forename>Rex</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="stoeckli_mt">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stöckli</surname>
                        <forename>Matthias Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="schnidrig_bf">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schnidrig</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara Franziska</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.5.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.4.0" when="2018-09-02" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Personenmarkierung abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.3.0" when="2018-09-27" who="stoeckli_mt">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Personen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2018-09-27" who="schnidrig_bf">Markup: added placeName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Orte.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="240" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Letter from M. <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName> to M. <persName key="delambre_jbj" >Delambre</persName>, relative to<lb break="yes"/>his Travels in <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <opener>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#k">my respectable friend,</hi>
                    </salute>
                    <dateline>
                        <hi rendition="#et">Lima, December 25, 1802.</hi>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I AM just arrived from the interior of the country, where, in an exten-<lb break="no"/>sive plain, I made experiments on the small horary variations of the needle;<lb break="yes"/>and I learn with regret that the frigate Astigarraga, which was not to have<lb break="yes"/>gone this fortnight, has hastened her departure for Cadiz, and sails this<lb break="yes"/>very night. It is the first opportunity for sending to Europe that has oc-<lb break="no" />curred these five months in the solitudes of the southern ocean; and the<lb break="yes"/>want of leisure prevents my writing as I could wish to the National Insti-<lb break="no"/>tute, which has just bestowed on me the most signal mark of the interest and<lb break="yes"/>favor with which it honors me. It was a few days before my departure for<lb break="yes"/>Jaen and <placeName key="amazonasregion">Amazonia</placeName> that I received the letter dated 2 Pluviose, year 9,<lb break="yes"/>which that illustrious society adressed to me through you. It was two years<lb break="yes"/>in reaching me among the Cordilleras of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>. I received it the day<lb break="yes"/>after I had returned from a second expedition to the crater of the volcano<lb break="yes"/>Pichinca, to which I took an electrometer of <persName key="volta_agv">Volta</persName>. I measured its diame-<lb break="no"/>ter, which I found to be 752 fathoms, while that of Vesuvius is but 312.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A considerable time before I received your letter, I addressed three letters<lb break="yes"/>successively to the physical and mathematical class, two from Santa Fe de<lb break="yes"/>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>Bagota</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Bogota</corr>
                    </choice>, accompanied with a work on the genus Cinchona, or Quinquina, con-<lb break="no"/>sisting of specimens of the bark of seven species, coloured drawings represent-<lb break="no"/>ing those productions, with the anatomy of the flower which differs so much in<lb break="yes"/>the length of its stamina, and the flowers themselves dried with care. Dr.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> presented me with about 100 splendid drawings in large folio, repre-<lb break="no"/>senting the new genera and species of his manuscript Flora of <choice>
                        <sic>Bagota</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Bogota</corr>
                    </choice>. This<lb break="yes"/>collection, as interesting to the botanist as it is remarkable for the beauty of<lb break="yes"/>the colours, could not, in my opinion, be in better hands than those of Jus-<lb break="no"/>sieu, <persName key="lamarck_jbpadmd">Lamarck</persName>, and <persName key="desfontaines_rl">Desfontaines</persName>; I have therefore offered them to the Na-<lb break="no"/>tional Institute as a feeble mark of my attachment. This collection, toge-<lb break="no"/>ther with the drawings of the Cinchona, set off for Carthagena in the month<lb break="yes"/>of June of the present year, and M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> himself has undertaken to procure<lb break="yes"/>their conveyance to Paris. A third letter for the Institute left Quito with a<lb break="yes"/>geological collection of the productions of Pichinca, <choice>
                        <sic>Catopaxi</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Cotopaxi</corr>
                    </choice>, and Chim-<lb break="no"/>borasso.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The little leisure I have to day prevents me from giving you a sketch of<lb break="yes"/>my travels and accupations since our return from Rio Negro. You know it<lb break="yes"/>was at Havannah that we received the false intelligence of Captain <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin&#x2019;s</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>departure for Buenos Ayres. Faithful to the promise I had given to join<lb break="yes"/>him if I could, and persuaded that I should render greater service to the<lb break="yes"/>sciences by labouring in conjunction with the naturalists who accompany<lb break="yes"/>Captain <persName key="baudin_tn" >Baudin</persName>, I did not hesitate a moment in sacrificing the insignificant<lb break="yes"/>honor of completing my own expedition, and instantly hired a small vessel<lb break="yes"/>at <placeName key="batabano" >Bataban</placeName>, for Carthagena. Stormy weather prolonged this short passage<lb break="yes"/>above a month. The trade-winds had ceased in the South Sea, where I<lb break="yes"/>imagined I should find Captain <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin</persName>, and I undertook the difficult journey<lb break="yes"/>through Honda, Ilagué, the passage of the mountain of Quindin, Popayan,<lb break="yes"/>Pastos, and Quito. My health withstood, in a wonderful manner, the changes<lb break="yes"/>of climate to which we were exposed on this route; descending every day<lb break="yes"/>from snowy regions, at an elevation of 2,460 fathoms, into burning vallies,<lb break="yes"/>where <persName key="reaumur_rafd">Reaumur&#x2019;s</persName> thermometer never falls below 26° or 24°.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>My companion, M. <choice><sic><persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bompland</persName></sic><corr type="editorial"><persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName></corr></choice>, whose abilities, courage, and unwearied<lb break="yes"/>activity were of the greatest assistance to me in my botanical and anatomical<lb break="yes"/>researches, has been afflicted with tertian fevers for two months. The rainy<lb break="yes" />season overtook us in the most critical part of our journey, the elevated plain<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">of</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="241" facs="#f0002"/> of Pastos; and after travelling eight months, we arrived at Quito, where<lb break="yes"/>we heard that Captain <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin</persName> had taken the route from west to east by the<lb break="yes"/>Cape of Good Hope. Accustomed to disappointments, we consoled our-<lb break="no"/>selves with the idea of having made such great sacrifices with good inten-<lb break="no"/>tions. Looking at our collection of observations of different kinds, our<lb break="yes"/>drawings and experiments on the atmosphere of the Cordilleras, we did not<lb break="yes"/>regret having traversed countries which have in a great measure never been<lb break="yes" />visited by any naturalist. We felt that man must not rely upon any thing<lb break="yes"/>but what he can produce by his own energy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The province of Quito, the most elevated plain in the world, and con-<lb break="no"/>vulsed by the great catastrophe of the 4th of Feb. 1797, afforded us a vast<lb break="yes"/>field for physical observations. Volcanoes of such magnitude, that the<lb break="yes"/>flames frequently rise 1000 yards above their summits, have never yet pro-<lb break="no"/>duced a drop of melted lava: they vomit forth water, sulphureous hydrogen<lb break="yes"/>gas, mud, and carbonated clay. Since 1797, all this portion of the globe has<lb break="yes" />been in agitation; we every moment feel the most alarming shocks; and<lb break="yes"/>the subterraneous rumbling in the plains of Rio Bamba is like that of a<lb break="yes"/>mountain falling to ruins beneath our feet. The atmospheric air and humid<lb break="yes"/>earth appear to be the grand agents of these combustions and subterraneous<lb break="yes"/>fermentations, all the volcanoes being formed of decomposed porphyry.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It has hitherto been imagined at Quito, that 2,470 fathoms were the<lb break="yes"/>greatest elevation at which man can resist the rarefaction of the air. In<lb break="yes"/>March 1802, we passed several days in the great plains which surround the<lb break="yes"/>volcano of <placeName key="antisana" >Antisana</placeName>, at the height of 2,107 fathoms, where the oxen, when<lb break="yes"/>pursued, frequently vomit blood. On the 16th of March, we discovered a<lb break="yes"/>road upon the snow, by which, with a gentle acclivity, we ascended to an<lb break="yes"/>elevation of 2773 fathoms. The air there contained ,008 of carbonic acid,<lb break="yes"/>,218 of oxygen, and<choice>
                        <sic>, 774</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial"> ,774</corr>
                    </choice> of azote. <persName key="reaumur_rafd">Reaumur&#x2019;s</persName> thermometer was only 1,5°.<lb break="yes"/>it was by no means cold, but the blood issued from our mouth and eyes.<lb break="yes"/>The situation would not admit of our making experiments with <persName key="borda_jcd" >Borda&#x2019;s</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>compass, excepting in a cavern lower down, at 2467 fathoms: the intensity<lb break="yes"/>of the magnetic power was greater at this height than at Quito, in the pro-<lb break="no"/>portion of 230 to 218; but it must not be forgotten, that frequently the<lb break="yes"/>number of oscillations increases when the inclination is diminished, and that<lb break="yes"/>the intensity is augmented by the mass of mountains, the porphyry in which<lb break="yes"/>affects the magnet. In our expedition to Chimborasso, the 23d of June,<lb break="yes"/>1802, we proved, that, with patience, it is possible to endure a still greater<lb break="yes"/>degree of rarefaction of the atmosphere. We reached 500 fathoms higher<lb break="yes"/>than <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName> (at Carazon); and at Chimborasso we carried instru-<lb break="no"/>ments to the elevation of 6,062 yards, where we observed the mercury of the<lb break="yes"/>barometer descend to 13in. 11,2 lines; the thermometer was 1°,3 below<lb break="yes"/>zero. We likewise bled here at the mouth. Our Indians left us as usual.<lb break="yes" />M. <choice><sic><persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bompland</persName></sic><corr type="editorial"><persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName></corr></choice> and M. <persName key="montufarylarrea_c">Montufar</persName>, son of the <persName key="montufarylarrea_jpd">Marquis of Selvalegre</persName>, of Quito,<lb break="yes"/>were the only persons who remained with me. We felt a certain indisposi-<lb break="no"/>tion, debility, and inclination to vomit, which are certainly owing as much to<lb break="yes"/>the want of oxygen in those regions as to the rarefaction of the air. I found<lb break="yes"/>only ,20 of oxygen at this immense height. A tremendous cleft prevented<lb break="yes"/>us from reaching the very summit of Chimborasso, of which we only wanted<lb break="yes"/>472 yards. You know that the height of this immense colossus is still un-<lb break="no"/>certain; that <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName>, who measured it at a great distance, makes it<lb break="yes"/>about 6,440 yards, while Don <persName key="juanysantacilia_j" >George Juan</persName> computes it to be 6,760; and<lb break="yes"/>that this difference does not arise from the different heights which these as-<lb break="no"/>tronomers adopt for the signal of Carabura. In the plain of Tapia I mea-<lb break="no"/>sured a base of 1,702 metres. According to two geometrical operations, I<lb break="yes"/>calculate Chimborasso at 6,534 yards above the level of the sea.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="242" facs="#f0003"/>
                <p>The volcano of Tunguragua has greatly diminished since the time of <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La<lb break="yes"/>Condamine</persName>: instead of 2,620 fathoms, I find that it is now not more than<lb break="yes"/>2,531; and I am convinced that this difference does not arise from an error<lb break="yes" />in the operations, because in my measures of Cayamba, <placeName key="antisana">Antisana</placeName>, <choice>
                        <sic>Cotapaxi</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Cotopaxi</corr>
                    </choice>,<lb break="yes"/>Iliniza, I differ but 10 or 15 fathoms from the results of <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName> and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="bouguer_p">Bouguer</persName>. All the inhabitants, likewise, of this unfortunate country say that<lb break="yes"/>Tunguragua is perceptibly diminished. On the other hand, I find Cotopaxi,<lb break="yes"/>which has had such dreadful eruptions, of the same height as in 1744, or, if<lb break="yes" />any thing, rather higher, which may perhaps proceed from some error of<lb break="yes"/>mine. But the stony summit of Cotopaxi shews that it is a chimney capable<lb break="yes"/>of resistance and of preserving its figure. The operations which we un-<lb break="no"/>dertook, from January to July, in the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> of Quito, gave the inhabitants<lb break="yes"/>the melancholy information that the crater of Pichinca, which <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>saw full of snow, burns afresh; and that Chimborasso, which has been<lb break="yes"/>thought so tranquil and innocent, has been a volcano, and will perhaps be so<lb break="yes"/>again. We found burnt rocks and pumice-stone at the height of 6,062<lb break="yes"/>yards. Unfortunate will it be for mankind if the volcanic fire (for the whole<lb break="yes"/>elevated plain of Quito may be said to be a single volcano with several sum-<lb break="no"/>mits) breaks forth from Chimborasso. It has frequently been asserted that<lb break="yes"/>this mountain is granit, but it contains not an atom of that substance. It is<lb break="yes"/>composed of porphyry here and there in columns, inclosing vitreous feld-<lb break="no"/>spar and olivine. This stratum of porphyry is 3,800 yards in depth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Besides the elephants&#x2019; teeth which we sent to M. <persName key="cuvier_g" >Cuvier</persName>, from the plain<lb break="yes"/>of Santa Fé, at an elevation of 2,700 yards, we have preserved for him se-<lb break="no"/>veral finer; some of them belonging to the carnivorous elephant, and others<lb break="yes"/>somewhat different from those of <placeName key="afrika" >Africa</placeName>, from the valley of Timana, the<lb break="yes"/>town of Ibarra and Chili. Thus it is ascertained that this carnivorous mon-<lb break="no"/>ster existed from the Ohio, or 50° of north latitude to 35° south.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have spent a very agreeable time at Quito. The president of the au-<lb break="no"/>dience, Baron <persName key="carondelet_flhd">de Carondelet</persName>, has loaded us with favors; and during my<lb break="yes"/>peregrinations of three years, I have not had reason to complain one single<lb break="yes"/>day of the agents of the Spanish government which has treated me with a<lb break="yes"/>delicacy and distinction that entitle it to my everlasting gratitude. How<lb break="yes"/>times and manners have changed!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After passing through <placeName key="assuay">Assonay</placeName> and Cuen&#x00E7;a, where we were entertained<lb break="yes"/>with bull-fights, we took the road to Oxa, to complete our labours on the<lb break="yes"/>Cinchona. We then spent a month in the province of Ja&#x00EB;n de Bracamorros<lb break="yes"/>and the Pongos of the <placeName key="amazonasregion" >Amazons</placeName>, whose banks are embellished with the <hi rendition="#i">An-<lb break="no"/>diva</hi> and <persName key="bougainville_lad">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Bougainvill&#x00E6;a</hi>
                    </persName> of <persName key="jussieu_ald">Jussieu</persName>. It appeared to me an interesting object<lb break="yes"/>to fix the longitude of Tomependa and Cluechungat, where <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine&#x2019;s</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>map begins, and to connect those points with the coast. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>could ascertain only the longitude of the mouth of the Napa; time-keepers<lb break="yes"/>were not then in existence, so that the longitudes of these countries must re-<lb break="no"/>quire correcting. My chronometer, by <persName key="berthoud_l">Louis Berthoud</persName>, is wonderfully cor-<lb break="no"/>rect, as I find by my own observations and by comparing point for point my<lb break="yes"/>differences of the meridian with those found by the expedition under M.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="fidalgo_jfd">Fidalgo</persName>, which, by the king&#x2019;s command, has been making trigonometrical<lb break="yes"/>operations from Cumana to Carthagena.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From the <placeName key="amazonasregion">Amazons</placeName> we crossed the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> to the mines of Hualgayoe,<lb break="yes"/>which yield a million of piastres per annum, and where the silver ore is found<lb break="yes"/>at the depth of 2,065 fathoms. We descended by Cascamusca, or the pa-<lb break="no"/>lace of <persName key="atahualpa" >Atahualpa</persName>, where I took drawings of the arches of the Peruvian<lb break="yes"/>vaults, to Truxillo, pursuing our route through the deserts along the coast of<lb break="yes"/>the South Sea to Lima, where, during half the year, the sky is obscured by<lb break="yes"/>thick vapours. I hastened to reach Lima, to observe there the passage of<lb break="yes"/>Mercury on the 9th of Nov. 1802.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">Our</fw>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="243" facs="#f0004"/>
                <p>Our collections of plants, and the drawings which I have made of the ana-<lb break="no"/>tomy of the genera, conformably to the ideas communicated to me by M.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="jussieu_ald">Jussieu</persName>, have been considerably augmented by the riches we discovered in<lb break="yes"/>the province of Quito, at Loxa, near the <placeName key="amazonasregion">Amazons</placeName>, and in the Cordilleras of<lb break="yes"/>Peru. We have found many of the plants described by <persName key="jussieu_jd">Joseph de Jussieu</persName> as<lb break="yes" />the <hi rendition="#i">Lloque affinis, Quillaj&#x00E6;,</hi> &#x0026;c. We have a new species of <hi rendition="#i">Jussi&#x00E6;a,</hi> which<lb break="yes"/>is charming, of <hi rendition="#i">colletia,</hi> several passion-flowers, and the coranthus in the form<lb break="yes"/>of a tree 60 feet in height. We are, in particular, very rich in palm-trees<lb break="yes"/>and grasses, on which M. <choice><sic><persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bompland</persName></sic><corr type="editorial"><persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName></corr></choice> has drawn up a very extensive work.<lb break="yes"/>We have now 3,784 very complete descriptions in Latin, and nearly one-<lb break="maybe"/>third of that number of plants in our herbaries, which we have not had time<lb break="yes"/>to describe. There is not a vegetable but what we can point out the rock it<lb break="yes" />inhabits, and the number of fathoms it is in height; so that the geography of<lb break="yes"/>plants will find in our manuscripts very accurate materials. To render them<lb break="yes"/>more perfect, M. <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bompland</persName> and myself have frequently written separate de-<lb break="no"/>scriptions of the same plant: but two-thirds, and more, of the descriptions<lb break="yes"/>are the fruit of M. <choice><sic><persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bompland</persName></sic><corr type="editorial"><persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland&#x2019;s</persName></corr></choice> assiduity alone; his zeal and exertions for the<lb break="yes"/>promotion of the sciences cannot be too much admired. We compared our<lb break="yes"/>herbaries with those of M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, and consulted a vast number of books in<lb break="yes"/>the immense library of that great man. We are persuaded that we have<lb break="yes"/>many new genera and new species; but it requires much time and great la-<lb break="no"/>bour to decide what is really new. We likewise have a silicious substance<lb break="yes"/>resembling the <hi rendition="#i">tabascher</hi> of the East Indies, which M. <persName key="macee_01">Macé</persName> has analysed.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>Is</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">It</corr>
                    </choice> exists in the joints of a gigantic species of grass, which is confounded<lb break="yes"/>with the bamboo, but the flower of which differs from the <hi rendition="#i">bambusa</hi> of <persName key="schreber_jcdev" >Schrei-<lb break="no"/>ber</persName>. I know not whether M. <persName key="fourcroy_afd">Fourcroy</persName> ever received the milk of the <hi rendition="#i">vege-<lb break="no"/>table cow</hi> (a tree so called by the Indians), which, when treated with nitric<lb break="yes"/>acid, yielded a caoutchouc with an aromatic smell, but which, far from being<lb break="yes" />caustic and injurious like all vegetable milks, is nourishing and agreeable to<lb break="yes"/>drink. We discovered it on the road to the Oronoko, in a plantation where<lb break="yes"/>the negroes drink it in great quantity. I likewise sent to M. <persName key="fourcroy_afd">Fourcroy</persName>, by<lb break="yes"/>way of Guadaloupe, and to Sir <persName key="banks_j">Joseph Banks</persName>, by way of Trinidad, our<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Dapiché,</hi> or oxygenated white caoutchouc, which oozes from the roots of a<lb break="yes"/>tree in the forests of Pimichin, in the remotest corner of the earth near the<lb break="yes"/>sources of Rio Negro.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I shall not go to the Philippines, but shall proceed by way of <placeName key="acapulco">Acapulco</placeName>,<lb break="yes"/>Mexico, and the Havannah, to Europe, and hope to embrace you in Septem-<lb break="no"/>ber or October, 1803, at Paris.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#et">Health and respect,<lb break="yes"/>(Signed) HUMBOLDT.</hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <postscript>
                    <p>In February I shall be at Mexico; in June, at the Havannah. I think of<lb break="yes"/>nothing but the preservation and publication of the manuscripts I possess.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 