<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023299100">
                        <surname>Clark</surname>
                        <forename>Rex</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="stoeckli_mt">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stöckli</surname>
                        <forename>Matthias Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="schnidrig_bf">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schnidrig</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara Franziska</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.5.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.4.0" when="2018-09-28" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Personenmarkierung abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.3.0" when="2018-09-27" who="stoeckli_mt">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Personen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2018-09-27" who="schnidrig_bf">Markup: added placeName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Orte.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="573" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">letter from mr. humboldt to prof. <persName key="cavanilles_aj">cavanilles</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Whilst we are anxiously expecting that Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>who has arrived at Paris on his way home, will soon pub-<lb break="no"/>lish some account of his travels, we doubt not but that, in<lb break="yes"/>the mean time, the following extract of a letter from this<lb break="yes"/>celebrated naturalist to the late Professor <persName key="cavanilles_aj">Cavanilles</persName>, will be<lb break="yes" />read with considerable interest. It has appeared in the 18th<lb break="yes" />number of the <hi rendition="#i">Anales de Ciencias Naturales,</hi> and is dated<lb break="yes"/>Mexico, April the 22d, 1803.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After remarking that both M. <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bompland</persName> and himself<lb break="yes"/>had preserved the most vigorous health, notwithstanding<lb break="yes"/>the want of shelter and hunger they endured, particularly<lb break="yes"/>in passing over the deserts, in a journey across the immense<lb break="yes"/>continent of <placeName key="suedamerika" >South America</placeName>, through the countries border-<lb break="no"/>ing on the <placeName key="amazonas">Amazon</placeName>, to Lima, Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>, so far from<lb break="yes" />confirming what has been said of the enervating effects of<lb break="yes" />these latitudes, supposed to disqualify for every mental<lb break="yes" />exertion, asserts on the contrary that they never found their<lb break="yes" />heads clearer than when contemplating the magnificent<lb break="yes"/>scenery which nature displays in those regions. They could<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">bear,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="574" facs="#f0002"/> bear, without inconvenience, an exposure for three hours<lb break="yes"/>together to the burning sun of <placeName key="acapulco">Acapulco</placeName> and Guayaquil,<lb break="yes"/>tread the glaciers of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>, cross the arid deserts, pe-<lb break="no"/>netrate the thick woods, and wade through the miry mo-<lb break="no"/>rasses, without feeling their courage fail, or even their<lb break="yes"/>spirits in the least depressed.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The travellers left Lima on the 25th of December 1802,<lb break="yes"/>stopped two months at Guayaquil, where they had the<lb break="yes"/>satisfaction of the company of two distinguished botanists,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="tafalla_jj">Tafalla</persName> and <persName key="manzanilla_ja" >Manzanilla</persName>, in their botanical excursions, and<lb break="yes" />arrived at <placeName key="acapulco">Acapulco</placeName> on the 22d of March, after experiencing<lb break="yes"/>a dreadful storm off the Gulf of Nicoya.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The volcano of Cotopaxi, over which,&#x201D; says Mr.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>, &#x201C;I had passed calmly the preceding year, on<lb break="yes"/>the 5th of January made so terrible an explosion, that the<lb break="yes"/>noise of it was heard by us, sailing at the distance of six<lb break="yes"/>leagues. It vomited forth torrents of flame and showers of<lb break="yes"/>ashes, and the snow was detached from its summit; but it<lb break="yes"/>does not appear as yet to have done the smallest mischief,<lb break="yes"/>though, not being extinguished, the province of Quito is<lb break="yes"/>kept in a continual alarm.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;You know the ardent enthusiasm of my friend and<lb break="yes"/>companion <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bompland</persName>, and can judge of the botanical<lb break="yes"/>riches we must have acquired in passing through a country<lb break="yes"/>where no botanist had ever trod before, and where nature<lb break="yes"/>delights in producing vegetables so different in form and<lb break="yes"/>organization from all that are hitherto known. Our col-<lb break="no"/>lection exceeds 4,200 species, among which are a great<lb break="yes"/>number of new genera, and very many grasses and palms.<lb break="yes"/>It contains a hundred species of Melastoma, though all<lb break="yes"/>those of <persName key="linne_cv" >Linn&#x00E6;us</persName> are not found in it. We have described<lb break="yes"/>4,200 plants, and made a great number of drawings from<lb break="yes"/>living specimens. We cannot ascertain the actual number of<lb break="yes"/>nondescript plants till we return to Europe, and have an oppor-<lb break="no"/>tunity of comparing them with those that have been already<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">published;</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="575" facs="#f0003"/> published; but we hope to have amassed sufficient materials<lb break="yes"/>to form a work worthy the attention of naturalists. Com-<lb break="no"/>parative anatomy, as well as botany, has formed a pursuit<lb break="yes"/>in addition to the principal object of our journey, and we<lb break="yes"/>shall bring home many preparations made by my compa-<lb break="no"/>nion <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bompland</persName>. I have designed a number of profiles, or<lb break="yes"/>geographical charts, with hygrometrical and eudiometrical<lb break="yes"/>tables, &#x0026;c. to determine the physical qualities which have<lb break="yes"/>so much influence on vegetable physiology; in such a<lb break="yes"/>manner that I can set down in toises the elevation above<lb break="yes"/>the sea at which each species of the tropical trees is found.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>I</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">&#x201C;I</corr>
                    </choice> am sorry to see what has been written on the Cin-<lb break="no" />chonas, because science never profits by the admixture of<lb break="yes" />personalities with these discussions, and am truly afflicted<lb break="yes" />at the manner in which the venerable <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> has been<lb break="yes"/>treated. The most unfounded notions have been propa-<lb break="no"/>gated in Europe of this celebrated naturalist, who treated<lb break="yes"/>us at Santafé with that frankness which seems the peculiar<lb break="yes"/>character of a <persName key="banks_j">Banks</persName>, communicating without reserve all<lb break="yes"/>his possessions in botany, zoology, and physics, and per-<lb break="no"/>mitting us to take notes of every thing we wished respecting<lb break="yes"/>the new genera of the Flora of Santafé. He is now old;<lb break="yes"/>but it is astonishing what he has done and is doing for<lb break="yes"/>posterity, and we cannot but admire that one man should<lb break="yes"/>have conceived and executed such vast designs.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;M. <persName key="lopezruiz_sj">Lopez</persName> showed me his memoir on Cinchona before<lb break="yes"/>it was printed, and I pointed out to him that in it was con-<lb break="no"/>tained evidence that <persName key="mutis_jc" >Mutis</persName> had discovered the Cinchona in<lb break="yes"/>the mountains of Tena in 1772, whereas M. <persName key="lopezruiz_sj" >Lopez</persName> himself<lb break="yes"/>had only seen it near Honda in 1774.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;With regard to the tree that affords the fine bark of<lb break="yes" />Loxa, having examined it in its native soil, we are of opi-<lb break="no" />nion that it has not yet been even described. We have<lb break="yes"/>compared it with the Cinchonas which we have seen in the<lb break="yes"/>provinces of Santafé, Payau, Peru, and Jaen; in its foliage<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">it</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="576" facs="#f0004"/> it resembles Cinchona glandulifera of the Flora Peruviana,<lb break="yes"/>but its flowers are different. We have sent to France a<lb break="yes"/>collection relative to the Cinchon&#x00E6;, consisting of fine<lb break="yes"/>specimens of the barks, with branches in flower and in<lb break="yes"/>fruit, and splendid coloured drawings presented to us by<lb break="yes"/>the generous <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>. To these we have added fossil bones<lb break="yes"/>of elephants, found in the Cordilleras, at an elevation of<lb break="yes"/>1400 toises<note place="foot" n="*">We understand that these subjects have been deposited in the national<lb break="yes"/>museum at Paris.</note>.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In speaking of that colossal grass called in Santafé <hi rendition="#i">Gua-<lb break="no"/>duas,</hi> which produces a siliceous earth similar to that of the<lb break="yes"/>bamboo, the writer remarks that this plant forms a new<lb break="yes"/>genus very different from Arundo of <persName key="linne_cv" >Linn&#x00E6;us</persName>, and from<lb break="yes"/>Bambusa of <persName key="schreber_jcdev">Schreber</persName>. It was not without great difficulty<lb break="yes"/>that they discovered the flowers of this plant which the In-<lb break="no"/>dians deny ever to bear any, and which even botanists who<lb break="yes"/>have observed it for thirty years in countries where it is very<lb break="yes"/>abundant, have never seen in blossom. Our travellers,<lb break="yes"/>however, were more fortunate, meeting with it in flower<lb break="yes"/>in one of the most remote corners of the world, on the<lb break="yes"/>Casiquiare, which unites the Oronoko with the Marignon,<lb break="yes"/>and afterwards in the valley of Cauca, in the province of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>Popayau</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Popayan</corr>
                    </choice>.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 