<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023299100">
                        <surname>Clark</surname>
                        <forename>Rex</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="stoeckli_mt">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stöckli</surname>
                        <forename>Matthias Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="schnidrig_bf">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schnidrig</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara Franziska</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.5.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.4.0" when="2018-09-02" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Personenmarkierung abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.3.0" when="2018-09-27" who="stoeckli_mt">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Personen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2018-09-27" who="schnidrig_bf">Markup: added placeName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Orte.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="237" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Account of the Travels of</hi> M. <persName key="humboldt_av" >A. <hi rendition="#k">de Humboldt</hi>
                    </persName>
                    <hi rendition="#i">in<lb break="yes"/>
                        <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>, extracted from some of his Letters</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">From <hi rendition="#i">Magazin Encyclopédique,</hi> Thermidor, an. 11.</note>.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">M.</hi>
                    <persName key="humboldt_wv">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt&#x2019;s</hi> brother</persName>, who is now at Rome, received<lb break="yes"/>from him lately three letters: one dated Quito, June 3,<lb break="yes"/>1802; another, Cuen&#x00E7;a, July 13, 1802; and the third, Lima,<lb break="yes"/>the capital of Peru, November 25, 1802. They announce<lb break="yes"/>that M. <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName> will soon return, and that he expected<lb break="yes" />to land in the month of August or September at Cadiz, or<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="acoruna">Corunna</placeName>; but the last of his letters in particular is the most<lb break="yes"/>interesting. In the following extract from it care has been<lb break="yes"/>taken to insert every thing worthy of attention in the other<lb break="yes"/>two:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <opener>
                        <salute>
                            <hi rendition="#k">my dear brother,</hi>
                        </salute>
                        <dateline>
                            <hi rendition="#et">Lima, Nov. 25, 1802.</hi>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>You must have learned by my preceding letters that I<lb break="yes"/>had reached Quito, at which we arrived by traversing the<lb break="yes"/>snow of Quiridian and Tolima; for as the cordillera of the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> forms three separate branches, and as we were at Santa<lb break="yes"/>Fé de Bogota, on that which is the most eastern, it was ne-<lb break="no"/>cessary to cross the highest to approach the coasts of the<lb break="yes"/>South Sea. Oxen are the only animals which can be employ-<lb break="no"/>ed in this passage for transporting baggage. Travellers in<lb break="yes"/>general are carried by men called <hi rendition="#i">largeros.</hi> They have a<lb break="yes"/>chair, in which the traveller is seated, tied to their back;<lb break="yes"/>they travel about four hours journey every day, and in five<lb break="yes"/>or six weeks earn only fourteen piastres. We preferred<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">travelling</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="238" facs="#f0002"/> travelling on foot; and the weather being exceedingly fine,<lb break="yes"/>we spent only seventeen days in these solitudes, which ex-<lb break="no"/>hibit no trace of their having ever been inhabited: we slept<lb break="yes"/>in huts constructed of the leaves of the heliconia, which<lb break="yes"/>travellers carry with them on purpose. On the western side<lb break="yes"/>of the <placeName key="anden" >Andes</placeName> there are marshes in which we sunk up to the<lb break="yes"/>knees. The weather had changed, and during the last days<lb break="yes"/>of our journey there fell such torrents of rain that our boots<lb break="yes"/>rotted on our legs; and we arrived at Carthago with our<lb break="yes"/>legs naked and covered with bruises, but enriched with a<lb break="yes"/>beautiful collection of new plants, of which I have a great<lb break="yes"/>number of drawings.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>From Carthago we went to Popayan by Buga, crossing<lb break="yes"/>the beautiful valley of the river Cauca, and having always<lb break="yes"/>at our sides the mountain of Choca, and the platina mines<lb break="yes"/>which it contains.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>During the month of November 1801 we remained at<lb break="yes"/>Popayan, and went to visit the basaltic mountains of Ju-<lb break="no"/>lusuito; the mouths of the volcano of Puracé, which with<lb break="yes"/>a horrid noise throw out vapours of hydro-sulphurous water;<lb break="yes"/>and the porphyritic granites of Pisché, which form columns<lb break="yes"/>of from five to seven planes, similar to those which I re-<lb break="no"/>member to have seen in the Fuganean mountains of Italy,<lb break="yes"/>and which are described by <persName key="strange_j">Strange</persName>.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The greatest difficulty still remained; which was, to go<lb break="yes"/>from Popayan to Quito. It was necessary to cross the<lb break="yes"/>Paramos from Pasto, and even in the rainy season, which<lb break="yes"/>had already commenced. The name of Paramo is given in<lb break="yes"/>the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> to every place at the height of 1700 or 2000<lb break="yes"/>toises, where vegetation ceases, and where a cold which pe-<lb break="no"/>netrates to the bones is experienced. To avoid the heats<lb break="yes"/>of the valley of Patia, where people in the course of one<lb break="yes"/>night are seized with fevers which continue three or four<lb break="yes"/>months, and which are known under the name of <hi rendition="#i">calcutu-<lb break="no"/>ras de Patia</hi> (fevers of Patia), we passed the summit of<lb break="yes"/>the cordillera by horrid precipices, in order to proceed from<lb break="yes"/>Popayan to <placeName key="almager">Almager</placeName>, and thence to Pasto, situated at the<lb break="yes"/>bottom of a terrible volcano.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Nothing can be more frightful than the entrance and out-<lb break="no"/>let of this valley, in which we spent the Christmas holidays,<lb break="yes" />and where the inhabitants received us with the utmost hos-<lb break="no" />pitality. They were covered with thick forests, situated<lb break="yes" />among marshes where the mules sunk half up to the backs,<lb break="yes" />and we passed ravines so deep and so narrow that we thought<lb break="yes" />we were entering the galleries of a mine. The roads there-<lb break="no" />fore are paved with the bones of mules which have perished<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">here</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="239" facs="#f0003"/> here of cold and fatigue. The whole province of Pasto,<lb break="yes"/>comprehending the environs of Guachucal and Tuqueres,<lb break="yes"/>is a cold plain, almost above that point at which vegetation<lb break="yes"/>can take place, and surrounded by volcanoes and soufrieres<lb break="yes"/>which continually throw up clouds of smoke. The un-<lb break="no"/>fortunate inhabitants of these deserts have no other food<lb break="yes"/>but potatoes; and when these fail, as they did last year, they<lb break="yes"/>go into the mountains to eat the trunk of a small tree called<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">achupalla</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">pourretia pitcarnia</hi>). As this tree however is<lb break="yes"/>the food also of the bears of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>, the latter often<lb break="yes"/>dispute with them the only nourishment which these ele-<lb break="no"/>vated regions afford. To the north of the volcano of Pasto<lb break="yes"/>I discovered in the small Indian village of Voisaco, at the<lb break="yes"/>height of 1370 toises above the level of the sea, a red por-<lb break="no"/>phyry with an argillaceous base inclosing vitreous feldspar<lb break="yes"/>and hornstone, which has all the properties of the serpen-<lb break="no"/>tine of the Fichtel-Gebirge. This porphyry has very evi-<lb break="no"/>dent poles, and shows no attractive force. After having<lb break="yes"/>been wet day and night for two months, and exposed to the<lb break="yes"/>danger of drowning by a very sudden rise of the waters,<lb break="yes"/>accompanied with earthquakes, we arrived on the 6th of<lb break="yes"/>January 1802 at Quito, where the <persName key="montufarylarrea_jpd">marquis of Salvaalegre</persName> was<lb break="yes"/>so kind as to prepare for us a house, which after so many<lb break="yes"/>fatigues afforded us all the conveniences that we could have<lb break="yes"/>wished for at Paris, or at London.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Quito is a beautiful town, but the sky is dismal and cloudy.<lb break="yes" />The neighbouring mountains exhibit little verdure, and the<lb break="yes" />cold is very considerable. The great earthquake of Fe-<lb break="no" />bruary 4th 1797, which agitated the whole province, and de-<lb break="no" />stroyed in a moment from thity-five to forty thousand peo-<lb break="no" />ple, has also been fatal to the survivors. It has so changed<lb break="yes"/>the temperature of the air, that the thermometer generally<lb break="yes"/>stands at from 4° to 10° of <persName key="reaumur_rafd">Reaumur</persName>, and rarely ascends to<lb break="yes"/>16° or 17°; while <persName key="bouguer_p" >Bouguer</persName> always observed it at 15° or 16°.<lb break="yes" />Since that catastrophe there have been continual earth-<lb break="no" />quakes: and what shocks! It is probable that the whole<lb break="yes" />elevated part is only one volcano. What are called the<lb break="yes" />mountains of Cotopaxi and Pinchincha are only small sum-<lb break="no" />mits, the craters of which form different apertures all ter-<lb break="no" />minating in the same hollow. The earthquake of 1797 un-<lb break="no" />fortunately proved this hypothesis, for the earth everywhere<lb break="yes"/>opened and vomited up sulphur, water, &#x0026;c. Notwith-<lb break="no"/>standing these horrors and dangers with which nature has<lb break="yes"/>surrounded the inhabitants of Quito, they are cheerful, lively,<lb break="yes"/>and agreeable. Their town breathes nothing but pleasure;<lb break="yes"/>and no where does there appear so decided a taste for amuse-<lb break="no"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">ments.</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="240" facs="#f0004"/> ments. It is in this manner that man is accustomed to sleep<lb break="yes"/>soundly on the brink of a precipice.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We resided nearly eight months in the province of Quito;<lb break="yes"/>that is to say, from the beginning of January to the month<lb break="yes"/>of August, and employed that time in visiting the different<lb break="yes" />volcanoes. We examined in succession the summits of Pin-<lb break="no" />chincha, Cotopaxi, <placeName key="antisana">Antisana</placeName>, and Ilini&#x00E7;a, spending from<lb break="yes"/>a fortnight to three weeks on each of them; and always re-<lb break="no"/>turning in the intervals to Quito, which we left on the 9th<lb break="yes"/>of June 1802 to proceed to the environs of Chimbora&#x00E7;o,<lb break="yes"/>which is situated in the southern part of the province.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I twice ascended, viz. on the 26th and 28th of May 1802,<lb break="yes"/>to the edge of the crater of Pinchincha, a mountain which<lb break="yes" />overlooks the town of Quito. Before, no person, as far as<lb break="yes" />I know, except <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condamine</persName>, ever saw it; and <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condamine</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>himself arrived there only after five or six days of fruitless<lb break="yes"/>researches, and without instruments; and, on account of<lb break="yes"/>the excessive cold, could remain on it only twelve or fifteen<lb break="yes"/>minutes. I succeeded in carrying thither my instruments;<lb break="yes"/>I made important measurements, and collected some of the<lb break="yes"/>air to analyse it. The first time I ascended I was accom-<lb break="no"/>panied only by an Indian. As <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName> approached<lb break="yes" />the crater at the lower part of its edge covered with snow,<lb break="yes" />I made my first attempt by following his traces; but we<lb break="yes" />were in danger of perishing. The Indian fell into a fis-<lb break="no" />sure up to the breast; and we observed with horror that we<lb break="yes" />had walked on a bridge of frozen snow, for at the distance<lb break="yes" />of some paces from us there were holes through which day-<lb break="no" />light appeared. We then found ourselves on arches which<lb break="yes" />adhere to the very crater. Alarmed, but not discouraged,<lb break="yes"/>I changed my project. From the circumference of the cra-<lb break="no"/>ter there arise, projecting themselves as I may say over the<lb break="yes" />abyss, three peaks or rocks not covered with snow; because<lb break="yes" />the vapours exhaled from the mouth of the volcano conti-<lb break="no" />nually dissolve it. I climbed up one of these rocks, and<lb break="yes" />found at its summit a stone, which being supported at one<lb break="yes" />end only, and hollow below, projected over the precipice<lb break="yes" />in the form of a balcony. Here I stationed myself to make<lb break="yes" />experiments. But this stone was only about twelve feet in<lb break="yes" />length and six in breadth, and was strongly agitated by fre-<lb break="no" />quent shocks of an earthquake, of which I counted eighteen<lb break="yes" />in less than thirty minutes. That we might examine the<lb break="yes" />bottom of the crater better, we lay down on our bellies;<lb break="yes" />and I do not think that the imagination can conceive any<lb break="yes" />thing more gloomy and frightful than what we then saw.<lb break="yes"/>The mouth of the volcano forms a circular hole of nearly a<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">league</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="241" facs="#f0005"/> league in circumference, the edges of which, cut perpendi-<lb break="no"/>cularly, are covered with snow at the top. The inside is very<lb break="yes"/>black, but the gulph is so immense, that the summits of<lb break="yes"/>several mountains placed there can be distinguished. These<lb break="yes"/>summits seemed to be 300 toises below us: you may judge<lb break="yes"/>then where their bases must be. I have no doubt that the<lb break="yes"/>bottom of the crater is on a level with the town of Quito. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La<lb break="yes" />Condamine</persName> found this crater extinct, and even covered with<lb break="yes"/>snow; but we had melancholy news to carry to the inha-<lb break="no"/>bitants of Quito, that the volcano in their neighbourhood was<lb break="yes"/>now burning. We were convinced of this beyond all doubt<lb break="yes"/>by the most evident signs. When we approached the mouth<lb break="yes"/>of it we were almost suffocated by sulphureous vapours.<lb break="yes"/>We even saw blue flames moving about here and there, and<lb break="yes"/>every two or three minutes we experienced strong shocks of<lb break="yes"/>an earthquake, with which the edges of the crater were agi-<lb break="no"/>tated, and of which nothing was perceived at the distance<lb break="yes"/>of 100 toises. I suppose that the great catastrophe of Fe-<lb break="no"/>bruary 7th 1797 kindled up the flames also of Pinchincha.<lb break="yes"/>After visiting this mountain alone I returned two days after,<lb break="yes"/>accompanied by my friend <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName>, and <persName key="montufarylarrea_c">Charles de Mon-<lb break="no"/>tufar</persName> the son of the <persName key="montufarylarrea_jpd">marquis de Selvaalegre</persName>. We were fur-<lb break="no"/>nished with more instruments than the preceding time, and<lb break="yes"/>measured the diameter of the crater and the height of the<lb break="yes"/>mountain. We found the former to be 754 toises <note place="foot" n="*">The crater of Ve&#x017F;uvius is only 312 toises in diameter.</note>, and<lb break="yes"/>the latter 2477. In the interval of two days which took<lb break="yes"/>place between our excursions to Pinchincha we had a very<lb break="yes"/>violent earthquake at Quito. The Indians ascribed it to some<lb break="yes"/>powder which I must have thrown into the volcano.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>During our journey to the volcano of <placeName key="antisana" >Antisana</placeName>, the wea-<lb break="no"/>ther was so favourable that we ascended to the height of<lb break="yes"/>2773 toises. The barometer fell in that elevated region to<lb break="yes"/>14 inches 7 lines; and in consequenee of the rarity of the<lb break="yes"/>air the blood flowed from our lips, gums, and even eyes.<lb break="yes"/>We experienced extreme weakness, and one of the persons<lb break="yes"/>who accompanied us fainted. It was before thought im-<lb break="no"/>possible to ascend higher than the summit called Corazon,<lb break="yes"/>which is 2470 toises in height, and which <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>reached. On analysing the air brought from the highest<lb break="yes"/>point to which we ascended, it gave 0&#x00B7;008 of carbonic acid<lb break="yes"/>for 0&#x00B7;218 of oxygen gas.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We paid a visit also to the volcano of Cotopaxi, but it was<lb break="yes" />impossible for us to reach the mouth of the crater. It is not<fw type="catch" place="bottom">true</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="242" facs="#f0006"/> true that this mountain has become lower since the earth-<lb break="no"/>quake of 1797.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>On the 9th of June 1802 we left Quito to proceed to the<lb break="yes" />southern part of the province, where we wished to examine<lb break="yes" />and measure Chimbora&#x00E7;o and Tunguragua; and to take<lb break="yes" />a plan of the whole country convulsed by the grand cata-<lb break="no" />strophe of 1797. We succeeded in approaching to within<lb break="yes" />about 250 toises of the summit of the immense colossus of<lb break="yes" />Chimbora&#x00E7;o. A ridge of volcanic rocks, destitute of snow,<lb break="yes"/>facilitated our ascent. We ascended to the height of 3031<lb break="yes"/>toises, and felt ourselves incommoded in the same manner<lb break="yes"/>as we had been on the summit of <placeName key="antisana">Antisana</placeName>. Two or three<lb break="yes"/>days even after our return to the plain we were still subject<lb break="yes"/>to an indisposition, which we could ascribe only to the effect<lb break="yes" />of the air in these elevated regions, which by analysis gave<lb break="yes"/>us 20 hundreds of oxygen. The Indians by whom we were<lb break="yes"/>accompanied deserted us before we reached that height, say-<lb break="no"/>ing that we intended to kill them. <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName>, <persName key="montufarylarrea_c">Charles<lb break="yes"/>Montufar</persName>, and one of my domestics, who carried a part of<lb break="yes"/>my instruments, were the only persons who remained with<lb break="yes"/>me: nevertheless, we could have continued our journey to<lb break="yes"/>the top had we not been prevented by a fissure too deep to be<lb break="yes"/>crossed. We therefore thought proper to descend. Being<lb break="yes"/>ill secured from the cold of these elevated regions, we suf-<lb break="no"/>fered very much; and I in particular had the misfortune to<lb break="yes"/>lacerate my foot by a fall a few days before, which subjected<lb break="yes"/>me to great pain in a road where we every moment struck our<lb break="yes"/>toes against sharp stones, and were obliged to examine the<lb break="yes"/>ground at every step. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName> found the height of<lb break="yes"/>Chimbora&#x00E7;o to be nearly 3217 toises. Trigonometrical mea-<lb break="no"/>surement, which I made at two different times, gave 3267<lb break="yes"/>toises, and I have reason to place some confidence in my<lb break="yes"/>operations. All this enormous colossus, as well as all the<lb break="yes"/>high mountains of the <placeName key="anden" >Andes</placeName>, consists not of granite, but of<lb break="yes" />porphyry, from the base to the summit; and the porphyry<lb break="yes"/>is 1900 toises in thickness. The short stay which we made<lb break="yes"/>at that enormous height was dismal and melancholy: we<lb break="yes"/>were enveloped by a thick fog, which only suffered us from<lb break="yes"/>time to time to have a glimpse of the horrid abysses by which<lb break="yes"/>we were surrounded. No living creature, not even the con-<lb break="no"/>dour, which on <placeName key="antisana">Antisana</placeName> continually hovered over our<lb break="yes"/>heads, was to be seen. Small kinds of moss were the only<lb break="yes"/>organized beings which reminded us that we were still in the<lb break="yes"/>neighbourhood of the earth.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It is almost probable that Chimbora&#x00E7;o, like Pinchincha<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">and</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="243" facs="#f0007"/> and <placeName key="antisana" >Antisana</placeName>, is of a volcanic nature. The ridge on which<lb break="yes"/>we ascended consists of burnt and scorified rock, mixed with<lb break="yes"/>pumice stone. It resembles all the currents of lava in this<lb break="yes"/>country; and continues beyond that point where I was ob-<lb break="no"/>liged to set bounds to my researches, towards the summit of<lb break="yes"/>the mountain. It is possible that this summit may be the<lb break="yes"/>crater of an extinguished volcano; and this is even probable.<lb break="yes"/>The idea of this possibility, however, makes one shudder&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>and with reason; for, if the volcano should be rekindled,<lb break="yes"/>this colossus would destroy the whole province.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The mountain of Tunguragua sunk down at the period of<lb break="yes"/>the earthquake of 1797. <persName key="bouguer_p">Bouguer</persName> makes its height to be<lb break="yes"/>2620 toises; I found it to be only 2531: it has lost there-<lb break="no"/>fore nearly 100 toises of its height. The inhabitants of the<lb break="yes"/>neighbouring country assert that they have seen its summit<lb break="yes"/>crumble down before their eyes.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>During our stay at Riobamba, where we spent some weeks<lb break="yes"/>with the brother of <persName key="montufarylarrea_c">Charles Montufar</persName>, who is corregidor<lb break="yes"/>there, we by chance made a very curious discovery. The<lb break="yes"/>state of the province of Quito before the conquest of the<lb break="yes"/>inca <persName key="tupacyupanqui">Tupayupagi</persName>
                        <note place="foot" n="*">Quito was conquered by the Peruvians in 1470.</note> is absolutely unknown. But the king of<lb break="yes"/>the Indians, <persName key="zapla_l">Leandro Zapla</persName>, who resides at Lican, and whose<lb break="yes"/>mind is highly cultivated, has in his possession manuscripts<lb break="yes"/>written by one of his an&#x00E7;estors in the sixteenth century,<lb break="yes"/>which contain the history of that period. These manuscripts<lb break="yes"/>are written in the language of Paraguay, which formerly was<lb break="yes"/>the general language of Quito; but in the course of time it<lb break="yes"/>gave place to that of the Incas, or the Anichna, and is now<lb break="yes"/>lost. Fortunately, another of <persName key="zapla_l">Zapla&#x2019;s</persName> ancestors amused<lb break="yes"/>himself in translating these manuscripts into Spanish. We<lb break="yes"/>made extracts from these valuable documents, and particu-<lb break="no"/>larly in regard to the memorable period of the eruption of<lb break="yes"/>the mountain called <hi rendition="#i">Nevado del Attas,</hi> which must have been<lb break="yes"/>the highest in the universe, superior even to Chimbora&#x00E7;o, and<lb break="yes"/>which the Indians called <hi rendition="#i">Capa-Urcu,</hi> &#x2018;the chief of moun-<lb break="no" />tains.&#x2019; <persName key="huainiaabomata">Ouainia Abomatha</persName>, the last independent <hi rendition="#i">cochocando</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>(king of the country), reigned at that time at Lican. The<lb break="yes"/>priests informed him that this catastrophe was a sinister pre-<lb break="no"/>sage of his destruction. &#x201C;The face of the universe,&#x201D; said<lb break="yes"/>they to him, &#x201C;is changing: other gods will expel ours. Let<lb break="yes"/>us not oppose what has been ordained by fate.&#x201D; The Pe-<lb break="no"/>ruvians indeed introduced into the country the worship of<lb break="yes"/>the sun. The eruption of the mountain continued seven<lb break="yes"/>years, and <persName key="zapla_l" >Zapla&#x2019;s</persName> manuscript asserts that the shower of<lb break="yes"/>ashes at Lican was so abundant that continual night pre-<lb break="no"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">vailed</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="244" facs="#f0008"/> vailed during that period. When the quantity of volcanic<lb break="yes"/>matters which are found in the plain of Tapia around the<lb break="yes"/>enormous mountain which then crumbled to pieces, is con-<lb break="no"/>sidered, and when we reflect that Cotopaxi has often in-<lb break="no"/>volved Quito in darkness for fifteen or eighteen hours, we<lb break="yes"/>may believe that the exaggeration of this account is not<lb break="yes"/>very great. This manuscript, the traditions which I col-<lb break="no"/>lected at Parime, and the hieroglyphics I saw in the desert<lb break="yes"/>of Casiquiare, where at present no vestiges of mankind re-<lb break="no"/>main, added to the ideas offered by <persName key="clavigero_fs">Clavigero</persName> respecting the<lb break="yes" />emigration of the Mexicans towards the southern part of<lb break="yes"/>
                        <placeName key="amerika">America</placeName>, have given rise to some conjectures on the origin<lb break="yes"/>of these people, which I purpose to explain as soon as I can<lb break="yes"/>find leisure.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I have applied also with great assiduity to the study of the<lb break="yes" />American languages, and I have seen how much what <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La<lb break="yes"/>Condamine</persName> says of their poverty is false. The Carib lan-<lb break="no"/>guage is rich, beautiful, energetic, and polished: it is in<lb break="yes"/>no want of expressions for abstract ideas. It speaks of<lb break="yes"/>posterity, eternity, existence, &#x0026;c.; and the numerical signs<lb break="yes"/>are sufficient to express all the possible combinations of fi-<lb break="no" />gures. I applied in particular to the Inca language: it is<lb break="yes" />generally spoken in company; and is so rich in delicate and<lb break="yes" />varied phrases, that the young men, in order to say soft<lb break="yes" />things to the ladies, when they have exhausted all the re-<lb break="no" />sources of the Castillan, begin to speak Inca. These two<lb break="yes" />languages, and others equally rich, are sufficient to prove<lb break="yes" />that <placeName key="amerika">America</placeName> formerly possessed a greater degree of culture<lb break="yes"/>than the Spaniards found there in 1492. But I have col-<lb break="no"/>lected still further proofs, not only at Mexico and in Peru,<lb break="yes"/>but even at the court of the king of Bogota, a country the<lb break="yes"/>history of which is absolutely unknown in Europe, and whose<lb break="yes"/>mythology even and fabulous traditions are highly inter-<lb break="no"/>esting. The priests were acquainted with the art of draw-<lb break="no"/>ing a meridian line, and observing the moment of the sol-<lb break="no"/>stice. They reduced the lunar year to a solar by interca-<lb break="no"/>lations; and I have in my possession a heptagon stone,<lb break="yes"/>found near Santa Fé, which they employed for calculating<lb break="yes"/>these intercalary days. But what is still more, even at Ere-<lb break="no"/>vato, in the interior of Parime, the savages believe that the<lb break="yes"/>moon is inhabited by men; and know by tradition from<lb break="yes"/>their ancestors, that it derives its light from the sun.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>From Riobamba I proceeded by the famous paramo of<lb break="yes"/>
                        <placeName key="assuay">Assuay</placeName> towards Cuen&#x00E7;a, after having visited the large sul-<lb break="no"/>phur mines of Tirrau. It was this mountain of sulphur<lb break="yes"/>which the negroes who revolted in 1797, after the earth-<lb break="no"/>quake, attempted to set on fire. This no doubt was the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">most</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="245" facs="#f0009"/> most desperate project ever attempted, for they hoped by<lb break="yes"/>these means to form a volcano which would swallow up the<lb break="yes"/>whole province of <placeName key="alausi" >Alaussy</placeName>. At the height of the paramo<lb break="yes"/>of <placeName key="assuay">Assuay</placeName>, an elevation of 2300 toises, are the magnificent<lb break="yes"/>ruins of the Inca&#x2019;s highway. It conducted almost to Cuzco,<lb break="yes"/>was entirely constructed of cut stone, and very straight, and<lb break="yes"/>resembled the most beautiful of the Roman roads. In the<lb break="yes"/>same neighbourhood are found also the ruins of the palace<lb break="yes"/>of the inca <persName key="tupacyupanqui">Tupayupangi</persName>, of which <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName> gave a<lb break="yes" />description in the Memoirs of the Academy of Berlin.<lb break="yes"/>In the quarry which furnished the stones there are still seen<lb break="yes" />several half cut. I do not know whether <persName key="lacondamine_cmd" >Condamine</persName> spoke<lb break="yes"/>also of the so-called Inca&#x2019;s billiard-table. The Indians<lb break="yes"/>name this place in the Quichua language, <hi rendition="#i">Inca-chun-<lb break="no" />gana,</hi> the Inca&#x2019;s game. But I much doubt whether it was<lb break="yes"/>ever destined for that purpose. It is a seat cut out in the<lb break="yes"/>rock, with ornaments in the arabesc form, in which it is<lb break="yes"/>believed that the ball ran. There is nothing more elegant<lb break="yes"/>in our gardens in the English style; and every thing proves<lb break="yes"/>the good taste of the inca, for the seat is so situated as to<lb break="yes"/>command a delightful view. In a wood not far from this<lb break="yes"/>place is found a round spot of yellow iron in freestone:<lb break="yes"/>the Peruvians have ornamented it with figures, supposing<lb break="yes"/>it to be the image of the sun. I made a drawing of it.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We remained only ten days at Cuen&#x00E7;a, and proceeded<lb break="yes" />thence to Lima through the province of Jaen, where we<lb break="yes" />spent a month in the neighbourhood of the river of the<lb break="yes" />Amazons. We arrived at Lima on the 23d of October<lb break="yes" />1802.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>In the month of December I purpose proceeding from<lb break="yes"/>this place to <placeName key="acapulco">Acapulco</placeName>, and thence to Mexico, that in the<lb break="yes"/>month of May 1803 I may reach the Havanna, where I<lb break="yes"/>shall embark without delay for Spain. I have given up, as<lb break="yes"/>you may see, the idea of returning by the Philippines. I<lb break="yes"/>should have crossed an immense tract of the ocean without<lb break="yes"/>seeing any thing but Manilla and the Cape; or, if I had<lb break="yes"/>attempted to proceed to the East Indies, I should have<lb break="yes"/>wanted the necessaries for that voyage, and which it was<lb break="yes"/>impossible for me to procure here.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We have had forty or fifty young crocodiles, on the <choice>
                            <sic>re <lb break="yes"/>spiration</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">re-<lb break="no"/>spiration</corr>
                        </choice> of which I have made very curious experiments.<lb break="yes" />Other animals diminish the volume of the air in which they<lb break="yes" />live, but the crocodile increases it. A crocodile immersed<lb break="yes" />in 1000 parts of atmospheric air, which contain 274 of oxy-<lb break="no" />gen gas, 15 of carbonic acid gas, and 711 of azot, increases<lb break="yes"/>this mass in one hour and forty-three minutes 124 parts;<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">and</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="246" facs="#f0010"/> and these 1124 parts contain then, as I found by exact<lb break="yes"/>analysis, 106&#x00B7;8 of oxygen, 79 of carbonic acid, and 938&#x00B7;2<lb break="yes"/>of azotic gas, mixed with other unknown gaseous sub-<lb break="no"/>stances. The crocodile then in one hour and three quarters<lb break="yes"/>produces 64 parts of carbonic acid, and absorbs 167&#x00B7;2 of<lb break="yes"/>oxygen; but as 46 parts are found in the 64 parts of carbonic<lb break="yes"/>acid, it appropriates to itself only 121 parts of oxygen;<lb break="yes"/>which is very little, considering the colour of its blood. It<lb break="yes"/>produces 227 parts of azote, or other gaseous substances, on<lb break="yes"/>which the acidifiable bases exercise no action.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I made these experiments in the town of Munpox with<lb break="yes"/>lime water and nitrous gas prepared with great care. The<lb break="yes" />crocodile is so sensible to carbonic acid gas and to its own<lb break="yes"/>exhalations, that it dies when put into air corrupted by one<lb break="yes"/>of its own species. It however can live two or three hours<lb break="yes"/>without breathing at all. I made these experiments on cro-<lb break="no"/>codiles seven or eight inches in length: notwithstanding<lb break="yes"/>this smallness of size, they are capable of cutting off a finger<lb break="yes"/>with their teeth, and they have the courage to attack a dog.<lb break="yes"/>These experiments are troublesome, and require great cir-<lb break="no"/>cumspection. We have made very minute descriptions of<lb break="yes"/>the ca&#x00EF;man or crocodile of <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>; but as the de-<lb break="no"/>scriptions of that of <placeName key="aegypten" >Egypt</placeName> which I saw before my depar-<lb break="no"/>ture from Europe were not equally circumstantial, I cannot<lb break="yes"/>venture to determine whether they are of the same species.<lb break="yes"/>The Institute of <placeName key="aegypten">Egypt</placeName> must undoubtedly have obtained de-<lb break="no"/>tails which will remove all doubt in regard to this point.<lb break="yes"/>This much however is certain, that there are three different<lb break="yes"/>species of crocodile in the tropical regions of the new con-<lb break="no"/>tinent, to which the inhabitants give the names of <hi rendition="#i">bava,<lb break="yes"/>ca&#x00EF;man,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">crocodile.</hi> No naturalist has yet sufficiently<lb break="yes"/>distinguished these species. These monsters, as at <placeName key="barcelona">New<lb break="yes"/>Barcelona</placeName>, are sometimes of so peaceable a nature that peo-<lb break="no"/>ple bathe before them; and sometimes, as at New Guiana,<lb break="yes"/>they are so mischievous and ferocious, that during the time<lb break="yes"/>we were there they devoured an Indian on the quay in the<lb break="yes"/>middle of the street. At <choice>
                        <sic>Oratuen</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Uritucu</corr>
                    </choice> we saw an Indian girl,<lb break="yes"/>eighteen years of age, whom a crocodile seized by the arm.<lb break="yes"/>She had the courage to put her other hand into her pocket<lb break="yes"/>to pull out her knife, with which she gave the monster so<lb break="yes"/>many wounds in the eyes that he let her go, but cut off the<lb break="yes"/>arm near the shoulder. This girl&#x2019;s presence of mind was as<lb break="yes" />astonishing as the skill displayed by the Indians in speedily<lb break="yes"/>curing so dangerous a wound: one might have said that the<lb break="yes"/>arm was amputated and dressed at Paris.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Near Santa-Fe there are found in the Campo de Gigante,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">at</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="247" facs="#f0011"/> at the height of 1370 toises, an immense number of fossil<lb break="yes"/>elephants&#x2019; bones, both of the African species and of the<lb break="yes"/>carnivorous kind discovered near the Ohio. We caused<lb break="yes"/>several to be dug up, and have sent some specimens of them<lb break="yes"/>to the National Institute. I much doubt whether any of<lb break="yes"/>these bones were ever before found at such a great height:<lb break="yes"/>since that time I have received two from a place of the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> situated about two degrees of latitude from Quito and<lb break="yes"/>Chili, so that I can prove the existence and destruction of<lb break="yes"/>these gigantic elephants from the Ohio to the country of<lb break="yes"/>the Patagonians. I shall bring with me a fine collection of<lb break="yes"/>these bones for M. <persName key="cuvier_g">Cuvier</persName>. About fifteen years ago the<lb break="yes"/>entire petrified skeleton of a crocodile was discovered in a<lb break="yes"/>calcareous rock in the valley of the Magdalen: it was broken<lb break="yes"/>through ignorance, and it was impossible for me to pro-<lb break="no"/>cure the head, which existed not long ago.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 