<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023299100">
                        <surname>Clark</surname>
                        <forename>Rex</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="stoeckli_mt">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stöckli</surname>
                        <forename>Matthias Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="schnidrig_bf">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schnidrig</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara Franziska</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.5.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.4.0" when="2018-09-28" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Personenmarkierung abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.3.0" when="2018-09-27" who="stoeckli_mt">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Personen.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2018-09-27" who="schnidrig_bf">Markup: added placeName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Orte.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="387" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>BARON HUMBOLDT.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>HE following abstract of the Ameri-<lb break="no"/>can Travels of the celebrated Ba-<lb break="no"/>ron <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName> and his companion <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bon-<lb break="no"/>pland</persName>, has been drawn up from notes<lb break="yes"/>which the former has kindly furnished,<lb break="yes"/>and will supercede the many very incor-<lb break="no"/>rect accounts hitherto published rela-<lb break="no"/>tive to this interesting object.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Baron <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>, having travelled<lb break="yes"/>from the year 1790, as a naturalist,<lb break="yes"/>through Germany, Poland, France,<lb break="yes"/>Switzerland, and through parts of Eng-<lb break="no"/>land, Italy, Hungary, and Spain, came<lb break="yes"/>to Paris in 1798, when he received an<lb break="yes"/>invitation, from the directors of the na-<lb break="no"/>tional museum to accompany captain<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin</persName> in his voyage round the world.<lb break="yes"/>Citizen <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Alexander Aime Gourjon <choice>
                            <sic>Bonp-<lb break="no"/>land</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">Bonp-<lb break="no"/>land,</corr>
                        </choice>
                    </persName> a native of Rochelle, and brought<lb break="yes"/>up in the Paris museum, was also to<lb break="yes"/>have accompanied them; when on the<lb break="yes"/>point of departing, the whole plan was<lb break="yes" />suspended until a more favorable op-<lb break="no"/>portunity, owing to the re-commence-<lb break="no"/>ment of the war with Austria, and the<lb break="yes"/>consequent want of funds.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>, who from 1792, had<lb break="yes"/>cenceived the plan of travelling through<lb break="yes"/>India at his own expense, with a view<lb break="yes"/>of adding to the knowledge of the scien-<lb break="no"/>ces connected with natural history, then<lb break="yes"/>resolved to follow the learned men, who<lb break="yes"/>had gone on the expedition to <placeName key="aegypten">Egypt</placeName>.<lb break="yes"/>His plan was to go to <placeName key="algier" >Algiers</placeName> in the<lb break="yes"/>Swedish frigate which carried the con-<lb break="no"/>sul <persName key="skjoldebrand_ma" >Skoldebrandt</persName>, to follow the caravan<lb break="yes"/>which goes from <placeName key="algier">Algiers</placeName> to Mecca, <choice>
                        <sic>go-<lb break="no"/>ng</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">go-<lb break="no"/>ing</corr>
                    </choice> through <placeName key="aegypten">Egypt</placeName> to <placeName key="arabien">Arabia</placeName>, and thence<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> by the Persian gulph to the English<lb break="yes"/>East-India establishments. The war<lb break="yes"/>which unexpectedly broke out in Octo-<lb break="no"/>ber, 1798, between France and the Bar-<lb break="no"/>bary powers, and the troubles in the<lb break="yes"/>East, prevented Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> from<lb break="yes"/>embarking at Marseilles, where he had<lb break="yes"/>been fruitlessly two months waiting to<lb break="yes"/>proceed. Impatient at this delay, and<lb break="yes" />continuing firm in his determination to<lb break="yes"/>go to <placeName key="aegypten">Egypt</placeName> he went to Spain, hoping to<lb break="yes" />pass more readily under the Spanish<lb break="yes"/>flag from Carthagena to <placeName key="algier">Algiers</placeName> and<lb break="yes"/>Tunis. He took with him the large<lb break="yes"/>collection of philosophical, chemical, and<lb break="yes"/>astronomical instruments, which he had<lb break="yes" />purchased in England and France.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From a happy concurrence of circum-<lb break="no"/>stances, he obtained, in February, 1789,<lb break="yes"/>from the court of Madrid, a permission<lb break="yes"/>to visit the <placeName key="spanischeskolonialreich">Spanish colonies of the two<lb break="yes"/>Americas</placeName>, a permission which was grant-<lb break="no"/>ed with a liberality and frankness,<lb break="yes" />which was honorable to the government<lb break="yes"/>and to a philosophic age. After a resi-<lb break="no"/>dence of some months at the Spanish<lb break="yes"/>court, during which time the king show-<lb break="no"/>ed a strong personal interest in the plan,<lb break="yes"/>Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>, in June, 1799, left Eu-<lb break="no" />rope, accompanied by Mr. <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>who, to a profound knowledge in botany<lb break="yes"/>and zoology, added an indefatigable<lb break="yes"/>zeal. It is with this friend that Mr.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> has accomplished, at his own<lb break="yes"/>expense, his travels in the two hemis-<lb break="no"/>pheres, by land and sea, probably the<lb break="yes"/>most extensive which any <hi rendition="#i">individual</hi> has<lb break="yes"/>ever undertaken.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These two travellers left <placeName key="acoruna">Corunna</placeName> in<lb break="yes"/>the Spanish ship <persName key="pizzaro_f">Pizarro</persName>, for the Cana-<lb break="no"/>ry Islands, where they ascended to the<lb break="yes"/>crater of the Peak of Teyde, and made<lb break="yes" />experiments on the analysis of the air.<lb break="yes"/>In July they arrived at the port of <choice>
                        <sic>Oma-<lb break="no"/>na</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Cuma-<lb break="no"/>na</corr>
                    </choice>, in <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>. In 1799, 1800,<lb break="yes"/>they visited the coast of Paria, the mis-<lb break="no"/>sions of the Chaymas Indians, the pro-<lb break="no"/>vince of New Andalusia (a country which<lb break="yes"/>had been rent by the most dreadful<lb break="yes"/>earthquakes, the hottest and yet the<lb break="yes" />most healthy, in the world,) of <placeName key="barcelona">New<lb break="yes" />Barcelona</placeName>, of Venezuela; and Spanish<lb break="yes" />Guayana.&#x2014;In January, 1800, they left<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas to visit the beautiful vallies<lb break="yes"/>of Aagca, where the great lake of Va-<lb break="no"/>lencia recals to mind the views of the<lb break="yes"/>lake of Geneva, embellished by the ma-<lb break="no"/>jesty of the vegetation of the tropics.<lb break="yes"/>From Porto Cabello they crossed, to<lb break="yes" />the south, the immense plains of Calo-<lb break="no"/>boza, of <placeName key="apure">Apure</placeName>, and of the Oronoco, al-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/> so los Llanos, a desert similar to those<lb break="yes"/>of <placeName key="afrika">Africa</placeName>, where in the shade (by the<lb break="yes" />reverberation of heat) the thermometer<lb break="yes"/>of <persName key="reaumur_rafd">Reaumur</persName> rose to 35 and 37 (111 to<lb break="yes"/>115 F.) degrees. The level of the coun-<lb break="no"/>try for 2000 square leagues does not dif-<lb break="no"/>fer 5 inches. The sand every where<lb break="yes"/>represents the <choice>
                        <sic>horaizon</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">horizon</corr>
                    </choice> of the sea, with-<lb break="no"/>out vegetation; and its dry bosom hides<lb break="yes"/>the crocodiles, and the torpid boa (a spe-<lb break="no"/>cies of serpent.)</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The <choice>
                        <sic>traveliing</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">travelling</corr>
                    </choice> here, as in all <placeName key="spanischeskolonialreich">Spanish<lb break="yes"/>America</placeName>, except Mexico, is performed<lb break="yes"/>on horseback. They passed whole days<lb break="yes"/>without seeing a palm-tree or the vestige<lb break="yes"/>of a human dwelling. At <placeName key="sanfernandodeapure">St. Fernando<lb break="yes"/>de Apure</placeName>, in the provinces of <placeName key="varinas" >Varinas</placeName>,<lb break="yes"/>Messrs. <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName> and <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName> began<lb break="yes"/>that fatiguing navigation of nearly 1000<lb break="yes"/>marine leagues, executed in Canoes<lb break="yes"/>making a chart of the country by the<lb break="yes"/>assistance of chronometers, the satel-<lb break="no"/>lites of Jupiter, and the lunar distances.<lb break="yes"/>They descended <placeName key="apure">the river Apure</placeName>, which<lb break="yes"/>empties itself into the Oronoco, in 7 de-<lb break="no"/>grees of latitude.&#x2014;They ascended the<lb break="yes" />last river (passing the celebrated cata-<lb break="no"/>racts of Mapure, and <placeName key="atures">Atures</placeName>) to the<lb break="yes"/>mouth of the Guaviare. From thence<lb break="yes"/>they ascended the small rivers of Taba-<lb break="no"/>pa, Juamina, and Tenie. From the mis-<lb break="no" />sion of Sarita they crossed by land to<lb break="yes"/>the sources of the famous Rio Negro,<lb break="yes"/>which <persName key="lacondamine_cmd" >Condamine</persName> saw, where it joins<lb break="yes"/>the <placeName key="amazonas">Amazon</placeName>, and which he calls a sea<lb break="yes" />of fresh water. About 30 Indians car-<lb break="no"/>ried the canoes through woods of Mami<lb break="yes"/>Lecythis and Laurus Cinamomoides to<lb break="yes" />the cano (or creek) of Pemichin. It<lb break="yes"/>was by this small stream that the tra-<lb break="no"/>vellers entered the Rio Negro, or Black<lb break="yes"/>River, which they descended to St. Car-<lb break="no"/>los, which has been erroneously suppo-<lb break="no"/>sed to be placed under the <placeName key="aequator">equator</placeName>, or just<lb break="yes"/>at the frontiers of great Para, in the go-<lb break="no"/>vernment of Bresil. A canal from Te-<lb break="no"/>nie to Pemichin, which from the level<lb break="yes"/>nature of the ground is very practicable,<lb break="yes"/>would present a fine internal communi-<lb break="no"/>cation between the Para and the pro-<lb break="no"/>vince of Carracas, a communication in-<lb break="no" />finitely shorter than that of Cassiquiare.<lb break="yes"/>From the fortress of St. Carlos on the<lb break="yes"/>Rio Negro, Mr. H. went north up that<lb break="yes"/>river and the Cassiquiare to the Orono-<lb break="no"/>co, and on this river to the volcano Dai-<lb break="no"/>da or the mission of Emeralda, near the<lb break="yes"/>sources of the Oronoco: the Indians<lb break="yes" />Guaicas (or race of men almost pigmies,<lb break="yes"/>very white and very warlike) render<lb break="yes"/>fruitless any attempts to reach the sour-<lb break="no"/>ces themselves.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="388" facs="#f0002"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>From the Esmeralda Messrs. H. and<lb break="yes"/>B. went down the Oronoco, when the<lb break="yes"/>waters rose, towards its mouths at St.<lb break="yes" />Thomas de la Guayana, or the <placeName key="angostura">Angos-<lb break="no" />tura</placeName>. It was during this long naviga-<lb break="no"/>tion that they were in a continued state<lb break="yes"/>of suffering, from want of nourishment,<lb break="yes"/>and shelter from the night rains, from<lb break="yes"/>living in the woods, from the musque-<lb break="no"/>toes, and an infinite variety of stinging<lb break="yes"/>insects, and from the impossibility of ba-<lb break="no"/>thing, owing to the fierceness of the cro-<lb break="no"/>codile and the little carib fish, and final-<lb break="no"/>ly the miasmata of a burning climate.<lb break="yes"/>They returned to Cumana by the plains<lb break="yes"/>of Cari and the mission of the Carib<lb break="yes"/>Indians, a race of men very different<lb break="yes" />from any other, and probably after the<lb break="yes"/>Patagonians, the tallest and most robust<lb break="yes"/>in the <choice>
                        <sic>world,</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">world.</corr>
                    </choice>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After remaining some months at<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="barcelona">New Barcelona</placeName> and Cumana, the travel-<lb break="no"/>lers arrived at the Havanna, after a te-<lb break="no"/>dious and dangerous navigation, the ves-<lb break="no"/>sel being in the night on the point of<lb break="yes"/>striking upon <placeName key="baxodelavibora">the Vibora rocks</placeName>. Mr.<lb break="yes"/>H. remained three months in the Island<lb break="yes"/>of Cuba, where he occupied himself in<lb break="yes" />ascertaining the longitude of the Hava-<lb break="no"/>na, and in constructing stoves on the<lb break="yes"/>sugar plantations, which have since<lb break="yes" />been pretty generally adopted. They<lb break="yes"/>were on the point of setting off for<lb break="yes"/>Vera Cruz, meaning, by the way of<lb break="yes" />Mexico and <placeName key="acapulco">Acapulco</placeName>, to go to the Phi-<lb break="no"/>lippine Islands, and from thence, it was<lb break="yes" />possible, by Bombay and <placeName key="aleppo">Aleppo</placeName>, to<lb break="yes"/>Constantinople, when some false reports<lb break="yes" />relative to <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin&#x2019;s</persName> voyage alarmed<lb break="yes"/>them, and made them change their plan.<lb break="yes"/>The gazettes held out the idea that this<lb break="yes" />navigator would proceed from France<lb break="yes"/>to Buenos Ayres, and from thence, by<lb break="yes"/>Cape Horn, for Chili and the coast of<lb break="yes" />Peru. Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> had promised to<lb break="yes"/>Mr. <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin</persName> and to the Museum of Pa-<lb break="no"/>ris, that wherever he might be, he<lb break="yes" />would endeavor to join the expedition,<lb break="yes"/>as soon as he should know of its having<lb break="yes"/>been commenced. He flattered himself<lb break="yes"/>that his researches, and those of his<lb break="yes"/>friend <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName>, might be more useful<lb break="yes"/>to science, if united to the labors of the<lb break="yes" />learned men who would accompany<lb break="yes"/>captain <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin</persName>.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These considerations induced Mr.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> to send his manuscripts, for<lb break="yes"/>1799 and 1800, direct to Europe, and<lb break="yes"/>to freight a small schooner at Bantabano,<lb break="yes"/>intending to go to Carthagena, and from<lb break="yes"/>thence, as quickly as possible, by the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> Isthmus of Panama, to the South Sea.<lb break="yes"/>He hoped to find captain <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin</persName> at<lb break="yes" />Guayaquil, or at Lima, and with him to<lb break="yes"/>visit New Holland, and the Islands of the<lb break="yes"/>Pacific Ocean, equally interesting in a<lb break="yes"/>moral point of view, as by the luxuri-<lb break="no"/>ance of their vegetation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It appeared imprudent to expose the<lb break="yes"/>manuscripts and collections already<lb break="yes"/>made to the risks of this proposed navi-<lb break="no"/>gation. These manuscripts, of the fate<lb break="yes"/>of which Mr. H. remained ignorant du-<lb break="no"/>ring three years, and until his arrival in<lb break="yes"/>Philadelphia, arrived safe, but one third<lb break="yes"/>part of the collection was lost by ship-<lb break="no"/>wreck. Fortunately, <choice>
                        <sic>except except</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">except</corr>
                    </choice> the<lb break="yes"/>insects of the Oronoco and Rio Negro<lb break="yes"/>they were only duplicates; but unhap-<lb break="no"/>pily, friar <persName key="gonzalez_j">John Gonzales</persName>, monk of the<lb break="yes"/>order of St. <persName key="franzvonassisi">Francis</persName>, the friend to whom<lb break="yes"/>they were entrusted, perished with them.<lb break="yes"/>He was a young man full of ardor, who<lb break="yes"/>had penetrated into this unknown world<lb break="yes"/>of Spanish Guayana further than any<lb break="yes"/>other European.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> left <placeName key="batabano">Batabano</placeName> in March<lb break="yes"/>1801, and passed to the south of the<lb break="yes"/>Island of Cuba, on which he determined<lb break="yes"/>many Geographical positions. The pas-<lb break="no"/>sage was rendered very long by calms,<lb break="yes"/>and the currents carried the little schoo-<lb break="no"/>ner too much to the west, to the mouths<lb break="yes"/>of the <placeName key="atrato">Attracto</placeName>. The vessel put into<lb break="yes"/>the river Sinu, where no botanist had<lb break="yes"/>ever before visited, and they had a very<lb break="yes" />difficult passage up to Carthagena. The<lb break="yes"/>season being too far advanced for the<lb break="yes"/>South Sea navigation, the project of<lb break="yes"/>crossing the Isthmus was abandoned;<lb break="yes"/>and animated by the desire of being ac-<lb break="no"/>quainted with the celebrated <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>and admiring his immencely rich col-<lb break="no"/>lections of objects of natural history,<lb break="yes"/>Mr. H. determined to pass some weeks<lb break="yes"/>in the woods of Turbaco, and to ascend<lb break="yes"/>(which took forty days) the beautiful ri-<lb break="no"/>ver of Madalaine, of the source of which<lb break="yes"/>he has sketched a chart.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From Honda, our travelers proceed-<lb break="no"/>ed thro&#x2019; forests of oaks, of <hi rendition="#i">malastomo,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and of <hi rendition="#i">cinchona,</hi> (the tree which affords<lb break="yes"/>the Peruvian bark,) to St. Fe de Bogo-<lb break="no" />ta, capital of the kingdom of New Gre-<lb break="no"/>nada, situated in a fine plain, elevated<lb break="yes"/>1360 toises (of six French feet) above<lb break="yes"/>the level of the sea. The superb collec-<lb break="no"/>tions of <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, the majestic cataract of<lb break="yes"/>the Tequendama (falls of 98 toises<lb break="yes"/>height) the mines of Mariquita, St. Ana,<lb break="yes"/>and of Tipaquira, the natural bridge of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> Scononza, (three stones thrown together<lb break="yes"/>in the manner of an arch, by an earth-<lb break="no"/>quake,) these curious objects stopped<lb break="yes"/>the progress of Messrs. <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName> and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName> until the month of September<lb break="yes"/>1801.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At this time, notwithstanding the rai-<lb break="no"/>ny season had commenced, they under-<lb break="no"/>took the journey to Quito, and passed<lb break="yes" />the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> of Quindiu, which are snowy<lb break="yes"/>mountains covered with wax palm-trees,<lb break="yes"/>(palmers a cire,) with passe flores, (pas-<lb break="no"/>sion flower) of the growth of trees, sto-<lb break="no"/>tax, and bambusa (bamboo.) They<lb break="yes"/>were, during 13 days, obliged to pass on<lb break="yes"/>foot thro&#x2019; places dreadfully swampy, and<lb break="yes"/>without any traces of population.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">(To be Continued.)</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="395" facs="#f0003"/>
                <cb/>
            </div>
            <div n="1">
                <head>BARON HUMBOLDT.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#i">(Continued from page</hi> 388<hi rendition="#i">)</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">F</hi>ROM the village of Carthago, in the<lb break="yes" />valley of Cauca, they followed the<lb break="yes"/>course of the Choco, the country of Pa-<lb break="no"/>latina, which was there found in round<lb break="yes"/>pieces of basalte and green rock (grein<lb break="yes"/>stein of <persName key="werner_ag">Werner</persName>,) and fossil wood.&#x2014;&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>They pass by Buga to Popayan, a bi-<lb break="no"/>ship&#x2019;s see, and situated near the volca-<lb break="no" />noes of <hi rendition="#i">Sotara and Purace,</hi> a most pic-<lb break="no" />turesque situation, and enjoying the most<lb break="yes"/>delicious climate in the world, the ther-<lb break="no"/>mometer of Reamur keeping constantly<lb break="yes"/>at 16 to 18 (68 to 72 Fahr.) They as-<lb break="no"/>cended to the crater of the volcano of<lb break="yes"/>Purace, whose mouth, in the middle of<lb break="yes"/>snow, throws out vapors of sulphurous<lb break="yes" />hydrogene, with continued and frightful<lb break="yes"/>rumbling.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From Papayan they passed by the<lb break="yes"/>dangerous defiles of <placeName key="almager">Almager</placeName>, avoiding<lb break="yes"/>the infected and contagious valley of Pa-<lb break="no"/>tia, to Posto, and from this town, even<lb break="yes"/>now situated at the foot of a burning<lb break="yes" />volcano, by Tuqueras and the province<lb break="yes"/>of Pastos, a flat portion of country, fer-<lb break="no"/>tile in European grain, but elevated<lb break="yes"/>more than 1500 to 1600 toises above the<lb break="yes"/>towns of Ibarra and Quito.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>They arrived, in January, 1802, at<lb break="yes"/>this beautiful capital, celebrated by the<lb break="yes"/>labors of the illustrious <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condamine</persName>, of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="bouguer_p">Bouger</persName>, <persName key="godin_l" >Godin</persName>, Dr. <persName key="juanysantacilia_j">George Juan</persName>, and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="ulloa_ad">Ulloa</persName>, and still more celebrated by the<lb break="yes"/>great amiability of its inhabitants, and<lb break="yes"/>their happy turn for the arts.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>They remained nearly a year in the<lb break="yes"/>kingdom of Quito: the height of its<lb break="yes"/>snow-capped mountains, its terrible<lb break="yes" />eathquakes (that of February 7, 1797,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> swallowed up 42,000 inhabitants, in a<lb break="yes"/>few seconds,) its fertility, and the<lb break="yes"/>manners of its inhabitants, combined to<lb break="yes"/>render it the most interesting spot in<lb break="yes"/>the universe. After three vain attempts,<lb break="yes"/>they twice succeeded in ascending to<lb break="yes"/>the crater of the volcane of Pichincha,<lb break="yes"/>taking with them electrometers, ba-<lb break="no"/>rometers, and hygrometers. Conda-<lb break="no"/>mine could only stop here a few mi-<lb break="no"/>nutes, <hi rendition="#i">and that without instruments.</hi> In<lb break="yes"/>his time, this immense crater was cold<lb break="yes" />and filled with snow. Our travellers<lb break="yes"/>found it inflamed; distressing informa-<lb break="no"/>tion for the town of Quito, which is dis-<lb break="no"/>ant from it only 5,000 to 6,000 toises.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>They made separate visits to the<lb break="yes"/>snowy and porphyritic mountains of An-<lb break="no"/>tisana, Cotopaxi, Tungarague, and<lb break="yes" />Chimborazo, the last the highest point<lb break="yes"/>of our globe. They studied the geolo-<lb break="no"/>gical part of the Cordillera of the An-<lb break="no"/>des, on which subject nothing has been<lb break="yes"/>published in Europe, mineralogy (if the<lb break="yes"/>expression may be used) having been<lb break="yes"/>created, as it were, since the time of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condamine</persName>. The geodesical measure-<lb break="no"/>ments proved that some mountains,<lb break="yes"/>particularly the volcano of Tungarague,<lb break="yes"/>has considerably lowered since 1750,<lb break="yes"/>which result agrees with the observations<lb break="yes"/>made to them by the inhabitants.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>During the whole of this part of the<lb break="yes"/>journey, they were accompanied by Mr.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="montufarylarrea_c">Charles <choice>
                            <sic>Montutar</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">Montufar</corr>
                        </choice>
                    </persName>, son of the <persName key="montufarylarrea_jpd">Marquis<lb break="yes"/>of Salva-alegre</persName>, of Quito, a person zea-<lb break="no"/>lous for the progress of science, and<lb break="yes"/>who is, at his own expense, re-building<lb break="yes"/>the pyramids of Saraqui, the extremity<lb break="yes"/>of the celebrated bases of the <hi rendition="#i" >triangles</hi> of<lb break="yes"/>the Spanish and French academicians.<lb break="yes"/>This interesting young man having fol-<lb break="no"/>lowed Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> in the remainder<lb break="yes"/>of his journey through Peru and the<lb break="yes"/>kingdom of New Spain, is now on his<lb break="yes"/>passage with him to Europe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Circumstances were so favorable to<lb break="yes"/>the efforts of the three travellers, that at<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="antisana">Antisana</placeName> they ascended 2,200 French<lb break="yes"/>feet, and at Chimborazo, on June 22d,<lb break="yes"/>1802, nearly 3,200 higher than Conda-<lb break="no"/>mine was able to carry his instruments.<lb break="yes"/>They ascended to 3,036 toises elevation<lb break="yes"/>above the level of the sea, the blood start-<lb break="no"/>ing from their eyes, lips and gums.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>An opening, of 80 toises deep, and ve-<lb break="no"/>ry wide, prevented them from reaching<lb break="yes"/>the top, from which they were only dis-<lb break="no"/>tant 134 toises.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>It was at Quito that Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>received a letter from the National In-<lb break="no"/>stitute of France, informing him, that<lb break="yes"/>captain <persName key="baudin_tn" >Baudin</persName> had proceeded by the<lb break="yes"/>Cape of Good Hope, and that there was<lb break="yes"/>no longer any hope of joining him.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After having examined the country<lb break="yes"/>overturned by the earthquake of Riobam-<lb break="no"/>ba, in 1797, they passed by the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>of <placeName key="assuay">Assuay</placeName> to Cuenza. The desire of<lb break="yes"/>comparing the barks (cinchona) disco-<lb break="no" />vered by Mr. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, at Santa Fe de Ba-<lb break="no"/>gota, and with those of Popayan, and<lb break="yes"/>the cuspa and cuspare of New Andalu-<lb break="no"/>sia, and of the river Caroni (named<lb break="yes"/>falsely Cortex Augustura) with the cin-<lb break="no"/>chona, (barks) of Loxa and Peru, they<lb break="yes"/>preferred deviating from the beaten<lb break="yes"/>track from Cuenza to Lima; but they<lb break="yes" />passed with immense difficulties in the<lb break="yes"/>carriage, their instruments and collec-<lb break="no"/>tions, by the forest (paramo) of Saragu-<lb break="no"/>ra to Loxa, and from thence to the pro-<lb break="no" />vince of Saen de Bracamoros. They<lb break="yes"/>had to cross thirty-five times, in two<lb break="yes"/>days the river Guancabamba, so dange-<lb break="no"/>rous for its sudden freshes. They saw<lb break="yes"/>the ruins of the supurb Ynga road, com-<lb break="no"/>parable to the finest roads in France,<lb break="yes"/>and which went upon the ridge of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> from Cusco to the <placeName key="assuay">Assuay</placeName>, ac-<lb break="no"/>commodated with fountains and ta-<lb break="no"/>verns.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>They descended the river Chamaya,<lb break="yes"/>which led them into that of the <placeName key="amazonas">Amazones</placeName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and they navigated this last river down<lb break="yes"/>to the cataracts of Tomeperda, one of<lb break="yes"/>the most fertile, but one of the hottest<lb break="yes"/>climates of the habitable globe. From<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="amazonas">the Amazone river</placeName> they returned to the<lb break="yes"/>south east by the Cordilleras of the An-<lb break="no"/>des to Montar, where they found they<lb break="yes"/>had passed the <placeName key="magnetaequator">magnetic equator</placeName>, the<lb break="yes" />inclination being 0, although at seven<lb break="yes"/>degrees of south latitude. They visit-<lb break="no"/>ed the mines of Hualgayoc, where na-<lb break="no"/>tive silver is found at the height of<lb break="yes"/>2000 toises. Some of the veins of these<lb break="yes"/>mines contain petrified shells, and<lb break="yes"/>which, with those of Pasco and Huan-<lb break="no" />tajayo, are actually the richest of Peru.<lb break="yes"/>From Caxamarca they descended to<lb break="yes"/>Truxillo, in the neighborhood of which<lb break="yes"/>are found the ruins of the immense Pe-<lb break="no"/>ruvian city, Mansiche.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It was on this western descent of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> that the three voyagers, for the<lb break="yes"/>first time, had the pleasure of seeing the<lb break="yes" />Pacific Ocean. They followed its barren<lb break="yes"/>sides, formerly watered by the canals<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="396" facs="#f0004"/>
                    <cb/> of the Yngas at Santa, Guerma, and Li-<lb break="no"/>ma. They remained some months in<lb break="yes"/>this interesting capital of Peru, of which<lb break="yes"/>the inhabitants are distinguished by the<lb break="yes" />vivacity of their genius and the liberali-<lb break="no"/>ty of their ideas.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> had the good fortune<lb break="yes"/>to observe the end of the passage of<lb break="yes"/>Mercury over the suns disk, in the port<lb break="yes"/>of Callao. He was astonished to find,<lb break="yes"/>at such a distance from Europe, the<lb break="yes" />most recent productions in chemistry,<lb break="yes"/>mathematics and medicine; and he<lb break="yes"/>found great activity of mind in the in-<lb break="no"/>habitants, who in a climate where it<lb break="yes"/>never either rains or thunders, have<lb break="yes"/>been falsely accused of indolence.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From Lima our travellers passed by<lb break="yes"/>sea to Guayaquil, situated on the brink<lb break="yes"/>of a river, where the growth of the<lb break="yes" />palm-tree is beautiful beyond descrip-<lb break="no"/>tion. They every moment heard the<lb break="yes"/>rumbling of the volcano of Cotopaxi,<lb break="yes" />which made an alarming explosion on<lb break="yes"/>the 6th January, 1803. They immedi-<lb break="no"/>ately set off to visit it a second time,<lb break="yes"/>when the unexpected intelligence of the<lb break="yes"/>speedy departure of the frigate Atalan-<lb break="no"/>ta determined them to return, after be-<lb break="no"/>ing seven days exposed to the dreadful<lb break="yes" />attacks of the musquitoes of <placeName key="babaoyo">Babaoya</placeName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and Ujibar.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>They had a fortunate passage, by the<lb break="yes"/>Pacific Ocean, to <placeName key="acapulco">Acupulco</placeName>, the western<lb break="yes"/>port of the kingdom of New Spain, fa-<lb break="no"/>mous for the beauty of its harbor, which<lb break="yes"/>appears to have been formed by earth-<lb break="no" />quakes, for the misery of its inhabitants,<lb break="yes"/>and for its climate, which is equally hot<lb break="yes"/>and unhealthy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">(To be continued.)</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="402" facs="#f0005"/>
                <cb/>
                <cb/>
                <cb/>
            </div>
            <div n="1">
                <head>BARON HUMBOLDT.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">(Continued from page 396.)</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">M</hi>R. HUMBOLDT had originally<lb break="yes"/>the intention to remain only a<lb break="yes"/>few months in Mexico, and to hasten his<lb break="yes"/>return to Europe; his voyage had alrea-<lb break="no" />dy been too much protracted, his in-<lb break="no"/>struments, particularly the chronome-<lb break="no"/>ters, began to be out of order, and eve-<lb break="no"/>ry effort that he made to have new<lb break="yes"/>ones sent him proved of no avail; add<lb break="yes"/>to this consideration, that the progress<lb break="yes"/>of science is so rapid in Europe, that,<lb break="yes"/>in a journey that lasts four or five<lb break="yes"/>years, great risk is run of contemplating<lb break="yes"/>the different phenomena under aspects,<lb break="yes"/>which are no longer interesting at the<lb break="yes"/>moment of publishing the result of your<lb break="yes" />labors.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> hoped to be in France<lb break="yes"/>in August or September, 1803, but the<lb break="yes" />attractions of a country, so beautiful<lb break="yes"/>and so varied, as is that of the kingdom<lb break="yes"/>of New Spain, the great hospitality of<lb break="yes"/>its inhabitants, and the fear of the yel-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="403" facs="#f0006"/>
                    <cb/> low fever, so fatal, from June to No-<lb break="no"/>vember, for those who come from the<lb break="yes"/>mountainous parts of the country, led<lb break="yes"/>him to stay a year in this kingdom.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Our travellers ascended from <placeName key="acapulco">Acapul-<lb break="no" />co</placeName> to Tasco, celebrated for its mines,<lb break="yes"/>as interesting as they are ancient.<lb break="yes"/>They rise, by small degrees, from the<lb break="yes"/>ardent valley of Mescala and Papagayo,<lb break="yes" />where the thermometer of <persName key="reaumur_rafd">Reaumur</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>stands in the shade, constantly from 28<lb break="yes"/>to 31 (95 to 101 Farh.) in a region 6 or<lb break="yes"/>700 toises above the level of the sea,<lb break="yes"/>where you find the oaks, the pines, and<lb break="yes" />the fougere (fern) as large as trees, and<lb break="yes"/>where the European grains are cultiva-<lb break="no"/>ted. They passed by Tasco, by Cuer-<lb break="no"/>na Vacca, to the capital of Mexico.<lb break="yes"/>This city, of 150,000 inhabitants, is<lb break="yes"/>placed upon the ancient site of Texoch-<lb break="no"/>titlan, between the lakes of Tezcuco and<lb break="yes"/>Xochimilco, lakes which have lessened<lb break="yes"/>somewhat since the Spaniards have open-<lb break="no"/>ed the canal of Hacheutoca, in the sight<lb break="yes"/>of two snow-topped mountains, of which<lb break="yes" />one, Hopocatepec, is even now an ac-<lb break="no"/>tive volcano, surrounded by a great<lb break="yes"/>number of walks, shaded with trees,<lb break="yes" />and by Indian villages.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This capital of Mexico, situated 1160<lb break="yes"/>toises <hi rendition="#i" >above the sea,</hi> in a mild and tem-<lb break="no"/>perate climate may doubtless be com-<lb break="no"/>pared to some of the finest towns in Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope. Great scientific establishments,<lb break="yes"/>such the Academy of Painting, Sculp-<lb break="no"/>ture, and Engraving, the College of<lb break="yes"/>Mines, (owing to the liberality of the<lb break="yes" />Company, of Miners of Mexico,) and<lb break="yes"/>the Botanic Garden, are institutions<lb break="yes"/>which do honor to the government<lb break="yes" />which has created them.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After remaining some months in the<lb break="yes"/>valley of Mexico, and after fixing the<lb break="yes"/>longitude of the capital, which had been<lb break="yes"/>laid down with an error of nearly two<lb break="yes"/>degrees, our travellers visited the mines<lb break="yes"/>of Moran and Real del Monte, and the<lb break="yes"/>Cerro of Oyamel, where the ancient<lb break="yes" />Mexicans had the manufactory of knives<lb break="yes"/>made of the obsidian stone. They soon<lb break="yes"/>after passed by Queretaro and Salaman-<lb break="no"/>ca to Guanaxoato, a town of fifty thou-<lb break="no"/>sand inhabitants, and celebrated for its<lb break="yes"/>mines, more rich than those of Potosi<lb break="yes"/>have ever been.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The mine of the count of Valenciana,<lb break="yes"/>which is 1840 French feet perpendicu-<lb break="no"/>lar depth, is the deepest and richest<lb break="yes"/>mine of the universe. This mine<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> alone gives to its proprietor nearly six<lb break="yes"/>hundred thousand dollars annual and<lb break="yes"/>constant profit.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From Guanaxoato they returned by<lb break="yes"/>the valley of St. Jago, to Valladolid, in<lb break="yes"/>the ancient kingdom of Michuacan, one<lb break="yes"/>of the most fertile and charming provin-<lb break="no"/>ces of the kingdom. They descended<lb break="yes"/>from Pascuaro towards the coast of the<lb break="yes"/>Pacific Ocean to the plains of Serullo,<lb break="yes" />where, in 1759, in one night, a volcano<lb break="yes"/>arose from the level, surrounded by two<lb break="yes"/>thousand small mouths, from whence<lb break="yes"/>smoke still continues to issue. They<lb break="yes"/>arrived almost to the bottom of the cra-<lb break="no"/>ter of the great volcano of Serullo, of<lb break="yes"/>which they analized the air, and found<lb break="yes"/>it strongly impregnated with carbonic<lb break="yes"/>acid. They returned to Mexico by the<lb break="yes"/>valley of Teluca, and visited the volca-<lb break="no"/>no, to the highest point of which they<lb break="yes" />ascended, 14,400 French feet above the<lb break="yes"/>level of the sea.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the months of January and Februa-<lb break="no"/>ry, 1804, they pursued their researches<lb break="yes"/>on the eastern descent of the Cordille-<lb break="no"/>ras, they measured the mountains Me-<lb break="no"/>rados, de la Peubla. Popocatyce, Izazi-<lb break="no"/>huatli, the great peak of Orizaba, and<lb break="yes"/>the Cofre de Perote; upon the top of<lb break="yes" />this last Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> observed the<lb break="yes"/>meridian height of the sun. In fine,<lb break="yes"/>after some residence at Xalappa, they<lb break="yes"/>embarked at Vera Cruz, for the Havan-<lb break="no"/>nah. They resumed the collections<lb break="yes"/>they had left there in 1801, and by the<lb break="yes"/>way of Philadelphia, embarked for<lb break="yes"/>France, in July, 1804, after six years<lb break="yes" />of absence and labors. A collection of<lb break="yes"/>6000 different species of plants (of which<lb break="yes"/>a great part are new) and numerous<lb break="yes"/>mineralogical, astronomical, chemical<lb break="yes"/>and moral observations, have been the<lb break="yes"/>result of this expedition. Mr. Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt gives the highest praises to the li-<lb break="no" />beral protection granted to his research-<lb break="no"/>es by the Spanish government.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Baron <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> was born in Prussia,<lb break="yes"/>on the 14th of September, 1769.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 