<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023299100">
                        <surname>Clark</surname>
                        <forename>Rex</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="stoeckli_mt">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stöckli</surname>
                        <forename>Matthias Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="schnidrig_bf">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schnidrig</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara Franziska</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.5.1" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.4.1" when="2018-10-06" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: correction. <note type="remarkRevision">Kodierungsfehler behoben.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.4.0" when="2018-09-28" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Personenmarkierung abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.3.0" when="2018-09-27" who="stoeckli_mt">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Personen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2018-09-27" who="schnidrig_bf">Markup: added placeName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Orte.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="353" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Short Account of Travels between the Tropics, by<lb break="yes"/>Messrs.</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">and</hi>
                    <persName key="bonpland_ajag">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Bonpland,</hi>
                    </persName>
                    <hi rendition="#i">in</hi> 1799, 1800,<lb break="yes"/>1801, 1802, 1803, <hi rendition="#i">and</hi> 1804. <hi rendition="#i">By</hi>
                    <persName key="lametherie_jcd">J. C. <hi rendition="#k">Delame-<lb break="no" />therie</hi>
                    </persName>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">From <hi rendition="#i">Journal de Physique,</hi> Thermidor, an 12.</note>.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>he</hi> interest which the learned world so justly takes in<lb break="yes"/>the travels of Messrs. <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName> and <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName>, as well as<lb break="yes"/>my friendship for them, impose on me the agreeable obli-<lb break="no"/>gation of giving an abstract of what I have been able to<lb break="yes"/>learn respecting them, either from their public and private<lb break="yes"/>correspondence, or from the memoirs read in the Institute.<lb break="yes"/>This account will be short, but correct.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After making physical researches for eight years in Ger-<lb break="no"/>many, Poland, England, France, Swisserland, and Italy,<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> came to Paris in 1798, where the Museum<lb break="yes"/>of Natural History afforded him an opportunity of making<lb break="yes"/>a voyage round the world with captain <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin</persName>. When on<lb break="yes"/>the point of setting out for Havre, with <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Alexander-Aimé<lb break="yes"/>Goujou Bonpland</persName>, a pupil of the School of Medicine and<lb break="yes"/>Garden of Plants, the war which recommenced with Austria,<lb break="yes"/>and the want of funds, induced the Directory to put off the<lb break="yes"/>voyage of <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin</persName> till a more favourable occasion. M. Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt, who since 1792 had conceived the design of under-<lb break="no"/>taking, at his own expense, a voyage to the tropics, in order<lb break="yes"/>to promote the physical sciences, resolved then to accom-<lb break="no"/>pany the men of science who were destined for <placeName key="aegypten">Egypt</placeName>. The<lb break="yes"/>battle of Aboukir having interrupted all direct communi-<lb break="no"/>cation with <placeName key="alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, his plan was to take advantage of<lb break="yes"/>a Swedish frigate which was to carry the consul Seziolde-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">brant</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="354" facs="#f0002"/> brant to <placeName key="algier" >Algiers</placeName>, to accompany the caravan thence to Mecca,<lb break="yes" />and to proceed to India by <placeName key="aegypten">Egypt</placeName> and the Persian Gulph:<lb break="yes"/>but the war, which broke out in an unexpected manner<lb break="yes"/>in the month of October 1798, between France and the<lb break="yes"/>Barbary powers, and the troubles in the East, prevented<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> from setting out from Marseilles, where he<lb break="yes"/>waited to no purpose for two months. Impatient at this<lb break="yes"/>new delay, but always firm in the project of joining the<lb break="yes"/>expedition in <placeName key="aegypten">Egypt</placeName>, he set out for Spain, hoping he should<lb break="yes"/>be able to proceed more easily under the Spanish flag from<lb break="yes"/>Carthagena to <placeName key="algier">Algiers</placeName> or Tunis. He took the road to Ma-<lb break="no"/>drid through Montpellier, Perpignan, <placeName key="barcelona">Barcelona</placeName>, and Va-<lb break="no"/>lentia; but the news from the East became every day more<lb break="yes"/>distressing. The war there was carried on with unexampled<lb break="yes"/>fury, and he was at length obliged to renounce the design<lb break="yes"/>of going through <placeName key="aegypten">Egypt</placeName> to Indostan. A happy concurrence<lb break="yes"/>of circumstances soon indemnified M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> for this<lb break="yes" />delay. In the month of March 1799, the court of Madrid<lb break="yes"/>granted him full permission to proceed to the <placeName key="spanischeskolonialreich" >Spanish colo-<lb break="no"/>nies in both the Americas</placeName>, in order to make such researches<lb break="yes"/>as might be useful to the sciences. His catholic majesty even<lb break="yes"/>deigned to show particular interest for the success of this<lb break="yes"/>expedition; and M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>, after residing some months<lb break="yes"/>at Madrid and <placeName key="aranjuez">Aranjues</placeName>, set out from Europe in June 1799,<lb break="yes"/>accompanied by his friend <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName>, who unites an exten-<lb break="no"/>sive knowledge of botany and zoology to that indefatigable<lb break="yes"/>zeal and love for the sciences which induce men to submit<lb break="yes"/>with indifference to every kind of hardship.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>With this friend M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> travelled for five years,<lb break="yes"/>at his own expense, between the tropics, passing over, by<lb break="yes"/>sea and land, nearly 9000 leagues. These two travellers,<lb break="yes"/>provided with recommendations from the court of Spain,<lb break="yes"/>embarked in the <persName key="pizzaro_f" >Pizarro</persName> frigate, at <placeName key="acoruna" >Corunna</placeName>, for the Ca-<lb break="no"/>naries. They touched at the island of Graciosa, near Lan-<lb break="no"/>cerotta, and at Teneriff, where they ascended to the crater of<lb break="yes"/>the peak, in order to analyse the atmospheric air, and make<lb break="yes"/>geological observations on the basaltes and porphyritic schist<lb break="yes"/>of <placeName key="afrika" >Africa</placeName>. In the month of July they arrived at the port of<lb break="yes"/>Cumana, in the gulph of Cariaco, a part of <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>celebrated by the labours and misfortunes of the indefatiga-<lb break="no"/>ble <persName key="loefling_p">Löfling</persName>. In the eourse of 1799 and 1800 they visited<lb break="yes"/>the coast of Paria, the Indian missions of Chaymas, and<lb break="yes"/>the province of New Andalusia, one of the hottest, but at<lb break="yes"/>the same time healthiest, countries in the world, though<lb break="yes"/>convulsed by dreadful and frequent earthquakes. They<lb break="yes"/>traversed the provinces of <placeName key="barcelona" >New Barcelona</placeName>, Venezuela, and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">Spanish</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="355" facs="#f0003"/> Spanish Guyana. After determining the longitude of Cu-<lb break="no"/>mana, Caraccas, and several other points by observations<lb break="yes"/>of the satellites of Jupiter; after collecting plants on the<lb break="yes"/>summits of Caripe and Silla de <placeName key="avila">Avila</placeName>, crowned by <hi rendition="#i">Befaria,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>they set out for the capital of Caraccas in February 1800,<lb break="yes"/>and the beautiful valleys of <placeName key="aragua" >Aragua</placeName>, where the large lake<lb break="yes"/>of Valentia calls to remembrance that of Geneva, but em-<lb break="no"/>bellished by the majestic vegetation of the tropics.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From Portocabello they proceeded south, penetrating<lb break="yes"/>from the coast of the <placeName key="antillischesmeer">sea of the Antilles</placeName> as far as the boun-<lb break="no"/>daries of Brazil towards the <placeName key="aequator">equator</placeName>. They first traversed<lb break="yes"/>the immense plains of Calabozo, <placeName key="apure">Apure</placeName>, and Lower Ore-<lb break="no"/>noko; the Llanos, deserts similar to those of <placeName key="afrika">Africa</placeName>, where<lb break="yes"/>by the reverberation of the heat, but under the shade, <persName key="reaumur_rafd">Reau-<lb break="no"/>mur&#x2019;s</persName> thermometer rises to 33° or 37°, and where the<lb break="yes"/>scorching soil, for more than 2000 leagues, differs in its<lb break="yes"/>level only five inches. The sand, similar to the horizon at<lb break="yes"/>sea, exhibits every where the most curious ph&#x00E6;nomena of<lb break="yes"/>refraction and elevation. Without any vegetation, in the<lb break="yes"/>dry months it affords shelter to the crocodile and the torpid<lb break="yes"/>boa.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The want of water, the heat of the sun, and the dust<lb break="yes"/>raised by the scorching winds, harass in turns the traveller,<lb break="yes"/>who directs himself and mule by the course of the stars, or<lb break="yes"/>by some scattered trunks of the <hi rendition="#i">mauritia</hi> and <hi rendition="#i" >embothrium</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>which are discovered every three or four leagues.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At <placeName key="sanfernandodeapure">St. Fernando d&#x2019;Apure</placeName>, in the province of <placeName key="varinas">Varinas</placeName>,<lb break="yes" />Messrs. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> and <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName> began a laborious navi-<lb break="no"/>gation of nearly 500 nautical leagues in canoes, during<lb break="yes"/>which they made a chart of the country by the help of<lb break="yes"/>timekeepers, the satellites, and lunar distances. They de-<lb break="no"/>scended the <placeName key="apure">river Apure</placeName>, which falls into the Orenoko in<lb break="yes"/>the latitude of seven degrees. Having escaped from the<lb break="yes"/>danger of imminent shipwreck near the island of Pana-<lb break="no"/>numa, they ascended the latter river as far as the mouth of<lb break="yes"/>the Rio Guaviare, passing the famous cataracts of <placeName key="atures">Atures</placeName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and Maypure, where the cavern of <placeName key="ataruipe" >Ataruipe</placeName> contains mum-<lb break="no"/>mies of a nation destroyed by the war of the Caribs and<lb break="yes"/>Maravitains. From the mouth of the Rio Guaviare, which<lb break="yes"/>descends from the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> of New Granada, and which fa-<lb break="no" />ther <persName key="gumilla_j">Gumilla</persName> erroneously took for the sources of the Ore-<lb break="no"/>noko, they quitted the latter and ascended the small rivers<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="atabapo">Atabapo</placeName>, Tuamini, and Temi.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From the mission of Javita they proceeded by land to the<lb break="yes"/>sources of the Guainia, which the Europeans call the Rio<lb break="yes"/>Negro, and which <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condamine</persName>, who saw it only at its<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">mouth</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="356" facs="#f0004"/> mouth in the <placeName key="amazonas">river Amazon</placeName>, calls a fresh water sea. Thirty<lb break="yes"/>Indians carried their canoes through bushy trees of <hi rendition="#i">hevea,<lb break="yes"/>lecythis,</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i">laurus cinnamomoides,</hi> to Cano Pimichin.<lb break="yes"/>By this small stream our travellers proceeded to the Rio Ne-<lb break="no"/>gro, which they descended as far as the small fortress of San<lb break="yes"/>Carlos, which has been erroneously believed to be situated<lb break="yes"/>under the <placeName key="aequator">equator</placeName>, and as far as the frontiers of the Grand<lb break="yes"/>Para, the captainry-general of Brazil. A canal from Temi<lb break="yes"/>to Pimichin, which on account of the level nature of the<lb break="yes"/>ground is very practicable, would form an interior com-<lb break="no"/>munication between the province of Caraccas and the ca-<lb break="no"/>pital of Para much shorter than that of Casquiare. By this<lb break="yes"/>canal also, such is the astonishing disposition of the rivers<lb break="yes"/>in this new continent, one might descend in a canoe from<lb break="yes"/>Rio Guallaga, within three days journey of Lima, or the<lb break="yes"/>South Sea, by the <placeName key="amazonas">river Amazon</placeName> and Rio Negro, as far as<lb break="yes"/>the mouths of the Orenoko opposite to Trinidad, a navi-<lb break="no"/>gation of nearly 2000 leagues. The misunderstanding which<lb break="yes"/>prevailed then between the courts of Madrid and Lisbon<lb break="yes"/>prevented M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> from carrying his operations be-<lb break="no"/>yond St. Gabriel de las Cochuellas, in the captainry-general<lb break="yes"/>of Great Para.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName> and Maldonado having <choice>
                        <sic>determineda stro-<lb break="no"/>nomically</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">determined astro-<lb break="no"/>nomically</corr>
                    </choice> the mouth of the Rio Negro, this obstacle was<lb break="yes"/>less sensible, and it remained to fix a part more unknown,<lb break="yes"/>which is the arm of the Orenoko called Casquiare, form-<lb break="no"/>ing the communication between the Orenoko and the <placeName key="amazonas">river<lb break="yes"/>Amazon</placeName>, and respecting the existence of which there have<lb break="yes"/>been so many disputes for fifty years past. To execute this<lb break="yes"/>labour, Messrs. <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName> and <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName> ascended from the<lb break="yes"/>Spanish fortress of St. Carlos along the Rio Negro and the<lb break="yes"/>Casquiare to the Orenoko, and on the latter to the mission<lb break="yes"/>of Esmeraldo, near the volcano Duida, or as far as the sources<lb break="yes"/>of that river.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Guaica Indians, a very white, small, and almost<lb break="yes"/>pigmy race of men, but exceedingly warlike, who inhabit<lb break="yes"/>the country to the east of the Pasimoni; and the Guajaribes,<lb break="yes"/>of a dark copper colour, extremely ferocious, and still an-<lb break="no"/>thropophagi, render fruitless every attempt to reach the<lb break="yes"/>sources of the Orenoko, which the maps of <persName key="caulin_a">Caulin</persName>, though<lb break="yes"/>in other respects meritorious, place in a longitude much too<lb break="yes"/>far east.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From the mission of Esmeralda, an assemblage of huts<lb break="yes"/>situated in the most remote and most solitary corner of this<lb break="yes"/>Indian world, our travellers descended, with the assistance<lb break="yes"/>of the floods, 340 leagues; that is to say, the whole of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">Orenoko,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="357" facs="#f0005"/> Orenoko, as far as towards its mouths at St. Thomas de la<lb break="yes"/>Nueva Guyana or <placeName key="angostura" >Angostura</placeName>, passing a second time the<lb break="yes"/>cataracts, to the south of which the two historiographers of<lb break="yes"/>these countries, father <persName key="gumilla_j">Gumilla</persName> and <persName key="caulin_a">Caulin</persName>, never penetrated.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the course of this long and painful navigation, the<lb break="yes"/>want of food and shelter; the nocturnal rains; living in<lb break="yes"/>the woods; the mosquitoes, and a multitude of other sting-<lb break="no"/>ing and venomous insects; the impossibility of cooling<lb break="yes"/>themselves by the bath, on account of the ferocity of the<lb break="yes"/>crocodile and of the small carib fish; together with the<lb break="yes"/>miasmata of a hot and damp climate, exposed our travellers<lb break="yes"/>to continual suffering. They returned from the Orenoko to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="barcelona">Barcelona</placeName> and Cumana by the plains of Cari and the mis-<lb break="no"/>sions of the Carib Indians, a very extraordinary race of<lb break="yes"/>men, and, next to the Patagonians, the tallest and most<lb break="yes"/>robust perhaps in the world.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After a stay of some months on the coast, they proceeded<lb break="yes"/>to the Havannah by the south of St. Domingo and Jamaica.<lb break="yes"/>This navigation, performed when the season was far ad-<lb break="no"/>vanced, was both long and dangerous, the vessel having<lb break="yes"/>been in great danger of being lost on the <placeName key="baxodelavibora">bank of Vibora</placeName>,<lb break="yes"/>the position of which M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> determined by the<lb break="yes" />timekeeper. He staid in the island of Cuba three months,<lb break="yes" />during which time he employed himself on the longitude<lb break="yes"/>of the Havannah, and the construction of a new kind of<lb break="yes"/>stove in the sugar-houses, which was speedily and gene-<lb break="no"/>rally adopted. When on the point of setting out for La<lb break="yes"/>Vera Cruz, intending to proceed by the way of Mexico<lb break="yes"/>and <placeName key="acapulco" >Acapulco</placeName> to the Philippines, and thence, if possible,<lb break="yes"/>by Bombay, <placeName key="bassora">Bussorah</placeName>, and Aleppo, to Constantinople,<lb break="yes"/>false intelligence respecting the voyage of captain <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>alarmed him, and induced him to alter his plan. The<lb break="yes"/>American papers announced that this navigator would set<lb break="yes"/>out from France for Buenos-Ayres, and that after doubling<lb break="yes"/>Cape Horn he would proceed along the coasts of Chili and<lb break="yes"/>Peru.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>, at the time of his departure from Paris<lb break="yes"/>in 1798, had promised to the Museum and to captain <persName key="baudin_tn">Bau-<lb break="no"/>din</persName>, that in whatever part of the world he might be, he<lb break="yes"/>would endeavour to join the French expedition as soon as<lb break="yes"/>he should hear of its having been set on foot. He flattered<lb break="yes"/>himself that his researches and those of <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName> would be<lb break="yes"/>more useful to the progress of the sciences if they united<lb break="yes"/>their labours to those of the men of science who were to<lb break="yes"/>accompany captain <persName key="baudin_tn" >Baudin</persName>. These considerations induced<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> to send his manuscripts of the years 1799<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">and</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="358" facs="#f0006"/> and 1800 directly to Europe, and to freight a small galliot<lb break="yes"/>in the port of <placeName key="batabano" >Batabano</placeName> to proceed to Carthagena in the<lb break="yes" />Indies, and thence, as soon as possible, by the isthmus of<lb break="yes" />Panama to the South Sea. He hoped to find captain <persName key="baudin_tn" >Baudin</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>at Guyaquil or at Lima, and to visit New Holland and the<lb break="yes"/>islands of the Pacific Ocean, so interesting in a moral point<lb break="yes"/>of view, and by the richness of their vegetation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It appeared to him imprudent to expose the manuscripts<lb break="yes"/>and collections already formed to the dangers of this long<lb break="yes" />navigation. The manuscripts, respecting the fate of which<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> remained in painful uncertainty for three<lb break="yes"/>years, till his arrival at Philadelphia, were saved; but a<lb break="yes"/>third of the collections were lost at sea by shipwreck: for-<lb break="no"/>tunately this loss, and that of some insects from the Ore-<lb break="no"/>noko and Rio Negro, extended only to duplicates; but<lb break="yes"/>this shipwreck proved fatal to a friend to whom M. Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt had intrusted his plants and insects, Fray <persName key="gonzalez_j">Juan Gon-<lb break="no"/>zales</persName>, a Franciscan, a young man of great courage and ac-<lb break="no"/>tivity, who had penetrated in this unknown world from<lb break="yes"/>Spanish Guyana much farther than any other European.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> set out from <placeName key="batabano">Batabano</placeName> in March 1801,<lb break="yes"/>coasting along the south side of the island of Cuba, and<lb break="yes"/>determining astronomically several points in that group of<lb break="yes"/>small isles called the King&#x2019;s Gardens, and the approaches<lb break="yes"/>to the port of Trinidad. A navigation which ought to have<lb break="yes"/>been only thirteen or fifteen days, was prolonged by cur-<lb break="no"/>rents beyond a month. The galliot was carried by them<lb break="yes"/>too far east, beyond the mouths of the <placeName key="atrato">Atracto</placeName>. They<lb break="yes"/>touched at Rio Sinu, where no botanist had ever searched<lb break="yes"/>for plants; but they found it difficult to land at Carthagena,<lb break="yes"/>on account of the violence of the breakers of St. Martha.<lb break="yes"/>The galliot had almost gone to pieces near Giant&#x2019;s Point;<lb break="yes"/>they were obliged to save themselves towards the shore in<lb break="yes"/>order to anchor; and this disappointment gave M. Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt an opportunity of observing the eclipse of the moon<lb break="yes"/>on the 2d of March 1801. Unfortunately they learned on<lb break="yes"/>this coast that the season for navigating the South Sea from<lb break="yes"/>Panama to Guyaquil was already too far advanced: it was<lb break="yes"/>necessary to give up the design of crossing the isthmus;<lb break="yes"/>and the desire of seeing the celebrated <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, and exa-<lb break="no"/>mining his immense treasures in natural history, induced<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> to spend some weeks in the forests of Tur-<lb break="no"/>baco, ornamented with <hi rendition="#i">gustavia, toluifera, anacardium ca-<lb break="no"/>racoli,</hi> and the <persName key="cavanilles_aj">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Cavanillesca</hi>
                    </persName> of the Peruvian botanists; and<lb break="yes"/>to ascend in thirty-five days the beautiful and majestic river<lb break="yes"/>of the Magdalen, of which he sketched out a chart, though<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">tormented</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="359" facs="#f0007"/> tormented by the mosquitoes, while <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName> studied the<lb break="yes" />vegetation, rich in <hi rendition="#i">heliconia, psychostria, melastoma, my-<lb break="no"/>rodia,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">dychotria emetica,</hi> the root of which is the ipe-<lb break="no"/>cacuanha of Carthagena.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Having landed at Honda, our travellers proceeded on<lb break="yes"/>mules, the only way of travelling in <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>, and<lb break="yes"/>by frightful roads through forests of oaks, <hi rendition="#i">melastoma</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">cinchona,</hi> to Santa Fé de Bagota, the capital of the kingdom<lb break="yes"/>of New Grenada, situated in a beautiful plain 1360 toises<lb break="yes"/>above the level of the sea, and, in consequence of a perpe-<lb break="no"/>tual spring temperature, abounding in the wheat of Europe<lb break="yes"/>and the sesamum of Asia. The superb collections of <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>;<lb break="yes"/>the grand and sublime cataract of Tequendama, 98 toises<lb break="yes"/>or 588 feet in height; the mines of Mariquita, St. Ana,<lb break="yes"/>and Zipaguira; the natural bridge of Icononzo, two de-<lb break="no"/>tached rocks which by means of an earthquake have been<lb break="yes"/>disposed in such a manner as to support a third; occupied<lb break="yes"/>the attention of our travellers at Santa Fé till September<lb break="yes"/>1801.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Though the rainy season had now rendered the roads al-<lb break="no"/>most impassable, they set out for Quito; they re-descended<lb break="yes"/>by Fusagasuga, in the valley of Magdalena, and passed the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> of Quindiu, where the snowy pyramid of Tolina rises<lb break="yes"/>amidst forests of <hi rendition="#i">styrax passiflora</hi> in trees, <hi rendition="#i">bambusa,</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>wax palms. For thirteen days they were obliged to drag<lb break="yes"/>themselves through horrid mud, and to sleep, as on the<lb break="yes"/>Orenoko, under the bare heavens, in woods where they saw<lb break="yes"/>no vestiges of man. When they arrived, bare-footed and<lb break="yes"/>drenched with continual rain, in the valley of the river<lb break="yes"/>Cauca, they stopped at Cathago and Buga, and proceeded<lb break="yes"/>along the province of Choco, the country of platina, which<lb break="yes"/>is found between rolled fragments of basaltes, filled with<lb break="yes"/>olivin and augite, green rock (the <hi rendition="#i" >grunstein</hi> of <persName key="werner_ag">Werner</persName>),<lb break="yes"/>and fossil wood.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>They ascended by Caloto and Quilichao, where gold is<lb break="yes"/>washed, to Popayan, visited by <persName key="bouguer_p">Bouguer</persName> when he returned<lb break="yes"/>to France, and situated at the bottom of the snowy volca-<lb break="no"/>noes of Puracé and Sotara, one of the most picturesque<lb break="yes"/>situations and in the most delightful climate of the uni-<lb break="no"/>verse, where <persName key="reaumur_rafd" >Reaumur&#x2019;s</persName> thermometer stands constantly be-<lb break="no" />tween 17 and 19 degrees. When they had reached, with<lb break="yes"/>much difficulty, the crater of the volcano of Puracé, filled<lb break="yes"/>with boiling water, which from the midst of the snow<lb break="yes"/>throws up, with a horrid roaring, vapours of sulphurated<lb break="yes"/>hydrogen, our travellers passed from Popayan by the steep<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">cordilleras</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="360" facs="#f0008"/> cordilleras of <placeName key="almager" >Almaguer</placeName> a Parto, avoiding the contagious<lb break="yes"/>air of the valley of Patia.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From Pasto, a town situated at the bottom of a burning<lb break="yes"/>volcano, they traversed by Guachucal the high plateau of<lb break="yes"/>the province of Pastos, separated from the Pacific Ocean<lb break="yes"/>by the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> of the volcano of Chili and Cumbal, and<lb break="yes"/>celebrated by its great fertility in wheat and the <hi rendition="#i">erytroxy-<lb break="no"/>lon Peruvianum,</hi> called cocoa. At length, after a journey<lb break="yes"/>of four months on mules, they arrived at the towns of<lb break="yes"/>Ibarra and Quito. This long passage through the cordillera<lb break="yes"/>of the high <placeName key="anden" >Andes</placeName>, at a season which rendered the roads<lb break="yes" />impassable, and during which they were exposed to rains<lb break="yes"/>which continued seven or eight hours a day, encumbered<lb break="yes"/>with a great number of instruments and voluminous collec-<lb break="no"/>tions, would have been almost impossible, without the ge-<lb break="no"/>nerous and kind assistance of M. <persName key="mendiunetta">Mendiunetta</persName>, viceroy of<lb break="yes"/>Santa Fé, and the baron <persName key="carondelet_flhd" >de Carondelet</persName>, president of Quito,<lb break="yes"/>who, being equally zealous for the progress of science,<lb break="yes"/>caused the roads and the most dangerous bridges to be re-<lb break="no"/>paired on a route of 450 leagues in length.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Messrs. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> and <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName> arrived on the 6th of<lb break="yes" />January 1802 at Quito, a capital celebrated in the annals<lb break="yes"/>of astronomy by the labours of <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName>, <persName key="bouguer_p">Bouguer</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="godin_l">Godin</persName>, and Don <persName key="juanysantacilia_j">Jorge-Juan</persName> and <persName key="ulloa_ad" >Ulloa</persName>; justly celebrated<lb break="yes"/>also by the great amiableness of its inhabitants and their<lb break="yes"/>happy disposition for the arts. Our travellers continued<lb break="yes"/>their geological and botanical researches for eight or nine<lb break="yes"/>months in the kingdom of Quito; a country rendered per-<lb break="no"/>haps the most interesting in the world by the colossal<lb break="yes"/>height of its snowy summits; the activity of its volcanoes,<lb break="yes"/>which in turns throw up flames, rocks, mud, and hydro-<lb break="no"/>sulphureous water; the frequency of its earthquakes, one<lb break="yes"/>of which, on the 7th of February 1797, swallowed up in<lb break="yes"/>a few seconds nearly 40,000 inhabitants; its vegetation;<lb break="yes"/>the remains of Peruvian architecture; and, above all, the<lb break="yes"/>manners of its antient inhabitants.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After two fruitless attempts, they succeeded in twice<lb break="yes"/>ascending to the crater of the volcano of Pinchinca, where<lb break="yes"/>they made experiments on the analysis of the air; its elec-<lb break="no"/>tric charge, magnetism, hygroscopy, electricity, and the<lb break="yes"/>temperature of boiling water. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName> saw the same<lb break="yes"/>crater, which he very properly compares to the chaos of<lb break="yes"/>the poets; but he was there without instruments, and could<lb break="yes"/>remain only some minutes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In his time this immense mouth, hollowed out in basaltic<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">porphyry,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="361" facs="#f0009"/> porphyry, was cooled and filled with snow: our travellers<lb break="yes"/>found it again on fire; and this intelligence was distressing<lb break="yes"/>to the town of Quito, which is distant only about four or<lb break="yes"/>five thousand toises. Here M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> was in danger<lb break="yes"/>of losing his life. Being alone with an Indian, who was<lb break="yes"/>as little acquainted with the crater as himself, and walking<lb break="yes"/>over a fissure concealed by a thin stratum of congealed snow,<lb break="yes"/>he had almost fallen into it.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Our travellers, during their stay in the kingdom of Quito,<lb break="yes"/>made several excursions to the snowy mountains of <placeName key="antisana">Anti-<lb break="no"/>sana</placeName>, Cotopaxi, Tunguragua, and Chimborazo, which is<lb break="yes"/>the highest summit of our earth, and which the French<lb break="yes"/>academicians measured only by approximation. They exa-<lb break="no"/>mined in particular the geognostic part of the cordillera of<lb break="yes"/>the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>, respecting which nothing has yet been published<lb break="yes"/>in Europe; mineralogy, as we may say, being newer than the<lb break="yes"/>voyage of <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName>, whose universal genius and in-<lb break="no"/>credible activity embraced every thing else that could be<lb break="yes"/>interesting to the sciences. The trigonometrical and baro-<lb break="no"/>metrical measurements of M. <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName> have proved that<lb break="yes"/>some of these volcanoes, and especially that of Tunguragua,<lb break="yes"/>have become considerably lower since 1753; a result which<lb break="yes"/>accords with what the inhabitants of Pelileo and the plains<lb break="yes"/>of Tapia have observed.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> found that all these large masses were<lb break="yes"/>the work of crystallization. &#x201C;Every thing I have seen,&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>says he in a letter to <persName key="lametherie_jcd">Delametherie</persName>, &#x201C;in these regions,<lb break="yes"/>where the highest elevations of the globe are situated, have<lb break="yes"/>confirmed me more and more in the grand idea that you<lb break="yes"/>threw out in your Theory of the Earth, the most complete<lb break="yes"/>work we have on that subject, in regard to the formation of<lb break="yes"/>mountains. All the masses of which they consist have<lb break="yes"/>united according to their affinities by the laws of attraction,<lb break="yes"/>and have formed these elevations, more or less considerable<lb break="yes"/>in different parts on the surface of the earth, by the laws of<lb break="yes"/>general crystallization. There can remain no doubt in this<lb break="yes"/>respect to the traveller who considers without prejudice<lb break="yes"/>these large masses. You will see in our relations that there<lb break="yes"/>is not one of the objects you treat of which we have not en-<lb break="no"/>deavoured to improve by our labours.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In all these excursions, begun in January 1802, our travel-<lb break="no"/>lers were accompanied by M. <persName key="montufarylarrea_c">Charles Montufar</persName>, son of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="montufarylarrea_jpd">marquis de Selvalegre</persName>, of Quito, an individual zealous for the<lb break="yes"/>progress of the sciences, and who caused to be reconstructed,<lb break="yes"/>at his own expense, the pyramids of Sarouguier, the boun-<lb break="no"/>daries of the celebrated base of the French and Spanish aca-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">demicians.</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="362" facs="#f0010"/> demicians. This interesting young man, having accom-<lb break="no"/>panied M. <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName> during the rest of his expedition to<lb break="yes" />Peru and the kingdom of Mexico, proceeded with him to<lb break="yes"/>Europe. The efforts of these three travellers were so much<lb break="yes"/>favoured by circumstances, that they reached the greatest<lb break="yes"/>heights to which man had ever attained in these mountains.<lb break="yes"/>On the volcano of <placeName key="antisana">Antisana</placeName> they carried instruments 2200,<lb break="yes"/>and on Chimborazo June 23, 1802, 3300 feet higher than<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condamine</persName> and <persName key="bouguer_p">Bouguer</persName> did on Corazon. They ascended to<lb break="yes"/>the height of 3036 toises above the level of the Pacific<lb break="yes"/>Ocean, where the blood issued from their eyes, lips, and<lb break="yes"/>gums, and where they experienced a cold not indicated by<lb break="yes"/>the thermometer, but which arose from the little caloric<lb break="yes"/>disengaged during the inspiration of air so much rarefied.<lb break="yes"/>A fissure eighty toises in depth and of great breadth pre-<lb break="no"/>vented them from reaching the top of Chimborazo when<lb break="yes"/>they were distant from it only about 224 toises.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">[To be continued.]</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <pb n="34" facs="#f0011"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>VIII. <hi rendition="#i">Short Account of Travels between the Tropics, by<lb break="yes"/>Messrs.</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">and</hi>
                    <persName key="bonpland_ajag">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Bonpland,</hi>
                    </persName>
                    <hi rendition="#i">in</hi> 1799, 1800,<lb break="yes"/>1801, 1802, 1803, <hi rendition="#i">and</hi> 1804. <hi rendition="#i">By</hi>
                    <persName key="lametherie_jcd">J. C. <hi rendition="#k">Delame-<lb break="no" />therie.</hi>
                    </persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#c">[Concluded from p. 362]</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#in">D</hi>uring</hi> his residence at Quito M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> received a<lb break="yes"/>letter from the French National Institute, informing him<lb break="yes"/>that captain <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin</persName> had set out for New Holland, pursuing<lb break="yes"/>an easterly course by the Cape of Good Hope. He found<lb break="yes"/>it necessary therefore to give up all idea of joining him,<lb break="yes"/>though our travellers had entertained this hope for thirteen<lb break="yes"/>months, by which means they lost the advantage of an easy<lb break="yes"/>passage from the Havannah to Mexico and the Philippines.<lb break="yes"/>It had made them travel by sea and by land more than a<lb break="yes"/>thousand leagues to the south, exposed to every extreme of<lb break="yes"/>temperature, from summits covered with perpetual snow to<lb break="yes"/>the bottom of those profound ravines where the thermo-<lb break="no"/>meter stands night and day between 25° and 31° of <persName key="reaumur_rafd">Reau-<lb break="no"/>mur</persName>. But, accustomed to disappointments of every kind,<lb break="yes"/>they readily consoled themselves on account of their fate.<lb break="yes"/>They were once more sensible that man must depend only<lb break="yes"/>on what can be produced by his own energy; and <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin&#x2019;s</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>voyage, or rather the false intelligence of the direction he<lb break="yes"/>had taken, made them traverse immense countries towards<lb break="yes"/>which no naturalist perhaps would otherwise have turned<lb break="yes"/>his researches. M. <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName> being then resolved to pursue<lb break="yes"/>his own expedition, proceeded from Quito towards the river<lb break="yes"/>Amazon and Lima, with a view of making the important<lb break="yes"/>observation of the transit of Mercury over the sun&#x2019;s disk.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Our travellers first visited the ruins of Lactacunga,<lb break="yes"/>Hambato, and Riobamba, a district convulsed by the<lb break="yes"/>dreadful earthquake of the year 1797. They passed through<lb break="yes"/>the snows of Assonay to Cuenca, and thence with great<lb break="yes"/>difficulty, on account of the carriage of their instruments<lb break="yes"/>and packages of plants, by the paramo of Saraguro to<lb break="yes"/>Loxa. It was here, in the forests of Gonzanama and Ma-<lb break="no"/>lacates, that they studied the valuable tree which first made<lb break="yes"/>known to man the febrifuge qualities of cinchona. The<lb break="yes"/>extent of the territory which their travels embraced, gave<lb break="yes"/>them an advantage never before enjoyed by any botanist,<lb break="yes"/>namely, that of comparing the different kinds of cinchona<lb break="yes"/>of Santa Fé, Popayan, Cuenca, Loxa, and Jaen, with the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">cuspa</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">cuspare</hi> of Cumana and Rio Carony, the latter<lb break="yes"/>of which, named improperly <hi rendition="#i">Cortex angustur&#x00E6;,</hi> appears to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">belong</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="55" facs="#f0012"/> belong to a new genus of the <hi rendition="#i" >pentandria monogynia,</hi> with<lb break="yes"/>alternate leaves.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From Loxa they entered Peru by <placeName key="ayavaca">Ayavaca</placeName> and Gounca-<lb break="no"/>bamba, traversing the high summit of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>, to pro-<lb break="no"/>ceed to the <placeName key="amazonas">river Amazon</placeName>. They had to pass thirty-five<lb break="yes"/>times in the course of two days the river Chamaya, some-<lb break="no"/>times on a raft, and sometimes by fording. They saw the<lb break="yes"/>superb remains of the causeway of Ynga, which may be<lb break="yes"/>compared to the most beautiful causeways in France and<lb break="yes"/>Spain, and which proceeds on the porphyritic ridge of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>, from Cusco to Assonay, and is furnished with<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">tambo</hi> (inns) and public fountains. They then embarked<lb break="yes"/>on a raft of <hi rendition="#i">ochroma,</hi> at the small Indian village of Cha-<lb break="no"/>maya, and descended by the river of the same name, to that<lb break="yes"/>of the <placeName key="amazonas" >Amazons</placeName>, determining by the culmination of several<lb break="yes"/>stars, and by the difference of time, the astronomical posi-<lb break="no"/>tion of that confluence.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName>, when he returned from Quito to Para and<lb break="yes"/>to France, embarked on the <placeName key="amazonas">river Amazon</placeName> only below<lb break="yes"/>Quebrada de Chucunga; he therefore observed the longi-<lb break="no"/>tude only at the mouth of the Rio Napo. M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>endeavoured to supply this deficiency in the beautiful chart<lb break="yes"/>of the French astronomer, navigating the <placeName key="amazonas">river Amazon</placeName> as<lb break="yes"/>far as the cataracts of Rentema, and forming at Tomependa,<lb break="yes"/>the capital of the province of Jaen de Bracamorros, a de-<lb break="no"/>tailed plan of that unknown part of the Upper Maranon,<lb break="yes"/>both from his own observations and the information ob-<lb break="no"/>tained from Indian travellers. M. <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName> in the mean<lb break="yes"/>time made an interesting excursion to the forests around<lb break="yes"/>the town of Jaen, where he discovered new species of cin-<lb break="no"/>chona; and after greatly suffering from the scorching heat<lb break="yes"/>of these solitary districts, and admiring a vegetation rich in<lb break="yes"/>new species of <hi rendition="#i">Jacquinia, Godoya, Porteria, <persName key="bougainville_lad">Bougainvillea</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>Colletia,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Pisonia,</hi> our three travellers crossed for the<lb break="yes"/>fifth time the cordillera of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> by Montan, in order<lb break="yes" />to return to Peru.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>They fixed the point where <persName key="borda_jcd">Borda&#x2019;s</persName> compass indicated the<lb break="yes"/>zero of the magnetic inclination, though at 7 degrees of<lb break="yes"/>south latitude. They examined the mines of Hualguayoc,<lb break="yes"/>where native silver is found in large masses at the height of<lb break="yes"/>2000 toises above the level of the sea, in mines, some<lb break="yes"/>metalliferous veins of which contain petrified shells, and<lb break="yes"/>which, with those of Huantajayo, are at present the richest<lb break="yes"/>of Peru. From Caxamarca, celebrated by its thermal<lb break="yes"/>waters, and by the ruins of the palace of <persName key="atahualpa">Atahualpa</persName>, they<lb break="yes"/>descended to Truxillo, in the neighbourhood of which are<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">found</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="56" facs="#f0013"/> found vestiges of the immense Peruvian city of Mansiche,<lb break="yes"/>ornamented with pyramids, in one of which was discovered,<lb break="yes"/>in the eighteenth century, hammered gold to the value of<lb break="yes"/>more than 150,000 l. sterling.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On this western declivity of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> our travellers en-<lb break="no"/>joyed, for the first time, the striking view of the Pacific<lb break="yes"/>Ocean; and from that long and narrow valley, the inhabi-<lb break="no"/>tants of which are unacquainted with rain or thunder, and<lb break="yes"/>where, under a happy climate, the most absolute power,<lb break="yes"/>and that most dangerous to man, theocracy itself, seems<lb break="yes"/>to imitate the beneficence of nature.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From Truxillo they followed the dry coasts of the South<lb break="yes"/>Sea, formerly watered and rendered fertile by the canals of<lb break="yes"/>the Ynga; nothing of which remains but melancholy<lb break="yes"/>ruins. When they arrived, by Santa and Guarmey, at Lima,<lb break="yes"/>they remained some months in that interesting capital of<lb break="yes"/>Peru, the inhabitants of which are distinguished by the<lb break="yes"/>vivacity of their genius and the liberality of their sentiments.<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName> had the happiness of observing, in a pretty<lb break="yes"/>complete manner, at the port of Callao at Lima, the end<lb break="yes"/>of the transit of Mercury: a circumstance the more fortu-<lb break="no"/>nate, as the thick fog which prevails at that season often<lb break="yes"/>prevents the sun&#x2019;s disk from being seen for twenty days.<lb break="yes"/>He was astonished to find in Peru, at so immense a distance<lb break="yes"/>from Europe, the newest literary productions in chemistry,<lb break="yes"/>mathematics, and physiology; and he admired the great<lb break="yes"/>intellectual activity of a people whom the Europeans accuse<lb break="yes"/>of indolence and luxury.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the month of January 1803 our travellers embarked in<lb break="yes"/>the king&#x2019;s corvette La Castora for Guyaquil; a passage which<lb break="yes" />is performed, by the help of the winds and the currents, in<lb break="yes" />three or four days, whereas the return from Guyaquil re-<lb break="no"/>quires as many months. In the former port, situated on<lb break="yes"/>the banks of an immense river, the vegetation of which in<lb break="yes"/>palms, <hi rendition="#i">plumeria, tabern&#x00E6;montana,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i" >scitamine&#x00E6;,</hi> is ma-<lb break="no"/>jestic beyond all description. They heard growling every<lb break="yes"/>moment the volcano of Catopaxi, which made a dreadful<lb break="yes"/>explosion on the 6th of January 1803.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>They immediately set out that they might have a nearer<lb break="yes"/>view of its ravages, and to visit it a second time; but the<lb break="yes"/>unexpected news of the sudden departure of the Atlanta<lb break="yes"/>frigate, and the fear of not finding another opportunity for<lb break="yes"/>several months, obliged them to return, after being tor-<lb break="no"/>mented for seven days by the mosquitoes of <placeName key="babaoyo">Babaoyo</placeName> and<lb break="yes"/>Ugibar.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>They had a favourable navigation of thirty days on the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">Pacific</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="57" facs="#f0014"/> Pacific Ocean to <placeName key="acapulco" >Acapulco</placeName>, the western port of the king-<lb break="no"/>dom of New Spain, celebrated by the beauty of its bason,<lb break="yes"/>which appears to have been cut out in the granite rocks by<lb break="yes"/>the violence of earthquakes; celebrated also by the wretch-<lb break="no"/>edness of its inhabitants, who see there millions of piastres<lb break="yes"/>embarked for the Philippines and China; and unfortunately<lb break="yes"/>celebrated by a climate as scorching as mortal.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> intended at first to stay only a few months<lb break="yes"/>in Mexico, and to hasten his return to Europe; his travels<lb break="yes"/>had already been too long; the instruments, and particularly<lb break="yes"/>the time-keepers, began to be gradually deranged; and all<lb break="yes"/>the efforts he had made to get new ones had proved fruit-<lb break="no"/>less. Besides, the progress of the sciences in Europe is<lb break="yes"/>so rapid, that in travels of more than four years a traveller<lb break="yes"/>may see certain ph&#x00E6;nomena under points of view which are<lb break="yes"/>no longer interesting when his labours are presented to the<lb break="yes"/>public.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> flattered himself with the hope, of being<lb break="yes"/>in England in the months of August or September 1803;<lb break="yes"/>but the attraction of a country so beautiful and so variegated<lb break="yes"/>as the kingdom of New Spain, the great hospitality of its<lb break="yes"/>inhabitants, and the dread of the yellow fever at Vera Cruz,<lb break="yes"/>which cuts off almost all those who between the months<lb break="yes"/>of June and October come down from the mountains, in-<lb break="no"/>duced him to defer his departure till the middle of winter.<lb break="yes"/>After having occupied his attention with plants, the state<lb break="yes"/>of the air, the hourly variations of the barometer, the ph&#x00E6;-<lb break="no"/>nomena of the magnet, and in particular the longitude of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="acapulco">Acapulco</placeName>, a port in which two able astronomers, Messrs.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="espinosa_01">Espinosa</persName> and Galeano, had before made observations, our<lb break="yes"/>travellers set out for Mexico. They ascended gradually from<lb break="yes"/>the scorching valleys of Mescala and Papagayo, where the<lb break="yes"/>thermometer in the shade stood at 32° of <persName key="reaumur_rafd">Reaumur</persName>, and<lb break="yes"/>where they passed the river on the fruit of the <hi rendition="#i">crescentia<lb break="yes" />pinnata,</hi> bound together by ropes of agave, to the high<lb break="yes" />plateaux of Chilpantzingo, Tehuilotepec and Tasco.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At these heights of six or seven hundred toises above the<lb break="yes"/>level of the sea, in consequence of the mildness and cool-<lb break="no"/>ness of the climate, the oak, cypress, fir, and fern, begin<lb break="yes"/>to be seen, together with the kinds of grain cultivated in<lb break="yes"/>Europe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Having spent some time in the mines of Tasco, the oldest<lb break="yes"/>and formerly the richest in the kingdom, and having studied<lb break="yes"/>the nature of those silvery veins which pass from the hard<lb break="yes" />calcareous rock to micaceous schist and inclose foliaceous<lb break="yes" />gypsum, they ascended, by Cuernaraca and the cold regions<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">of</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="58" facs="#f0015"/> of Guchilaqua, to the capital of Mexico. This city, which<lb break="yes"/>has 150,000 inhabitants, and stands on the site of the old<lb break="yes"/>Tenochtitlan, between the lakes of Tezcuco and Xochimilo,<lb break="yes"/>which have decreased in size since the Spaniards, to lessen<lb break="yes"/>the danger of inundations, have opened the mountains of<lb break="yes"/>Sincoc, is intersected by broad straight streets. It stands<lb break="yes"/>in sight of two snowy mountains, one of which is named<lb break="yes"/>Popocatepec; and of a volcano still burning; and, at the<lb break="yes"/>height of 1160 toises, enjoys a temperate and agreeable cli-<lb break="no"/>mate: it is surrounded by canals, walks bordered with trees,<lb break="yes"/>a multitude of Indian hamlets, and without doubt may be<lb break="yes"/>compared to the finest cities of Europe. It is distinguished<lb break="yes"/>also by its large scientific establishments, which may vie<lb break="yes"/>with several of the old continent, and to which there are<lb break="yes"/>none similar in the new.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The botanical garden, directed by that excellent botanist<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="cervantes_vicente">Cervantes</persName>; the expedition of M. <persName key="sesselacasta_md">Sesse</persName>, who is accom-<lb break="no"/>panied by able draftsmen, and whose object is to acquire<lb break="yes"/>a knowledge of the plants of Mexico; the School of Mines,<lb break="yes"/>established by the liberality of the corps of miners and by<lb break="yes"/>the creative genius of M. <persName key="elhuyar_fd" >d&#x2019;Elhuyar</persName>; and the Academy of<lb break="yes"/>Painting, Engraving, and Sculpture; all tend to diffuse<lb break="yes"/>taste and knowledge in a country the riches of which<lb break="yes"/>seem to oppose intellectual culture.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>With instruments taken from the excellent collection of<lb break="yes"/>the School of Mines, M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> determined the lon-<lb break="no"/>gitude of Mexico, in which there was an error of nearly<lb break="yes"/>two degrees, as has been confirmed by corresponding ob-<lb break="no"/>servations of the satellites made at the Havannah.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After a stay of some months in that capital, our travellers<lb break="yes" />visited the celebrated mines of Moran and Real-del-Monte,<lb break="yes" />where the vein of La Biscayna has given millions of piastres<lb break="yes" />to the counts De Regla; they examined the obsidian stones<lb break="yes"/>of Oyamel, which form strata in the pearl stone and por-<lb break="no"/>phyry, and served as knives to the antient Mexicans. The<lb break="yes"/>whole of this country, filled with basaltes, amygdaloids,<lb break="yes"/>and calcareous and secondary formations, from the large<lb break="yes"/>cavern of Danto, traversed by a river to the porphyritic<lb break="yes"/>rocks of Actopan, presents ph&#x00E6;nomena interesting to the<lb break="yes"/>geologue, which have been already examined by M. <persName key="rio_amd">del Rio</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>the pupil of <persName key="werner_ag">Werner</persName>, and one of the most learned minera-<lb break="no"/>logists of the present day.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On their return from their excursion to Moran in July<lb break="yes"/>1803, they undertook another to the northern part of the<lb break="yes"/>kingdom. At first they directed their researches to Hue-<lb break="no"/>huetoca, where, at the expense of six millions of piastres,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">an</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="59" facs="#f0016"/> an aperture has been formed in the mountain of Sincoc to<lb break="yes"/>drain off the waters from the valley of Mexico to the river<lb break="yes"/>Montezuma. They then passed Queretaro, by Salamanca<lb break="yes"/>and the fertile plains of Yrapuato, to Guanaxuato, a town<lb break="yes"/>which contains 50,000 inhabitants: it is situated in a narrow<lb break="yes"/>defile, and celebrated by its mines, which are of far greater<lb break="yes"/>consequence than those of Potosi.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The mine of count de Valenciana, which has given birth<lb break="yes"/>to a considerable town on a hill which thirty years age<lb break="yes"/>scarcely afforded pasture to goats, is already 1840 feet in<lb break="yes"/>perpendicular depth. It is the deepest and richest in the<lb break="yes"/>world; the annual profit of the proprietors having never<lb break="yes"/>been less than three millions of livres, and it sometimes<lb break="yes"/>amounts to five or six.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After two months employed in measurements and geo-<lb break="no"/>logical researches, and after having examined the thermal<lb break="yes"/>waters of Comagillas, the temperature of which is 11° of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="reaumur_rafd">Reaumur</persName> higher than those of the Philippine islands, which<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="sonnerat">Sonnerat</persName> considers as the hottest in the world, our travel-<lb break="no"/>lers proceeded through the valley of St. Jago, where they<lb break="yes"/>thought they saw in several lakes at the summits of the ba-<lb break="no"/>saltic mountains so many craters of burnt-out volcanoes, to<lb break="yes"/>Valladolid, the capital of the antient kingdom of Michoa-<lb break="no"/>can. They thence descended, notwithstanding the con-<lb break="no"/>tinual autumnal rains, by Patzquaro, situated on the margin<lb break="yes"/>of a very extensive lake towards the coast of the Pacific<lb break="yes"/>Ocean, to the plains of Jorullo, where in the course of one<lb break="yes"/>night in 1759, during one of the greatest convulsions which<lb break="yes"/>the globe ever experienced, there issued from the earth a<lb break="yes"/>volcano 1494 feet in height, surrounded by more than<lb break="yes"/>2000 mouths still emitting smoke. They descended into<lb break="yes"/>the burning crater of the great volcano to the perpendicular<lb break="yes"/>depth of 258 feet, jumping over fissures which exhaled<lb break="yes"/>flaming sulphurated hydrogen gas. After great danger,<lb break="yes"/>arising from the brittleness of the basaltic and sienitic lava,<lb break="yes"/>they reached nearly the bottom of the crater, and analysed<lb break="yes"/>the air in it, which was found to be surcharged in an extra-<lb break="no"/>ordinary manner with carbonic acid.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From the kingdom of Michoacan, one of the most agree-<lb break="no"/>able and most fertile countries in the Indies, they returned<lb break="yes"/>to Mexico by the high plateau of Tolucca, in which they<lb break="yes"/>measured the snowy mountain of the same name, ascending<lb break="yes"/>to its highest summit, the peak of Fraide, which rises 2364<lb break="yes"/>toises above the level of the sea: they visited also at Toluc-<lb break="no"/>ca the famous hand-tree the <hi rendition="#i">cheiranthost&#x00E6;mon</hi> of M. <persName key="cervantes_vicente">Cer-<lb break="no"/>vantes</persName>, a genus which presents a ph&#x00E6;nomenon almost<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">unique,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="60" facs="#f0017"/> unique,&#x2014;that of there being only one individual of it,<lb break="yes"/>which has existed since the remotest antiquity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On their return to the capital of Mexico they remained<lb break="yes"/>there several months to arrange their herbals, abundant in<lb break="yes"/>gramineous plants, and their geological collections; to cal-<lb break="no"/>culate their barometric and trigonometrical measurements<lb break="yes"/>performed in the course of that year; and in particular to<lb break="yes"/>make fair drawings of the geological atlas, which M. Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt proposes to publish.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Their return furnished them also with an opportunity of<lb break="yes"/>assisting at the erection of the colossal equestrian statue of<lb break="yes"/>the king, which one artist, M. Tolsa, overcoming diffi-<lb break="no"/>culties of which a proper idea cannot be formed in Europe,<lb break="yes"/>modelled, cast, and erected on a very high pedestal: it is<lb break="yes"/>wrought in the simplest style, and would be an ornament to<lb break="yes"/>the finest capitals in Europe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In January 1804 our travellers left Mexico to explore the<lb break="yes"/>eastern declivity of the cordillera of New Spain: they mea-<lb break="no"/>sured geometrically the two volcanoes of Puebla, Popoca-<lb break="no"/>tepec and Itzaccihuatl. According to a fabulous tradition,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="ordaz_dd">Diego Ordaz</persName> entered the inaccessible crater of the former<lb break="yes"/>suspended by ropes, in order to collect sulphur, which may<lb break="yes"/>be found every where in the plains.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> discovered that the volcano of Popocatepec,<lb break="yes"/>on which M. <persName key="sonneschmidt_ft" >Sonnenschmidt</persName>, a zealous mineralogist, had<lb break="yes"/>the courage to ascend 2557 toises, is higher than the peak<lb break="yes"/>of Orizaba, which has hitherto been considered the highest<lb break="yes"/>colossus of the country of <placeName key="anahuac">Anahuac</placeName>: he measured also the<lb break="yes"/>great pyramid of Cholula, a mysterious work constructed<lb break="yes"/>of unbaked brick by the Tultequas, and from the summit<lb break="yes"/>of which there is a most beautiful view over the snowy<lb break="yes"/>summits and smiling plains of Tlaxcala.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After these researches they descended by Perote to Xa-<lb break="no"/>lapa, a town situated at the height of 674 toises above the<lb break="yes"/>level of the sea, at a mean height at which the inhabitants<lb break="yes"/>enjoy the fruits of all climates, and a temperature equally<lb break="yes"/>mild and beneficial to the health of man. It was here that,<lb break="yes"/>by the kindness of Mr. <persName key="murphy_t">Thomas Murphy</persName>, a respectable in-<lb break="no"/>dividual, who to a large fortune adds a taste for the sciences,<lb break="yes"/>our travellers found every facility imaginable for performing<lb break="yes"/>their operations in the neighbouring mountains.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The level of the horrid road which leads from Xalapa to<lb break="yes"/>Perote, through almost impenetrable forests of oaks and firs,<lb break="yes"/>and which has begun to be converted into a magnificent<lb break="yes"/>causeway, was three times taken with the barometer.<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName>, notwithstanding the quantity of snow which<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">had</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="61" facs="#f0018"/> had fallen the evening before, ascended to the summit of<lb break="yes"/>the famous Cofre, which is 162 toises higher than the peak<lb break="yes"/>of Teneriffe, and fixed its position by direct observations.<lb break="yes"/>He measured also trigonometrically the peak of Orizava,<lb break="yes"/>which the Indians call Sitlaltepetl, because the luminous<lb break="yes"/>exhalations of its crater resemble at a distance a falling star,<lb break="yes"/>and respecting the longitude of which M. <persName key="ferrerycafranga_jj">Ferrer</persName> published<lb break="yes"/>very exact operations.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After an interesting residence in these countries, where,<lb break="yes"/>under the shade of the <hi rendition="#i">liquidambar</hi> and <hi rendition="#i" >amyris,</hi> are found<lb break="yes"/>growing the <hi rendition="#i" >epidendrum vanilla</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">convolvulus jalappa,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>two productions equally valuable for exportation, our tra-<lb break="no"/>vellers descended towards the coast of Vera Cruz, situated<lb break="yes"/>between hills of shifting sand, the reverberation of which<lb break="yes"/>causes a suffocating heat; but happily escaped the yellow<lb break="yes"/>fever, which prevailed there at the time.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>They proceeded in a Spanish frigate to the Havannah to<lb break="yes"/>get the collections and herbals left there in 1800, and, after<lb break="yes"/>a stay of two months, embarked for the United States: but<lb break="yes"/>they were exposed to great danger in the channel of the Ba-<lb break="no"/>hamas from a hurricane which lasted seven days.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After a passage of thirty-two days they arrived at Phila-<lb break="no"/>delphia; remained in that city and in Washington two<lb break="yes"/>months; and returned to Europe in August 1804 by the<lb break="yes"/>way of Bourdeaux with a great number of drawings, thirty-<lb break="maybe"/>five boxes of collections, and 6000 species of plants.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 