<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023299100">
                        <surname>Clark</surname>
                        <forename>Rex</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="stoeckli_mt">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stöckli</surname>
                        <forename>Matthias Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="schnidrig_bf">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schnidrig</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara Franziska</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.5.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.4.0" when="2018-09-28" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Personenmarkierung abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.3.0" when="2018-09-27" who="stoeckli_mt">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Personen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2018-09-27" who="schnidrig_bf">Markup: added placeName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Orte.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="2" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#c">
                    <hi rendition="#i">From the New-York Daily Advertiser</hi>
                </hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>BARON HUMBOLDT.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following abstract of the American Travels of<lb break="yes"/>the celebrated Baron <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> and his companion<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName>, has been drawn up from notes which the<lb break="yes"/>former has kindly furnished, and will supercede the<lb break="yes"/>many very incorrect accounts hitherto published rela-<lb break="no"/>tive to this interesting object.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Baron <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>, having travelled from the year<lb break="yes"/>1790, as a naturalist, through Germany, Poland,<lb break="yes"/>France, Switzerland, and through parts of England,<lb break="yes"/>Italy, Hungary, and Spain, came to Paris in 1798,<lb break="yes"/>when he received an invitation, from the directors of<lb break="yes"/>the national museum to accompany captain <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin</persName> in<lb break="yes"/>his voyage round the world. Citizen <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Alexander Aime<lb break="yes" />Gourjon Bonpland</persName>, a native of Rochelle, and brought<lb break="yes"/>up in the Paris museum, was also to have accompanied<lb break="yes"/>them; when on the point of departing, the whole<lb break="yes" />plan was suspended until a more favourable opportuni-<lb break="no"/>ty, owing to the re-commencement of the war with<lb break="yes"/>Austria, and the consequent want of funds.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>, who, from 1792, had conceived<lb break="yes"/>the plan of travelling through India at his own ex-<lb break="no"/>pense, with a view of adding to the knowledge of the<lb break="yes"/>sciences connected with natural history, then resolved<lb break="yes"/>to follow the learned men, who had gone on the expe-<lb break="no"/>dition to <placeName key="aegypten">Egypt</placeName>. His plan was to go to <placeName key="algier">Algiers</placeName> in<lb break="yes"/>the Swedish frigate which carried the consul <persName key="skjoldebrand_ma" >Skolde-<lb break="no"/>brandt</persName>, to follow the caravan which goes from Al-<lb break="no"/>giers to Mecca, going through <placeName key="aegypten">Egypt</placeName> to <placeName key="arabien" >Arabia</placeName>, and<lb break="yes"/>thence by the Persian golph to the English East-India<lb break="yes"/>establishments. The war which unexpectedly broke<lb break="yes"/>out in October, 1798, between France and the Bar-<lb break="no"/>bary powers, and the troubles in the East, prevented<lb break="yes"/>Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> from embarking at Marseilles, where<lb break="yes"/>he had been fruitlessly two months waiting to proceed.<lb break="yes"/>Impatient at this delay, and continuing firm in his<lb break="yes"/>determination to go to <placeName key="aegypten">Egypt</placeName>, he went to Spain,<lb break="yes"/>hoping to pass more readily under the Spanish flag<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="3" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>from Carthagena to <placeName key="algier">Algiers</placeName> and Tunis. He took with<lb break="yes"/>him the large Collection of philosophical, chymical,<lb break="yes"/>and astronomical instruments, which he had purchased<lb break="yes"/>in England and France.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From a happy concurrence of circumstances, he<lb break="yes"/>obtained, in
                    February, 1789, from the court of Ma-<lb break="no"/>drid, a permission to visit
                    the <placeName key="spanischeskolonialreich">Spanish colonies of the<lb
                            break="yes"/>two Americas</placeName>, a permission which was granted
                        with<lb break="yes"/>a liberality and frankness, which was honourable to<lb
                        break="yes"/>the government and to a philosophick age. After a<lb
                        break="yes"/>residence of some months at the Spanish court, during<lb
                        break="yes"/>which time the king showed a strong personal interest<lb
                        break="yes"/>in the plan, Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av"
                        >Humboldt</persName>, in June, 1799, left Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope,
                    accompanied by Mr. <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName>, who, to a
                        pro-<lb break="no"/>found knowledge in botany and zoology, added an in-<lb
                        break="no"/>defatigable zeal. It is with this friend that Mr. Hum-<lb
                        break="no"/>boldt has accomplished, at his own expense, his travels<lb
                        break="yes"/>in the two hemispheres, by land and sea, <choice>
                        <sic>brobably</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">probably</corr>
                    </choice> the<lb break="yes"/>most extensive which any individual has ever
                        under-<lb break="no"/>taken.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These two travellers left <placeName key="acoruna">Corunna</placeName> in the Spanish<lb break="yes"/>ship <persName key="pizzaro_f">Pizarro</persName>, for the Canary Islands, where they ascen-<lb break="yes"/>ded to the crater of the Peak of Teyde, and made ex-<lb break="no"/>periments on the analysis of the air. In July they<lb break="yes"/>arrived at the port of <choice>
                        <sic>Omana</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Cumana</corr>
                    </choice>, in <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>. In<lb break="yes"/>1799, 1800, they visited the coast of Paria, the mis-<lb break="no"/>sions of the Chaymas Indians, the province of New<lb break="yes" />Andalusia (a country which had been rent by the most<lb break="yes"/>dreadful earthquakes, the hottest, and yet the most<lb break="yes"/>healthy, in the world) of <placeName key="barcelona">New Barcelona</placeName>, of Venezue-<lb break="no"/>la, and Spanish Guayana. In January, 1800, they<lb break="yes" />left Caraccas to visit the beautiful vallies of <choice>
                        <sic>Aagca</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">
                            <placeName key="aragua">Aragua</placeName>
                        </corr>
                    </choice>,<lb break="yes"/>where the great lake of Valencia recals to mind the<lb break="yes"/>views of the lake of Geneva, embellished by the ma-<lb break="no"/>jesty of the vegetation of the tropics. From Porto<lb break="yes"/>Cabello they crossed to the south, the immense plains<lb break="yes"/>of Caloboza, of <placeName key="apure">Apure</placeName>, and of the Oronoco, also los<lb break="yes"/>Llanos, a desert similar to those of <placeName key="afrika">Africa</placeName>, where in<lb break="yes"/>the shade (by the reverberation of heat) the thermo-<lb break="yes"/>meter of <persName key="reaumur_rafd">Reaumur</persName> rose to 35 and 37 (111 to 115 F.)<lb break="yes"/>degrees. The level of the country for 2000 square<lb break="yes"/>leagues does not differ 5 inches. The sand every where<lb break="yes"/>represents the horizon of the sea, without vegetation;<lb break="yes"/>and its dry bosom hides the crocodiles, and the torpid<lb break="yes"/>boas (a species of serpent.) The travelling here, as in<lb break="yes"/>all <placeName key="spanischeskolonialreich">Spanish America</placeName>, except Mexico, is performed on<lb break="yes" />horseback. They passed whole days without seeing a<lb break="yes"/>palm tree or the vestige of a human dwelling. At<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="sanfernandodeapure">St. Fernando de Apure</placeName>, in the provinces of <placeName key="varinas">Varinas</placeName>,<lb break="yes" />Messrs. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> and <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName> began that fatiguing<lb break="yes" />navigation of nearly 1000 marine leagues, executed in<lb break="yes"/>canoes, making a chart of the country by the assist-<lb break="yes"/>ance of chronometers, the satellites of Jupiter, and<lb break="yes"/>the lunar distances. They descended the <placeName key="apure">river Apure</placeName>,<lb break="yes"/>which empties itself into the Oronoco, in 7 degrees<lb break="yes"/>of latitude.&#x2014;They ascend the last river (passing the<lb break="yes"/>celebrated cataracts of Mapure and <placeName key="atures" >Atures</placeName>) to the<lb break="yes"/>mouth of the Guaviare. From thence they ascended<lb break="yes"/>the small rivers of <placeName key="atabapo">Tabapa</placeName>, Juamini, and Tenie.<lb break="yes"/>From the mission of Sarita they crossed by land to<lb break="yes"/>the sources of the famous Rio Negro, which Conda-<lb break="no"/>mine saw, where it joins the <placeName key="amazonas">Amazon</placeName>, and which he<lb break="yes" />calls a sea of fresh water. About 30 Indians carried<lb break="yes"/>the canoes through woods of Mami Lecythis and Lau-<lb break="no"/>rus Cinamomoides to the cano (or creek) of Pemichin.<lb break="yes"/>It was by this small stream that the travellers enter-<lb break="yes"/>ed the Rio Negro, or Black River which they des-<lb break="no"/>cended to St. Carlos, which has been erroneously sup-<lb break="no"/>posed to be placed under the <placeName key="aequator" >equator</placeName>, or just at the<lb break="yes"/>frontiers of Great Para, in the government of Brasil.<lb break="yes"/>A canal from Tenie to Pemichin, which from the level<lb break="yes"/>nature of the ground is very practicable, would pre-<lb break="no"/>sent a fine internal communication between the Para<lb break="yes"/>and the province of Carracas, a communication infi-<lb break="yes"/>nitely shorter than that of Cassiquiare. From the for-<lb break="no"/>tress of St. Carlos on the Rio Negro, Mr. H. went<lb break="yes"/>north up that river and the Cassiquiare to the Oronoco,<lb break="yes"/>and on this river to the volcano Daida or the mission<lb break="yes"/>of the Esmeralda, near the sources of the Oronoco;<lb break="yes"/>the Indians, Guaicas (or race of men almost pigmies,<lb break="yes"/>very white and very warlike) render fruitless any at-<lb break="no"/>tempts to reach the sources themselves.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After remaining some months at <placeName key="barcelona">New Barcelona</placeName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and Cumana, the travellers arrived at the Havanna,<lb break="yes"/>after a tedious and dangerous navigation, the vessel<lb break="yes"/>being in the night on the point of striking upon the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="baxodelavibora">Vibora rocks</placeName>. Mr. H. remained three months in the<lb break="yes"/>island of Cuba, where he occupied himself in ascer-<lb break="no"/>taining the longitude of the Havanna, and in con-<lb break="no"/>structing stoves on the sugar plantations, which have<lb break="yes"/>since been pretty generally adopted. They were on<lb break="yes"/>the point <choice>
                        <sic>off</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">of</corr>
                    </choice> setting off for Vera Cruz, meaning, by<lb break="yes"/>the way of Mexico and <placeName key="acapulco">Acapulco</placeName>, to go to the Philip-<lb break="no"/>pine Islands, and from thence, if it was possible, by<lb break="yes"/>Bombay and <placeName key="aleppo">Aleppo</placeName>, to Constantinople, when some<lb break="yes"/>false reports relative to <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin&#x2019;s</persName> voyage alarmed them,<lb break="yes"/>and made them change their plan. The gazettes held<lb break="yes"/>out the idea that this navigator would proceed from<lb break="yes"/>France to Buenos Ayres and from thence, by Cape<lb break="yes" />Horn, for Chili and the coast of Peru. Mr. Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt had promised to Mr. <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin</persName> and to the Museum<lb break="yes"/>of Paris, that wherever he might be, he would endea-<lb break="no"/>vour to join the expedition, as soon as he should know<lb break="yes"/>of its having been commenced. He flattered himself<lb break="yes"/>that his researches, and those of his friend <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>might be more useful to science, if united to the la-<lb break="no"/>bours of the learned men who would accompany cap-<lb break="yes"/>tain <persName key="baudin_tn" >Baudin</persName>.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These considerations induced Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> to<lb break="yes"/>send his manuscripts, for 1799 and 1800, direct to<lb break="yes"/>Europe, and to freight a small schooner at Bantabano,<lb break="yes"/>intending to go to Carthagena, and from thence, as<lb break="yes"/>quickly as possible, by the Isthmus of Panama, to the<lb break="yes"/>South Sea. He hoped to find captain <persName key="baudin_tn" >Baudin</persName> at<lb break="yes"/>Guayaquil, or at Lima, and with him to visit New-<lb break="maybe"/>Holland, and the Islands of the Pacific Ocean, equally<lb break="yes"/>interesting in a moral point of view, as by the luxuri-<lb break="no"/>ance of their vegetation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From the Esmeralda Messrs. H. and B. went down<lb break="yes"/>the Oronoco, when the water rose, towards its mouth<lb break="yes"/>at St. Thomas de la Guayana, or the <placeName key="angostura">Angostura</placeName>. It<lb break="yes"/>was during this long navigation that they were in a<lb break="yes"/>continued state of suffering, from want of nourishment<lb break="yes"/>and shelter from the night rains, from living in the<lb break="yes"/>woods, from the mosquettoes, and an infinite variety<lb break="yes"/>of stinging insects, and the impossibility of bathing,<lb break="yes"/>owing to the fierceness of the crocodile and the little<lb break="yes"/>carib fish, finally the miasmata of a burning climate.<lb break="yes"/>They returned to Cumana by the plains of Cari and<lb break="yes"/>the mission of the Carib Indians, a race of men very<lb break="yes"/>different from any other, and probably, after the Pata-<lb break="no"/>gonians, the tallest and most robust in the world.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It appeared imprudent to expose the manuscripts<lb break="yes"/>and collections already made to the risks of this pro-<lb break="no"/>posed navigation. These manuscripts, of the fate of<lb break="yes"/>which Mr. H. remained ignorant during three years,<lb break="yes"/>and until his arrival in Philadelphia, arrived safe, but<lb break="yes"/>one third part of the collection was lost by shipwreck.<lb break="yes"/>Fortunately, except the insects of the Oronoco and<lb break="yes"/>Rio Negro they were only duplicates; but unhappily,<lb break="yes"/>friar <persName key="gonzalez_j">John Gonzales</persName>, monk of the order of St. <persName key="franzvonassisi">Francis</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>the friend to whom they were entrusted, perished with<lb break="yes"/>them. He was a young man full of ardour, who had<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>penetrated into this unknown world of Spanish Guay-<lb break="no"/>ana further than any other European.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> left <placeName key="batabano">Batabano</placeName> in March 1801, and<lb break="yes" />passed to the south of the Island of Cuba, on which<lb break="yes"/>he determined many geographical positions. The pas-<lb break="no"/>sage was rendered very long by calms, and the cur-<lb break="no"/>rents carried the little schooner too much to the west,<lb break="yes"/>to the mouths of the <placeName key="atrato">Attracto</placeName>. The vessel put into<lb break="yes"/>the river Sinu, where no botanist had ever before visit-<lb break="no"/>ed, and they had a very difficult passage up to Car-<lb break="no"/>thagena. The season being too far advanced for the<lb break="yes"/>South Sea navigation, the project of crossing the isth-<lb break="no"/>mus was abandoned; and animated by the desire of<lb break="yes" />being acquainted with the celebrated <persName key="mutis_jc" >Mutis</persName>, and ad-<lb break="no"/>miring his immensely rich collections of objects of na-<lb break="no"/>tural history, Mr. H. determined to pass some weeks<lb break="yes"/>in the woods of Tobaco, and to ascend (which took<lb break="yes"/>forty days) the beautiful river Madalaine of the<lb break="yes" />source of which he has sketched a chart.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From Honda, our travellers proceed through forests<lb break="yes"/>of oaks, of <hi rendition="#i">melaslomo</hi>, and of <hi rendition="#i">cinchona</hi>, (the tree<lb break="yes"/>which affords the Peruvian bark,) to St. Fe de Bogo-<lb break="no"/>ta, capital of the kingdom of New Grenada, situated<lb break="yes"/>in a fine plain, elevated 1360 toises (of six French<lb break="yes"/>feet) about the level of the sea. The superb collec-<lb break="no"/>tions of <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, the majestic cataract of the Tequen-<lb break="no"/>dama (falls of 98 toises height) the mines of Mari-<lb break="no"/>quita, St. Ana, and of Tipaquira, the natural bridge<lb break="yes"/>of Scononza, (three stones thrown together in the<lb break="yes"/>manner of an arch, by an earthquake,) these curious<lb break="yes"/>objects stopped the progress of Messrs. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName> until the month of September 1801.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At this time, notwithstanding the rainy season had<lb break="yes"/>commenced, they undertook the journey to Quito,<lb break="yes"/>and passed the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> of Quindin, which are snowy<lb break="yes" />mountains covered with wax palm-trees, (palmers a<lb break="yes"/>cire,) with passe flores, (passion flower) of the growth<lb break="yes"/>of trees, storax, and bambusa (bamboo.) They were,<lb break="yes"/>during 13 days, obliged to pass on foot through<lb break="yes"/>places dreadfully swampy, and without any traces of<lb break="yes"/>population.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#i">(To be continued.)</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <pb n="2" facs="#f0003"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>BARON HUMBOLDT.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#i">(Concluded)</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From the village of Carthago, in the valley of<lb break="yes"/>Cauca, they followed the course of the choco, the<lb break="yes"/>country of Palatina, which was there found in round<lb break="yes"/>pieces of basalte and green rock (grein stein of <persName key="werner_ag">Wer-<lb break="no"/>ner</persName>), and fossil wood. They pass by Buga to Pop-<lb break="no"/>ayan, a bishop&#x2019;s see, and situated near the volcanoes<lb break="yes"/>of <hi rendition="#i" >Sotara and Purace,</hi> a most picturesque situation,<lb break="yes"/>and enjoying the most delicious climate in the world,<lb break="yes"/>the thermometer of Reamur keeping constantly at 16<lb break="yes"/>to 18 (68 to 72 Fahr.) They ascended to the crater<lb break="yes"/>of the volcano of purace, whose mouth, in the middle<lb break="yes"/>of snow, throws out vapours of sulphureous hydrogene,<lb break="yes"/>with continued and frightful rumbling.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From <choice>
                        <sic>Papayan</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial"> Popayan</corr>
                    </choice> they passed by the dangerous defiles<lb break="yes"/>of <placeName key="almager">Almager</placeName>, avoiding the infected and contagious<lb break="yes"/>valley of Patia, to Posto, and from this town, even<lb break="yes"/>now situated at the foot of a burning volcano, by<lb break="yes"/>Tuqueras and the province of Pastos, a flat portion of<lb break="yes"/>country, fertile in European grain, but elevated more<lb break="yes"/>than 1500 to 1600 toises above the towns of Ibarra and Quito.</p>
                <p>They arrived, in January, 1802, at this beautiful<lb break="yes"/>capital, celebrated by the labours of the illustrious<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condamine</persName>, of <persName key="bouguer_p">Bouger</persName>, <persName key="godin_l">Godin</persName>, Dr. <persName key="juanysantacilia_j">George Juan</persName>,<lb break="yes" />and <persName key="ulloa_ad">Ulloa</persName>, and still more celebrated by the great<lb break="yes"/>amiability of its inhabitants, and their happy turn for<lb break="yes"/>the arts.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>They remained nearly a year in the kingdom of<lb break="yes"/>Quito; the height of its snow-capped mountains, its<lb break="yes"/>terrible earthquakes (that of February 7, 1797, swal-<lb break="no"/>lowed up 42,000 inhabitants, in a few seconds), its fer-<lb break="no"/>tility, and the manners of its inhabitants, combined<lb break="yes"/>to render it the most interesting spot in the universe.<lb break="yes"/>After three vain attempts, they twice succeeded in<lb break="yes"/>ascending to the crater of the volcano of Pichincha,<lb break="yes"/>taking with them electrometers, barometers, and hy-<lb break="no"/>drometers. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condamine</persName> could only stop here a few<lb break="yes"/>minutes, <hi rendition="#i">and that without instruments.</hi> In his time,<lb break="yes"/>this immense crater was cold and filled with snow.<lb break="yes"/>Our travellers found it inflamed; distressing informa-<lb break="no"/>tion for the town of Quito, which is distant from it<lb break="yes"/>only 5000 to 6000 toises.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>They made separate visits to the snowy and por-<lb break="no"/>phyritic mountains of <placeName key="antisana">Antisana</placeName>, Cotopaxi, Tunga-<lb break="no"/>raque, and Chimborazo, the last the highest point of<lb break="yes"/>our globe. They studied the geological part of the<lb break="yes"/>Cordillera of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>, on which subject nothing<lb break="yes"/>has been published in Europe, mineralogy (if the ex-<lb break="no"/>pression may be used) having been created, as it<lb break="yes"/>were, since the time of <persName key="lacondamine_cmd" >Condamine</persName>. The geodesical<lb break="yes"/>measurements proved that some mountains, particu-<lb break="no"/>larly the volcano of Tungaraque, has considerably<lb break="yes"/>lowered since 1750, which result agrees with the ob-<lb break="no"/>servations made to them by the inhabitants.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>During the whole of this part of the journey,<lb break="yes"/>they were accompanied by Mr. <persName key="montufarylarrea_c">Charles Montufar</persName>, son of<lb break="yes"/>the <persName key="montufarylarrea_jpd">marquis of Selva-alegree</persName>, of Quito, a person zealous<lb break="yes"/>for the progress of science, and who is, at his own ex-<lb break="no"/>pense, rebuilding the pyramids of Saraqui, the extre-<lb break="no"/>mity of the celebrated bases of the <hi rendition="#i" >triangles</hi> of the<lb break="yes"/>Spanish and French academicians. This interesting<lb break="yes"/>young man having followed Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> in the re-<lb break="no"/>mainder of his journey through Peru and the kingdom<lb break="yes"/>of New Spain, is now on his passage with him to Europe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Circumstances were so favourable to the efforts of<lb break="yes"/>the three travellers, that at <placeName key="antisana">Antisana</placeName> they ascended<lb break="yes"/>2200 French feet, and at Chimborazo, on June 22,<lb break="yes"/>1802, nearly 3200 feet higher than <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condamine</persName> was a-<lb break="no"/>ble to carry his instruments. They ascended to 3036<lb break="yes"/>toises elevation above the level of the sea, the blood<lb break="yes"/>starting from their eyes, lips, and gums. An open-<lb break="no"/>ing, of 80 toises deep, and very wide, prevented them<lb break="yes"/>from reaching the top, from which they were only dis-<lb break="no"/>tant 134 toises.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It was at Quito that Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> received a let-<lb break="no"/>ter from the National Institute of France, informing<lb break="yes"/>him; that captain <persName key="baudin_tn">Baudin</persName> had proceeded by the Cape<lb break="yes"/>of Good Hope, and that there was no longer any hope<lb break="yes"/>of joining him.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After having examined the country overturned by<lb break="yes"/>the earthquake of Riobamba, in 1797, they passed<lb break="yes"/>by the <placeName key="anden" >Andes</placeName> of <placeName key="assuay">Assuay</placeName> to Cuenza. The desire of<lb break="yes"/>comparing the barks (cinchona) discovered by Mr.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, at Santa Fe de Bogota, and with those of Po-<lb break="no"/>payan, and the cuspa and cuspare of New Andalusia,<lb break="yes"/>and of the river Caroni (named falsely Cortex Angus-<lb break="no"/>tura) with the cinchona, (barks) of Loxa and Peru;<lb break="yes"/>they preferred deviating from the beaten track from<lb break="yes"/>Cuenza to Lima; but they passed with immense diffi-<lb break="no"/>culties in the carriage of their instruments and collec-<lb break="no"/>tions, by the forest (Paramo) of Saragura to Loxa,<lb break="yes"/>and from thence to the province of Saen de Bracamo-<lb break="no"/>ros. They had to cross thirty-five times, in two days,<lb break="yes"/>the river Guancabamba, so dangerous for its sudden<lb break="yes"/>freshes. They saw the ruins of the superb Ynga<lb break="yes" />road comparable to the finest roads in France, and<lb break="yes"/>which went upon the ridge of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> from Cusco<lb break="yes"/>to the <placeName key="assuay">Assuay</placeName>, accommodated with fountains and ta-<lb break="no"/>verns.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>They descended the river Chamaya, which led them<lb break="yes"/>into that of <placeName key="amazonas">the Amazones</placeName>, and they navigated this<lb break="yes"/>last river down to the cataracts of Tomeperda, one<lb break="yes"/>of the most fertile, but one of the hottest, climates of<lb break="yes"/>the habitable globe. From <placeName key="amazonas">the Amazone river</placeName> they<lb break="yes"/>returned to the south-east by the Cordillera of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> to Montar, where they found they had passed<lb break="yes"/>the <placeName key="magnetaequator">magnetic equator</placeName>, the inclination being 0, although<lb break="yes"/>at seven degrees of south latitude. They visited the<lb break="yes"/>mines of Hualguayoc, where native silver is found at<lb break="yes"/>the height of 2000 toises. Some of the veins of these<lb break="yes"/>mines contain petrified shells, and which, with those<lb break="yes"/>of Pasco and Huantajayo, are actually the richest of<lb break="yes"/>Peru. From Caxamarca they descended to Truxillo,<lb break="yes"/>in the neighbourhood of which are found the ruins of<lb break="yes"/>the immense Peruvian city, Mansiche.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It was on this western descent of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> that<lb break="yes"/>the three voyagers, for the first time, had the pleasure<lb break="yes"/>of seeing the Pacifick Ocean. They followed its<lb break="yes"/>barren sides, formerly watered by the canals Yngas<lb break="yes"/>at Santa Guerma, and Lima. They remained some<lb break="yes" />months in this interesting capital of Peru, of which<lb break="yes"/>the inhabitants are distinguished by the vivacity of<lb break="yes"/>their genius, and the liberality of their ideas.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> had the good fortune to observe the<lb break="yes"/>end of the passage of Mercury over the sun&#x2019;s disk,<lb break="yes"/>in the port of Callao. He was astonished to find, at<lb break="yes"/>such a distance from Europe, the most recent produc-<lb break="no"/>tions in chemistry, mathematicks, and medicine; and<lb break="yes"/>he found great activity of mind in the inhabitants,<lb break="yes"/>who in a climate where it never either rains or thun-<lb break="no"/>ders, have been falsely accused of indolence.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From Lima our travellers passed by sea to Guaya-<lb break="no"/>quil, situated on the brink of a river, where the<lb break="yes"/>growth of the palm tree is beautiful beyond descrip-<lb break="no"/>tion. They every moment heard the rumbling of the<lb break="yes"/>volcano of Cotopaxi, which made an alarming explo-<lb break="no"/>sion on the 6th January, 1803. They immediately<lb break="yes"/>set off to visit it a second time, when the unexpected<lb break="yes"/>intelligence of the speedy departure of the frigate<lb break="yes"/>Atalanta determined them to return, after being seven<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>days exposed to the dreadful attacks of the musquetoes<lb break="yes"/>of <placeName key="babaoyo">Babaoya</placeName> and Ujibar.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>They had a fortunate passage, by the Pacific O-<lb break="no"/>cean, to <placeName key="acapulco">Acapulco</placeName>, the western port of the Kingdom<lb break="yes"/>of New Spain, famous for the beauty of its harbour,<lb break="yes"/>which appears to have been formed by earthquakes, for<lb break="yes"/>the misery of its inhabitants, and for its climate,<lb break="yes"/>which is equally hot and unhealthy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> had originally the intention to re-<lb break="no"/>main only a few months in Mexico, and to hasten<lb break="yes"/>his return to Europe; his voyage had already been too<lb break="yes"/>much protracted, his intruments, particularly the<lb break="yes"/>chronometers, began to be out of order, and every<lb break="yes"/>effort that he made to have new ones sent to him<lb break="yes" />proved of no avail; add to this consideration, that<lb break="yes"/>the progress of science is so rapid in Europe, that,<lb break="yes"/>in a journey that lasts four or five years, great risk is<lb break="yes"/>run of contemplating the different phenomena under<lb break="yes"/>aspects, which are no longer interesting at the mo-<lb break="no"/>ment of publishing the result of your labours. Mr.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> hoped to be in France in August or Sep-<lb break="no"/>tember, 1803, but the attractions of a country, so<lb break="yes"/>beautiful and so varied, as is that of the kingdom of<lb break="yes"/>New Spain, the great hospitality of its inhabitants,<lb break="yes"/>and the fear of the yellow fever, fatal, from June to<lb break="yes"/>November, for those who come from the mountainous<lb break="yes"/>parts of the country, led him to stay a year in this<lb break="yes"/>kingdom.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Our travellers ascended from <placeName key="acapulco">Acapulco</placeName> to Tasco,<lb break="yes"/>celebrated for its mines, as interesting as they are an-<lb break="no"/>cient. They rise, by small degrees, from the ardent<lb break="yes"/>valley of Mescala and Papagayo, where the thermo-<lb break="no" />meter of <persName key="reaumur_rafd">Reaumur</persName> stands, in the shade, constantly<lb break="yes"/>from 28 to 31 (95 to 101 Fah.), in a region 6 or 700<lb break="yes"/>toises above the level of the sea, where you find the<lb break="yes"/>oaks, the pines, and the fougere (fern) as large as<lb break="yes"/>trees, and where the European grains are cultivated.<lb break="yes"/>They passed by Tasco, by Cuerna Vacca, to the capi-<lb break="no"/>tal of Mexico. This city of 150,000 inhabitants, is<lb break="yes"/>placed upon the ancient site of Texochtitlan, between<lb break="yes"/>the lakes of Tezcuco and Xochimilco, lakes which<lb break="yes" />have lessened somewhat since the Spaniards have open-<lb break="no"/>ed the canal of Hucheutoca, in sight of two snow-<lb break="no"/>topped mountains, of which one, Hopocatepec, is even<lb break="yes"/>now an active volcano, surrounded by a great number<lb break="yes"/>of walks, shaded with trees, and by Indian villages.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This capital of Mexico, situated 1160 toises <hi rendition="#i">above<lb break="yes"/>the sea,</hi> in a mild and temperate climate, may doubt-<lb break="no"/>less be compared to some of the finest towns in Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope. Great scientific establishments, such as the a-<lb break="no"/>cademy of painting, sculpture, and engraving, the col-<lb break="no"/>lege of mines, [owning to the liberality of the company<lb break="yes"/>of miners of Mexico] and the botanick garden, are in-<lb break="no"/>stitutions which do honour to the government which<lb break="yes"/>has created them.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After remaining some months in the valley of Mex-<lb break="no"/>ico, and after fixing the longitude of the capital,<lb break="yes"/>which had been laid down with an error of nearly two<lb break="yes"/>degrees, our travellers visited the mines of Moran and<lb break="yes"/>Real del Monte, and the Cerro of Oyamel, where the<lb break="yes"/>ancient Mexicans had the manufactory of knives<lb break="yes"/>made of the obsidian stone. They soon after passed<lb break="yes"/>by Queretaro and Salamanca to Guanaxoato, a town<lb break="yes" />of fifty thousand inhabitants, and celebrated for its<lb break="yes"/>mines, more rich than those of Potosi have ever been.<lb break="yes"/>The mine of the count of Valenciana, which is 1840<lb break="yes"/>French feet perpendicular depth, is the deepest and<lb break="yes"/>richest mine of the universe. This mine alone gives<lb break="yes"/>to its proprietor nearly six hundred thousand dollars<lb break="yes"/>annual and constant profit.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From Guanaxoato they returned by the valley of<lb break="yes"/>St. Jago to Valladolid, in the ancient kingdom of Mi-<lb break="no"/>choacan, one of the most fertile and charming pro-<lb break="no"/>vinces of the kingdom. They descended from Pascu-<lb break="no"/>ara towards the coast of the Pacifick Ocean to the<lb break="yes"/>plains of Serullo, where, in 1759, in one night, a vol-<lb break="no"/>cano arose from the level, surrounded by two thousand<lb break="yes"/>small mouths, from whence smoke still continues to is-<lb break="no"/>sue. They arrived almost to the bottom of the crater<lb break="yes"/>of the great volcano of Serullo, of which they ana-<lb break="no"/>lysed the air, and found it strongly impregnated with<lb break="yes"/>carbonick acid. They returned to Mexico by the val-<lb break="no"/>ley of Teluca, and visited the volcano, to the highest<lb break="yes"/>point of which they ascended, 14,400 French feet a-<lb break="no"/>bove the level of the sea.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the months of January and February, <choice>
                        <sic>1801</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">1804</corr>
                    </choice>,<lb break="yes"/>they pursued their researches on the eastern descent of<lb break="yes"/>the Cordilleras, they measured the mountains Mora-<lb break="no"/>dos de la Puebla, Popocatyce, Izazihuatli, the great<lb break="yes"/>peak of Orizaba, and the Cofre de Perote; upon the<lb break="yes"/>top of this last Mr. <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName> observed the meredian<lb break="yes"/>height of the sun. In fine, after some residence at<lb break="yes"/>Xalappa, they embarked at Vera Cruz, for the Havan-<lb break="no"/>ah. They resumed the collections they had left there<lb break="yes"/>in 1801, and by the way of Philadelphia, embarked for<lb break="yes"/>France, in July, <choice>
                        <sic>1801</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">1804</corr>
                    </choice>, after six years of absence and<lb break="yes"/>labours. A collection of 6000 different species of plants<lb break="yes"/>(of which a great part are new) and numerous mine-<lb break="no"/>ralogical, astronomical, chemical, and moral observa-<lb break="no"/>tions, have been the result of this expedition. Mr.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> gives the highest praises to the liberal pro-<lb break="no"/>tection granted to his researches by the Spanish government.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Baron <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> was born in Prussia, on the 14th<lb break="yes"/>of September, 1769.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 