<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023299100">
                        <surname>Clark</surname>
                        <forename>Rex</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="stoeckli_mt">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stöckli</surname>
                        <forename>Matthias Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="schnidrig_bf">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schnidrig</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara Franziska</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.5.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.4.0" when="2018-09-28" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Personenmarkierung abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.3.0" when="2018-09-27" who="stoeckli_mt">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Personen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2018-09-27" who="schnidrig_bf">Markup: added placeName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Orte.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="356" facs="#f0001"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Experiments on the Torpedo, by Messrs.</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">and</hi>
                    <persName key="gaylussac_jl">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Gay-Lussac.</hi>
                    </persName>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Extracted from a Letter<lb break="yes"/>from M.</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">to M.</hi>
                    <persName key="berthollet_cl">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Berthollet,</hi>
                    </persName>
                    <hi rendition="#i">dated Rome,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <date>15 <hi rendition="#i">Fructid. Year</hi> 13</date>
                    <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">From <hi rendition="#i">Annales de Chimie,</hi> no. 166.</note>.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>he</hi> ph&#x00E6;nomena of electric fish ought to be the subject of<lb break="yes"/>our renewed researches, with a view to the opinion of many<lb break="yes"/>philosophers, who conceive that they are capable of being<lb break="yes"/>explained upon the principles of that beautiful theory with<lb break="yes"/>which <persName key="volta_agv">Volta</persName> has enriched science. You well know, my<lb break="yes"/>respected friend, what must have been our anxiety to pro-<lb break="no"/>cure the torpedo; and you will perhaps be astonished that<lb break="yes"/>I should be so long in writing to you respecting it. At<lb break="yes"/>Genoa we found some of them, but we were then without<lb break="yes"/>instruments. At Civita Vecchia we searched for them in<lb break="yes"/>vain. At last, during our stay at Naples, we procured<lb break="yes"/>them very frequently, of great size, and very vigorous. I<lb break="yes"/>shall relate to you, in this letter, the series of experiments<lb break="yes"/>which M. <persName key="gaylussac_jl" >Gay-Lussac</persName> and I have instituted upon the action<lb break="yes" />of the torpedo (Raja Torpedo of <persName key="linne_cv" >Linn&#x00E6;us</persName>). M. de Buch,<lb break="yes"/>a German mineralogist, was present at our experiments. I<lb break="yes"/>present to you the results which they afforded, and relate<lb break="yes"/>the facts without introducing any theoretical notions.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Our experiments were principally intended to discover<lb break="yes"/>those conditions in which the torpedo is unable to commu-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">nicate</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="357" facs="#f0002"/> nicate those shocks termed electric, although the feeling is<lb break="yes"/>very different from that which is occasioned by the dis-<lb break="no"/>charge of a Leyden phial. Having at hand no other work<lb break="yes"/>besides that of <persName key="aldini_g" >Aldini</persName>, in which he has combined into one<lb break="yes"/>view the beautiful researches of <persName key="geoffroyshilaire_e" >Geoffroy</persName> with those of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="spallanzani_l">Spallanzani</persName> and <persName key="galvani_la">Galvani</persName>, we shall not have it in our power<lb break="yes"/>to compare our own labours with those of preceding phi-<lb break="no"/>losophers.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>1. Although the power of the torpedo cannot be com-<lb break="no"/>pared to that of the gymnotus, it is not less capable of oc-<lb break="no"/>casioning disagreeable sensations. A person much in the<lb break="yes"/>custom of receiving electric shocks, supports with some<lb break="yes"/>difficulty the shock of a torpedo 14 inches long, and in a<lb break="yes"/>state of perfect vigour. The gymnotus communicates its<lb break="yes"/>influence under water, unless when much weakened.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. <persName key="gaylussac_jl">Gay-Lussac</persName> has observed, that the action of the tor-<lb break="no"/>pedo in this condition is not perceptible until it is raised<lb break="yes"/>above the surface of the water. It is with this fish, as with<lb break="yes"/>frogs on which <persName key="galvani_la" >Galvanic</persName> experiments are made: the cir-<lb break="no" />cumstances under which the contraction takes place, vary<lb break="yes" />according to the degree of excitability in the organs.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>2. I have remarked, while in <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>, that the<lb break="yes"/>gymnotus gives the most frightful shocks without making<lb break="yes"/>any external motion of the eyes, head, or fins: it moves no<lb break="yes"/>more than one person communicating an idea or sensation<lb break="yes"/>to another. But the torpedo, on the contrary, moves its<lb break="yes"/>pectoral fins in a convulsive manner before each shock;<lb break="yes"/>and the violence of the stroke is always proportioned to the<lb break="yes"/>extent of the surface of contact.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>3. The organs of the torpedo, or gymnotus, cannot be<lb break="yes"/>discharged by us at will, like a Leyden phial or a <persName key="galvani_la" >Galvanic</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>pile; nor does the electric fish uniformly communicate a<lb break="yes"/>shock when touched. It must be irritated that it may give<lb break="yes"/>its stroke; for this action depends upon the will of the<lb break="yes"/>animal, which in all probability does not always keep its<lb break="yes"/>electric organs charged: it charges them, however, with<lb break="yes"/>astonishing celerity, and is thus able to give a long series<lb break="yes"/>of shocks.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>4. The shock is felt, provided the animal is disposed to<lb break="yes"/>give it, when a single finger is applied to a single surface of<lb break="yes"/>the electric organs; or when the two hands are placed one<lb break="yes"/>on the upper and the other on its under surface at the same<lb break="yes"/>time. And in either of these cases the shock is equally<lb break="yes"/>communicated, whether the person be insulated or not.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>5. If a person while insulated touches the torpedo with<lb break="yes"/>his finger, it is indispensably necessary that the finger be in<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">immediate</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="358" facs="#f0003"/> immediate contact; for no shock is communicated when a<lb break="yes"/>conducting body, such as a piece of metal, is interposed<lb break="yes"/>between the finger and the organs of the fish. Thus we<lb break="yes"/>may touch the animal with a key, or other metallic instru-<lb break="no"/>ment, and experience no shock in consequence.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>6. M. <persName key="gaylussac_jl">Gay-Lussac</persName> having observed this important fact,<lb break="yes"/>we placed the torpedo on a plate of metal, so that the in-<lb break="no"/>ferior surface of its electric organs was in contact with the<lb break="yes"/>metal. The hand which supported the plate felt no shock,<lb break="yes"/>although another person in a state of insulation irritated the<lb break="yes"/>animal, and when the convulsive motions of its pectoral<lb break="yes"/>fins plainly indicated very powerful discharges of its elec-<lb break="no"/>tric fluid.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>7. If on the contrary a person support the torpedo placed<lb break="yes"/>on a metallic plate, with his left hand as in the preceding<lb break="yes" />experiment, and with his right touches the upper surface of<lb break="yes" />the electric organ, then a violent shock is felt in both arms<lb break="yes" />at the same moment.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>8. The same feeling is experienced when the fish is<lb break="yes"/>placed between two plates of metal, the edges of which do<lb break="yes"/>not touch, and the person applies a hand to each plate at<lb break="yes"/>the same instant.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>9. But if in the preceding experiment there exists an<lb break="yes"/>immediate communication between the edges of the two<lb break="yes"/>plates, no shock is felt in the arms; for in this case the<lb break="yes"/>chain of connection between the two surfaces of the organ<lb break="yes"/>is formed by the plates, and the new communication esta-<lb break="no"/>blished by applying the two hands to the plates becomes al-<lb break="no"/>together inefficient.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>10. The most delicate electrometer does not indicate the<lb break="yes"/>state of electricity of the organs of the torpedo: it is no<lb break="yes"/>way affected by any method which we can have recourse to,<lb break="yes"/>either by bringing it near to the organs, or by insulating<lb break="yes"/>the fish, covering it with a plate of metal, and then form-<lb break="no"/>ing a communication by means of a wire between the plate<lb break="yes"/>and the condenser of <persName key="volta_agv">Volta</persName>. Nothing shows here, as in<lb break="yes" />the gymnotus, that the animal can modify the state of<lb break="yes" />electricity of surrounding bodies.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>11. As electric fish act while in a state of health with<lb break="yes"/>the same power under water as in the air, we examined the<lb break="yes"/>conducting properties of this fluid. A number of persons<lb break="yes"/>having formed a circle of connection between the upper and<lb break="yes"/>under surfaces of the organs of the torpedo, no shock was<lb break="yes"/>experienced till they had moistened their hands with water.<lb break="yes"/>The shock is equally felt when two persons who have their<lb break="yes"/>right hands applied to the torpedo, instead of taking hold of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">each</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="359" facs="#f0004"/> each other&#x2019;s left hands, plunge a pointed piece of metal into<lb break="yes"/>a drop of water placed upon an insulating body.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>12. By substituting flame instead of a drop of water, the<lb break="yes" />communication is interrupted, and no sensation is expe-<lb break="no"/>rienced until the two pieces of metal touch each other<lb break="yes"/>within the flame.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>13. We must also observe that no shock will take place<lb break="yes"/>either in air or under water, unless we immediately touch<lb break="yes"/>the body of the electric fish. They are unable to give their<lb break="yes"/>stroke through a layer of water, however thin; a fact<lb break="yes"/>which is the more remarkable, as we know that in <persName key="galvani_la">Galvanic</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>experiments, where the frog is placed under water, it is<lb break="yes"/>sufficient to bring the silver forceps near to the muscles,<lb break="yes"/>and that the contraction takes place when the layer of water<lb break="yes"/>interposed is one or two millimetres in thickness.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Such, my respected friend, are the principal observations<lb break="yes"/>which we have made upon the torpedo. Experiments 4th<lb break="yes"/>and 10th prove that the electric organs of these animals<lb break="yes"/>manifest no tension or excess of charge. We should rather<lb break="yes"/>be inclined to compare their action to a chain of small<lb break="yes"/>Leyden phials than to the pile of <persName key="volta_agv">Volta</persName>. As some commu-<lb break="no" />nication is always necessary for the occurrence of a shock,<lb break="yes" />and having received strokes from the gymnotus through<lb break="yes"/>very dry cords, I conclude that in the case where this<lb break="yes"/>powerful animal appeared to give these violent shocks with-<lb break="no"/>out the existence of any communication, it must have<lb break="yes"/>arisen from my imperfect insulation. If the torpedo acts<lb break="yes"/>by poles, by an electrical equilibrium which tends to re-<lb break="no"/>establish itself, experiments 5th and 6th seem to prove that<lb break="yes"/>these poles exist near one another upon the same surface of<lb break="yes"/>the organ: for we feel the shock by touching a single sur-<lb break="no"/>face with the finger. A plate interposed between the hand<lb break="yes"/>and the organ (6.) re-establishes of itself the equilibrium,<lb break="yes"/>and the hand which supports this plate feels nothing, be-<lb break="no"/>cause it is out of the current of the electric influence. But<lb break="yes"/>if we suppose a number of poles of different descriptions<lb break="yes"/>upon each surface of the organ, why is it that, by cover-<lb break="no"/>ing these with two metallic plates the edges of which do<lb break="yes"/>not touch, and placing the hands upon these plates, the<lb break="yes"/>equilibrium is re-established through the medium of the<lb break="yes"/>arms? Wherefore, it may be asked, does not the positive<lb break="yes"/>electricity of the inferior surface seek, at the moment of<lb break="yes"/>explosion, the negative electricity of the neighbouring pole?<lb break="yes"/>and wherefore does it find it only in the superior surface of<lb break="yes"/>the electric organ? These difficulties are perhaps not in-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">surmountable,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="360" facs="#f0005"/> sumountable, but the theory of these <hi rendition="#i">vital actions</hi> requires<lb break="yes"/>still further research. <persName key="geoffroyshilaire_e">Geoffroy</persName>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">For M. <persName key="geoffroyshilaire_e" >Geoffroy&#x2019;s</persName> paper, see Phil. Mag. vol. xv. p. 126.</note> has proved that rays,<lb break="yes"/>which do not exhibit any marks of electricity, possess or-<lb break="no"/>gans very analogous to those of the torpedo. The least<lb break="yes"/>injury of the brain of this animal prevents its electrical<lb break="yes"/>action. The nerves, therefore, without doubt, act the<lb break="yes"/>chief part in the production of these ph&#x00E6;nomena; and the<lb break="yes"/>physiologist, who takes a general and enlarged view of the<lb break="yes"/>vital actions, would with reason oppose the ideas of the<lb break="yes"/>philosopher, who conceives he can explain the whole by<lb break="yes"/>the contact of the albumino-gelatinous pulp with the ten-<lb break="no"/>dinous septa which nature has combined in the formation<lb break="yes"/>of the organs of the torpedo.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 