<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Particulars respecting the Volcanoes in the Andes, and the Fishes thrown out by them</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:46</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">II.44</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1806-Memoir_on_a_new_species_of_Pimelodus-3-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1806-Memoir_on_a_new_species_of_Pimelodus-1.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1806-Memoir_on_a_new_species_of_Pimelodus-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1806-Memoir_on_a_new_species_of_Pimelodus-3-neu.xml" type="self"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Particulars respecting the Volcanoes in the Andes, and the Fishes thrown out by them</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1806</date>
          <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Scots Magazine, and Edinburgh Literary Miscellany&lt;/i&gt; (Juli 1806), S. 511–513.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Schmuck: Initialen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="511" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Particulars respecting the</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Volcanoes</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">in the</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>,</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">and the Fishes thrown<lb break="yes"/>out by them. By M. Von <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#g">HE</hi> chain of the <placeName key="anden" >Andes</placeName>, extend-<lb break="no"/>ing more than 2000 leagues,<lb break="yes"/>from the Straits of Magellan to the<lb break="yes"/>northern shores which border on<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="asien">Asia</placeName>, contains above fifty volcanoes<lb break="yes"/>still active, of which the phenomena<lb break="yes"/>are as various as their height and lo-<lb break="no"/>cal situation. A small number of<lb break="yes"/>the least elevated of these volcanoes<lb break="yes" />throw out running lava. I have seen,<lb break="yes"/>at the volcano of Zurullo, in Mexico,<lb break="yes"/>a basaltic cone that sprung from the<lb break="yes"/>earth the 15th of September 1759,<lb break="yes"/>and at present rising 1593&#x2154; feet<lb break="yes"/>above the surrounding plain. The<lb break="yes"/>volcanic ridges of Guatimala cast out<lb break="yes"/>a prodigious quantity of muriat of<lb break="yes"/>ammonia. Those of Popayan and the<lb break="yes"/>high plain of Pasto contain either<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">solfatares,</hi> which exhale sulphure-<lb break="no"/>ous acid, or little craters filled<lb break="yes"/>with boiling water, and disengaging<lb break="yes"/>sulphurated hydrogen, which de-<lb break="no" />composes by contact with the oxy-<lb break="no"/>gen of the atmosphere. The volca-<lb break="no"/>noes of the kingdom of Quito throw<lb break="yes"/>out pumice stone, basaltes, and sco-<lb break="no"/>rified porphyries; and vomit enor-<lb break="no"/>mous quantities of water, carburet-<lb break="no"/>ted argil, and muddy matter, which<lb break="yes"/>spreads fertility from eight to ten<lb break="yes"/>leagues around. But since the period<lb break="yes"/>to which the traditions of the na-<lb break="no"/>tives ascend, they have never pro-<lb break="no"/>duced great masses of running melted<lb break="yes" />lava. The height of these colossal<lb break="yes"/>mountains, being five times greater<lb break="yes"/>than that of Vesuvius, and their in-<lb break="no" />land situation are, no doubt, the<lb break="yes"/>principal causes of these anomalies.<lb break="yes"/>The subterranean noise of Cotopaxi<lb break="yes" />during its great explosions, extends<lb break="yes"/>as far as the distance between Vesu-<lb break="no"/>vius and Dijon. But not withstand-<lb break="no" />ing this prodigious force, it is known,<lb break="yes"/>that if the volcanic fire was at a<lb break="yes"/>great depth, the melted lava could<lb break="yes" />neither raise itself to the edge of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">crater,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="512" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/> crater, nor pierce the flank of these<lb break="yes"/>mountains, which, to the height of<lb break="yes"/>8970 feet, are fortified by high sur-<lb break="no"/>rounding plains. It appears, there-<lb break="no"/>fore natural, that volcanoes so ele-<lb break="no"/>vated should discharge from their<lb break="yes"/>mouth only detached stones, volca-<lb break="no"/>nic cinders or ashes, flames, boiling<lb break="yes"/>water, and, above all, this carburet-<lb break="no"/>ted argil impregnated with sulphur,<lb break="yes" />that is called <hi rendition="#i">moga</hi> in the language of<lb break="yes" />the country.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The mountains of the kingdom of<lb break="yes"/>Quito sometimes offer to the natura-<lb break="no"/>list another spectacle less alarming,<lb break="yes" />but not less curious. The great ex-<lb break="no"/>plosions are periodical, and some-<lb break="no"/>what rare. Cotopaxi, Tungurahua,<lb break="yes"/>and Sangay, sometimes do not pre-<lb break="no"/>sent one in twenty or thirty years.<lb break="yes"/>But during such intervals, even these<lb break="yes" />volcanoes will discharge enormous<lb break="yes"/>quantities of argillaceous mud; and,<lb break="yes"/>what is more extraordinary, an innu-<lb break="no" />merable quantity of fish. By acci-<lb break="no"/>dent, none of these volcanic inunda-<lb break="no"/>tions took place the year that I pas-<lb break="no" />sed the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName> of Quito; but the fish<lb break="yes"/>vomited from the volcanoes is a phe-<lb break="no"/>nomenon so common, and so <choice><sic>gene-<lb break="no"/>rality</sic><corr type="editorial">gene-<lb break="no"/>rally</corr></choice> known by all the inhabitants<lb break="yes"/>of that country, that there cannot<lb break="yes"/>remain the least doubt of its authen-<lb break="no"/>ticity. As there are in these regions<lb break="yes"/>several very well informed persons,<lb break="yes" />who have successfully devoted them-<lb break="no"/>selves to the physical sciences, I have<lb break="yes"/>had an opportunity of procuring exact<lb break="yes"/>information respecting these fishes.<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="larreayvillavicencio_j">de Larrae</persName>, at Quito, well versed<lb break="yes"/>in the study of chemistry, who has<lb break="yes" />formed a cabinet of the minerals of his<lb break="yes"/>country, has been particularly use-<lb break="no"/>ful to me in these researches. Exa-<lb break="no"/>mining the archives of several little<lb break="yes"/>towns in the neighbourhood of Co-<lb break="no"/>topaxi, in order to extract the e-<lb break="no"/>pochs of the great earthquakes, that<lb break="yes"/>fortunately have been preserved with<lb break="yes"/>care, I there found some notes on<lb break="yes"/>the fish ejected from the volcanoes.<lb break="yes"/>On the estates of the <persName key="montufarylarrea_jpd">Marquis of<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> Selvalegre</persName> the Cotopaxi had thrown<lb break="yes"/>a quantity so great, that their putre-<lb break="no"/>faction spread a fetid odour around.<lb break="yes"/>In 1691, the almost extinguished vol-<lb break="no" />cano of Imbaburu threw out thou-<lb break="no"/>sands on the fields in the environs of<lb break="yes"/>the city of Ibarra. The putrid fevers<lb break="yes" />which commenced at that period<lb break="yes"/>were attributed to the miasma which<lb break="yes"/>exhaled from these fish, heaped on<lb break="yes"/>the surface of the earth, and exposed<lb break="yes"/>to the rays of the sun. The last<lb break="yes"/>time that Imbaburu ejected fish, was<lb break="yes"/>on the 19th of June 1798, when the<lb break="yes"/>volcano of Corgneirazo sunk, and<lb break="yes"/>thousands of these animals, enveloped<lb break="yes"/>in argillaceous mud, were thrown<lb break="yes"/>over the crumbling borders.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Cotopaxi and Tungurahua<lb break="yes"/>throw out fish, sometimes by the<lb break="yes"/>crater which is at the top of these<lb break="yes"/>mountains, sometimes by lateral vents,<lb break="yes"/>but constantly at 15,000 or 16,000<lb break="yes"/>feet above the level of the sea: the<lb break="yes" />adjacent plains being 9000 feet high,<lb break="yes"/>we may conclude that these animals<lb break="yes"/>issue from a point which is 9000<lb break="yes" />feet higher than the plains on which<lb break="yes"/>they are thrown. Some Indians<lb break="yes"/>have assured me that the fish thrown<lb break="yes" />out by the volcanoes were sometimes<lb break="yes"/>still alive, as they descended along<lb break="yes"/>the flank of the mountain: but this<lb break="yes"/>fact does not appear to me sufficient-<lb break="no"/>ly proved: certain it is that among<lb break="yes"/>the thousands of dead fish that in a<lb break="yes"/>few hours are seen descending from<lb break="yes"/>Cotopaxi with great bodies of cold<lb break="yes"/>fresh water, there are very few that<lb break="yes"/>are so much disfigured that we can<lb break="yes" />believe them to have been exposed to<lb break="yes"/>the action of a strong heat. This<lb break="yes"/>fact becomes still more striking,<lb break="yes" />when we consider the soft flesh of<lb break="yes"/>these animals, and the thick smoke<lb break="yes"/>which the volcano exhales during<lb break="yes"/>the eruption. It appeared to me of<lb break="yes"/>very great importance to descriptive<lb break="yes"/>natural history to verify sufficiently<lb break="yes"/>the nature of these animals. All<lb break="yes"/>the inhabitants agree that they are<lb break="yes"/>the same with those which are found<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">in</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="513" facs="#f0003"/>
                    <cb/> in the rivulets at the foot of these<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes, and called prennadillas:<lb break="yes"/>they are even the only species of fish<lb break="yes"/>that is discovered at the height of<lb break="yes"/>above 7 500 toises, in the waters of<lb break="yes"/>the kingdom of Quito. M. <persName key="lacepede_bg">Lace-<lb break="no"/>pede</persName>, who has also examined it, ad-<lb break="no"/>vised me to place it in that division<lb break="yes"/>of Silurus, which, in the fifth volume<lb break="yes"/>of his natural history of fishes, he<lb break="yes"/>has described under the name of <hi rendition="#i">pi-<lb break="no"/>melodes.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From the enormous quantity of<lb break="yes"/>Pimelodes the volcanoes of the king-<lb break="no"/>dom of Quito occasionally discharge,<lb break="yes"/>we cannot doubt, that this coun-<lb break="no"/>try contains great subterranean lakes<lb break="yes"/>which conceal these, for in the little<lb break="yes" />rivers around there are very few. A<lb break="yes"/>part of those rivers may communicate<lb break="yes"/>with the subterranean pits; it is also<lb break="yes"/>probable that the first pimelodes<lb break="yes"/>which have inhabited these pits have<lb break="yes"/>mounted there against the current.<lb break="yes"/>I have seen fish in the caverns of<lb break="yes"/>Derbyshire in England; and near<lb break="yes"/>Gailenreath, in Germany, where the<lb break="yes"/>fossil heads of bears and lions are<lb break="yes"/>found, there are living trouts in the<lb break="yes"/>grottoes, which at present are very<lb break="yes"/>distant from any rivulet, and greatly<lb break="yes" />elevated above the level of the neigh-<lb break="no"/>bouring waters. In the province of<lb break="yes"/>Quito, the subterraneous roarings<lb break="yes" />that accompany the earthquakes;<lb break="yes"/>the masses of rocks that we think<lb break="yes"/>we hear crumbling down below the<lb break="yes"/>earth we walk on; the immense<lb break="yes"/>quantity of water that issues from<lb break="yes"/>the earth during the volcanic explo-<lb break="no"/>sions, and numerous other phenome-<lb break="no"/>na, indicate that all the soil of this<lb break="yes"/>elevated plain is undermined. But,<lb break="yes"/>if it is easy to conceive that vast sub-<lb break="no"/>terranean basins may be filled, it is<lb break="yes"/>more difficult to explain how these<lb break="yes" />animals are attracted by volcanoes<lb break="yes"/>that ascend to the height of 9000<lb break="yes"/>feet, and discharged either by their<lb break="yes" />craters or by their lateral vents.<lb break="yes"/>Should we suppose that the pimelodes<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> exist in subterranean basins of the<lb break="yes"/>same height at which they are seen<lb break="yes"/>to issue? How conceive their origin<lb break="yes" />in a position so extraordinary; in<lb break="yes"/>the flank of a cone so often heated,<lb break="yes"/>and perhaps partly produced by vol-<lb break="no" />canic fire? Whatever may be the<lb break="yes"/>source from which they issue, the per-<lb break="no"/>fect state in which they are found<lb break="yes" />induces us to believe that those vol-<lb break="no"/>canoes, the most elevated and the<lb break="yes"/>most active in the world, experience<lb break="yes" />from time to time, convulsive move-<lb break="no"/>ments, during which the disengage-<lb break="no"/>ment of caloric appears less consi-<lb break="no" />derable than we should suppose it.<lb break="yes"/>Earthquakes do not always accom-<lb break="no"/>pany those phenomena.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The corregidor of the city of Ibar-<lb break="no"/>ra, Don <persName key="pardo_jp">José <choice>
                        <sic>Posc</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Posse</corr>
                    </choice> Pardo</persName>, has com-<lb break="no"/>municated to me an interesting ob-<lb break="no"/>servation on the pimelodes. <choice>
                        <sic>It</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">&#x201E;It</corr>
                    </choice> is<lb break="yes"/>known (says he in a letter which<lb break="yes"/>I have still preserved,) that the vol-<lb break="no"/>cano of Imbaburu, at the time of<lb break="yes"/>its great eruption on the side next<lb break="yes"/>our city, threw out an enormous<lb break="yes"/>quantity of prennadillas; it even<lb break="yes"/>continues still occasionally to do so,<lb break="yes" />especially after great rains. It<lb break="yes"/>is observed, that these fishes ac-<lb break="no"/>tually live in the interior of the<lb break="yes" />mountain, and that the Indians of<lb break="yes"/>St Pabla fish for them in a rivulet<lb break="yes"/>at the very place whence they issue<lb break="yes" />from the rock. The fishery does<lb break="yes"/>not succeed either in the day or in<lb break="yes"/>moonlight: a very dark night is<lb break="yes"/>therefore necessary, as the prenna-<lb break="no"/>dillas will not otherwise come out<lb break="yes"/>of the volcano, the interior of which<lb break="yes"/>is hollow.&#x201D; It appears then that<lb break="yes"/>the light is injurious to these sub-<lb break="no"/>terraneous fishes, which are not ac-<lb break="no" />customed to so strong a stimulus;<lb break="yes"/>an observation so much the more<lb break="yes"/>curious, that the pimelodes of the<lb break="yes"/>same species, which inhabit the<lb break="yes"/>brooks in the vicinity of the city of<lb break="yes"/>Quito, live exposed to the bright-<lb break="no"/>ness of the meridian sun.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 