<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Memoir on a new Species of Monkey found in the eastern Declivity of the Andes</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:46</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">II.43</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1806-Memoir_on_a_new_Species_of_Monkey-1</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>als „Mémoire sur une nouvelle espèce de singe, trouvée sur la pente orientale des Andes“, in: Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Recueil d’observations de zoologie et d’anatomie comparée, faites dans l’Océan Atlantique, dans l’intérieur du Nouveau Continent et dans la Mer du Sud pendant les années 1799, 1800, 1801, 1802 et 1803&lt;/i&gt;, 2 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell / G. el Dufour 1811 [1812], J. Smith / Gide [1813–] 1833, Band 1, S. 14–16.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Memoir on a new Species of Monkey found in the eastern Declivity of the Andes</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1806</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Philosophical Magazine&lt;/i&gt; 24:96 (Februar–Mai 1806), S. 339–341, Tafel.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="339" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Memoir on a new Species of Monkey found in the<lb break="yes" />eastern Declivity of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>. By M.</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">de <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">From <hi rendition="#i">Recueil d&#x2019;Observations de Zoologie et d&#x2019; Anatomie comparé,</hi> 1re livraison.</note>.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#in">I</hi>n</hi> the vast plains which extend from the eastern declivity<lb break="yes"/>of the <placeName key="anden" >Andes</placeName> towards the shores of the Brazils, in the thick<lb break="yes"/>forests on the <placeName key="amazonasregion" >Amazons</placeName>, Rio Negro (Black River), and<lb break="yes"/>Oronoco, the <hi rendition="#i">cavia capybara, sus tajassu,</hi> and the monkeys,<lb break="yes"/>are the quadrupeds most common. The marmose and alou-<lb break="no"/>ate prevail over all the others, whether for variety of species<lb break="yes"/>or number of individuals. Some of these monkeys, such<lb break="yes"/>as the capuchin of Oronoco, very different from the <hi rendition="#i">simia<lb break="yes"/>capucina</hi>
                    <persName key="linne_cv">Linn.</persName>, the tiger-monkey or cusicusi, and the wi-<lb break="no"/>dow, (three new species which I have discovered,) live in<lb break="yes"/>pairs, melancholy, mistrustful, flying (like man in a savage<lb break="yes"/>state) their proper species. Others, especially the sagouin<lb break="yes"/>and howling monkey, are seen in troops, from 80 to 100,<lb break="yes"/>springing from branch to branch in search of nourishment.<lb break="yes"/>The <hi rendition="#i">saimiri</hi> of <persName key="buffon_gllcd">Buffon</persName>, that are the <hi rendition="#i">titi</hi> of <placeName key="atures">Atures</placeName> (<hi rendition="#i">simia<lb break="yes"/>sciurea</hi>), so esteemed on account of their gaiety, their mild-<lb break="no"/>ness, and extreme littleness, assemble together when it be-<lb break="no"/>gins to rain. A fall of temperature of three or four degrees<lb break="yes"/>of the centigrade thermometer disturbs them so much, that<lb break="yes"/>they mutually embrace each other and form balls or knots,<lb break="yes"/>of which each individual seeks to occupy the middle, in<lb break="yes"/>order to find shelter. The Indian hunters, advertised by the<lb break="yes"/>cry of the titi, direct their arrows towards these flocks.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Notwithstanding the great number of monkeys that na-<lb break="no"/>turalists have described, it is probable that we are still ig-<lb break="no"/>norant of the tenth part existing. In <placeName key="afrika">Africa</placeName>, and even<lb break="yes"/>in <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>, there are vast plains of twenty thousand<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">square</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="340" facs="#f0002"/> square leagues which have not yet been visited by any Eu-<lb break="no"/>ropean. On the other hand, the monkeys the most com-<lb break="no"/>mon are still so imperfectly represented even in the most<lb break="yes"/>recent works, executed with the greatest elegance, that those<lb break="yes"/>who have seen the living individuals would have difficulty to<lb break="yes"/>recognise them in the drawings published. Of this I might<lb break="yes"/>cite as examples the <hi rendition="#i">simia sciurea,</hi> varieties of the <hi rendition="#i">simia ca-<lb break="no" />pucina,</hi> and even the <hi rendition="#i">simia paniscus,</hi> which is the game<lb break="yes"/>commonly eaten in the Upper Oronoco.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Among the great number of new <hi rendition="#i">sapajous,</hi> or marmoses,<lb break="yes"/>that I had the opportunity of describing in my voyage to the<lb break="yes"/>tropics, I have chosen a monkey of the plains of Mocoa,<lb break="yes"/>remarkable for its resemblance with the lion of <placeName key="afrika">Africa</placeName>, of<lb break="yes"/>which I made a drawing during my residence at Popayan.<lb break="yes"/>My sketch has been copied and improved by M. <persName key="turpin_pjf">Turpin</persName>.<lb break="yes" />(Plate VIII.)</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The <hi rendition="#i">leoncito</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Leoncito,</hi> from <hi rendition="#i">leon</hi> (lion) a diminutive of endearment more common even<lb break="yes"/>with the Spaniards than the Italians.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Translator.</hi>
                    </note> is very rare, even in its native country. It<lb break="yes"/>inhabits the plains which border on the eastern declivity of<lb break="yes"/>the Cordelliers, the fertile banks of the Putumayo and Ca-<lb break="no"/>queta: it never ascends even to the temperate regions, while<lb break="yes"/>the wandering bands of the <hi rendition="#i">simia beelzebul</hi> sometimes push<lb break="yes"/>their excursions to heights equal to those of Canigou, and<lb break="yes"/>even Mont Perdu. The <hi rendition="#i">leoncito</hi> of Mocoa, which I name<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">simia leonina,</hi> differs essentially from all known species. It<lb break="yes"/>has not the white head of the <hi rendition="#i">s. leucocephala</hi> figured in the<lb break="yes"/>work of <persName key="audebert_jb">Audebert</persName>. It differs from the <hi rendition="#i">s. rosalia,</hi> and the<lb break="yes"/>saki or fox-tailed monkey (<hi rendition="#i">s. pithecia</hi>), by a white spot<lb break="yes" />which covers the top of the nose, the mouth, and the chin;<lb break="yes"/>and from the <hi rendition="#i">s. iacchus</hi> of Brazil, by a tail without white<lb break="yes"/>rings, by its black visage, and by the disparity of conforma-<lb break="no"/>tion that exists between the claws of its fore-feet and the<lb break="yes"/>nails on its hinder ones; the former almost resembling the<lb break="yes"/>claws of a cat, and the latter having nails like the human<lb break="yes"/>toes. The <hi rendition="#i">leoncito</hi> is but seven or eight inches long,<lb break="yes"/>without counting the tail, which is of the length of the<lb break="yes"/>body. It is one of the least and most elegant monkeys that<lb break="yes"/>we have seen. It is gay and sportive, but, like most little<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">animals,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="341" facs="#f0003"/> animals, very irascible. When it is vexed it bristles up the<lb break="yes"/>hair on its neck, that increases its resemblance to the African<lb break="yes"/>lion. I have seen but two individuals of this very rare mon-<lb break="no"/>key: they were the first that had been brought living to the<lb break="yes"/>west of the Cordellier. They were kept in a cage; and their<lb break="yes"/>movements were so rapid and so continual, that I had much<lb break="yes"/>difficulty to design them. Their hissing imitates the song<lb break="yes"/>of little birds, and I suppose that the conformation of their<lb break="yes"/>larynx (having a particular sac) is analogous to that which<lb break="yes"/>I have described in the <hi rendition="#i">simia &#x0153;dipus.</hi> I have been assured,<lb break="yes"/>that in the cottages of the Indians of Mocoa the leoncito<lb break="yes"/>breeds in the domestic state. By the way of Grand-Para<lb break="yes"/>and <placeName key="amazonas">the river of Amazons</placeName> they might be brought into Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope. If a government, interested in the progress of de-<lb break="no"/>scriptive natural history, would undertake an expedition in<lb break="yes"/>which that interest would not be rendered subservient to<lb break="yes"/>geographical discoveries; if that government sent canoes or<lb break="yes"/>small boats to ascend the Oronoco, and to penetrate by the<lb break="yes"/>Casiquiaré and Rio Negro to <placeName key="amazonas" >the river of Amazons</placeName>; in<lb break="yes"/>short, if, after having explored the mouths of the Caqueta<lb break="yes"/>and Putumayo, it would make these same boats descend to<lb break="yes"/>Grand-Para, it would in a little time unite collections the<lb break="yes"/>most precious to the study of zoology and botany. Such an<lb break="yes"/>expedition would be of little expense, and its success certain.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2" xml:lang="lat">
                    <head>SIMIA <hi rendition="#k">leonina.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Ex olivaceo fuscescens, facie atra, ore albo, dorso striis<lb break="yes"/>albo-flavescentibus notato.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Caput parvum, depressum, nigrescens. Facies anthropo-<lb break="no"/>morpha, atra; macula <choice>
                            <sic>albo-c&#x0153;rulescens</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">albo-c&#x00E6;rulescens</corr>
                        </choice> circa os et nares.<lb break="yes"/>Auricul&#x00E6; subtriangulares distantes, margine superiori de-<lb break="no"/>flexo, magn&#x00E6;, aterrim&#x00E6;, pilos&#x00E6;. Corpus ex badio oliva-<lb break="no"/>ceum, pilis nigro-annulatis, in collo longioribus. Dorsum<lb break="yes"/>maculis et striis albo-flavescentibus variegatum. Cauda non<lb break="yes" />prehensilis, longitudine corporis, superne atra, inferne badia,<lb break="yes"/>apice incurva et incrassata. Manus et pedes aterrimi, in-<lb break="no"/>ferne nudi, pollice in manibus anterioribus et posteriorbus<lb break="yes"/>distante. Ungues acuti, incurvi, atri; pollicis ungue in ma-<lb break="no"/>nibus anterioribus oblongo, acuto, in manibus posterioribus<lb break="yes"/>(pedibus) obtuso, anthropomorpho.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
      <back>
        <div type="editorial">
          <head>Abbildungen</head>
          <figure facs="1806-Memoir_on_a_new_Species_of_Monkey-1.jpg"/>
        </div>
      </back>
    </text>
</TEI> 