<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023299100">
                        <surname>Clark</surname>
                        <forename>Rex</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="stoeckli_mt">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stöckli</surname>
                        <forename>Matthias Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="schnidrig_bf">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schnidrig</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara Franziska</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.5.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.4.0" when="2018-09-28" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Personenmarkierung abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.3.0" when="2018-09-27" who="stoeckli_mt">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Personen.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2018-09-27" who="schnidrig_bf">Markup: added placeName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Orte.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="333" facs="#f0001"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Memoir on a new Species of Pimelodus thrown out of<lb break="yes"/>the Volcanoes in the Kingdom of Quito; with some<lb break="yes"/>Particulars respecting the Volcanoes of the Andes. By<lb break="yes"/>M.</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">De <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">From <hi rendition="#i">Recueil d&#x2019;Observations de Zoologie et d&#x2019;Anatomie comparé,</hi> 1re livraison.</note>.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>he</hi> chain of the Andes, from the Straits of Magellan to<lb break="yes"/>the northern shores bordering on Asia, extending over more<lb break="yes"/>than 2000 leagues, presents above fifty volcanoes still active,<lb break="yes"/>of which the ph&#x00E6;nomena are as various as their height and<lb break="yes"/>local situation. A small number of the least elevated of<lb break="yes"/>these volcanoes throw out running lava. I have seen, at<lb break="yes"/>the volcano of Zurullo, in Mexico, a basaltic cone that<lb break="yes"/>sprung from the earth the 15th September 1759, and at<lb break="yes"/>present rising 249 toises (1595<formula notation="TeX" >\frac{2}{3}</formula> feet) above the surrounding<lb break="yes"/>plain. The volcanic ridges of Guatimala cast out a prodi-<lb break="no"/>gious quantity of muriate of ammonia. Those of Popayan<lb break="yes"/>and the high plain of Pasto present either <hi rendition="#i">solfatares,</hi> which<lb break="yes" />exhale sulphureous acid, or little craters filled with boiling<lb break="yes" />water, and disengaging sulphurated hydrogen, which de-<lb break="no"/>composes by contact with the oxygen of the atmosphere.<lb break="yes"/>The volcanoes of the kingdom of Quito throw out pumice-<lb break="maybe"/>stone, basaltes <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">It would have been of some use to geology had the author here men-<lb break="no"/>tioned whether the stone which he calls basaltes has been submitted to<lb break="yes"/>the action of fire or water; or whether, in addition to the other well known<lb break="yes"/>characters of this mineral, it yielded hydrogen gas on distillation, the latter<lb break="yes"/>being the peculiar characteristic of what is properly denominated basaltes.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Translator.</hi>
                    </note>, and scorified porphyries; and vomit enor-<lb break="no"/>mous quantities of water, carburetted argil, and muddy mat-<lb break="no"/>ter, which spreads fertility from eight to ten leagues around.<lb break="yes"/>But, since the period to which the traditions of the natives<lb break="yes"/>ascend, they have never produced great masses of running<lb break="yes"/>melted lava. The height of these colossal mountains, that<lb break="yes"/>surpasses five times that of Vesuvius, and their inland situa-<lb break="no"/>tion, are, without doubt, the principal causes of these ano-<lb break="no"/>malies. The subterranean noise of Cotopaxi, at the time<lb break="yes"/>of its great explosions, extends to distances equal to that<lb break="yes"/>from Vesuvius to Dijon. But, notwithstanding this inten-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">sity</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="334" facs="#f0002"/> sity of force, it is known, that if the volcanic fire was at a<lb break="yes"/>great depth, the melted lava could neither raise itself to the<lb break="yes"/>edge of the crater, nor pierce the flank of these mountains,<lb break="yes"/>which to the height of 1400 toises (8971<formula notation="TeX">\frac{2}{3}</formula> feet) are fortified<lb break="yes"/>by high surrounding plains. It appears, therefore, natural,<lb break="yes"/>that volcanoes so elevated should discharge from their mouth<lb break="yes"/>but isolated stones, volcanic cinders or ashes, flames, boil-<lb break="no"/>ing water, and, above all, this carburetted argil impregnated<lb break="yes"/>with sulphur, that is called <hi rendition="#i">moya</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">M. <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> seems not to have been aware that this name has been<lb break="yes"/>affixed to it in consequence of its having some resemblance to a kind of<lb break="yes"/>blackish coarse bread made of grits or pollard, and used in Spain by some<lb break="yes"/>very poor but proud people, or for purposes of penitence in cases of a <hi rendition="#i">pecado<lb break="yes" />mortal.&#x2014;Translator.</hi>
                    </note> in the language of the<lb break="yes"/>country.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The mountains of the kingdom of Quito occasionally offer<lb break="yes"/>another spectacle, less alarming, but not less curious to the<lb break="yes" />naturalist. The great explosions are periodical, and some-<lb break="no"/>what rare. Cotopaxi, Tungurahua, and Sangay, some-<lb break="no"/>times do not present one in twenty or thirty years. But<lb break="yes"/>during such intervals even these volcanoes will discharge<lb break="yes"/>enormous quantities of argillaceous mud; and, what is more<lb break="yes"/>extraordinary, an innumerable quantity of fish. By acci-<lb break="no"/>dent, none of these volcanic inundations took place the year<lb break="yes"/>that I passed the Andes of Quito; but the fish vomited from<lb break="yes"/>the volcanoes is a ph&#x00E6;nomenon so common, and so gene-<lb break="no"/>rally known by all the inhabitants of that country, that there<lb break="yes"/>cannot remain the least doubt of its authenticity. As there<lb break="yes"/>are in these regions several very well informed persons, who<lb break="yes"/>have successfully devoted themselves to the physical sciences,<lb break="yes"/>I have had an opportunity of procuring exact information (<hi rendition="#i">ren-<lb break="no" />seignemens</hi>) respecting these fishes. M. de Larrea, at Quito,<lb break="yes"/>well versed in the study of chemistry, who has formed a<lb break="yes"/>cabinet of the minerals of his country, has been, above all<lb break="yes"/>others, the most useful to me in these researches. Exa-<lb break="no"/>mining the archives of several little towns in the neighbour-<lb break="no"/>hood of Cotopaxi, in order to extract the epochs of the great<lb break="yes"/>earthquakes, that fortunately have been preserved with care,<lb break="yes"/>I there found some notes on the fish ejected from the vol-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">canoes.</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="335" facs="#f0003"/> canoes. On the estates of the marquis of Selvalegre the<lb break="yes"/>Cotopaxi had thrown a quantity so great, that their putre-<lb break="no"/>faction spread a fetid odour around. In 1691 the almost<lb break="yes"/>extinguished volcano of Imbaburu threw out thousands on<lb break="yes"/>the fields in the environs of the city of Ibarra. The putrid<lb break="yes"/>fevers which commenced at that period were attributed to<lb break="yes"/>the miasma which exhaled from these fish, heaped on the sur-<lb break="no"/>face of the earth and exposed to the rays of the sun. The<lb break="yes"/>last time that Imbaburu ejected fish was on the 19th of June<lb break="yes"/>1698, when the volcano of Cargneirazo sunk, and thousands<lb break="yes"/>of these animals enveloped in argillaceous mud were thrown<lb break="yes"/>over the crumbling borders.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Cotopaxi and Tungurahua throw out fish, sometimes<lb break="yes"/>by the crater which is at the top of these mountains, sometimes<lb break="yes"/>by lateral vents, but constantly at 2500 or 2600 toises above<lb break="yes"/>the level of the sea: the adjacent plains being 1300 toises<lb break="yes"/>high, one may conclude that these animals issue from a<lb break="yes"/>point which is 1300 toises more elevated than the plains on<lb break="yes"/>which they are thrown. Some Indians have assured me<lb break="yes"/>that the fish vomited by the volcanoes were sometimes still<lb break="yes"/>living in descending along the flank of the mountain: but<lb break="yes"/>this fact does not appear to me sufficiently proved: certain it<lb break="yes"/>is, that among the thousands of dead fish that in a few hours<lb break="yes"/>are seen descending from Cotopaxi with great bodies of cold<lb break="yes"/>fresh water, there are very few that are so much disfigured<lb break="yes"/>that one can believe them to have been exposed to the action<lb break="yes"/>of a strong heat. This fact becomes still more striking when<lb break="yes"/>we consider the soft flesh of these animals, and the thick<lb break="yes"/>smoke which the volcano exhales during the eruption. It ap-<lb break="no"/>peared to me of very great importance to descriptive natural<lb break="yes"/>history to verify sufficiently the nature of these animals.<lb break="yes"/>All the inhabitants agree that they are identical with those<lb break="yes"/>which are found in the rivulets at the foot of these volcanoes,<lb break="yes"/>and called <hi rendition="#i">prennadillas</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">This word is an indifferent or contemptuous diminutive, indicating abun-<lb break="no"/>dant, pregnant, fruitful, easily taken, but not a pleasing or desirable object.<lb break="yes"/>The name is purely Spanish and not Indian, of course could never have been<lb break="yes" />applied to any fish used as food by Spaniards.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i" >Translator.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <hi rendition="#i">:</hi> they are even the only species<lb break="yes"/>of fish that is discovered at the height of above 1400 toises<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">in</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="336" facs="#f0004"/> in the waters of the kingdom of Quito. I have designed it,<lb break="yes"/>with care, on the spot, and my design has been coloured by<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="turpin_pjf">Turpin</persName>. I have observed that the <hi rendition="#i">prennadilla</hi> is a new<lb break="yes"/>species of the genus <hi rendition="#i">silurus.</hi> M. <persName key="lacepede_bg">Lacepede</persName>, who has also<lb break="yes" />examined it, advised me to place it in that division of <hi rendition="#i" >silurus</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>which, in the fifth volume of his Natural History of Fishes,<lb break="yes"/>he has described under the name of <hi rendition="#i" >pimelodes.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This new species of <hi rendition="#i">pimelodus</hi> has a depressed body of an<lb break="yes"/>olive colour mixed with little black spots. The mouth, which<lb break="yes"/>is at the extremity of the nose, is very large, and furnished<lb break="yes"/>with two barbillons or whiskers attached to the jaws. The<lb break="yes"/>nostrils are tubulous; the eyes are very small, and placed<lb break="yes"/>towards the middle of the head. The skin of the body and<lb break="yes"/>the tail is covered with an abundant mucus, and the mouth<lb break="yes"/>is furnished with very small teeth. The branchial membrane<lb break="yes"/>has four radii, like the <hi rendition="#i" >pimelodus chilensis;</hi> the pectoral fin<lb break="yes"/>has nine; the ventral five; the first dorsal six; the fin of the<lb break="yes"/>anus seven; and that of the tail, which is bifid, has twelve<lb break="yes"/>radii. The first radius of all the fins is indented on the out-<lb break="no"/>side: the second dorsal fin is adipose, and placed near the<lb break="yes"/>tail. This little <hi rendition="#i">pimelodus,</hi> which is found in lakes even to<lb break="yes"/>the height of 1700 toises, is, without doubt, the fish that<lb break="yes"/>lives in the most elevated regions of our globe. Its common<lb break="yes"/>length scarcely amounts to ten centimetres (four inches);<lb break="yes"/>but there are varieties which do not appear to reach five cen-<lb break="no"/>timetres (two inches) in length.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the system of ichthyology this new species of <hi rendition="#i" >pimelodus</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>should be ranged in the first sub-genus established by <persName key="lacepede_bg">Lace-<lb break="no"/>pede</persName>, among the forked-tailed pimelodes. It must be in the<lb break="yes"/>first species, before the <hi rendition="#i">pimelodus bagre.</hi> As it is the only<lb break="yes" />one of that division that has but two whiskers, I give it the<lb break="yes" />name of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#c">PIMELODUS <hi rendition="#k">Cyclopum.</hi> (Plate VIII.)<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Cirris duobus, corpore olivaceo nigro-punctato.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This little fish lives in rivulets at the temperature of 10°<lb break="yes"/>of the centigrade thermometer, while other species of the<lb break="yes"/>same genus exist in rivers in the plains the water of which is<lb break="yes"/>at 27°. The <hi rendition="#i">pimelodus</hi> is but very rarely eaten, and then<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">only</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="337" facs="#f0005"/> only by the most indigent race of Indians; its aspect and<lb break="yes"/>the sliminess of its skin render it very disgusting.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From the enormous quantity of <hi rendition="#i">pimelodes</hi> that the vol-<lb break="no"/>canoes of the kingdom of Quito occasionally discharge, one<lb break="yes"/>cannot doubt that country contains great subterranean<lb break="yes"/>lakes which conceal these fishes; for the individuals that<lb break="yes"/>exist in the little rivers around are very few in number.<lb break="yes"/>A part of those rivers may communicate with the subterra-<lb break="no"/>nean pits: it is also probable that the first <hi rendition="#i" >pimelodes</hi> which<lb break="yes"/>have inhabited these pits have mounted there against the<lb break="yes"/>current. I have seen fish in the caverns of Derbyshire, in<lb break="yes"/>England; and near Gailenreuth, in Germany, where the<lb break="yes"/>fossil heads of bears and lions are found, there are living<lb break="yes"/>trouts in the grottoes, which at present are very distant from<lb break="yes"/>any rivulet, and greatly elevated above the level of the neigh-<lb break="no"/>bouring waters. In the province of Quito, the subterraneous<lb break="yes"/>roarings that accompany the earthquakes; the masses of<lb break="yes"/>rocks that we think we hear crumbling down below the<lb break="yes"/>earth we walk on; the immense quantity of water that<lb break="yes"/>issues from the earth in the driest places during the volcanic<lb break="yes"/>explosions; and numerous other ph&#x00E6;nomena, indicate that<lb break="yes"/>all the soil of this elevated plain is undermined. But, if it is<lb break="yes"/>easy to conceive that vast subterranean basins may be filled<lb break="yes"/>with water which nourishes fishes, it is more difficult to ex-<lb break="no"/>plain how these animals are attracted by volcanoes that<lb break="yes"/>ascend to the height of 1300 toises, and discharged either<lb break="yes"/>by their craters or by their lateral vents. Should we sup-<lb break="no"/>pose that the <hi rendition="#i">pimelodes</hi> exist in subterranean basins of the<lb break="yes"/>same height at which they are seen to issue? How conceive<lb break="yes"/>their origin in a position so extraordinary; in the flank of a<lb break="yes"/>cone so often heated, and perhaps partly produced by vol-<lb break="no"/>canic fire? Whatever may be the source from which they<lb break="yes"/>issue, the perfect state in which they are found induces us<lb break="yes"/>to believe that those volcanoes, the most elevated and the<lb break="yes"/>most active in the world, experience, from time to time, con-<lb break="no"/>vulsive movements, during which the disengagement of ca-<lb break="no"/>loric appears less considerable than we should suppose it.<lb break="yes"/>Earthquakes do not always accompany those ph&#x00E6;nomena.<lb break="yes"/>Perhaps, in the different concamerations that may be ad-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">mitted</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="338" facs="#f0006"/> mitted in the interior of a volcano, the air is found occa-<lb break="no"/>sionally condensed, and that it is this condensed air which<lb break="yes"/>contributes to raise the water and fish; perhaps they issue<lb break="yes"/>from a concavity distant from those which emit volcanic<lb break="yes"/>fire; possibly, in fine, the argillaceous mud in which those<lb break="yes"/>animals are enveloped defends them from the action of great<lb break="yes"/>heat. Notwithstanding all the researches that have been re-<lb break="no"/>cently made on volcanoes, there is nothing but the study of<lb break="yes"/>volcanic productions that has made any progress. As to<lb break="yes"/>the nature of the combustibles which nourish those sub-<lb break="no"/>terranean fires, and the mode of action of those fires them-<lb break="no"/>selves, I believe that all persons who have visited the bor-<lb break="no"/>ders of craters, and who have lived a long time in the vici-<lb break="no"/>nity of volcanoes, will sincerely avow, with me, that we are<lb break="yes"/>still very far from being able to give an explication, which,<lb break="yes"/>without being contrary to the principles of chemistry and of<lb break="yes"/>physics, could account for the great ph&#x00E6;nomena which vol-<lb break="no"/>canic explosions present.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The corregidor of the city of Ibarra, don José <choice>
                        <sic>Posc</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Pose</corr>
                    </choice> Pardo,<lb break="yes"/>has communicated to me an interesting observation on the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">pimelodes.</hi> &#x201C;It is known (says he, in a letter which I have<lb break="yes"/>still preserved,) that the volcano of Imbaburu, at the time<lb break="yes"/>of its great eruption on the side next our city, threw out an<lb break="yes"/>enormous quantity of <hi rendition="#i" >prennadillas:</hi> it even continues still<lb break="yes"/>occasionally to do so, especially after great rains. It is ob-<lb break="no"/>served that these fishes actually live in the interior of the<lb break="yes"/>mountain, and that the Indians of S. Pabla fish <note place="foot" n="*">This is an assertion somewhat contrary to that of their being very bad<lb break="yes"/>food, and disagreeable in appearance. It is within the particular knowledge<lb break="yes"/>of the translator, that the Spaniards of South America are both very scep-<lb break="no"/>tical and very witty, and that to play upon the philosophical faith of Eu-<lb break="no"/>ropeans would be their highest delight. He must therefore be pardoned for<lb break="yes"/>regarding the letter of <hi rendition="#i">el Senor Corregidor</hi> as a <hi rendition="#i">jeu d&#x2019;esprit en revanche</hi> for the<lb break="yes"/>sarcastic observations of French travellers on the Spaniards.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Translator.</hi>
                    </note> for them<lb break="yes"/>in a rivulet at the very place whence they issue from the<lb break="yes"/>rock. This fishery does not succeed either in the day or<lb break="yes"/>in moonlight: a very dark night is therefore necessary, as<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">prennadillas</hi> will not otherwise come out of the volcano,<lb break="yes"/>the interior of which is hollow.&#x201D; It appears, then, that the<lb break="yes"/>light is injurious to those subterranean fishes, which are not<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">accustomed</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="339" facs="#f0007"/> accustomed to so strong a stimulus: an observation so much<lb break="yes"/>the more curious, that the <hi rendition="#i" >pimelodes</hi> of the same species,<lb break="yes"/>which inhabit the brooks in the vicinity of the city of Quito,<lb break="yes"/>live exposed to the brightness of the meridian sun.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 