<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Baron Humboldt’s description of the mode of catching the Gymnotus, or Electrical Eel</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:46</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">II.52</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1807-Jagd_und_Kampf-8-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1807-Jagd_und_Kampf-1.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1807-Jagd_und_Kampf-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1807-Jagd_und_Kampf-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1807-Jagd_und_Kampf-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1807-Jagd_und_Kampf-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1807-Jagd_und_Kampf-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1807-Jagd_und_Kampf-7-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1807-Jagd_und_Kampf-8-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Textstelle bisher nicht gefunden</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Baron Humboldt’s description of the mode of catching the Gymnotus, or Electrical Eel</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1834</date>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Friend. A Religious and Literary Journal&lt;/i&gt; 7:16 (25. Januar 1834), S. 122–124.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="122" facs="#f0001"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Baron <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName>&#x2019;s description of the mode of<lb break="yes" />catching the Gymnotus, or Electrical Eel.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>While traversing the immense plains of the<lb break="yes"/>province of Caraccas, in order to embark at<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="sanfernandodeapure">St. Fernando de Apure</placeName>, and commence our<lb break="yes"/>voyage on the Orinoco, we stayed five days<lb break="yes"/>at Calabozo, a small town situated, according<lb break="yes" />to my observations, in 8° 56&#x2032; 56&#x2033; north lati-<lb break="no" />tude. The object of this visit was to study<lb break="yes"/>the electric eels (Gymnoti,) an innumerable<lb break="yes"/>quantity of which are found in the neighbour-<lb break="no"/>hood. Indeed I was assured, that near Uri-<lb break="no"/>tuca a road, once much frequented, had been<lb break="yes" />entirely abandoned on account of these elec-<lb break="no"/>tric fishes; travellers being obliged to ford a<lb break="yes"/>stream in which a number of mules were an-<lb break="no"/>nually drowned, stunned by the shocks they<lb break="yes"/>received from the gymnoti.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="123" facs="#f0002"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>In order to perform our experiments with<lb break="yes"/>more precision, we were desirous of having<lb break="yes"/>the electric eels in the house which we inha-<lb break="no"/>bited at Calabozo. Our host took all possi-<lb break="no"/>ble pains to gratify our desires. He sent<lb break="yes" />Indians on horseback to fish in the pools. It<lb break="yes"/>was easy enough to procure plenty of dead<lb break="yes"/>gymnoti; but an almost puerile fear prevent-<lb break="no"/>ed the natives from bringing them alive. We<lb break="yes"/>were afterwards, it is true, convinced of the<lb break="yes" />difficulty of handling this fish whilst it still<lb break="yes"/>retained all its powers: but the dread of the<lb break="yes"/>common people is the more extraordinary in<lb break="yes"/>these countries, as they pretend that any one<lb break="yes"/>with tobacco in his mouth may touch a gym-<lb break="no" />notus with impunity. If the Indian had full<lb break="yes"/>confidence in this preservative, which is alto-<lb break="no"/>gether false, why did he not avail himself of<lb break="yes"/>it to gain the ten francs which we had pro-<lb break="no"/>mised for every living electric eel that was<lb break="yes" />brought to us? The love of the marvellous<lb break="yes"/>is so great among the natives, that they often<lb break="yes"/>maintain and spread abroad as facts what they<lb break="yes"/>themselves are far from putting faith in. It<lb break="yes"/>is thus that man thinks he must needs add to<lb break="yes" />the wonders of nature, as if nature was not<lb break="yes"/>of herself sufficiently mysterious, grand and<lb break="yes"/>imposing.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After three days of fruitless attempts in the<lb break="yes"/>town of Calabozo, during which we received<lb break="yes"/>only one eel alive, and that in a very weak<lb break="yes"/>state, we resolved to transport ourselves to<lb break="yes"/>the spot, and make our experiments in the<lb break="yes"/>open air, on the banks of the pools in which<lb break="yes"/>the gymnoti abounded. We reached first a<lb break="yes"/>little village called Rastro de Abaxo; thence<lb break="yes"/>the Indians conducted us to Can&#x0303;o de Bera, a<lb break="yes"/>muddy stagnant pool of water, but surround-<lb break="no"/>ed with a beautiful vegetation of the <hi rendition="#i">Clusia<lb break="yes" />rosea,</hi> the <hi rendition="#i">Hymenea Courbaril,</hi> the large Indian<lb break="yes"/>figs, and <hi rendition="#i">Mimos&#x00E6;</hi> with odoriferous flowers.<lb break="yes"/>We were much surprised on being told that<lb break="yes"/>thirty wild horses must be caught in the<lb break="yes" />neighbouring savannahs, to serve for the<lb break="yes"/>fishery of the electric eels. The idea of this<lb break="yes"/>mode of fishing, which they call <hi rendition="#i">embarbascar<lb break="yes"/>con caballos,</hi> (to stupify by means of horses,)<lb break="yes"/>is truly very odd, The word <hi rendition="#i">barbasco</hi> signi-<lb break="no"/>fies the roots of <hi rendition="#i">Jacquinia,</hi> of <hi rendition="#i">Piscidia,</hi> or of<lb break="yes"/>any other poisonous plant, by the contact of<lb break="yes" />which a great extent of water receives in an<lb break="yes"/>instant the power of killing, or at least of<lb break="yes"/>intoxicating or benumbing, the fishes. The<lb break="yes"/>latter rise to the surface of the water when<lb break="yes"/>they are poisoned in this way. As the horses<lb break="yes" />driven here and there in a pool cause the<lb break="yes"/>same effect with respect to the frightened<lb break="yes"/>fishes, the natives, confounding cause and<lb break="yes"/>effect, call the two modes of fishing by the<lb break="yes"/>same name.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Whilst our host was explaining to us this<lb break="yes"/>strange mode of catching fish in this coun-<lb break="no"/>try, the troop of horses and mules arrived.<lb break="yes"/>The Indians formed a sort of <hi rendition="#i" >battue,</hi> and en-<lb break="no"/>circling the poor quadrupeds closely on every<lb break="yes"/>side, compelled them to enter the pool. I<lb break="yes"/>can but imperfectly depict the interesting<lb break="yes" />spectacle which the attack of the eels upon<lb break="yes"/>the horses presented to us. The Indians,<lb break="yes"/>holding long canes and harpoons, place them-<lb break="no"/>selves around the pool; some of them climb<lb break="yes"/>the trees whose branches project over the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> surface of the water; and all of them by their<lb break="yes"/>shouts and their weapons prevent the horses<lb break="yes"/>from gaining the bank. The eels, confound-<lb break="no"/>ed by the hubbub and splashing of the horses,<lb break="yes"/>defend themselves by the reiterated discharge<lb break="yes" />of their electric batteries.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>For a long time they seem victorious over<lb break="yes"/>the horses and mules; every where we see<lb break="yes"/>the latter, stunned with the frequency and<lb break="yes"/>force of the electric shocks, disappearing be-<lb break="no" />neath the water. Some of the horses recover<lb break="yes"/>themselves, and, despite the active vigilance<lb break="yes"/>of the Indians, gain the bank; overcome by<lb break="yes"/>fatigue, and their limbs paralysed by the power<lb break="yes"/>of the electric commotions, they lay out-<lb break="no" />stretched upon the earth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>How I wished that a clever painter could<lb break="yes"/>have seized the moment when the scene was<lb break="yes"/>at its greatest animation. The groups of In-<lb break="no"/>dians surrounding the pools,&#x2014;the horses, with<lb break="yes"/>mane erect, and eyes of fright and pain,<lb break="yes" />struggling to escape from the storm which<lb break="yes"/>had surprised them;&#x2014;those yellow livid eels,<lb break="yes"/>like great aquatic serpents, swimming upon<lb break="yes"/>the surface of the water, and pursuing their<lb break="yes"/>enemy;&#x2014;all these objects presented, in truth,<lb break="yes"/>a most picturesque ensemble. I remembered<lb break="yes"/>the superb painting which represents a horse<lb break="yes" />entering a cavern and scared at the sight of<lb break="yes"/>a lion! The expression of terror was not<lb break="yes"/>stronger than we witnessed in this unequal<lb break="yes"/>conflict.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In less than five minutes, two horses were<lb break="yes"/>already drowned. The eel, being more than<lb break="yes"/>five feet in length, glides beneath the body<lb break="yes"/>of the horse or mule; it then gives a dis-<lb break="no"/>charge from the whole length of its electric<lb break="yes" />organ. It attacks at the same time the heart,<lb break="yes"/>the digestive viscera, and above all the <hi rendition="#i">plexus</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>of the gastric nerves. One cannot feel as-<lb break="no" />tonished, then, that the effect produced by<lb break="yes"/>the fish upon a great quadruped much exceeds<lb break="yes"/>that produced on man, which it only touches<lb break="yes"/>by one of the extremities. I doubt, how-<lb break="no"/>ever, that the gymnoti kill the horses imme-<lb break="no" />diately; I rather imagine that the latter, stun-<lb break="no"/>ned by the electric shocks which they receive<lb break="yes"/>in rapid succession, fall into a profound le-<lb break="no"/>thargy. Deprived of all sensibility, they dis-<lb break="no"/>appear beneath the water, the other horses<lb break="yes"/>and mules pass over their bodies, and a few<lb break="yes" />minutes suffice to make them perish.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After this commencement, I began to fear<lb break="yes"/>that this conflict would terminate very tragi-<lb break="no"/>cally. I did not doubt but that I should in a<lb break="yes"/>little time see all the mules drowned. We<lb break="yes" />pay, however, only eight francs for each, if<lb break="yes"/>the master of it is known. But the Indians<lb break="yes"/>assured us that the fishing would soon be<lb break="yes"/>over, and that it was only the first assault of<lb break="yes"/>the gymnoti that was formidable. In fact,<lb break="yes" />whether it is that the <persName key="galvani_la">galvanic</persName> electricity ac-<lb break="no"/>cumulates during a state of rest, or that the<lb break="yes"/>electric organ ceases to perform its functions<lb break="yes" />when fatigued by too long usage, the eels,<lb break="yes"/>after a certain time, resemble discharged bat-<lb break="no"/>teries. Their muscular motions continue<lb break="yes"/>equally lively, but they have no longer the<lb break="yes"/>power of discharging very energetic shocks.<lb break="yes" />When the conflict had lasted a quarter of an<lb break="yes"/>hour, the mules and horses seemed less alarm-<lb break="no"/>ed; they did not erect the mane, their eye<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> expressed less pain and terror; we saw them<lb break="yes"/>no longer fall over. On the other hand the<lb break="yes"/>eels, swimming half out of the water, and<lb break="yes"/>endeavouring to avoid the horses in place of<lb break="yes"/>attacking them, in their turn approached to-<lb break="no" />wards the bank. The Indians assured us,<lb break="yes"/>that no horse is killed when driven two days<lb break="yes"/>afterwards into the pool. These electric<lb break="yes"/>fishes require rest and abundant nourishment<lb break="yes"/>to produce and to accumulate a great quan-<lb break="no"/>tity of the <persName key="galvani_la">galvanic</persName> electricity. We know,<lb break="yes"/>by the experiments that have been made upon<lb break="yes"/>the torpedos (electric rays) of Italy, that on<lb break="yes"/>cutting or tying the nerves which go to the<lb break="yes"/>electric organs, the functions of these parts<lb break="yes"/>cease, as the movement of a muscle is sus-<lb break="no"/>pended as long as the ligature of the main<lb break="yes" />artery or nerve remains. The organs of the<lb break="yes"/>torpedo or gymnotus depend upon the nervous<lb break="yes"/>system and the vital functions: they are not<lb break="yes"/>mere electro-motive apparatuses, which at-<lb break="no" />tract from the surrounding bed of water the<lb break="yes"/>electricity they have lost. One cannot, there-<lb break="no"/>fore, be surprised that the power of the elec-<lb break="no"/>tric shocks of the gymnoti depends upon<lb break="yes"/>their health, and consequently upon rest,<lb break="yes" />nourishment, age, and probably a great as-<lb break="no"/>semblage of physical and moral conditions.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The eels, making towards the bank, are<lb break="yes"/>taken with great facility. Small harpoons,<lb break="yes"/>attached to cords, are cast at them; the har-<lb break="no"/>poon sometimes brings up two at a time. By<lb break="yes"/>this means they are drawn out of the water<lb break="yes"/>without the cord, which is very dry and of<lb break="yes"/>some length, communicating the shock to the<lb break="yes"/>person who holds it. In a few minutes five<lb break="yes" />large eels were on dry land. One might have<lb break="yes"/>caught twenty, if as many had been wanted<lb break="yes"/>for our experiments. Many were only slight-<lb break="no"/>ly wounded in the tail; others severely in the<lb break="yes"/>head. We were enabled to observe the na-<lb break="no"/>tural electricity of these fishes, modified by<lb break="yes"/>the different degrees of the vital force which<lb break="yes"/>they enjoyed. I shall describe in this me-<lb break="no"/>moir not only the experiments made, in con-<lb break="no" />junction with M. <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName>, on the gymnoti<lb break="yes"/>taken in our presence, but also those which<lb break="yes"/>we had an opportunity of making upon an eel<lb break="yes"/>of an enormous size, which we found in our<lb break="yes"/>house on our return from Rastro de Calabozo.<lb break="yes"/>This latter had been caught in a net; it had<lb break="yes"/>not received any wound. Immediately on<lb break="yes" />being drawn out of the water, it had been<lb break="yes"/>put into the same tray in which it was brought<lb break="yes"/>to Calabozo. Remaining thus in the same<lb break="yes"/>water it was accustomed to, <persName key="galvani_la" >galvanic</persName> electri-<lb break="no"/>city had not been altered. We shall see,<lb break="yes"/>however, in the course of this memoir, that<lb break="yes"/>the wounded gymnoti, that is to say, those of<lb break="yes" />less power, are much more instructive in the<lb break="yes"/>enquiry into <persName key="galvani_la">galvanic</persName> phenomena than the<lb break="yes"/>very active gymnoti, for many shades escape<lb break="yes"/>the eye of the observer when the electric tor-<lb break="no"/>rent takes as impetuous a course across good<lb break="yes"/>conductors, as across those which are more<lb break="yes"/>imperfect.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When one has seen the eels knock down a<lb break="yes"/>horse, and deprive it of
                    all sensibility, he is<lb break="yes"/>naturally afraid to touch them the
                        moment<lb break="yes"/>they are brought out of the water. So strong,<lb
                        break="yes"/>in fact, is this dread among the people of the<lb break="yes"
                    />country, that none of them could muster up<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="124" facs="#f0003"/> resolution to disengage the gymnoti from the<lb
                        break="yes"/>cords of the harpoon, or to transport them<lb break="yes"/>to
                    the little holes filled with water which we<lb break="yes"/>had made along the
                    bank of the Can&#x0303;o de<lb break="yes"/>Bera. It needed all our fortitude to
                        receive<lb break="yes"/>ourselves the first shocks, which certainly<lb
                        break="yes"/>were not very agreeable. The most energe-<lb break="no"/>tic
                    surpassed in power the most painful elec-<lb break="no"/>tric shocks I ever
                    remembered to have re-<lb break="no"/>ceived, accidentally, from a large and
                        com-<lb break="no"/>pletely charged Leyden jar. From that time<lb
                        break="yes"/>we readily conceived that, without doubt,<lb break="yes"/>there
                    was no exaggeration in the story of the<lb break="yes"/>Indians, when they
                    assert that persons who<lb break="yes"/>are swimming are drowned when one of
                        these<lb break="yes"/>eels attacks them by the leg or the arm. A<lb
                        break="yes"/>discharge so violent is fully capable of de-<lb break="no"
                    />priving a man for many minutes of all use of<lb break="yes"/>his limbs. If the
                    gymnotus should glide along<lb break="yes"/>the belly or the chest, death might
                    even fol-<lb break="no"/>low instantaneously the electric shock; for,<lb
                        break="yes"/>as we have before observed, the most noble<lb break="yes"
                    />parts, as the heart, the gastric system, the<lb break="yes"/>c&#x0153;liac
                    plexus, and all the nerves that depend<lb break="yes"/>upon it, would at once be
                    deprived of their<lb break="yes"/>irritability. A feeble electricity augments<lb
                        break="yes"/>the vital forces,&#x2014;a strong degree extinguishes<lb
                        break="yes"/>them entirely.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Voyage de <persName
                            key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName> et <persName key="bonpland_ajag"
                                >Bon-<lb break="no"/>pland</persName>.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 