<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023299100">
                        <surname>Clark</surname>
                        <forename>Rex</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="stoeckli_mt">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stöckli</surname>
                        <forename>Matthias Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="schnidrig_bf">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schnidrig</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara Franziska</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.5.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.4.0" when="2018-09-28" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Personenmarkierung abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.3.0" when="2018-09-27" who="stoeckli_mt">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Personen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2018-09-27" who="schnidrig_bf">Markup: added placeName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Orte.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="76" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">baron humboldt&#x2019;s description of the mode of catch-<lb break="no"/> ing the gymnotus, or electrical eel.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#in">W</hi>hile</hi> traversing the immense plains of the province of<lb break="yes"/> Caraccas, in order to embark at <placeName key="sanfernandodeapure">St. Fernando de Apure</placeName>, and<lb break="yes"/> commence our voyage on the Orinoco, we stayed five days<lb break="yes"/> at Calabozo, a small town situated, according to my observa-<lb break="no"/> tions, in 8° 56&#x2032; 56&#x2033; north latitude. The object of this visit<lb break="yes"/> was to study the electric eels (Gymnoti), an innumerable<lb break="yes"/> quantity of which are found in the neighbourhood. Indeed I<lb break="yes"/> was assured, that near Urituca a road, once much frequented,<lb break="yes"/> had been entirely abandoned on account of these electric fishes;<lb break="yes"/> travellers being obliged to ford a stream in which a number<lb break="yes"/> of mules were annually drowned, stunned by the shocks they<lb break="yes"/> received from the Gymnoti.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In order to perform our experiments with more precision,<lb break="yes"/> we were desirous of having the electric eels in the house which<lb break="yes"/> we inhabited at Calabozo. Our host took all possible pains<lb break="yes"/> to gratify our desires. He sent Indians on horseback to fish<lb break="yes"/> in the pools. It was easy enough to procure plenty of dead<lb break="yes"/> Gymnoti; but an almost puerile fear prevented the natives<lb break="yes"/> from bringing them alive. We were afterwards, it is true, con-<lb break="no"/> vinced of the difficulty of handling this fish whilst it still<lb break="yes"/> retained all its powers: but the dread of the common people<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="77" facs="#f0002"/> is the more extraordinary in these countries, as they pretend<lb break="yes"/> that any one with tobacco in his mouth may touch a gymnotus<lb break="yes"/> with impunity. If the Indian had full confidence in this pre-<lb break="no"/> servative, which is altogether false, why did he not avail him-<lb break="no"/> self of it to gain the ten francs which we had promised for<lb break="yes"/> every living electric eel that was brought to us? The love of<lb break="yes"/> the marvellous is so great among the natives, that they often<lb break="yes"/> maintain and spread abroad as facts what they themselves<lb break="yes"/> are far from putting faith in. It is thus that man thinks he<lb break="yes"/> must needs add to the wonders of Nature, as if Nature was<lb break="yes"/> not of herself sufficiently mysterious, grand and imposing.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After three days of fruitless attempts in the town of Cala-<lb break="no"/> bozo, during which we received only one eel alive, and that<lb break="yes"/> in a very weak state, we resolved to transport ourselves to<lb break="yes"/> the spot, and make our experiments in the open air, on the<lb break="yes"/> banks of the pools in which the gymnoti abounded. We<lb break="yes"/> reached first a little village called Rastro de Abaxo; thence<lb break="yes"/> the Indians conducted us to Can&#x0303;o de Bera, a muddy stag-<lb break="no"/> nant pool of water, but surrounded with a beautiful vegeta-<lb break="no"/> tion of the <hi rendition="#i">Clusia rosea,</hi> the <hi rendition="#i">Hymenea Courbaril,</hi> the large<lb break="yes"/> Indian figs, and <hi rendition="#i">Mimos&#x00E6;</hi> with odoriferous flowers. We were<lb break="yes"/> much surprised on being told that thirty wild horses must be<lb break="yes"/> caught in the neighbouring savannahs, to serve for the fish-<lb break="no"/> ery of the electric eels. The idea of this mode of fishing,<lb break="yes"/> which they call <hi rendition="#i">embarbascar con caballos,</hi> (to stupify by means<lb break="yes"/> of horses,) is truly very odd. The word <hi rendition="#i">barbasco</hi> signifies the<lb break="yes" /> roots of <hi rendition="#i">Jacquinia,</hi> of <hi rendition="#i" >Piscidia,</hi> or of any other poisonous<lb break="yes"/> plant, by the contact of which a great extent of water re-<lb break="no"/> ceives in an instant the power of killing, or at least of intoxi-<lb break="no"/> cating or benumbing, the fishes. The latter rise to the sur-<lb break="no"/> face of the water when they are poisoned in this way. As<lb break="yes"/> the horses driven here and there in a pool cause the same<lb break="yes"/> effect with respect to the frightened fishes, the natives, con-<lb break="no"/> founding cause and effect, call the two modes of fishing by<lb break="yes"/> the same name.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Whilst our host was explaining to us this strange mode of<lb break="yes"/> catching fish in this country, the troop of horses and mules<lb break="yes"/> arrived. The Indians formed a sort of <hi rendition="#i">battue,</hi> and encircling<lb break="yes"/> the poor quadrupeds closely on every side, compelled them<lb break="yes"/> to enter the pool. I can but imperfectly depict the interest-<lb break="no"/> ing spectacle which the attack of the eels upon the horses<lb break="yes"/> presented to us. The Indians, holding long canes and har-<lb break="no"/> poons, place themselves around the pool; some of them climb<lb break="yes"/> the trees whose branches project over the surface of the water;<lb break="yes"/> and all of them by their shouts and their weapons prevent the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="78" facs="#f0003"/> horses from gaining the bank. The eels, confounded by the<lb break="yes"/> hubbub and splashing of the horses, defend themselves by the<lb break="yes"/> reiterated discharge of their electric batteries.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>For a long time they seem victorious over the horses and<lb break="yes"/> mules; everywhere we see the latter, stunned with the fre-<lb break="no"/> quency and force of the electric shocks, disappearing beneath<lb break="yes"/> the water. Some of the horses recover themselves, and, despite<lb break="yes"/> the active vigilance of the Indians, gain the bank; overcome<lb break="yes"/> by fatigue, and their limbs paralyzed by the power of the<lb break="yes"/> electric commotions, they lay outstretched upon the earth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>How I wished that a clever painter could have seized the<lb break="yes"/> moment when the scene was at its greatest animation. The<lb break="yes"/> groups of Indians surrounding the pools,&#x2014;the horses, with<lb break="yes"/> mane erect, and eyes of fright and pain, struggling to<lb break="yes"/> escape from the storm which had surprised them;&#x2014;those<lb break="yes"/> yellow livid eels, like great aquatic serpents, swimming upon<lb break="yes"/> the surface of the water, and pursuing their enemy;&#x2014;all these<lb break="yes"/> objects presented, in truth, a most picturesque ensemble. I<lb break="yes"/> remembered the superb painting which represents a horse<lb break="yes"/> entering a cavern and scared at the sight of a lion! The ex-<lb break="no"/> pression of terror was not stronger than we witnessed in this<lb break="yes"/> unequal conflict.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In less than five minutes, two horses were already drowned.<lb break="yes"/> The eel, being more than five feet in length, glides beneath<lb break="yes"/> the body of the horse or mule; it then gives a discharge from<lb break="yes"/> the whole length of its electric organ. It attacks at the same<lb break="yes"/> time the heart, the digestive viscera, and above all the <hi rendition="#i" >plexus</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/> of the gastric nerves. One cannot feel astonished, then, that<lb break="yes"/> the effect produced by the fish upon a great quadruped much<lb break="yes"/> exceeds that produced on man, which it only touches by one<lb break="yes"/> of the extremities. I doubt, however, that the Gymnoti kill<lb break="yes"/> the horses immediately; I rather imagine that the latter,<lb break="yes"/> stunned by the electric shocks which they receive in rapid<lb break="yes"/> succession, fall into a profound lethargy. Deprived of all<lb break="yes"/> sensibility, they disappear beneath the water, the other horses<lb break="yes"/> and mules pass over their bodies, and a few minutes suffice<lb break="yes"/> to make them perish.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After this commencement, I began to fear that this conflict<lb break="yes"/> would terminate very tragically. I did not doubt but that<lb break="yes"/> I should in a little time see all the mules drowned. We pay,<lb break="yes"/> however, only eight francs for each, if the master of it is<lb break="yes"/> known. But the Indians assured us that the fishing would<lb break="yes"/> soon be over, and that it was only the first assault of the<lb break="yes"/> gymnoti that was formidable. In fact, whether it is that<lb break="yes"/> the <persName key="galvani_la">galvanic</persName> electricity accumulates during a state of rest, or<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="79" facs="#f0004"/> that the electric organ ceases to perform its functions when<lb break="yes"/> fatigued by too long usage, the eels, after a certain time, re-<lb break="no"/> semble discharged batteries. Their muscular motions con-<lb break="no"/> tinue equally lively, but they have no longer the power of<lb break="yes"/> discharging very energetic shocks. When the conflict had<lb break="yes"/> lasted a quarter of an hour, the mules and horses seemed less<lb break="yes"/> alarmed; they did not erect the mane, their eye expressed<lb break="yes"/> less pain and terror; we saw them no longer fall over. On<lb break="yes"/> the other hand the eels, swimming half out of the water, and<lb break="yes"/> endeavouring to avoid the horses in place of attacking them,<lb break="yes"/> in their turn approached towards the bank. The Indians as-<lb break="no"/> sured us, that no horse is killed when driven two days after-<lb break="no"/> wards into the pool. These electric fishes require rest and<lb break="yes"/> abundant nourishment to produce and to accumulate a great<lb break="yes"/> quantity of the <persName key="galvani_la" >galvanic</persName> electricity. We know, by the expe-<lb break="no"/> riments that have been made upon the torpedos (electric rays)<lb break="yes"/> of Italy, that on cutting or tying the nerves which go to the<lb break="yes"/> electric organs, the functions of these parts cease as the move-<lb break="no"/> ment of a muscle is suspended, as long as the ligature of the<lb break="yes"/> main artery or nerve remains. The organs of the torpedo or<lb break="yes"/> gymnotus depend upon the nervous system and the vital func-<lb break="no"/> tions: they are not mere electro-motive apparatuses, which<lb break="yes"/> attract from the surrounding bed of water the electricity they<lb break="yes"/> have lost. One cannot, therefore, be surprised that the<lb break="yes"/> power of the electric shocks of the gymnoti depends upon<lb break="yes"/> their health, and consequently upon rest, nourishment, age,<lb break="yes"/> and probably a great assemblage of physical and moral con-<lb break="no"/> ditions.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The eels, making towards the bank, are taken with great<lb break="yes"/> facility. Small harpoons, attached to cords, are cast at them;<lb break="yes"/> the harpoon sometimes brings up two at a time. By this<lb break="yes"/> means they are drawn out of the water without the cord,<lb break="yes"/> which is very dry and of some length, communicating the<lb break="yes"/> shock to the person who holds it. In a few minutes five<lb break="yes"/> large eels were on dry land. One might have caught twenty,<lb break="yes"/> if as many had been wanted for our experiments. Many<lb break="yes"/> were only slightly wounded in the tail; others severely in the<lb break="yes"/> head. We were enabled to observe the natural electricity of<lb break="yes"/> these fishes, modified by the different degrees of the vital<lb break="yes"/> force which they enjoyed. I shall describe in this Memoir<lb break="yes"/> not only the experiments made, in conjunction with M. <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bon-<lb break="no"/> pland</persName>, on the gymnoti taken in our presence, but also those<lb break="yes"/> which we had an opportunity of making upon an eel of an<lb break="yes"/> enormous size, which we found in our house on our return<lb break="yes"/> from Rastro to Calabozo. This latter had been caught in a<lb break="yes"/> net; it had not received any wound. Immediately on being<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="80" facs="#f0005"/> drawn out of the water, it had been put into the same tray in<lb break="yes"/> which it was brought to Calabozo. Remaining thus in the<lb break="yes"/> same water it was accustomed to, <persName key="galvani_la">galvanic</persName> electricity had not<lb break="yes"/> been altered. We shall see, however, in the course of this<lb break="yes"/> Memoir, that the wounded gymnoti, that is to say, those of<lb break="yes"/> less power, are much more instructive in the inquiry into<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="galvani_la">galvanic</persName> ph&#x00E6;nomena than the very active gymnoti, for many<lb break="yes"/> shades escape the eye of the observer when the electric tor-<lb break="no"/> rent takes as impetuous a course across good conductors, as<lb break="yes"/> across those which are more imperfect.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When one has seen the eels knock down a horse, and de-<lb break="no"/> prive it of all sensibility, he is naturally afraid to touch them<lb break="yes"/> the moment they are brought out of the water. So strong,<lb break="yes"/> in fact, is this dread among the people of the country, that<lb break="yes"/> none of them could muster up resolution to disengage the<lb break="yes"/> gymnoti from the cords of the harpoon, or to transport them<lb break="yes"/> to the little holes filled with water which we had made along<lb break="yes"/> the bank of the Can&#x0303;o de Bera. It needed all our fortitude<lb break="yes"/> to receive ourselves the first shocks, which certainly were not<lb break="yes"/> very agreeable. The most energetic surpassed in power the<lb break="yes"/> most painful electric shocks I ever remembered to have re-<lb break="no"/> ceived, accidentally, from a large and completely charged<lb break="yes"/> Leyden jar. From that time we readily conceived that, with-<lb break="no"/> out doubt, there was no exaggeration in the story of the In-<lb break="no"/> dians, when they assert that persons who are swimming are<lb break="yes"/> drowned when one of these eels attacks them by the leg or<lb break="yes"/> the arm. A discharge so violent is fully capable of depriving<lb break="yes"/> a man for many minutes of all use of his limbs. If the gym-<lb break="no"/> notus should glide along the belly or the chest, death might<lb break="yes"/> even follow instantaneously the electric shock; for, as we have<lb break="yes"/> before observed, the most noble parts, as the heart, the ga-<lb break="no"/> stric system, the c&#x0153;liac plexus, and all the nerves that de-<lb break="no"/> pend upon it, would at once be deprived of their irritability.<lb break="yes"/> A feeble electricity augments the vital forces,&#x2014;a strong de-<lb break="no"/> gree extinguishes them entirely.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Voyage de <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName> et<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName>
                    </hi>; <hi rendition="#i">Zoologie,</hi> p. 54.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 