<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023299100">
                        <surname>Clark</surname>
                        <forename>Rex</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="stoeckli_mt">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stöckli</surname>
                        <forename>Matthias Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="schnidrig_bf">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schnidrig</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara Franziska</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.5.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.4.0" when="2018-09-28" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Personenmarkierung abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.3.0" when="2018-09-27" who="stoeckli_mt">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Personen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2018-09-27" who="schnidrig_bf">Markup: added placeName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Orte.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="52" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <cb/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Clay-Eaters of <placeName key="suedamerika">South<lb break="yes"/>America</placeName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">It</hi> is currently reported through the<lb break="yes" />coasts of Cumana, <placeName key="barcelona">New Barcelona</placeName>, and<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas, that there are men living on<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the Orinoco who eat earth.<lb break="yes"/>On the 6th of June, 1800, on our re-<lb break="no"/>turn from the Rio Negro, when we de-<lb break="no" />scended the Orinoco in thirty-six days,<lb break="yes"/>we spent the day at the mission inhab-<lb break="no"/>ited by these people, (the Otomacs.)<lb break="yes"/>The earth which they eat is an unctu-<lb break="no"/>ous, almost tasteless, clay,&#x2014;true potters&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>earth, of a yellowish gray color, in con-<lb break="no"/>sequence of a slight admixture of oxide<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="53" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/> of iron. They select it with great care,<lb break="yes"/>and seek it on certain banks on the<lb break="yes"/>shores of the Orinoco and Meta. They<lb break="yes"/>distinguish the flavor of one kind of<lb break="yes"/>earth from that of another; all kinds of<lb break="yes"/>clay not being alike acceptable to their<lb break="yes"/>palate. They knead this earth into<lb break="yes"/>balls, measuring from four to six inches<lb break="yes"/>in diameter, and bake them before a<lb break="yes"/>slow fire, until the outer surface as-<lb break="no"/>sumes a reddish color. Before they<lb break="yes" />are eaten, the balls are again moistened.<lb break="yes"/>These Indians are mostly wild, uncivil-<lb break="no"/>ized men, who abhor all tillage. There<lb break="yes"/>is a proverb current among the most<lb break="yes"/>distant of the tribes living on the<lb break="yes"/>Orinoco, when they wish to speak of<lb break="yes"/>anything very unclean, &#x2014; &#x201C;So dirty<lb break="yes" />that the Otomacs eat of it.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As long as the waters of the Orinoco<lb break="yes"/>and the Meta are low, these people live<lb break="yes"/>on fish and turtles. They kill the for-<lb break="no"/>mer with arrows, shooting the fish, as<lb break="yes"/>they rise to the surface of the water,<lb break="yes"/>with a skill and dexterity that have fre-<lb break="no"/>quently excited my admiration. At the<lb break="yes" />periodical swelling of the rivers, the<lb break="yes"/>fishing is stopped, for it is difficult to<lb break="yes"/>fish in deep river water as in the deep<lb break="yes"/>sea. It is during these intervals, which<lb break="yes"/>last from two to three months, that the<lb break="yes"/>Otomacs are observed to devour an<lb break="yes"/>enormous quantity of earth. We found<lb break="yes" />in their huts considerable stores of these<lb break="yes"/>clay balls, piled up in pyramidal heaps.<lb break="yes"/>An Indian will consume from three-<lb break="maybe"/>quarters of a pound to a pound and a<lb break="yes"/>quarter of this food daily, as we were<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> assured by the intelligent monk, Fray<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="bueno_r">Raymon Bueno</persName>, a native of Madrid,<lb break="yes"/>who had lived among these Indians for<lb break="yes"/>a period of twelve years. According<lb break="yes"/>to the testimony of the Otomacs them-<lb break="no"/>selves, the earth constitutes their main<lb break="yes" />support in the rainy season. In addi-<lb break="no"/>tion, however, they eat, when they can<lb break="yes"/>get them, lizards, several small species<lb break="yes"/>of fish, and the roots of a fern. But<lb break="yes"/>they are so partial to clay, that even in<lb break="yes"/>the dry season, when there is an abun-<lb break="no"/>dance of fish, they still partake of some<lb break="yes" />of their earth-balls, by way of a <hi rendition="#i">bonne<lb break="yes" />bouche</hi> after their regular meals.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These people are of a dark, copper-<lb break="no"/>brown color, have unpleasant, Tartar-<lb break="maybe"/>like features, and are stout, but not<lb break="yes"/>protuberant. The Franciscan, who had<lb break="yes"/>lived amongst them as a missionary,<lb break="yes"/>assured us that he had observed no dif-<lb break="no"/>ference in the condition and well-being<lb break="yes" />of the Otomacs during the period in<lb break="yes"/>which they lived on earth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In all tropical countries, men exhibit<lb break="yes"/>a wonderful and almost irresistible desire<lb break="yes"/>to devour earth&#x2014;unctuous, strong-<lb break="maybe"/>smelling clay. It is often found neces-<lb break="no"/>sary to shut children up, in order to<lb break="yes"/>prevent their running into the open<lb break="yes"/>air to devour earth after recent rain.<lb break="yes" />The Indian women, who are engaged in<lb break="yes"/>the river Magdalena, in the small vil-<lb break="no"/>lage of <placeName key="banco">Banco</placeName>, in turning earthen-ware<lb break="yes"/>pots, continually fill their mouths with<lb break="yes"/>large lumps of clay, as I have frequently<lb break="yes"/>observed, much to my surprise. Wolves<lb break="yes"/>eat earth, especially clay, during the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="54" facs="#f0003"/>
                    <cb/> winter. Individuals of all other tribes<lb break="yes"/>except the Otomacs lose their health, if<lb break="yes"/>they yield to this singular propensity<lb break="yes"/>for eating clay. In the mission of San<lb break="yes"/>Borju, we found the child of an Indian<lb break="yes"/>woman, which, according to the state-<lb break="no"/>ment of its mother, would hardly eat<lb break="yes" />anything but earth. It was, however,<lb break="yes"/>much emaciated, and looked like a mere<lb break="yes"/>skeleton.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In Guinea, the negroes eat a yellow-<lb break="no"/>ish earth, which they call caouac; and<lb break="yes"/>when they are carried as slaves to the<lb break="yes"/>West Indies, they even endeavor to<lb break="yes"/>procure for themselves some similar<lb break="yes"/>species of food, maintaining that the<lb break="yes"/>eating of earth is perfectly harmless<lb break="yes"/>in their <placeName key="afrika">African home</placeName>. The caouac<lb break="yes" />of the <placeName key="amerika">American islands</placeName>, however, de-<lb break="no"/>ranges the health of the slaves who par-<lb break="no"/>take of it; for which reason the eating<lb break="yes"/>of earth was long since forbidden in the<lb break="yes"/>West Indies, notwithstanding which a<lb break="yes"/>species of red or yellowish tuff was se-<lb break="no"/>cretly sold in the public market of Mar-<lb break="no"/>tinique, in the year 1751.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The negroes of Guinea say, that in<lb break="yes"/>their own country they <hi rendition="#i">habitually</hi> eat a<lb break="yes"/>certain earth, the flavor of which is most<lb break="yes"/>agreeable to them, and which does not<lb break="yes"/>occasion them any inconvenience.<lb break="yes"/>Those who have addicted themselves to<lb break="yes"/>the excessive use of caouac are so par-<lb break="no"/>tial to it that no punishment can pre-<lb break="no" />vent them from devouring this earth.<lb break="yes"/>In the island of Java, between Soura-<lb break="no"/>baya and Samarang, <persName key="labillardiere_jjd">Labillardiere</persName> saw<lb break="yes"/>small square reddish cakes publicly sold<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> in the villages. On examining them<lb break="yes"/>more closely, he found that they were<lb break="yes"/>cakes made of a reddish clay, and in-<lb break="no"/>tended for eating. The edible clay of<lb break="yes"/>Samarang has recently, (1847,) been<lb break="yes"/>sent by Mohnike to Berlin, in the shape<lb break="yes"/>of rolled tubes, like cinnamon, and has<lb break="yes" />been examined by Ehrenberg.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The natives of New Caledonia, to<lb break="yes"/>appease their hunger, eat lumps of fria-<lb break="no"/>ble steatite, as large as the fist, in which<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="vauquelin_ln">Vauquelin</persName> detected an appreciable quan-<lb break="no"/>tity of copper. In Papayan, and many<lb break="yes" />parts of Peru, calcareous earth is sold<lb break="yes"/>in the streets, as an article of food for<lb break="yes"/>the Indians. We thus find that the<lb break="yes"/>practice of eating earth is common<lb break="yes"/>throughout the whole of the torrid zone,<lb break="yes"/>among the indolent races, who inhabit<lb break="yes"/>the most beautiful and fruitful regions<lb break="yes"/>of the earth. But accounts have also<lb break="yes"/>come from the north, through Berzelius<lb break="yes"/>and <persName key="retzius_aj" >Retzino</persName>, from which we learn that<lb break="yes"/>in the most remote parts of Sweden,<lb break="yes"/>hundreds of cartloads of earth, contain-<lb break="no"/>ing infusoria, are annually consumed as<lb break="yes"/>breadmeal, more from fancy (like the<lb break="yes"/>smoking of tobacco) than from necessity.<lb break="yes"/>In some parts of Finland, a similar kind<lb break="yes"/>of earth is mixed with the bread. It<lb break="yes" />consists of empty shells of animalcules,<lb break="yes"/>so small and soft that they break be-<lb break="no"/>tween the teeth, without any percepti-<lb break="no"/>ble noise, filling the stomach, without<lb break="yes"/>yielding any actual nourishment. Chron-<lb break="no"/>icles and archives often make mention,<lb break="yes"/>during times of war, of the employment<lb break="yes"/>as food of infusorial earth, which is<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="55" facs="#f0004"/>
                    <cb/> spoken of under the indefinite and gen-<lb break="no"/>eral term of &#x201C;mountain meal.&#x201D; Such,<lb break="yes"/>for instance, was the case in the thirty<lb break="yes"/>years&#x2019; war at Camin, in Pomerania,<lb break="yes"/>Muskan in the Lausiz, and Klecken in<lb break="yes"/>the Dessau territory; and, subsequently,<lb break="yes"/>in 1719 and 1733, at the fortress of<lb break="yes"/>Wittenberg. &#x2014;</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#et">
                            <hi rendition="#i">
                                <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 