<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On the Cinchona Forests in South America</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:46</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">II.57</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1807-Ueber_die_Chinawaelder-3</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1807-Ueber_die_Chinawaelder-1.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1807-Ueber_die_Chinawaelder-2.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1807-Ueber_die_Chinawaelder-3.xml" type="self"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On the Cinchona Forests in South America</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1821</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: Aylmer Bourke Lambert, &lt;i&gt;An Illustration of the Genus Cinchona; Comprising Descriptions of All the Officinal Peruvian Barks, Including Several New Species&lt;/i&gt;, London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, and Brown 1821, S. [19]–59.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Fußnoten mit Asterisken und Kreuzen; Schmuck: Initialen, Kapitälchen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="19" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>ON THE<lb break="yes"/>CINCHONA FORESTS OF SOUTH<lb break="yes"/>AMERICA.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/> BY A. VON HUMBOLDT.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>SECTION I.</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#k">
                            <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>he</hi> present Essay is written with a view to examine the Cin-<lb break="no"/>chona tree as an object of physical or botanical geography.<lb break="yes"/>Amongst the numerous writers mentioning the Cinchona, there<lb break="yes"/>are none but <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName>, <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>, <persName key="pavon_j" >Pavon</persName>, and Zea, who them-<lb break="no"/>selves have observed this beneficial tree upon the South Ameri-<lb break="no"/>can continent. Only the first of these gives a physical descrip-<lb break="no" />tion of this plant; the others, as well as <persName key="jacquin_njfv" >Jacquin</persName> and <persName key="swarz_01">Swartz</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>who saw the Cinchon&#x00E6; in the West-India Islands, and <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName> and<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="lambert_ab">Lambert</persName>, who occupied themselves with dried specimens, have<lb break="yes"/>merely treated on the natural history and the botanical diagno-<lb break="no"/>sis. During my stay of four years in <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>, I had<lb break="yes"/>occasion to reside a long time in countries where the Cinchona<lb break="yes"/>trees are indigenous. M. <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName> and myself have observed<lb break="yes"/>them north and south of the <placeName key="aequator" >equator</placeName>, in the kingdom of New<lb break="yes"/>Granada, betwixt Honda and Santa Fe de Bogota, in the pro-<lb break="no"/>vince of Popayan, in the corregiment of Loxa, on the Ama-<lb break="no"/>zon river, in the province of Jaen de Bracamoros; and in the<lb break="yes"/>northerly part of Peru. During our abode in the house of<lb break="yes"/>Don <persName key="mutis_jc">Jose Celestino Mutis</persName>, in Santa Fe, the botanical treasures<lb break="yes"/>of that great natural philosopher were opened to us. In Spain,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="20" facs="#f0002"/> also, we were enabled to collect, from the editor of the <hi rendition="#i">Flora<lb break="yes"/>Peruviana,</hi> in Guayaquil, (the harbour of Quito on the coast<lb break="yes"/>of the South Sea) from M. <persName key="tafalla_jj">Tafalla</persName>, a pupil of <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>, in the little<lb break="yes"/>town of Loxa, from Don <persName key="olmedo_v">Vincente Olmedo</persName>, royal inspector of<lb break="yes"/>the Cinchona forests, many interesting accounts respecting objects<lb break="yes"/>which, but for the obliging communications from those friends,<lb break="yes" />would have remained unknown to us. Respecting the very violent<lb break="yes"/>controversy on the question, whether the orange-coloured Cin-<lb break="no"/>chona bark of New Granada, or the Peruvian <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona nitida,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>described by <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito" >Ruiz</persName> and <persName key="pavon_j">Pavon</persName>, be identical with the genuine Cin-<lb break="no"/>chona of Uritusinga, famed already since 1638, he only can decide<lb break="yes"/>who has himself explored the regions producing these three plants.<lb break="yes"/>But of the contending parties, neither <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, Zea, nor <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName> and<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="pavon_j">Pavon</persName>, have ever set their feet in the corregiment of Loxa.<lb break="yes"/>Thence it is, that each party has, with equal want of foundation,<lb break="yes"/>asserted that the most efficacious Cinchona bark of their re-<lb break="no"/>spective districts was the genuine one from Uristusinga. In the<lb break="yes"/>second fasciculus of our &#x00C6;quinoctial Plants<note place="foot" n="*">Plantes &#x00C6;quinoctiales, par Messrs. <persName key="bonpland_ajag" >Bonpland</persName> et <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName>, Troisieme livraison, p. 39.</note> we have shown, that<lb break="yes"/>this latter, the <hi rendition="#i">Cascarilla fina de Loxa,</hi> is entirely different from<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona lancifolia</hi> of <persName key="mutis_jc" >Mutis</persName>, and from all those Peruvian<lb break="yes"/>Cinchona barks described in <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito" >Ruiz&#x2019;s</persName>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Quinologia,</hi> in the <hi rendition="#i">Flora<lb break="yes"/>Peruviana,</hi> and in the recent <hi rendition="#i" >Supplement</hi> to the <hi rendition="#i">Quinologia.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>Averse as we are from entering into competition with the above-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>named excellent botanists, yet the accidental advantage has fallen<lb break="yes"/>to our lot, of having ourselves seen the Cinchona forests near<lb break="yes"/>Santa Fe, as also those of Loxa. In fact, for the last sixty years,<lb break="yes"/>since the time of <persName key="jussieu_jd">Joseph de Jussieu</persName>, whose observations were<lb break="yes"/>moreover never published, no travelling naturalist has preceded<lb break="yes"/>us in visiting the beautiful mountain plains of Loxa. Favoured<lb break="yes"/>by these circumstances, I think myself enabled to speak with<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="21" facs="#f0003"/> some confidence on so difficult a subject, which, by a variety of<lb break="yes"/>controversies, has become more and more perplexed.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It would be superfluous to repeat the fictions concerning the<lb break="yes" />history of the discovery of the medicinal powers of the Cinchona<lb break="yes"/>bark. Some say a patient had drank out of a lake the waters<lb break="yes"/>of which had acquired a bitter taste from Cinchona trunks which<lb break="yes"/>had lain in them; others, that a lion had cured himself of the<lb break="yes"/>ague by chewing Cinchona bark, and had thus directed the at-<lb break="no"/>tention of the Indians to this tree. <persName key="lambert_ab">Lambert</persName>, in his <hi rendition="#i">Mono-<lb break="no"/>graph of Cinchona,</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="*">A Description of the Genus Cinchona, 1792, p. 39.</note> has collected all these opinions. That<lb break="yes" />animals have taught men, is a very common form of the traditions<lb break="yes"/>of nations. The valuable antidote <hi rendition="#i">Vijuco del guaco,</hi> a plant de-<lb break="no"/>scribed by <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, which is related to the <hi rendition="#i">Mikania,</hi> and has been<lb break="yes"/>erroneously confounded with the <hi rendition="#i">Ayapana</hi> of Brazil, is also said<lb break="yes"/>to have attracted the notice of the Indians (as is affirmed of the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Falco serpentarius)</hi> by the <hi rendition="#i">Falco guaco</hi> of New Granada fighting<lb break="yes"/>with serpents. However, that the great American lion without<lb break="yes"/>mane, <hi rendition="#i">Felis concolor,</hi> should be subject to the ague, is just as<lb break="yes"/>bold an hypothesis as the assertion of the inhabitants of the<lb break="yes"/>pestilential valley Gualla Bamba,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Near to the town of Quito.</note> that even the vultures <hi rendition="#i">(Vul-<lb break="no"/>tur aura)</hi> in their neighbourhood were subject to that disorder.<lb break="yes"/>Indeed, in the regions of the Cinchona forests there is not even<lb break="yes"/>a <hi rendition="#i">Felis concolor</hi> so fond of warmth to be found; but at the most<lb break="yes"/>the cat <hi rendition="#i">Puma,</hi> not yet properly described, (<persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine&#x2019;s</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Petit lion du volcan de Pinchincha,</hi> which I should be inclined<lb break="yes"/>to call <hi rendition="#i">Felis andicola,)</hi> and which we have met with in heights<lb break="yes"/>of 2,500 toises.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The story, so often copied, respecting the <persName key="chinchon_01" >Countess Chinchon</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>vice-queen of Peru, is probably still more doubtful than it is<lb break="yes"/>generally supposed to be. There certainly was a Count Chin-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="22" facs="#f0004"/> chon, Don <persName key="fernandezdecabreraybobadilla_lj">Geronimo Fernandez de Cabrera Bobadella y Mendoza</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>who was Viceroy in Lima from 1629 to 1639. It is very pro-<lb break="no"/>bable that his wife, after her return to Spain in 1640, was the<lb break="yes"/>first who introduced the Cinchona bark into Europe. The name<lb break="yes"/>of <hi rendition="#i">Pulvis Comitiss&#x00E6;</hi> appears even more ancient than that of<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Pulvis Jesuiticus</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">Pulvis Patrum.</hi> But I do not believe (and<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="olmedo_v">Olmedo</persName> in Loxa is of the same opinion with me) that the<lb break="yes"/>corregidor of Loxa, Don <persName key="cannizares_jld">Juan Lopez de Cannizares</persName>,<note place="foot" n="*">Flora Peruviana, tom. ii. p. 2.</note> who<lb break="yes"/>is said to have cured the Countess of the ague, received this re-<lb break="no"/>medy from the Indians. In Loxa there is no tradition whatever<lb break="yes"/>of this kind; nor is it probable that the discovery of the medi-<lb break="no"/>cinal power of the Cinchona belongs to the primitive nations<lb break="yes"/>of <placeName key="amerika" >America</placeName>, if it is considered that these nations (like the Hin-<lb break="no"/>doos) adhere with unalterable pertinacity to their customs, to<lb break="yes"/>their food, and to their nostrums, and that, notwithstanding all<lb break="yes"/>this, the use of the Cinchona bark is entirely unknown to them<lb break="yes"/>in Loxa, Guancabamba, and far around. In the deep and hot<lb break="yes"/>valleys of the mountains of Catamago, Rio Calvas, and Macara,<lb break="yes"/>agues are extremely common. But the natives there, as well<lb break="yes"/>as in Loxa, of whatever cast, would die rather than have re-<lb break="no"/>course to Cinchona bark, which, together with opiates, they<lb break="yes"/>place in the class of poisons exciting mortification. The Indians<lb break="yes" />cure themselves by lemonades, by the oleaginous aromatic peel of<lb break="yes"/>the small green wild lemon, by infusions of <hi rendition="#i">Scoparia dulcis,</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>by strong coffee.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Among the Indians on the Orinoco, particularly in <placeName key="atures">Atures</placeName> and Maypura, we have found<lb break="yes"/>an excellent febrifuge, the <hi rendition="#i">frutta de Burro,</hi> the fruit of a new species of <hi rendition="#i">Uvaria,</hi> which we<lb break="yes"/>have described by the name of <hi rendition="#i">Uvaria febrifuga.</hi>
                        </note> In Malacatis only, where many bark-peelers<lb break="yes"/>live, they begin to put confidence in the Cinchona bark. In<lb break="yes"/>Loxa there is no document to be found which can elucidate the<lb break="yes" />history of the discovery of the Cinchona: an old tradition, how-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="23" facs="#f0005"/> ever, is current there, that the Jesuits at the felling of the wood had<lb break="yes"/>distinguished, according to the custom of the country, the dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent kinds of trees by chewing their barks, and that on such occa-<lb break="no"/>sions they had taken notice of the considerable bitterness of the<lb break="yes"/>Cinchona. There being always medical practitioners among the<lb break="yes" />Missionaries, it is said they had tried an infusion of the Cinchona<lb break="yes"/>in the tertian ague, a complaint which is very common in that<lb break="yes"/>part of the country. This tradition is less improbable than the asser-<lb break="no"/>tion of European authors, and among them the late writers <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito" >Ruiz</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>and <persName key="pavon_j">Pavon</persName>, who ascribe the discovery to the Indians. The medi-<lb break="no"/>cinal powers of the Cinchona was likewise entirely unknown<lb break="yes"/>to the inhabitants of the kingdom of New Granada.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A century elapsed before any botanical description was ob-<lb break="no" />tained of the tree whose pulverized bark yielded the Jesuit&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>Powder. The astronomer <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName>, who ranged with in-<lb break="no"/>describable vivacity through all departments of human know-<lb break="no"/>ledge, and by whom there are several neat botanical drawings<lb break="yes"/>in the collection of <persName key="jussieu_ald">Jussieu</persName> in Paris, was the first man of science<lb break="yes"/>who examined and described the Cinchona tree. In the year<lb break="yes"/>1737<note place="foot" n="*" >Voyage à l&#x2019;<placeName key="aequator">Equateur</placeName>, p. 31, 75, 186, and 203.</note> he travelled through Loxa to Lima, and his description<lb break="yes"/>of the Cinchona appeared in 1738 in the <hi rendition="#i">Mem. de l&#x2019;Academie.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>Afterwards, in the year 1739, <persName key="jussieu_jd" >Joseph de Jussieu</persName> explored the<lb break="yes"/>country in the vicinity of Loxa. There, and in the neighbour-<lb break="no"/>hood of Zaruma, he gathered a great number of specimens, which<lb break="yes"/>are still to be found in <persName key="jussieu">Jussieu&#x2019;s</persName> collection at Paris, and which<lb break="yes"/>we have compared with our own, collected sixty years later on<lb break="yes"/>the same spot. Amongst these was the <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona pubescens,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>which <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName> has described as new, but which, as we shall<lb break="yes"/>subsequently prove, is the first <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona officinalis</hi> of <persName key="linne_cv">Linné&#x2019;s</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Systema Natur&#x00E6;</hi> (12th edition). In the year 1743 <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Con-<lb break="no"/>
                            <pb n="24" facs="#f0006"/> damine</persName> was a second time in Loxa, from whence he travelled,<lb break="yes"/>as we did in the year 1802, to Tomepinda and the <placeName key="amazonas">Amazon river</placeName>.<lb break="yes"/>At that time the first and (what is singular enough) the last<lb break="yes"/>attempt was made to bring young Cinchona trees alive to Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope. After the astronomer had carefully nursed them for eight<lb break="yes"/>months during a passage of 1200 leagues, they were swallowed<lb break="yes"/>up by a wave, which washed over the boat, near Cape Orange,<lb break="yes"/>north of Para.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Botanists for a long time were acquainted with only one spe-<lb break="no" />cies of Cinchona, which <persName key="linne_cv">Linn&#x00E6;us</persName> called <hi rendition="#i">officinalis,</hi> and in the<lb break="yes" />description of which, he united, without knowing it, our <hi rendition="#i">C.<lb break="yes"/>
                            <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condaminea</persName>
                        </hi> and <hi rendition="#i">C. cordifolia</hi>
                        <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>; for the specimen sent him<lb break="yes"/>from Santa Fe was yellow Cinchona, and totally different from<lb break="yes"/>that drawn, though imperfectly, by <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName>. At last <persName key="jacquin_njfv">Jac-<lb break="no"/>quin&#x2019;s</persName> voyage made us acquainted with another species, viz. the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. carib&#x00E6;a.</hi> The West India Islands, the South Seas, even the<lb break="yes"/>East Indies, offered from time to time more species of Cinchona<lb break="yes"/>to the traveller, but the most efficacious and the most remark-<lb break="no"/>able ones of the continent of <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName> remained longest<lb break="yes"/>unnoticed.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>From 1638 to 1776 no other Cinchona bark was met with in com-<lb break="no" />merce, except that of the corregiment of Loxa and its neigh-<lb break="no" />bourhood. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName> makes mention of the bark from<lb break="yes"/>Riobamba and Cuenca in the province of Quito, as also of that<lb break="yes"/>from <placeName key="ayabaca" >Ayavanca</placeName> and Jaen de Bracamoros. But the bark from<lb break="yes"/>the interior of Peru (around Huanuca, and in the province La<lb break="yes"/>Paz) or even the bark from the kingdom of New Granada was<lb break="yes"/>entirely unknown to him.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>They did not suppose it possible for Cinchona trees to exist<lb break="yes" />north of the <placeName key="aequator">Equator</placeName>, and consequently in our hemisphere, till<lb break="yes"/>a fortunate accident led a man, who had a long time lived in<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="25" facs="#f0007"/> Loxa, in some department connected with the peeling of<lb break="yes"/>barks, on his return to Spain, across Popayan to Santa Fe<lb break="yes"/>de Bogota. This observing traveller was the upper Mint Di-<lb break="no"/>rector <hi rendition="#i">(Superintendente general de moneda de Santa Fe)</hi> Don<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="santiesteban_md">Miguel de Santistevan</persName>, who, without any botanical knowledge,<lb break="yes"/>discovered physiognomically, that is to say, by mere habitus,<lb break="yes"/>the Cinchona trees from Loxa up to 2<formula notation="TeX" >\frac{1}{2}</formula>° N. lat. In a memo-<lb break="no"/>rial concerning the royal administration of the whole trade of<lb break="yes" />Cinchona bark <hi rendition="#i">(Estanco de Cascarilla)</hi> which in 1753 he ad-<lb break="no"/>dressed to the viceroy <persName key="pizarro_ja" >Marquis de Villar</persName>, he expressly says that<lb break="yes"/>he had found Cinchona trees not only betwixt Loxa and Quito,<lb break="yes" />for instance, easterly from Cuenca near the villages Paute and<lb break="yes"/>Gualasco, westerly from Riobamba on the declivity of the Chim-<lb break="no"/>borazo near <placeName key="angas" >Angas</placeName>, and on the Cuesta de S. Antonio, but also<lb break="yes"/>betwixt Quito and Santa Fe in all situations, where the ground is<lb break="yes"/>of an equal height with Loxa, consequently 800 toises above the<lb break="yes"/>level of the sea. The estimate of the height according to modern<lb break="yes"/>measurements, and even according to the earlier ones of <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Con-<lb break="no" />damine</persName>,<note place="foot" n="*">Voyage de la Rivière de <placeName key="amazonas">l&#x2019;Amazone</placeName>, p. 25.</note> is certainly too low by at least 250 toises; but the acute<lb break="yes"/>observation, respecting the mean height in which the Cinchona<lb break="yes"/>trees are always met with on the mountainous declivity, is the<lb break="yes"/>more striking, since even learned philosophers at that time paid<lb break="yes"/>attention to the geography of plants, or to the height of their<lb break="yes"/>situation. It is also to be observed, that although M. <persName key="santiesteban_md">Santis-<lb break="no"/>tevan</persName>, according to the manuscript accounts which I procured of<lb break="yes"/>him, speaks generally of Cinchona trees betwixt Quito and Santa<lb break="yes"/>Fe, yet we can perceive from his enumeration of particular places,<lb break="yes"/>that he discovered this precious produce only in the valley of<lb break="yes"/>Rio Tuanamba north of Pasto, in the forests of Beruccos, and in<lb break="yes"/>the vicinity of Popayan, near Guanacas, the dangerous pass of<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="26" facs="#f0008"/> the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>, betwixt the village of this name and the Sitia de<lb break="yes"/>los Corrales.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Such was the state of the discovery of Cinchona north of the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <placeName key="aequator">equator</placeName> until the year 1772. All the Cinchona bark of com-<lb break="no"/>merce was from Loxa, Gauancabamba, and Jaen, perhaps even<lb break="yes"/>from Riobamba and Cuenza. The whole was shipped at the<lb break="yes"/>ports of the Pacific. No advantage was derived from the im-<lb break="no"/>portant discovery in the provinces of Pasto and Popayan. In<lb break="yes"/>the year 1772 Don <persName key="mutis_jc">Jose Celestino Mutis</persName> discovered the Cinchona<lb break="yes"/>about Santa Fe, and since this epoch Europe received Cinchona<lb break="yes"/>bark which did not double Cape Horn, and which came by way<lb break="yes"/>of Carthagena de Indias to Cadiz.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> had resided already twelve years in the kingdom of<lb break="yes"/>New Granada. He had travelled twice through the forests be-<lb break="no"/>tween Guaduas and Santa Fe, where the Cinchona tree is surround-<lb break="no"/>ed by the beautiful Granada oaks. If we consider the diversity of<lb break="yes"/>plants which engage the attention of the botanist in these coun-<lb break="no"/>tries; if we reflect that in the tropics the height of the trunks<lb break="yes"/>withdraws from our eyes both leaves and blossoms; we shall be<lb break="yes"/>the less surprised that M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> discovered the Cinchona only in<lb break="yes"/>1772, when he found it in blossom. This excellent explorer of<lb break="yes"/>nature, who is a native of Cadiz, studied three years in Madrid,<lb break="yes"/>and was induced by a love of botany to accompany the vice-<lb break="no"/>roy Don <persName key="cerda_pmdl">Pedro Misia de la Cerda</persName>, as his physician, to Santa<lb break="yes"/>Fe. He lived a long time in the districts of Pampelona and<lb break="yes"/>de la Montuosa, a name which, to the greatest dissatisfaction<lb break="yes"/>of M. <persName key="mutis_jc" >Mutis</persName>, <persName key="linne_cv">Linn&#x00E6;us</persName> has construed into Mexico; so that<lb break="yes"/>this Swedish botanist has quoted all the New Granada spe-<lb break="no"/>cimens which he received from la Montuosa, as Mexican ones.<note place="foot" n="*">For instance, <hi rendition="#i">Mannettia reclinata.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <lb break="yes"/>This error is the more singular, since <persName key="linne_cv">Linn&#x00E6;us</persName>, who correspond-<lb break="no" />ed with <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> always by way of Carthagena de Indias, must have<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="27" facs="#f0009"/> perceived that he never resided in Mexico. The absence of<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> in the mines north of Santa Fe had kept him far<lb break="yes"/>from the Cinchona forests of Mave, Gascas, and the <placeName key="aseradero" >Aseradero</placeName>.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, in a report to the viceroy Don <persName key="flores_ma">Manuel Antonio Florez</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>alleges as a ground of the later discovery of the Cinchona, that<lb break="yes"/>up to 1772 he had directed all his botanical excursions out of<lb break="yes"/>the limits of the first 5 degrees of N. lat., which he held to be the<lb break="yes"/>exclusive country of the Cinchona in the northern hemisphere.<lb break="yes"/>This great naturalist did not at that time suspect, that soon after-<lb break="no"/>wards the Cinchona tree would be found to exist even at the<lb break="yes"/>mouth of the Rio Opon, and as far as Santa Martha, conse-<lb break="no"/>quently in the 10th degree of N. lat.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> had procured the first dried specimens of the yellow<lb break="yes"/>Cinchona of Loxa <hi rendition="#i" >(C. cordifolia)</hi> from M. <persName key="santiesteban_md" >Santistevan</persName>, director<lb break="yes"/>of the Mint. According to these, the genus <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona</hi> was es-<lb break="no" />tablished in such manner as he communicated it to <persName key="linne_cv" >Linn&#x00E6;us</persName>.<lb break="yes"/>In the year 1772, when M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, in company with his friend<lb break="yes"/>Don Pedro <persName key="ugarte_p">Ugarte</persName>, rode through the forest of Tena, not far from<lb break="yes"/>the mountainous declivity of Santa Fe, he discovered Cinchona<lb break="yes"/>trees. A year afterwards he also found them betwixt Honda<lb break="yes"/>and Guaduas; and presented to the viceroy Don <persName key="guirior_md">Manuel de<lb break="yes"/>Guirior</persName>, who had just embarked on the Magdalen river, a flower-<lb break="no"/>ing branch of Cinchona, as a newly-discovered valuable pro-<lb break="no"/>duct of that country, which nature had also enriched with aro-<lb break="no"/>matic Nutmegs <hi rendition="#i">(Myristica Otoba),</hi> with an excellent Cinnamon<lb break="yes"/>tree <hi rendition="#i">(Laurus cinnamomoides</hi> Mut.) with aromatic <hi rendition="#i">Puchery</hi> or<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Todaspuie (Laurus</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="*">The <hi rendition="#i">Laurus Putseri</hi> of <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> is the same as the <hi rendition="#i">Laurus Pucheri</hi> of <hi rendition="#i">Fl. Peruviana,</hi> vol. iv.<lb break="yes"/>t. 352. ined. The number of species of this genus figured in the fourth vol. ined. of the <hi rendition="#i">Flora<lb break="yes"/>Peruviana,</hi> amounts to thirty. The fruit of the <hi rendition="#i">Laurus Pucheri</hi> is frequently sold in the Lon-<lb break="no"/>don shops under the name of Sassafras nuts. <hi rendition="#i">Caryocar amygdaliferum, Fl. Peruv.</hi> vol. v. ined.<lb break="yes"/>t. 470. <hi rendition="#i" >Myrospermum balsamiferum, Fl. Peruv.</hi> 4, ined. t. 373.</note>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Putseri</hi> Mut.), with Almonds <hi rendition="#i" >(Caryocar<lb break="yes"/>amygdaliferum</hi> Mut.), with four kinds of Styrax, with the Bal-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="28" facs="#f0010"/> sam of Tolu <hi rendition="#i">(Toluifera</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="*">
                            <hi rendition="#i">Myrospermum balsamiferum.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <hi rendition="#i">indica),</hi> with a Tea tree <hi rendition="#i" >(Alstonia<lb break="yes"/>the&#x00E6;formis</hi> Mut.), with Ipecacuanha <hi rendition="#i">(Psychotria emetica</hi> Mut.),<lb break="yes"/>with Wax-palms <hi rendition="#i">(Ceroxylon andicola</hi>
                        <persName key="humboldt_av">Humb.</persName>), with Carannia<lb break="yes" />gum <hi rendition="#i">(&#x00C6;ginetia cannifera</hi> Mut.), with Winter&#x2019;s bark <hi rendition="#i">(<persName key="wynter_w" >Wintera</persName>
                            <lb break="yes"/>granadensis),</hi> with <hi rendition="#i">Quassia simarouba,</hi> and with the valuable<lb break="yes"/>dyeing woods.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>In the history of sciences, it often happens that the person<lb break="yes" />who knows how to diffuse, with a certain degree of boldness,<lb break="yes"/>the discovery of another, passes for the discoverer himself, in-<lb break="no"/>stead of him who made that discovery. M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, a man of a li-<lb break="no" />beral and enlightened mind, asked no reward from the Go-<lb break="no" />vernment. He occupied himself without ostentation in botani-<lb break="no" />cal examinations of the kinds of Cinchona which he discovered,<lb break="yes"/>and in the application of their barks through an extensive me-<lb break="no"/>dical practice. In the year 1783 only, he obtained a royal sa-<lb break="no"/>lary, when the botanical expedition of Santa Fe was organized<lb break="yes"/>by M. <persName key="caballeroygongora_a" >Gongora</persName>, who was both archbishop and viceroy.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>In the year 1776, four years after M. <persName key="mutis_jc" >Mutis&#x2019;s</persName> discovery, Don<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="lopezruiz_sj">Sebastian Jose Lopez Ruiz</persName>, a cunning and petulant physician<lb break="yes"/>at Santa Fe, a native of Ganama, found means to persuade<lb break="yes"/>the Spanish Government that he had first discovered Cinchona<lb break="yes"/>trees in New Granada. He sent samples of the new Cinchona<lb break="yes"/>to Madrid, spoke a great deal of the importance of this new<lb break="yes"/>article of commerce, and obtained a yearly pension of 2000 pias-<lb break="no"/>tres for his reward. From records which M. <persName key="lopezruiz_sj">Lopez</persName> remitted to<lb break="yes"/>me in the year 1802, by his brother, a canon in Quito, in order<lb break="yes"/>to prove to me the priority of his discovery, I have found that<lb break="yes"/>he knew the Cinchona about Honda only in the year 1774, and<lb break="yes"/>that he made the first medicinal experiment with it in the year<lb break="yes"/>1775. M. <persName key="lopezruiz_sj">Lopez</persName> did not long enjoy his full salary. The vice-<lb break="no"/>roy <persName key="caballeroygongora_a" >Gongora</persName>, who besides esteemed M. <persName key="mutis_jc" >Mutis</persName> greatly, and his<lb break="yes"/>first secretary Don <persName key="alonzo_c">Zenon de Alonzo</persName>, who was a zealous pro-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="29" facs="#f0011"/> moter of the sciences, represented to the Court, that M. <persName key="lopezruiz_sj">Lopez</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>was not the first discoverer of the New Granada Cinchona bark.<lb break="yes"/>They immediately withdrew one half of the royal pension, or-<lb break="no"/>dered M. <persName key="lopezruiz_sj" >Lopez</persName> to travel to the Darien, where it was also pre-<lb break="no"/>tended that Cinchona had been discovered; and as he refused to<lb break="yes"/>undertake a journey to such a pestilential climate, the viceroy dis-<lb break="no"/>continued the other half of his salary. Since this epoch a violent<lb break="yes"/>dispute has arisen respecting the priority of the discovery. <persName key="lopezruiz_sj">Lopez</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>made a voyage to Europe, and again contrived to procure for<lb break="yes"/>himself a salary of 1000 piastres. He ingratiated himself with<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="mutis_jc" >Mutis&#x2019;s</persName> botanical opponents, and these have mentioned him<lb break="yes"/>frequently since as co-discoverer. It is still more remarkable,<lb break="yes"/>that Colonel Don <persName key="torreymiranda_adl">Antonio de la Torre Miranda</persName> wishes to prove,<lb break="yes"/>in his Topography of the province of Carthagena, (<hi rendition="#i">Noticia indi-<lb break="no"/>vidual de los Poblaciones nuevas fundadas en la Provincia de<lb break="yes" />Carthagena,</hi>) by means of testimonies, that to him belongs the<lb break="yes"/>honour of discovering the Cinchona bark in New Granada, be-<lb break="no"/>cause in the year 1783 (consequently eleven years after M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mu-<lb break="no"/>tis</persName>) he had discovered it near Fusagasuga. M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> had be-<lb break="no"/>gun, in Mariquita, a plantation of Cinchona and of Cinnamon<note place="foot" n="*">
                            <hi rendition="#i">Laurus cinnamomoides,</hi>
                            <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>.&#x2014;Edit.</note>
                        <lb break="yes"/>of the Andaquia Missions, the remains of which we also saw.<lb break="yes"/>In the year 1800 the Spanish Government commissioned a French<lb break="yes"/>physician, M. <persName key="derieux_l">Louis Derieux</persName>, to continue these plantations; to cul-<lb break="no"/>tivate the indigenous <hi rendition="#i" >Myristica,</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">
                            <hi rendition="#i">Myristica otoba,</hi>
                            <persName key="humboldt_av">Humb.</persName> et <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpl.</persName> Plant&#x00E6; &#x00C6;quin. 2. p. 78. tab. 103.&#x2014;Edit.</note>and to superintend generally<lb break="yes"/>the packing of the Cinchona bark in New Granada. He received a<lb break="yes"/>salary of 2000 piastres, with the title of <hi rendition="#i">Commissionado y Encar-<lb break="no"/>gada de Investigaciones de Historia Natural en el Nuevo Reyno<lb break="yes"/>de Granada.</hi> He possessed as little botanical knowledge as<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="lopezruiz_sj">Lopez</persName>, but was a man of strong mind and intellectual capa-<lb break="no"/>city. He had long before lived in Santa Fe, from whence he<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="30" facs="#f0012"/> was dragged in chains to Carthagena, and thence to a prison in<lb break="yes"/>Cadiz, under the false accusation of revolutionary principles.<lb break="yes"/>After his innocence had been acknowledged, the Minister of State<lb break="yes"/>Don <persName key="urquijo_mld">Mariano de Urquijo</persName> conferred on him the superintendance<lb break="yes"/>of the Cinchona forests. I travelled with him upon the Magdalen<lb break="yes"/>River, during which time his amiable son made several drawings<lb break="yes"/>of plants for me. The father stepped forth betwixt M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>and M. <persName key="lopezruiz_sj">Lopez</persName>. As the specific characters of the species of Cin-<lb break="no"/>chona excited the bitterest disputes between Zea, <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito" >Ruiz</persName>, and<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="pavon_j">Pavon</persName>, at Madrid, so the Cinchona bark, ever since its first<lb break="yes"/>discovery, has been an odious object of persecution in Santa Fe.<lb break="yes"/>I have learned with great regret, that soon after I left <placeName key="suedamerika">South<lb break="yes" />America</placeName>, M. <persName key="derieux_l">Derieux</persName> had lost his salary, and had even been<lb break="yes"/>compelled to leave the vice-royalty, so that the Cinchona trees<lb break="yes"/>again grow without any superintendance, which, indeed, has<lb break="yes"/>hitherto not promoted their increase or preservation.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>In this simple historical narrative we have shown, that till<lb break="yes" />the year 1772 all Cinchona bark was collected in the forests of<lb break="yes"/>Loxa, <placeName key="ayabaca">Ayavaca</placeName>, and Jaen de Bracamoros, consequently between<lb break="yes"/>the 3rd and 5th degrees of south latitude, and that only<lb break="yes"/>from the year 1772 the medicinal Cinchon&#x00E6; on the <placeName key="suedamerika">South<lb break="yes"/>American</placeName> continent became used in the northern hemisphere;<lb break="yes"/>which species of Cinchona were discovered between the 4th and 5th<lb break="yes"/>degrees of south latitude. Until then, none were known in Peru<lb break="yes"/>Proper, especially in the mountains situated nearer to Lima, the<lb break="yes" />capital. The vale of Rio Calvas, and the village <placeName key="ayabaca" >Ayavaca</placeName>, in<lb break="yes"/>whose neighbourhood the <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona <persName key="lacondamine_cmd" >Condaminea</persName>
                        </hi> grows, famed<lb break="yes"/>since the year 1738, belong indeed in a political respect to<lb break="yes"/>Peru, but both are situated close to the confines of the corregi-<lb break="no"/>ment of Loxa; and the bark of <placeName key="ayabaca">Ayavaca</placeName>, like that of Jaen, was<lb break="yes"/>sold by the name of <hi rendition="#i">Cascarilla fina de Uritusinga,</hi> as well as<lb break="yes"/>that which was shipped in Payta.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="31" facs="#f0013"/>
                    <p>It was only in 1776 that the real commerce in Peruvian Cin-<lb break="no" />chona bark began. Don <persName key="renquifo_f">Francisco Renquifo</persName> discovered near<lb break="yes"/>Huanuco, on the mountain San Christo val de Cuchero, the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. nitida</hi> of <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito" >Ruiz</persName>, a species very nearly related to the orange-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>coloured one of <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> (<hi rendition="#i">Cinchona lancifolia</hi>). An enterprising<lb break="yes"/>man, Don <persName key="alcarraz_e">Emanuel Alcarraz</persName>, brought the first sample of it to<lb break="yes" />Lima, and turned the use of it to advantage. The editors of<lb break="yes" />the <hi rendition="#i">Flora Peruviana</hi> did certainly not penetrate, in 1779, as far<lb break="yes"/>as the <placeName key="amazonas">Amazon River</placeName> itself, but only to those rivers which flow<lb break="yes"/>immediately into it. They visited the beautiful valleys of Thar-<lb break="no"/>ma, Xauxa, and Huamalies, and in 1779 determined the bota-<lb break="no"/>nical characters of the North Peruvian species. This was con-<lb break="no"/>sequently seven years after M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> began his labours on the<lb break="yes" />Cinchon&#x00E6; of New Granada. Shortly afterwards, medicinal<lb break="yes"/>Cinchona bark was discovered at almost one and the same<lb break="yes"/>time in the most northern and in the most southern part of <placeName key="suedamerika">South<lb break="yes"/>America</placeName>, in the mountains of Santa Martha, and in the king-<lb break="no"/>dom of Buenosayres, near La Paz and Cochabamba, where a<lb break="yes"/>naval officer, <persName key="celis_rd">Rubin de Celis</persName>, and the German botanist <persName key="haenke_t">Tadd&#x00E6;us<lb break="yes" />Haenke</persName>, drew the attention of the inhabitants to this valuable<lb break="yes"/>produce.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>After the year 1780, therefore, Europe was superabundantly<lb break="yes" />supplied from the ports of Payta, Guayaquil, Lima, Buenosayres,<lb break="yes"/>Carthagena, and Santa Martha, with Barks of various medicinal<lb break="yes"/>powers. Of these barks, some went direct to Spain, and some<lb break="yes"/>were transmitted by the smuggling trade to <placeName key="nordamerika">North America</placeName> and<lb break="yes"/>England. West-Indian Cinchona barks were also occasionally<lb break="yes"/>mixed with those of the continent. They gave the name of Cin-<lb break="no"/>chona to barks which indeed possess great febrifuge powers, but<lb break="yes"/>which are derived from trees which do not even belong to the genus<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona.</hi> Thus they spoke in Cadiz of <hi rendition="#i">Cascarilla</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">Quina de</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="32" facs="#f0014"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Cumana</hi> and of <hi rendition="#i">Quina de la <placeName key="angostura">Angostura</placeName>.</hi> They divided all bark<lb break="yes"/>into genuine and into spurious, without considering, that, al-<lb break="no"/>though true Cinchona barks possess equal medicinal power, yet<lb break="yes"/>that they are capable of displaying specific differences in the<lb break="yes"/>manner of their efficacy. They asked for bark like that of Loxa,<lb break="yes"/>without considering that three or four kinds of Cinchona bark<lb break="yes"/>had ever since 1738 come from Loxa itself to Europe, which were<lb break="yes" />the produce of quite different species of Cinchona. They for-<lb break="no"/>got that the quality of the bark did not depend merely on its<lb break="yes"/>being from the <hi rendition="#i">C. lancifolia</hi> or from <hi rendition="#i">C. macrocarpa,</hi> but that<lb break="yes" />locality of growth, the age of the tree, quick or slow drying,<lb break="yes"/>determine its efficacy. They mistook the same species, if the<lb break="yes"/>bark was, instead of <hi rendition="#i">canutillos, i. e.</hi> in thin quills, in thick <hi rendition="#i">cor-<lb break="no"/>tizones,</hi> or even powdered. They mixed, sometimes through mis-<lb break="no"/>take, sometimes intentionally, the bark of <hi rendition="#i">
                            <persName key="wynter_w">Wintera</persName> granadensis</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>and of the tanning <hi rendition="#i">Weinmannias,</hi> with the Cinchona bark, and<lb break="yes"/>even stained them with an infusion of Brazil wood.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>These circumstances gave rise to very singular prejudices<lb break="yes"/>in judging of Cinchona bark. Certain mercantile houses in<lb break="yes" />Spain, which half a century since were in possession of the<lb break="yes" />exclusive trade in Cinchona bark, endeavoured to throw disrepute<lb break="yes"/>on that from New Granada and southern Peru. They found com-<lb break="no"/>plaisant botanists, who, by boldly exalting varieties to species,<lb break="yes"/>proved that all Peruvian Cinchon&#x00E6; were specifically different from<lb break="yes"/>those which grow about Santa Fe. Physicians, like the Popes,<lb break="yes"/>drew lines of demarcation on the map. They insisted, that be-<lb break="no"/>yond a certain degree of latitude in the northern hemisphere no<lb break="yes" />efficacious Cinchona could grow. But as the commerce with<lb break="yes" />Cinchona bark from Huamalies and Huanuco, which <persName key="gomezortega_c">Ortega</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>, <persName key="pavon_j" >Pavon</persName>, and <persName key="tafalla_jj">Tafalla</persName> recommended, soon fell into the hands<lb break="yes"/>of those who had formerly carried on the South Sea trade in the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="33" facs="#f0015"/> Cinchona bark of Loxa, the new Peruvian Cinchona barks na-<lb break="no"/>turally gained easier access into Spain than those from Santa<lb break="yes"/>Fe. The latter, on the contrary, which the English and North<lb break="yes"/>Americans could easily procure in Carthagena, as a port more<lb break="yes"/>accessible to the smuggling trade, obtained a preferable fame<lb break="yes"/>in London, Germany, and Italy. The effect of mercantile<lb break="yes"/>cunning went so far, that, at the royal command, a quantity of<lb break="yes"/>the best orange-coloured Cinchona bark from New Granada,<lb break="yes"/>which M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> had caused to be peeled at the expense of the<lb break="yes"/>king, was burned, as a decidedly inefficacious remedy, at a<lb break="yes"/>time when all the Spanish field-hospitals were in the greatest<lb break="yes"/>want of this valuable product of <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>. A part of the<lb break="yes"/>Cinchona bark condemned to destruction was secretly bought by<lb break="yes"/>English merchants in Cadiz, and publicly sold in London at<lb break="yes"/>high prices. Since M. Zea, the present director of the botanic gar-<lb break="no"/>den at Madrid, has maintained, in the <hi rendition="#i">Annales de Ciencias Natu-<lb break="no"/>rales,</hi> against the editors of the <hi rendition="#i">Flora Peruviana,</hi> that their Pe-<lb break="no"/>ruvian species of Cinchona are identical with those of M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>but that they have described one and the same species under<lb break="yes"/>two or three names, the dispute concerning the quality of<lb break="yes"/>Cinchona bark from Santa Fe has again become very animated.<lb break="yes"/>The Supplement of the <hi rendition="#i">Quinologia,</hi> by <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName> and <persName key="pavon_j" >Pavon</persName>, is writ-<lb break="no"/>ten with a bitterness which ought always to remain foreign to the<lb break="yes"/>calm course of scientific inquiries.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Before we proceed from the history of the discovery of the Cin-<lb break="no" />chona to its geographical diffusion, and their remaining phy-<lb break="no"/>sical relations, we must cast a glance upon the specific diffe-<lb break="no"/>rences of the several kinds of Cinchona. A properly complete<lb break="yes"/>botanical disquisition is foreign to the purpose of this Treatise.<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="bonpland_ajag" >Bonpland</persName> and myself will attempt it on another occasion,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="34" facs="#f0016"/> viz. in the description of the two thousand new species of plants<lb break="yes"/>discovered during our expedition, and partly determined already<lb break="yes"/>by our excellent friend M. <persName key="willdenow_kl">Willdenow</persName>. As almost every spe-<lb break="no"/>cies of Cinchona is peculiar to its own region, to its own alti-<lb break="no"/>tude on the mountainous declivity of the chain of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>,<lb break="yes"/>it is unavoidably necessary, for the satisfactory treatment of<lb break="yes"/>the subject, to adjust at least the synonymy of the most impor-<lb break="no" />tant officinal species. I shall certainly make mention of that<lb break="yes"/>only, which I have had the opportunity of observing with my<lb break="yes"/>own eyes.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <pb n="35" facs="#f0017"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>ON THE<lb break="yes"/>CINCHONA FORESTS OF SOUTH<lb break="yes"/>AMERICA.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/> BY A. VON HUMBOLDT.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                </head>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>SECTION II.</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#k">
                            <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>he</hi> genus <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona</hi> belongs to those tribes of plants, whose<lb break="yes"/>species have been considerably multiplied of late. <persName key="linne_cv" >Linn&#x00E6;us</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>knew but two of them, viz. <hi rendition="#i">C. officinalis</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">C. Carib&#x00E6;a.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>,<note place="foot" n="*">Skrivter of Naturhistorie Selskabet, B. i. H. i. p. 16.</note> in his treatise on Cinchona Bark, enumerates nine;<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="lambert_ab">Lambert</persName>,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Description of the genus <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona,</hi> 1797.</note> in his English Monograph, eleven; <persName key="persoon_ch">Persoon</persName>, in<lb break="yes"/>his little <hi rendition="#i">Enchiridium Botanicum,</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Synopsis Plantarum, P. i. p. 196.</note>one-and-twenty species. If<lb break="yes"/>we yet add to these, two <hi rendition="#i">Cosmibuen&#x00E6;</hi> of the <hi rendition="#i" >Flora Peruviana,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>belonging formerly to the genus <hi rendition="#i" >Cinchona,</hi> the <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona excelsa</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>of <persName key="roxburgh_w">Roxburgh</persName>, found in the East Indies, my <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd" >Condaminea</persName>,</hi>
                        <persName key="vavasseur_01">Vavas-<lb break="no"/>sour&#x2019;s</persName>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. spinosa,</hi> and <persName key="willdenow_kl" >Willdenow&#x2019;s</persName> yet undescribed small-leaved<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. brasiliensis,</hi> for which we are indebted to Count <persName key="hoffmannsegg_jcv">Hoffmann-<lb break="no" />segg</persName> in the expedition instituted by him for objects of natural<lb break="yes"/>history, then the number of species of Cinchona appears to have<lb break="yes"/>increased to twenty-seven. The authors of the <hi rendition="#i">Flora Peruviana</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>alone have entertained the notion of describing thirteen new spe-<lb break="no"/>cies, while M. <persName key="mutis_jc" >Mutis</persName> has reduced all the <hi rendition="#i" >Cinchon&#x00E6;,</hi> examined<lb break="yes"/>by him in <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName>, to seven only. Even Professor Zea, in<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="36" facs="#f0018"/> the <hi rendition="#i">Annales de Ciencias Naturales de Madrid,</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="*">Anno 1801, No. 5.</note>has ventured<lb break="yes" />to prove that almost all the efficacious species, enumerated by<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName> and <persName key="pavon_j">Pavon</persName>, can be reduced to four, viz. <hi rendition="#i">C. lancifolia,<lb break="yes"/>C. oblongifolia, C. cordifolia,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">C. ovalifolia,</hi> described by<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, in the year 1793, in the literary news of Santa Fe de<lb break="yes"/>Bogota.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;" >Papel Periodico de Santa Fe, 1793, No. 111.</note>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Indeed I hardly know any one tree varying more in the shape<lb break="yes" />of its leaves than the Cinchona. Whoever determines single spe-<lb break="no"/>cimens of dried collections, and has no opportunity to examine or<lb break="yes"/>observe them in their native forests, will, as is the case with the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">
                            <persName key="broussonet_pma">Broussonettia</persName> papyrifera,</hi> be led to discover different species by<lb break="yes"/>leaves which are of one and the same branch. The yellow bark,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. pubescens,</hi>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>, we have found at one and the same time with<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">fol. ovato-oblongis, ovato-lanceolatis,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">ovato-cordatis.</hi>
                        <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>calls it <hi rendition="#i">C. cordifolia,</hi> because it is the only kind on which some-<lb break="no"/>times cordate leaves are found. The same species varies like the<lb break="yes"/>white Cinchona, <hi rendition="#i">C. ovalifolia,</hi> Mut. <hi rendition="#i">(C. macrocarpa,</hi>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>) <hi rendition="#i">fo-<lb break="no" />liis utrinque levibus</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">foliis utrinque pubescentibus.</hi> These<lb break="yes"/>varieties are represented in those well executed coloured draw-<lb break="no"/>ings which M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> presented me during my residence in Santa<lb break="yes"/>Fe, and which have been deposited, together with a complete<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">hortus siccus</hi> of my expedition to the tropics, in the <hi rendition="#i">Jardin<lb break="yes"/>des Plantes</hi> at Paris. Even the laurel-leaved <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd" >Condaminea</persName>,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>the finest bark from Uritusinga, has very diversified leaves,<lb break="yes"/>according to the altitude at which it grows, and which equals<lb break="yes"/>that of Saint Gothard&#x2019;s or Mount &#x00C6;tna. It would deceive the<lb break="yes"/>bark-peelers <hi rendition="#i">(cascarilleros)</hi> themselves, if they did not know<lb break="yes"/>the tree by the glands, left so long unobserved by botanists. In<lb break="yes"/>Gonzanama, not far from Loxa, we made a great number of im-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="37" facs="#f0019"/> pressions, by means of printer&#x2019;s ink, from these heterogeneous<lb break="yes"/>forms of leaves, in order to prove how unsafe all those distinc-<lb break="no"/>tions are, which have been derived from the leaves only. The<lb break="yes"/>long known but yet very imperfect method of ectypa is parti-<lb break="no"/>cularly advantageous for this and similar purposes, as it offers<lb break="yes"/>to much-occupied travellers the means of procuring in a few mi-<lb break="no"/>nutes the most correct outlines.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The more the Cinchona trees vary in the shape and smooth-<lb break="no"/>ness of the leaves, according to the altitude in which they grow;<lb break="yes" />to the severity or mildness of the climate; to the trees standing<lb break="yes"/>singly, or being closely surrounded by other plants; to the luxu-<lb break="no"/>riance of growth, and greater or less humidity of the soil; the<lb break="yes"/>more necessary is it, with regard to the <hi rendition="#i">diagnostic</hi> indications, to<lb break="yes"/>pay attention to the form of the flowers, particularly to the<lb break="yes" />length of the anthers, to the proportion between the stamens<lb break="yes"/>and anthers, as also between the free and the adherent part<lb break="yes"/>of the filaments. It is not sufficient to examine the species in<lb break="yes"/>such as have a smooth or hirsute corolla, or the stamens exsert-<lb break="no"/>ed, or inclosed in the tube of the corolla. An attentive observer<lb break="yes"/>finds in almost every species a striking difference in the struc-<lb break="no"/>ture of the corolla. Thus, the <hi rendition="#i">C. parviflora,</hi> Mut. has pubescent<lb break="yes"/>filaments, and dilated at the base. <hi rendition="#i">C. macrocarpa,</hi>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>, anthers<lb break="yes"/>nearly sessile, placed in the upper part of the tube of the corolla.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. oblongifolia,</hi> Mut. filaments very short, anthers situated below<lb break="yes"/>the middle of the tube of the corolla. The <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona ovalifolia,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>Mut., or the white Cinchona, varies frequently with from six to<lb break="yes"/>seven, the <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condaminea</persName>
                        </hi> with from three to four stamens only. In<lb break="yes"/>the first, the limb of the corolla is frequently found divided into<lb break="yes"/>six or seven, in that of the latter, mostly into four segments. In<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">Cascarilla fina de la Provincia de Jaen,</hi> which M. <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>intends shortly to describe, I found the anthers always shorter than<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="38" facs="#f0020"/> the free part of the filaments, and this free part again longer than<lb break="yes"/>the adherent one. On the other hand, I oberved that in the <hi rendition="#i">Cas-<lb break="no"/>carilla fina de Uritusinga,</hi> or the <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condaminea</persName>,</hi> the anthers<lb break="yes"/>are twice the length of the free portion of the filaments, and the<lb break="yes"/>free parts are two-thirds shorter than the adherent one. There is<lb break="yes"/>scarcely any mention of these proportions in the otherwise ex-<lb break="no"/>cellent descriptions of Cinchon&#x00E6; for which we are indebted to<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>, <persName key="swarz_01" >Swartz</persName>, and the authors of the <hi rendition="#i">Flora Peruviana.</hi> In the<lb break="yes"/>mercantile world, several barks are called Peruvian bark which<lb break="yes"/>do not belong to the genus Cinchona. Thus, the excellent remedy<lb break="yes"/>which the Catalan Capuchin friars of the missions on the River<lb break="yes"/>Carony first made known, was called in Spain <hi rendition="#i">Quina de la Guay-<lb break="no"/>ana,</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">de la <placeName key="angostura">Angostura</placeName>.</hi> M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> became acquainted with this<lb break="yes"/>bark in 1759 in Madrid, at the house of Don <persName key="rivas_vrd">Vincente Rodriguez<lb break="yes"/>de Rivas</persName>:<note place="foot" n="*">Pupel periodico de Santa Fe, No. 95. p. 337.</note> he employed it in his medical practice, and even then<lb break="yes"/>supposed that it did not belong to the genus <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona.</hi>
                        <persName key="loefling_p">L&#x0153;fling</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>died in the missions of Carony without knowing this valuable<lb break="yes"/>substance. It was afterwards ascribed, sometimes to the <hi rendition="#i">
                            <persName key="bruce_j">Brucea</persName>
                            <lb break="yes"/>ferruginea,</hi> which however grows in <placeName key="abessinien">Abyssinia</placeName>; sometimes to the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Magnolia glauca;</hi> sometimes (which certainly was more probable)<lb break="yes"/>to the <hi rendition="#i">Magnolia <persName key="plumier_c">Plumieri</persName>.</hi> In our expedition we had an oppor-<lb break="no"/>tunity of examining botanically the Cuspare tree, which yields<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">cortex Angostur&#x00E6;.</hi> We discovered it to be a new genus, on<lb break="yes"/>which our excellent friend <persName key="willdenow_kl" >Willdenow</persName>, in the Transactions of the<lb break="yes"/>Royal Academy of Berlin, has conferred the name of <persName key="bonpland_ajag">
                            <hi rendition="#i">Bonplandia</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Samml. Deutscher Abhandl. für 1801 und 1802, S. 36.</note>.<lb break="yes"/>This name of my travelling companion has been retained for the<lb break="yes"/>Cuspare plant, since we have changed the Mexican <hi rendition="#i">
                            <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonplandia</persName>
                            <lb break="yes"/>geminiflora,</hi> described by <persName key="cavanilles_aj">Cavanilles</persName>, to <hi rendition="#i" >Caldasia heterophylla.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The bark of Cumana, which for the last four or five years has<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="39" facs="#f0021"/> been sent to Spain, through the exertions of Governor Don <persName key="emparan_v">Vin-<lb break="no"/>cente Emparan</persName>, under the name of <hi rendition="#i">Cascarilla de Nueva Andalu-<lb break="no"/>sia,</hi> is likewise different from Cinchona. A chemist would hard-<lb break="no"/>ly be able to distinguish this Cuspa bark from true Cinchona<lb break="yes"/>bark. It is an excellent remedy in the ague. Although we<lb break="yes"/>observed for almost a twelvemonth the Cuspa trees of Rio<lb break="yes"/>Manzanario near Cumana, yet it never fell to our lot to meet<lb break="yes"/>with its flowers. We do not know, therefore, by what distinctive<lb break="yes"/>mark it differs from the genus <persName key="bonpland_ajag">
                            <hi rendition="#i">Bonplandia</hi>
                        </persName> and <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona.</hi> The<lb break="yes"/>want of stipul&#x00E6;, however, the situation of the leaves, and the<lb break="yes"/>whole habitus, make it more than probable that the <hi rendition="#i">Cuspa</hi> is<lb break="yes"/>not a <hi rendition="#i" >Cinchona.</hi> The absence of stipul&#x00E6; is particularly striking.<lb break="yes"/>Yet notwithstanding its alternate leaves, the Bark-tree of Cuma-<lb break="no"/>na might still be a Cinchona, for the same reason that <hi rendition="#i">Cornus<lb break="yes"/>alternifolia</hi> stands isolated amongst twelve species of <hi rendition="#i">Cornus</hi> with<lb break="yes"/>opposite leaves. It has likewise remained doubtful to us, whe-<lb break="no"/>ther the bark of Acatamez, a village situated westward of Ville<lb break="yes"/>de Ibarra on the coast of the South Sea, betwixt Rio Verde and<lb break="yes"/>Rio Esmeraldita, be the produce of a species of Cinchona. The<lb break="yes"/>flower of this Acatamez bark-tree, with which we became ac-<lb break="no"/>quainted during our stay in the town of Popayan, has not been<lb break="yes"/>hitherto examined by botanists. Mr. <persName key="brown_d">Brown</persName>, who long before us<lb break="yes"/>was in the South Sea, (in 1793,) has already given some account in<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="lambert_ab">Lambert&#x2019;s</persName> Monograph of Cinchona<note place="foot" n="*">
                            <persName key="lambert_ab">Lambert</persName>, p. 30.</note> of this new species of the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone. Either from want of geographical information, or<lb break="yes"/>by corruption of the name, he calls it <hi rendition="#i">Bark of <placeName key="atacamez" >Tecamez</placeName>,</hi> instead<lb break="yes"/>of <hi rendition="#i" >Cascarilla of Acatamez.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A fourth tribe of plants producing Peruvian bark, although<lb break="yes"/>of less medicinal power, is the genus <hi rendition="#i">Cosmibuena</hi> of the <hi rendition="#i">Flora<lb break="yes"/>Peruviana.</hi> To this belongs <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona longiflora,</hi> Mut. or <hi rendition="#i" >C. gran-</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="40" facs="#f0022"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">diflora,</hi>
                        <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>. It is a tree of great beauty, which we have fre-<lb break="no"/>quently seen in deep hot valleys exhibiting its beautiful fragrant<lb break="yes"/>blossoms. The stamens lie deep and hidden in the tube of the<lb break="yes"/>corolla; and the fructification is so similar to that of the other<lb break="yes"/>species of Cinchona, that the <hi rendition="#i">Cosmibuena</hi> can hardly be admitted<lb break="yes"/>to constitute a distinct genus.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>On the other hand, it might be advisable to form the <hi rendition="#i" >Cin-<lb break="no"/>chon&#x00E6;</hi> with long stamina far projecting from the tube of the<lb break="yes"/>corolla, such as <persName key="jacquin_njfv">Jacquin&#x2019;s</persName>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. Carib&#x00E6;a,</hi>
                        <persName key="swarz_01">Swartz&#x2019;s</persName>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. angustifo-<lb break="no"/>lia, C. brachycarpa,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">C. floribunda,</hi> into a separate genus<lb break="yes"/>nearly allied to Cinchona. The seven species belonging to it<lb break="yes"/>possess this peculiarity, that all of them, except one, inhabit<lb break="yes"/>islands, viz. the Philippine, the West Indian, and the South Sea<lb break="yes"/>Islands, and that they prefer hot valleys, or even plains, to a high<lb break="yes"/>mountainous situation. I know but two species upon the <placeName key="suedamerika">South<lb break="yes" />American</placeName> continent which have <hi rendition="#i">stamina exserta,</hi>
                        <persName key="lambert_ab">Lambert&#x2019;s</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. longiflora</hi> from French Guiana, and the yet undescribed <hi rendition="#i">Cin-<lb break="no"/>chona dissimiliflora,</hi> Mut. <hi rendition="#i">(staminibus longe exsertis, coroll&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>laciniis tubo longioribus, foliis cordato-oblongis)</hi> which, in the<lb break="yes"/>kingdom of New Granada, descends from the declivity of the<lb break="yes"/>mountains towards the plains as low as 200 toises above the level<lb break="yes"/>of the sea. <hi rendition="#i">C. Carib&#x00E6;a</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">C. angustifolia</hi> are found in the<lb break="yes"/>West Indies in still lower spots, even in regions which are suf-<lb break="no"/>ficiently warm for plantations of sugar canes. All these Island<lb break="yes" />Cinchon&#x00E6; with projecting stamens have a smooth corolla. All<lb break="yes"/>of them have a capitate or obtuse stigma, the <hi rendition="#i">C. Philippina</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="*">
                            <persName key="cavanilles_aj">Cavanilles</persName> Icones, t. iv. p. 15. t. 329.</note>
                        <lb break="yes"/>alone excepted, which M. <persName key="nee_l" >Nee</persName> discovered at Santa Cruz de la<lb break="yes"/>Laguna, near Manilla. A divided stigma is, on the contrary,<lb break="yes"/>observed in all Cinchon&#x00E6; with inclosed stamens. The co-<lb break="no"/>rolla of the latter is sometimes smooth, sometimes hairy. M.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="41" facs="#f0023"/>
                        <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> has already proposed, in the literary News of Santa Fe, to<lb break="yes"/>separate the Cinchona with long projecting stamina from the<lb break="yes"/>rest. &#x201C;I know not,&#x201D; says he, &#x201C;what my friend <persName key="linne_cv" >Linn&#x00E6;us</persName> thought<lb break="yes"/>of the Cinchona of the South Sea, for its reception in the Sup-<lb break="no"/>plement only proves the favour of the son, whose opinion has<lb break="yes"/>not with me the weight of the opinions of the father.&#x201D; The au-<lb break="no" />thors of the <hi rendition="#i">Flora Peruviana</hi> wish to make the Island-Cinchon&#x00E6;,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Portlandi&#x00E6;</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="*">Flor. Peruv. t. ii. praef. and p. 49.</note>; but M. <persName key="swarz_01">Swarz</persName>, in <persName key="schrader_ha" >Schrader&#x2019;s</persName>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Journal für die Bo-<lb break="no"/>tanik</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Band. I. p. 358.</note>, proves, that in the Island-Cinchon&#x00E6;, as in those of the<lb break="yes"/>continent, the capsule is a dissepimentum loculorum exacte pa-<lb break="no"/>rallelum, and in <hi rendition="#i">Portlandia</hi> a dissepimentum vere contrarium.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz&#x2019;s</persName>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Portlandia corymbosa</hi> is therefore no <hi rendition="#i">Portlandia,</hi> but<lb break="yes"/>belongs to the <hi rendition="#i">Cinchon&#x00E6; filamentis e basi tubi ortis,</hi> to <hi rendition="#i">C. Ca-<lb break="no"/>rib&#x00E6;a, C. floribunda,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">C. brachycarpa,</hi> a groupe of plants<lb break="yes"/>which M. <persName key="swarz_01">Swarz</persName> also wishes to unite into a separate genus on ac-<lb break="no"/>count of the flower, but not on the score of fructification. The<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. excelsa,</hi> with enormous leaves, frequently of twelve inches<lb break="yes"/>length and fifteen inches breadth, discovered in the East Indies,<lb break="yes"/>stands almost in the middle, betwixt the West-Indian and South-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>American Cinchona, and its existence seems to dissuade us, as it<lb break="yes"/>were, from the proposed separation of the two tribes. However,<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">C. excelsa</hi>
                        <persName key="roxburgh_w">Roxb.</persName> approaches less to the Island-Cinchona than<lb break="yes"/>to the New Granada and Peruvian ones, corolla pubescenti, sta-<lb break="no"/>minibus medio tubi insertis, nec e basi tubi nascentibus, antheris<lb break="yes"/>nec filamentis exsertis, margine seminum lacero, haud integro.<lb break="yes"/>The anther&#x00E6; in this East India species are eight times longer<lb break="yes"/>than the filaments. It is difficult to find reasons for uniting the<lb break="yes" />Island-Cinchon&#x00E6; into a separate genus, in the formation of the<lb break="yes"/>fruit. They differ<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">
                            <persName key="schrader_ha">Schrader</persName>, a. a. O. S. 359.</note> from the Cinchon&#x00E6; of the continent of <placeName key="suedamerika" >South<lb break="yes"/>
                            <pb n="42" facs="#f0024"/> America</placeName>, &#x201C;valvulis minus extrorsum divergentibus et recepta-<lb break="no"/>culo ovato nec lineari seminumque margine integro nec lacero.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>But except the smooth unindented coat of the seed wings, which<lb break="yes"/>I mostly find, the remaining forms of the fruits exhibit grada-<lb break="no"/>tions, which link together, as it were, all the Cinchon&#x00E6;. For<lb break="yes" />the new genus of Island-Cinchon&#x00E6;, delighting in hot plains,<lb break="yes"/>there would consequently remain: corolla glabra, filamentis<lb break="yes"/>longe exsertis ex basi tubi nascentibus. Semina margine integro<lb break="yes"/>cincta. Stigma simplex capitatum. But 1°. Many Cinchon&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>staminibus inclusis, and <hi rendition="#i">C. grandiflora</hi>
                        <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>, have corollam<lb break="yes"/>glabram. 2°. <hi rendition="#i">C. Phillippina</hi> has far projecting filaments, stig-<lb break="no"/>ma bilamellatum, and yet, as it appears, semina margine integro<lb break="yes"/>cincta. 3°. <hi rendition="#i">C. excelsa</hi> has stigma subcapitatum leviter emargi-<lb break="no"/>natum, the seed not indented, and the filaments not projecting.<lb break="yes"/>Under these exceptions, it would certainly be bold to separate<lb break="yes"/>tribes of plants so nearly allied.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The singular prickly <hi rendition="#i">C. spinosa</hi> of St. Domingo appears at<lb break="yes"/>first sight to belong least to the genus Cinchona. It is wonder-<lb break="no"/>fully small-leaved, and has frequently folia terna verticillata.<lb break="yes"/>Another prickly Cinchona differs still more in colour from the<lb break="yes"/>genuine Cinchona bark trees; it grows near Guayaquil, on the<lb break="yes"/>coast of the Pacific, and M. <persName key="tafalla_jj">Tafalla</persName> showed it to us in the winter<lb break="yes"/>of 1803, during our stay there. This undescribed species is a<lb break="yes"/>creeper, and on that account in some measure related to the genus<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Danais</hi> from Madagascar, which <persName key="persoon_ch">Persoon</persName> ranks next in succession<lb break="yes"/>to the <hi rendition="#i">Portlandia,</hi> since the <hi rendition="#i">P&#x00E6;deira fragrans,</hi> more resembling<lb break="yes"/>the Cinchona, has been separated from <hi rendition="#i" >P&#x00E6;deira f&#x0153;tida.</hi> This new<lb break="yes"/>C. <hi rendition="#i">scandens</hi> of <persName key="tafalla_jj" >Tafalla</persName> has in other respects the complete fructi-<lb break="no"/>fication of the ague-curing Cinchona, and belongs indisputably to<lb break="yes"/>the most remarkable phenomena of the physiognomy of plants.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The very same fruit of the genuine Cinchona is also produced<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="43" facs="#f0025"/> by <hi rendition="#i">Pinkneya pubens</hi>
                        <persName key="michaux_a">Michaux</persName>,<note place="foot" n="*">Flor. Americana, I. p. 105.</note> a tree which I found cultivated<lb break="yes"/>together with <hi rendition="#i">C. Carib&#x00E6;a</hi> in the excellent botanic garden of Mr.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="hamilton_w02">Hamilton</persName> near Philadelphia. The <hi rendition="#i">Pinkneya</hi> grows on Mary&#x2019;s<lb break="yes" />River, in the province of Georgia, and is already described by<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="bartram_01">Bartram</persName>, propter calycis laciniam unicam foliaceam bracte&#x00E6;for-<lb break="no"/>mem, by the name of <hi rendition="#i">Mussuenda bracteolata.</hi> The medicinal<lb break="yes" />powers for the cure of ague possessed by this plant, nearly al-<lb break="no"/>lied to the genus Cinchona, and growing without the tropics,<lb break="yes"/>have not yet been investigated. On the other hand Mr. <persName key="walker_jm">Wal-<lb break="no"/>ker</persName> has shown in two excellent treatises, that the bark of <hi rendition="#i" >Cor-<lb break="no"/>nus florida</hi> from Virginia, and of <hi rendition="#i">C. sericea</hi> from Pensylvania<lb break="yes"/>and South Carolina, and even the Tulip tree <hi rendition="#i">(Liriodendron<lb break="yes"/>Tulipifera)</hi> may be used with advantage in <placeName key="nordamerika">North America</placeName> as<lb break="yes" />remedies against agues.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">
                            <persName key="walker_jm">Walker</persName> on the virtues of the <hi rendition="#i">Cornus</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona</hi> compared. Philad. 1803. <persName key="roger_01" >Rogers&#x2019;s</persName>
                            <lb break="yes"/>Diss. on the properties of the <hi rendition="#i" >Liriodendron.</hi> Phil. 1802.</note> In the kingdom of New Spain, where<lb break="yes"/>hitherto no species of Cinchona has been discovered, as the cu-<lb break="no"/>rator of the Academical Botanic Garden at Mexico has assured<lb break="yes"/>me, the yet undescribed <hi rendition="#i">Portlandia mexicana,</hi> discovered by<lb break="yes" />M. <persName key="sesselacasta_md">Sesse</persName>, may supply the place of the Cinchona bark of Loxa. In<lb break="yes"/>the East Indies (according to D. <persName key="klein_01">Klein</persName> in Tranquebar) the <hi rendition="#i">Swie-<lb break="no"/>tenia febrifuga,</hi> figured by <persName key="roxburgh_w">Roxburgh</persName>, a plant of <persName key="swarz_01">Swarz&#x2019;s</persName> and<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="jacquin_njfv">Jacquin&#x2019;s</persName>, <hi rendition="#i" >Portlandia hexandra</hi> (<persName key="aublet_jcf" >Aublet&#x2019;s</persName>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Coutaria Speciosa),</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>nearly allied to Cinchona, produces the bark of French Guyana,<lb break="yes"/>known in France by the name of <hi rendition="#i">Ecorce fébrifuge de Cayenne</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">
                            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/117681768"><choice><sic>Ventenat</sic><corr type="editorial">Ventenant</corr></choice></persName> Tableau du Regne Vegetal, t. ii. p. 578.</note>,<lb break="yes"/>and which is no more derived from a Cinchona, than is the bark<lb break="yes"/>of Cumana or the Cuspare of <placeName key="angostura">Angostura</placeName>.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Thus much respecting the generic characters of the plants<lb break="yes" />which approximate to Cinchona, and all of which belong to the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="44" facs="#f0026"/> great family of <hi rendition="#i" >Rubiace&#x00E6;.</hi> We see that as Caoutchouc<note place="foot" n="*" >The <hi rendition="#i">Cecropia peltata</hi> is frequently mentioned as a tree yielding a part of the American<lb break="yes"/>caoutchouc. But I doubt whether any part of the new continent makes use of a juice so dif-<lb break="no"/>ficult to inspissate.</note> is obtained<lb break="yes"/>in abundance from the juices of the most diversified plants on<lb break="yes"/>the Orinoco and in Cayenne; from the <hi rendition="#i">Hevea</hi> on the Canno Pi-<lb break="no"/>michin, a branch of the Negro; from the tree <hi rendition="#i">Jacio</hi> in the<lb break="yes"/>kingdom of New Granada; from a new species of <hi rendition="#i">Ficus</hi> in the<lb break="yes"/>province of Popayan, near the Indian village La Cruz; from a<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Lobelia</hi> (to be described by us) in <placeName key="bengalen">Bengal</placeName>; from the <hi rendition="#i">Urecola elas-<lb break="no"/>tica,</hi> figured in the 5th volume of Asiatic Researches; in Mada-<lb break="no"/>gascar, from the <hi rendition="#i" >Commiphora madagascarensis;</hi> so does nature<lb break="yes"/>also offer to us the ague-curing principle, or that mixture con-<lb break="no" />taining tannin and absorbing oxygene, which we obtain of a pre-<lb break="no"/>ferable quality from <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condaminea</persName>, C. pubescens,</hi>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>.<lb break="yes"/>and <hi rendition="#i">C. lancifolia,</hi> Mut. in plants which do not even belong to<lb break="yes"/>one and the same genus. A chemist would perhaps find greater<lb break="yes"/>differences between the West-Indian and South-American Cin-<lb break="no"/>chona barks, than between the Cuspa of Cumana and the Cin-<lb break="no"/>chona bark of Loxa; and yet the Cuspa tree, <hi rendition="#i">foliis alternis,<lb break="yes"/>stipulis nullis,</hi> is most probably a very remote genus from Cin-<lb break="no"/>chona.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>After we have separated with care, partly what in a botani-<lb break="no" />cal point of view is nearly related to Cinchona, partly what<lb break="yes"/>passes in commerce amongst different nations by the name of<lb break="yes"/>China, Cascarilla, Quinquina, or Ecorce fébrifuge; after we have<lb break="yes"/>separated the Cinchon&#x00E6; with inclosed filaments, not growing<lb break="yes"/>from the lower end of the flower tube with divided stigma and<lb break="yes"/>indented margins of the seeds, from the Island-Cinchona, whose<lb break="yes"/>long projecting filaments grow from the bottom of the flower<lb break="yes"/>tube, and which have, together with unindented seed wings, an<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="45" facs="#f0027"/> undivided stigma; after we have examined the relation and<lb break="yes"/>supposed similarity of mixture of Cinchona, Portlandia, Couta-<lb break="no"/>rea, Cosmibuena, Pinkneya, Danais, <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonplandia</persName>, Cuspa, and the<lb break="yes"/>Acatamez tree, we pass to the definition of those species of Cin-<lb break="no"/>chona which have become an object of great importance in the<lb break="yes"/>practice of physic and in the intercourse of nations. Without<lb break="yes"/>the fundamental exposition of the specific characters, and with-<lb break="no"/>out adjusting some part of the synonymy, every thing which I<lb break="yes"/>am going to state respecting the geographical diffusion of the<lb break="yes"/>Cinchon&#x00E6;, and their physical relations, would remain indi-<lb break="no"/>stinct and dubious, since (as I have mentioned above) a pecu-<lb break="no"/>liar region has been destined for almost every species, and<lb break="yes"/>some botanists have, to the great detriment of science, given<lb break="yes"/>one and the same name to the most heterogeneous species. Thus,<lb break="yes"/>for instance, <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona longiflora,</hi> Mut. is totally different from<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. longiflora,</hi>
                        <persName key="lambert_ab">Lambert</persName>. It is true, they both have a smooth<lb break="yes"/>corolla, and belong to the Cinchon&#x00E6; which are fond of heat<lb break="yes"/>and possess fewer medicinal powers. But the first, from New<lb break="yes"/>Granada, has inclosed stamens, and is probably identical with<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. grandiflora, Flor. Peruv.</hi> On the other hand, the <hi rendition="#i">C. longi-<lb break="no"/>flora,</hi>
                        <persName key="lambert_ab">Lambert</persName>, from French Guiana, belongs to those species<lb break="yes"/>which have long projecting filaments and very short capsules.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona Carib&#x00E6;a,</hi> Jacq. is totally different from that <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona<lb break="yes"/>Carib&#x00E6;a</hi> described in the <hi rendition="#i">Journal de Physique,</hi> Oct. 1790. The<lb break="yes"/>diagnoses which I add are not borrowed from works already<lb break="yes"/>published, but arise partly from my own observations made from<lb break="yes"/>nature itself, partly from an instructive intercourse with M. <persName key="mutis_jc" >Mutis</persName>.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="46" facs="#f0028"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#c">
                            <hi rendition="#i">Characteristics of some Species of Cinchona.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#k">
                            <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>,</hi> in his excellent Monograph, augmented by <persName key="lambert_ab">Lambert</persName>,<lb break="yes" />divides all the species into two groupes of plants, floribus to-<lb break="no"/>mentosis, staminibus inclusis, and floribus glabris, staminibus<lb break="yes"/>exsertis. This division possesses this fault, that two characters<lb break="yes"/>are placed opposite each other, which are by no means observed<lb break="yes"/>at one and the same time in all the species at present known. Cer-<lb break="no"/>tainly no Cinchona with tomentose flowers has long projecting sta-<lb break="no"/>mens, for in the East Indian species the anthers are merely visi-<lb break="no"/>ble; but there are Cinchon&#x00E6; which have, like <hi rendition="#i">C. parviflora,</hi> Mut.<lb break="yes"/>and <hi rendition="#i">C. grandiflora, Flor. Peruv.</hi> a smooth corolla and inclosed<lb break="yes"/>stamens. With more, although not with perfect justice, we<lb break="yes"/>might separate Cinchon&#x00E6; staminibus inclusis, stigmate bilamel-<lb break="no"/>lato, seminum ala denticulat&#x00E2; vel lacer&#x00E2;, and Cinchon&#x00E6; filamen-<lb break="no"/>tis insertis ex imo tubi nascentibus, seminibus membran&#x00E2; inte-<lb break="no" />gr&#x00E2; cinctis. However, it seems more correctly logical to divide<lb break="yes"/>the Cinchon&#x00E6; into those with smooth and into those with hairy<lb break="yes"/>corollas. The first division merely subdivides itself, according<lb break="yes"/>to the length of the stamens, into two smaller tribes, and (what<lb break="yes"/>is certainly an important object) all the useful and ague-curing<lb break="yes"/>species associate into one groupe.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#c">A. <hi rendition="#k">Cinchon&#x00E6; corollis tomentosis.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>1. <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd" >Condaminea</persName>, coroll&#x00E6; tubo hirto, foliis ovato-lanceolatis<lb break="yes"/>utrinque glaberrimis, in axillis nervorum inferne scrobiculatis.<lb break="yes"/>
                            <persName key="humboldt_av">Humb.</persName> et <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpl.</persName> Plant. &#x00C6;quin. fasc.</hi> ii. <hi rendition="#i">p.</hi> 29. <hi rendition="#i" >tab.</hi> 10.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>This species, the fine bark of Uritusinga, could only be taken<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="47" facs="#f0029"/> for the <hi rendition="#i">C. glandulifera, Flor. Peruv.</hi>; but this latter differs<lb break="yes"/>coroll&#x00E2; solummodo intus lanuginos&#x00E2;, tubo externe glaberrimo,<lb break="yes" />foliis inferne villosis.<note place="foot" n="*">Flor. Peruv. t. iii. p. 1. t. 224.</note> The inhabitants also enumerate the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. glandulifera,</hi> which is called (at Chicoplaya) Cascarilla ne-<lb break="no"/>grilla, among the less efficacious species of Cinchona.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>If any one species deserved exclusively the name <hi rendition="#i">C. offici-<lb break="no"/>nalis,</hi> it would be the tree which produces the Cascarilla fina<lb break="yes"/>de Uritusinga, a bark which has always been held in Spain as<lb break="yes"/>the most efficacious in tertian agues, and which at present is ga-<lb break="no"/>thered only for the Royal Apothecaries&#x2019; Hall, and is therefore ne-<lb break="no"/>ver met with in trade by lawful channels. Notwithstanding these<lb break="yes" />preferences, we have, for several reasons, preferred giving it a<lb break="yes"/>new name, not derived from its quality or medicinal powers.<lb break="yes"/>1°. Not one species, but all provided with hairy and woolly blos-<lb break="no"/>soms, are Cinchon&#x00E6; of the shops, and no species deserves an ab-<lb break="no"/>solute preference, since different species are to be applied accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to the difference and form of the disease: for instance, in in-<lb break="no"/>termittent fevers of long standing, the <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd" >Condaminea</persName>
                        </hi> and <hi rendition="#i">C. lan-<lb break="no"/>cifolia,</hi> Mut.; in diseases of the muscles or suppurating ulcers,<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">C. oblongifolia,</hi> Mut.; in the after treatment, to prevent<lb break="yes"/>relapses, the more mild <hi rendition="#i">C. cordifolia,</hi> Mut. 2°. In botanical<lb break="yes"/>writings, species of Cinchona totally distinct have been de-<lb break="no"/>scribed by the name of <hi rendition="#i">C. officinalis.</hi> Had we bestowed the<lb break="yes"/>same name on the Cinchona of Uritusinga, it would have been<lb break="yes"/>confounded with the yellow <hi rendition="#i">C. cordifolia,</hi> Mut., the white<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. macrocarpa,</hi>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>, or even with the <hi rendition="#i" >C. nitida,</hi>
                        <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>, which at<lb break="yes" />different periods have been called <hi rendition="#i">C. officinalis.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>This latter point, equally important to the botanical synonymy<lb break="yes" />and to the materia medica, merits a more circumstantial expla-<lb break="no"/>nation. It is asked, What plant did <persName key="linne_cv" >Linn&#x00E6;us</persName>, in the 12th edition<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="48" facs="#f0030"/> of the <hi rendition="#i">Systema Natur&#x00E6;,</hi> call <hi rendition="#i">C. officinalis?</hi>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName> maintains that<lb break="yes"/>it was his <hi rendition="#i">C. macrocarpa</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="*">Act. Havn. I. p. 19. <persName key="lambert_ab" >Lambert</persName>, p. 22.</note> from the kingdom of New Granada,<lb break="yes"/>which he received from <persName key="gomezortega_c">Ortega</persName>. But since <hi rendition="#i">C. macrocarpa,</hi>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>is nothing else but our white large-flowered Cinchona of Santa<lb break="yes"/>Fe, <hi rendition="#i">C. ovalifolia,</hi> Mut.; and as, according to M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis&#x2019;s</persName> own<lb break="yes"/>testimony, it had never been seen by <persName key="linne_cv">Linn&#x00E6;us</persName>, then the <hi rendition="#i">C. ma-<lb break="no"/>crocarpa,</hi>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName> cannot be quoted as synonymous with <hi rendition="#i">C. offici-<lb break="no"/>nalis,</hi>
                        <persName key="linne_cv">Linn.</persName>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Syst. Nat. ed.</hi> 12. The great botanist of Copenha-<lb break="no"/>gen, whose early death is so justly deplored by all the friends<lb break="yes"/>of science, was misled to an erroneous synonymy in the follow-<lb break="no"/>ing manner: 1°. He knew that <persName key="linne_cv">Linn&#x00E6;us</persName> had at a later period<lb break="yes"/>founded his description of <hi rendition="#i">C. officinalis</hi> on specimens which he<lb break="yes"/>received from Santa Fe; and 2°. he erroneously presupposed<lb break="yes"/>that all the Cinchona forests in the neighbourhood of Santa Fe,<lb break="yes" />discovered by M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, consisted of white Cinchona, or <hi rendition="#i">C. ma-<lb break="no"/>crocarpa.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <persName key="linne_cv">Linn&#x00E6;us</persName> united, as already observed, two quite different<lb break="yes"/>plants under the denomination of <hi rendition="#i">C. officinalis.</hi> The dried spe-<lb break="no" />cimen of which he made use for establishing the diagnosis,<lb break="yes" />was (as M. <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> has repeatedly and orally assured me) yellow<lb break="yes"/>Cinchona, <hi rendition="#i">C. cordifolia,</hi> Mut., and the same species which <persName key="vahl_m" >Vahl</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>calls <hi rendition="#i">C. pubescens,</hi> but of which one variety has entirely smooth<lb break="yes"/>leaves, <hi rendition="#i" >folia utrinque glabra.</hi>
                        <persName key="linne_cv">Linn&#x00E6;us</persName> quotes as synonymous<lb break="yes"/>the species described by <persName key="lacondamine_cmd" >Condamine</persName> in the <hi rendition="#i">Mem. de l&#x2019;Academie,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>1738: he consequently united one species from Santa Fe with<lb break="yes"/>another which grows exclusively in the neighbourhood of Loxa.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>, in his <hi rendition="#i">Quinologia</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Cascarilla officinal. Quinolog. Arct. II. p. 56.</note>, calls a species <hi rendition="#i">C. officinalis,</hi> which<lb break="yes"/>he afterwards describes in the <hi rendition="#i" >Flor. Peruv.</hi> by the name of<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. nitida.</hi> He maintained at the time, that this tree, which<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="49" facs="#f0031"/> grows in the forests of Huamalies and Xauxa, consequently far<lb break="yes"/>from Loxa, between the 10th and 12th degree South lat., was<lb break="yes"/>the Cinchona described by <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName>. In the <hi rendition="#i" >Supplemento<lb break="yes"/>a la Quinologia,</hi> p. 68, a botanical disputation which appeared<lb break="yes"/>against M. Zea, <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, and <persName key="cavanilles_aj">Cavanilles</persName>, this assertion is very<lb break="yes"/>justly withdrawn. Indeed the <hi rendition="#i">C. nitida</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">C. officinalis</hi>
                        <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>is no other than the Cascarilla naranjanda from Santa Fe, or<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. lancifolia</hi> Mut.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Since therefore four different species, the <hi rendition="#i">Cascarilla fina de<lb break="yes"/>Uritusinga,</hi> which <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condamine</persName> has figured, <hi rendition="#i">C. pubescens</hi>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. nitida</hi>
                        <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>, and <hi rendition="#i" >C. macrocarpa</hi>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>, have already received<lb break="yes" />the name of <hi rendition="#i">C. officinalis,</hi> we have called the Cinchona of Uri-<lb break="no"/>tusinga, in commemoration of its first discoverer, <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd" >Condaminea</persName>.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>It is true that M. <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito" >Ruiz</persName>, in his <hi rendition="#i">Supplemento a la Quinologia,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>gives it as his opinion, that the plant called at present Casca-<lb break="no"/>rilla fina at Loxa, was not the plant described by the French<lb break="yes"/>astronomer; but not only the unanimous testimony of all inha-<lb break="no"/>bitants of Loxa, Caxanuma, and Uritusinga, speaks against this,<lb break="yes"/>but also <persName key="jussieu" >Jussieu&#x2019;s</persName>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Hortus Siccus</hi> at Paris. M. <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName> has<lb break="yes"/>carefully compared our <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd" >Condaminea</persName>
                        </hi> with the specimens which<lb break="yes"/>were collected by <persName key="jussieu_jd">Joseph de Jussieu</persName> and <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">La Condamine</persName>. No<lb break="yes"/>doubt remained concerning the identity of the species.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd" >Condaminea</persName>,</hi> like <hi rendition="#i">Myristica, Caryocar amygdalife-<lb break="no"/>rum,</hi> and many precious products of the tropics, is confined to<lb break="yes"/>a very small space, and it has been hitherto most imperfectly<lb break="yes"/>described. No botanists, neither <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName> and <persName key="pavon_j">Pavon</persName>, nor <persName key="tafalla_jj" >Tafalla</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>nor <persName key="nee_l" >Nee</persName>, nor <persName key="haenke_t">Hänke</persName>, nor <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, have observed it before us at<lb break="yes"/>its place of growth. The following may be considered as im-<lb break="no"/>perfect figures of the <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condaminea</persName>:</hi> Mem. de l&#x2019;Acad. de<lb break="yes"/>1738, p. 114.; <persName key="lamarck_jbpadmd">Lamarck</persName> Encyclopédie, pl. 164. fig. 1.; <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>Skrivt. af Naturh. <choice>
                            <sic>Selfkabet</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">Selskabet</corr>
                        </choice> I. tab. 1., and <persName key="lambert_ab">Lambert</persName>. Monogr.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="50" facs="#f0032"/> tab. 1. The true character of the leaves has been missed every<lb break="yes"/>where; and it would be bold to quote these synonyms, if it were<lb break="yes"/>not possible to verify them by examining the specimens which<lb break="yes"/>have served for the drawings.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Our <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd" >Condaminea</persName>
                        </hi> grows under the 4th degree south lati-<lb break="no"/>tude, on the mountainous declivity in the mean altitude be-<lb break="no"/>tween 900 and 1200 toises. It requires a milder climate than<lb break="yes"/>the orange-coloured Cinchona, <hi rendition="#i">C. lancifolia</hi> Mut., from Santa<lb break="yes"/>Fe. It is exposed to a mean temperature from 15 to 16 de-<lb break="no"/>grees <persName key="reaumur_rafd">Reaumur</persName>, which is about the mean warmth of the Canary<lb break="yes"/>Islands.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I here insert an exact diagnosis of the <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condaminea</persName>,</hi> which<lb break="yes"/>I drew up at Gonzanama, and of which (as it remained buried<lb break="yes"/>beneath astronomical manuscripts) M. <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland</persName> could not avail<lb break="yes" />himself in the publication of the second fasciculus of <hi rendition="#i" >Plant&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>&#x00C6;quinoctiales.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Calyx</hi> tubulosus basi angustatus sub-5-gonus subhirsutus ore<lb break="yes"/>5-dentato, dentibus ovatis acuminatis patentibus. <hi rendition="#i">Cor.</hi> hypo-<lb break="no"/>crateri-formis tubo cylindrico rubro l&#x00E6;vissime hirto 5-gono (ad<lb break="yes" />basin pers&#x00E6;pe fisso) limbo 5-fido s&#x00E6;pissime 4-fido, laciniis ovatis<lb break="yes"/>acutis apice et margine ciliatis, vel tomentosis ciliis albis. <hi rendition="#i">Faux</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>coroll&#x00E6; et totius tubi pars interior rubra glabra, nec ciliata.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Stamina</hi> quinque, rarius tria et quatuor. In coroll&#x00E2; 4-fid&#x00E2; s&#x00E6;pius<lb break="yes"/>stamina quinque numeravi. <hi rendition="#i">Filamenta</hi> ex rubro albescentia imo<lb break="yes"/>tubi adnata, cum eo coh&#x00E6;rentia, tertiam tubi partem &#x00E6;quantia,<lb break="yes"/>eademque tantum terti&#x00E2; su&#x00E6; longitudinis parte liber&#x00E2;. <hi rendition="#i" >Anther&#x00E6;</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>plan&#x00E6; lineares, parte liber&#x00E2; filamenti duplo longiores. <hi rendition="#i">Germen</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>rotundum subdepressum rubescens, s&#x00E6;pe punctatum et 5-sulca-<lb break="no"/>tum. <hi rendition="#i">Stylus</hi> fere longitudine tubi, crassus, teres. <hi rendition="#i">Stigma</hi> tubum<lb break="yes"/>vix superans, viridescens, compressum, bifidum s&#x00E6;pe bipartitum.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Capsula</hi> calyce coronata, oblonga, flore terti&#x00E2; parte longior, bi-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="51" facs="#f0033"/> partibilis, striato-costata, de medio hiscens, dissepimento pa-<lb break="no"/>rallelo. <hi rendition="#i">Semina</hi> plura compressa al&#x00E2; membranace&#x00E2; crenulat&#x00E2;<lb break="yes"/>cincta. <hi rendition="#i">Rami</hi> cicatrisati post casum foliorum, sub-4-goni; juniores<lb break="yes"/>glaberrimi, subpulverulenti. <hi rendition="#i">Folia</hi> petiolata decussatim oppo-<lb break="no" />sita lanceolata acuta; integerrima, utrinque viridia, nullis ve-<lb break="no"/>nis rubris picta, fere laurina, glaberrima, in axillis nervorum<lb break="yes"/>infernè screbiculata. <hi rendition="#i" >Glandul&#x00E6;</hi> nullis pilis obsit&#x00E6;, convexitate<lb break="yes"/>in pagin&#x00E2; superiori folii conspicua, venas altitudine superantes.<lb break="yes"/>Pagina folii inferior scrobiculum demonstrat. <hi rendition="#i">Petioli</hi> s&#x00E6;pè ru-<lb break="no" />bescentes, supernè plani, infernè teretes. <hi rendition="#i" >Stipul&#x00E6;</hi> decidu&#x00E6;, ob-<lb break="no"/>long&#x00E6;, carinat&#x00E6;. <hi rendition="#i">Panicula</hi> axillaris et terminalis, folio longior<lb break="yes"/>floribus brevè pedicellatis.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Size of the parts in a tree flowering for the first time:&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Calyx, 1<formula notation="TeX">\frac{7}{10}</formula> lines long; corolla, 5<formula notation="TeX">\frac{4}{10}</formula> lines; capsule; 8 lines long,<lb break="yes"/>3<formula notation="TeX" >\frac{1}{2}</formula> lines broad; according to Parisian measure. Full-grown leaves<lb break="yes"/>exclusive of the petioles, 4 inches 3 lines long, and 1 inch 9 lines<lb break="yes"/>broad. The young leaves frequently have a length of 5 inches,<lb break="yes"/>and the great breadth of 4 inches 7 lines.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd" >Condaminea</persName>
                        </hi> varies amazingly in the leaves before<lb break="yes"/>the tree comes into flower. In the shoots and very young trees<lb break="yes"/>we frequently find folia latè ovata and ovato-lanceolata. The<lb break="yes" />older the tree is, the narrower are its leaves. In great luxu-<lb break="no"/>riance of growth, the little grooves frequently vanish, which<lb break="yes"/>appear on the upper side of the leaf as convex glands. On very<lb break="yes"/>broad leaves, in which the parenchyma is considerably extended,<lb break="yes"/>they are almost entirely wanting. However, even then, we al-<lb break="no"/>ways meet with single folia scrobiculata upon the same branch.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>2. <hi rendition="#i">C. lancifolia foliis lanceolatis acutis utrinque glaberri-<lb break="no"/>mis.</hi>
                        <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, Period. de S. Fe, p. 465. (et Flor. Bogot. Mss.) In<lb break="yes"/>Santa Fe it is known by the names of Quina naranjanda, Quin-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="52" facs="#f0034"/> quina orangé, or orange-coloured Bark. Next to <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd" >Condaminea</persName>,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>it is the most efficacious febrifuge of all the kinds of Cinchona;<lb break="yes"/>the species which M. <persName key="mutis_jc" >Mutis</persName>, in his <hi rendition="#i">Quinologia,</hi> calls the Quina<lb break="yes"/>primitiva directamente febrifuga, because he prefers it to the<lb break="yes"/>three following species, and because he thinks (what is errone-<lb break="no"/>ous, however) the fine Cinchona of Uritusinga is the same species<lb break="yes"/>as Quina naranjanda of New Granada. The <hi rendition="#i">C. lancifolia</hi> has<lb break="yes" />smaller leaves than the others with tomentose corollas. They are<lb break="yes"/>also continually smooth, when on the contrary the place of growth<lb break="yes"/>produces, in the yellow and white Cinchon&#x00E6;, varieties with hairy<lb break="yes"/>leaves.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The Quina naranjanda loves a rough climate. It grows be-<lb break="no"/>tween the 4th and 5th degree north lat. on mountainous decli-<lb break="no" />vities from 700 to 1500 toises high. The mean temperature of<lb break="yes"/>this place of growth is about equal with that of Rome. It<lb break="yes"/>amounts to 13° <persName key="reaumur_rafd" >Reaumur</persName>; however the Cinchona trees ascend-<lb break="no" />ing highest towards the summit of the mountains are mostly ex-<lb break="no"/>posed to a temperature of from 8° to 9°. During the cold at<lb break="yes"/>nights, the thermometer falls in these alpine forests for hours as<lb break="yes"/>low as the freezing point; however, as far as 1500 toises high no<lb break="yes"/>snow falls in this latitude.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The Quina naranjanda, together with the C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">
                            <hi rendition="#i">Condaminea,</hi>
                        </persName> be-<lb break="no"/>longs to the more scarce species. Nature herself has produced<lb break="yes"/>them in the kingdom of New Granada in a much smaller num-<lb break="no"/>ber than those of the yellow and red Cinchon&#x00E6;, which latter<lb break="yes"/>ones form here and there almost closely-connected shrubberies.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. lancifolia,</hi> on the contrary, stands always single; and what<lb break="yes"/>is to be regretted in so valuable a produce is, that it does not<lb break="yes"/>increase so easily by shoots from the root, as the <hi rendition="#i">C. cordifolia</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. oblongifolia.</hi> In the Monographs of <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName> and <persName key="lambert_ab" >Lambert</persName>, no<lb break="yes"/>mention is made of the species called Naranjanda of Santa Fe. An<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="53" facs="#f0035"/> indisputable synonym on the contrary is <hi rendition="#i">Cinchona angustifolia</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>, <hi rendition="#i" >Suppl. à la Quinologia,</hi> p. 21, where an excellent figure<lb break="yes"/>is given. It is indeed surprising, that so exact a botanist as<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName> should change the old <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutisian</persName> name <hi rendition="#i">C. lancifolia</hi> for<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. angustifolia,</hi> since that name has previously been given by<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="swarz_01">Swartz</persName>
                        <note place="foot" n="*">Flor. Ind. occ. I. p. 380. <persName key="lambert_ab">Lambert</persName>, p. 29. Pl. 9.</note> to an Island-Cinchona with a smooth corolla and long<lb break="yes"/>projecting stamens.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Professor Zea thinks, and, as it appears to me, with perfect<lb break="yes" />propriety, that several species of the <hi rendition="#i">Flora Peruviana</hi> denote<lb break="yes"/>merely different states of the Quina naranjanda, such as depend<lb break="yes"/>on the age, the climate, and the place of growth. The following<lb break="yes"/>appear to be varieties of the <hi rendition="#i">C. lancifolia</hi> Mut.: 1°. <hi rendition="#i">C. nitida<lb break="yes"/>Flor. Peruv. II. Icon. t.</hi> 191. (<persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>, <hi rendition="#i" >Quinol. II.</hi> p. 56.) <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito" >Ruiz&#x2019;s</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>Cascarilla officinal. 2°. <hi rendition="#i">C. lanceolata Flor. Per. II.</hi> p. 51. and<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. glabra</hi>
                        <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Quin. II.</hi> p. 64. Cascarilla lampina, of which<lb break="yes"/>no figure is given. M. Zea thinks he may venture to add to<lb break="yes"/>these, the <hi rendition="#i">C. rosea Flor. Peruv. II. Ic.</hi> 199. a species which is<lb break="yes"/>said to be the most scarce in Peru, and (what agrees little with<lb break="yes"/>the nature of C. <hi rendition="#i">lancifolia</hi>) to descend from the mountains into<lb break="yes"/>the lowest regions.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">
                            <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName> Supplem. à la Quinol. p. 54.</note>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The Cinchona Bark so famous in Cadiz by the name of Cali-<lb break="no" />saya, and of such particular medicinal power, belongs, accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName>, indisputably to <hi rendition="#i">C. lancifolia.</hi>
                        <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName> considers it,<lb break="yes"/>in his <hi rendition="#i">Quinologia,</hi> as synonymous with his <hi rendition="#i">C. glabra.</hi> But in<lb break="yes"/>his disputation against Zea, he withdraws this opinion, and as-<lb break="no" />sures us that there is no species growing in the neighbourhood<lb break="yes"/>of Huanuco which produces a bark similar to the Calisaya.<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">P. 73 and 95.</note>
                        <lb break="yes"/>The name Calisaya is that of the province producing this bark,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="54" facs="#f0036"/> which is situated in the most southerly of Peru, in the Intenden-<lb break="no"/>cia de la Paz.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The second edition of a modern French work, <persName key="alibert_jl" >Alibert&#x2019;s</persName>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Traité<lb break="yes"/>de Fièvres intermittentes,</hi> contains very exact figures of the<lb break="yes"/>orange-coloured Cinchona, as well as of the three following <persName key="mutis_jc">Mu-<lb break="no" />tisian</persName> species. They have been made from dried specimens, de-<lb break="no"/>termined by M. <persName key="mutis_jc" >Mutis</persName>, and supplied by M. Zea from his collection<lb break="yes"/>during his residence at Paris.<note place="foot" n="*">Some of these figures are evidently copied from those in <hi rendition="#i" >Flora Peruviana.</hi>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Edit.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>3. <hi rendition="#i">C. cordifolia fol. orbiculato-ovatis s&#x00E6;pe subcordatis subtus<lb break="yes"/>tomentosis supra pubescentibus,</hi> Mut. Mss. Quina amarilla,<lb break="yes"/>Quinquina jaune, yellow Bark from Santa Fe, the species, as<lb break="yes"/>observed above, described by <persName key="linne_cv">Linn&#x00E6;us</persName> in <hi rendition="#i" >Syst. Nat. t.</hi> ii. <hi rendition="#i">ed.</hi> 12.<lb break="yes" />p. 64. under the name of <hi rendition="#i">C. officinalis.</hi> The anthers in <hi rendition="#i">C. cor-<lb break="no"/>difolia</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">C. lancifolia</hi> reach as far as the upper parts of the<lb break="yes"/>flower-tube; when on the contrary, in the red Cinchona (<hi rendition="#i">C. ob-<lb break="no"/>longifolia)</hi> they are deeply hidden in the middle of the tube.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. cordifolia</hi> has two varieties. Var. &#x03B2; <hi rendition="#i">foliis vix cordatis utrin-<lb break="no"/>que glabris. &#x03B3; foliis utrinque hirsutis.</hi> By the common peo-<lb break="no" />ple, in the kingdom of New Granada, it is called Velvet Bark.<lb break="yes"/>It grows under the 4th degree North latitude, in heights be-<lb break="no"/>twixt 900 and 1440 toises. Cordate leaves occur but seldom:<lb break="yes"/>however, almost every branch exhibits some of them. <hi rendition="#i">C. cor-<lb break="no"/>difolia</hi> Mut. is, according to <persName key="bonpland_ajag">Bonpland&#x2019;s</persName> examination, identical<lb break="yes"/>with <hi rendition="#i">C. pubescens</hi>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>, as proved by <persName key="jussieu" >Jussieu&#x2019;s</persName> collection, from<lb break="yes"/>which <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName> received his specimen. <persName key="jussieu_jd">Joseph Jussieu</persName> had collect-<lb break="no" />ed, in 1738, this species of Cinchona and <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condaminea</persName>
                        </hi> in the<lb break="yes"/>forests of Loxa.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The <hi rendition="#i">C. ovata Flor. Peruv. II. t.</hi> 195. <hi rendition="#i">Cascarilla pallida</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>, <hi rendition="#i" >Quinol. Art.</hi> 7. p. 74. called in the neighbourhood of<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="55" facs="#f0037"/> Pozuzo <hi rendition="#i">Pala de Guallerata,</hi> is likewise a synonym of <hi rendition="#i">C. cor-<lb break="no"/>difolia</hi> Mut. <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito" >Ruiz</persName> and <persName key="pavon_j">Pavon</persName> themselves have latterly acknow-<lb break="no"/>ledged this identity.<note place="foot" n="*">Supplem. à la Quinol. p. 18.</note>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The <hi rendition="#i">C. hirsuta Flor. Peruv. II. Ic.</hi> 192. Cascarillo delgado,<lb break="yes"/>or <hi rendition="#i">C. tenuis</hi>
                        <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>, <hi rendition="#i" >Quinol. II.</hi> p. 56. is, according to Zea, a<lb break="yes"/>variety of <hi rendition="#i">C. cordifolia</hi> Mut. Does <hi rendition="#i">C. purpurea Flor. Per. II.<lb break="yes"/>t.</hi> 193. or Cascarilla morado <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Quinol. Art.</hi> v. p. 67. also<lb break="yes"/>belong here? This species varies surprisingly in its leaves, and<lb break="yes"/>on one and the same tree too.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>4. <hi rendition="#i">C. oblongifolia foliis oblongis acuminatis glabris, fila-<lb break="no"/>mentis brevissimis, antheris infra medium tubi latentibus.</hi> Mut.<lb break="yes"/>Mss.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Quina roxa, Quinquina rouge de Santa Fe, differt a <hi rendition="#i">C. lan-<lb break="no"/>cifoli&#x00E2;,</hi> 1°. foliis latioribus, majoribus oblongis nec lanceolatis;<lb break="yes"/>2°. antheris haud in summo tubi latentibus.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It grows under the 5th degree North lat. in heights from 600<lb break="yes" />to 1300 toises, and is particularly common in the neighbourhood<lb break="yes"/>of Mariquita, a small town, which was for a long time the seat<lb break="yes"/>of M. <persName key="mutis_jc" >Mutis&#x2019;s</persName> botanical expedition. It frequently bears much<lb break="yes"/>larger fruit than the white Cinchona, <hi rendition="#i">C. ovalifolia,</hi> for which<lb break="yes"/>reason it would deserve the name of <hi rendition="#i">macrocarpa</hi> with more pro-<lb break="no"/>priety than the latter one. Its bark is less efficacious than that<lb break="yes"/>of <hi rendition="#i">C. <persName key="lacondamine_cmd">Condaminea</persName>
                        </hi> and <hi rendition="#i">C. lancifolia,</hi> yet more so than the yel-<lb break="no"/>low Cinchona, <hi rendition="#i">(C. cordifolia.)</hi> It is more stimulating, for weak<lb break="yes" />constitutions, in inflammatory diseases frequently dangerous, but<lb break="yes"/>the more beneficial when applied externally in diseases of the<lb break="yes"/>muscles, suppurating and sphacelous ulcers.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The yellow Cinchona, <hi rendition="#i">Cascarilla amarilla Quinol. Art.</hi> vi.<lb break="yes"/>p. 71. or <hi rendition="#i">C. magnifolia Flor. Per. II. Ic.</hi> 196. which, on ac-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="56" facs="#f0038"/> count of the fragrant and orange-flower smell of its blossoms, is<lb break="yes"/>called in Peru, Flor. de Azahar, and in Popayan, Palo de re-<lb break="no"/>queson,<note place="foot" n="*">Period. de Santa Fe, p. 335.</note> is, according to the latter confessions of <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>, iden-<lb break="no" />tical with <hi rendition="#i">C. oblongifolia</hi> Mut. or with the red Cinchona of<lb break="yes"/>Santa Fe.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>5. <hi rendition="#i">C. ovalifolia fol. ellipticis supra glaberrimis subtus pu-<lb break="no"/>bescentibus antheris in parte tubi superiori latentibus filamentis<lb break="yes"/>vix ullis.</hi> Mut. Mss.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Quina blanca, Quinquina blanc: White Cinchona of Santa<lb break="yes" />Fe.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#et">Var. &#x03B2; fol. utrinque pubescentibus.<lb break="yes"/>&#x03B3;. fol. utrinque l&#x00E6;vibus.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Both varieties, particularly the first, have frequently a corolla<lb break="yes"/>with 6 or 7 divisions, and 6 or 7 stamens.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It grows under the 3d to the 6th degree North lat. in heights<lb break="yes" />from betwixt 700 and 1400 toises. The variety with smooth leaves<lb break="yes"/>is frequent near San Martha. The <hi rendition="#i" >Cinchona macrocarpa</hi>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>.<lb break="yes"/>(<persName key="lambert_ab">Lambert</persName>, p. 22. t. 3.) is a true synonym of this, acknowledged by<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="mutis_jc">Mutis</persName> and <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName> themselves.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Suppl. p. 18.</note> Amongst the Cinchon&#x00E6; with hairy<lb break="yes"/>corollas it is the largest-flowering one of all. It must not, how-<lb break="no"/>ever, be confounded with <hi rendition="#i" >C. grandiflora Flor. Peruv. II. p.</hi> 54.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">(Cosmibuena obtusifolia Flor. Peruv. III. t.</hi> 198.<hi rendition="#i">)</hi> having a quite<lb break="yes"/>smooth corolla.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>6. <hi rendition="#i">C. brasiliensis foliis oblongis acuminatis, venis subtus pu-<lb break="no"/>bescentibus panicul&#x00E2; terminali, tubo calycis longitudine.</hi>
                        <persName key="willdenow_kl">Willd.</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>Mss.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A very small-flowering species, for which we are indebted, as<lb break="yes" />observed already, to Count <persName key="hoffmannsegg_jcv" >Hoffmannsegg</persName>, together with <persName key="aublet_jcf" >Aublet&#x2019;s</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="57" facs="#f0039"/> and <persName key="lambert_ab" >Lambert&#x2019;s</persName>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. longiflora</hi> from French Guiana, the only Cin-<lb break="no"/>chona which grows on the easterly coast of the <placeName key="suedamerika">South American</placeName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>continent. Nothing decisive is known about the height of its<lb break="yes"/>place of growth; but as it has been sent from the neighbour-<lb break="no"/>hood of the town of Gran Para, at the mouth of the <placeName key="amazonas">Amazon river</placeName>,<lb break="yes"/>and as in this region there are only low hills found, we are allowed<lb break="yes"/>to suppose that <hi rendition="#i">C. Brasiliensis</hi> belongs to the hot regions.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The character of this species by M. <persName key="willdenow_kl" >Willdenow</persName>, tube of the corol-<lb break="no"/>la the length of the calyx, distinguishes this Cinchona from every<lb break="yes"/>one hitherto described. Throat of the coroll&#x00E6; hairy; hairs few,<lb break="yes"/>short, appressed, situated on the interior surface of the corolline<lb break="yes"/>lacini&#x00E6;.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>7. <hi rendition="#i">C. excelsa coroll&#x00E2; pubescente, filamentis e medio tubi na-<lb break="no"/>scentibus, antheris exsertis, foliis oblongis subtus pubescentibus.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName key="roxburgh_w">Roxb.</persName> Plant. of the Coast of Coromandel, ii. t. 106.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The only Cinchona hitherto discovered on the continent of<lb break="yes"/>
                        <placeName key="altewelt">the ancient world</placeName>, about whose medicinal use and its bitter<lb break="yes"/>no trials have however as yet been made. It has very small<lb break="yes"/>greenish-white flowers, and of all Cinchon&#x00E6; the largest leaves,<lb break="yes"/>sometimes one foot long and five inches broad.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The <hi rendition="#i">C. excelsa (Bundarvo</hi> of the Felinga Indians) grows in<lb break="yes"/>the mountain chain of the Circars, which runs along the north-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>easterly coast of the great peninsula of Hindostan. <persName key="retzius_aj">Retzius</persName>
                        <note place="foot" n="*">Observ. Bot. fasc. iv. p. 6.</note>
                        <lb break="yes"/>has at an earlier date, from accounts communicated to him<lb break="yes"/>by <persName key="koenig_jg">König</persName>, mentioned a Cinchona which grows in Malacca, op-<lb break="no"/>posite to the coast of Coromandel, and which produces the ge-<lb break="no"/>nuine <hi rendition="#i">terra japonica,</hi> called <hi rendition="#i">Cotta Cambar,</hi> a vegetable produce,<lb break="yes"/>which for a long time was erroneously ascribed to <hi rendition="#i">Mimosa spi-<lb break="no" />cata</hi> Pluk. Might not this Cinchona from Malacca be a diffe-<lb break="no"/>rent species from <hi rendition="#i">C. excelsa?</hi>
                    </p>
                    <pb n="58" facs="#f0040"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#et">B. <hi rendition="#i">Cinchon&#x00E6; corollis glaberrimis.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#et">a. <hi rendition="#i">staminibus inclusis.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>8. <hi rendition="#i">C. grandiflora, tubo coroll&#x00E6; longissimo, fol. lanceolato-<lb break="no"/>oblongis utrinque glabris.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I have retained the former name of the <hi rendition="#i">Flor. Per.</hi> M. <persName key="ruizlópez_hipolito">Ruiz</persName>
                        <lb break="yes"/>calls this species at present <hi rendition="#i">Cosmibuena obtusifolia. (Flor. Per.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>vol. iii.) It is identical with <hi rendition="#i">C. longiflora</hi> Mut., a name which<lb break="yes"/>would cause confusion, since <persName key="lambert_ab">Lambert</persName> enumerates as <hi rendition="#i">C. longi-<lb break="no"/>flora</hi> the Island-Cinchona staminibus longe exsertis, described as<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">C. Carib&#x00E6;a</hi> in <hi rendition="#i">Journ. de Phys.</hi> Oct. 1790.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It is fond of warm regions, and descends from the mountains<lb break="yes" />in heights from two and three hundred toises. It grows in re-<lb break="no"/>gions whose mean temperature is from 18 to 19 degrees.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>9. <hi rendition="#i">C. parviflora foliis ovatis glabris, filamentis basi dilatatis<lb break="yes"/>et pubescentibus.</hi> Mut. Mss.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It has the smallest fruit of all Cinchon&#x00E6;.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#et">b. <hi rendition="#i">staminibus exsertis.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>10. <hi rendition="#i">C. dissimiliflora foliis cordato-oblongis glaberrimis, limbo<lb break="yes"/>coroll&#x00E6; tubo longiori, capsulis sublinearibus angustissimis.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>Mut. Mss.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Next to <hi rendition="#i">C. longiflora</hi>
                        <persName key="lambert_ab">Lamb</persName>. the only species of the con-<lb break="no"/>tinent which has stamina exserta. Grows in heights betwixt<lb break="yes"/>200 and 700 toises in warm regions.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>11. <hi rendition="#i">C. Carib&#x00E6;a</hi>
                        <persName key="swarz_01">Swartz</persName>.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>12. <hi rendition="#i">C. longiflora</hi>
                        <persName key="lambert_ab">Lamb</persName>.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>13. <hi rendition="#i">C. lineata</hi>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>14. <hi rendition="#i">C. floribunda</hi>
                        <persName key="swarz_01">Swartz</persName>.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="59" facs="#f0041"/>
                    <p>15. <hi rendition="#i">C. angustifolia</hi>
                        <persName key="swarz_01">Swartz</persName>.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>16. <hi rendition="#i">C. brachycarpa</hi>
                        <persName key="vahl_m">Vahl</persName>.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>These six latter species grow all in the West-India Islands,<lb break="yes" />and love a temperature of from 17 to 22 degrees R.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>17. <hi rendition="#i">C. corymbifera</hi>
                        <persName key="forster_g">Forster</persName>.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Native of the Friendly Islands.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>18. <hi rendition="#i">C. Philippica,</hi> discovered near Manilla by Nec.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I do not venture to assert that all Cinchon&#x00E6; hitherto known<lb break="yes"/>are comprehended within the eighteen species arranged here. I<lb break="yes"/>have merely wished to enumerate those which are known to me,<lb break="yes"/>partly in their natural state partly from good figures, and which<lb break="yes"/>to me appear indisputably specific from each other. <hi rendition="#i">C. acuti-<lb break="no"/>folia, C. micrantha, C. glandulifera, C. dichotoma, C. (Cosmi-<lb break="no"/>buena) acuminata,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">C. spinosa,</hi> deserve a closer investigation.<lb break="yes"/>The genus might perhaps increase to twenty-four species.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 