<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023299100">
                        <surname>Clark</surname>
                        <forename>Rex</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="stoeckli_mt">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stöckli</surname>
                        <forename>Matthias Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="schnidrig_bf">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schnidrig</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara Franziska</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.5.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.4.0" when="2018-09-28" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Personenmarkierung abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.3.0" when="2018-09-27" who="stoeckli_mt">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Personen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2018-09-27" who="schnidrig_bf">Markup: added placeName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Orte.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="316" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Account of the Ottomacs, a People who eat Clay.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">Tableaux de la Nature, par <hi rendition="#i">A. de <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>,</hi> 2 vol. 12mo. Paris, 1808.<lb break="yes"/>vol. i. p. 191.<lb break="yes"/>For an account of the practice of eating clay among some tribes of Africans,<lb break="yes" />the reader may consult Mr William Hunter&#x2019;s Essay on the Diseases incident to<lb break="yes"/>Indian seamen, or Lascars, on long voyages, Appendix, No. X. and the several<lb break="yes"/>authorities referred to by him.</note>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">O</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">n</hi> the coasts of Cumana, of <placeName key="barcelona" >new Barcelona</placeName>, and of Caraccas,<lb break="yes"/>visited by the Franciscan monks of Guayana in returning<lb break="yes"/>from their missions, there was a tradition prevalent, that tribes<lb break="yes"/>inhabiting the banks of the Orinoco eat earth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On the 6th of June 1800, when, on our return from Rio Negro,<lb break="yes"/>we came down the Orinoco, where we had remained thirty-six<lb break="yes"/>days; we spent a day in a mission inhabited by the Ottomacs, who<lb break="yes"/>eat earth. The village called La Concepcion of Uruana, is situ-<lb break="no"/>ated, in a very picturesque manner, upon the declivity of a rock<lb break="yes"/>of granite. Its latitude I determined to be 7° 8&#x2032; 3&#x2033; north,<lb break="yes"/>and its longitude 4° 38&#x2032; 38&#x2033; west of Paris. The earth which<lb break="yes"/>the Ottomacs eat is a fat and unctuous clay, a real potter&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>earth, of a greyish-yellow tint, coloured by a little oxide of<lb break="yes"/>iron. They select it with much care, and gather it on particu-<lb break="no"/>lar banks on the sides of the Orinoco, and of the Meta. They<lb break="yes"/>distinguish, by the taste, one kind of earth from another, for<lb break="yes"/>all kinds of clay are not equally agreeable to their palates. They<lb break="yes"/>knead this earth into balls, of from four to six inches in diame-<lb break="no"/>ter, and bake it at a slow fire, till its outer surface becomes red-<lb break="no"/>dish. Before they eat these balls, they moisten them anew.<lb break="yes"/>These Ottomacs are for the most part a very savage race,<lb break="yes"/>and have an aversion to improvement. The nations of the<lb break="yes"/>Orinoco, that are farthest from that canton, say proverbially,<lb break="yes"/>when they wish to speak of any thing very filthy, &#x201C;It is dis-<lb break="no"/>gusting enough for an Ottomac to eat it.&#x201D; When the waters<lb break="yes"/>of the Orinoco and Meta are low, the Ottomacs support them-<lb break="no"/>selves on fish and tortoises. When the fish appear at the sur-<lb break="no"/>face of the water, they kill them by means of darts, with a dex-<lb break="no"/>terity which we have often admired. When the rivers experi-<lb break="no"/>ence their periodical overflow, the fishing ceases; for it is as<lb break="yes"/>difficult to fish in rivers become too deep, as in the open sea.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="317" facs="#f0002"/> During this inundation, which lasts two or three months, the<lb break="yes"/>Ottomacs swallow prodigious quantities of earth. We have<lb break="yes"/>found in their huts immense stores of it, heaped up in pyramids.<lb break="yes"/>Each individual consumes daily three-fourths or four-fifths of a<lb break="yes"/>pound of earth, according to the account which Fray <persName key="bueno_r">Ramon<lb break="yes"/>Bueno</persName>, a very intelligent monk, a native of Madrid, who has<lb break="yes"/>lived twelve years among these Indians, gave us. The Ottomacs<lb break="yes"/>themselves say, that, in the rainy season, this earth is their<lb break="yes"/>principal food. In addition, they eat little fishes, lizards, and<lb break="yes"/>fern-roots, when they can procure them. They are so fond of<lb break="yes"/>this earth, that every day they eat a little of it after their repast,<lb break="yes"/>to regale themselves, even in the dry seasons, and when they<lb break="yes"/>have abundance of fish. These people are of a very dark cop-<lb break="no"/>per colour. Their features are as ugly as those of the Tartars.<lb break="yes"/>They are fat, but they have not a large belly. The missionary<lb break="yes"/>who resides among them, assured us, that he has remarked no<lb break="yes" />difference in the health of these savages, during the time that<lb break="yes" />they eat this earth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Such is the simple narration of facts. The Indians eat great<lb break="yes" />quantities of earth, without their health suffering from it. They<lb break="yes"/>consider it as a nourishing kind of food; that is to say, they<lb break="yes"/>find that this food satisfies them for some time. They attribute<lb break="yes"/>this satiety to the earth, and not to the other very bad articles<lb break="yes"/>of diet which they are enabled to add to it. If they are asked<lb break="yes"/>what is their provision in winter, the season, which in the warm<lb break="yes"/>parts of <placeName key="suedamerika">South America</placeName> is called the rainy-season, they point<lb break="yes" />out the heaps of earth piled up in their huts. But these partial<lb break="yes"/>facts do not decide the following questions. Can earth, in real-<lb break="no"/>ity, be a nutritive substance? Can earth assimilate itself to our<lb break="yes"/>nature? Or is it but a load upon the stomach? Does it not<lb break="yes"/>serve only to keep its sides distended, and in this manner con-<lb break="no"/>tribute to alleviate hunger? It is very singular, that Father Gu-<lb break="no"/>mila, in other respects so credulous, and whose work is so void of<lb break="yes"/>sound criticism, should absolutely deny that the Indians eat earth.<note place="foot" n="*">History of the Orinoco, vol. i. p. 283.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>He pretends that the balls of clay are mixed with the flour of<lb break="yes"/>Indian corn and the fat of the crocodile. But the missionary<lb break="yes"/>Fray <persName key="bueno_r">Ramon Bueno</persName>, and brother Fray <persName key="gonzalez_j">Juan Gonzales</persName>, our<lb break="yes"/>friend and travelling companion, whom the sea on the coast of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="afrika">Africa </placeName>swallowed up along with a part of our collections, both<lb break="yes"/>assured us that the Ottomacs do not mix this earth with the<lb break="yes"/>fat of the crocodile. At Uruana we never heard a word about<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="318" facs="#f0003"/> the mixture of flour. The earth which we brought home with<lb break="yes"/>us, and which <persName key="vauquelin_ln" >Vauquelin</persName> analyzed, was pure, and without any<lb break="yes" />mixture. May not Gumila, confounding strange facts, have<lb break="yes" />wished to allude to the bread which is prepared with the long<lb break="yes" />pods of a species of <hi rendition="#i">inga?</hi> This fruit is buried in the earth,<lb break="yes"/>that it may ferment the sooner.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But what surprises me more is, that the use of so great a<lb break="yes" />quantity of earth does not occasion any disease among the Otto-<lb break="no" />macs. Has this colony been habituated to this kind of food for<lb break="yes" />many generations? In all the countries of the torrid zone, men<lb break="yes" />have an astonishing, and almost irresistible desire of eating earth;<lb break="yes"/>not an alkaline or calcareous earth to neutralize the acid juices,<lb break="yes"/>but a clay which is very fat, and of which the odour is very<lb break="yes"/>strong. They are often obliged to tie children, to hinder them<lb break="yes"/>from going out and eating the earth when the rains have ceased.<lb break="yes"/>At the village of <placeName key="banco" >Banco</placeName>, on the banks of the river Magdalena,<lb break="yes"/>the native women, who make earthen pots, put large pieces of<lb break="yes"/>clay into their mouth, as I have often seen with surprise. <note place="foot" n="*">
                        <persName key="gilij_fs">Gily</persName> has made the same remark, Saggio di Storia dell&#x2019; <placeName key="amerika">America</placeName>, t. ii. p. 311.<lb break="yes"/>In winter, the wolves eat earth, but, above all, clay. In general it would be inte-<lb break="no"/>resting to analyze the feces of man, and all those animals who eat earth.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>The other tribes of <placeName key="amerika" >America</placeName> never fail to become diseased when<lb break="yes"/>they give themselves up to the singular desire of eating earth.<lb break="yes"/>In the mission of San Borgia, we saw a child, who, according<lb break="yes"/>to what its mother told us, would not eat any thing but earth,<lb break="yes" />which diet had made it as lean as a skeleton. Whence is it,<lb break="yes" />that, in the cold and temperate zones, the desire of eating earth<lb break="yes"/>is so rare, and exists only among children and pregnant wo-<lb break="no"/>men? It may be asserted, that, in all the regions of the tor-<lb break="no"/>rid zone, this desire for earth has been observed. In Guinea,<lb break="yes"/>the negroes eat a yellowish earth which they call <hi rendition="#i">caouac.</hi> The<lb break="yes"/>slaves which are brought into <placeName key="amerika">America</placeName>, endeavour to procure<lb break="yes"/>a similar gratification; but it is always to the detriment of their<lb break="yes"/>health.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Another very general cause of the <hi rendition="#i">mal d&#x2019;estomac,</hi>&#x201D; says a<lb break="yes"/>modern traveller, &#x201C;is, that many of the slaves who come from<lb break="yes"/>Guinea eat earth. This does not arise from a depraved taste;<lb break="yes"/>it is a custom contracted in their own country, where they say<lb break="yes"/>that they habitually eat a certain kind of earth, the taste of<lb break="yes"/>which pleases them, and which does not hurt them. They<lb break="yes"/>search among us for earth most resembling it. That which they<lb break="yes"/>prefer is a reddish yellow tufa, very common in our islands.<lb break="yes"/>This they even sell secretly in our public markets, under the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="319" facs="#f0004"/> name of <hi rendition="#i">caouac.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">
                        <persName key="chanvalon_jbtd">
                            <hi rendition="#i">Thibaut de Chanvallon,</hi>
                        </persName> Voyage à la Martinique, p. 85.</note> (M. Thibaut was at Martinique in the year<lb break="yes"/>1751.) Those who are accustomed to the use of it are so fond<lb break="yes"/>of it, that no chastisement can prevent them from eating it.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the villages of the isle of Java, between Sourabaya and<lb break="yes" />Samarang, M. <persName key="labillardiere_jjd">La Billardière</persName> saw little square reddish cakes ex-<lb break="no"/>posed to sale. The natives call them <hi rendition="#i">tanaampo.</hi> Upon examin-<lb break="no"/>ing them more narrowly, they were found to be cakes of reddish<lb break="yes"/>earth, which they eat. <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Voyage à la recherche de <persName key="laperouse_jfdgcd">La Peyrouse</persName>, Vol. II. p. 322.</note> The inhabitants of New Caledonia,<lb break="yes"/>eat, to satisfy their hunger, pieces as large as the fist, of friable<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">lapis ollaris.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. <persName key="vauquelin_ln">Vauquelin</persName>, upon analyzing it, found in it a considerable<lb break="yes"/>quantity of copper. <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Ibid. p. 205.</note> At Popayan, and in many parts of Pe-<lb break="no"/>ru, the inhabitants purchase at the market calcareous earth, with<lb break="yes"/>other commodities. In using it, they mix with it the cocca, or<lb break="yes"/>the leaves of the <hi rendition="#i">erythroxilon peruvianum.</hi> Thus we find, that<lb break="yes"/>this taste for eating earth, which it would seem that nature ought<lb break="yes"/>to have reserved to the inhabitants of the ungrateful regions of<lb break="yes"/>the north, extends through all the torrid zone, among the indo-<lb break="no"/>lent races of men, who live in the most beautiful and the most<lb break="yes"/>fertile countries in the world.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 