<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023299100">
                        <surname>Clark</surname>
                        <forename>Rex</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="stoeckli_mt">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stöckli</surname>
                        <forename>Matthias Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="schnidrig_bf">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schnidrig</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara Franziska</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.5.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.4.0" when="2018-09-28" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Personenmarkierung abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.3.0" when="2018-09-27" who="stoeckli_mt">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Personen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2018-09-27" who="schnidrig_bf">Markup: added placeName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Orte.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="3" facs="#f0001"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">From <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>&#x2019;s Political Essay on New<lb break="yes"/>Spain.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the month of January, 1804, the vaccine<lb break="yes"/>inoculation was introduced at Mexico through<lb break="yes"/>the activity of a respectable citizen, Don<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="murphy_t">Thomas Murphy</persName>, who brought several times<lb break="yes"/>the virus from <placeName key="nordamerika">North America</placeName>. This in-<lb break="no"/>troduction found a few obstacles; the cow-<lb break="maybe"/>pox appeared under the aspect of a very trivial<lb break="yes"/>malady; and the small pox inoculation had<lb break="yes"/>already accustomed the Indians to the idea<lb break="yes"/>that it might be useful to submit to a tempo-<lb break="no"/>rary evil for the sake of evading a greater evil.<lb break="yes"/>If the vaccine inoculation, or even the ordinary<lb break="yes"/>inoculation, had been known in the <placeName key="amerika">new world</placeName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>in the sixteenth century, several millions of<lb break="yes" />Indians would not have perished victims to<lb break="yes"/>the small-pox, and particularly to the absurd<lb break="yes"/>treatment by which the disease was rendered<lb break="yes"/>so fatal. To this disease the fearful diminu-<lb break="no"/>tion of the number of Indians in California is<lb break="yes" />to be ascribed. The ships of war commis-<lb break="no"/>sioned to carry the vaccine matter into <placeName key="amerika">Ameri-<lb break="no" />ca</placeName> and <placeName key="asien">Asia</placeName> arrived at Vera Cruz shortly af-<lb break="no"/>ter my arrival.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Don Antonio Valmis, physician general of<lb break="yes"/>this expedition, visited Porto Rico, Cuba,<lb break="yes"/>Mexico, and the Philippine islands; and his<lb break="yes"/>stay at Mexico, were nevertheless the cow-<lb break="maybe" />pox was known before his arrival, contributed<lb break="yes"/>singularly to facilitate the propagation of this<lb break="yes"/>salutary preservative. In the principal cities<lb break="yes"/>of the kingdom, vaccine committees were for-<lb break="no"/>med, <hi rendition="#i">(juntas <choice><sic>sentrales</sic><corr type="editorial">centrales</corr></choice>,)</hi> composed of the most<lb break="yes"/>enlightened individuals, who, by vaccinating<lb break="yes"/>monthly, preserve the miasma from being<lb break="yes"/>lost. It is so much the less liable to be lost,<lb break="yes"/>as it exists in the country. M. Valmis dis-<lb break="no"/>covered it in the environs of Valladolid, and in<lb break="yes"/>the village of Atlisco, near la Puebla, in the<lb break="yes"/>udders of the Maxican cows. The commis-<lb break="no"/>sion having fulfilled the beneficent views of the<lb break="yes"/>king of Spain, we may indulge a hope that<lb break="yes"/>through the influence of the clergy, and es-<lb break="no"/>pecially of the religious missionaries, vaccina-<lb break="no"/>tion will be gradually introduced into the ve-<lb break="no"/>ry interior of the country. The voyage of<lb break="yes"/>M. Valmis will thus remain for ever memora-<lb break="no"/>ble in the annals of history.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The arrival of the armed frigates in which<lb break="yes"/>M. Valmis made the circuit of the <placeName key="atlantik">Atlantic</placeName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and Pacific Oceans gave rise on several<lb break="yes"/>coasts to one of the most simple, and there-<lb break="no"/>fore most affecting ceremonies. The bishops,<lb break="yes"/>military governors, and persons of great dis-<lb break="no"/>tinction, repaired to the shore, where they<lb break="yes"/>took in their arms the children who were to<lb break="yes" />carry the cow-pox to the indigenous Ameri-<lb break="no"/>cans and the Malays of the Philippine islands,<lb break="yes"/>and followed with public acclamations, they<lb break="yes"/>laid at the foot of the altar those precious pre-<lb break="no"/>servative deposits, returning thanks to the<lb break="yes"/>Supreme Being for having been the witnesses<lb break="yes"/>of so happy an event. We must have some<lb break="yes"/>knowledge of the ravages occasioned by the<lb break="yes"/>small-pox in the torrid zone, and especially<lb break="yes"/>among a race of men whose physical consti-<lb break="no"/>tution seems adverse to cutaneous eruptions,<lb break="yes"/>in order to feel all the importance of M.<lb break="yes"/>Jenner&#x2019;s discovery. It is a much greater<lb break="yes"/>blessing for the equinoxial part of the new con-<lb break="no"/>tinent than for the temperate climate of the<lb break="yes"/>old.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It was accidently discovered in the course<lb break="yes"/>of the same epidemic in 1802, that the <choice>
                        <sic>bene</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">bene-</corr>
                    </choice>
                    <lb break="yes"/>ficent effect of vaccination had been long<lb break="yes" />known to the country people among the Pe-<lb break="no"/>ruvian <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>. A negro slave had been ino-<lb break="no" />culated for the small-pox in the house of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="valleumbroso_md">Marquis de Valleumbroso</persName> who showed no<lb break="yes"/>symptom of the disease. They were going<lb break="yes" />to repeat the inoculation, when the young<lb break="yes"/>man told them that he was certain of never<lb break="yes"/>having the small-pox, because in milking cows,<lb break="yes"/>in the Cordellera of the <placeName key="anden" >Andes</placeName> he had had a sort<lb break="yes"/>of cutaneous eruption, caused, as the Indian<lb break="yes"/>herdsmen said, by the contact of certain tu-<lb break="no"/>bercles sometimes found on the udders of cows.<lb break="yes"/>Those who have had this eruption, said the<lb break="yes" />negro, never take the small-pox. The Afri-<lb break="no"/>cans, and especially the Indians, display great<lb break="yes"/>sagacity in observing the character, habits,<lb break="yes"/>and diseases of the animals with which they<lb break="yes"/>live. We need not therefore be astonished,<lb break="yes" />that, on the introduction of horned cattle<lb break="yes"/>into <placeName key="amerika">America</placeName>, the lower people remarked,<lb break="yes" />that the pustules on the udders of cows com-<lb break="no"/>municated to the herdsmen a species of benig-<lb break="no"/>nant small pox, and that those once infected are<lb break="yes"/>secure from the general contagion during the<lb break="yes"/>epochs when the disease is epidemical.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 