<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On the Volcanoes of Jorullo</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:48</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">II.71</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1809-Description_du_volcan-09-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1809-Description_du_volcan-01.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1809-Description_du_volcan-02.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1809-Description_du_volcan-03.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1809-Description_du_volcan-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1809-Description_du_volcan-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1809-Description_du_volcan-06.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1809-Description_du_volcan-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1809-Description_du_volcan-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1809-Description_du_volcan-09-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1809-Description_du_volcan-10.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1809-Description_du_volcan-11.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1809-Description_du_volcan-12.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On the Volcanoes of Jorullo</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1811</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The New Annual Register, or General Repository of History, Politics, and Literature, for the year 1810&lt;/i&gt; (1811), S. 224–227.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Schmuck: Initialen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="224" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">On the Volcanoes of Jorullo.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>[From <hi rendition="#k">
                        <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>&#x2019;s Essay</hi> on <hi rendition="#k">New Spain.</hi>]</head>
                <lb break="yes"/><cb/>
                <p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#in">T</hi>HE grand catastrophe in<lb break="yes"/>which this volcanic moun-<lb break="no"/>tain issued from the earth, and by<lb break="yes"/>which the face of a considerable<lb break="yes"/>extent of ground was totally alter-<lb break="no"/>ed, was perhaps one of the most<lb break="yes"/>extensive physical changes, that<lb break="yes"/>the history of our globe exhibits.<lb break="yes"/>Geology points out spots in the<lb break="yes"/>ocean, where, within the last two<lb break="yes"/>thousand years, volcanic islets have<lb break="yes"/>arisen above the surface of the sea,<lb break="yes"/>as near the <placeName key="azoren">Azores</placeName>, in the Archi-<lb break="no"/>pelago, and on the south of Ice-<lb break="no" />land: but it records no instance of<lb break="yes"/>a mountain of scori&#x00E6; and ashes,<lb break="yes"/>517 met. [563 yards] above the old<lb break="yes"/>level of the neighbouring plains,<lb break="yes"/>suddenly formed in the centre of a<lb break="yes"/>thousand small burning cones, thir-<lb break="no"/>ty-six leagues from the seashore,<lb break="yes"/>and forty-two leagues from any<lb break="yes"/>other volcano. This phenomenon<lb break="yes" />remained unknown to the miner-<lb break="no"/>alogists and natural philosophers of<lb break="yes"/>Europe, though it took place but<lb break="yes" />fifty years ago, and within six days<lb break="yes"/>journey of the capital of Mexico.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Descending from the central<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>flat toward the coasts of the Pacific<lb break="yes"/>ocean, a vast plain extends from<lb break="yes"/>the hills of <placeName key="aguasarco" >Aguasarco</placeName> to the vil-<lb break="no"/>lages of Toipa, and Patatlan, equally<lb break="yes"/>celebrated for their fine cotton plan-<lb break="no"/>tations. Between the picachos del<lb break="yes"/>Mortero and the cerras de las Cuevas<lb break="yes"/>and de Cuiche, this plain is only<lb break="yes"/>from 750 to 800 met. [820 to 880<lb break="yes"/>yards] above the level of the sea.<lb break="yes"/>Basaltic hills rise in the midst of a<lb break="yes"/>country, in which porphyry with<lb break="yes"/>base of green-stone predominates.<lb break="yes"/>Their summits are crowned with<lb break="yes"/>oaks always in verdure, and the fo-<lb break="no"/>liage of laurels and olives inter-<lb break="no"/>mingled with dwarf fan palms.<lb break="yes"/>This beautiful vegetation forms a<lb break="yes"/>singular contrast with the arid plain,<lb break="yes"/>which has been laid waste by vol-<lb break="no"/>canic fire.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;To the middle of the eighteenth<lb break="yes"/>century fields of sugar-canes and<lb break="yes"/>indigo extended between two rivu-<lb break="no" />lets, called Cuitimba and San Pedro.<lb break="yes"/>They were skirted by basaltic moun-<lb break="no"/>tains, the structure of which seems<lb break="yes" />to indicate, that all the country, in<lb break="yes"/>remote periods, has several times<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">experinced</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="225" facs="#f0002"/><cb/>experienced the violent action of<lb break="yes" />volcanoes. These fields, irrigated<lb break="yes"/>by art, belonged to the estate of<lb break="yes"/>San Pedro de Jorullo (Xorullo, or<lb break="yes" />Juvriso), one of the largest and most<lb break="yes"/>valuable in the country. In the<lb break="yes"/>month of June, 1759, fearful rum-<lb break="no"/>bling noises were accompanied with<lb break="yes"/>frequent shocks of an earthquake,<lb break="yes"/>which succeeded each other at in-<lb break="no" />tervals for fifty or sixty days, and<lb break="yes"/>threw the inhabitants of the estate<lb break="yes"/>into the greatest consternation. From<lb break="yes" />the beginning of the month of Sep-<lb break="no"/>tember, every thing seemed per-<lb break="no"/>fectly quiet, when in the night of<lb break="yes"/>the 28th of that month a terrible<lb break="yes"/>subterranean noise was heard anew.<lb break="yes"/>The frightened Indians fled to the<lb break="yes" />mountains of <placeName key="aguasarco">Aguasarco</placeName>. A space<lb break="yes"/>of three or four square miles, known<lb break="yes"/>by the name of Malpays, rose in<lb break="yes"/>the shape of a bladder. The boun-<lb break="no"/>daries of this rising are still distin-<lb break="no"/>guishable in the ruptured strata.<lb break="yes"/>The Malpays towards the edge is<lb break="yes"/>only 12 met. [13 yards] above the<lb break="yes"/>former level of the plain, called las<lb break="yes"/>playas de Jorullo; but the con-<lb break="no"/>vexity of the ground increases pro-<lb break="no"/>gressively toward the centre, till it<lb break="yes"/>reaches the height of 160 met. [175<lb break="yes"/>yards].</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;They who witnessed this grand<lb break="yes"/>catastrophe from the top of <placeName key="aguasarco">Agua-<lb break="no"/>sarco</placeName> assert, that they saw flames<lb break="yes"/>issue out of the ground for the<lb break="yes"/>space of more than half a league<lb break="yes"/>square; that fragments of red hot<lb break="yes"/>rocks were thrown to a prodigious<lb break="yes"/>height; and that through a thick<lb break="yes"/>cloud of ashes, illumined by the<lb break="yes"/>volcanic fire, and resembling a<lb break="yes"/>stormy sea, the softened crust of<lb break="yes"/>the earth was seen to swell up. The<lb break="yes"/>rivers of Cuitimba and San Pedro<lb break="yes"/>then precipitated themselves into<lb break="yes"/>the burning crevices. The decom-<lb break="no"/>position of the water contributed to<lb break="yes"/>reanimate the flames, which were<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>perceptible at the city of Pascuoro,<lb break="yes"/>though standing on a very wide<lb break="yes"/>plain 1400 met. [1530 yards] above<lb break="yes"/>the level of the playas de Jorullo.<lb break="yes"/>Eruptions of mud, particularly of<lb break="yes"/>the strata of clay including decom-<lb break="no"/>posed nodules of basaltes with con-<lb break="no"/>centric layers, seem to prove, that<lb break="yes"/>subterranean waters had no small<lb break="yes"/>part in this extraordinary revolu-<lb break="no"/>tion. Thousands of small cones,<lb break="yes"/>only two or three yards high, which<lb break="yes"/>the Indians call ovens, issued from<lb break="yes"/>the raised dome of the Malpays.<lb break="yes"/>Though the heat of these volcanic<lb break="yes"/>ovens has diminished greatly within<lb break="yes"/>these fifteen years, according to the<lb break="yes"/>testimony of the Indians, I found<lb break="yes"/>the thermometer rise to 95&#x00B0; [if cen-<lb break="no"/>tig. 203&#x00B0; F.] in the crevices that<lb break="yes"/>emitted an aqueous vapour. Each<lb break="yes"/>little cone is a chimney, from which<lb break="yes"/>a thick smoke rises to the height of<lb break="yes"/>ten or fifteen met. [11 or 16 yards.]<lb break="yes"/>In several a subterranean noise is<lb break="yes"/>heard like that of some fluid boiling<lb break="yes"/>at no great depth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Amid these ovens, in a fissure,<lb break="yes"/>the direction of which is from<lb break="yes"/>N. N. E. to S. S. E, six large hum-<lb break="no" />mocks rise 400 or 500 met. [440 or<lb break="yes"/>550 yards] above the old level of<lb break="yes"/>the plain. This is the phenomenon<lb break="yes"/>of Monte Novo at Naples repeated<lb break="yes"/>several times in a row of volcanic<lb break="yes"/>hills. The loftiest of these huge<lb break="yes" />hummocks, which reminded me of<lb break="yes"/>the country of <placeName key="auvergne">Auvergne</placeName>, is the<lb break="yes"/>large volcano of Jorullo. It is con-<lb break="no"/>stantly burning, and has thrown<lb break="yes"/>out on the north side an immense<lb break="yes"/>quantity of scorified and basaltic<lb break="yes"/>lava, including fragments of pri-<lb break="no"/>mitive rocks. These grand erup-<lb break="no"/>tions of the central volcano con-<lb break="no"/>tinued till February 1760. In the<lb break="yes"/>succeeding years they became gra-<lb break="no"/>dually less frequent. The In-<lb break="no"/>dians, alarmed by the horrible noise<lb break="yes"/>of the new volcano, at first deserted<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="220" facs="#f0003"/>the villages for seven or eight leagues<lb break="yes"/>round the plain of Jorullo. In a<lb break="yes"/>few months they became familiar<lb break="yes"/>with the alarming sight, returned<lb break="yes"/>to their huts, and went down to the<lb break="yes"/>mountains of <placeName key="aguasarco">Aguasarco</placeName> and Santa<lb break="yes" />Ines, to admire the sheaves of fire<lb break="yes"/>thrown out by an infinite number<lb break="yes"/>of large and small volcanic open-<lb break="no" />ings. The ashes then covered the<lb break="yes"/>houses of Queretoro, more than 48<lb break="yes"/>leagues [120 miles] in a right line<lb break="yes"/>from the place of the explosion.<lb break="yes"/>Though the subterranean fire ap-<lb break="no"/>pears to be in no great activity at<lb break="yes"/>present, and the Malpays and the<lb break="yes"/>great volcano begin to be covered<lb break="yes"/>with vegetables, we found the air<lb break="yes"/>so heated by the little ovens, that in<lb break="yes"/>the shade, and at a considerable<lb break="yes"/>distance from the ground, the ther-<lb break="no"/>mometer rose to 43&#x00B0; [109&#x00B7;4&#x00B0; F].<lb break="yes"/>This fact evinces, that there is no<lb break="yes"/>exaggeration in the report of some<lb break="yes"/>of the old Indians, who say, that<lb break="yes"/>the plains of Jorullo were unin-<lb break="no"/>habitable for several years, and even<lb break="yes"/>to a considerable distance from the<lb break="yes"/>ground raised up, on account of the<lb break="yes"/>excessive heat.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Near the cerro of Santa Ines<lb break="yes"/>the traveller is still shown the rivers<lb break="yes"/>of Cuitimba and San Pedro, the<lb break="yes"/>limpid waters of which formerly<lb break="yes"/>refreshed the sugar-canes on the<lb break="yes"/>estate of Don <persName key="pimantel_a">Andrew Pimantel</persName>.<lb break="yes"/>These springs were lost in the<lb break="yes"/>night of the 29th of September,<lb break="yes"/>1759: but 2000 met. [near 2200<lb break="yes"/>yards] to the westward, in the soil<lb break="yes"/>that has been elevated, two rivulets<lb break="yes"/>are seen to break out of the clayey<lb break="yes"/>dome of the furnaces, exhibit-<lb break="no"/>ing themselves as thermal waters,<lb break="yes"/>in which the thermometer rises to<lb break="yes"/>52&#x00B7;7&#x00B0; [126&#x00B7;86&#x00B0; F.]. The Indians<lb break="yes"/>still give these the names of San<lb break="yes"/>Pedro and Cuitimba, because in se-<lb break="no"/>veral parts of the Malpays large<lb break="yes"/>bodies of water are supposed to be<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>heard running from east to west,<lb break="yes"/>from mountains of Santa Ines<lb break="yes"/>to the estate of the Presentation.<lb break="yes"/>Near this estate is a brook, that<lb break="yes"/>emits the sulphuretted hidrogen gas:<lb break="yes"/>it is more than 7 met. [near 8 yards]<lb break="yes" />wide, and is the most copious hidro-<lb break="no"/>sulphurous spring I ever saw.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In the opinion of the natives<lb break="yes"/>these extraordinary changes I have<lb break="yes"/>described, the crust of earth raised<lb break="yes"/>and cracked by volcanic fire, the<lb break="yes"/>mountains of scori&#x00E6; and ashes heap-<lb break="no"/>ed up, are the works of monks;<lb break="yes"/>the greatest, no doubt, they ever<lb break="yes"/>produced in either hemisphere. Our<lb break="yes"/>Indian host, at the hut we inhabited<lb break="yes"/>in the plain of Jorullo, told us,<lb break="yes"/>that some missionary capuchins<lb break="yes"/>preached at the estate of San Pedro,<lb break="yes"/>and, not meeting a favourable re-<lb break="no"/>ception, uttered the most horri-<lb break="no"/>ble and complicated imprecations<lb break="yes"/>against this plain, then so beautiful<lb break="yes"/>and fertile. They prophesied, that<lb break="yes"/>the estate should first be swallowed<lb break="yes"/>up by flames issuing out of the<lb break="yes"/>bowels of the Earth; and that the<lb break="yes"/>air should afterward be cooled to<lb break="yes"/>such a degree, that the neighbour-<lb break="no"/>ing mountains should remain for<lb break="yes"/>ever covered with ice and snow.<lb break="yes"/>The first of these maledictions hav-<lb break="no"/>ing been so fatally verified, the<lb break="yes"/>common people foresee in the gra-<lb break="no"/>dual cooling of the volcano the<lb break="yes"/>presage of a perpetual winter. I<lb break="yes"/>have thought it right to mention<lb break="yes"/>this vulgar tradition, worthy a place<lb break="yes"/>in the epic poem of the jesuit <persName key="landivar_rsj">Lan-<lb break="no"/>divar</persName>, because it exhibits a striking<lb break="yes"/>feature of the manners and preju-<lb break="no"/>dices of these remote countries. It<lb break="yes"/>shows the active industry of a class<lb break="yes"/>of men, who, too frequently abusing<lb break="yes"/>the credulity of the people, and pre-<lb break="no" />tending to possess the power of<lb break="yes"/>suspending the immutable laws of<lb break="yes"/>nature, know how to avail them-<lb break="no"/>selves of every event for establish-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">ing</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="227" facs="#f0004"/>ing their empire by the fear of phy-<lb break="no" />sical evil.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The situation of the new vol-<lb break="no"/>cano of Jorullo leads to a very cu-<lb break="no"/>rious geological observation. It has<lb break="yes" />already been observed in the third<lb break="yes"/>chapter, that there is in New Spain<lb break="yes"/>a line of great heights, or a narrow<lb break="yes" />zone included between the latitudes<lb break="yes"/>of 18&#x00B0; 59&#x2032; and 19&#x00B0; 12&#x2032;, in which<lb break="yes"/>are all the summits of <placeName key="anahuac">Anahuac</placeName> that<lb break="yes"/>rise above the region of perpetual<lb break="yes"/>snow. These summits are either<lb break="yes" />volcanoes still actually burning; or<lb break="yes"/>mountains, the form of which, as<lb break="yes"/>well as the nature of their rocks,<lb break="yes" />renders it extremely probable, that<lb break="yes"/>they formerly contained subter-<lb break="no"/>ranean fire. Setting out from the<lb break="yes" />coast of the Gulf of Mexico, and<lb break="yes"/>procceding westward, we find the<lb break="yes"/>peak of Oribaza, the two volcanoes<lb break="yes"/>of la Puebla, the Nevado de Toluca,<lb break="yes"/>the peak of Tancitaro, and the<lb break="yes"/>volcano of Colima. These great<lb break="yes"/>heights, instead of forming the ridge<lb break="yes"/>of the cordillera of <placeName key="anahuac">Anahuac</placeName>, and<lb break="yes"/>following its direction, which is<lb break="yes"/>from S. E. to N. W., are on the<lb break="yes"/>contrary in a line perpendicular to<lb break="yes"/>the axis of the great chain of moun-<lb break="no"/>tains. It is certainly worthy remark,<lb break="yes"/>that in the year 1759 the new vol-<lb break="no"/>cano of Jorullo was formed in the<lb break="yes"/>continuation of this line, and on<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>the same parallel as the ancient<lb break="yes"/>Mexican volcanoes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;A view of my plan of the en-<lb break="no"/>virons of Jorullo will show, that<lb break="yes"/>the six large hummocks have risen<lb break="yes"/>out of the earth on a vein, that<lb break="yes"/>crosses the plain from the cerro of<lb break="yes"/>las Cuevas to the pichaco del Mon-<lb break="no"/>tero. The new mouths of Vesuvius<lb break="yes"/>too are found ranged along a fissure.<lb break="yes"/>Do not these analogies give us rea-<lb break="no" />son to suppose, that there exists in<lb break="yes"/>this part of Mexico, at a great depth<lb break="yes"/>within the Earth, a fissure stretch-<lb break="no" />ing from east to west through a<lb break="yes"/>space of 137 leagues [343 miles],<lb break="yes"/>and through which the volcanic fire<lb break="yes" />has made its way at different times,<lb break="yes"/>bursting the outer crust of porphy-<lb break="no"/>ritic rocks, from the coasts of the<lb break="yes" />Gulf of Mexico to the South Sea?<lb break="yes"/>Is this fissure prolonged to that little<lb break="yes"/>groupe of islands, called by <persName key="collnet_j">Colluet</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="archipelderevillagigedo">the Archipelago of Regigedo</placeName>, and<lb break="yes"/>round which, in the same parallel<lb break="yes"/>with the Mexican volcanoes, pumice<lb break="yes"/>stone has been seen floating? Na-<lb break="no"/>turalists who distinguish the facts<lb break="yes"/>offered by descriptive mineralogy<lb break="yes"/>from theoretical reveries concerning<lb break="yes"/>the primitive state of our planet will<lb break="yes"/>pardon me for having consigned<lb break="yes"/>these observations to the general<lb break="yes"/>Map of New Spain, contained in<lb break="yes"/>the Mexican Atlas.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 