<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023299100">
                        <surname>Clark</surname>
                        <forename>Rex</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="stoeckli_mt">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stöckli</surname>
                        <forename>Matthias Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="schnidrig_bf">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schnidrig</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara Franziska</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.5.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.4.0" when="2018-09-28" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Personenmarkierung abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.3.0" when="2018-09-27" who="stoeckli_mt">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Personen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2018-09-27" who="schnidrig_bf">Markup: added placeName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Orte.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">
                        <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>&#x2019;s History of New Spain.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The &#x201C;Literary Panorama&#x201D; contains a very<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#et">excellent review of <hi rendition="#i">
                            <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>&#x2019;s Political<lb break="yes"/>Essay on the Kingdom of New Spain.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>We shall present our readers with fre-<lb break="no"/>quent extracts from this valuable track<lb break="yes"/>of information. At present we have only<lb break="yes"/>room for the following: <hi rendition="#i">Bos. Gaz.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">
                            <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>he</hi>
                    </hi> condition of man is the most in-<lb break="no"/>teresting object in every country; and we<lb break="yes"/>confess ourselves gratified by finding that<lb break="yes"/>in New Spain the number of slaves [ne-<lb break="no"/>groes] is comparatively few, and the state<lb break="yes"/>of the Indians is less unhappy than we had<lb break="yes"/>been accustomed to suppose. We extract<lb break="yes"/>with pleasure a passage from which it ap-<lb break="no"/>pears that the mines, though a considera-<lb break="no"/>ble source of wealth, are not the only, or<lb break="yes"/>even the <hi rendition="#i">chief</hi> wealth of the province of<lb break="yes"/>Mexico.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The Indian cultivator is poor, but he<lb break="yes"/>is free. His state is even greatly prefera-<lb break="no"/>ble to that of the peasantry in a greater<lb break="yes"/>part of the north of Europe. There are<lb break="yes"/>neither corvees nor villanage in New Spain;<lb break="yes"/>and the number of slaves is next to nothing.<lb break="yes"/>Sugar is chiefly the produce of free hands.<lb break="yes"/>There the principal objects of agriculture<lb break="yes"/>are not the productions to which European<lb break="yes"/>luxury has assigned a variable and arbi-<lb break="no"/>trary value, but cereal gramina, nutrive<lb break="yes"/>roots, and the agave, the vine of the In-<lb break="no"/>dians. The appearance of the country<lb break="yes"/>proclaims to the traveller, that the soil<lb break="yes" />nourishes him who cultivates it, and that<lb break="yes"/>the true prosperity of the Mexican people<lb break="yes"/>neither depends on the accidents of foreign<lb break="yes"/>commerce, nor on the unruly politicks of<lb break="yes"/>Europe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Those who only know the interiour of<lb break="yes"/>the Spanish colonies from the vague and<lb break="yes"/>uncertain notions hitherto published, will<lb break="yes"/>have some difficulty in believing that the<lb break="yes" />principal sources of the Mexican riches<lb break="yes"/>are by no means the mines; but an agri-<lb break="no"/>culture which has been gradually ameli-<lb break="no"/>orating since the end of the last century.<lb break="yes" />Without reflecting on the immense extent<lb break="yes"/>of the country, and especially the great<lb break="yes"/>number of provinces which appear totally<lb break="yes"/>destitute of precious metals, we generally<lb break="yes" />imagine that all the activity of the Mexi-<lb break="no"/>can population is directed to the working<lb break="yes"/>of the mines. Because the agriculture has<lb break="yes"/>made a very considerable progress in the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">capitania general</hi> of Caraccas, in the king-<lb break="no"/>dom of Guatimala, the island of Cuba,<lb break="yes"/>and wherever the mountains are accounted<lb break="yes"/>poor in mineral productions, it has been<lb break="yes"/>inferred that it is to the working of the<lb break="yes"/>mines that we are to attribute the small<lb break="yes" />care bestowed on the cultivation of the<lb break="yes"/>soil in other parts of the Spanish colonies.<lb break="yes"/>This reasoning is just when applied to<lb break="yes"/>small portions of territory. No doubt, in<lb break="yes"/>the provinces of Chaco and Antioqua, and<lb break="yes"/>the coast of Barbacoas, the inhabitants are<lb break="yes"/>fonder of seeking for gold washed down in<lb break="yes"/>the brooks and ravines, than of cultivating<lb break="yes"/>a virgin and fertile soil; and in the begin-<lb break="no"/>ning of the conquest, the Spaniards who<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>abandoned the peninsula or Canary islands,<lb break="yes"/>to settle in Peru and Mexico, had no other<lb break="yes"/>view but the discovery of the precious<lb break="yes"/>metals. <hi rendition="#i">Auri rabida sitis a cultura His-<lb break="no"/>panos divertit,</hi> says a writer of those<lb break="yes"/>times, Pedro Martyr, in his work on the<lb break="yes" />discovery of Yutacan and the colonization<lb break="yes"/>of the <placeName key="antillen">Antilles</placeName>.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In Mexico, the best cultivated fields,<lb break="yes"/>those which recall to the mind of the tra-<lb break="no"/>veller the beautiful plains of France, are<lb break="yes"/>those which extend from Salamanca to-<lb break="no" />wards Siloe, Guanaxuato, and the Villa de<lb break="yes"/>Leon, and, which surround the richest<lb break="yes"/>mines of the known world. Wherever<lb break="yes"/>metallick seams have been discovered in<lb break="yes" />the most uncultivated parts of the Cordil-<lb break="no"/>leras, on the insulated and desert table-<lb break="no"/>lands, the working of mines, far from im-<lb break="no"/>peding the cultivation of the soil, has been<lb break="yes"/>singularly favourable to it. Travelling<lb break="yes"/>along the ridge of the <placeName key="anden">Andes</placeName>, or the moun-<lb break="no"/>tainous part of Mexico, we every where<lb break="yes"/>see the most striking examples of the ben-<lb break="no"/>eficial influence of the mines on agricul-<lb break="no"/>ture. Were it not for the establishments<lb break="yes"/>formed for the working of the mines, how<lb break="yes"/>many places would have remained desert?<lb break="yes"/>How many districts uncultivated in the four<lb break="yes"/>intendancies of Guanaxuato, Zacatecas,<lb break="yes"/>San Luis Potosi, and Durango, between the<lb break="yes"/>parallels of 21 and 25 where the most con-<lb break="no" />siderable metallick wealth of New Spain is<lb break="yes"/>to be found? If the town is placed on the<lb break="yes"/>arid side, or the crest of the Cordilleras,<lb break="yes"/>the new colonists can only draw from a dis-<lb break="no"/>tance the means of their subsistence, and<lb break="yes"/>the maintenance of the great number of<lb break="yes"/>cattle employed in drawing off the water,<lb break="yes"/>and raising and amalgamating the mineral<lb break="yes"/>produce. <choice><sic>What</sic><corr type="editorial">Want</corr></choice> soon awakens industry.&#x2014;<lb break="yes" />The soil begins to be cultivated in the ra-<lb break="no"/>vines and declivities of the neighbouring<lb break="yes"/>mountains, wherever the rock is covered<lb break="yes"/>with earth. Farms are established in the<lb break="yes"/>neighbourhood of the mine. The high<lb break="yes"/>price of provision, from the competition of<lb break="yes"/>the purchasers indemnifies the cultivator<lb break="yes"/>for the privations to which he is exposed,<lb break="yes"/>from the hard life of the mountains. Thus,<lb break="yes"/>from the hope of gain alone, and the mo-<lb break="no"/>tives of mutual interest, which are the<lb break="yes"/>most powerful bonds of society, and with-<lb break="no"/>out any interference on the part of the gov-<lb break="no" />ernment in colonization, a mine which, at<lb break="yes"/>first, appeared insulated in the midst of<lb break="yes"/>wild and desert mountains, becomes, in a<lb break="yes"/>short time, connected with the lands which<lb break="yes" />have long been under cultivation.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="1" facs="#f0002"/>
                <cb/>
            </div>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">
                        <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>&#x2019;s History of New Spain.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">[<hi rendition="#i">Extracts continued.</hi>]</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">
                            <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>he</hi>
                    </hi> valley in which the city of Mex-<lb break="no"/>ico stands, is upwards of 6500 feet above<lb break="yes"/>the level of the sea. It is of an oval form,<lb break="yes"/>encompassed on all sides by mountains. It<lb break="yes" />contains several lakes. The largest is<lb break="yes"/>salt. Formerly it surrounded the city,<lb break="yes"/>which was approached only by causeways,<lb break="yes"/>constructed in the water. But, at present,<lb break="yes"/>the extent of this lake is diminished, and<lb break="yes"/>the city is now on the land, at some dis-<lb break="no"/>tance from the water&#x2019;s edge. The cir-<lb break="no"/>cumference of the valley is 67 leagues.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Mexico is undoubtedly one of the finest<lb break="yes"/>cities ever built by Europeans in either<lb break="yes"/>hemisphere. With the exception of Pe-<lb break="no"/>tersburgh, Berlin, Philadelphia, and some<lb break="yes" />quarters in Westminster, there does not<lb break="yes"/>exist a city of the same extent, which can<lb break="yes"/>be compared to the capital of New Spain,<lb break="yes"/>for the uniform level of the ground on<lb break="yes" />which it stands, for the regularity and<lb break="yes"/>breadth of the streets, and the extent of<lb break="yes"/>the publick places. The architecture is<lb break="yes"/>generally of a very pure style, and there<lb break="yes" />are even edifices of very beautiful struc-<lb break="no"/>ture. The exteriour of the houses is not<lb break="yes"/>loaded with ornaments.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The Ballustrades and gates are all of<lb break="yes"/>Biscay iron, ornamented with bronze, and<lb break="yes"/>the houses, instead of roofs, have terraces<lb break="yes"/>like those in Italy, and other southern<lb break="yes"/>countries.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Mexico has been very much embellish-<lb break="no"/>ed since the residence of the Abbe <persName key="chappedauteroche_j">Chappe</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>there, in 1769. The edifice destined to the<lb break="yes" />School of Mines, for which the richest in-<lb break="no"/>habitants of the country furnished a sum<lb break="yes"/>of more than three millions of francks,<lb break="yes"/>would adorn the principal places of Paris<lb break="yes"/>or London. Two great palaces (hotels)<lb break="yes"/>were recently constructed by Mexican ar-<lb break="no"/>tists, pupils of the academy of fine arts of<lb break="yes"/>the capital. One of these palaces, in the<lb break="yes"/>quarter <hi rendition="#i">della Traspana,</hi> exhibited in the<lb break="yes"/>interiour of a court a very beautiful oval<lb break="yes"/>peristyle of coupled columns. The tra-<lb break="no"/>veller justly admires a vast circumference,<lb break="yes"/>paved with porphyry flags, and enclosed<lb break="yes"/>with an iron railing, richly ornamented<lb break="yes"/>with bronze, containing an equestrian sta-<lb break="no"/>tue of King <persName key="karliv">Charles the fourth</persName>, placed on<lb break="yes"/>a pedestal of Mexican marble, in the midst<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i"><choice><sic>Paza</sic><corr type="editorial">Plaza</corr></choice> Major</hi> of Mexico, opposite<lb break="yes"/>the cathedral, and the Viceroy&#x2019;s palace.<lb break="yes"/>However, it must be agreed, that notwith-<lb break="no"/>standing the progress of the arts, within<lb break="yes"/>these last thirty years, it is much less,<lb break="yes"/>from the grandeur and beauty of the monu-<lb break="no"/>ments, than from the breadth and straight-<lb break="no"/>ness of the streets, and much less from its<lb break="yes"/>edifices, than from its uniform regularity,<lb break="yes"/>its extent and position, that the capital of<lb break="yes" />New Spain attracts the admiration of Eu-<lb break="no"/>ropeans.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Nothing can present a more rich and<lb break="yes"/>varied appearance, than the valley, when,<lb break="yes"/>in a fine summer morning, the sky without<lb break="yes"/>a cloud, and of that deep azure which is<lb break="yes"/>peculiar to the dry and rarefied air of high<lb break="yes" />mountains, we transport ourselves to the<lb break="yes"/>top of one of the towers of the cathedral of<lb break="yes"/>Mexico, or ascend the hill of Chapoltepeck.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>A beautiful vegetation surrounds this hill.<lb break="yes"/>Old cypress trunks, of more than 15 and<lb break="yes"/>16 metres in circumference, raise their<lb break="yes"/>naked heads above those of the schinus,<lb break="yes" />which resemble, in their appearance, the<lb break="yes"/>weeping willows of the east. From the<lb break="yes"/>centre of this solitude, the summit of the<lb break="yes"/>porphyritical rock of Chapoltepeck, the<lb break="yes"/>eye sweeps over a vast plain of carefully<lb break="yes"/>cultivated fields, which extend to the very<lb break="yes"/>feet of the colossal mountains covered with<lb break="yes"/>perpetual snow. The city appears as if<lb break="yes" />washed by the waters of the lake of Tezeu-<lb break="no"/>co, whose basin, surrounded with villages<lb break="yes"/>and hamlets, brings to mind the most beau-<lb break="no"/>tiful lakes of the mountains of Switzerland.<lb break="yes"/>Large avenues of elms and poplars lead in<lb break="yes"/>every direction to the capital; and two<lb break="yes"/>acqueducts, constructed over arches of<lb break="yes"/>very great elevation, cross the plain, and<lb break="yes"/>exhibit an appearance equally agreeable<lb break="yes"/>and interesting. The magnificent convent<lb break="yes"/>of Nuestra Sonora de Guadaloupe, appears<lb break="yes"/>joined to the mountains of Tepeyacack,<lb break="yes"/>among ravines, which shelter a few date<lb break="yes"/>and young yucca trees. Towards the<lb break="yes"/>south, the whole tract between San Angle,<lb break="yes"/>Tacabaya, and San Augustin de las Cuevas<lb break="yes"/>appears an immense garden of orange,<lb break="yes"/>peach, apple, cherry, and other European<lb break="yes"/>fruit trees. This beautiful cultivation<lb break="yes"/>forms a singular contrast with the wild ap-<lb break="no"/>pearance of the naked mountains which<lb break="yes"/>enclose the valley, among which the fa-<lb break="no"/>mous volcanos of La Puebla, Popocatepelt,<lb break="yes"/>and Iztaccicolchuatl are the most distin-<lb break="no"/>guished. The first of these forms an enor-<lb break="no"/>mous cone, of which the crater, continual-<lb break="no"/>ly inflamed, and throwing up smoak and<lb break="yes"/>ashes, opens in the midst of eternal snows.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 