<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023299100">
                        <surname>Clark</surname>
                        <forename>Rex</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="stoeckli_mt">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stöckli</surname>
                        <forename>Matthias Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="schnidrig_bf">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schnidrig</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara Franziska</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.5.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.4.0" when="2018-09-28" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Personenmarkierung abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.3.0" when="2018-09-27" who="stoeckli_mt">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Personen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2018-09-27" who="schnidrig_bf">Markup: added placeName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Orte.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="50" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Account of the Eruption of the Volcano of Jo-<lb break="no" />rullo in Mexico.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">We have given the above abridged account of this remarkable vol-<lb break="no"/>cano, in reference to a new theory of its formation by Mr <persName key="scrope_01">Scrope</persName>, which<lb break="yes"/>forms the subject of the next Article. See <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>&#x2019;s <hi rendition="#i">Essai Politique<lb break="yes"/>sur la Nouvelle Espagne,</hi> his <hi rendition="#i">Essai Geognostique,</hi> p. 351, and his <hi rendition="#i">Rela-<lb break="no"/>tion Historique.</hi>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Ed.</hi>
                    </note> By <hi rendition="#k">Baron Alexander de <persName key="humboldt_av" >Humboldt</persName>.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>With a Section of the Mountain.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>o the east of the Pic de Tancitaro, the <hi rendition="#i">Volcan de Jorullo</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(Xorullo, or Juruyo) was formed in the night of the 29th<lb break="yes"/>September 1759. M. <persName key="bonpland_ajag" >Bonpland</persName> and myself reached its cra-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="51" facs="#f0002"/> ter on the 19th September 1803. The great catastrophe in<lb break="yes"/>which this mountain rose from the earth, and by which a con-<lb break="no"/>siderable extent of ground totally changed its appearance, is,<lb break="yes"/>perhaps, one of the most extraordinary physical revolutions in<lb break="yes"/>the annals of the history of our planet. Geology gives us no<lb break="yes"/>example of the formation, from the centre of a thousand<lb break="yes"/>small burning cones, of a mountain of scoria and ashes 517<lb break="yes"/>metres (1695 feet) in height, comparing it only with the level<lb break="yes"/>of the old adjoining plains in the interior of a continent, 36<lb break="yes"/>leagues distant from the coast, and more than 42 leagues<lb break="yes"/>from every other active volcano.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A vast plain extends from the hills of <placeName key="aguasarco" >Aguasarco</placeName> to near<lb break="yes"/>the villages of Teipa and Petatlan, both equally celebrated<lb break="yes"/>for their fine plantations of cotton. This plain, between the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Picachos del Mortero,</hi> the <hi rendition="#i">Cerros de las Cuevas, y de Cuiche,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>is only from 750 to 800 metres (from 2460 to 2624 feet)<lb break="yes"/>above the level of the sea. In the middle of a tract of ground<lb break="yes"/>in which porphyry, with a base of greenstone predominates,<lb break="yes"/>basaltic cones appear, the summits of which are crowned with<lb break="yes"/>evergreen oaks of a laurel and olive foliage, intermingled with<lb break="yes"/>small palm trees with flabelliform leaves. This beautiful ve-<lb break="no"/>getation forms a singular contrast with the aridity of the plain,<lb break="yes"/>which was laid waste by volcanic fire.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Till the middle of the 18th century, fields cultivated with<lb break="yes" />sugar-cane and indigo occupied the extent of ground between<lb break="yes" />the two brooks called Cuitamba and San Pedro. They were<lb break="yes" />bounded by basaltic mountains, of which the structure seems<lb break="yes"/>to indicate that all this country, at a very remote period, had<lb break="yes" />been already several times convulsed by volcanoes. These<lb break="yes" />fields, watered by artificial means, belonged to the plantation<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">(hacienda)</hi> of San Pedro de Jorullo, one of the greatest and<lb break="yes"/>richest of the country. In the month of June 1759, a sub-<lb break="no"/>terraneous noise was heard. Hollow noises of a most alarming<lb break="yes"/>nature <hi rendition="#i">(bramidos,)</hi> were accompanied by frequent earth-<lb break="no"/>quakes, which succeeded one another for from 50 to 60 days,<lb break="yes"/>to the great consternation of the inhabitants of the <hi rendition="#i">hacienda.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>From the beginning of September every thing seemed to an-<lb break="no"/>nounce the complete re-establishment of tranquillity, when, in<lb break="yes"/>the night between the 28th and 29th, the horrible subterrane-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="52" facs="#f0003"/> ous noise recommenced. The affrighted Indians fled to the<lb break="yes"/>mountains of <placeName key="aguasarco" >Aguasarco</placeName>. A tract of ground from three to four<lb break="yes" />square miles in extent, which goes by the name of <hi rendition="#i" >Malpays,</hi> rose<lb break="yes"/>up in the shape of a bladder. The bounds of this convulsion<lb break="yes"/>are still distinguishable in the fractured strata. The <hi rendition="#i">Malpays</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>near its edges is only 39 feet above the old level of the plain<lb break="yes"/>called the <hi rendition="#i">playas de Jorullo;</hi> but the convexity of the ground<lb break="yes"/>thus thrown up increases progressively towards the centre to<lb break="yes"/>an elevation of 524 feet. See Plate I. Fig. 6.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Those who witnessed this great catastrophe from the top<lb break="yes"/>of <placeName key="aguasarco">Aguasarco</placeName> assert that flames were seen to issue forth for<lb break="yes"/>an extent of more than half a square league, that fragments<lb break="yes"/>of burning rocks were thrown up to prodigious heights, and<lb break="yes"/>that, through a thick cloud of ashes, illumined by the volcanic<lb break="yes"/>fire, the softened surface of the earth was seen to swell up like<lb break="yes"/>an agitated sea. The rivers of Cuitamba and San Pedro pre-<lb break="no"/>cipitated themselves into the burning chasms. The decom-<lb break="no"/>position of the water contributed to invigorate the flames,<lb break="yes"/>which were distinguishable at the city of Pascuaro, though<lb break="yes"/>situated on a very extensive table land 1400 metres (4592 feet)<lb break="yes"/>elevated above the plains of <hi rendition="#i">las playas</hi> de Jorullo. Erup-<lb break="no"/>tions of mud, and especially of strata of clay, enveloping balls<lb break="yes"/>of decomposed basaltes in concentrical layers, appear to indi-<lb break="no"/>cate, that subterraneous water had no small share in produc-<lb break="no"/>ing this extraordinary revolution. Thousands of small cones,<lb break="yes"/>from two to three metres (from 6.5 feet to 9.8 feet) in height,<lb break="yes"/>called by the indigenes <hi rendition="#i">ovens</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">hornitos,</hi>) issued forth from the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Malpays.</hi> Although within the last fifteen years, according<lb break="yes"/>to the testimony of the Indians, the heat of these volcanic<lb break="yes"/>ovens has suffered a great diminution, I have seen the ther-<lb break="no"/>mometer rise to 95° (202° of Fahrenheit) on being plunged in-<lb break="no"/>to fissures which exhale an aqueous vapour. Each small cone<lb break="yes"/>is a <hi rendition="#i">fumarola,</hi> from which a thick vapour ascends to the<lb break="yes"/>height of ten or fifteen metres. In many of them a subter-<lb break="no"/>raneous noise is heard, which appears to announce the proxi-<lb break="no"/>mity of a fluid in ebullition.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the midst of the ovens six large masses, elevated from<lb break="yes"/>4 to 500 metres (from 312 to 1640 feet) each above the old<lb break="yes"/>level of the plains, sprung up from a chasm, of which the di-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="53" facs="#f0004"/> rection is from the N.N.E. to the S.S.E. This is the phe-<lb break="no"/>nomenon of the Montenovo of Naples, several times repeated<lb break="yes"/>in a range of volcanic hills. The most elevated of these enor-<lb break="no"/>mous masses, which bears some resemblance to the <hi rendition="#i">pays</hi> de<lb break="yes"/>l&#x2019;<placeName key="auvergne">Auvergne</placeName>, is the great Volcan de Jorullo. It is continually<lb break="yes"/>burning, and has thrown up from the north side an immense<lb break="yes"/>quantity of scorified and basaltic lavas, containing fragments<lb break="yes"/>of primitive rocks. These great eruptions of the central vol-<lb break="no"/>cano continued till the month of 1760. In the following<lb break="yes"/>years they became gradually less frequent. The Indians,<lb break="yes"/>frightened at the horrible noises of the new volcano, abandon-<lb break="no"/>ed, at first, all the villages situated within seven or eight<lb break="yes"/>leagues distance of the playas de Jorullo. They became<lb break="yes"/>gradually, however, accustomed to this terrific spectacle; and,<lb break="yes"/>having returned to their cottages, they advanced towards the<lb break="yes"/>mountains <placeName key="aguasarco" >Aguasarco</placeName> and Santa In&#x0304;es, to admire the streams<lb break="yes"/>of fire discharged from an infinity of great and small volcanic<lb break="yes"/>apertures. The roofs of the houses of Queretaro were then<lb break="yes"/>covered with ashes at a distance of more than 48 leagues in a<lb break="yes"/>straight line from the scene of the explosion. Although the<lb break="yes"/>subterraneous fire now appears far from violent,<note place="foot" n="*">We found, in the bottom of the crater, the air at 116°, 130°, and<lb break="yes"/>139° of Fahrenheit. We passed over crevices which exhaled a sulphu-<lb break="no"/>reous vapour, in which the thermometer rose to 185° Fahrenheit. The pas-<lb break="no"/>sage over these crevices and heaps of scoria, which cover considerable hol-<lb break="no" />lows, render the descent into the crater very dangerous.</note> and the<lb break="yes"/>Malpays, and the great volcano, begin to be covered with<lb break="yes"/>vegetables, we, nevertheless, found the ambient air heated to<lb break="yes"/>such a degree by the action of the small ovens (<hi rendition="#i">hornitos,</hi>) that<lb break="yes"/>the thermometer, at a great distance from the surface, and in<lb break="yes"/>the shade, rose as high as 48° (109° of Fahrenheit.) This<lb break="yes"/>fact appears to prove, that there is no exaggeration in the ac-<lb break="no"/>counts of several old Indians, who affirm that, for many<lb break="yes"/>years after the first eruption, the plains of Jorullo, even<lb break="yes"/>at a great distance from the scene of the explosion, were<lb break="yes"/>uninhabitable, from the excessive heat which prevailed in<lb break="yes"/>them.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The traveller is still shown, near the Cerro de Santa In&#x0304;es,<lb break="yes"/>the rivers of Cuitamba and San Pedro, of which the limpid<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="54" facs="#f0005"/> waters formerly watered the sugar-cane plantation of Don<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="pimantel_a">André Pimentel</persName>. These streams disappeared in the night of<lb break="yes"/>the 29th September 1759; but, at a distance of 2000 metres<lb break="yes"/>(6561 feet) farther west, in the tract which was the theatre<lb break="yes"/>of the convulsion, two rivers are now seen bursting through<lb break="yes"/>the argillaceous vault of the <hi rendition="#i" >hornitos,</hi> of the appearance of<lb break="yes"/>mineral waters, in which the thermometer rises to 52°,7<lb break="yes"/>(126°,8 of Fahrenheit.) The Indians continue to give them<lb break="yes"/>the names of San Pedro and Cuitamba, because, in several<lb break="yes"/>parts of the Malpays, great masses of water are heard to run<lb break="yes"/>in the direction from east to west, from the mountains of San-<lb break="no"/>ta In&#x0304;es towards <hi rendition="#i">l&#x2019;Hacienda de la Presentacion.</hi> Near this ha-<lb break="no"/>bitation there is a brook, which disengages itself from the sul-<lb break="no"/>phureous hydrogen. It is more than nine yards in breadth,<lb break="yes"/>and is the most abundant hydro-sulphureous spring which I<lb break="yes"/>have ever seen.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The position of the new Volcana de Jorullo gives rise to a<lb break="yes"/>very curious geological observation. In New Spain there is<lb break="yes"/>a <hi rendition="#i">parallel of great elevations,</hi> or a narrow zone contain-<lb break="no"/>ed between 18°, 59&#x2032; and 19°, 12&#x2032; of latitude, in which all the<lb break="yes"/>summits of <placeName key="anahuac" >Anahuac</placeName> which rise above the region of perpetual<lb break="yes" />snow are situated. These summits are either volcanoes which<lb break="yes" />still continue to burn, or mountains which, from their form,<lb break="yes" />as well as the nature of their rocks, have, in all probability,<lb break="yes" />formerly contained subterraneous fire. As we recede from<lb break="yes"/>the coast of the <placeName key="atlantik">Atlantic</placeName>, we find, in a direction from east to<lb break="yes"/>west, the Pic d&#x2019;Orizaba, the two volcanoes of la Puebla, the<lb break="yes"/>Nevada de Toluca, the Pic de Tancitaro, and the Volcan de<lb break="yes"/>Colima. These great elevations, in place of forming the<lb break="yes"/>crest of the Cordillera of <placeName key="anahuac">Anahuac</placeName>, and following its direc-<lb break="no" />tion, which is from the south-east to the north-west, are, on<lb break="yes" />the contrary, placed on a line perpendicular to the axis of the<lb break="yes" />great chain of mountains. It is undoubtedly worthy of ob-<lb break="no" />servation, that, in 1759, the new volcano of Jorullo was form-<lb break="no" />ed in the prolongation of that line, on the same parallel with<lb break="yes" />the ancient Mexican volcanoes!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A single glance bestowed on my plan of the environs of<lb break="yes"/>Jorullo will prove that the six large masses rose out of the<lb break="yes"/>earth, in a line which runs through the plain from the Cerro<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="55" facs="#f0006"/> de las Cuevas to the Picacho del Mortero; and it is thus also<lb break="yes"/>that the bocche nove of Vesuvius are ranged along the pro-<lb break="no"/>longation of a chasm. Do not these analogies entitle us to<lb break="yes"/>suppose that there exists, in this part of Mexico, at a great<lb break="yes"/>depth in the interior of the earth, a chasm in a direction<lb break="yes"/>from east to west, for a length of 137 leagues, along which<lb break="yes"/>the volcanic fire, bursting through the interior crust of the<lb break="yes"/>porphyritical rocks, has made its appearance at different<lb break="yes"/>epochas from the gulf of Mexico to the South Sea? Does<lb break="yes"/>this chasm extend to the small group of islands called by M.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName key="collnet_j">Collnet</persName> the <placeName key="archipelderevillagigedo">archipelago of Revillagigedo</placeName>, around which, in<lb break="yes"/>the same parallel with the Mexican volcanoes, pumice-stone<lb break="yes"/>has been seen floating? Those naturalists who make a dis-<lb break="no"/>tinction between the facts which are offered us by descrip-<lb break="no"/>tive geology and theoretical reveries on the primitive state of<lb break="yes"/>our planet, will forgive us these general observations on the<lb break="yes"/>general map of New Spain. Moreover, from the lake of<lb break="yes"/>Cuiseo, which is impregnated with muriate of soda, and<lb break="yes"/>which exhales sulphuretted hydrogen, as far as the city of Val-<lb break="no"/>ladolid, for an extent of 48 square leagues, there are a great<lb break="yes"/>quantity of hot wells, which generally contain only muriatic<lb break="yes"/>acid, without any vestiges of terreous sulphates or metallic salts.<lb break="yes"/>Such are the mineral waters of the Chucandiro, Cuinche, San<lb break="yes"/>Sebastian, and San Juan Tarraramco.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 