<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023299100">
                        <surname>Clark</surname>
                        <forename>Rex</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="stoeckli_mt">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stöckli</surname>
                        <forename>Matthias Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="schnidrig_bf">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schnidrig</surname>
                        <forename>Barbara Franziska</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Studentische Hilfskraft</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.5.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.4.0" when="2018-09-28" who="wernicke_nd">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Personenmarkierung abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.3.0" when="2018-09-27" who="stoeckli_mt">Markup: added persName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Personen.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2018-09-27" who="schnidrig_bf">Markup: added placeName. <note type="remarkRevision">Erster Durchgang Markierung der Orte.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="81" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Volcanoes of Jorullo; by</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Alexander <persName key="humboldt_av">Humboldt</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">Extracted from his Essay on New Spain. Journal de Physique,<lb break="yes"/>vol. LXIX, p. 149.</note>.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">
                            <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>he</hi>
                    </hi> grand catastrophe in which this volcanic mountain<note place="right">Large hill<lb break="yes"/>thrown up by a<lb break="yes"/>volcano in<lb break="yes"/>1759.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>issued from the earth, and by which the face of a consi-<lb break="no"/>derable extent of ground was totally altered, was perhaps<lb break="yes"/>one of the most extensive physical changes, that the history<lb break="yes"/>of our globe exhibits. Geology points out spots in the<lb break="yes"/>ocean, where, within the last two thousand years, volcanic<lb break="yes"/>islets have arisen above the surface of the sea, as near the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName key="azoren">Azores</placeName>, in the Archipelago, and on the south of Iceland:<lb break="yes"/>but it records no instance of a mountain of scori&#x00E6; and<lb break="yes"/>ashes, 517 met. [563 yards] above the old level of the<lb break="yes"/>neighbouring plains, suddenly formed in the centre of a<lb break="yes"/>thousand small burning cones, thirty-six leagues from the<lb break="yes"/>seashore, and forty-two leagues from any other volcano.<lb break="yes"/>This phenomenon remained unknown to the mineralogists<lb break="yes"/>and natural philosophers of Europe, though it took place<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">but</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="82" facs="#f0002"/> but fifty years ago, and within six days journey of the capi-<lb break="no"/>tal of Mexico.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <note place="left">Country de-<lb break="no"/>scribed.</note>
                <p>Descending from the central flat toward the coasts of the<lb break="yes"/>Pacific ocean, a vast plain extends from the hills of <placeName key="aguasarco" >Agua-<lb break="no"/>sarco</placeName> to the villages of Toipa, and Patatlan, equally cele-<lb break="no"/>lebrated for their fine cotton plantations. Between the<lb break="yes"/>picachos del Mortero and the cerras de las Cuevas and de<lb break="yes"/>Cuiche, this plain is only from 750 to 800 met. [820 to 880<lb break="yes"/>yards] above the level of the sea. Basaltic hills rise in the<lb break="yes"/>midst of a country, in which porphyry with base of green-<lb break="no"/>stone predominates. Their summits are crowned with oaks<lb break="yes"/>always in verdure, and the foliage of laurels and olives in-<lb break="no"/>termingled with dwarf fan palms. This beautiful vegeta-<lb break="no"/>tion forms a singular contrast with the arid plain, which<lb break="yes"/>has been laid waste by volcanic fire.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <note place="left">A fertile plain</note>
                <p>To the middle of the eighteenth century fields of sugar-<lb break="no"/>canes and indigo extended between two rivulets, called Cui-<lb break="no"/>timba and San Pedro. They were skirted by basaltic<lb break="yes"/>mountains, the structure of which seems to indicate, that<lb break="yes"/>all the country, in remote periods, has several times expe-<lb break="no"/>rienced the violent action of volcanoes. These fields, irri-<lb break="no"/>gated by art, belonged to the estate of San Pedro de Jo-<lb break="no"/>rullo (Xorullo, or Juvriso), one of the largest and most<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="left">shaken by an<lb break="yes"/>earthquake,</note>valuable in the country. In the month of June, 1759, fear-<lb break="no"/>ful rumbling noises were accompanied with frequent shocks<lb break="yes"/>of an earthquake, which succeeded each other at intervals<lb break="yes"/>for fifty or sixty days, and threw the inhabitants of the es-<lb break="no"/>tate into the greatest consternation. From the beginning<lb break="yes"/>of the month of September, every thing seemed perfectly<lb break="yes"/>quiet, when in the night of the 28th of that month a terri-<lb break="no"/>ble subterranean noise was heard anew. The frightened<lb break="yes"/>Indians fled to the mountains of <placeName key="aguasarco">Aguasarco</placeName>. A space of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="left">and a hill rais-<lb break="no"/>ed on it.</note>three or four square miles, known by the name of Malpays,<lb break="yes"/>rose in the shape of a bladder. The boundaries of this<lb break="yes"/>rising are still distinguishable in the ruptured strata. The<lb break="yes"/>Malpays towards the edge is only 12 met. [13 yards] above<lb break="yes"/>the former level of the plain, called las playas de Jorullo;<lb break="yes"/>but the convexity of the ground increases progressively<lb break="yes"/>toward the centre, till it reaches the height of 160 met.<lb break="yes"/>[175 yards].</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">They</fw>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="83" facs="#f0003"/>
                <p>They who witnessed this grand catastrophe from the top<note place="right">The event de-<lb break="no"/>scribed.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>of <placeName key="aguasarco">Aguasarco</placeName> assert, that they saw flames issue out of the<lb break="yes"/>ground for the space of more than half a league square;<lb break="yes"/>that fragments of red hot rocks were thrown to a prodigious<lb break="yes"/>height; and that through a thick cloud of ashes, illumined<lb break="yes"/>by the volcanic fire, and resembling a stormy sea, the soft-<lb break="no"/>ened crust of the earth was seen to swell up. The rivers<lb break="yes"/>of Cuitimba and San Pedro then precipitated themselves<lb break="yes"/>into the burning crevices. The decomposition of the water<lb break="yes"/>contributed to reanimate the flames, which were percepti-<lb break="no"/>ble at the city of Pascuoro, though standing on a very wide<lb break="yes"/>plain 1400 met. [1530 yards] above the level of the playas<lb break="yes"/>de Jorullo. Eruptions of mud, particularly of the strata<lb break="yes"/>of clay including decomposed nodules of basaltes with con-<lb break="no"/>centric layers, seem to prove, that subterranean waters had<lb break="yes"/>no small part in this extraordinary revolution. Thousands<lb break="yes"/>of small cones, only two or three yards high, which the<lb break="yes"/>Indians call ovens, issued from the raised dome of the Mal-<lb break="no"/>pays. Though the heat of these volcanic ovens has dimi-<lb break="no"/>nished greatly within these fifteen years, according to the<lb break="yes"/>testimony of the Indians, I found the thermometer rise to<lb break="yes"/>95° [if centig. 203° F.] in the crevices that emitted an<lb break="yes"/>aqueous vapour. Each little cone is a chimney, from which<lb break="yes"/>a thick smoke rises to the height of ten or fifteen met. [11<lb break="yes"/>or 16 yards]. In several a subterranean noise is heard like<lb break="yes"/>that of some fluid boiling at no great depth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Amid these ovens, in a fissure, the direction of which is<note place="right">Six large hills<lb break="yes"/>in one line.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>from N. N. E. to S. S. E., six large hummocks rise 400<lb break="yes"/>or 500 met. [440 or 550 yards] above the old level of the<lb break="yes"/>plain. This is the phenomenon of Monte Novo at Naples<lb break="yes"/>repeated several times in a row of volcanic hills. The lof-<lb break="no"/>tiest of these huge hummocks, which reminded me of the<lb break="yes"/>country of <placeName key="auvergne">Auvergne</placeName>, is the large volcano of Jorullo. It<lb break="yes"/>is constantly burning, and has thrown out on the north side<lb break="yes"/>an immense quantity of scorified and basaltic lava, includ-<lb break="no"/>ing fragments of primitive rocks. These grand eruptions<lb break="yes"/>of the central volcano continued till February, 1760. In<lb break="yes"/>the succeeding years they became gradually less frequent.<lb break="yes"/>The Indians, alarmed by the horrible noise of the new vol-<lb break="no"/>cano, at first deserted the villages for seven or eight leagues<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">round</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="84" facs="#f0004"/> round the plain of Jorullo. In a few months they became<lb break="yes"/>familiar with the alarming sight, returned to their huts,<lb break="yes"/>and went down to the mountains of <placeName key="aguasarco">Aguasarco</placeName> and Santa<lb break="yes"/>Ines, to admire the sheaves of fire thrown out by an infi-<lb break="no"/>nite number of large and small volcanic openings. The<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="left">Ashes carried<lb break="yes"/>to a great dis-<lb break="no" />tance.</note>ashes then covered the houses of Queretoro, more than 48<lb break="yes"/>leagues [120 miles] in a right line from the place of the ex-<lb break="no"/>plosion. Though the subterranean fire appears to be in no<lb break="yes"/>great activity <note place="foot" n="*">In the bottom of the crater we found the heat of the air 47°<lb break="yes"/>[116&#x00B7;6° F.], and in some places 58° and 60° [136&#x00B7;4° and 140°]. We<lb break="yes"/>had to pass over cracks exhaling sulphurous vapours, in which the<lb break="yes"/>thermometer rose to 85° [185°]. From these cracks, and the heaps<lb break="yes"/>of scori&#x00E6; that cover considerable hollows, the descent into the crater<lb break="yes"/>is not without danger.</note> at present, and the Malpays and the great<lb break="yes" />volcano begin to be covered with vegetables, we found the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="left">The air still<lb break="yes"/>heated by the<lb break="yes" />subterranean<lb break="yes"/>fire.</note>air so heated by the little ovens, that in the shade, and at a<lb break="yes"/>considerable distance from the ground, the thermometer<lb break="yes"/>rose to 43° [109&#x00B7;4° F.]. This fact evinces, that there is no<lb break="yes"/>exaggeration in the report of some of the old Indians, who<lb break="yes"/>say, that the plains of Jorullo were uninhabitable for seve-<lb break="no"/>ral years, and even to a considerable distance from the<lb break="yes"/>ground raised up, on account of the excessive heat.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <note place="left">Two rivers lost,</note>
                <p>Near the cerro of Santa Ines the traveller is still shown<lb break="yes"/>the rivers of Cuitimba and San Pedro, the limpid waters<lb break="yes"/>of which formerly refreshed the sugarcanes on the estate<lb break="yes"/>of Don <persName key="pimantel_a">Andrew Pimantel</persName>. These springs were lost in the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="left">and supposed to appear again much heated.</note>night of the 29th of September, 1759: but 2000 met.<lb break="yes"/>[near 2200 yards] to the westward, in the soil that has been<lb break="yes"/>elevated, two rivulets are seen to break out of the clayey<lb break="yes"/>dome of the furnaces, exhibiting themselves as thermal<lb break="yes"/>waters, in which the thermometer rises to 52&#x00B7;7° [126&#x00B7;86° F.].<lb break="yes"/>The Indians still give these the names of San Pedro and<lb break="yes"/>Cuitimba, because in several parts of the Malpays large<lb break="yes"/>bodies of water are supposed to be heard running from east<lb break="yes"/>to west, from the mountains of Santa Ines to the estate of<lb break="yes"/>the Presentation. Near this estate is a brook, that emits<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="left">Sulphurous<lb break="yes"/>water.</note>sulphuretted hidrogen gas: it is more than 7 met. [near 8<lb break="yes"/>yards] wide, and is the most copious hidrosulphurous spring<lb break="yes"/>I ever saw.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">In</fw>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="85" facs="#f0005"/>
                <p>In the opinion of the natives these extraordinary changes<note place="right">The catastro-<lb break="no"/>phe supposed<lb break="yes"/>owing to the<lb break="yes"/>vengeance of<lb break="yes"/>some monks.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>I have described, the crust of earth raised and cracked by<lb break="yes"/>volcanic fire, the mountains of scori&#x00E6; and ashes heaped up,<lb break="yes"/>are the works of monks; the greatest, no doubt, they ever<lb break="yes"/>produced in either hemisphere. Our Indian host, at the<lb break="yes"/>hut we inhabited in the plain of Jorullo, told us, that some<lb break="yes"/>missionary capuchins preached at the estate of San Pedro,<lb break="yes"/>and, not meeting a favourable reception, uttered the most<lb break="yes"/>horrible and complicated imprecations against this plain,<lb break="yes"/>then so beautiful and fertile. They prophesied, that the<lb break="yes"/>estate should first be swallowed up by flames issuing out of<lb break="yes"/>the bowels of the Earth; and that the air should afterward<lb break="yes"/>be cooled to such a degree, that the neighbouring moun-<lb break="no"/>tains should remain for ever covered with ice and snow.<lb break="yes"/>The first of these maledictions having been so fatally veri-<lb break="no"/>fied, the common people foresee in the gradual cooling of<lb break="yes"/>the volcano the presage of a perpetual winter. I have<lb break="yes"/>thought it right to mention this vulgar tradition, worthy a<lb break="yes"/>place in the epic poem of the jesuit <persName key="landivar_rsj">Landivar</persName>, because it<lb break="yes"/>exhibits a striking feature of the manners and prejudices<lb break="yes"/>of these remote countries. It shows the active industry of<lb break="yes"/>a class of men, who, too frequently abusing the credulity<lb break="yes"/>of the people, and pretending to possess the power of sus-<lb break="no"/>pending the immutable laws of nature, know how to avail<lb break="yes"/>themselves of every event for establishing their empire by<lb break="yes"/>the fear of physical evil.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The situation of the new volcano of Jorullo leads to a<note place="right">Line of volca-<lb break="no"/>noes in Mexico<lb break="yes"/>crossing the<lb break="yes"/>chain of hills.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>very curious geological observation. It has already been<lb break="yes"/>observed in the 3d chapter, that there is in New Spain a<lb break="yes"/>line of great heights, or a narrow zone included between<lb break="yes"/>the latitudes of 18° 59&#x2032; and 19° 12&#x2032;, in which are all the<lb break="yes"/>summits of <placeName key="anahuac" >Anahuac</placeName> that rise above the region of perpetual<lb break="yes" />snow. These summits are either volcanoes still actually<lb break="yes" />burning; or mountains, the form of which, as well as the<lb break="yes" />nature of their rocks, renders it extremely probable, that<lb break="yes" />they formerly contained subterranean fire. Setting out<lb break="yes"/>from the coast of the Gulf of Mexico, and proceeding west-<lb break="no"/>ward, we find the peak of Oribaza, the two volcanoes of<lb break="yes"/>la Puebla, the Nevado de Toluca, the peak of Tancitaro,<lb break="yes"/>and the volcano of Colima. These great heights, instead<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">of</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="86" facs="#f0006"/> of forming the ridge of the cordillera of <placeName key="anahuac">Anahuac</placeName>, and fol-<lb break="no"/>lowing its direction, which is from S. E. to N. W., are on<lb break="yes"/>the contrary in a line perpendicular to the axis of the great<lb break="yes"/>chain of mountains. It is certainly worthy remark, that in<lb break="yes"/>the year 1759 the new volcano of Jorullo was formed in the<lb break="yes"/>continuation of this line, and on the same parallel as the<lb break="yes"/>ancient Mexican volcanoes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <note place="left">Indicate a long<lb break="yes"/>interior fissure<lb break="yes" />in the Earth.</note>
                <p>A view of my plan of the environs of Jorullo will show,<lb break="yes"/>that the six large hummocks have risen out of the earth on<lb break="yes"/>a vein, that crosses the plain from the cerro of las Cuevas<lb break="yes"/>to the pichaco del Montero. The new mouths of Vesuvius<lb break="yes"/>too are found ranged along a fissure. Do not these analo-<lb break="no"/>gies give us reason to suppose, that there exists in this part<lb break="yes"/>of Mexico, at a great depth within the Earth, a fissure<lb break="yes"/>stretching from east to west through a space of 137 leagues<lb break="yes"/>[343 miles], and through which the volcanic fire has made<lb break="yes"/>its way at different times, bursting the outer crust of por-<lb break="no"/>phyritic rocks, from the coasts of the Gulf of Mexico to<lb break="yes"/>the South Sea? Is this fissure prolonged to that little<lb break="yes"/>groupe of islands, called by <persName key="collnet_j">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Colluet</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">Collnet</corr>
                        </choice>
                    </persName> the <placeName key="archipelderevillagigedo">Archipelago of<lb break="yes"/>Regigedo</placeName>, and round which, in the same parallel with the<lb break="yes"/>Mexican volcanoes, pumice stone has been seen floating?<lb break="yes"/>Naturalists who distinguish the facts offered by descriptive<lb break="yes"/>mineralogy from theoretical reveries concerning the primi-<lb break="no"/>tive state of our planet will pardon me for having consigned<lb break="yes"/>these observations to the general Map of New Spain, con-<lb break="no"/>tained in the Mexican Atlas.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 