<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-26-neu</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="40" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">cargueroes, or man-carriers of quindiu.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> mountain of Quindiu is considered as the most difficult passage in the Cordilleras<lb break="yes"/>of the Andes. It is a thick uninhabited forest, which, in the finest season, cannot be<lb break="yes" />traversed in less than ten or twelve days. Not even a hut is to be seen, nor can any<lb break="yes"/>means of subsistence be found.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Travellers, at all times of the year, furnish themselves with a month&#x2019;s provi-<lb break="no"/>sion, since it often happens, that by the melting of the snows, and the sudden swell<lb break="yes"/>of the torrents, they find themselves so circumstanced, that they can descend neither<lb break="yes"/>on the side of Carthago, nor on that of Ibague. The highest point of the road,<lb break="yes"/>the Garito del Paramo, is three thousand five hundred and five metres (11,500 feet)<lb break="yes"/>above the level of the sea. As the foot of the mountain, towards the banks of the<lb break="yes"/>Cauca, is only nine hundred and sixty metres (3,150 feet high), the climate there is<lb break="yes" />in general mild and temperate. The pathway which forms the passage of the<lb break="yes"/>Cordilleras is only three or four decimetres in breadth (from a foot to a foot and a<lb break="yes"/>half), and has the appearance, in several places, of a gallery dug, and left open to the<lb break="yes"/>sky. In this part of the Andes, as almost in every other, the rock is covered with a<lb break="yes"/>thick stratum of clay. The streamlets, which flow down the mountains, have hollowed<lb break="yes"/>out gullies, six or seven metres deep (from 20 to 23 feet). Along these crevices,<lb break="yes"/>which are full of mud, the traveller is forced to grope his passage, the darkness of<lb break="yes"/>which is increased by the thick vegetation that covers the opening above. The oxen,<lb break="yes"/>which are the beasts of burden commonly made use of in this country, can scarcely<lb break="yes"/>force their way through these galleries, some of which are two thousand metres (2,200<lb break="yes"/>yards) in length; and if, perchance, the traveller meets them in one of these passages,<lb break="yes"/>he finds no means of avoiding them but by turning back, and climbing the earthen<lb break="yes"/>wall which borders the crevice, and keeping himself suspended, by laying hold of the<lb break="yes" />roots which penetrate to this depth from the surface of the ground.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We traversed the mountain of Quindiu in the month of October 1801, on foot,<lb break="yes"/>followed by twelve oxen, which carried our collections and instruments, amidst a<lb break="yes"/>deluge of rain, to which we were exposed during the last three or four days, in our<lb break="yes"/>descent on the western side of the Cordilleras. The road passes through a country<lb break="yes"/>full of bogs, and covered with bamboos. Our shoes were so torn by the prickles,<lb break="yes"/>which shoot out from the roots of these gigantic Gramina, that we were forced, like<lb break="yes"/>all other travellers who dislike being carried on men&#x2019;s backs, to go barefooted. This<lb break="yes"/>circumstance, the continual humidity, the length of the passage, the muscular force<lb break="yes"/>required to tread in a thick and muddy clay, the necessity of fording deep torrents of<lb break="yes"/>icy water, render this journey extremely fatiguing; but however painful, it is accom-<lb break="no"/>panied by none of those dangers with which the credulity of the people alarm travel-<lb break="no"/>lers. The road is narrow, but the places where it skirts precipices are very rare.<lb break="yes"/>As the oxen are accustomed to put their feet in the same tracks, they form small<lb break="yes" />furrows across the road, separated from each other by narrow ridges of earth. In<lb break="yes"/>very rainy seasons these ridges are covered with water, which renders the traveller&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>step doubly uncertain, since he knows not whether he places his foot on the ridge or<lb break="yes"/>in the furrow. As few persons in easy circumstances travel on foot in these climates,<lb break="yes"/>through roads so difficult, during fifteen or twenty days together, they are carried by<lb break="yes"/>men in a chair tied on their back; for, in the present state of the passage of Quindiu,<lb break="yes" />it would be impossible to go on mules. They talk in this country of going on a<lb break="yes"/>man&#x2019;s back (<hi rendition="#i">andar en carguero</hi>), as we mention going on horseback, no humiliating<lb break="yes"/>idea is annexed to the trade of cargueroes; and the men who follow this occupation<lb break="yes"/>are not Indians but Mulattoes, and sometimes even whites. It is often curious to<lb break="yes"/>hear these men, with scarcely any covering, and following a profession which we<lb break="yes" />should consider so disgraceful, quarrelling in the midst of the forest because one has<lb break="yes"/>refused the other, who pretends to have a whiter skin, the pompous title of <hi rendition="#i">don</hi>, or<lb break="yes"/>of <hi rendition="#i">su merced.</hi> The usual load of a carguero is six or seven arrobas (about 180 lbs.);<lb break="yes"/>those who are very strong carry as much as nine arrobas (about 250 lbs.) When<lb break="yes"/>we reflect on the enormous fatigue to which these miserable men are exposed,<lb break="yes" />journeying eight or nine hours a day over a mountainous country; when we know<lb break="yes"/>that their backs are sometimes as raw as those of beasts of burden, and that<lb break="yes"/>travellers have often the cruelty to leave them in the forest when they are sick;<lb break="yes"/>that they earn by a journey from Ibague to Carthago only twelve or fourteen piastres<lb break="yes" />(from L.2, 10s. to L.3), in a space of fifteen, and sometimes even twenty-five or<lb break="yes"/>thirty days, we are at a loss to conceive how this employment of a carguero, one<lb break="yes"/>of the most painful which can be undertaken by man, is eagerly embraced by all the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> robust young men who live at the foot of the mountains. The taste for a wandering<lb break="yes"/>and vagabond life, the idea of a certain independence amidst forests, leads them to<lb break="yes"/>prefer this employment to the sedentary and monotonous labour of cities.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The passage of the mountain of Quindiu is not the only part of South America<lb break="yes"/>which is traversed on the backs of men. The whole of the province of Antioquia is<lb break="yes"/>surrounded by mountains so difficult to pass, that they who dislike entrusting them-<lb break="no"/>selves to the skill of a carrier, and who are not strong enough to travel on foot from<lb break="yes"/>Santa Fé de Antioquia to Bocca de Nares or Rio Samana, must relinquish all<lb break="yes"/>thoughts of lcaving the country. I was acquainted with an inhabitant of this pro-<lb break="no"/>vince, so immensely bulky, that he had not met with more than two Mulattoes<lb break="yes"/>capable of carrying him; and it would have been impossible for him to return home<lb break="yes"/>if these two carriers had died, while he was on the banks of the Magdalena, at<lb break="yes"/>Mompox or Honda. The number of young men who undertake the employment of<lb break="yes"/>beasts of burden at Choco, Ibague, and Medellin, is so considerable, that we some-<lb break="no"/>times met a file of fifty or sixty. A few years ago, when a project was formed to<lb break="yes"/>make the passage from Nares to Antioquia passable for mules, the cargueroes<lb break="yes"/>presented formal remonstrances against mending the road, and the government was<lb break="yes"/>weak enough to yield to their clamours. We may here observe, that a class of men<lb break="yes"/>near the mines of Mexico, have no other employment than that of carrying other<lb break="yes"/>men on their backs. In these climates the indolence of the whites is so great, that<lb break="yes"/>every director of a mine has one or two Indians at his service, who are called his<lb break="yes"/>horses (cavallitoes), because they are saddled every morning, and supported by a<lb break="yes"/>small cane, and, bending forwards, they carry their master from one part of the mine<lb break="yes"/>to another. Among the cavallitoes or cargueroes, those who have a sure foot and<lb break="yes"/>easy step are known and recommended to travellers. It is distressing to hear the<lb break="yes"/>qualities of man spoken of in terms by which we are accustomed to denote the gait<lb break="yes" />of mules and horses. The persons who are carried in a chair by a carguero must<lb break="yes"/>remain several hours motionless and leaning backwards; the least motion is sufficient<lb break="yes"/>to throw down the carrier; and his fall would be so much the more dangerous, as the<lb break="yes"/>carguero, too confident in his skill, chooses the most rapid declivities, or crosses a<lb break="yes"/>torrent on a narrow and slippery trunk of a tree. These accidents are, however,<lb break="yes"/>rare, and those which happen must be attributed to the imprudence of travellers,<lb break="yes"/>who, frightened at a false step of the carguero, leap down from their chairs.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When the cargueroes reach Ibague and prepare for their journey, they pluck in<lb break="yes"/>the neighbouring mountains several hundred leaves of the <hi rendition="#i">Vijao</hi>, a plant of the family<lb break="yes"/>of the Bananas, which forms a genus approaching the <hi rendition="#i">Thalia</hi>, and which must not<lb break="yes"/>be confounded with the <hi rendition="#i" >Heliconia bihai.</hi> These leaves, which are membraneous and<lb break="yes"/>silky, like those of the Musa, are of an oval form, fifty-four centimetres (twenty<lb break="yes"/>inches) long, and thirty-seven centimetres (fourteen inches) in breadth. Their lower<lb break="yes"/>surface is a silvery white, and covered with a farinaccous substance which falls off in<lb break="yes"/>scales. This peculiar varnish enables them to resist the rain during a long time.<lb break="yes"/>In gathering these leaves, an incision is made in the middle rib, which is the continua-<lb break="no"/>tion of the footstalk, and this serves as a hook to suspend them when the moveable<lb break="yes"/>roof is formed. On taking it down, they are spread out and carefully rolled up in a<lb break="yes"/>cylindrical bundle. It requires about a hundred weight of leaves (50 kilogrammes)<lb break="yes"/>to cover a hut large enough to hold six or eight persons. When the travellers<lb break="yes"/>reach a spot in the midst of the forest, where the ground is dry, and where they<lb break="yes"/>propose to pass the night, the cargueroes lop a few branches from the trees, with<lb break="yes"/>which they make a tent. In a few minutes the slight timber work is divided by the<lb break="yes"/>stalks of some climbing plant, or threads of the Agave, placed in parallel lines, three<lb break="yes" />or four decimetres from each other. The Vijao leaves meanwhile have been unrolled,<lb break="yes"/>and are now spread over the above work, so as to cover each other like tiles of a<lb break="yes"/>house. These huts thus hastily built, are cool and commodious. If during the<lb break="yes"/>night the traveller feels the rain, he points out the spot where it enters, and a single<lb break="yes"/>leaf is sufficient to obviate the inconvenience. We passed several days in the<lb break="yes"/>valley of Boquia under one of these leafy tents, which was perfectly dry amidst<lb break="yes"/>violent and incessant rains. The mountain of Quindiu is one of the richest spots in<lb break="yes"/>useful and interesting plants. Here we found the Palm Tree (<hi rendition="#i">Ceroxylon andicola</hi>),<lb break="yes"/>the trunk of which is covered with a vegetable wax, the Passiflora in trees, and the<lb break="yes" />majestic <hi rendition="#i">Mutisia grandiflora</hi>, with flowers of a scarlet colour, sixteen centimetres,<lb break="yes"/>or six inches long. &#x2014;</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Humboldt.</hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 