<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="42" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>THE WORKS OF GOD DISPLAYED.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <div>
                            <head>
                                <hi rendition="#i">To the Editor of the Methodist Magazine.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <opener>
                                <salute>
                                    <hi rendition="#et">
                                        <hi rendition="#k">Rev. Sir,</hi>
                                    </hi>
                                </salute>
                            </opener>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>At a period when <choice>
                                    <sic>philosophicul</sic>
                                    <corr type="editorial">philosophical</corr>
                            </choice> research is pressed into the<lb break="yes"/>service of scepticism and infidelity, it must be highly gratifying to<lb break="yes"/>real Christians of every creed, to peruse that valuable department<lb break="yes"/>of your excellent Magazine, where you have recorded so many<lb break="yes"/>important facts, in which <hi rendition="#i">the works of God are displayed.</hi> The<lb break="yes"/>following description of the Volcano of Cotopaxi, is extracted<lb break="yes"/>from M. de Humboldt&#x2019;s Researches in South America. That ma-<lb break="no"/>jestic monument of Omnipotence, is on one of those huge moun-<lb break="no"/>tains, of that extended chain called the Andes, or the Cordilleras,<lb break="yes"/>which stretches from the isthmus of Darien, to the straits of<lb break="yes"/>Magellan, a distance of near four thousand miles. While the<lb break="yes"/>sceptical philosopher views the stupendous mountain, and is con-<lb break="no"/>founded in every attempt to account for its formation, the humble<lb break="yes"/>believer <hi rendition="#i">in God, in Christ, in the Bible,</hi> on the wings of devout<lb break="yes" />contemplation, soars to its towering height; and on its lofty<lb break="yes"/>summit finds an altar, where he offers to the Maker of the uni-<lb break="no"/>verse the incense of his astonishment and praise. Whether the<lb break="yes"/>scientific and indefatigable traveller will approve or blame my<lb break="yes"/>effort, to throw his sublime description of Cotopaxi into the trea-<lb break="no" />sury of the church of God, I cannot determine; but I sincerely<lb break="yes"/>hope, that its insertion in your useful Miscellany will contribute<lb break="yes"/>to the pleasure and profit of many of your pious readers.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <closer>
                                <salute>
                                    <hi rendition="#et">I am, your&#x2019;s, &amp;c. G*****.</hi>
                                </salute>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <dateline>
                                    <hi rendition="#i">Margate, Feb.</hi> 10, 1819.</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Cotopaxi is the loftiest of those volcanos of the Andes,<lb break="yes"/>which at recent epochs have undergone eruptions. Its absolute<lb break="yes"/>height is five thousand seven hundred and fifty-four metres;<note place="foot" n="*" >The French metre is equal to 3,987100 English inches.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(about eighteen thousand seven hundred and thirty-six English<lb break="yes"/>feet.) It is double that of Canigou; and consequently eight<lb break="yes"/>hundred metres higher than Vesuvius would be, were it placed<lb break="yes"/>on the top of the peak of Teneriffe.<note place="foot" n="†">Vesuvius is 3900 feet above the level of the sea; the peak of Teneriffe<lb break="yes"/>12,236 feet.</note> Cotopaxi is also the most<lb break="yes"/>dreadful volcano of the kingdom of Quito, and its explosions the<lb break="yes"/>most frequent and disastrous. The mass of scoria, and the<lb break="yes"/>huge pieces of rock thrown out of this volcano, which are spread<lb break="yes"/>over the neighbouring valleys, covering a surface of several<lb break="yes"/>square leagues, would form, were they heaped together a colossal<lb break="yes"/>mountain. In 1738, the flames of Cotopaxi rose nine hundred<lb break="yes"/>metres <choice><sic>ahove</sic><corr type="editorial">above</corr></choice> the brink of the crater. In 1744, the roarings of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="43" facs="#f0002"/> volcano were heard as far as Henda, a town on the borders of the<lb break="yes"/>Magdalena, and at a distance of two hundred common leagues.<lb break="yes"/>On the 4th of April, 1768, the quantity of ashes ejected by the<lb break="yes"/>mouth of Cotopaxi was so great, that in the towns of Hambato<lb break="yes"/>and Tacunga day broke only at three in the afternoon, and the<lb break="yes"/>inhabitants were obliged to use lanterns in walking the streets.<lb break="yes"/>The explosion which took place in the month of January, 1803,<lb break="yes"/>was preceded by a most dreadful phenomenon, the sudden melting<lb break="yes"/>of the snows that covered the mountain. For twenty years<lb break="yes"/>before, no smoke or vapour, that could be perceived, had issued<lb break="yes"/>from <choice>
                        <sic>t he</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">the</corr>
                    </choice> crater; and in a single night the subterraneous fire<lb break="yes" />became so active, that at sun-rise the external walls of the cone,<lb break="yes"/>heated, no doubt, to a very considerable temperature, appeared<lb break="yes"/>naked, and of a dark colour, which is peculiar to vitrified scor&#x00E6;.<lb break="yes"/>At the port of Guayaquil, fifty-two leagues distant in a straight<lb break="yes"/>line from the crater, we heard, day and night, the constant noises<lb break="yes"/>of the volcano, like continual discharges of a battery; we distin-<lb break="no"/>guished these tremendous sounds even on the Pacific Ocean, to<lb break="yes"/>the south-west of the island of Puna.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Cotopaxi is situated to the south-east of the city of Quito,<lb break="yes"/>at the distance of twelve leagues, between the mountain of Rumin-<lb break="no" />navi, the summit of which, rugged with small separate rocks,<lb break="yes" />extends itself like a wall of enormous height; and Quelendanna,<lb break="yes" />which enters the boundary of the eternal snows. It is in this part<lb break="yes"/>of the Andes, that a longitudinal valley separates the Cordilleras<lb break="yes"/>into two parallel chains. The bottom of the valley is three<lb break="yes"/>thousand metres above the level of the ocean, so that Chimborazo<lb break="yes"/>and Cotopaxi, seen from the elevated plains of Lican and Mulalo,<lb break="yes"/>appear no higher than the Col de Geant and du Cramont, mea-<lb break="no"/>sured by Saussure. As there is reason to suppose, that the prox-<lb break="no"/>imity of the ocean contributes to feed the volcanic fire, the geo-<lb break="no"/>logist is astonished to find, that the most active volcanoes in the<lb break="yes"/>kingdom of Quito, Cotopaxi, Tungurahua, and Sangay, belong<lb break="yes"/>to the eastern chain of the Andes, and consequently that which<lb break="yes"/>is the farthest from the coasts. The whole of the peaks, except<lb break="yes"/>Ruca-Pichincha, which crown the western Cordilleras, seem to<lb break="yes"/>be volcanos extinguished for a long series of ages; but this moun-<lb break="no"/>tain, which is 2&#x00B0; 2&#x2032; distant from the nearest coasts, those of Esme-<lb break="no"/>ralda, and the bay of San-Mateo, spouts out at different periods<lb break="yes"/>cataracts of fire, and spreads destruction over the surrounding<lb break="yes"/>plains.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The form of Cotopaxi is the most beautiful and regular of<lb break="yes"/>the colossal summits of the high Andes. It is a perfect cone,<lb break="yes"/>which, covered with an enormous layer of snow, shines with daz-<lb break="no"/>zling splendor at the setting of the sun, and detaches itself in the<lb break="yes" />most picturesque manner from the azure vault of heaven. This<lb break="yes" />covering of snow conceals from the eye of the observer, even the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="44" facs="#f0003"/> smallest inequalities of the soil; no point of rock, no stony mass,<lb break="yes"/>penetrates the coating of ice, or breaks the regularity of the<lb break="yes"/>figure of the cone. The summit of Cotopaxi resembles the<lb break="yes"/>sugar-loaf, (Pan de azucar) which terminates the peak of Teyde;<lb break="yes"/>but the height of the cone is six times the height of that great<lb break="yes"/>volcano in the island of Teneriffe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;It is only at the brink of the crater we see ledges of rocks,<lb break="yes" />that are never covered with snow, and that look at a distance<lb break="yes" />like stripes of the darkest hue; the greatest steepness of this part<lb break="yes"/>of the cone, and the crevices from which issue currents of heated<lb break="yes"/>air, are <choice><sic>probaby</sic><corr type="editorial">probably</corr></choice> the causes of this phenomenon. The crater,<lb break="yes"/>like that of the peak of Teneriffe, is surrounded by a small circu-<lb break="no"/>lar wall, which, examined with a good telescope, looks like a<lb break="yes"/>parapet. This is more distinctly seen on the southern declivity,<lb break="yes"/>when the beholder is placed either on the Lion mountain, (Puona<lb break="yes"/>Urcu) or on the banks of the small lake of Yuracoche.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The conic point of the peak of Teneriffe is of easy access,<lb break="yes" />rising from the midst of a plain, covered with pumice stones, and<lb break="yes"/>on which a few tufts of spartium supranubium vegetate. In scal-<lb break="no"/>ing the volcano of Cotopaxi, it is extremely difficult to attain the<lb break="yes"/>inferior boundary of the <choice>
                        <sic>perpetutl</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">perpetual</corr>
                </choice> snows, as we experienced in<lb break="yes"/>an excursion we made in the month of May, in the year 1802.<lb break="yes"/>The cone is surrounded by deep crevices, which at the moment<lb break="yes"/>of the eruptions bear down scori&#x00E6;, pumice stone, water, and<lb break="yes"/>blocks of ice, to Rio Napo, and Rio de les Alaques. After a<lb break="yes"/>nearer examination of the summit of Cotopaxi, we may venture<lb break="yes"/>to assert, that it would be impossible to reach the brink of the<lb break="yes"/>crater. <hi rendition="#g" >**************</hi> I sketched Cotopaxi,<lb break="yes"/>and the head of the Inca, to the west of the volcano, at the farm<lb break="yes"/>Sienega, <hi rendition="#g">************</hi>. The colossal volcano, the<lb break="yes" />pyramidal peaks of Ilinisa, and the Nevado de Quelendana, open<lb break="yes" />here at once on the spectator, and in dreadful proximity. This<lb break="yes" />is one of the most majestic and awful views I ever beheld in either<lb break="yes"/>hemisphere.&#x2019;&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#et">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Researches in South America by Alexander de Humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 