<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="548" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>VIEW OF AMERICA AND ITS NATIVE TRIBES,<lb break="yes"/>BY ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It cannot but excite astonishment, that, at the conclusion, of the<lb break="yes" />fifteenth century, there should have been found, in a world which we<lb break="yes"/>denominate <hi rendition="#i">the new,</hi> the very same kind of antiquarian remains, the<lb break="yes"/>same religious notions, and forms of architecture, as seem to belong<lb break="yes"/>to the earliest ages of civilization in Asia. It is with the characteris-<lb break="no"/>tics of nations, as with the internal structure of the plants that are<lb break="yes" />spread over the face of the earth. The stamp of the original stock<lb break="yes"/>remains indelible, notwithstanding the numberless modifications pro-<lb break="no"/>duced by climate, soil, and various other incidents.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the first period after the discovery of America, the attention of<lb break="yes"/>the Europeans was more particularly directed to the gigantic edifices<lb break="yes"/>of Corzco, to the high roads through the midst of the Cordilleras, to<lb break="yes"/>the lofty graduated pyramids, to the religious rites, and symbolical<lb break="yes"/>writings of the Mexicans. Descriptions of different provinces of<lb break="yes"/>Mexico and Peru were then as frequent as are, in our days, the ac-<lb break="no"/>counts of the vicinity of Port Jackson, in New Holland, or the Island<lb break="yes"/>of Otaheite. It is absolutely necessary to have been upon the spot,<lb break="yes"/>in order to appreciate justly the noble simplicity and the character of<lb break="yes" />truth and fidelity which pervade the narrations of the earliest Spanish<lb break="yes"/>travellers: and, in perusing their works, we lament only the want of<lb break="yes"/>graphic illustrations, which would have given us more satisfactory<lb break="yes"/>ideas of many monuments, partly demolished by fanaticism, and partly<lb break="yes"/>fallen to decay through culpable neglect.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The ardor for those American investigations diminished after the<lb break="yes" />commencement of the seventeenth century. The Spanish colonies,<lb break="yes" />whose territory alone had been inhabited by civilized nations, were<lb break="yes"/>shut against foreigners; and when, more recently, the Abbé Clavigero<lb break="yes"/>published, in Italy, his work on the ancient history of Mexico, doubts<lb break="yes"/>were raised concerning many facts which were formerly confimed by<lb break="yes"/>numerous eye-witnesses, frequently persons by no means amicably<lb break="yes"/>disposed towards each other. Celebrated writers, who received less<lb break="yes"/>pleasure from the harmony of nature than from her contrasts, have<lb break="yes"/>represented America as one vast swamp, unfavourable to the propaga-<lb break="no"/>tion of the animal species, and not till of late inhabited by races of<lb break="yes" />men not surpassing the South Sea islanders in civilization. An unli-<lb break="no"/>mited scepticism had banished sound criticism from the historical dis-<lb break="no"/>quisitions on the Americans. The fictions of a Solis and some other<lb break="yes"/>travellers who had never quitted Europe, were blended with the faith-<lb break="no"/>ful and simple relations of the earliest visitors of the New World; and<lb break="yes"/>it was deemed the duty of a philosophic historian to protest, in the<lb break="yes"/>first place, against all that the missionaries had observed.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Towards the end of the past century, a happy alteration took place<lb break="yes" />in regard to the opinions entertained respecting the civilisation of na-<lb break="no"/>tions, and the causes that alternately promote and obstruct its progress.<lb break="yes"/>We became acquainted with nations whose manners, institutions, and<lb break="yes"/>arts, are almost as different from those of the Greeks and Romans, as<lb break="yes"/>the original forms of the extinct species of animals from those which<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="549" facs="#f0002"/> at present engage the attention of naturalists. The society of Cal-<lb break="no"/>cutta has thrown a brilliant light over the history of the Asiatic na-<lb break="no"/>tions. The monuments of Egypt have, of late, been partly described<lb break="yes"/>with admirable correctness, and partly compared with those of the<lb break="yes"/>most distant regions; and my researches concerning the native tribes<lb break="yes"/>of America appear at an epoch, when that which does not approach<lb break="yes"/>to the style and manner of which the Greeks have left us inimitable<lb break="yes"/>models, is nevertheless deemed well worthy of attention.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the description of the historical monuments of America, I have<lb break="yes" />endeavoured to observe a due mean between two routes alternately<lb break="yes"/>pursued by those literati who have entered into the discussion of such<lb break="yes"/>monuments, languages, and national traditions. The one adopting<lb break="yes"/>hypotheses which, though brilliant, rest on tottering foundations, have<lb break="yes"/>deduced general conclusions from a small number of insulated facts.<lb break="yes"/>They found, in America, Chinese and Egyptian colonies, Celtic<lb break="yes"/>dialects, and the alphabet of the Ph&#x0153;nicians. While we yet remain<lb break="yes"/>in the dark respecting the origin of the Osci, the Goths, and the<lb break="yes"/>Celts, they pretended to pronounce decisively on the origin of the<lb break="yes"/>tribes of the New World. Other writers, on the contrary, amassed<lb break="yes"/>materials, without ever raising themselves to any general notions: a<lb break="yes" />proceeding from which the history of nations can derive as little bene-<lb break="no"/>fit as the different branches of the natural sciences. I shall deem<lb break="yes"/>myself fortunate if I shall be thought to have equally avoided both<lb break="yes"/>these extremes. A small number of tribes, far distant from one ano-<lb break="no"/>ther, as the Etruscans, the Egyptians, the Tibetians, the Aztekians,<lb break="yes"/>exhibit striking co-incidences in their buildings and religious institu-<lb break="no"/>tions, in their division of the year, in their returning periods of time,<lb break="yes"/>and in their mystical representations. The historian ought not to<lb break="yes"/>overlook these coincidence, for which it is just as difficult to account<lb break="yes" />as for the resemblance between the Sanscrit, Persian, Greek, and<lb break="yes"/>German idioms; but while he rises to general ideas, he should know<lb break="yes"/>how to stop at the point where we are abandoned by certain facts.<lb break="yes"/>Agreeably to these principles, I will attempt to state the results de-<lb break="no"/>duced from the data which I have been enabled to collect concerning<lb break="yes"/>the native tribes of America.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>An attentive examination of the geological relations of the New<lb break="yes" />World, and a consideration of the equilibrium of the waters spread over<lb break="yes"/>the surface of the earth, forbid the assumption that the new and the<lb break="yes"/>old continents rose at different times from the bosom of the deep.<lb break="yes"/>On both hemispheres we perceive the like series of rocky strata lying<lb break="yes"/>one above another, and probably the granite, gypsum, and sand-stone<lb break="yes"/>formations in the mountains of Peru, had their origin at the same pe-<lb break="no"/>riod as the corresponding strata in the Alps of Switzerland. The<lb break="yes"/>whole globe has apparently been visited by the same catastrophes.<lb break="yes"/>On the summits of the Andes, at an elevation exceeding that of<lb break="yes"/>Mont Blanc, are found the petrified muscles of the ocean. Fossile<lb break="yes"/>bones of elephants are scattered over the equatorial regions, and,<lb break="yes"/>what is remarkable, they are met with, not only under the palms in<lb break="yes"/>the torrid valleys of the Oronoko, but on the highest and coldest<lb break="yes"/>plains of the Cordilleras. In the new as in the old world, whole crea-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="550" facs="#f0003"/> tions and whole species of organic bodies have become extinct, to<lb break="yes"/>give place to those which now people the earth, the air, and the<lb break="yes"/>waters.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>No grounds exist for presuming that America was first peopled by<lb break="yes" />men at a much later period than the other continents. The luxuriant<lb break="yes"/>vegetation, the breadth of the rivers, and the partial in-undations are<lb break="yes"/>powerful obstacles to the migration of nations in tropical countries.<lb break="yes"/>Extensive tracts of northern Asia are as thinly peopled as the savan-<lb break="no"/>nahs of New Mexico and Paraguay, and we should by no means pre-<lb break="no"/>suppose that the countries first inhabited must necessarily be the most<lb break="yes"/>populous.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The question relative to the origin of the population of America can<lb break="yes"/>no more belong to the province of history, than those concerning the<lb break="yes"/>origin of plants and animals, and on the distribution of organic germs,<lb break="yes"/>to the natural sciences. History, when it goes back to the most an-<lb break="no"/>cient periods, exhibits to us almost all the parts of the globe inhabited<lb break="yes"/>by people who look upon themselves as aborigines, because their an-<lb break="no"/>cestry is unknown to them. Amidst a variety of tribes who succeed-<lb break="no"/>ed and intermingled with one another, it is impossible to decide with<lb break="yes" />certainty from which of them the population first proceeded, and to<lb break="yes"/>define the limits beyond which the empire of cosmogonal tradition<lb break="yes"/>commences.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The tribes of America, with the exception of those that are nearest<lb break="yes"/>to the polar circle, belong all to one single race, which is distinguish-<lb break="no"/>ed by the form of the skull, complexion, very scanty beard, and<lb break="yes"/>straight hair. The American race exhibits striking analogies with<lb break="yes"/>that of the Mongol tribes, which comprehends the descendants of the<lb break="yes"/>Hiong-nu, so famous under the denomination of Huns, the Kalkases,<lb break="yes"/>the Calmucks, and the Burattes. Recent observations have even de-<lb break="no"/>monstrated, that not only the inhabitants of Oonalashka, but several<lb break="yes"/>South American tribes also, denote, by the osteological characters of<lb break="yes"/>the skull, a transition from the American to the Mongol race. If the<lb break="yes" />sable African race, and the numberless tribes which inhabit the in-<lb break="no"/>terior of Asia and its north-eastern regions, and to which systematic<lb break="yes"/>geographers have given the indefinite appellation of Tartars or<lb break="yes"/>Tschoudes, should ever become better known to us, the Caucasian,<lb break="yes"/>Mongol, American, Malay, and Negro races will be less widely se-<lb break="no"/>parated than they have been, and we shall recognize, in this great<lb break="yes"/>family of man, one single original, which has undergone various modi-<lb break="no"/>fications from circumstances that we shall, perhaps, never be able to<lb break="yes"/>penetrate.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The native tribes of the new world, though all of them are allied<lb break="yes" />by very essential characteristics, yet, on the other hand, present, in<lb break="yes"/>their moveable features, in their more or less dark complexion, in<lb break="yes"/>their shape and size, varieties not less striking than the difference<lb break="yes"/>which we perceive between the Arabs, Persians, and Slavonians of<lb break="yes"/>the Circassian race. The hordes, however, which rove about in the<lb break="yes"/>burning plains of the equinoctial regions are by no means of a darker<lb break="yes"/>colour than the mountaineers, or the inhabitants of the temperate<lb break="yes"/>zone; whether it be that in man, as in most animals, there is a cer-<lb break="no"/>tain period of life beyond which the influence of climate and food is<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="551" facs="#f0004"/> insignificant, or that the deviation from the original mode is not per-<lb break="no"/>ceptible till the expiration of many centuries. From all that has<lb break="yes"/>been observed, however, it results, that the Americans, like the Mon-<lb break="no"/>gol tribes, have a less flexible organization than the other Asiatic and<lb break="yes"/>European nations.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The American race, though less numerous than any other, is dis-<lb break="no" />persed over the greatest portion of the globe. It extends, through<lb break="yes"/>both hemispheres, from 68&#x00B0; N. L. to 55&#x00B0; S. L. It is the only one<lb break="yes"/>that, at the same time, inhabits the scorching vallies bounded by the<lb break="yes"/>ocean, and the ridges of mountains elevated more than 200 fathoms<lb break="yes"/>above the Peak of Teneriffe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The number of the languages which distinguish the indigenous na-<lb break="no" />tions from one another seems to be still greater in America than in<lb break="yes"/>Africa, where, according to the recent researches of Messrs. Seetzen<lb break="yes"/>and Vater, they exceed 140. In this respect the whole of America<lb break="yes"/>resembles the Caucasus, Italy before the conquest of the Romans,<lb break="yes"/>and Asia Minor at the time when the Cilicians, of Semitic origin, the<lb break="yes"/>Phrygians, of Thracian descent, the Lydians and the Celts dwelt<lb break="yes"/>here together within a small compass. The formation of the earth,<lb break="yes"/>the extreme luxuriance of the vegetable kingdom, and the dread of<lb break="yes"/>the intense heat of the vallies entertained by the inhabitants of the<lb break="yes" />tropical regions, impede mutual intercourse and create an astonish-<lb break="no"/>ing diversity of American dialects. This diversity is not so great in<lb break="yes"/>the savannahs and forests of the north, which are traversed by hunters,<lb break="yes"/>on the banks of the great rivers, along the coasts of the ocean, and<lb break="yes"/>wherever the Incas have introduced their theocracy by force of arms.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When we speak of more than a hundred languages, on a continent<lb break="yes" />whose total population is not equal to that of France, we term those<lb break="yes"/>different languages which have the same affinity to one another as,<lb break="yes"/>I will not say the German to the Dutch, or the Italian to the Spanish;<lb break="yes"/>but as the Danish to the German, the Chaldee to the Arabic, the<lb break="yes"/>Greek to the Latin. As a person becomes more and more familiar<lb break="yes"/>with the labyrinth of American languages, he perceives that many of<lb break="yes"/>them belong to one and the same family, while a great number of<lb break="yes"/>others remain insulated like the Basque among the Europeans, and<lb break="yes"/>the Japanese among the Asiatic languages. This insulation is per-<lb break="no"/>haps only apparent, and it may be presumed that those languages<lb break="yes"/>which seem to defy all ethnographic classification, are allied to others<lb break="yes"/>either long extinct, or peculiar to nations whom no travellers have<lb break="yes"/>hitherto visited.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Most of the American languages, even those whose groups differ<lb break="yes" />from one another in the same manner as the dialects of German,<lb break="yes" />Celtic, and Slavonian origin, exhibit a certain resemblance in their<lb break="yes"/>general organization, which if it does not indicate one common stock,<lb break="yes"/>at least denotes a very close analogy in the intellectual faculties of<lb break="yes"/>the American nations from Greenland to the streights of Magellan.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Very minute enquiries, conducted according to a method before<lb break="yes" />unknown in etymological studies, have proved, that there is a small<lb break="yes"/>number of words common to the language of the Old and New<lb break="yes"/>World. In 83 American <choice>
                        <sic>languagegs</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">languages</corr>
                    </choice>, examined by Messrs. Barton<lb break="yes"/>and Vater, have been found about 170 words which seemed to have<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="552" facs="#f0005"/> the same roots; and we may easily convince ourselves that these re-<lb break="no"/>semblances are by no means accidental or an imitative harmony, and<lb break="yes"/>perhaps resulting only from the uniform structure of the organs which<lb break="yes"/>renders the first articulated tones of children pretty nearly the same<lb break="yes"/>in all parts of the world. Out of 170 words, in which this similarity<lb break="yes"/>is perceived, three fifths seem to claim affinity with the languages of<lb break="yes"/>the Mantchous, Tungusians, Mongols, and Samojedes, and the other<lb break="yes" />two-fifths with Celtic and Tschoudian dialects, and with the Basque,<lb break="yes"/>Coptic, and Congo languages. Those words were found out on a<lb break="yes"/>comparison of the whole of the American languages, with the whole<lb break="yes"/>of the languages of the Old World; for as yet we know not of any<lb break="yes"/>American dialect which can be deemed more nearly allied than the<lb break="yes"/>rest to any of the numerous groups of Asiatic, African, or European<lb break="yes"/>languages. The assertions of some scholars, proceeding upon abstract<lb break="yes"/>theories, respecting the supposed poverty of all the American langua-<lb break="no"/>ges, as well as the extraordinary scantiness of their system of num-<lb break="no"/>bers, are as rash and unfounded as the statements of others who con-<lb break="no"/>tend for the imbecility and stupidity of the human race in the New<lb break="yes"/>World, the diminution of organic bodies, and the degeneracy of the<lb break="yes" />animals transported thither from our hemisphere.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Various dialects at present spoken by barbarous nations alone,<lb break="yes" />seem to be relics of copious and flexible languages, which denote a<lb break="yes"/>considerable progress in civilization. I shall not here enter into an<lb break="yes"/>examination of the question&#x2014;whether the original condition of man-<lb break="no"/>kind was a state of rudeness and stupidity, or whether the savage<lb break="yes"/>hordes are descended from nations whose mental powers, as well as<lb break="yes"/>the language in which they are reflected, were previously both equally<lb break="yes"/>developed: but I shall merely observe that the little which we know<lb break="yes"/>of the history of the Americans seems to demonstrate that those<lb break="yes"/>tribes which migrated from north to south, possessed in their northern<lb break="yes"/>abodes that variety of languages which we discover in the tropical<lb break="yes" />regions. Hence we may draw the analogical inference that the rami-<lb break="no"/>fication, or to use an expression independent of all systems the diver-<lb break="no"/>sity of the languages is a very ancient phenomenon. Perhaps the<lb break="yes"/>languages which we term American originally belong no more to this<lb break="yes"/>quarter of the globe than the Madjarian or Hungarian, and the<lb break="yes"/>Tschoudian or Finnish do to Europe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It must be admitted that the comparison of the languages of the<lb break="yes" />Old and New World has led as yet to no general results; but we<lb break="yes" />ought not on this account to relinquish our hopes that this study will<lb break="yes"/>prove more productive when the sagacity of scholars shall possess a<lb break="yes"/>larger stock of materials. How many languages of America, as well<lb break="yes"/>as of the interior and eastern part of Asia may there still be, whose<lb break="yes"/>mechanism is as unknown to us as that of the Tyrrhenian, Oscian,<lb break="yes"/>and Sabine dialects! Of the nations which disappeared from the<lb break="yes"/>Old World, there may perhaps still exist some petty detached tribes<lb break="yes"/>in the vast wilds of America.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If, however, the early intercourse between the two worlds can be<lb break="yes" />but very imperfectly proved by the languages, it is on the other hand<lb break="yes"/>unequivocally demonstrated by the cosmogonies, the monuments,<lb break="yes"/>hieroglyphics, and institutions of the American and Asiatic nations.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="553" facs="#f0006"/> I think that to the evidences already adduced on this point, I have ad-<lb break="no"/>ded no small number that were hitherto unknown. I have every<lb break="yes"/>where endeavoured to discriminate that which denotes a common ori-<lb break="no"/>gin from what must be considered as the result of analogous relations,<lb break="yes"/>subsisting between nations which have attained the highest degree of<lb break="yes"/>civilization.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>To determine the period of the ancient connexion between the two<lb break="yes" />worlds was previously impracticable, and it would be too presumptuous<lb break="yes"/>to pretend to designate the group of nations in the Old World, to<lb break="yes"/>which the Toltekes, Aztekes, Muyscas, or Peruvians, are nearest al-<lb break="no"/>lied, since the relations here alluded to are founded upon such <choice><sic>tradic-<lb break="no"/>tions,</sic><corr type="editorial">tradi-<lb break="no"/>tions,</corr></choice> monuments, and usages, as may possibly be of higher antiquity<lb break="yes"/>than the present division of the Asiatics into Mongols, Hindoos,<lb break="yes"/>Tongouses, and Chinese.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the time of the discovery of the New World, or to speak more<lb break="yes" />correctly, at the period of the first Spanish invasion, the American na-<lb break="no"/>tions, which had made the greatest progress in civilization were<lb break="yes"/>mountaineers. People born in the valleys of a temperate region<lb break="yes"/>climbed the ridges of the Cordilleras, which become more elevated as<lb break="yes"/>they approach the equator; and on these heights they found a tempera-<lb break="no"/>ture and vegetation similar to those of their native land.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>All those situations in which man has to struggle with natural ob-<lb break="no" />stacles on a soil of inferior fertility, and is not absolutely vanquished<lb break="yes"/>in too unequal a conflict, are most favourable to the development of<lb break="yes"/>his energies. On the Caucasus and in the centre of Asia the barren<lb break="yes"/>mountains afford an asylum to independent and savage tribes. In the<lb break="yes"/>equinoctial regions of America, where ever verdant savannahs rise above<lb break="yes"/>the region of the clouds, the Cordilleras alone are inhabited by polish-<lb break="no"/>ed tribes; the first advances in science were there coeval with the<lb break="yes"/>extraordinary institutions by no means favourable to individual<lb break="yes"/>liberty.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We perceive in the New World, as in Asia and Africa, various<lb break="yes" />centres whence spread an original civilization, whose mutual relations,<lb break="yes"/>however, we are as incapable of discovering as those of Meröe, Tibet,<lb break="yes"/>and China. Mexico derived its civilization from a more northern re-<lb break="no"/>gion. In South America it was the extensive structures of Tiahuana-<lb break="no"/>ko that furnished the models of those monuments which the Incas<lb break="yes"/>erected at Coutzko. Ramparts of considerable extent, bronze weapons,<lb break="yes"/>and engraved stones found in the vast plains of Upper Canada, in<lb break="yes"/>Florida, and in the wilds bounded by the Oronoko, Cassiquaire, and<lb break="yes"/>Guainia, attest that these regions now traversed only by hordes of<lb break="yes"/>savage hunters were once the abode of nations who had made some<lb break="yes"/>proficiency in the arts.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The unequal distribution of the different species of brute animals<lb break="yes" />over the earth, had a powerful influence on the condition of nations,<lb break="yes"/>and on their more or less rapid progress in civilization. In the Old<lb break="yes"/>World, it was the pastoral life that formed the link between the hunter<lb break="yes"/>and the husbandman. The ruminating animals, so easily naturalized<lb break="yes"/>in every climate, were the companions of the African Negro, as well<lb break="yes"/>as of the Mongols, the Malays, and Caucasian race. Now, though<lb break="yes"/>several quadrupeds, and very numerous species of vegetables, are<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="554" facs="#f0007"/> common to the northernmost parts of both worlds, yet the only kinds<lb break="yes"/>of horned cattle possessed by America are the buffalo and the bison,<lb break="yes"/>two varieties which it is very difficult to domesticate, and the females<lb break="yes"/>of which, notwithstanding the richness of the pastures, yield but little<lb break="yes"/>milk. The American hunter, therefore, was not prepared, by the care<lb break="yes"/>of flocks and herds, and the occupations of a pastoral life, for the pur-<lb break="no"/>suits of agriculture. Never did the inhabitants of the Cordilleras at-<lb break="no" />tempt to milk the lama, alpaca, or guanaco; and milk diet was form-<lb break="no"/>erly as unknown to the Americans, as it is to many of the tribes of<lb break="yes"/>eastern Asia.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There is no instance of the savage living in the forests of the temperate<lb break="yes"/>zone, having voluntarily exchanged the <choice><sic>chace</sic><corr type="editorial">chase</corr></choice> for agriculture. This<lb break="yes"/>transition, the most important and the most difficult in the history of<lb break="yes"/>human society, cannot be effected but by compulsory means. When<lb break="yes"/>in their great migrations troops of hunters, persecuted by other war-<lb break="no"/>rior hordes, reach the plains of the equinoctial zone, the impenetrable<lb break="yes"/>closeness of the woods, and the luxuriant growth of the vegetable<lb break="yes"/>species, produce an essential change in their character and way of<lb break="yes"/>life. Between the Oronoko, Ukajale, and the river of Amazons, there<lb break="yes" />are tracts where man finds scarcely any thing but streams and lakes.<lb break="yes"/>Here on the banks of the rivers, even the most savage inhabitants sur-<lb break="no"/>round their huts with the fig of Paradise, the jatropha tree, and some<lb break="yes"/>other vegetables, which contribute to their subsistence.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Neither historical facts nor popular tradition record that any con-<lb break="no" />nexion ever subsisted between the South American nations and those<lb break="yes"/>dwelling to the north of the isthmus of Panama. The annals of the<lb break="yes"/>Mexican empire seem to go back to the sixth century of our &#x00E6;ra.<lb break="yes"/>They state the periods of the migrations which took place, the causes<lb break="yes"/>which occasioned them, the names of the leaders belonging to the<lb break="yes"/>illustrious family of the Citins who conducted northern tribes from the<lb break="yes"/>unknown regions of Aztlan and Teocolhuacan to the plains of Anahuac.<lb break="yes"/>The founding of Tenochtilan happens like that of Rome in the heroic<lb break="yes"/>age, and it is only from the 12th century that the Aztekian chronicles,<lb break="yes"/>like those of the Chinese and Tibetians, contain the almost uninter-<lb break="no" />rupted record of the secular festivals, the succession of the kings, the<lb break="yes"/>tributes imposed upon the conquered, the foundation of cities, meteo-<lb break="no"/>rological phenomena, and many trivial incidents which have an influ-<lb break="no"/>ence on society in infant states.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But though no traditions denote any immediate connexion between<lb break="yes" />the nations of the two grand divisions of America, their history on the<lb break="yes"/>other hand exhibits striking coincidences in the political and religious<lb break="yes"/>revolutions which led to the civilization of the Aztekes, Muyscas and<lb break="yes"/>Peruvians. Bearded men of a lighter complexion than the natives of<lb break="yes"/>Anahuac, Cundinamarca, and the plain of Couzco, make their appear-<lb break="no"/>ance, without its being known from what country they come. As high<lb break="yes"/>priests, legislators, friends of peace, and of the arts and sciences,<lb break="yes"/>which it promotes, they accomplish a change in the state of the na-<lb break="no"/>tions, from whom they experience a respectful reception. Quetzal-<lb break="no"/>coat, Bochica, and Mango Capac, are the sacred names of these<lb break="yes" />mysterious beings. Quetzalcoat comes in black priestly attire from<lb break="yes"/>Panuco and the shores of the Mexican Gulf: Bochica, the Buddha of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="555" facs="#f0008"/> the Muyscas appears on the elevated plains of Bogota advancing from<lb break="yes"/>the savannahs situated on the east side of the <choice>
                        <sic>Corderillas</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Cordilleras</corr>
                    </choice>. The history<lb break="yes"/>of these lawgivers is full of marvellous stories, religious fictions, and<lb break="yes"/>such circumstances as betray an allegorical meaning. Some scholars<lb break="yes"/>have conjectured that these foreigners might have been shipwrecked<lb break="yes"/>Europeans, or descendants of the <choice>
                        <sic>Scandinivians</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Scandinavians</corr>
                    </choice>, who as early as the<lb break="yes"/>11th century visited Greenland, Newfoundland, and perhaps even<lb break="yes"/>Nova Scotia; but the slightest reflection on the period of the first<lb break="yes"/>Toltekian emigrations, on the monastic institutions, the religious sym-<lb break="no"/>bols, the calendar and the forms of the monuments of Cholula, Soga-<lb break="no"/>mozo, and Couzco, will lead to the conviction that the codes of Quet-<lb break="no" />zalcoat, Bochica, and Mango Capac, could not possibly derive their<lb break="yes"/>origin from the north of Europe. Every thing, on the contrary, seems<lb break="yes"/>to point to eastern Asia, and to people connected with the Tibetians,<lb break="yes"/>the Shamanists, the Tartars, and the bearded Ainos of the islands of<lb break="yes"/>Jesso and Sachalin.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When I employ the terms&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Monuments of the New World&#x2014;progress<lb break="yes"/>in the imitative arts&#x2014;cultivation of the understanding,</hi> in my inquiries <lb break="yes"/>respecting America, it is by no means my intention to denote a state<lb break="yes"/>of things which is rather vaguely denominated a higher degree of cul-<lb break="no"/>ture and civilization. Nothing is more difficult than to institute com-<lb break="no"/>parisons between nations who have advanced by different roads to so-<lb break="no"/>cial improvement. The Mexicans and Peruvians must not be judged<lb break="yes"/>by such principles as are deduced from the history of the nations of<lb break="yes"/>whom our studies are continually reminding us. They differ from<lb break="yes"/>the Greeks and Romans in the same ratio as they resemble the<lb break="yes"/>Etruscans and Tibetians. The theocratic government of the Peruvians<lb break="yes"/>favoured on the one hand the progress of industry, public works, and,<lb break="yes"/>if I may be allowed the expression, whatever relates to civilization in<lb break="yes" />general and in mass: on the other hand it prevented the development<lb break="yes"/>of individual energies. Among the Greeks it was just the reverse,<lb break="yes"/>and till the time of Pericles the free and rapid mental development of<lb break="yes"/>individuals bore no proportion to the slow advance of national cultiva-<lb break="no"/>tion. The empire of the Incas might be likened to a vast monastic<lb break="yes"/>institution, in which every member had prescribed to him what he was<lb break="yes"/>to do for the general benefit. Whoever makes himself acquainted on<lb break="yes"/>the spot with those Peruvians, who for ages retained their national<lb break="yes"/>physiognomy without alteration, will be enabled duly to appreciate<lb break="yes"/>the code of Mango Capac and its influence on morals and the public<lb break="yes"/>weal. There was general prosperity, but no individual happiness;<lb break="yes" />resignation to the will of the sovereign usurped the place of patriotism;<lb break="yes"/>for great enterprizes there was patient obedience, but no genuine<lb break="yes"/>courage; a spirit of order, which by petty laws for regulating the con-<lb break="no"/>duct in the most indifferent transactions, extinguished at once all free-<lb break="no"/>dom of thought and all greatness of character. The most complicated<lb break="yes"/>of all political institutions recorded in history had nipped the bud of<lb break="yes"/>individual liberty; and the founder of the empire of Couzco, who<lb break="yes"/>flattered himself that he should render men happy through restraint,<lb break="yes"/>in fact transformed into mere machines. The Peruvian theocracy<lb break="yes"/>was indeed less oppressive than the government of the Mexican<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="556" facs="#f0009"/> monarch, but both contributed essentially to impart to the monu-<lb break="no"/>ments the religious worship and mythology of these mountaineers that<lb break="yes"/>dismal and gloomy air, which forms so striking a contrast with the<lb break="yes"/>arts and the pleasing fictions of the people of Greece.</p>
                <dateline>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Paris, April,</hi> <choice><sic>1823.</sic><corr type="editorial">1813.</corr></choice></dateline>
                <lb break="yes"/>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 