<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="247" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <p>Chimborazo is 21,000 feet above the<lb break="yes"/>level of the sea, and 9000 above the ele-<lb break="no"/>vated plains on which they stand; and<lb break="yes" />Cotopaxi, 19,000. Till the discovery of<lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>the Himalayas, they were considered the<lb break="yes"/>highest points on the globe.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>We distinguish, says Humboldt, three<lb break="yes"/>kinds of principal forms belonging to the<lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="248" facs="#f0002"/>
                <cb/>high tops of the Andes: the volcanoes<lb break="yes"/>which are yet burning; volcanoes, the<lb break="yes"/>summits of which have sunk after a long<lb break="yes"/>series of eruptions, exhibiting ridges<lb break="yes"/>bristled with points, needles leaning in<lb break="yes"/>different directions, and broken rocks fall-<lb break="no"/>ing into ruins; and a third form of the<lb break="yes" />high tops of the Andes, and the most<lb break="yes"/>majestic of the whole, is that of <hi rendition="#k">Chim-<lb break="no"/>borazo,</hi> the summit of which is circular.<lb break="yes"/>The aspect of mountains of granite has<lb break="yes" />little analogy with that of Chimborazo.<lb break="yes"/>Granite summits are flattened hemispheres,<lb break="yes"/>and the trappean porphyry forms slender<lb break="yes"/>cupolas: but Chimborazo appears like a<lb break="yes"/>cloud at the distance of 200 miles. It<lb break="yes"/>detaches itself from the neighbouring sum-<lb break="no"/>mits, and towers over the whole chain of<lb break="yes"/>the Andes, like that majestic dome pro-<lb break="no"/>duced by the genius of Michael Angelo,<lb break="yes"/>over the antique monuments which sur-<lb break="no" />round the Roman Capitol.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>The bulk of Chimborazo is so enor-<lb break="no"/>mous, that the part which the eye em-<lb break="no"/>braces at once, near the limit of the eternal<lb break="yes" />snows, is 8000 yards in breadth. The ex-<lb break="no"/>treme rarity of the strata of air, across<lb break="yes"/>which we see the tops of the Andes, con-<lb break="no"/>tributes, too, greatly to the splendour of<lb break="yes"/>the snow, and the magical effect of its<lb break="yes"/>reflection. Under the Tropics, at a height<lb break="yes"/>of 6000 yards, the azure vault of the sky<lb break="yes" />appears of an indigo tint. The outlines<lb break="yes"/>of the mountain detach themselves from<lb break="yes"/>the sky in this pure and transparent<lb break="yes" />atmosphere; while the interior strata of<lb break="yes"/>the air, reposing on a plain destitute of<lb break="yes"/>vegetation, which reflects the radiant<lb break="yes"/>heat, are vaporous, and appear to veil the<lb break="yes"/>middle of the mountain.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#k">Cotopaxi</hi> is the loftiest of the volca-<lb break="no"/>noes of the Andes, which at recent epochs<lb break="yes"/>have undergone eruptions; and, notwith-<lb break="no"/>standing it lies near the Equator, its sum-<lb break="no"/>mits are covered with perpetual snows.<lb break="yes"/>The absolute height of Cotopaxi is 18,876<lb break="yes"/>feet, or three miles and a half; conse-<lb break="no"/>quently it is 2,622 feet, or half a mile,<lb break="yes" />higher than Vesuvius would be, were that<lb break="yes"/>mountain placed on the top of the Peak<lb break="yes"/>of Teneriffe! Cotopaxi is the most mis-<lb break="no"/>chievous of the volcanoes in the kingdom<lb break="yes"/>of Quito, and its explosions are the<lb break="yes"/>most frequent and disastrous. The masses<lb break="yes"/>of scori&#x00E6; and the pieces of rock thrown<lb break="yes"/>out of this volcano cover a surface of several<lb break="yes" />square leagues, and would form, were they<lb break="yes"/>heaped together, a prodigious mountain.<lb break="yes"/>In 1738, the flames of Cotopaxi rose<lb break="yes"/>3000 feet, or upwards of half a mile, above<lb break="yes"/>the brink of the crater. In 1744, the<lb break="yes"/>roarings of this volcano were heard at the<lb break="yes"/>distance of 600 miles. On the 4th of<lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>April, 1768, the quantity of ashes ejected<lb break="yes"/>at the mouth of Cotopaxi was so great,<lb break="yes"/>that it was dark till three in the afternoon.<lb break="yes"/>The form of Cotopaxi is the most beauti-<lb break="no"/>ful and regular of the colossal summits of<lb break="yes"/>the high Andes. It is a perfect cone,<lb break="yes"/>which, covered with a perpetual layer of<lb break="yes"/>snow, shines with dazzling splendour at<lb break="yes"/>the setting of the sun, and detaches itself<lb break="yes"/>in the most picturesque manner from the<lb break="yes"/>azure vault above. This covering of snow<lb break="yes"/>conceals from the eye of the observer even<lb break="yes"/>the smallest inequalities of the soil; no<lb break="yes"/>point of rock, no stony mass, penetrating<lb break="yes"/>this coat of ice, or breaking the regularity<lb break="yes"/>of the figure of the cone.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 