<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="127" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">view</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">of</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">america</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">and its</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">native tribes.</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">By</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">alexander</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">von</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#g">hum</hi>boldt.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">From the Introduction to the Pic-<lb break="no"/>turesque Atlas of his Travels not yet<lb break="yes"/>published.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>IT cannot but excite astonishment,<lb break="yes"/>that, at the conclusion of the fifteenth<lb break="yes"/>century, there should have been found,<lb break="yes"/>in a world which we denominate <hi rendition="#i">the new</hi>,
                    <lb break="yes"/>the very same kind of antiquarian re-<lb break="no"/>mains, the same religious notions, and<lb break="yes"/>forms of architecture, as seem to belong<lb break="yes"/>to the earliest ages of civilization in<lb break="yes"/>Asia. It is with the characteristics of<lb break="yes" />nations, as with the internal structure of<lb break="yes"/>the plants that are spread over the face<lb break="yes"/>of the earth. The stamp of the original<lb break="yes"/>stock remains indelible, notwithstanding<lb break="yes"/>the numberless modifications produced<lb break="yes"/>by climate, soil, and various other inci-<lb break="no"/>dents.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the first period after the discovery<lb break="yes"/>of America, the attention of the Euro-<lb break="no"/>peans was more particularly directed to<lb break="yes"/>the gigantic edifices of Corzco, to the<lb break="yes"/>high roads through the midst of the Cor-<lb break="no"/>dilleras, to the lofty graduated pyramids,<lb break="yes"/>to the religious rites, and symbolical<lb break="yes"/>writings of the Mexicans. Descriptions<lb break="yes"/>of different provinces of Mexico and<lb break="yes"/>Peru were then as frequent as are, in our<lb break="yes"/>days, the accounts of the vicinity of Port<lb break="yes"/>Jackson, in New Holland, or the Island<lb break="yes"/>of Otaheite. It is absolutely necessary<lb break="yes"/>to have been upon the spot, in order to<lb break="yes"/>appreciate justly the noble simplicity<lb break="yes"/>and the character of truth and fidelity<lb break="yes"/>which pervade the narrations of the ear-<lb break="no"/>liest Spanish travellers: and, in perusing<lb break="yes"/>their works, we lament only the want of<lb break="yes"/>graphic illustrations, which would have<lb break="yes"/>given us more satisfactory ideas of many<lb break="yes"/>monuments, partly demolished by fana-<lb break="no"/>ticism, and partly fallen to decay through<lb break="yes"/>culpable neglect.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The ardor for those American investi-<lb break="no"/>gations diminished after the commence-<lb break="no"/>ment of the seventeenth century. The<lb break="yes" />Spanish colonies, whose territory alone<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> had been inhabited by civilized nations,<lb break="yes"/>were shut against foreigners; and when,<lb break="yes"/>more recently, the Abbé Clavigero pub-<lb break="no"/>lished, in Italy, his work on the ancient<lb break="yes" />history of Mexico, doubts were raised<lb break="yes"/>concerning many facts which were for-<lb break="no"/>merly confirmed by numerous eye-wit-<lb break="no"/>nesses, frequently persons by no means<lb break="yes"/>amicably disposed towards each other.<lb break="yes"/>Celebrated writers, who received less<lb break="yes"/>pleasure from the harmony of nature<lb break="yes" />than from her contrasts, have represented<lb break="yes"/>America as one vast swamp, unfavour-<lb break="no"/>able to the propagation of the animal<lb break="yes"/>species, and not till of late inhabited by<lb break="yes" />races of men not surpassing the South<lb break="yes"/>Sea islanders in civilization. An unli-<lb break="no"/>mited scepticism had banished sound<lb break="yes"/>criticism from the historical disquisitions<lb break="yes"/>on the Americans. The fictions of a<lb break="yes"/>Solis and some other travellers who had<lb break="yes"/>never quitted Europe, were blended<lb break="yes"/>with the faithful and simple relations of<lb break="yes"/>the earliest visitors of the New World;<lb break="yes"/>and it was deemed the duty of a philoso-<lb break="no"/>phic historian to protest, in the first<lb break="yes"/>place, against all that the missionaries<lb break="yes"/>had observed.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Towards the end of the past century, a<lb break="yes"/>happy alteration took place in regard to<lb break="yes"/>the opinions entertained respecting the<lb break="yes"/>civilisation of nations, and the causes<lb break="yes"/>that alternately promote and obstruct its<lb break="yes"/>progress. We became acquainted with<lb break="yes"/>nations whose manners, institutions, and<lb break="yes"/>arts, are almost as different from those<lb break="yes"/>of the Greeks and Romans, as the origi-<lb break="no"/>nal forms of the extinct species of ani-<lb break="no"/>mals from those which at present engage<lb break="yes" />the attention of naturalists. The society<lb break="yes"/>of Calcutta has thrown a brilliant light<lb break="yes"/>over the history of the Asiatic nations.<lb break="yes"/>The monuments of Egypt have, of late,<lb break="yes"/>been partly described with admirable<lb break="yes" />correctness, and partly compared with<lb break="yes"/>those of the most distant regions; and<lb break="yes"/>my researches concerning the native<lb break="yes"/>tribes of America appear at an epoch,<lb break="yes"/>when that which does not approach to<lb break="yes"/>the style and manner of which the<lb break="yes"/>Greeks have left us inimitable models, is<lb break="yes" />nevertheless deemed well worthy of at-<lb break="no"/>tention.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the description of the historical<lb break="yes"/>monuments of America, I have endea-<lb break="no"/>voured to observe a due mean between<lb break="yes" />two routes alternately pursued by those<lb break="yes"/>literati who have entered into the discus-<lb break="no"/>sion of such monuments<choice><sic>.</sic><corr type="editorial">,</corr></choice> languages, and<lb break="yes"/>national traditions. The one adopting<lb break="yes" />hypotheses which, though brilliant, rest<lb break="yes"/>on tottering foundations, have deduced<lb break="yes"/>general conclusions from a small num-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="128" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/> ber of insulated facts. They found, in<lb break="yes"/>America, Chinese and Egyptian colonies,<lb break="yes"/>Celtic dialects, and the alphabet of the<lb break="yes"/>Phœnicians. While we yet remain in<lb break="yes"/>the dark respecting the origin of the<lb break="yes"/>Osci, the Goths, and the Celts, they pre-<lb break="no"/>tended to pronounce decisively on the<lb break="yes"/>origin of the tribes of the New World.<lb break="yes"/>Other writers, on the contrary, amassed<lb break="yes"/>materials, without ever raising them-<lb break="no"/>selves to any general notions: a pro-<lb break="no" />ceeding from which the history of nations<lb break="yes"/>can derive as little benefit as the different<lb break="yes"/>branches of the natural sciences. I shall<lb break="yes"/>deem myself fortunate if I shall be<lb break="yes" />thought to have equally avoided both<lb break="yes"/>these extremes. A small number of<lb break="yes"/>tribes, far distant from one another, as<lb break="yes"/>the Etruscans, the Egyptians, the Tibe-<lb break="no"/>tians, the Aztekians, exhibit striking co-<lb break="no"/>incidences in their buildings and religious<lb break="yes"/>institutions, in their division of the year,<lb break="yes"/>in their returning periods of time, and<lb break="yes"/>in their mystical representations. The<lb break="yes"/>historian ought not to overlook these<lb break="yes"/>coincidences, for which it is just as diffi-<lb break="no"/>cult to account as for the resemblance<lb break="yes"/>between the Sanscrit, Persian, Greek,<lb break="yes"/>and German idioms; but while he rises<lb break="yes"/>to general ideas, he should know how to<lb break="yes" />stop at the point where we are abandon-<lb break="no"/>ed by certain facts. Agreeably to these<lb break="yes"/>principles, I will attempt to state the re-<lb break="no"/>sults deduced from the data which I<lb break="yes"/>have been enabled to collect concerning<lb break="yes"/>the native tribes of America.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>An attentive examination of the geo-<lb break="no"/>logical relations of the New World, and<lb break="yes"/>a consideration of the equilibrium of the<lb break="yes"/>waters spread over the surface of the<lb break="yes"/>earth, forbid the assumption that the<lb break="yes"/>new and the old continents rose at dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent times from the bosom of the deep.<lb break="yes" />On both hemispheres we perceive the like<lb break="yes"/>series of rocky strata lying one above<lb break="yes"/>another, and probably the granite, gyp-<lb break="no"/>sum, and sand-stone formations in the<lb break="yes" />mountains of Peru, had their origin at<lb break="yes"/>the same period as the corresponding<lb break="yes"/>strata in the Alps of Switzerland. The<lb break="yes"/>whole globe has apparently been visited<lb break="yes"/>by the same catastrophes. On the sum-<lb break="no"/>mits of the Andes, at an elevation ex-<lb break="no"/>ceeding that of Mont Blanc, are found<lb break="yes"/>the petrified muscles of the ocean. Fos-<lb break="no"/>sile bones of elephants are scattered over<lb break="yes"/>the equatorial regions, and, what is re-<lb break="no"/>markable, they are met with, not only<lb break="yes"/>under the palms in the torrid valleys of<lb break="yes"/>the Oronoko, but on the highest and<lb break="yes"/>coldest plains of the Cordilleras. In the<lb break="yes" />new as in the old world, whole creations<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>and whole species of organic bodies have<lb break="yes"/>become extinct, to give place to those<lb break="yes"/>which now people the earth, the air, and<lb break="yes"/>the waters.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>No grounds exist for presuming that<lb break="yes"/>America was first peopled by men at a<lb break="yes"/>much later period than the other conti-<lb break="no" />nents. The luxuriant vegetation, the<lb break="yes"/>breadth of the rivers, and the partial in-<lb break="no"/>undations are powerful obstacles to the<lb break="yes"/>migration of nations in tropical coun-<lb break="no"/>tries. Extensive tracts of northern Asia<lb break="yes"/>are as thinly peopled as the savannahs<lb break="yes"/>of New Mexico and Paraguay, and we<lb break="yes" />should by no means presuppose that the<lb break="yes"/>countries first inhabited must necessarily<lb break="yes"/>be the most populous.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The question relative to the origin of<lb break="yes"/>the population of America can no more<lb break="yes"/>belong to the province of history, than<lb break="yes"/>those concerning the origin of plants<lb break="yes"/>and animals, and on the distribution of<lb break="yes"/>organic germs, to the natural sciences.<lb break="yes"/>History, when it goes back to the most<lb break="yes"/>ancient periods, exhibits to us almost all<lb break="yes"/>the parts of the globe inhabited by peo-<lb break="no"/>ple who look upon themselves as abori-<lb break="no"/>gines, because their ancestry is unknown<lb break="yes" />to them. Amidst a variety of tribes who<lb break="yes"/>succeeded and intermingled with one<lb break="yes"/>another, it is impossible to decide with<lb break="yes"/>certainty from which of them the popu-<lb break="no" />lation first proceeded, and to define the<lb break="yes"/>limits beyond which the empire of cos-<lb break="no"/>mogonal tradition commences.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The tribes of America, with the ex-<lb break="no"/>ception of those that are nearest to the<lb break="yes"/>polar circle, belong all to one single<lb break="yes"/>race, which is distinguished by the form<lb break="yes"/>of the skull, complexion, very scanty<lb break="yes"/>beard, and straight hair. The American<lb break="yes"/>race exhibits striking analogies with that<lb break="yes"/>of the Mongol tribes, which comprehends<lb break="yes"/>the descendants of the Hiong-nu, so fa-<lb break="no"/>mous under the denomination of Huns,<lb break="yes"/>the Kalkases, the Cahnucks, and the<lb break="yes" />Burattes. Recent observations have<lb break="yes"/>even demonstrated, that not only the in-<lb break="no"/>habitants of Oonalashka, but several<lb break="yes" />South American tribes also, denote, by<lb break="yes"/>the osteological characters of the skull,<lb break="yes"/>a transition from the American to the<lb break="yes"/>Mongol race. If the sable African race,<lb break="yes" />and the numberless tribes which inhabit<lb break="yes"/>the interior of Asia and its north-eastern<lb break="yes"/>regions, and to which systematic geo-<lb break="no"/>graphers have given the indefinite appel-<lb break="no"/>lation of Tartars or Tschoudes, should<lb break="yes"/>ever become better known to us, the<lb break="yes"/>Caucasian, Mongol, American, Malay,<lb break="yes"/>and Negro races will be less widely<lb break="yes"/>separated than they have been, and we<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="129" facs="#f0003"/>
                    <cb/> shall recognize, in this great family of<lb break="yes"/>man, one single original, which has un-<lb break="no"/>dergone various modifications from cir-<lb break="no"/>cumstances that we shall, perhaps, never<lb break="yes" />be able to penetrate.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The native tribes of the new world,<lb break="yes"/>though all of them are allied by very<lb break="yes"/>essential characteristics, yet, on the<lb break="yes" />other hand, present, in their moveable<lb break="yes"/>features, in their more or less dark com-<lb break="no"/>plexion, in their shape and size, varieties<lb break="yes"/>not less striking than the difference which<lb break="yes"/>we perceive between the Arabs, Per-<lb break="no"/>sians, and Slavonians of the Circassian<lb break="yes"/>race. The hordes, however, which rove<lb break="yes"/>about in the burning plains of the equi-<lb break="no"/>noctial regions are by no means of a<lb break="yes"/>darker colour than the mountaineers, or<lb break="yes"/>the inhabitants of the temperate zone;<lb break="yes"/>whether it be that in man, as in most<lb break="yes"/>animals, there is a certain period of life<lb break="yes"/>beyond which the influence of climate<lb break="yes"/>and food is insignificant, or that the de-<lb break="no"/>viation from the original mode is not<lb break="yes" />perceptible till the expiration of many<lb break="yes"/>centuries. From all that has been ob-<lb break="no"/>served, however, it results, that the Ame-<lb break="no"/>ricans, like the Mongol tribes, have a less<lb break="yes" />flexible organization than the other<lb break="yes"/>Asiatic and European nations.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The American race, though less nu-<lb break="no"/>merous than any other, is dispersed<lb break="yes"/>over the greatest portion of the globe.<lb break="yes"/>It extends, through both hemispheres,<lb break="yes"/>from 68° N. L. to 55° S. L. It is the<lb break="yes"/>only one that, at the same time, inhabits<lb break="yes"/>the scorching vallies bounded by the<lb break="yes" />ocean, and the ridges of mountains ele-<lb break="no"/>vated more than 200 fathoms above the<lb break="yes"/>Peak of Teneriffe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">(To be continued.)</hi></hi>
                </p>
                <cb/>
                <pb n="311" facs="#f0004"/>
                <cb/>
                <cb/>
            </div>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">view</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">of</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">america</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">and its</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">native tribes.<lb break="yes"/>by alexander von humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">From the Introduction to the Picturesque<lb break="yes" />Atlas of his Travels.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">Continued from p.</hi> 166.)</head>
                <p>THE number of the languages which<lb break="yes"/>distinguish the indigenous nations from<lb break="yes"/>one another seems to be still greater<lb break="yes"/>in America than in Africa, where,<lb break="yes"/>according to the recent researches of<lb break="yes"/>Messrs. Seetzen and Vater, they ex-<lb break="no"/>ceed 140. In this respect the whole of<lb break="yes"/>America resembles the Caucasus, Italy<lb break="yes"/>before the conquest of the Romans, and<lb break="yes"/>Asia Minor at the time when the Cili-<lb break="no" />cians, of Semitic origin, the Phrygians,<lb break="yes"/>of Thracian descent, the Lydians and<lb break="yes"/>the Celts dwelt here together within a<lb break="yes"/>small compass. The formation of the<lb break="yes"/>earth, the extreme luxuriance of the ve-<lb break="no"/>getable kingdom, and the dread of the<lb break="yes"/>intense heat of the vallies entertained by<lb break="yes"/>the inhabitants of the tropical regions,<lb break="yes"/>impede mutual intercourse and create<lb break="yes"/>an astonishing diversity of American<lb break="yes"/>dialects. This diversity is not so great<lb break="yes"/>in the savannahs and forests of the<lb break="yes"/>north, which are traversed by hunters,<lb break="yes"/>on the banks of the great rivers, along<lb break="yes"/>the coasts of the ocean, and wherever<lb break="yes"/>the Incas have introduced their theocracy<lb break="yes"/>by force of arms.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When we speak of more than a hun-<lb break="no"/>dred languages, on a continent whose<lb break="yes"/>total population is not equal to that of<lb break="yes"/>France, we term those different lan-<lb break="no"/>guages which have the same affinity to<lb break="yes"/>one another as, I will not say the Ger-<lb break="no"/>man to the Dutch, or the Italian to the<lb break="yes" />Spanish; but as the Danish to the Ger-<lb break="no"/>man, the Chaldee to the Arabic, the<lb break="yes"/>Greek to the Latin. As a person be-<lb break="no" />comes more and more familiar with the<lb break="yes"/>labyrinth of American languages, he per-<lb break="no"/>ceives that many of them belong to one<lb break="yes"/>and the same family, while a great num-<lb break="no"/>ber of others remain insulated like the<lb break="yes"/>Basque among the European, and the<lb break="yes"/>Japanese among the Asiatic languages.<lb break="yes" />This insulation is perhaps only apparent,<lb break="yes"/>and it may be presumed that those lan-<lb break="no"/>guages which seem to defy all ethnogra-<lb break="no"/>phic classification, are allied to others<lb break="yes"/>either long extinct, or peculiar to na-<lb break="no"/>tions whom no travellers have hitherto<lb break="yes"/>visited.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Most of the American languages, even<lb break="yes"/>those whose groups differ from one<lb break="yes"/>another in the same manner as the dia-<lb break="no" />lects of German, Celtic, and Slavonian<lb break="yes"/>origin, exhibit a certain resemblance in<lb break="yes"/>their general organization, which if it<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="312" facs="#f0005"/>
                    <cb/>does not indicate one common stock, at<lb break="yes"/>least denotes a very close analogy in the<lb break="yes"/>intellectual faculties of the American na-<lb break="no"/>tions, from Greenland to the streights of<lb break="yes" />Magellan.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Very minute enquiries, conducted ac-<lb break="no"/>cording to a method before unknown in<lb break="yes"/>etymological studies, have proved, that<lb break="yes"/>there is a small number of words com-<lb break="no"/>mon to the languages of the Old and<lb break="yes"/>New World. In 83 American languages,<lb break="yes"/>examined by Messrs. Barton and Vater,<lb break="yes"/>have been found about 170 words which<lb break="yes"/>seemed to have the same roots; and we<lb break="yes"/>may easily convince ourselves that these<lb break="yes" />resemblances are by no means acci-<lb break="no"/>dental or an imitative harmony, and per-<lb break="no"/>haps resulting only from the uniform<lb break="yes"/>structure of the organs which renders<lb break="yes"/>the first articulated tones of children<lb break="yes"/>pretty nearly the same in all parts of the<lb break="yes"/>world. Out of 170 words, in which this<lb break="yes"/>similarity is perceived, three fifths seem<lb break="yes"/>to claim affinity with the languages of<lb break="yes"/>the Mantchous, Tungusians, Mongols,<lb break="yes"/>and Samojedes, and the other two-fifths<lb break="yes"/>with Celtic and Tschoudian dialects, and<lb break="yes"/>with the Basque, Coptic, and Congo lan-<lb break="no"/>guages. Those words were found out on<lb break="yes"/>a comparison of the whole of the Ameri-<lb break="no" />can languages, with the whole of the lan-<lb break="no"/>guages of the Old World; for as yet we<lb break="yes"/>know not of any American dialect which<lb break="yes"/>can be deemed more nearly allied than<lb break="yes"/>the rest to any of the numerous groups of<lb break="yes"/>Asiatic, African, or European languages.<lb break="yes"/>The assertions of some scholars, proceed-<lb break="no"/>ing upon abstract theories, respecting<lb break="yes"/>the supposed poverty of all the Ameri-<lb break="no"/>can languages, as well as the extraor-<lb break="no"/>dinary scantiness of their system of num-<lb break="no"/>bers, are as rash and unfounded as the<lb break="yes" />statements of others who contend for<lb break="yes"/>the imbecility and stupidity of the hu-<lb break="no"/>man race in the New World, the di-<lb break="no"/>minution of organic bodies, and the de-<lb break="no"/>generacy of the animals transported<lb break="yes"/>thither from our hemisphere.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Various dialects at present spoken by<lb break="yes"/>barbarous nations alone, seem to be<lb break="yes"/>relics of copious and flexible languages,<lb break="yes"/>which denote a considerable progress in<lb break="yes" />civilization. I shall not here enter into<lb break="yes"/>an examination of the question&#x2014;whether<lb break="yes"/>the original condition of mankind was a<lb break="yes"/>state of rudeness and stupidity, or<lb break="yes" />whether the savage hordes are descended<lb break="yes"/>from nations whose mental powers, as<lb break="yes"/>well as the language in which they are<lb break="yes"/>reflected, were previously both equally<lb break="yes" />developed: but I shall merely observe<lb break="yes"/>that the little which we know of the<lb break="yes"/>history of the Americans seems to de-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/>monstrate that those tribes which mi-<lb break="no"/>grated from north to south, possessed in<lb break="yes"/>their northern abodes that variety of lan-<lb break="no"/>guages which we discover in the tropical<lb break="yes" />regions. Hence we may draw the ana-<lb break="no"/>logical inference that the ramification,<lb break="yes"/>or to use an expression independent of<lb break="yes"/>all systems the diversity of the languages<lb break="yes"/>is a very ancient phenomenon. Perhaps<lb break="yes"/>the languages which we term American<lb break="yes"/>originally belong no more to this quarter<lb break="yes"/>of the globe than the Madjarian or Hun-<lb break="no"/>garian, and the Tschoudian or Finnish<lb break="yes"/>do to Europe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It must be admitted that the compari-<lb break="no"/>son of the languages of the Old and New<lb break="yes"/>World has led as yet to no general re-<lb break="no" />sults; but we ought not on this account<lb break="yes"/>to relinquish our hopes that this study<lb break="yes"/>will prove more productive when the sa-<lb break="no"/>gacity of scholars shall possess a larger<lb break="yes"/>stock of materials. How many languages<lb break="yes"/>of America, as well as of the interior and<lb break="yes"/>eastern part of Asia may there still be,<lb break="yes"/>whose mechanism is as unknown to us as<lb break="yes"/>that of the Tyrrhenian, Oscian, and<lb break="yes"/>Sabine dialects! Of the nations which<lb break="yes"/>disappeared from the Old World, there<lb break="yes" />may perhaps still exist some petty de-<lb break="no"/>tached tribes in the vast wilds of America.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If, however, the early intercourse be-<lb break="no"/>tween the two worlds can be but very<lb break="yes"/>imperfectly proved by the languages, it<lb break="yes" />is on the other hand unequivocally de-<lb break="no"/>monstrated by the cosmogonies, the mo-<lb break="no"/>numents, hieroglyphics, and institutions<lb break="yes"/>of the American and Asiatic nations.<lb break="yes"/>I think that to the evidences already ad-<lb break="no"/>duced on this point, I have added no<lb break="yes"/>small number that were hitherto un-<lb break="no" />known. I have every where endeavoured<lb break="yes"/>to discriminate that which denotes a com-<lb break="no"/>mon origin from what must be considered<lb break="yes"/>as the result of analogous relations,<lb break="yes" />subsisting between nations which have<lb break="yes"/>attained the highest degree of civi-<lb break="no"/>lization.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>To determine the period of the ancient<lb break="yes"/>connection between the two worlds was<lb break="yes"/>previously impracticable, and it would be<lb break="yes"/>too presumptuous to pretend to de-<lb break="no"/>signate the group of nations in the Old<lb break="yes"/>World, to which the Toltekes, Aztekes,<lb break="yes"/>Muyscas, or Peruvians, are nearest al-<lb break="no"/>lied, since the relations here alluded to<lb break="yes"/>are founded upon such traditions, monu-<lb break="no"/>ments, and usages, as may possibly be<lb break="yes"/>of higher antiquity than the present di-<lb break="no"/>vision of the Asiatics into Mongols, Hin-<lb break="no"/>doos, Tongouses, and Chinese.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the time of the discovery of the<lb break="yes"/>New World, or to speak more correctly,<lb break="yes"/>at the period of the first Spanish inva-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="313" facs="#f0006"/>
                    <cb/>sion, the American nations, which had<lb break="yes"/>made the greatest progress in civilization<lb break="yes"/>were mountaineers. People born in<lb break="yes"/>the valleys of a temperate region climbed<lb break="yes"/>the ridges of the Cordilleras, which be-<lb break="no"/>come more elevated as they approach<lb break="yes"/>the equator; and on these heights they<lb break="yes"/>found a temperature and vegetation si-<lb break="no"/>milar to those of their native land.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>All those situations in which man has<lb break="yes"/>to struggle with natural obstacles on a<lb break="yes"/>soil of inferior fertility, and is not abso-<lb break="no"/>lutely vanquished in too unequal a con-<lb break="no"/>flict, are most favourable to the de-<lb break="no"/>velopment of his energies. On the Cau-<lb break="no"/>casus and in the centre of Asia the bar-<lb break="no" />ren mountains afford an asylum to inde-<lb break="no"/>pendent and savage tribes. In the equi-<lb break="no"/>noctial regions of America, where ever-<lb break="no"/>verdant savannahs rise above the region<lb break="yes"/>of the clouds, the Cordilleras alone are<lb break="yes"/>inhabited by polished tribes; the first<lb break="yes"/>advances in science were there coeval<lb break="yes" />with the extraordinary institutions by no<lb break="yes"/>means favourable to individual liberty.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We perceive in the New World, as in<lb break="yes"/>Asia and Africa, various centres whence<lb break="yes"/>spread an original civilization, whose<lb break="yes"/>mutual relations, however, we are as<lb break="yes"/>incapable of discovering as those of<lb break="yes"/>Meröe, Tibet, and China. Mexico de-<lb break="no"/>rived its civilization from a more northern<lb break="yes"/>region. In South America it was the<lb break="yes"/>extensive structures of Tiahuanako that<lb break="yes"/>furnished the models of those monu-<lb break="no"/>ments which the Incas erected at Coutz-<lb break="no" />ko. Ramparts of considerable extent,<lb break="yes"/>bronze weapons, and engraved stones<lb break="yes"/>found in the vast plains of Upper Ca-<lb break="no"/>nada, in Florida, and in the wilds<lb break="yes"/>bounded by the Oronoko, Cassiquiare,<lb break="yes"/>and Guainia, attest that these regions<lb break="yes"/>now traversed only by hordes of savage<lb break="yes"/>hunters were once the abode of nations<lb break="yes"/>who had made some proficiency in the<lb break="yes"/>arts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">(To be concluded in our next.)</hi></hi>
                </p>
                <cb/>
                <pb n="402" facs="#f0007"/>
                <cb/>
                <cb/>
            </div>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">view</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">of</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">america</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">and its</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">native tribes.</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">By</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">alexander von humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">Concluded from p.</hi> 313.)</head>
                <p>THE unequal distribution of the diffe-<lb break="no"/>rent species of brute animals over the<lb break="yes"/>earth, had a powerful influence on the<lb break="yes"/>condition of nations, and on their more<lb break="yes"/>or less rapid progress in civilization. In<lb break="yes"/>the Old World, it was the pastoral life<lb break="yes"/>that formed the link between the hunter<lb break="yes"/>and the husbandman. The ruminating<lb break="yes"/>animals, so easily naturalized in every<lb break="yes"/>climate, were the companions of the<lb break="yes"/>African Negro, as well as of the Mon-<lb break="no" />gols, the Malays, and Caucasian race.<lb break="yes"/>Now, though several quadrupeds, and<lb break="yes"/>very numerous species of vegetables, are<lb break="yes"/>common to the northernmost parts of<lb break="yes"/>both worlds, yet the only kinds of<lb break="yes"/>horned cattle possessed by America are<lb break="yes"/>the buffalo and the bison, two varieties<lb break="yes" />which it is very difficult to domesticate,<lb break="yes"/>and the females of which, notwithstand-<lb break="no"/>ing the richness of the pastures, yield<lb break="yes"/>but little milk. The American hunter,<lb break="yes" />therefore, was not prepared, by the care<lb break="yes"/>of flocks and herds, and the occupations<lb break="yes"/>of a pastoral life, for the pursuits of<lb break="yes"/>agriculture. Never did the inhabitants<lb break="yes"/>of the Cordilleras attempt to milk the<lb break="yes"/>lama, alpaca, or guanaco; and milk diet<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="403" facs="#f0008"/>
                    <cb/>was formerly as unknown to the Ameri-<lb break="no"/>cans, as it is to many of the tribes of<lb break="yes"/>eastern Asia.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There is no instance of the savage<lb break="yes"/>living in the forests of the temperate<lb break="yes"/>zone, having voluntarily exchanged the<lb break="yes"/><choice><sic>chace</sic><corr type="editorial">chase</corr></choice> for agriculture. This transition,<lb break="yes"/>the most important and the most diffi-<lb break="no"/>cult in the history of human society,<lb break="yes"/>cannot be effected but by compulsory<lb break="yes" />means. When in their great migrations<lb break="yes"/>troops of hunters, persecuted by other<lb break="yes"/>warrior hordes, reach the plains of the<lb break="yes"/>equinoctial zone, the impenetrable close-<lb break="no"/>ness of the woods, and the luxuriant<lb break="yes"/>growth of the vegetable species, produce<lb break="yes"/>an essential change in their character<lb break="yes"/>and way of life. Between the Oronoko,<lb break="yes"/>Ukajale, and the river of Amazons,<lb break="yes"/>there are tracts where man finds scarcely<lb break="yes"/>any thing but streams and lakes. Here<lb break="yes"/>on the banks of the rivers, even the most<lb break="yes" />savage inhabitants surround their huts<lb break="yes"/>with the fig of Paradise, the jatropha<lb break="yes"/>tree, and some other vegetables, which<lb break="yes"/>contribute to their subsistence.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Neither historical facts nor popular<lb break="yes"/>tradition record that any connexion<lb break="yes"/>ever subsisted between the South Ameri-<lb break="no"/>can nations and those dwelling to the<lb break="yes"/>north of the isthmus of Panama. The<lb break="yes"/>annals of the Mexican empire seem to<lb break="yes"/>go back to the sixth century of our æra.<lb break="yes" />They state the periods of the migrations<lb break="yes"/>which took place, the causes which oc-<lb break="no"/>casioned them, the names of the leaders<lb break="yes"/>belonging to the illustrious family of the<lb break="yes" />Citins who conducted northern tribes<lb break="yes"/>from the unknown regions of Aztlan and<lb break="yes"/>Teocolhuacan to the plains of Anahuac.<lb break="yes"/>The founding of Tenochtilan happens<lb break="yes"/>like that of Rome in the heroic age, and<lb break="yes"/>it is only from the 12th century that the<lb break="yes"/>Aztekian chronicles, like those of the<lb break="yes" />Chinese and Tibetians, contain the al-<lb break="no"/>most uninterrupted record of the secu-<lb break="no"/>lar festivals, the succession of the kings,<lb break="yes"/>the tributes imposed upon the conquered,<lb break="yes"/>the foundation of cities, meteorological<lb break="yes" />phenomena, and many trivial incidents<lb break="yes"/>which have an influence on society in in-<lb break="no"/>fant states.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But though no traditions denote any<lb break="yes"/>immediate connexion between the na-<lb break="no"/>tions of the two grand divisions of Ame-<lb break="no" />rica, their history on the other hand ex-<lb break="no"/>hibits striking coincidences in the politi-<lb break="no"/>cal and religious revolutions which led<lb break="yes"/>to the civilization of the Aztekes, Muys-<lb break="no" />cas and Peruvians. Bearded men of a<lb break="yes"/>lighter complexion than the natives of<lb break="yes"/>Anahuac, Cundinamarca, and the plain<lb break="yes"/>of Couzco, make their appearance, with-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/> out its being known from what country<lb break="yes"/>they come. As high priests, legislators,<lb break="yes"/>friends of peace, and of the arts and<lb break="yes"/>sciences, which it promotes, they accom-<lb break="no"/>plish a change in the state of the nations,<lb break="yes"/>from whom they experience a respectful<lb break="yes"/>reception. Quetzalcoatl, Bochica, and<lb break="yes"/>Mango Capac, are the sacred names of<lb break="yes"/>these mysterious beings. <choice>
                        <sic>Quetzalcoat</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Quetzalcoatl</corr>
                    </choice>
                    <lb break="yes"/>comes in black priestly attire from Pa-<lb break="no"/>nuco and the shores of the Mexican<lb break="yes"/>Gulf: Bochica, the Buddha of the<lb break="yes"/>Muyscas appears on the elevated plains<lb break="yes"/>of Bogota advancing from the savannahs<lb break="yes"/>situated on the east side of the <choice>
                        <sic>Corderil-<lb break="no"/>las</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Cordille-<lb break="no"/>ras</corr>
                    </choice>. The history of these lawgivers is<lb break="yes"/>full of marvellous stories, religious fic-<lb break="no"/>tions, and such circumstances as betray<lb break="yes"/>an allegorical meaning. Some scholars<lb break="yes" />have conjectured that these foreigners<lb break="yes"/>might have been shipwrecked Europeans,<lb break="yes"/>or descendants of the <choice>
                        <sic>Scandinivians</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Scandinavians</corr>
                    </choice>,<lb break="yes"/>who as early as the 11th century visited<lb break="yes"/>Greenland, Newfoundland, and perhaps<lb break="yes"/>even Nova Scotia; but the slightest re-<lb break="no"/>flection on the period of the first Tol-<lb break="no"/>tekian emigrations, on the monastic in-<lb break="no" />stitutions, the religious symbols, the ca-<lb break="no"/>lendar and the forms of the monuments<lb break="yes"/>of Cholula, Sogamozo, and Couzco, will<lb break="yes"/>lead to the conviction that the codes of<lb break="yes" />Quetzalcoatl, Bochica, and Mango<lb break="yes"/>Capac, could not possibly derive their<lb break="yes"/>origin from the north of Europe. Every<lb break="yes"/>thing, on the contrary, seems to point to<lb break="yes" />eastern Asia, and to people connected<lb break="yes"/>with the Tibetians, the Shamanists, the<lb break="yes"/>Tartars, and the bearded Ainos of the<lb break="yes"/>islands of Jesso and Sachalin.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When I employ the terms&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Monu-<lb break="no"/>ments of the New World&#x2014;progress in<lb break="yes"/>the imitative arts&#x2014;cultivation of the un-<lb break="no"/>derstanding</hi>, in my inquiries respecting<lb break="yes"/>America, it is by no means my inten-<lb break="no"/>tion to denote a state of things which is<lb break="yes"/>rather vaguely denominated a higher de-<lb break="no"/>gree of culture and civilization. Nothing<lb break="yes"/>is more difficult than to institute com-<lb break="no"/>parisons between nations who have ad-<lb break="no" />vanced by different roads to social im-<lb break="no"/>provement. The Mexicans and Peru-<lb break="no"/>vians must not be judged by such princi-<lb break="no" />ples as are deduced from the history of<lb break="yes"/>the nations of whom our studies are con-<lb break="no"/>tinually reminding us. They differ from<lb break="yes"/>the Greeks and Romans in the same<lb break="yes"/>ratio as they resemble the Etruscans and<lb break="yes"/>Tibetians. The theocratic government<lb break="yes"/>of the Peruvians favoured on the one<lb break="yes"/>hand the progress of industry, public<lb break="yes"/>works, and, if I may be allowed the <choice>
                        <sic>ex-<lb break="no"/>presion</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">ex-<lb break="no"/>pression</corr>
                    </choice>, whatever relates to civilization<lb break="yes"/>in general and in mass: on the other<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="404" facs="#f0009"/>
                    <cb/> hand it prevented the development of<lb break="yes"/>individual energies. Among the Greeks<lb break="yes"/>it was just the reverse, and till the time<lb break="yes"/>of Pericles the free and rapid mental<lb break="yes" />development of individuals bore no pro-<lb break="no"/>portion to the slow advance of national<lb break="yes"/>cultivation. The empire of the Incas<lb break="yes"/>might be likened to a vast monastic in-<lb break="no" />stitution, in which every member had<lb break="yes"/>prescribed to him what he was to do<lb break="yes"/>for the general benefit. Whoever makes<lb break="yes" />himself acquainted on the spot with those<lb break="yes"/>Peruvians, who for ages retained their<lb break="yes"/>national physiognomy without alteration,<lb break="yes"/>will be enabled duly to appreciate the<lb break="yes"/>code of Mango Capac and its influence<lb break="yes"/>on morals and the public weal. There<lb break="yes"/>was general prosperity, but no indi-<lb break="no" />vidual happiness; resignation to the will<lb break="yes"/>of the sovereign usurped the place of<lb break="yes"/>patriotism; for great enterprizes there<lb break="yes"/>was patient obedience, but no genuine<lb break="yes"/>courage; a spirit of order, which by<lb break="yes"/>petty laws for regulating the conduct in<lb break="yes"/>the most indifferent transactions, ex-<lb break="no" />tinguished at once all freedom of thought<lb break="yes"/>and all greatness of character. The<lb break="yes"/>most complicated of all political institu-<lb break="no"/>tions recorded in history had nipped the<lb break="yes"/>bud of individual liberty; and the foun-<lb break="no"/>der of the empire of Couzco, who flat-<lb break="no"/>tered himself that he should render men<lb break="yes" />happy through restraint, in fact trans-<lb break="no"/>formed into mere machines. The Peru-<lb break="no"/>vian theocracy was indeed less oppres-<lb break="no"/>sive than the government of the Mexi-<lb break="no"/>can monarch, but both contributed es-<lb break="no"/>sentially to impart to the monuments<lb break="yes"/>the religious worship and mythology of<lb break="yes"/>these mountaineers that dismal and<lb break="yes"/>gloomy air, which forms so striking a<lb break="yes"/>contrast with the arts and the pleasing<lb break="yes"/>fictions of the people of Greece.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <dateline>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Paris, April,</hi> 1813.</dateline>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 