<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="100" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">description of the volcano at cotopaxi.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#i">From the London Methodist Magazine.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#c">
                            <hi rendition="#k">to the editor.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#et">
                            <hi rendition="#k">Rev. Sir,</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#k">At</hi> a period when philosophical research is pressed into the<lb break="yes"/>service of scepticism and infidelity, it must be highly gratifying<lb break="yes"/>to real christians of every creed, to peruse that valuable de-<lb break="no"/>partment of your excellent Magazine, where you have recorded<lb break="yes"/>so many important facts, in which <hi rendition="#i">the works of God are display-<lb break="no"/>ed.</hi> The following description of the volcano at Cotopaxi, is<lb break="yes" />extracted from M. de Humboldt’s Researches in South Amer-<lb break="no" />ica. That majestic monument of Omnipotence, is on one of<lb break="yes" />those huge mountains of that extended chain called the Andes,<lb break="yes"/>or the Cordilleras, which stretches from the isthmus of Darien,<lb break="yes"/>to the straights of <choice>
                            <sic>Magellen</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">Magellan</corr>
                        </choice>, a distance of near four thousand<lb break="yes"/>miles. While the sceptical philosopher views the stupendous<lb break="yes"/>mountain, and is confounded in every attempt to account for<lb break="yes"/>its formation, the humble believer <hi rendition="#i">in God, in Christ, in the bible</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>on the wings of <choice>
                            <sic>dovout</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">devout</corr>
                        </choice> contemplation, soars to its towering<lb break="yes"/>height; and on its lofty summit finds an altar, where he offers<lb break="yes"/>to the Maker of the universe the incense of his astonishment<lb break="yes"/>and praise. Whether this scientific and indefatigable traveller<lb break="yes" />will approve or blame my effort, to throw his sublime descrip-<lb break="no"/>tion of Cotopaxi, into the treasury of the church of God, I can-<lb break="no"/>not determine: but I sincerely hope, that its insertion in your<lb break="yes"/>useful miscellany will contribute to the pleasure and profit of<lb break="yes"/>many of your pious readers.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <closer>
                        <salute>
                            <hi rendition="#et">I am, your’s, &amp;c. G*****.</hi>
                        </salute>
                    </closer>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <dateline>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Margate, Feb.</hi> 10,</dateline>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <p>“<hi rendition="#k">Cotopaxi</hi> is the loftiest of those volcanoes of the Andes<lb break="yes"/>which at recent epochs have undergone eruptions. Its abso-<lb break="no"/>lute height is five thousand seven hundred and fifty-four metres;<note place="foot" n="*">The French metre is equal to 3,987,100 English inches.</note>
                        <lb break="yes"/>(about eighteen thousand seven hundred and thirty six English<lb break="yes"/>feet.) It is double that of Canigou; and consequently eight<lb break="yes"/>hundred metres higher than Vesuvius would be were it placed<lb break="yes"/>on the top of the peak of Teneriffe.<note place="foot" n="†">Vesuvius is 3900 feet above the level of the sea; the Peak of Teneriffe<lb break="yes"/>12,236 feet.</note> Cotopaxi is also the<lb break="yes"/>most dreadful volcano of the kingdom of Quito, and its explo-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="101" facs="#f0002"/>sions the most frequent and disastrous. The mass of scoria,<lb break="yes"/>and the huge pieces of rock thrown out of this volcano, which<lb break="yes"/>are spread over the neighboring vallies, covering a surface of<lb break="yes"/>several square leagues, would form, were they heaped together,<lb break="yes"/>a collossial mountain. In 1738, the flames of Cotopaxi rose nine<lb break="yes"/>hundred metres above the brink of the crater. In 1744, the<lb break="yes"/>roarings of the volcano were heard as far Henda, a town on<lb break="yes"/>the borders of the Magdalena, and at a distance of two hundred<lb break="yes"/>common leagues. On the 4th of April, 1768, the quantity of<lb break="yes"/>ashes ejected by the mouth of Cotopaxi was so great, that in<lb break="yes"/>the towns of Hambato and Tacunga day broke only at three<lb break="yes"/>in the afternoon, and the inhabitants were obliged to use lan-<lb break="no"/>terns in walking the streets. The explosion which took place<lb break="yes"/>in the month of January, 1803, was preceded by a most dread-<lb break="no"/>ful phenomenon, the sudden melting of the snows that covered<lb break="yes"/>the mountain. For twenty years before, no smoke or vapour,<lb break="yes"/>that could be perceived, had issued from the crater; and in a<lb break="yes" />single night the subterraneous fire became so active, that at<lb break="yes"/>sun rise the external walls of the cone, heated, no doubt, to a<lb break="yes"/>very considerable temperature, appeared naked, and of a dark<lb break="yes"/>colour, which is peculiar to vitrified scor&#x00E6;. At the port of<lb break="yes"/>Guayaquil, fifty-two leagues distant in a straight line from the<lb break="yes"/>crater, we heard, day and night, the constant noises of the vol-<lb break="no"/>cano, like continual discharges of a battery: we distinguished<lb break="yes"/>these tremendous sounds even on the Pacific ocean, to the<lb break="yes"/>south west of the island of Puna.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>“Cotopaxi is situated to the south east of the city of Quito,<lb break="yes" />at the distance of twelve leagues, between the mountain of<lb break="yes" />Ruminnavi, the summit of which, rugged with small separate<lb break="yes" />rocks, extends itself like a wall of enormous height; and Que-<lb break="no"/>lendanna, which enters the boundary of the eternal snows.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It is in this part of the Andes, that a longitudinal valley sepa-<lb break="no"/>rates the Cordilleras into two parallel chains. The bottom of<lb break="yes"/>the valley is three thousand metres above the level of the<lb break="yes"/>ocean, so that Chimborazo and Cotopaxi, seen from the ele-<lb break="no"/>vated plains of Lican and Mulalo, appear no higher than the<lb break="yes"/>Col de Geant and du Cramont, measured by Saussure. As<lb break="yes"/>there is reason to suppose, that the proximity of the ocean con-<lb break="no"/>tributes to feed the volcanic fire, the geologist is astonished<lb break="yes"/>to find that the most active volcanoes in the kingdom of Quito,<lb break="yes"/>Cotopaxia, Tungurahua, and Sangay, belong to the eastern<lb break="yes"/>chain of the Andes, and consequently that which is the farthest<lb break="yes"/>from the coasts. The whole of the peaks, except Ruca-Pi-<lb break="no"/>chincha, which crown the western Cordilleras, seem to be vol-<lb break="no"/>canoes extinguished for a long series of ages: but this mountain,<lb break="yes"/>which is 2 deg. 2 min. distant from the nearest coasts, those of<lb break="yes"/>Esmeralda, and the bay of San Mateo, spouts out at different<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="102" facs="#f0003"/> periods cataracts of fire, and spreads destruction over the sur-<lb break="no"/>rounding plains.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>“The form of Cotopaxi is the most beautiful and regular of<lb break="yes" />the collossial summits of the high Andes. It is a perfect cone,<lb break="yes"/>which covered with an enormous layer of snow, shines with<lb break="yes"/>dazzling splendor at the setting of the sun, and detaches itself<lb break="yes"/>in the most picturesque manner from the azure vault of heaven.<lb break="yes"/>This covering of snow conceals from the eye of the observer,<lb break="yes"/>even the smallest inequalities of the soil; no point of rock, no<lb break="yes"/>stony mass, penetrates the coating of ice, or breaks the regu-<lb break="no"/>larity of the figure of the cone. The summit of Cotopaxi re-<lb break="no"/>sembles the sugar loaf, (Pan de azucar) which terminates the<lb break="yes"/>peak of Teyde; but the height of the cone is six times the<lb break="yes"/>height of that great volcano in the island of Teneriffe.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>“It is only at the brink of the crater we see ledges of rocks,<lb break="yes" />that are never covered with snow, and that look at a distance<lb break="yes"/>like stripes of the darkest hue; the greatest steepness of this<lb break="yes"/>part of the cone, and the crevices from which issue currents of<lb break="yes"/>heated air, are probably the causes of this phenomenon. The<lb break="yes"/>crater, like that of the Peak of Teneriffe, is surrounded by a<lb break="yes"/>small circular wall, which, examined with a good telescope,<lb break="yes"/>looks like a parapet. This is more distinctly seen on the<lb break="yes"/>southern declivity, when the beholder is placed either on the<lb break="yes"/>Lion mountain, (Puona Urcu) or on the banks of the small lake<lb break="yes"/>of Yuracoche.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>“The conic point of the Peak of Teneriffe is of easy access,<lb break="yes" />rising from the midst of a plain, covered with pumice stones,<lb break="yes"/>and on which a few tufts of spartium supranubium vegetate.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>In scaling the volcano of Cotopaxi, it is extremely difficult to<lb break="yes"/>attain the inferior boundary of the perpetual snows, as we ex-<lb break="no"/>perienced in an excursion we made in the month of May, in<lb break="yes"/>the year 1802. The cone is surrounded by deep crevices,<lb break="yes"/>which at the moment of the eruptions bear down scor&#x00E6;, pumice<lb break="yes"/>stone, water and blocks of ice, to Rio Napo, and Rio de les<lb break="yes"/>Alaques. After a nearer examination of the summit of Coto-<lb break="no"/>paxi, we may venture to assert, that it would be impossible to<lb break="yes"/>reach the brink of the crater. <hi rendition="#g">**************</hi> I<lb break="yes" />sketched Cotopaxi, and the head of the Inca, to the west of the<lb break="yes"/>volcano, at the farm Sienega, <hi rendition="#g" >************</hi>. The co-<lb break="no"/>lossial volcano, the pyramidal peaks of Ilinisa, and the Nevado<lb break="yes"/>de Quelendana, open here at once on the spectator, and in<lb break="yes"/>dreadful proximity. This is one of the most majestic and awful<lb break="yes"/>views I ever beheld in either hemisphere.”</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#et">Researches in South America, by Alexander de Humboldt.</hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 