<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="40" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>ANCIENT MEXICAN CITIES AND PYRAMIDS.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">(Humboldt’s Views of the Cordilleras.)</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>“<hi rendition="#in">A</hi>MONG those swarms of nations, which, from the<lb break="yes"/>seventh to the twelfth century of the Christian<lb break="yes" />era, successively inhabited the country of Mexico, five<lb break="yes"/>are enumerated, the Toltecks, the Cicimecks, the Acol-<lb break="no"/>huans, the Tlascaltecks, and the Axtecks, who, not-<lb break="no"/>withstanding their political divisions, spoke the same<lb break="yes"/>language, followed the same worship, and built pyra-<lb break="no"/>midal edifices, which they regarded as <hi rendition="#i">teocallis,</hi> that is<lb break="yes"/>to say, the house of their gods.&#x2014;These edifices were all<lb break="yes"/>of the same form, though of very different dimensions;<lb break="yes"/>they were pyramids, with several terraces, and the sides<lb break="yes"/>of which stood exactly in the direction of the meridian,<lb break="yes"/>and the parallel of the place. Each house of a Mexican<lb break="yes"/>divinity, like the ancient temple of Baal Berith, burnt<lb break="yes"/>by Abimelech, was a strong place. A great staircase<lb break="yes"/>led to the top of the truncated pyramid, and on the<lb break="yes"/>summit of the platform were one or two chapels, built<lb break="yes"/>like towers, which contained the colossal idols of the<lb break="yes"/>divinity, to whom the Teocalli was dedicated. The in-<lb break="no"/>side of the edifice was the burial place of the kings and<lb break="yes"/>principal personages of Mexico. It is impossible to read<lb break="yes"/>the descriptions, which Herodotus and Diodorus Siculus<lb break="yes"/>have left us of the temple of Jupiter Belus, without be-<lb break="no"/>ing struck with the resemblance of that Babylonian mo-<lb break="no"/>nument to the Teocallis of Anahuac.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the period when the Mexicans, or Aztecks, one<lb break="yes"/>of the seven tribes of the Anahuatlacks, (inhabitants of<lb break="yes"/>the banks of rivers,) took possession, in the year 1190,<lb break="yes"/>of the equinoctial region of New Spain, they already found<lb break="yes"/>the pyramidal monuments of Teotihuacan, of Cholula,<lb break="yes"/>or Cholollan, and of Papantla. They attributed these<lb break="yes"/>great edifices to the Toltecks, a powerful and civilized<lb break="yes"/>nation, who inhabited Mexico five hundred years earlier,<lb break="yes"/>who made use of hieroglyphical characters, who com-<lb break="no"/>puted the year more precisely, and had a more exact<lb break="yes"/>chronology than the greater part of the people of the old<lb break="yes"/>continent. We ought not to be astonished, that no his-<lb break="no"/>tory of any American nation should precede the seventh<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="41" facs="#f0002"/>century; and that the annals of the Toltecks should be<lb break="yes"/>as uncertain as those of the Pelasgi and the Ausonians.<lb break="yes"/>The learned Mr. Schloezer has clearly proved, that the<lb break="yes"/>history of the north of Europe reaches no higher than<lb break="yes"/>the tenth century, an epocha when Mexico was in a<lb break="yes"/>more advanced state of civilization than Denmark,<lb break="yes"/>Sweden and Russia.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Teocalli of Mexico was dedicated to Tezcatlipo-<lb break="no"/>lica, the first of the Azteck divinities after Teotl, who is<lb break="yes"/>the supreme and visible Being; and to Huitzilopochtli,<lb break="yes"/>the God of war. It was built by the Aztecks, on the<lb break="yes"/>model of the pyramids of Teotihuacan, six years only<lb break="yes"/>before the discovery of America by Christopher Colum-<lb break="no"/>bus. This truncated pyramid, called by Cortez the<lb break="yes"/>principal temple, was ninety-seven metres<note place="foot" n="*">A French revolutionary measure of 3 feet, 11½<lb break="yes"/>inches.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Ed.</hi>
                    </note> in breadth<lb break="yes"/>at its basis, and nearly fifty-four metres in height.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The group of the pyramids of Teotihuacan is in the<lb break="yes"/>valley of Mexico, eight leagues north east from the ca-<lb break="no"/>pital, in a plain that bears the name of Micoatl, or the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Path of the Death.</hi> There are two large pyramids de-<lb break="no"/>dicated to the Sun (Tonatiuh,) and to the Moon (Meztli);<lb break="yes"/>and these are surrounded by several hundreds of small<lb break="yes"/>pyramids, which form streets in exact lines from north<lb break="yes"/>to south, and from east to west. Of these two great<lb break="yes"/>Teocallis, one is fifty-five, the other is forty-four metres<lb break="yes"/>in perpendicular height. The basis of the first is two<lb break="yes"/>hundred and eighty metres in length; whence it results,<lb break="yes"/>that the Tonatiuh Yztaqual, according to Mr. Oteyza’s<lb break="yes"/>measurement, made in 1803, is higher than the Myce-<lb break="no"/>rinus, or third of the three great pyramids of Geeza in<lb break="yes"/>Egypt, and the length of its base nearly equal to that of<lb break="yes"/>the Cephren. The small pyramids, which surround the<lb break="yes"/>great houses of the Sun and the Moon, are scarcely nine<lb break="yes"/>or ten metres high; and served, according to the tradi-<lb break="no"/>tion of the natives, as burial places for the chiefs of the<lb break="yes"/>tribes. Around the Cheops and the Mycerinus in Egypt,<lb break="yes"/>there are eight small pyramids, placed with symmetry,<lb break="yes"/>and parallel to the fronts of the greater. The two Te-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="42" facs="#f0003"/> ocallis of Teotihuacan had four principal stories, each of<lb break="yes"/>which was subdivided into steps, the edges of which are<lb break="yes"/>still to be distinguished. The nucleus is composed of<lb break="yes"/>clay mixed with small stones, and it is encased by a thick<lb break="yes"/>wall of tezontli, or porous amygdaloid.<note place="foot" n="*" >Mandelstein of the German mineralogists.</note> This construc-<lb break="no"/>tion recalls to mind that of one of the Egyptian pyramids<lb break="yes"/>of Sakharah, which has six stories; and which, accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to Pocock, is a mass of pebbles and yellow mortar,<lb break="yes"/>covered on the outside with rough stones. On the top<lb break="yes"/>of the great Mexican Teocallis were two colossal statues<lb break="yes"/>of the Sun and Moon: they were of stone, and covered<lb break="yes"/>with plates of gold, of which they were stripped by the<lb break="yes"/>soldiers of Cortez.&#x2014;When bishop Zumaraga, a Francis-<lb break="no"/>can monk, undertook the destruction of whatever related<lb break="yes"/>to the worship, the history, and the Antiquities of the<lb break="yes"/>natives of America, he ordered also the demolition of<lb break="yes"/>the idols of the plain of Micoatl. We still discover the<lb break="yes"/>remains of a staircase built with large hewn stone, which<lb break="yes"/>formerly led to the platform of the Teocalli.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On the east of the group of the pyramids of Teoti-<lb break="no"/>huacan, on descending the Cordillera towards the Gulph<lb break="yes"/>of Mexico, in a thick forest, called Tajin, rises the<lb break="yes"/>pyramid of Papantla. This monument was by chance<lb break="yes"/>discovered scarcely thirty years ago, by some Spanish<lb break="yes"/>hunters; for the Indians carefully conceal from the whites<lb break="yes"/>whatever was an object of ancient veneration. The form<lb break="yes"/>of this Teocalli, which had six, perhaps seven stories,<lb break="yes"/>is more tapering than that of any other monument of<lb break="yes"/>this kind; it is nearly eighteen metres in height, while<lb break="yes"/>the breadth of its basis is only twenty-five. This small<lb break="yes"/>edifice is built entirely with hewn stones, of an extraor-<lb break="no"/>dinary size, and very beautifully and regularly shaped.<lb break="yes"/>Three staircases lead to the top. The covering of its<lb break="yes"/>steps is decorated with hieroglyphical sculpture, and<lb break="yes"/>small niches, which are arranged with great symmetry.<lb break="yes"/>The number of these niches seems to allude to the three<lb break="yes"/>hundred and eighteen simple and compound signs of the<lb break="yes"/>days of the Cempohualilhuitl, or civil calendar of the<lb break="yes"/>Toltecks.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="43" facs="#f0004"/>
                <p>The greatest, most ancient, and most celebrated of<lb break="yes"/>the whole of the pyramidal monuments of Anahuac is<lb break="yes"/>the Teocalli of Cholula. It is called in the present day<lb break="yes"/>the Mountain made by the hand of man <hi rendition="#i">(monte hecho a<lb break="yes"/>manos.)</hi> At a distance it has the aspect of a natural hill<lb break="yes"/>covered with vegetation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A vast plain, the Puebla, is separated from the<lb break="yes"/>valley of Mexico by the chain of volcanic mountains,<lb break="yes"/>which extend from Popocatepetl, toward Rio Frio, and<lb break="yes"/>the peak of Telapon. This plain, fertile though desti-<lb break="no"/>tute of trees, is rich in memorials, interesting to Mexi-<lb break="no"/>can history. In it flourished the capitals of three repub-<lb break="no"/>lics of Tlascalla, Huexocingo and Cholula, which, not-<lb break="no"/>withstanding their continual dissensions, resisted with<lb break="yes"/>no less firmness the despotism and usurping spirit of the<lb break="yes"/>Azteck kings.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The small city of Cholula, which Cortez, in his<lb break="yes"/>Letters to Charles V. compares with the most populous<lb break="yes"/>cities of Spain, contains at present scarcely sixteen<lb break="yes"/>thousand inhabitants. The pyramid is to the east of the<lb break="yes"/>city, on the road which leads from Cholula to Puebla.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Teocalli of Cholula has four stories, all of equal<lb break="yes"/>height. It appears to have been constructed exactly in<lb break="yes"/>the direction of the four cardinal points; but as the<lb break="yes"/>edges of the stories are not very distinct, it is difficult<lb break="yes"/>to ascertain their primitive direction. This pyramidical<lb break="yes"/>monument has a broader basis than that of any other<lb break="yes"/>edifice of the same kind in the old continent. I mea-<lb break="no"/>sured it carefully, and ascertained, that its perpendicular<lb break="yes"/>height is only fifty metres, but that each side of its basis<lb break="yes"/>is four hundred and thirty-nine metres in length. Tor-<lb break="no"/>quemada computes its height at seventy-seven metres;<lb break="yes"/>Betancourt, at sixty-five; and Clavigero, at sixty-one.<lb break="yes"/>Bernal Diaz del Castillo, a common soldier in the army<lb break="yes"/>of Cortez, amused himself by counting the steps of the<lb break="yes"/>staircase, which led to the platform of the Teocallis;<lb break="yes"/>he found one hundred and fourteen in the great temple<lb break="yes"/>of Tenochtitlan, one hundred and seventeen in that of<lb break="yes"/>Tezcuco, and one hundred and twenty in that of Cholula.<lb break="yes"/>The basis of the pyramid of Cholula is twice as broad as<lb break="yes"/>that of Cheops; but its height is very little more than<lb break="yes"/>that of the pyramid of Mycerinus. An adit dug<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="44" facs="#f0005"/> through the Teocalli of Cholula, to examine its exter-<lb break="no"/>nal structure, would be an interesting operation; and it<lb break="yes"/>is singular, that the desire of discovering hidden trea-<lb break="no"/>sure has not prompted the undertaking.&#x2014;During my<lb break="yes"/>travels in Peru, in visiting the vast ruins of the city of<lb break="yes"/>Chimu, near Mansiche, I went into the interior of the<lb break="yes"/>famous Huaca de Toledo, the tomb of a Peruvian prince,<lb break="yes"/>in which Garci Gutierez de Toledo <choice>
                        <sic>discovered.</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">discovered</corr>
                    </choice> on digg-<lb break="no"/>ing a gallery, in 1576, massive gold amounting in value<lb break="yes"/>to more than five millions of francs, as is proved by the<lb break="yes"/>book of accounts, preserved in the mayor’s office at<lb break="yes"/>Truxillo.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The size of the platform of the pyramid of Cholula,<lb break="yes"/>on which I made a great number of astronomical obser-<lb break="no"/>vations, is four thousand two hundred square metres.<lb break="yes"/>From it the eye ranges over a magnificent prospect;<lb break="yes"/>Popocatepetl, Iztaceihuatl, the peak of Orizaba, and the<lb break="yes"/>Sierra de Tlascalla, famous for the tempests which gather<lb break="yes"/>around its summit. We view at the same time three<lb break="yes"/>mountains higher than Mount Blanc, two of which are<lb break="yes"/>still burning volcanoes. A small chapel, surrounded<lb break="yes"/>with cypress, and dedicated to the Virgin de los Reme-<lb break="no"/>dios, has succeeded to the temple of the god of the air,<lb break="yes"/>or the Mexican Indra. An ecclesiastic of the Indian<lb break="yes"/>race celebrates mass every day on the top of this antique<lb break="yes"/>monument.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the time of Cortez, Cholula was considered as a<lb break="yes"/>holy city. No where existed a greater number of Teo-<lb break="no"/>callis, of priests, and religious orders <hi rendition="#i">(tlamacazque;)</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>no spot displayed greater magnificence in the celebration<lb break="yes"/>of public worship, or more austerity in its penances and<lb break="yes"/>fasts. Since the introduction of Christianity among the<lb break="yes"/>Indians, the symbols of a new worship have not entirely<lb break="yes"/>effaced the remembrance of the old. The people assem-<lb break="no"/>ble in crowds, from distant quarters, at the summit of<lb break="yes"/>the pyramid, to celebrate the festival of the Virgins. A<lb break="yes"/>mysterious dread, a religious awe, fills the soul of the<lb break="yes"/>Indian at the sight of this immense pile of bricks,<lb break="yes"/>covered with shrubs and perpetual verdure.”</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 