<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-06-neu</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>TRAVELS IN SOUTH AMERICA.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following interesting passages are<lb break="yes"/>taken from the recent publications of the<lb break="yes"/>celebrated Humboldt; the first, from his<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Researches in South America;</hi> the second<lb break="yes" />and third, from his <hi rendition="#i">Travels</hi> in that country.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#k">
                            <hi rendition="#g">man.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;There is no proof, that the existence of man<lb break="yes"/>is much more recent in America than in the<lb break="yes"/>other continent. Within the tropics, the strength<lb break="yes"/>of vegetation, the breadth of rivers, and par-<lb break="no"/>tial inundations have presented powerful ob-<lb break="no"/>stacles to the migration of nations. The ex-<lb break="no" />tensive countries of the north of Asia are as<lb break="yes"/>thinly peopled as the savannahs of New Mexi-<lb break="no"/>co and Paraguay; nor is it necessary to suppose,<lb break="yes"/>that the countries first peopled are those, which<lb break="yes"/>offer the greatest mass of inhabitants. The<lb break="yes"/>problem of the first population of America, is<lb break="yes" />no more the province of history, than the ques-<lb break="no"/>tions on the origin of plants and animals, and on<lb break="yes"/>the distribution of organic germs, are that of<lb break="yes"/>natural science. History, in carrying us back<lb break="yes"/>to the earliest epochs, instructs us that almost<lb break="yes"/>every part of the globe is occupied by men who<lb break="yes" />think themselves aborigines, because they are<lb break="yes"/>ignorant of their origin. Among a multitude of<lb break="yes"/>nations, who have succeeded, or have been in-<lb break="no"/>corporated with each other, it is impossible to<lb break="yes"/>discover with precision, the first basis of popu-<lb break="no"/>lation, that primitive stratum beyond which the<lb break="yes" />region of cosmogonical tradition begins.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The nations of America, except those which<lb break="yes"/>border on the polar circle, form a single race,<lb break="yes"/>characterized by the formation of the skull, the<lb break="yes"/>colour of the skin, the extreme thinness of the<lb break="yes"/>beard, and straight and glossy hair. The<lb break="yes"/>American race bears a very striking resemblance<lb break="yes"/>to that of the Mongul nations, which include<lb break="yes"/>the descendants of the Hiong-Nu, known here-<lb break="no"/>tofore by the name of Huns, the Kalkas, the<lb break="yes" />Kalmucks, and the Burats. It has been ascer-<lb break="no"/>tained, by late observations, that not only the<lb break="yes"/>inhabitants of Unalashka, but several tribes of<lb break="yes"/>South America, indicate, by the osteological<lb break="yes"/>characters of the head, a passage from the<lb break="yes"/>American to the Mongul race. When we shall<lb break="yes"/>have more completely studied the brown men<lb break="yes"/>of Africa, and that swarm of nations, who in-<lb break="no"/>habit the interior and north-east of Asia, and<lb break="yes"/>who are vaguely described by systematic tra-<lb break="no"/>vellers under the name of Tartars and Tsch-<lb break="no" />oudes, the Caucasian, Mongul, American,<lb break="yes"/>Malay, and Negro races, will appear less insu-<lb break="no"/>lated, and we shall acknowledge, in this great<lb break="yes"/>family of the human race, one single organic<lb break="yes"/>type, modified by circumstances which perhaps<lb break="yes" />will ever remain unknown.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Though the nations of the new continent<lb break="yes"/>are connected by intimate ties, they exhibit, in<lb break="yes"/>the mobility of their features, in their com-<lb break="no"/>plexions, tanned in a greater or less degree, and<lb break="yes"/>in their stature, a difference as remarkable as<lb break="yes"/>the Arabians, the Persians, and Sclavonians,<lb break="yes" />who are all of the Caucasian race. The hordes<lb break="yes"/>who wander along the burning plains of the<lb break="yes"/>equinoctial regions have, however, no darker<lb break="yes"/>skins than the mountaineers of the temperate<lb break="yes"/>zone; whether it be that in the human race,<lb break="yes"/>and in the greater part of animals, there is a<lb break="yes"/>certain period of organic life, beyond which the<lb break="yes"/>influence of climate and food have no effect, or<lb break="yes"/>that the deviation from the primitive type be-<lb break="no"/>comes apparent only after a long series of ages.<lb break="yes"/>Besides, every thing concurs to prove, that the<lb break="yes" />Americans, as well as the people of the Mon-<lb break="no"/>gul race, have less flexibility of organization<lb break="yes"/>than the other nations of Asia and Europe.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb facs="#f0002"/>
                <cb/>
            </div>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">southern constellation</hi>.
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;From the time we entered the torrid zone,<lb break="yes"/>we were never wearied with admiring, every<lb break="yes"/>night, the beauty of the southern sky, which, as<lb break="yes"/>we advanced towards the south, opened new<lb break="yes"/>constellations to our view. We feel an inde-<lb break="no" />scribable sensation, when, on approaching the<lb break="yes"/>equator, and particularly on passing from one<lb break="yes"/>hemisphere to the other, we see those stars<lb break="yes"/>which we have contemplated from our infancy,<lb break="yes"/>progressively sink, and finally disappear. Noth-<lb break="no" />ing awakens in the traveller a livelier remem-<lb break="no"/>brance of the immense distance by which he is<lb break="yes"/>separated from his country, than the aspect of<lb break="yes"/>an unknown firmament. The grouping of the<lb break="yes"/>stars of the first magnitude, some scattered<lb break="yes" />nebul&#x00E6;, rivalling in splendor the milky way, and<lb break="yes"/>tracks of space remarkable for their extreme<lb break="yes"/>blackness, give a particular physiognomy to the<lb break="yes"/>southern sky. This sight fills with admiration<lb break="yes"/>even those, who, uninstructed in the branches of<lb break="yes"/>accurate science, feel the same emotion of de-<lb break="no"/>light in the contemplation of the heavenly vault,<lb break="yes" />as in the view of the beautiful landscape, or a<lb break="yes"/>majestic site. A traveller has no need of being<lb break="yes"/>a botanist, to recognize the torrid zone on the<lb break="yes"/>mere aspect of its vegetation; and without hav-<lb break="no"/>ing acquired any notions of astronomy, without<lb break="yes"/>any acquaintance with the celestial charts of<lb break="yes" />Flamstead and de la Caille, he feels he is not in<lb break="yes"/>Europe, when he sees the immense constellation<lb break="yes"/>of the Ship, or the phosphorescent clouds of<lb break="yes"/>Magellan, arise on the horizon. The heaven,<lb break="yes"/>and the earth, every thing in the equinoctial re-<lb break="no"/>gions, assumes an exotic character.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;We saw distinctly, for the first time, the<lb break="yes"/>Cross of the South only in the night of the 4th<lb break="yes"/>and 5th of July, in the sixteenth degree of lati-<lb break="no"/>tude; it was strongly inclined, and appeared<lb break="yes"/>from time to time between the clouds, the centre<lb break="yes"/>of which, furrowed by uncondensed lightnings,<lb break="yes" />reflected a silver light.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The pleasure we felt on discovering the<lb break="yes"/>Southern Cross, was warmly shared by such of<lb break="yes"/>the crew as had lived in the colonies. In the<lb break="yes"/>solitude of the seas, we hail a star as a friend,<lb break="yes"/>from whom we have long been separated. &#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Among the Portuguese and the Spaniards pecu-<lb break="no" />liar motives seem to increase this feeling; a re-<lb break="no"/>ligious sentiment attaches them to a constella-<lb break="no"/>tion, the form of which recalls the sign of the<lb break="yes"/>faith planted by their ancestors in the deserts of<lb break="yes"/>the new world.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The two great stars which mark the summit<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> and the foot of the Cross having nearly the<lb break="yes"/>same right ascension, it follows hence, that the<lb break="yes"/>constellation is almost perpendicular at the mo-<lb break="no"/>ment when it passes the meridian. This cir-<lb break="no"/>cumstance is known to every nation that lives<lb break="yes"/>beyond the tropics, or in the southern hemis-<lb break="no" />phere. It has been observed at what hour of<lb break="yes"/>the night, in different seasons, the Cross of the<lb break="yes"/>South is erect, or inclined. It is a time-piece<lb break="yes"/>that advances very regularly near four minutes<lb break="yes"/>a-day, and no other group of stars exhibits to<lb break="yes"/>the naked eye, an observation of time so easily<lb break="yes" />made. How often have we heard our guides<lb break="yes"/>exclaim, in the Savannas of Venezuela, or in the<lb break="yes"/>desert extending from Lima to Truxillo, &#x201C;Mid-<lb break="no"/>night is past, the Cross begins to bend!&#x201D; How<lb break="yes"/>often those words reminded us of that affecting<lb break="yes"/>scene, where Paul and Virginia, seated near the<lb break="yes"/>source of the river of Lataniers, conversed to-<lb break="no" />gether for the last time, and where the old man,<lb break="yes"/>at the sight of the Southern Cross, warns them<lb break="yes"/>that it is time to separate.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <pb facs="#f0003"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">canary birds</hi>.
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;As we approached the town of Orotava, we<lb break="yes"/>met great flocks of canaries. These birds, well<lb break="yes"/>known in Europe, were in general uniformly<lb break="yes"/>green; some had a yellow tint on their backs;<lb break="yes"/>their note was the same as that of the tame ca-<lb break="no" />nary. It is nevertheless remarked, that those<lb break="yes"/>which have been taken in the isle of the Great<lb break="yes"/>Canary, and in the islet of Monte Clara, near<lb break="yes"/>Lanzerota, have a stronger, and at the same<lb break="yes"/>time the most harmonious song. Under every<lb break="yes" />zone, among birds of the same species, each<lb break="yes"/>flock has its peculiar note. The yellow cana-<lb break="no"/>ries are a variety which has taken birth in<lb break="yes"/>Europe; and those we saw in cages at Orotava<lb break="yes"/>and Santa Cruz had been bought at Cadiz, and<lb break="yes"/>in other ports of Spain. But of all the birds of<lb break="yes"/>the Canary Islands, that which has the most<lb break="yes"/>heart-soothing song is unknown in Europe;<lb break="yes"/>this is the capirote, which no effort has been<lb break="yes"/>able to tame, so sacred to his soul is liberty. I<lb break="yes"/>have stood in admiration at his soft and melo-<lb break="no" />dious warbling, in a garden at Orotava; but I<lb break="yes"/>have never seen him sufficiently near, to know<lb break="yes"/>to what family he belongs.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 