<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="259" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>CARGUEROES, OR MAN-CARRIERS OF QUINDIU.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <cb/><hi rendition="#k">The</hi> mountain of Quindiu is considered as the<lb break="yes"/>most difficult passage in the Cordilleras of the An-<lb break="no"/>des. It is a thick uninhabited forest, which, in the<lb break="yes"/>finest season, cannot be traversed in less than ten or<lb break="yes"/>twelve days. Not even a hut is to be seen, nor can<lb break="yes"/>any means of subsistence be found.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Travellers, at all times of the year, furnish them-<lb break="no"/>selves with a month’s provision, since it often hap-<lb break="no"/>pens, that by the melting of the snows, and the sud-<lb break="no"/>den swell of the torrents, they find themselves so<lb break="yes"/>circumstanced, that they can descend neither on<lb break="yes"/>the side of Carthago, nor on that of Ibague. The<lb break="yes" />highest point of the road, the Garito del Paramo, is<lb break="yes"/>three thousand five hundred and five metres (eleven<lb break="yes"/>thousand, and five hundred feet) above the level of<lb break="yes"/>the sea. As the foot of the mountain, towards the<lb break="yes"/>banks of the Cauca, is only nine hundred and sixty<lb break="yes"/>metres, (three thousand, one hundred and fifty feet<lb break="yes"/>high,) the climate there is in general mild and tem-<lb break="no"/>perate. The pathway, which forms the passage of<lb break="yes" />the Cordilleras, is only three or four decimetres in<lb break="yes"/>breadth, (from a foot, to a foot and a half;) and has<lb break="yes"/>the appearance, in several places, of a gallery dug,<lb break="yes"/>and left open to the sky. In this part of the Andes,<lb break="yes"/>as almost in every other, the rock is covered with a<lb break="yes"/>thick stratum of clay. The streamlets, which flow<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="260" facs="#f0002"/> <cb/>down the mountains, have hollowed out gullies, six<lb break="yes"/>or seven metres deep, (from twenty, to twenty-three<lb break="yes"/>feet.) Along these crevices, which are full of mud,<lb break="yes"/>the traveller is forced to grope his passage, the<lb break="yes"/>darkness of which is increased by the thick vegeta-<lb break="no"/>tion that covers the opening above. The oxen,<lb break="yes" />which are the beasts of burden commonly made<lb break="yes"/>use of in this country, can scarcely force their way<lb break="yes"/>through these galleries, some of which are two<lb break="yes"/>thousand metres (two thousand, two hundred yards)<lb break="yes"/>in length; and if, perchance, the traveller meets<lb break="yes"/>them in one of these passages, he finds no means<lb break="yes" />of avoiding them but by turning back, and climbing<lb break="yes"/>the earthen wall which borders the crevice, and<lb break="yes"/>keeping himself suspended, by laying hold of the<lb break="yes"/>roots which penetrate to this depth from the surface<lb break="yes"/>of the ground.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We traversed the mountain of Quindiu, in the<lb break="yes"/>month of October, 1801, on foot, followed by twelve<lb break="yes"/>oxen, which carried our collections and instruments,<lb break="yes"/>midst a deluge of rain, to which we were exposed,<lb break="yes"/>during the last three or four days, in our descent on<lb break="yes"/>the western side of the Cordilleras. The road<lb break="yes"/>passes through a country full of bogs, and covered<lb break="yes"/>with bamboos. Our shoes were so torn by the<lb break="yes" />prickles, which shoot out from the roots of these<lb break="yes"/>gigantick gramina, that we were forced, like all other<lb break="yes"/>travellers who dislike being carried on men’s backs,<lb break="yes"/>to go barefooted. This circumstance, the continual<lb break="yes"/>humidity, the length of the passage, the muscular<lb break="yes"/>force required to tread in a thick and muddy clay,<lb break="yes"/>the necessity of fording deep torrents of icy water,<lb break="yes"/>render this journey extremely fatiguing; but how-<lb break="no"/>ever painful, it is accompanied, by none of those<lb break="yes" />dangers with which the credulity of the people alarm<lb break="yes" />travellers. The road is narrow, but the places<lb break="yes"/>where it skirts precipices, are very rare. As the<lb break="yes"/>oxen are accustomed to put their feet in the same<lb break="yes"/>tracks, they form small furrows, across the road,<lb break="yes"/>separated from each other, by narrow ridges of earth.<lb break="yes"/>In very rainy seasons, these ridges are covered with<lb break="yes"/>water, which renders the traveller’s step doubly un-<lb break="no"/>certain, since he knows not whether he places his<lb break="yes" />foot on the ridge, or in the furrow. As few persons,<lb break="yes"/>in easy circumstances, travel on foot in these climates,<lb break="yes"/>through roads so difficult, during fifteen or twenty<lb break="yes"/>days together, they are carried by men in a chair tied<lb break="yes"/>to their back; for, in the present state of the passage<lb break="yes"/>of Quindiu, it would be impossible to go on mules.<lb break="yes"/>They talk in this country, of going on a man’s<lb break="yes"/>back, (<hi rendition="#i">andar en carguero,</hi>) as we mention going on<lb break="yes"/>horseback; no humiliating idea is annexed to the<lb break="yes"/>trade of the cargueroes; and the men who follow<lb break="yes"/>this occupation, are not Indians, but Mulattoes, and<lb break="yes"/>sometimes even whites. It is often curious to hear<lb break="yes"/>these men, with scarcely any covering, and following<lb break="yes"/>a profession which we should consider so disgrace-<lb break="no"/>ful, quarrelling in the midst of the forest, because<lb break="yes"/>one has refused the other, who pretends to have a<lb break="yes"/>whiter skin, the pompous title of <hi rendition="#i">don,</hi> or of <hi rendition="#i">su merced.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>The usual load of a carguero, is six or seven arro-<lb break="no"/>bas, (about one hundred and eighty pounds;) those<lb break="yes" />who are very strong, carry as much as nine arrobas,<lb break="yes"/>(about two hundred and fifty pounds.) When we<lb break="yes"/>reflect on the enormous fatigue to which these miser-<lb break="no"/>able men are exposed, journeying eight or nine hours<lb break="yes"/>a day, over a mountainous country; when we know<lb break="yes"/>that their backs are sometimes as raw as those of<lb break="yes"/><cb/>beasts of burden, and that travellers have often the<lb break="yes"/>cruelty to leave them in the forest, when they are<lb break="yes"/>sick; that they earn by a journey from Ibague to<lb break="yes" />Carthago, only twelve or fourteen piastres, (a sum<lb break="yes"/>equal in amount to as many dollars,) in a space<lb break="yes"/>of fifteen, and sometimes even twenty-five or thirty<lb break="yes"/>days; we are at a loss, to conceive how this employ-<lb break="no"/>ment of a carguero, one of the most painful which<lb break="yes"/>can be undertaken by man, is eagerly embraced by<lb break="yes"/>all the robust young men, who live at the foot of the<lb break="yes"/>mountains. The taste for a wandering and vagabond<lb break="yes"/>life, the idea of a certain independence amidst<lb break="yes" />forests, leads them to prefer this employment to the<lb break="yes"/>sedentary and monotonous labour of cities.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The passage of the mountain of Quindiu is not<lb break="yes"/>the only part of South America, which is traversed<lb break="yes"/>on the backs of men. The whole of the province<lb break="yes"/>of Antioquia is surrounded by mountains so difficult<lb break="yes"/>to pass, that they who dislike intrusting themselves<lb break="yes"/>to the skill of a carrier, and who are not strong<lb break="yes"/>enough to travel on foot from Santa Fé de Antioquia<lb break="yes"/>to Bocca de Nares or Rio Samana, must relinquish<lb break="yes"/>all thoughts of leaving the country. I was acquaint-<lb break="no"/>ed with an inhabitant of this province, so immense-<lb break="no"/>ly bulky, that he had not met with more than two<lb break="yes"/>Mulattoes capable of carrying him; and it would<lb break="yes" />have been impossible for him to return home, if these<lb break="yes"/>two carriers had died, while he was on the banks of<lb break="yes"/>the Magdalena, at Mompox or Honda. The number<lb break="yes"/>of young men who undertake the employment of<lb break="yes"/>beasts of burden at Chaco, Ibague, and Medellin, is<lb break="yes"/>so considerable, that we sometimes met a file of<lb break="yes"/>fifty or sixty. A few years ago, when a project was<lb break="yes"/>formed to make the passage from Nares to Antiquia<lb break="yes"/>passable for mules, the cargueroes presented formal<lb break="yes"/>remonstrances against mending the road, and the<lb break="yes" />government was weak enough to yield to their<lb break="yes"/>clamours. We may here observe, that a class of<lb break="yes"/>men near the mines of Mexico, have no other em-<lb break="no"/>ployment than that of carrying other men on their<lb break="yes"/>backs. In these climates, the indolence of the whites<lb break="yes"/>is so great, that every director of a mine, has one or<lb break="yes"/>two Indians at his service, who are called his horses,<lb break="yes"/>(cavallitoes,) because, they are saddled every morn-<lb break="no"/>ing, and supported by a small cane, and bending for-<lb break="no"/>ward, they carry their master from one part of the<lb break="yes"/>mine to another. Among the cavallitoes or car-<lb break="no" />gueroes, those who have a sure foot and step easy,<lb break="yes"/>are known and recommended to travellers. It is<lb break="yes"/>distressing, to hear the qualities of man spoken of<lb break="yes"/>in terms, by which we are accustomed to denote<lb break="yes"/>the gait of mules and horses. The persons who are<lb break="yes"/>carried in a chair by a carguero, must remain several<lb break="yes"/>hours motionless, and leaning backward; the least<lb break="yes"/>motion is sufficient to throw down the carrier; and<lb break="yes"/>his fall would be so much the more dangerous, as the<lb break="yes"/>carguero, too confident in his skill, chooses the most<lb break="yes"/>rapid declivities, or crosses a torrent on a narrow<lb break="yes"/>and slippery trunk of a tree. These accidents are,<lb break="yes"/>however, rare, and those which happen, must be at-<lb break="no"/>tributed to the imprudence of travellers, who fright-<lb break="no"/>ened at a false step of the carguero, leap down from<lb break="yes"/>their chairs.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When the cargueroes reach Ibague, and prepare<lb break="yes"/>for their journey, they pluck in the neighbouring<lb break="yes"/>mountains, several hundred leaves of the <hi rendition="#i">vijao,</hi> a<lb break="yes"/>plant of the family of the bananas, which forms a<lb break="yes"/>genus approaching the <hi rendition="#i">thalia,</hi> and which must not<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="261" facs="#f0003"/> <cb/>be confounded with the <hi rendition="#i">heliconia bihai.</hi> These<lb break="yes"/>leaves, which are membraneous and silky, like those<lb break="yes"/>of the Musa, are of an oval form, fifty-four centime-<lb break="no"/>tres (twenty inches) in length. Their lower sur-<lb break="no"/>face is a silvery white, and covered with a farinace-<lb break="no"/>ous substance, which falls off in scales. This pe-<lb break="no" />culiar varnish enables them to resist the rain, du-<lb break="no"/>ring a long time. In gathering these leaves, an in-<lb break="no"/>cision is made in the middle rib, which is the con-<lb break="no"/>tinuation of the footstalk, and this serves as a hook,<lb break="yes"/>to suspend them when the moveable roof is formed.<lb break="yes"/>On taking it down, they are spread out, and carefully<lb break="yes"/>rolled up in a cylindrical bundle. It requires about<lb break="yes"/>a hundred weight of leaves (fifty killogrammes) to<lb break="yes"/>cover a hut, large enough to hold six or eight per-<lb break="no"/>sons. When the travellers reach a spot in the midst<lb break="yes"/>of the forest, where the ground is dry, and where<lb break="yes"/>they propose to pass the night, the cargueroes lop a<lb break="yes"/>few branches from the trees, with which they make<lb break="yes"/>a tent. In a few minutes, the slight timber-work is<lb break="yes"/>divided by the stalks of some climbing plant, or<lb break="yes" />threads of the agave, placed in parallel lines, three<lb break="yes"/>or four decimetres from each other. The vijao<lb break="yes"/>leaves meanwhile have been unrolled, and are now<lb break="yes"/>spread over the above work, so as to cover each<lb break="yes"/>other, like tiles of a house. These huts thus<lb break="yes"/>hastily built, are cool and commodious. If, during<lb break="yes"/>the night the traveller feels the rain, he points out<lb break="yes"/>the spot where it enters, and a single leaf is suffi-<lb break="no"/>cient to obviate the inconvenience. We passed<lb break="yes" />several days in the valley of Boquia under one of<lb break="yes"/>these leafy tents, which was perfectly dry amidst<lb break="yes"/>violent and incessant rains. The mountain of<lb break="yes"/>Quindiu, is one of the richest spots in useful and<lb break="yes"/>interesting plants. Here we found the palm-tree,<lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">Ceroxylon andicola,</hi>) the trunk of which is covered<lb break="yes"/>with a vegetable wax, the Passiflora in trees, and<lb break="yes"/>the majestick <hi rendition="#i">Mutisia grandiflora,</hi> with flowers of a<lb break="yes"/>scarlet colour, sixteen centimetres, or six inches<lb break="yes"/>long.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#et">Humboldt.</hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 