<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Description of the volcano at Cotopaxi</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:49</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.3</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-13-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-01.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-07.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-12.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-13-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-21-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-22-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-23-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-24-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-25-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-26-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-27-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-28-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-29-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-30-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-31-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-32-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-33-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-34-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-35-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-36-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-37-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-38-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-39-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-40-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1810-Pittoreske_Ansichten_in-41-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>"Researches in South America, by Alexander de Humboldt."</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Description of the volcano at Cotopaxi</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1821</date>
          <pubPlace>Chillicothe, Ohio</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Weekly Recorder&lt;/i&gt; 7:28/340 (14. März 1821), S. 221–222.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Fußnoten mit Asterisken und Kreuzen; Schmuck: Trennzeichen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="221" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">description of the volcano at<lb/>cotopaxi.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb/>
                <div n="2">
                    <p>&#x201C;Cotopaxi is the loftiest of those volcanos of<lb/>the Andes, which at recent epochs have under-<lb/>gone eruptions. Its absolute height is five thou-<lb/>sand seven hundred and fifty four metres;<note place="foot" n="*">The French metre is equal to 3,987,100 Eng-<lb/>lish inches.</note>
                        <lb/>(about eighteen thousand seven hundred and<lb/>thirty-six English feet.) It is double that of<lb/>Canigou; and consequently eight hundred metres<lb/>higher than Vesuvius would be, were it placed<lb/>on the top of the Peak of Teneriffe.<note place="foot" n="†">Vesuvius is 3,900 feet above the level of the<lb/>sea; the Peak of Teneriffe 12,236 feet.</note> Cotopaxi<lb/>is also the most dreadful volcano of the kingdom<lb/>of Quito, and its explosions the most frequent<lb/>and disastrous. The mass of scoria, and the<lb/>huge pieces of rock thrown out of this volcano,<lb/>which are spread over the neighbouring valleys,<lb/>covering a surface of several square leagues,<lb/>would form, were they heaped together, a collos-<lb/>sal mountain.</p> 
                    <p>In 1738, the flames of Cotopaxi rose nine hun-<lb/>dred metres above the brink of the crater. In<lb/>1744, the roaring of the volcano were heard as<lb/>far as Henda, a town on the boarders of the Mag-<lb/>dalena, and at a distance of two hundred com-<lb/>mon leagues. On the 4th of April, 1768, the<lb/>quantity of ashes ejected by the mouth of Coto-<lb/>paxi was so great, that in the towns of Hambato<lb/>and Tacunga day broke only at three in the af-<lb/>ternoon, and the inhabitants were obliged to use<lb/>lanterns in walking the streets. The explosion<lb/>which took place in the month of January, 1803,<lb/>was preceded by a most dreadful phenomenon,<lb/>the sudden melting of the snows that covered the<lb/>mountain. For twenty years before, no smoke<lb/>or vapour, that could be perceived, had issued<lb/>from the crater; and in a single night the subter-<lb/>raneous fire became so active, that at sun-rise the<lb/>external walls of the cone, heated, no doubt, to<lb/>a very considerable temperature, appeared naked<lb/>and of a dark colour, which is peculiar to vitri-<lb/>fied scor&#x00E6;. At the port of Guayaquil, fifty two<lb/>leagues distant in a straight line from the crater,</p>
                    <pb n="222" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <p>we heard, day and night, the constant noises of<lb/>the volcano, like continual discharges of a batte-<lb/>ry: we distinguished these tremendous sounds<lb/>even on the Pacific ocean, to the south-west of<lb/>the island of Puna.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;Cotopaxi is situated to the south-east of the<lb/>city of Quito, at the distance of twelve leagues,<lb/>between the mountain of Ruminnavi, the summit<lb/>of which, rugged with small separate rocks, ex-<lb/>tends itself like a wall of enormous height; and<lb/>Quelendanna, which enters the boundary of the<lb/>eternal snows.</p>
                    <p>It is in this part of the Andes, that a longitu-<lb/>dinal valley separates the Cordilleras into two<lb/>parallel chains. The bottom of the valley is three<lb/>thousand metres above the level of the ocean, so<lb/>that Chimborazo and Cotopaxi, seen from the<lb/>elevated plains of Lican and Mulalo, appear no<lb/>higher than the Col de Geant and du Cramont,<lb/>measured by Saussure. As there is reason to<lb/>suppose, that the proximity of the ocean contri-<lb/>butes to feed the volcanic fire, the geologist is as-<lb/>tonished to find that the most active volcanoes in<lb/>the kingdom of Quito, Cotopaxia, Tungurahua,<lb/>and Sangay, belong to the eastern chain of the<lb/>Andes, and consequently that which is the far-<lb/>thest from the coasts. The whole of the peaks,<lb/>except Ruca-Pichinca, which crown the western<lb/>Cordilleras, seem to be volcanoes extinguished<lb/>for a long series of ages; but this mountain,<lb/>which is 2 deg. 2 sec. distant from the nearest<lb/>coasts, those of Esmeralda, and the bay of San-<lb/>Mateo, spouts out at different periods cataracts<lb/>of fire, and spreads destruction over the surround-<lb/>ing plains.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;The form of Cotopaxi is the most beautiful<lb/>and regular of the collossal summits of the high<lb/>Andes. It is a perfect cone, which, covered with<lb/>an enormous layer of snow, shines with dazzling<lb/>splendor at the setting of the sun, and detaches<lb/>itself in the most picturesque manner from the<lb/>azure vault of heaven. This covering of snow<lb/>conceals from the eye of the observer, even the<lb/>smallest inequalities of the soil; <choice><sic>on</sic><corr type="editorial">no</corr></choice> point of rock,<lb/>no stony mass, penetrates the coating of ice, or<lb/>breaks the regularity of the figure of the cone.<lb/>The summit of Cotopaxi resembles the sugar-loaf,<lb/>(Pan de azucar) which terminates the peak of<lb/>Teyde; but the height of the cone is six times the<lb/>height of that great volcano in the island of Ten-<lb/>eriffe.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;It is only at the brink of the crater we see<lb/>ledges of rocks, that are never covered with snow,<lb/>and that look at a distance like stripes of the<lb/>darkest hue; the greatest steepness of this part<lb/>of the cone; and the crevices from which issue<lb/>currents of heated air, are probably the causes of<lb/>this phenomenon. The crater, like that of the<lb/>Peak of Teneriffe, is surrounded by a small circu-<lb/>lar wall, which, examined with a good telescope,<lb/>looks like a parapet. This is more distinctly<lb/>seen on the southern declivity, when the behold-<lb/>er is placed either on the Lion mountain, (Puona<lb/>Urcu) or on the banks of the small lake of Yura-<lb/>coche.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;The conic point of the Peak of Teneriffe is of<lb/>easy access, rising from the midst of a plain, co-<lb/>vered with pumice stones, and on which a few<lb/>tufts of spartium supranubium vegetate.&#x2014;In scal-<lb/>ing the volcano of Cotopaxi, it is extremely diffi-<lb/>cult to attain the inferior boundary of the per-<lb/>petual snows, as we experienced in an excursion<lb/>we made in the month of May, in the year 1802.<lb/>The cone is surrounded by deep crevices, which<lb/>at the moment of the eruptions bear down scor&#x00E6;,<lb/>pumice stone, water, and blocks of ice, to Rio<lb/>Napo, and Rio de les Alaques. After a near ex-<lb/>amination of the summit of Cotopaxi, we may<lb/>venture to assert, that it would be impossible to<lb/>reach the brink of the crater. <hi rendition="#g">*********</hi> <lb/>I sketched Cotopaxi, and the head of the Inca, to</p>
                    <cb/>
                    <p>the west of the volcano, at the farm Sienega,<lb/><hi rendition="#g">*****</hi>. The colossal volcano, the pyramidal<lb/>peaks of Illinisa, and the Nevado de Quelendana,<lb/>open here at once on the spectator, and in dread-<lb/>ful proximity. This is one of the most majestic<lb/>and awful views I ever beheld in either hemis-<lb/>phere.&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Researches in South America, by Alex-<lb/>ander de Humboldt.</hi></p>
                   
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>