<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="xx" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>CHIMBORAZO AND COTOPAXI.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Chimborazo is 21,000 feet above the level of the sea, and<lb break="yes"/>9000 above the elevated plains on which they stand; and<lb break="yes"/>Cotopaxi, 19,000. Till the discovery of the Himalayas,<lb break="yes"/>they were considered the highest points on the globe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We distinguish, says Humboldt, three kinds of principal<lb break="yes"/>forms belonging to the high tops of the Andes: the volca-<lb break="no"/>noes which are yet burning; volcanoes, the summits of<lb break="yes"/>which have sunk after a long series of eruptions, exhibiting<lb break="yes"/>ridges bristled with points, needles leaning in different di-<lb break="no"/>rections, and broken rocks falling into ruins; and a third<lb break="yes"/>form of the high tops of the Andes, and the most majestic<lb break="yes"/>of the whole, is that of <hi rendition="#k">Chimborazo,</hi> the summit of which<lb break="yes"/>is circular. The aspect of mountains of granite has little<lb break="yes"/>analogy with that of Chimborazo. Granite summits are<lb break="yes"/>flattened hemispheres, and the trappean porphyry forms<lb break="yes"/>slender cupolas: but Chimborazo appears like a cloud at the<lb break="yes"/>distance of 200 miles. It detaches itself from the neigh-<lb break="no"/>bouring summits, and towers over the whole chain of the<lb break="yes"/>Andes, like that majestic dome produced by the genius of<lb break="yes"/>Michael Angelo, over the antique monuments which sur-<lb break="no"/>round the Roman Capitol.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The bulk of Chimborazo is so enormous, that the part<lb break="yes"/>which the eye embraces at once, near the limit of the<lb break="yes"/>eternal snows, is 8000 yards in breadth. The extreme rarity<lb break="yes"/>of the strata of air, across which we see the tops of the<lb break="yes"/>Andes, contributes, too, greatly to the splendour of the<lb break="yes"/>snow, and the magical effect of its reflection. Under<lb break="yes"/>the Tropics, at a height of 6000 yards, the azure vault of<lb break="yes"/>the sky appears of an indigo tint. The outlines of the<lb break="yes"/>mountain detach themselves from the sky in this pure and<lb break="yes"/>transparent atmosphere; while the inferior strata of the air,<lb break="yes"/>reposing on a plain destitute of vegetation, which reflects<lb break="yes"/>the radiant heat, are vaporous, and appear to veil the middle<lb break="yes"/>of the mountain.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="xxi" facs="#f0002"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Cotopaxi</hi> is the loftiest of the volcanoes of the Andes,<lb break="yes"/>which at recent epochs have undergone eruptions; and,<lb break="yes"/>notwithstanding it lies near the Equator, its summits are<lb break="yes"/>covered with perpetual snows. The absolute height of<lb break="yes"/>Cotopaxi is 18,876 feet, or these miles and a half; conse-<lb break="no"/>quently it is 2,622 feet, or half a mile, higher than Vesuvius<lb break="yes"/>would be, were that mountain placed on the top of the Peak<lb break="yes"/>of Teneriffe! Cotopaxi is the most mischievous of the<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes in the kingdom of Quito, and its explosions are<lb break="yes"/>the most frequent and disastrous. The masses of scori&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>and the pieces of rock thrown out of this volcano cover a<lb break="yes"/>surface of several square leagues, and would form, were<lb break="yes"/>they heaped together, a prodigious mountain. In 1738,<lb break="yes"/><choice><sic>th e</sic><corr type="editorial">the</corr></choice> flames of Cotopaxi rose 3000 feet, or upwards of half a<lb break="yes"/>mile; above the brink of the crater. In 1744, the roarings<lb break="yes"/>of this volcano were heard at the distance of 600 miles.<lb break="yes"/>On the 4th of April, 1768, the quantity of ashes ejected at<lb break="yes"/>the mouth of <choice>
                        <sic>Cotopoxi</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Cotopaxi</corr>
                    </choice> was so great, that it was dark till<lb break="yes"/>three in the afternoon. The form of Cotopaxi is the most<lb break="yes"/>beautiful and regular of the colossal summits of the high<lb break="yes"/>Andes. It is a perfect cone, which, covered with a perpetual<lb break="yes"/>layer of snow, shines with dazzling splendour at the setting<lb break="yes"/>of the sun, and detaches itself in the most picturesque<lb break="yes"/>manner from the azure vault above. This covering of snow<lb break="yes"/>conceals from the eye of the observer even the smallest<lb break="yes"/>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>nequalities</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">inequalities</corr>
                    </choice> of the soil; no point of rock, no stony mass,<lb break="yes" />penetrating this coat of ice, or breaking the regularity of<lb break="yes" />the figure of the cone.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 