<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Yellow Fever</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:50</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.7</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1811-Fragment_d_un-4-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1811-Fragment_d_un-1.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1811-Fragment_d_un-2.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1811-Fragment_d_un-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1811-Fragment_d_un-4-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1811-Fragment_d_un-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1811-Fragment_d_un-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1811-Fragment_d_un-7-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Yellow Fever</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1820</date>
          <pubPlace>Boston, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;Boston Intelligencer &amp;amp; Evening Gazette&lt;/i&gt; 6 (13. Mai 1820), S. [1]</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>YELLOW FEVER.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>WE published, last week, some extracts from<lb break="yes"/>the personal narrative of Mesns <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Bompland</hi>, respecting the contagion of this disease<lb break="yes"/>M. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi> proceeds in his pertinent observa-<lb break="no"/>tions on this subject, by citing a series of pathologi-<lb break="no"/>cal facts, for the judgment of his readers The<lb break="yes"/>well-known and acknowledged accuracy of this tra-<lb break="no" />veller, induces us to consider all his facts as authentic</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After mentioning the mystery attending the doc-<lb break="no"/>trine of contagion, he enquires how we can explore<lb break="yes"/>why during the eighteen years which preceeded<lb break="yes"/>the year 1794, there was not a single instance of<lb break="yes"/>Yellow-Fever at <hi rendition="#i" >Vera-Cruz,</hi> though the concourse<lb break="yes"/>of unseasoned Europeans and of Mexicans from the<lb break="yes"/>interior was very considerable; though the sailors<lb break="yes"/>indulged in the same excesses with which they are<lb break="yes"/>still reproached, and though the town was not so<lb break="yes"/>clean as it has been since the year 1800?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following is the series of patho-<lb break="no"/>logical facts, considered in their great-<lb break="no"/>est simplicity. When a great number<lb break="yes" />of persons, born in a cold climate, ar-<lb break="no"/>rive at the same time in a port of the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone, not particularly dreaded by<lb break="yes"/>navigators, the typhus of America be-<lb break="no"/>gins to appear. Those persons have<lb break="yes"/>not had the typhus during their passage;<lb break="yes"/>it manifests itself among them only on<lb break="yes"/>the very spot. Is the atmospheric con-<lb break="no"/>stitution changed? or does a new form<lb break="yes"/>of disease display itself among individ-<lb break="no"/>uals, whose irritability is highly increas-<lb break="no"/>ed?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The typhus soon begins to exert its<lb break="yes"/>ravages among the Europeans, born in<lb break="yes"/>more southern countries. If it propa-<lb break="no" />gate itself by contagion, it seems sur-<lb break="no"/>prising, that in the towns of the equinoc-<lb break="no"/>tial continent it does not attach itself to<lb break="yes"/>certain streets; and that immediate<lb break="yes" />contact does not augment the danger,<lb break="yes"/>any more than seclusion diminishes it.<lb break="yes"/>The sick, when removed to the inland<lb break="yes"/>country, and especially to cooler and<lb break="yes"/>more elevated spots, to Xalappa, for in-<lb break="no"/>stance, do not communicate the typhus<lb break="yes"/>to the inhabitants of those places, eith-<lb break="no"/>er because it is not contagious in it’s na-<lb break="no"/>ture, or that the predisposing causes<lb break="yes"/>are not the same as in the regions of<lb break="yes"/>the shore. When there is a considera-<lb break="no" />ble diminution of the temperature, the<lb break="yes"/>epidemy usually ceases, even on the<lb break="yes"/>spot where it first appeared. It again<lb break="yes"/>begins at the approach of the hot sea-<lb break="no"/>son, and sometimes long before; though<lb break="yes"/>during several months there has been<lb break="yes"/>no sick person in the harbour, and no<lb break="yes" />ship has entered it.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The typhus of America appears to<lb break="yes"/>be confined to the shore, either be-<lb break="no"/>cause those persons who bring the dis-<lb break="no" />ease disembark there, and goods sup-<lb break="no"/>posed to be impregnated with deleteri-<lb break="no"/>ous miasmata are there accumulated;<lb break="yes" />or because on the seaside gaseous ema-<lb break="no"/>nations of a particular nature are form-<lb break="no"/>ed. The aspect of the places where<lb break="yes"/>typhus exerts it’s ravages seems often<lb break="yes"/>to exclude all idea of a local or endem-<lb break="no"/>ical origin. It has been seen to prevail<lb break="yes"/>in the Canaries, the Bermudas, and a-<lb break="no"/>mong the smaller West India Islands, in<lb break="yes"/>dry places formerly distinguished for<lb break="yes"/>the great salubrity of their climate.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Examples of the propagation of the<lb break="yes"/>yellow fever in the inland parts of the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone appear very doubtful; this<lb break="yes"/>malady may have been confounded with<lb break="yes"/>remitting bilious fevers. With respect<lb break="yes" />to the temperate zone, in which the<lb break="yes"/>contagious character of the typhus of<lb break="yes"/>America is more decided, the disease<lb break="yes"/>has indubitably spread far from the<lb break="yes"/>shore, even into very elevated places,<lb break="yes"/>exposed to cool and dry winds, as in<lb break="yes"/>Spain, at Medina-Sidonia, at Carlotta,<lb break="yes" />and the city of Murcia. That variety<lb break="yes"/>of phenomena, which the same epidem-<lb break="no"/>ic exhibits, according to the difference<lb break="yes"/>of climates, the union of predisposing<lb break="yes"/>causes, it’s shorter or longer duration,<lb break="yes"/>and the degree of it’s <hi rendition="#i">exacerbation,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>should render us extremely circumspect<lb break="yes"/>in tracing the secret causes of the A-<lb break="no"/>merican typhus. An enlightened ob-<lb break="no"/>server, who, at the time of the violent<lb break="yes"/>epidemics in 1802 and 1803, was chief<lb break="yes"/>physician to the colony of St. Domingo,<lb break="yes"/>and who has studied that disease in the<lb break="yes"/>Island of Cuba, the U. States and Spain,<lb break="yes" />Mr. Bailly, thinks like me, ‘that the ty-<lb break="no"/>phus is very often, but not always, con-<lb break="no"/>tagious.’</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Since the yellow fever has made<lb break="yes"/>such cruel ravages in La Guayra, the<lb break="yes"/>want of cleanliness in that little town<lb break="yes" />has been exaggerated, like that of Vera<lb break="yes"/>Cruz, and of the quays or wharfs of<lb break="yes"/>Philadelphia. In a place where the soil<lb break="yes"/>is extremely dry, destitute of vegeta-<lb break="no"/>tion, and where a few drops of water<lb break="yes"/>scarcely fall in seven or eight months,<lb break="yes"/>the causes, that produce what are call<lb break="yes"/>ed miasmata, cannot be very frequent.<lb break="yes"/>The streets of La Guayra appeared to<lb break="yes"/>me in general to be tolerably clean.<lb break="yes"/>with the exception of the quarter of<lb break="yes" />the slaughter houses. The sea side has<lb break="yes"/>no beach, on which the remains of fuct<lb break="yes"/>and of Molluscæ are heaped up; but<lb break="yes"/>the neighboring coast, which stretches<lb break="yes"/>to the east towards Cape Codera, and<lb break="yes"/>consequently to the windward of La<lb break="yes"/>Guayra, is extremely unhealthy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The yellow fever and the black vomit<lb break="yes"/>cease periodically at the Havana and<lb break="yes"/>Vera Cruz, when the north winds bring<lb break="yes" />the cold air of Canada toward the Gulf<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> of Mexico. But from the extreme e-<lb break="no"/>quality of temperature, which charac-<lb break="no"/>terizes the climates of Porto-Cabello,<lb break="yes"/>La Guayra, New Barcelona, and Coma-<lb break="no"/>na, it may be feared, that the typhus<lb break="yes"/>will there become permanent, when<lb break="yes"/>ever, from a great concourse of stran-<lb break="no"/>gers, it has acquired a high degree of<lb break="yes"/>exacerbation. Happily the mortality<lb break="yes"/>has diminished since the treatment of<lb break="yes"/>this epidemic has been varied, according<lb break="yes"/>to the character it presents in different<lb break="yes"/>years; and since the different stages of<lb break="yes"/>the disease have been better studied,<lb break="yes"/>which are recognized by symptoms of<lb break="yes" />inflammation, and of <hi rendition="#i">ataxy</hi> or debility.<lb break="yes" />It would, I think, be unjust to deny the<lb break="yes"/>success, which the new <choice>
                        <sic>tystem</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">system</corr>
                    </choice> of medi-<lb break="no"/>cine has obtained over this terrible<lb break="yes"/>scourge; yet the persuasion of this suc-<lb break="no"/>cess has not made much progress in the<lb break="yes"/>colonies. It is there said pretty gener-<lb break="no"/>ally, ‘that the physicians now explain<lb break="yes"/>the course of the disease in a more sat-<lb break="no" />isfactory manner than they did former-<lb break="no"/>ly, but that they do not cure it better:<lb break="yes"/>that heretofore the patient was left to<lb break="yes"/>die slowly, taking no other remedy than<lb break="yes"/>an infusion of tamarinds; and that in<lb break="yes"/>our days a more active practice carries<lb break="yes"/>him to the grave in a more direct and<lb break="yes"/>expeditious manner.’</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This opinion is not founded upon an<lb break="yes"/>accurate knowledge of what was done<lb break="yes"/>formerly in the West India Islands.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>The voyage of Father Labat sufficient-<lb break="no"/>ly demonstrates, that in the beginning of<lb break="yes"/>the 18th century the physicians of the<lb break="yes"/>West Indies did not suffer the sick to die<lb break="yes"/>so tranquilly, as seems to be supposed.<lb break="yes"/>They did not then kill by emetics, bark,<lb break="yes"/>and opium, employed in two large doses,<lb break="yes"/>and unseasonably;&#x2014;but by frequent<lb break="yes"/>bleedings, and the abuse of purgatives.<lb break="yes"/>The physicians indeed seemed so well<lb break="yes"/>aware of the effects of their treatment<lb break="yes"/>that they had the candour ‘to present<lb break="yes"/>themselves at the bed-side of the sick,<lb break="yes" />accompanied at their first visit by a con-<lb break="no"/>fessor and a notary.’ At present, in<lb break="yes"/>neat and well conducted hospitals, they<lb break="yes"/>often succeed in reducing the number of<lb break="yes" />deaths to eighteen or fifteen in a hund-<lb break="no"/>red, and even a little less. But when-<lb break="no"/>ever the sick are crowded together, the<lb break="yes"/>mortality increases to one half, or even<lb break="yes"/>to three quarters, of which the French<lb break="yes"/>army in St. Domingo afforded an exam-<lb break="no"/>ple in 1802.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 
