<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">[Lettre à l’éditeur du Moniteur]</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:50</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.11</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1811-xxx-Lettre_a_l-4-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1811-xxx-Lettre_a_l-1-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1811-xxx-Lettre_a_l-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1811-xxx-Lettre_a_l-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1811-xxx-Lettre_a_l-4-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1811-xxx-Lettre_a_l-5.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">[Lettre à l’éditeur du Moniteur]</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1811</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in:&lt;i&gt; The Naval Chronicle for 1811: Containing a general and biographical history of the Royal Navy of the United Kingdom; with a variety of original papers on nautical subjects&lt;/i&gt; 26 (Juli–Dezember 1811), S. 401–402.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <relatedItem type="reprint">
            <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Ueber die künftigen Verhältnisse von Europa und Amerika. Politische und historographische Schriften zur Neuen Welt&lt;/i&gt;, herausgegeben von Oliver Lubrich, Hannover: Wehrhahn 2010, S. 26–31. Und übersetzt als "Concerning a Map of New Spain Published by
              Mr. Arrowsmith in 1810", in: David Y. Allen, „Alexander von Humboldt’s Critique of Aaron Arrowsmith’s 1810 Map of Mexico“, in: &lt;i&gt;Imago Mundi: International Journal for the History of Cartography&lt;/i&gt; 68:2 (2016), S. 232–236.</bibl>
          </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="401" facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>HE <hi rendition="#i">Moniteur</hi> of the 11th contains a long letter to the Editor from<lb break="yes"/>Mr. De Humboldt, in which he brings a charge of plagiarism against<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Arrowsmith, a well-known English geographer.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>After some prefatory observations, Mr. De H. proceeds as follows:&#x2014;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>“I was engaged during four years in the construction of a map of<lb break="yes" />Mexico, which was published at Paris, in September, 1809, on two large<lb break="yes"/>sheets, in my &#x2018;Geographical and Physical Atlas of the Kingdom of New<lb break="yes"/>Spain.&#x2019; I had first drawn it up in Mexico, in 1803, and it was engraved at<lb break="yes"/>Paris by MM. Aubert and Barriere: it was entitled, &#x2018;General Map of<lb break="yes"/>the Kingdom of New Spain, drawn up from astronomical observations, and<lb break="yes"/>the whole of the materials which existed in Mexico, at the commencement<lb break="yes"/>of the year 1804, by Alexander De Humboldt.&#x2019; The astronomical obser-<lb break="no"/>vations, the geodesic surveys, and the barometrical admeasurements of<lb break="yes"/>heights which I made in the course of my travels in the equinoctial regions<lb break="yes"/>of the new Continent, from 1799 to 1803, are to be found in the second<lb break="yes"/>volume of my &#x2018;Collection of Astronomical Observations,&#x2019; published con-<lb break="no" />jointly with M. Oltmanns. The numerous and unpublished materials which<lb break="yes"/>assisted in the construction of the 20 maps contained in the Mexican atlas,<lb break="yes"/>are indicated and discussed in an analysis prefixed to my Political Essay on<lb break="yes"/>the kingdom of New Spain.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;All these long and painful labours, however imperfect they appear to<lb break="yes" />me, Mr. Arrowsmith has entirely appropriated to himself; he faithfully<lb break="yes"/>copied my general map of Mexico, and published it in London, before the<lb break="yes"/>appearance of the English translation of my Political Essay; and he sub-<lb break="no"/>
                <pb n="402" facs="#f0002"/> stituted his own name instead of mine, under the title of &#x2018;New Map of<lb break="yes"/>Mexico, <hi rendition="#i">compiled from original documents</hi>, by Arrowsmith.&#x2019; The positions<lb break="yes"/>of the towns, of the villages and mines, the boundaries of the intendan-<lb break="no"/>ces, the ranges of mountains, the indications of the heights in toises, the<lb break="yes" />notes on the migrations of the Azteques, and on the history of navigation,<lb break="yes"/>the small arrows annexed to a number of rivers, every thing, in short, is to<lb break="yes"/>be found in the copy of Mr. Arrowsmith. I was obliged to employ several<lb break="yes"/>new signs, for instance, two hammers placed crosswise to denote the chief<lb break="yes"/>station of a provincial council of the mines; and Mr. Arrowsmith, in <choice>
                    <sic>adopt-<lb break="no"/>iug</sic>
                    <corr type="editorial">adopt-<lb break="no"/>ing</corr>
                </choice> my signs, has also adopted their explanation; he has copied without<lb break="yes"/>translating, and without changing a single word; on his English map he<lb break="yes"/>has engraved my explanations in French, always leaving out the sign<lb break="yes"/>pointing to the places where I made astronomical observations. If my<lb break="yes"/>name is looked for in the copy of the great map, it is only to be found in<lb break="yes"/>one of the three squares which contain the same number of sketches bor-<lb break="no"/>rowed from my Mexican Atlas. These small squares present hydrographic<lb break="yes"/>plans of the ports of Vera-Cruz and Acapulco, and the chart of the valley<lb break="yes"/>of Mexico. To the words &#x2018;Valley of Mexico,&#x2019; Mr. Arrowsmith has<lb break="yes"/>thought fit to annex the following words, &#x2018;from Mr. Humboldt&#x2019;s Map.&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>But the only thing which Mr. Arrowsmith chooses to ascribe to me is not<lb break="yes"/>my own: it was a plan drawn up by Don Louis Martin, in 1804.&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>After a variety of other observations, Mr. De Humboldt adds: &#x201C;This<lb break="yes" />silence with regard to the sources of their information is become too com-<lb break="no"/>mon with geographers; particularly with those who do not accompany their<lb break="yes"/>maps with analytical memoirs on the subject of their construction, though<lb break="yes"/>a very different example has been given by the most distinguished of that<lb break="yes"/>class of literary men, such as d&#x2019;Anville, Dalrymple, Fleurieu, and Rennell.&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>Mr. de H. concludes with expressing his hope, that the reclamations of a<lb break="yes"/>traveller will meet with some attention, when he proves that mere copies<lb break="yes"/>of his labours are disseminated under the name of another person. The<lb break="yes"/>letter itself is written with every appearance of candor, and deserves the<lb break="yes"/>attention of those whom it may concern.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 