<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>The <hi rendition="#i">Moniteur</hi> of the 11th contains a long letter<lb break="yes"/>to the Editor from M. De Humboldt, in which he<lb break="yes" />brings a charge of plagiarism against Mr. Arrow-<lb break="no"/>smith, a well-known English Geographer.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>After some prefatory observations, M. De H.<lb break="yes"/>proceeds as follows:&#x2014;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;I was engaged during four years in the con-<lb break="no"/>struction of a map of Mexico, which was published<lb break="yes"/>at Paris, in September, 1809, in two large <choice>
                    <sic>sheest</sic>
                    <corr type="editorial">sheets</corr>
                </choice>, in<lb break="yes"/>my &#x2018;Geographical and Physical Atlas of the<lb break="yes"/>Kingdom of New Spain.&#x2019; I had first drawn it up<lb break="yes"/>in Mexico, in 1803, and it was engraved at Paris<lb break="yes"/>by M. M. Aubert and Barriere: it was entitled,<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;General Map of the Kingdom of New Spain,<lb break="yes"/>drawn up from astronomical observations, and the<lb break="yes"/>whole of the materials which existed in Mexico, at<lb break="yes"/>the commencement of the year 1804, by Alexander<lb break="yes"/>De Humboldt.&#x2019; The astronomical observations,<lb break="yes"/>the geodesic surveys, and the barometrical admea-<lb break="no"/>surements of heights which I made in the course of<lb break="yes"/>my travels in the equinoctial regions of the New<lb break="yes"/>Continent, from 1799 to 1803, are to be found in<lb break="yes"/>the second volume of my &#x2018;Collection of Astrono-<lb break="no"/>mical Observations,&#x2019; published conjointly with M.<lb break="yes"/>Oltmanns. The numerous and unpublished ma-<lb break="no"/>terials which assisted in the construction of the 20<lb break="yes"/>maps contained in the Mexican atlas, are indicated<lb break="yes"/>and discussed in an analysis prefixed to my Political<lb break="yes"/>Essay on the kingdom of New Spain.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;All these long and painful labours, however<lb break="yes"/>imperfect they appear to me, Mr. Arrowsmith has<lb break="yes"/>entirely appropriated to himself; he faithfully<lb break="yes"/>copied my general map of Mexico, and published<lb break="yes"/>it in London, before the appearance of the English<lb break="yes" />translation of my Political Essay; and he substi-<lb break="no"/>tuted his own name instead of mine, under the title<lb break="yes"/>of &#x201C;New Map of Mexico, <hi rendition="#i">compiled from original<lb break="yes"/>documents,</hi> by Arrowsmith.&#x201D; The positions of the<lb break="yes"/>towns, of the villages and mines, the boundaries of<lb break="yes"/>the intendances, the ranges of mountains, the indi-<lb break="no"/>cations of the heights in toises, the notes on the<lb break="yes"/>migrations of the Azteques, and on the history of<lb break="yes" />navigation, the small arrows annexed to a number<lb break="yes"/>of rivers, every thing, in short, is to be found in<lb break="yes"/>the copy of Mr. Arrowsmith. I was obliged to<lb break="yes"/>employ several new signs; for instance, two ham-<lb break="no"/>mers placed crosswise to denote the chief station of<lb break="yes" />a provincial council of the mines; and Mr. Arrow-<lb break="no"/>smith, in adopting my signs, has also adopted their<lb break="yes"/>explanation; he has copied without translation, and<lb break="yes"/>without changing a single word; on his English<lb break="yes"/>map he has engraved my explanations in French,<lb break="yes"/>always leaving out the sign pointing to the places<lb break="yes" />where I made astronomical observations. If my<lb break="yes"/>name is looked for in the copy of the great map, it<lb break="yes"/>is only to be found in one of the three squares which<lb break="yes"/>contain the same number of sketches borrowed<lb break="yes"/>from my Mexican Atlas. These small squares pre-<lb break="no"/>sent hydrographic plans of the ports of Vera Cruz<lb break="yes"/>and Acapulco, and the chart of the valley of<lb break="yes"/>Mexico. To the words &#x201C;Valley of Mexico,&#x201D; Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Arrowsmith has thought fit to annex the following<lb break="yes"/>words, &#x201C;from M. Humboldt&#x2019;s Map.&#x201D; But the only<lb break="yes"/>thing which Mr. Arrowsmith choses to ascribe to<lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="2" facs="#f0002"/><cb/>me is not my own; it was a plan drawn up by D.<lb break="yes"/>Louis Martin, in 1804.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>After a variety of other observations, M. de Hum-<lb break="no"/>bolt adds, &#x201C;This silence with regard to the sources<lb break="yes"/>of their information is become too common with<lb break="yes"/>geographers, particularly with those who do not<lb break="yes"/>accompany their maps with analytical memoirs on<lb break="yes"/>the subject of their construction, though a very<lb break="yes" />different example has been given by the most dis-<lb break="no"/>tinguished of that class of literary men, such as<lb break="yes"/>d&#x2019;Anville, Dalrymple, <choice>
                    <sic>Fleuriu</sic>
                    <corr type="editorial">Fleurieu</corr>
                </choice>, and Rennell.&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>M. d. H. concludes with expressing his hope,<lb break="yes"/>that the reclamations of a traveller will meet with<lb break="yes"/>some attention, when he proves that mere copies of<lb break="yes"/>his labours are disseminated under the name of<lb break="yes"/>another person. The letter itself is written with<lb break="yes" />every appearance of candour, and deserves the at-<lb break="no"/>tention of those whom it concerns.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 