<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="342" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>Extract from a report made to the class of phisico-mathematical<lb break="yes" />sciences, on the 9th of Sept. 1811, by a committee, composed of<lb break="yes" />Messrs. Hallé, Humboldt and Percy, on a memorial of Mr. Le-<lb break="no" />gallois, M. D. concerning the principle of action of the<lb break="yes" />heart, and the seat of that principle. Translated from the Paris<lb break="yes"/>Moniteur by J. D. Synott, M. M. &amp; C. F. M. and Professor<lb break="yes"/>of Belles Lettres in St. Mary’s college.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <p>M. LEGALLOIS has undertaken to prove, in the me-<lb break="no"/>moir which he presented to the class, that the principle<lb break="yes"/>of the action of the heart resides in the spinal marrow.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The committee, in the first place, give a succinct ac-<lb break="no"/>count of the divers systems suggested since the discove-<lb break="no"/>ry of the circulation to explain the action of the heart.<lb break="yes"/>The several systems of Descartes, Sylvius, Delebre and Bo-<lb break="no"/>relli, and that of Willis, as revised and corrected by Boerr-<lb break="no"/>haave, the systems of Stahl, Ens and Stachelin, are noticed by<lb break="yes"/>them in their turn. But the one which Haller founded on<lb break="yes"/>irritability has particularly attracted their attention. As this<lb break="yes"/>last has consigned all the others to oblivion, it has given rise<lb break="yes"/>to lively discussions which have been continued to the present<lb break="yes" />day. These disputes proceed from this fact; that Haller’s<lb break="yes" />system, as well as those that preceded it, are not sufficiently<lb break="yes"/>satisfactory to account for all the phenomena.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>In taking a general view (say the committee) of the differ-<lb break="no" />ent systems invented before Haller, we may remark, that the<lb break="yes" />nervous power, in one way or other, has always been consi-<lb break="no" />dered as one of the essential conditions to produce the mo-<lb break="no" />tions of the heart, and the seat of this power has constantly<lb break="yes"/>and uniformly been placed in the brain.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The cardiac nerves had of course a determinate use in all<lb break="yes" />these systems, and it was easy to conceive how the heart<lb break="yes" />was subjected to the influence of the passions; but they could<lb break="yes"/>not explain why the circulation continues in acephalous ani-<lb break="no"/>mals, nor why, in experimenting on animals, the interruption<lb break="yes"/>of all communication between the brain and the heart, does<lb break="yes"/>not stop the action of the latter organ. Since the days of<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="343" facs="#f0002"/>Haller, irritability has been the basis of every system: in con-<lb break="no"/>sidering this property as essential to the muscular fibre, and<lb break="yes"/>independent of the nervous power, the circulation in acephal-<lb break="no"/>ous animals and the different phenomena observed in the ex-<lb break="no"/>periments above alluded to, present no difficulty; but the use<lb break="yes"/>of the nerves of the heart, and the influence of the passions<lb break="yes"/>on that organ became inexplicable. The necessity of ob-<lb break="no"/>viating these difficulties has split the advocates of irritability<lb break="yes"/>into two sects. On one side the zealous defenders of pure<lb break="yes" />irritability have called to their assistance the most inconsist-<lb break="no"/>ent hypotheses, and all their exertions tend only to prove how<lb break="yes"/>very difficult it is to defend the cause they have embraced.<lb break="yes"/>Their opponents have introduced the nervous power with ir-<lb break="no"/>ritability, and consider the latter as one of the functions of the<lb break="yes"/>former; but then they were necessitated to admit, either with<lb break="yes"/>regard to the seat, or the mode of existence of this nervous<lb break="yes"/>power, certain conditions, which as they themselves confess,<lb break="yes"/>are far from being demonstrated, on which they do not agree<lb break="yes"/>among themselves, and which, when applied to the action of<lb break="yes"/>the heart, do not entirely remove the old difficulties, or else<lb break="yes"/>give rise to new ones.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It is easy to perceive whence it is, that so little progress has<lb break="yes"/>been made in this long and important controversy. If we<lb break="yes"/>examine all that has been said on the subject since the time<lb break="yes"/>of Haller, we shall find nearly the same facts, the same ex-<lb break="no"/>periments, and the same reasonings advanced by either party.<lb break="yes"/>The only new experiments are the application of Galvanism<lb break="yes"/>to stimulate the cardiac nerves, and even these are new only<lb break="yes"/>in appearance, as in the days of Haller electricity was employ-<lb break="no"/>ed for the same purpose and with the same results. It is<lb break="yes"/>evident that we have nothing more to hope for the advance-<lb break="no"/>ment of this interesting part of physiology by following the<lb break="yes"/>track already beaten by so many celebrated men, for nearly<lb break="yes"/>sixty years. New paths must then be opened, and new me-<lb break="no"/>thods discovered for the investigation of nature: above all,<lb break="yes"/>that degree of precision and strict logical reasoning must be<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="344" facs="#f0003"/> introduced into physiological researches, which has been al-<lb break="no"/>ready employed with such success in the other departments<lb break="yes"/>of natural philosophy. This is what M. Legallois has en-<lb break="no"/>deavoured to effect.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It was not, at first, the object of M. Legallois to search into<lb break="yes"/>the causes of the movements of the heart. He was attached<lb break="yes"/>to the theory of Haller, until experiments, undertaken with<lb break="yes"/>quite a different view, led him to conclude that it was still a<lb break="yes"/>mystery to him how the nervous power, if it interfered at all,<lb break="yes"/>was interested in aiding the functions of the heart.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>That we may give a clear view of his investigations, we<lb break="yes"/>will relate on what occasion, and by what chain of facts and<lb break="yes" />reasoning he was induced to engage in this research.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A particular case of midwifery gave him, some years ago,<lb break="yes"/>a wish to know how long a full grown fœtus may live with-<lb break="no"/>out breathing, counting from the moment when, from any<lb break="yes"/>cause whatever, it has ceased to have any communication<lb break="yes"/>with the mother. This question, so very curious in itself,<lb break="yes"/>and so interesting to the practice of midwifery and medi-<lb break="no"/>cine, had scarcely been glanced at by authors. M. Legal-<lb break="no"/>lois undertook to solve it by direct experiments. And<lb break="yes"/>in order that the solution might extend to as great a num<lb break="yes"/>ber of cases as possible, he placed the fœtus of different<lb break="yes"/>animals in such different situations as might resemble the<lb break="yes"/>principle accidents that may happen to the human fœtus whilst<lb break="yes"/>its communication with the mother is intercepted. Among<lb break="yes"/>these accidents there is one which but too often takes place;<lb break="yes"/>this is separating the head from the body in the delivery of a<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">footling</hi> case. The author wished to know what became of the<lb break="yes"/>fœtus in this case, whether it died at the moment of decapita-<lb break="no"/>tion, and of what death it died? He discovered that the trunk<lb break="yes"/>remains living, and that, by preventing hemorrhage by pass-<lb break="no"/>ing ligatures around the vessels of the neck, it does not die<lb break="yes"/>except in the same space of time, and with the same phenom-<lb break="no"/>ena, as if, without being separated from the head, respira-<lb break="no"/>tion had been completely intercepted. And what evidently<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="345" facs="#f0004"/> proved to him that the decollated animal is only in a state of<lb break="yes"/>asphyxy, is, that he could at will prolong its existence by sup-<lb break="no"/>plying respiration by means of the inflation of the lungs.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>M. Legallois concludes from these facts, that decapitation<lb break="yes" />does no more than arrest the inspiratory motions, and that<lb break="yes" />consequently the principle of all these motions is in the brain,<lb break="yes"/>but that the principle of the life of the trunk resides in the<lb break="yes"/>trunk itself. Searching afterwards for the immediate seat of<lb break="yes"/>each of these principles, he found that the principle of the<lb break="yes"/>inspiratory motions resides in that part of the <hi rendition="#i">medulla ablon-<lb break="no"/>gata,</hi> that gives origin to the nerves of the eighth pain, and that<lb break="yes"/>that of the life of the trunk has its source in the <hi rendition="#i">medula spin-<lb break="no"/>alis.</hi> It is not by the whole of the spinal marrow that each<lb break="yes"/>part of the body is animated, but only by that portion from<lb break="yes"/>which it receives its nerves: so that by destroying a portion of<lb break="yes"/>the spinal marrow, we deprive of life those parts only of the<lb break="yes"/>body that correspond with this portion. Besides, if we in-<lb break="no"/>tercept the circulation of the blood in a portion of the spinal<lb break="yes"/>marrow, life languishes and soon becomes entirely extinct in<lb break="yes"/>all the parts that receive their nerves from that portion of<lb break="yes"/>marrow. There are then two means of destroying life in<lb break="yes"/>this or that part of an animal body; one by destroying the<lb break="yes"/>marrow from which the part receives its nerves, the other, by<lb break="yes"/>intercepting the circulation of the blood therein.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The result of the above was, that the maintenance of life<lb break="yes"/>in any part of the body essentially depended on two condi-<lb break="no" />tions; namely, the integrity of the corresponding portion of<lb break="yes"/>the spinal marrow, and the circulation of the blood: and con-<lb break="no"/>sequently, that it was possible to continue life in any part of<lb break="yes"/>an animal as long as these two conditions could be made to<lb break="yes"/>subsist; that one might, for example, continue life to the an-<lb break="no"/>terior parts alone, after having deprived the hinder parts of<lb break="yes"/>life, by the destruction of the spinal marrow that corresponds<lb break="yes"/>with them, or to the hinder parts, after having, in like man-<lb break="no"/>ner, killed the anterior parts.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>M. Legallois wished to know if his experiments would<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="346" facs="#f0005"/> confirm these consequences, and if it were in reality possible<lb break="yes"/>to enable this or that portion of an animal to live, independ-<lb break="no"/>ently of the other parts.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>He first submitted to experiment a rabbit twenty days old;<lb break="yes"/>in this animal he destroyed all the lumbar portion of the spi-<lb break="no" />nal marrow. This operation not immediately interfering<lb break="yes" />with the rest of the marrow, and the circulation, according to<lb break="yes"/>Haller, not being necessarily affected by it, there was suf-<lb break="no"/>ficient room to expect, in reasoning from preceding experi-<lb break="no"/>ments, that the animal would survive a considerable length<lb break="yes"/>of time; but in less than two minutes respiration was sus-<lb break="no"/>pended, and in less than four minutes it no longer gave signs<lb break="yes"/>of life. The same experiment frequently repeated was al-<lb break="no"/>ways attended with the same results, without the possibility<lb break="yes"/>of preventing them by any means whatsoever, and it was in-<lb break="no"/>variably true that a rabbit twenty days old could not survive<lb break="yes"/>the destruction of its lumbar marrow. This was the more<lb break="yes"/>surprizing as rabbits of that age can continue to live after de-<lb break="no"/>capitation, that is, after losing the whole of the brain. This is<lb break="yes"/>the fact that M. Legallois could not reconcile with his pre-<lb break="no"/>ceding experiments, and which has led him to discover that<lb break="yes"/>the principle of the powers of the heart resides in the spinal<lb break="yes"/>marrow.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>He first of all assured himself that the destruction of ei-<lb break="no" />ther the dorsal or cervical portion of the marrow was mortal<lb break="yes"/>to rabbits of twenty days old, as also of the lumbar portion, and<lb break="yes"/>even in less than two minutes. He next discovered that the<lb break="yes"/>same experiments repeated on rabbits of different ages did not<lb break="yes"/>produce the same effects. In general, the destruction of the<lb break="yes"/>lumbar marrow is not suddenly mortal to these animals be-<lb break="no"/>fore the age of ten days; many even of fifteen days survived<lb break="yes"/>it. With rabbits above twenty days the effect is the same as<lb break="yes"/>with those of twenty days. Very young rabbits may continue<lb break="yes"/>to live after the destruction of either the dorsal or the cervi-<lb break="no"/>cal marrow, but a much shorter time, and in fewer cases<lb break="yes"/>when the latter is destroyed, than the former. Those that<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="347" facs="#f0006"/>have passed the age of fifteen days can survive the destruc-<lb break="no"/>tion of either the one or the other.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>In all these partial injuries, even when death speedily en-<lb break="no" />sues, it is never instantaneous, except in such parts as receive<lb break="yes"/>their nerves from the portion of marrow destroyed. It does<lb break="yes"/>not take place in the rest of the body until after a certain<lb break="yes"/>time; but this time is determinate, and no means can prolong<lb break="yes"/>it. This time, which is the same for animals of the same<lb break="yes"/>age and species, is longer in proportion as the animals are<lb break="yes"/>younger. For example when the cervical marrow is des-<lb break="no"/>troyed in rabbits, life is extinguished on the instant through<lb break="yes"/>all the neck, but it continues in the head, which we may as-<lb break="no"/>certain from the spasmodic motions of the mouth. Life re-<lb break="no"/>mains also in the posterior parts, from the shoulders down-<lb break="no"/>wards, as may be perceived by the sensations and voluntary<lb break="yes"/>motions they exhibit. On the day of birth, the motions of<lb break="yes"/>the mouth continue about twenty minutes, those of the rest of<lb break="yes"/>the body fifteen minutes; at the age of fifteen days, the spas-<lb break="no"/>modic gaspings do not last longer than three minutes, nor<lb break="yes"/>are the motions of the body perceptible longer than two min-<lb break="no"/>utes and an half. In fine, at the age of thirty days all mo-<lb break="no"/>tions cease within a minute or a minute and an half. After<lb break="yes"/>the destruction of the dorsal marrow, it is the breast and not<lb break="yes"/>the neck that is struck with death; in the rest of the body,<lb break="yes"/>the same phenomena and duration may be observed. If the<lb break="yes"/>three portions of the marrow be simultaneously destroyed,<lb break="yes"/>the gapings, (the only signs of life that then are manifest,)<lb break="yes"/>have, in different ages, the duration above mentioned.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The author, who had so often practised decapitation on<lb break="yes" />rabbits of different ages, had constantly remarked, that the<lb break="yes"/>head, when separated from the body, continued to gape, and<lb break="yes"/>that during a time proportioned to the age of each animal.<lb break="yes"/>Now this space of time was the same as after the destruction<lb break="yes"/>of the spinal marrow. But it is evident that after decapita-<lb break="no"/>tion there is no longer any circulation in the head, and that<lb break="yes"/>the spasmodic gapings which take place in this case, do not<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="348" facs="#f0007"/> continue longer than life subsists in the brain after the cir-<lb break="no"/>culation has totally ceased.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>This was what first indicated to M. Legallois, that when<lb break="yes"/>the partial destruction of the spinal marrow extinguished life<lb break="yes" />in the rest of the body, it was by suddenly arresting the cir-<lb break="no"/>culation. To make himself certain of this, he cut out, at the<lb break="yes"/>base of the large vessels, the heart of rabbits from the age of<lb break="yes"/>five or six days to a month; and having attentively remarked<lb break="yes"/>the duration of the different signs of life, counting from the<lb break="yes"/>moment when the circulation was arrested by the above<lb break="yes"/>method, he found that the spaces of time were exactly the<lb break="yes"/>same with those he had observed after the destruction of the<lb break="yes"/>spinal marrow. He might have considered this correspon-<lb break="no"/>dence of time as sufficient to decide the question. But he<lb break="yes"/>wished to determine to a certainty, whether the circulation<lb break="yes"/>is really intercepted at the very moment when the spinal<lb break="yes"/>marrow is destroyed. The absence of hemorrhage, and the<lb break="yes"/>vacuity of the arteries were the most evident signs he could<lb break="yes"/>have of the fact, and he found that in effect, the carotids are<lb break="yes"/>empty immediately after this operation, and no blood was<lb break="yes"/>yielded on the amputation of the members, even when it was<lb break="yes"/>performed close to the body, and before life is extinct in<lb break="yes"/>parts the marrow of which has not been destroyed. In a<lb break="yes"/>word, all the signs that serve to give a knowledge of the<lb break="yes"/>state of the circulation proved to him that whenever the des-<lb break="no"/>truction of any portion of the spinal marrow suddenly caus-<lb break="no"/>es death in the rest of the body, it is by arresting that func-<lb break="no"/>tion. This last effect takes place, not because the action of<lb break="yes"/>the heart ceases on a sudden, but because it loses all its force,<lb break="yes" />so as not to be able to impel the blood into the carotids.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The result of all this is, that it is from the spinal marrow<lb break="yes" />that the heart derives the principle of its powers, and from the<lb break="yes"/>whole of this marrow, since the destruction of any one of the<lb break="yes"/>three portions can, according to the age arrest the circula-<lb break="no"/>tion, and the destroying of the three portions arrests it in all<lb break="yes"/>ages. Another result is, that each portion of this marrow<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="349" facs="#f0008"/> has on life two modes of action very distinct from each oth-<lb break="no"/>er. One, by which it essentially constitutes life in all the<lb break="yes"/>parts that receive their nerves from it; the other, by which it<lb break="yes"/>serves to maintain life in all the parts of the body, by con-<lb break="no"/>tributing to furnish all the organs that receive twigs from the<lb break="yes"/>great sympathetic, and especially the heart, with the princi-<lb break="no"/>ple of life and power, necessary for their functions.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It is plain then, that in order to enable the fore or hinder<lb break="yes" />parts of an animal to live singly, (after having caused death<lb break="yes"/>in the other parts of the body by destroying the correspond-<lb break="no"/>ing marrow,) it is necessary to be able to prevent this des-<lb break="no"/>truction from arresting the circulation. To effect this it is<lb break="yes"/>sufficient to diminish by ligatures passed round the arteries,<lb break="yes"/>the extent of the parts to which the heart has to distribute<lb break="yes"/>blood. We have seen, for instance, that the destruction of<lb break="yes"/>the lumbar marrrow is immediately mortal for rabbits that<lb break="yes"/>have attained or passed the age of twenty days; but<lb break="yes"/>they would not die of this operation, if, before we des-<lb break="no"/>troy the marrow, we were to commence by tying the ab-<lb break="no"/>dominal aorta between the celiac and anterior mesenteric ar-<lb break="no"/>teries.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The application of this principle to other parts of the body<lb break="yes" />leads to a circumstance very singular in appearance; it is,<lb break="yes" />that to be able to support life in rabbits of a certain age, af-<lb break="no"/>ter having destroyed the cervical marrow, we must begin by<lb break="yes"/>cutting off the head. They die inevitably, if without be-<lb break="no"/>heading them, we destroy this marrow. This fact ceases to<lb break="yes"/>surprise, when we remark that by decapitation we remove<lb break="yes"/>the entire head from the dominion of the circulation, and<lb break="yes"/>that by this means the heart having need of less force to con-<lb break="no"/>tinue its functions, we may weaken it by the destruction of<lb break="yes"/>the cervical marrow, without its ceasing to perform them. It<lb break="yes"/>is also easy to conceive that every other operation capable of<lb break="yes"/>suspending or considerably lessening the circulation in a cer-<lb break="no"/>tain extent of the body of an animal, must produce a similar<lb break="yes"/>effect, and afford an equal power of attacking without any<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="350" facs="#f0009"/> immediately fatal effects, a portion of the spinal marrow, the<lb break="yes"/>destruction of which would have been mortal without that<lb break="yes"/>preliminary.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>This is what is obtained by the effect itself of destruction<lb break="yes" />of the marrow. This destruction has two effects on the cir-<lb break="no" />culation: By the one it weakens the general circulation, by<lb break="yes" />depriving the heart of the contingent powers it received from<lb break="yes"/>the marrow destroyed; by the other, without entirely arrest-<lb break="no"/>ing the circulation in the dead parts, it there diminishes it to<lb break="yes"/>a very great degree, so as to be to a certain point, equivalent<lb break="yes"/>to ligatures on the arteries of the parts.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>But this effect does not plainly appear for many minutes<lb break="yes" />after the destruction of the marrow. Thence it happens that<lb break="yes" />the destruction of a first portion of the spinal marrow affords<lb break="yes"/>the means of destroying a second, this of a third, and so on.<lb break="yes"/>For instance, when, in beheading a rabbit of any age whatev-<lb break="no"/>er, we are enabled to destroy the cervical marrow, the des-<lb break="no"/>truction of this marrow will, in a certain number of minutes,<lb break="yes"/>enable us to destroy the quarter of the dorsal marrow, and<lb break="yes"/>by continuing to operate thus at intervals on equal lengths of<lb break="yes"/>this same marrow, we at last succeed in destroying it entirely<lb break="yes"/>without arresting the circulation, which is then kept up by<lb break="yes"/>the lumbar marrow only.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We may gather from what we have said, that in rabbits any<lb break="yes" />portion of the spinal marrow furnishes the heart with force<lb break="yes" />sufficient to keep up the circulation in all the parts that cor-<lb break="no"/>respond with this portion, and that consequently, if we were<lb break="yes"/>to cut a rabbit transversely, into several pieces, each piece<lb break="yes"/>might be made to live although insolated, if the lungs and<lb break="yes"/>heart, necessary to the formation and circulation of the ar-<lb break="no"/>terial blood, could be included in the piece. But these can<lb break="yes"/>only form a part of the thorax; we might therefore very easi-<lb break="no"/>ly support life in the thorax alone, after having separated it<lb break="yes"/>from the rest of the body, and prevented hemorrhage by pro-<lb break="no"/>per ligatures, and this would be the case in rabbits of thirty<lb break="yes"/>days and upwards.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="351" facs="#f0010"/>
                    <p>Such are the principle results of M. Legallois’s investi-<lb break="no" />gations. These results, which have a mutual dependance on<lb break="yes" />each other, are founded on direct experiments, performed<lb break="yes" />with a degree of accuracy hitherto unknown in physiology.<lb break="yes" />The author, say the committee, has repeated them in our pre-<lb break="no" />sence; we have spent three sittings, each of several hours, in<lb break="yes"/>examining them, and to avoid all precipitation, as well as to<lb break="yes"/>give ourselves time to weigh all the facts at leisure, we have<lb break="yes"/>suffered the interval of a week to pass between each session.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>All the experiments which were repeated before the com-<lb break="no"/>mittee are ranked, in the report, under two heads. One of<lb break="yes"/>which contains those that go to prove that the <hi rendition="#i">primum mobile</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>of all the inspiratory motions resides in that part of the me-<lb break="no"/>dulla ablongata which gives origin to the nerves of the eighth<lb break="yes"/>pair. The other contains those whose object is to shew that<lb break="yes"/>the principle of the powers of the heart is in the spinal mar-<lb break="no"/>row. As these details, however interesting, are too long to<lb break="yes"/>be inserted here, we shall only say that the author has made<lb break="yes"/>similar experiments on warm blooded and cold blooded ani-<lb break="no"/>mals, and it is astonishing to observe the uniformity which<lb break="yes"/>experiments made on animals so different, offer in the results,<lb break="yes"/>even with regard to the principle of the inspiratory motions.<lb break="yes"/>It is well known, that it was particularly after experiments<lb break="yes"/>made on frogs that the followers of Haller, and among others<lb break="yes"/>Fontana had maintained that the motions of the heart were<lb break="yes"/>independant of the nervous power. But experiments re-<lb break="no"/>peated with the greatest care on the same animals before the<lb break="yes"/>committee, demonstrated at once the inacuracy of this opin-<lb break="no"/>ion, and of the experiments on which it was founded. The<lb break="yes"/>gentlemen of the committee conclude the recital of the ex-<lb break="no"/>periments repeated before them, by declaring that they com-<lb break="no"/>pletely confirmed all the results above mentioned, and by<lb break="yes"/>adopting all the conclusions which the author has deduced<lb break="yes"/>from them.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>They then continue in these words:</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>That we may here confine ourselves to the principle points<lb break="yes"/>we will say what we consider as demonstrated.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="352" facs="#f0011"/>
                    <p>1st. That the principle of all inspiratory motions has its<lb break="yes" />seat in that part of the <hi rendition="#i">medulla ablongata</hi> which gives origin<lb break="yes"/>to the nerves of the eighth pair.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>2d. That the principle which animates each part of the<lb break="yes"/>body resides in that part of the spinal marrow whence arise<lb break="yes"/>the nerves of that part.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>3d. That it is, in like manner the spinal marrow which fur-<lb break="no" />nishes the principle of life and action; but in this the spinal<lb break="yes"/>marrow is throughout concerned, and not a particular portion<lb break="yes"/>of it.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>4th. That the great sympathetic has its origin in the spi-<lb break="no"/>nal marrow and that the particular function of this nerve is<lb break="yes"/>to bring all the parts to which it is distributed under the im-<lb break="no" />mediate influence of all the nervous power.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>These results easily solve all the difficulties that have sprung<lb break="yes"/>up since the days of Haller, on the causes of the motions of<lb break="yes"/>the heart. The principle of these were, to explain for what<lb break="yes"/>purpose the heart receives nerves, why it is submitted to the<lb break="yes"/>empire of the passions; and why the circulation continues in<lb break="yes"/>acephalous animals and such as have been beheaded. No<lb break="yes"/>explication hitherto given was sufficient to reconcile all these<lb break="yes"/>points. But at present we can easily conceive why the heart<lb break="yes"/>receives nerves; and why it is so evidently subject to the em-<lb break="no"/>pire of the passions, since it is animated by the whole of the<lb break="yes"/>spinal marrow. We may also see that when the circulation<lb break="yes"/>continues in acephalous animals, &amp;c. it is because the motions<lb break="yes"/>of the heart do not depend on the brain, or at most depend<lb break="yes"/>on it but secondarily.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We ought to remark that this last point, on which M. Le-<lb break="no" />gallois has thrown so much light, presents nothing but confu-<lb break="no"/>sion and error in the authors of the Hallerian, as well as of<lb break="yes"/>the new school. None of them have distinguished the mo-<lb break="no"/>tions of the heart that take place after decapitation, from<lb break="yes"/>those that are observed after the excision of this organ, or<lb break="yes"/>after the destruction of the spinal marrow.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The committee next proceed to testify that M. Legallois<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="353" facs="#f0012"/> is indebted to his own industry and zeal for his success in<lb break="yes"/>these researches. They then conclude in these terms:</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>In a word, it appears to us that we may say of the different<lb break="yes" />authors who have considered the matters that M. Legallois has<lb break="yes"/>treated, what M. La Place so justly said on a like occasion.<lb break="yes"/>“One may find among them many facts, but these are almost<lb break="yes"/>always blended with numberless errors, and the discovery of<lb break="yes"/>the truth belongs only to him who separates it from the mass,<lb break="yes"/>and establishes it on a solid basis, by calculation or by ob-<lb break="no"/>servations.”</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The opinion of your committee is, that M. Legallois by<lb break="yes"/>the service he has done to physiology, merits all the encour-<lb break="no" />agement the class can afford him; and that his researches are<lb break="yes"/>of more importance to this branch of knowledge than any<lb break="yes"/>that have been made since the days of Haller.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <closer>
                        <salute>
                            <hi rendition="#et">(Signed,)<lb break="yes"/>DE HUMBOLT,<lb break="yes" />HALLE,<lb break="yes"/>PERCY.</hi>
                        </salute>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <p>The class approves of the report, and admits the conclusions<lb break="yes" />drawn in it.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The class moreover decrees that the report shall be printed<lb break="yes" />in the records of the class, and that a committee shall consult<lb break="yes"/>with M. Legallois with regard to the expense incurred by<lb break="yes"/>him for the experiments already made, and the means of con-<lb break="no"/>tinuing them.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#et">G. CUVIER,<lb break="yes"/>
                            <hi rendition="#i">Perpetual Secretary.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 