<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.1" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.1" when="2018-10-10" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung für Verlag.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="587" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">PERSONAL NARRATIVE<lb break="yes"/>OF TRAVELS<lb break="yes" />TO THE<lb break="yes"/>EQUINOCTIAL REGIONS<lb break="yes"/>OF THE</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#fr">New Continent,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>During the Years 1799&#x2014;1804.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#g">BY<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">ALEXANDER DE HUMBOLDT,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>AND<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">AIME BONPLAND;</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>WITH MAPS, PLANS,</hi> &amp;c.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Written in French by</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>ALEXANDER DE HUMBOLDT,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">And Translated into English</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">By</hi> HELEN MARIA WILLIAMS.<lb break="yes"/>In 2 vols. 8vo.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>[The jealous policy of the Spanish govern-<lb break="no"/>
                    <hi rendition="#et">ment having limited the travellers in its<lb break="yes" />American colonies to privileged natives<lb break="yes"/>of Spain, no parts of the world are less<lb break="yes"/>known than the vast regions composing<lb break="yes"/>those colonies; at the same time that<lb break="yes"/>no countries are more interesting to<lb break="yes" />naturalists, geologists, and philosophers.<lb break="yes"/>It would be superfluous to describe<lb break="yes"/>the superior pretensions of M. <hi rendition="#k">de Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt</hi> to gratify in the most ample<lb break="yes"/>manner the strongly-excited curiosity<lb break="yes"/>of the public on the various topics<lb break="yes"/>which these colonies present, his ar-<lb break="no"/>dour in the pursuit of science having<lb break="yes"/>commanded our repeated eulogies, and<lb break="yes"/>excited the admiration of all his <choice>
                            <sic>cotem-<lb break="no"/>poraries</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">contem-<lb break="no"/>poraries</corr>
                        </choice>. The extracts themselves will<lb break="yes"/>justify our taste in submitting so many<lb break="yes"/>of them to our readers.]</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">the author’s views.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">I</hi> HAD in view a double purpose in<lb break="yes"/>the travels, of which I now publish<lb break="yes"/>the historical narrative. I wished to<lb break="yes"/>make known the countries I had vi-<lb break="no" />sited; and to collect such facts as are<lb break="yes"/>fitted to elucidate a science, of which<lb break="yes"/>we have possessed scarcely the outline,<lb break="yes"/>and which has been vaguely denomi-<lb break="no"/>nated <hi rendition="#i">natural history of the world, theory<lb break="yes"/>of the Earth,</hi> or physical <hi rendition="#i">geography.</hi> The<lb break="yes"/>last of these two objects seemed to me<lb break="yes"/>the most important. I was passionate-<lb break="no"/>ly devoted to botany, and certain parts<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> of zoology, and I flattered myself that<lb break="yes"/>our investigations might add some new<lb break="yes"/>species to those which have been al-<lb break="no"/>ready described; but, preferring the<lb break="yes"/>connection of facts, which have been<lb break="yes"/>long observed, to the knowledge of in-<lb break="no"/>sulated facts, although they were new,<lb break="yes" />the discovery of an unknown genus<lb break="yes"/>seemed to me far less interesting than<lb break="yes"/>an observation on the geographical re-<lb break="no"/>lations of the vegetable world, on the<lb break="yes"/>migration of the social plants, and the<lb break="yes"/>limit of the height which their diffe-<lb break="no"/>rent tribes attain on the flanks of the<lb break="yes" />Cordilleras.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The natural sciences are connected<lb break="yes"/>by the same ties that link all the phe-<lb break="no"/>nomena of nature. The classification<lb break="yes"/>of the species which we ought to con-<lb break="no"/>sider as the fundamental part of bo-<lb break="no"/>tany, and the study of which is be-<lb break="no"/>come more attractive and more easy<lb break="yes"/>by the introduction of natural methods,<lb break="yes"/>is to the geography of plants, what<lb break="yes" />descriptive mineralogy is to the indi-<lb break="no"/>cation of the rocks which constitute<lb break="yes"/>the exterior crust of the globe. To<lb break="yes"/>comprehend the laws which are ob-<lb break="no"/>served in the position of these rocks,<lb break="yes"/>and determine the age of their succes-<lb break="no"/>sive formations, and their identity in<lb break="yes" />the most distant regions, the geologist<lb break="yes"/>ought to be previously acquainted with<lb break="yes"/>the simple fossils, which compose the<lb break="yes"/>mass of mountains, and of which the<lb break="yes"/>names and character are the object of<lb break="yes"/>oryctognostical knowledge. It is the<lb break="yes"/>same with that part of the natural his-<lb break="no" />tory of the globe, that treats of the rela-<lb break="no"/>lations the plants have to each other,<lb break="yes"/>with the soil whence they spring, or<lb break="yes"/>the air which they inhale and modify.<lb break="yes"/>The progress of the geography of<lb break="yes"/>plants depends in a great measure on<lb break="yes"/>that of descriptive botany; and it<lb break="yes"/>would be injurious to the advance-<lb break="no"/>ment of the sciences to attempt rising<lb break="yes"/>to general ideas, in neglecting the know-<lb break="no"/>ledge of particular facts.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Journeys by land are attended with<lb break="yes"/>considerable difficulty in the carriage<lb break="yes"/>of instruments and collections, but<lb break="yes" />these difficulties are compensated by<lb break="yes"/>real advantages, which it would be<lb break="yes"/>useless to enumerate. It is not by<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">sailing</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="588" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>sailing along the coast, that we can<lb break="yes"/>discover the direction of the chains of<lb break="yes"/>mountains, and their geological consti-<lb break="no"/>tution, the climate of each zone, and<lb break="yes"/>its influence on the forms and the ha-<lb break="no"/>bits of organized beings. In pro-<lb break="no"/>portion to the breadth of the conti-<lb break="no" />nents, the greater is the display on the<lb break="yes"/>surface of the soil, of the richness of<lb break="yes"/>the animal and vegetable productions;<lb break="yes"/>the more distant the central chain of<lb break="yes"/>mountains from the shores of the ocean,<lb break="yes"/>the greater variety we find, in the bo-<lb break="no"/>som of the earth, of those stony strata,<lb break="yes" />the regular succession of which unfolds<lb break="yes"/>to us the history of our planet. In the<lb break="yes"/>same manner, as every being consider-<lb break="no"/>ed apart is impressed with a particular<lb break="yes"/>type, we find the same impression in<lb break="yes"/>the arrangement of brute matter orga-<lb break="no"/>nized in rocks, in the distribution and<lb break="yes" />mutual relations of plants and animals.<lb break="yes"/>The great problem of the physical de-<lb break="no"/>scription of the globe, is the determi-<lb break="no"/>nation of the form of these types, the<lb break="yes"/>laws of their relations with each other,<lb break="yes"/>and the eternal ties which link the phe-<lb break="no"/>nomena of life, and those of inanimate<lb break="yes" />nature.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">his collections.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The maritime war, during our abode<lb break="yes"/>in America, having rendered the com-<lb break="no"/>munications with Europe very uncer-<lb break="no"/>tain, we found ourselves compelled, in<lb break="yes"/>order to diminish the chance of losses,<lb break="yes"/>to form three different collections. Of<lb break="yes"/>these, the first was embarked for Spain<lb break="yes"/>and France, the second for the United<lb break="yes"/>States and England, and the third,<lb break="yes"/>which was the most considerable, re-<lb break="no" />mained almost constantly under our<lb break="yes"/>eyes. Towards the close of our expe-<lb break="no"/>dition, this last collection formed forty-<lb break="maybe"/>two boxes, containing an herbal of six<lb break="yes"/>thousand equinoctial plants, seeds,<lb break="yes"/>shells, insects, and, what had hitherto<lb break="yes"/>never been brought to Europe, geolo-<lb break="no" />gical specimens from the Chimborazo,<lb break="yes"/>New Grenada, and the banks of the ri-<lb break="no"/>ver of the Amazons.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After the journey to the Orinoco<lb break="yes"/>we left a part of these objects at the<lb break="yes"/>island of Cuba, in order to take them<lb break="yes"/>on our return from Peru to Mexico.<lb break="yes"/>The rest followed us during the space<lb break="yes"/>of five years, on the chain of the<lb break="yes" />Andes, across New Spain, from the<lb break="yes"/>shores of the Pacific Ocean to the West<lb break="yes"/>Indian seas. The conveyance of these<lb break="yes" />objects, and the minute care they re-<lb break="no"/>quired, occasioned us such embarrass-<lb break="no"/>ments as would scarcely be conceived,<lb break="yes"/>by those even who have traversed the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> most uncultivated parts of Europe.<lb break="yes"/>Our progress was often retarded by the<lb break="yes"/>threefold necessity of dragging after<lb break="yes"/>us, during expeditions of five or six<lb break="yes"/>months, twelve, fifteen, and some-<lb break="no"/>times more than twenty loaded mules,<lb break="yes"/>exchanging these animals every eight<lb break="yes" />or ten days, and superintending the<lb break="yes"/>Indians who were employed in leading<lb break="yes"/>so numerous a caravan. Often, in or-<lb break="no" />der to add to our collections of new<lb break="yes"/>mineral substances, we found ourselves<lb break="yes"/>obliged to throw away others, which<lb break="yes"/>we had collected a considerable time<lb break="yes"/>before. These sacrifices were not less<lb break="yes"/>painful than the losses which we acci-<lb break="no"/>dentally made. Sad experience taught<lb break="yes" />us, but too late, that, from the sultry<lb break="yes"/>humidity of the climate, and the fre-<lb break="no"/>quent falls of the beasts of burden, we<lb break="yes"/>could preserve neither the skins of<lb break="yes"/>animals too hastily prepared, nor the<lb break="yes"/>fishes and reptiles placed in phials<lb break="yes"/>filled with alcohol. I have thought<lb break="yes" />proper to enter into these details,<lb break="yes"/>which, although little interesting in<lb break="yes"/>themselves, prove that we had no<lb break="yes" />means of bringing back, in their natu-<lb break="no"/>ral state, many objects of zoology and<lb break="yes"/>comparative anatomy, of which we<lb break="yes" />have published descriptions and draw-<lb break="no"/>ings. Notwithstanding some obstacles<lb break="yes"/>and the expense occasioned by the car-<lb break="no"/>riage of these articles, I had reason to<lb break="yes"/>applaud the resolution I had taken be-<lb break="no"/>fore my departure, of sending to Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope the duplicates only of the produc-<lb break="no" />tions we had collected. I cannot too<lb break="yes"/>often repeat, that, when the seas are<lb break="yes"/>infested with privateers, a traveller<lb break="yes"/>can be sure only of the objects in his<lb break="yes"/>own possession. A very small num-<lb break="no"/>ber of the duplicates, which we ship-<lb break="no"/>ped for the ancient continent during<lb break="yes" />our abode in America, were saved;<lb break="yes"/>the greater part fell into the hands of<lb break="yes"/>persons unknown to science. When a<lb break="yes" />ship is condemned in a foreign part,<lb break="yes"/>boxes containing only dried plants or<lb break="yes"/>stones, far from being sent to the<lb break="yes"/>scientific men to whom they are ad-<lb break="no"/>dressed, remain consigned to oblivion.<lb break="yes"/>Some of our geological collections<lb break="yes"/>taken in the Southern Ocean had,<lb break="yes" />however, a happier fate. We were<lb break="yes"/>indebted for their preservation to the<lb break="yes"/>generous activity of Sir Joseph Banks,<lb break="yes"/>President of the Royal Society of Lon-<lb break="no"/>don, who, amidst the political agita-<lb break="no"/>tions of Europe, has unceasingly la-<lb break="no"/>boured to strengthen the ties by<lb break="yes"/>which are united the scientific of all<lb break="yes"/>nations.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">
                    <hi rendition="#g">CURRENTS</hi>
                </fw>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="589" facs="#f0003"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">currents of the atlantic.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The 9th of June, latitude 39° 50′,<lb break="yes"/>and longitude 16° 10′ west of the me-<lb break="no"/>ridian of the observatory of Paris, we<lb break="yes" />began to feel the effects of the great<lb break="yes"/>current, which from the Azores directs<lb break="yes"/>itself towards the straits of Gibraltar,<lb break="yes"/>and the Canary Islands. Comparing<lb break="yes"/>the place of our ship deduced from<lb break="yes"/>Berthoud’s time-keeper with the pilot’s<lb break="yes"/>reckoning, I was able to discover the<lb break="yes"/>smallest variations in the direction and<lb break="yes"/>velocity of the currents. From 37° to<lb break="yes"/>30° of latitude, the vessel was some-<lb break="no" />times carried, in twenty-four hours,<lb break="yes"/>from eighteen to twenty-six miles to<lb break="yes"/>the east. The direction of the cur-<lb break="no"/>rent was at first E. by S. but nearer<lb break="yes"/>the straits it became due east. Capt.<lb break="yes"/>Mackintosh, and one of the most dis-<lb break="no"/>tinguished navigators of our time, Sir<lb break="yes" />Erasmus Gower, have noticed the mo-<lb break="no"/>difications of this movement of the wa-<lb break="no"/>ters at different seasons of the year.<lb break="yes"/>Several pilots who frequent the Cana-<lb break="no"/>ry Islands have found themselves on<lb break="yes"/>the coasts of Lancerotte, when they<lb break="yes"/>expected to make good their landing<lb break="yes"/>on the Isle of Teneriffe. M. de Bou-<lb break="no"/>gainville, in his passage from Cape<lb break="yes"/>Finisterre to the Canary Islands, found<lb break="yes"/>himself in sight of the Isle of<lb break="yes"/>Ferro, 4° more to the east than his<lb break="yes"/>reckoning indicated.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The current which is felt between<lb break="yes"/>the Azores, the southern coasts of<lb break="yes"/>Portugal, and the Canary Islands, is<lb break="yes" />commonly attributed to that tendency<lb break="yes"/>towards the east, which the straits of<lb break="yes"/>Gibraltar impress on the waters of<lb break="yes" />the Atlantic Ocean. M. de Fleurieu,<lb break="yes"/>in notes added to the voyage of Capt.<lb break="yes"/>Marchant, observes even that the Me-<lb break="no"/>diterranean losing, by evaporation,<lb break="yes"/>more water than the rivers can supply,<lb break="yes"/>causes a movement in the neighbour-<lb break="no"/>ing ocean, and that the influence of<lb break="yes"/>the Straits is felt at the distance of six<lb break="yes" />hundred leagues. Without deroga-<lb break="no"/>ting from the sentiments of esteem<lb break="yes"/>which I owe to this celebrated navi-<lb break="no" />gator, from whose works I have de-<lb break="no"/>rived much instruction, I may be per-<lb break="no"/>mitted to consider this important ob-<lb break="no" />ject in a far more general point of<lb break="yes"/>view.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When we cast our eyes over the At-<lb break="no"/>lantic, or that deep valley which di-<lb break="no"/>vides the western coasts of Europe and<lb break="yes" />Africa from the eastern coasts of the<lb break="yes"/>new continent, we distinguish a con-<lb break="no"/>trary direction in the motion of the<lb break="yes"/>waters. <hi rendition="#i">Between the tropics, especially</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">from the coasts of Senegal to the Caribbean<lb break="yes" />sea, the general current, that which was<lb break="yes"/>earliest known to mariners, flows constantly<lb break="yes"/>from east to west.</hi> This is called the<lb break="yes"/>equinoctial current. Its mean rapi-<lb break="no" />dity, corresponding to different lati-<lb break="no"/>tudes, <hi rendition="#i">is nearly the same in the Atlantic<lb break="yes"/>and in the Southern Ocean,</hi> and may be<lb break="yes"/>estimated at nine or ten miles in twen-<lb break="no"/>ty four hours, consequently from 0.59<lb break="yes"/>to 0.65 of a foot every second! In<lb break="yes"/>those latitudes the waters run towards<lb break="yes"/>the west, with a velocity equal to a<lb break="yes"/>fourth of the rapidity of the greater<lb break="yes"/>part of the large rivers of Europe.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">The movement of the ocean, in a direction<lb break="yes" />contrary to that of the rotation of the globe,<lb break="yes"/>is probably connected <choice>
                            <sic>wtth</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">with</corr>
                        </choice> this last phenome-<lb break="no"/>non, only as far as the rotation changes the<lb break="yes"/>polar winds, which, in the low regions of<lb break="yes"/>the atmosphere, bring back the cold air of<lb break="yes" />the high latitudes towards the equator, into<lb break="yes"/>trade winds. To this general impulsion,<lb break="yes"/>which these trade winds give the surface of<lb break="yes"/>the seas, we must attribute the equinoctial<lb break="yes"/>current, the force and rapidity of which are<lb break="yes" />not sensibly modified by the local variations<lb break="yes"/>of the atmosphere.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">the gulf stream.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The equinoctial current drives the<lb break="yes"/>waters of the Atlantic towards the<lb break="yes"/>coasts inhabited by the Mosquito In-<lb break="no" />dians, and towards those of Honduras.<lb break="yes"/>The New Continent, stretching from<lb break="yes"/>south to north, forms an obstruction<lb break="yes"/>to this current. The waters are car-<lb break="no"/>ried at first to the north-west, and, pass-<lb break="no"/>ing into the gulf of Mexico through<lb break="yes"/>the strait which is formed by False<lb break="yes" />Cape and Cape St. Antonio, follow the<lb break="yes"/>bendings of the Mexican coast, from<lb break="yes"/>Vera Cruz to the mouth of the Rio<lb break="yes" />del Norte, and thence to the mouths<lb break="yes"/>of the Mississippi, and the shoals to<lb break="yes"/>the west of the southern extremity of<lb break="yes"/>Florida. Having made this vast cir-<lb break="no"/>cuit to the west, the north, the east,<lb break="yes"/>and the south, the current takes a new<lb break="yes"/>direction towards the north, and<lb break="yes"/>throws itself with impetuosity into<lb break="yes"/>the Gulf of Florida. I there ob-<lb break="no"/>served, in the month of May, 1804, in<lb break="yes"/>the 26th and 27th degrees of latitude,<lb break="yes"/>a celerity of eighty miles in twenty-<lb break="maybe"/>four hours, or five feet every second,<lb break="yes" />though at this period the north wind<lb break="yes"/>blew with great violence. At the end<lb break="yes"/>of the Gulf of Florida, in the parallel<lb break="yes"/>of Cape Cannaveral, the Gulf-stream,<lb break="yes"/>or current of Florida, runs to the<lb break="yes"/>north-east. Its rapidity resembles that<lb break="yes"/>of a torrent, and is sometimes five miles<lb break="yes"/>an hour. The pilot may judge, with<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">some</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="590" facs="#f0004"/>
                    <cb/>some certainty, of the error of his<lb break="yes"/>reckoning, and of the proximity of his<lb break="yes"/>approach toward New York, Philadel-<lb break="no"/>phia, or Charles-town, when he reaches<lb break="yes"/>the edge of the stream; for the ele-<lb break="no"/>vated temperature of their waters,<lb break="yes"/>their strong saltness, indigo-blue co-<lb break="no"/>lour, and the shoals of sea weed which<lb break="yes"/>cover the surface, as well as the heat<lb break="yes"/>of the surrounding atmosphere, sensi-<lb break="no" />ble even in winter, all indicate the<lb break="yes"/>Gulf-stream. Its rapidity diminishes<lb break="yes"/>towards the north, at the same time<lb break="yes"/>that its breadth increases, and the wa-<lb break="no"/>ters cool. Between Cayo Biscaino and<lb break="yes"/>the bank of Bahama, the breadth is<lb break="yes"/>only 15 leagues, whilst in the latitude<lb break="yes" />of 28 degrees and a half it is 17, and<lb break="yes"/>in the parallel of Charles-town, oppo-<lb break="no"/>site Cape Henlopen, from 40 to 50<lb break="yes"/>leagues. The rapidity of the current<lb break="yes"/>is from three to five miles an hour,<lb break="yes"/>where the stream is the narrowest, and<lb break="yes"/>is only one mile as it advances towards<lb break="yes" />the north. The waters of the Mexican<lb break="yes"/>Gulf, forcibly drawn to the north-east,<lb break="yes"/>preserve their warm temperature to<lb break="yes"/>such a point, that at 40 and 41 degrees<lb break="yes"/>of latitude I found them at 22.5°<lb break="yes"/>(18° R.), when, out of the current,<lb break="yes"/>the heat of the ocean at its surface was<lb break="yes"/>scarcely 17.5° (14° R.). In the parallel<lb break="yes"/>of New York and Oporto, the tempera-<lb break="no"/>ture of the Gulf-stream is consequent-<lb break="no"/>ly equal to that of the seas of the tro-<lb break="no"/>pics in the 18th degree of latitude; as,<lb break="yes"/>for instance, in the parallel of Porto<lb break="yes"/>Rico, and the islands of Cape Verd.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>To the east of the port of Boston,<lb break="yes"/>and on the meridian of Halifax, under<lb break="yes"/>41° 25′ of latitude, and 67° of longi-<lb break="no"/>tude, the current is near 80 leagues<lb break="yes"/>broad. From this point it turns sud-<lb break="no"/>denly to the east, so that its west-<lb break="no"/>ern edge, as it bends, becomes the<lb break="yes"/>western limit of the running waters,<lb break="yes"/>skirting the extremity of the great<lb break="yes"/>bank of Newfoundland, which Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Volney ingeniously calls the bar of the<lb break="yes"/>mouth of this enormous sea river.<lb break="yes"/>The cold waters of this bank, which<lb break="yes" />according to my experiments are at the<lb break="yes"/>temperature of 8.7° or 10° (7° or 8°<lb break="yes"/>R.) present a striking contrast with<lb break="yes"/>the waters of the torrid zone, driven<lb break="yes"/>to the north by the Gulf-stream, the<lb break="yes"/>temperature of which is from 21° to<lb break="yes"/>22.5° (7° to 8° R.)<choice><sic></sic><corr type="editorial">.</corr></choice></p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From the bank of Newfoundland, or<lb break="yes"/>from the 52d degree of longitude to<lb break="yes"/>the Azores, the Gulf-stream <hi rendition="#i" >continues<lb break="yes"/>its course towards the east, and the east-<lb break="no"/>south-east.</hi> The waters still preserve a<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>part of the impulsion they have re-<lb break="no"/>ceived near a thousand leagues dis-<lb break="no"/>tance, in the straits of Florida, be-<lb break="no" />tween the Isle of Cuba, and the shoals<lb break="yes"/>of Tortoise Island. This distance is<lb break="yes"/>double the length of the course of the<lb break="yes"/>river of the Amazons, from Jaen, or<lb break="yes"/>the Straits of Manseriche, to Grand-<lb break="maybe"/>Para. On the meridian of the isles of<lb break="yes"/>Corvo and Flores, the most western of<lb break="yes"/>the group of the Azores, the breadth of<lb break="yes"/>the current is 160 leagues. When ves-<lb break="no"/>sels, on their return from South Ame-<lb break="no" />rica to Europe, endeavour to make<lb break="yes"/>these two islands to rectify their longi-<lb break="no"/>tudes, they constantly perceive the<lb break="yes" />motion of the waters to the south-east.<lb break="yes"/>At the 33d degree of latitude the equi-<lb break="no"/>noctial current of the tropics is in the<lb break="yes"/>near vicinity of the Gulf-stream. In<lb break="yes"/>this part of the ocean we may in a sin-<lb break="no"/>gle day pass from waters that flow<lb break="yes"/>towards the west, into those which<lb break="yes"/>run to the south-east or east-south-east.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From the Azores the current of Flo-<lb break="no"/>rida turns towards the Straits of Gib-<lb break="no"/>raltar, the Isle of Madeira, and the<lb break="yes" />group of the Canary Islands. The<lb break="yes"/>opening of the pillars of Hercules has<lb break="yes"/>no doubt accelerated the motion of the<lb break="yes"/>waters towards the east.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We may in this point of view assert,<lb break="yes"/>that the strait, by which the Mediter-<lb break="no"/>ranean communicates with the Atlan-<lb break="no" />tic, produces its effects at a great dis-<lb break="no"/>tance; but it is probable also that<lb break="yes"/>without the assistance of this strait the<lb break="yes"/>vessels which sail to Teneriff would be<lb break="yes"/>driven to the south-east by a cause,<lb break="yes"/>which we must seek on the coasts of<lb break="yes"/>the New World. Every motion is the<lb break="yes"/>cause of another motion in the vast<lb break="yes"/>basin of the seas, as well as in the<lb break="yes"/>aerial ocean. Pursuing the currents<lb break="yes"/>to their most distant sources, and re-<lb break="no"/>flecting on their variable celerity,<lb break="yes"/>sometimes decreasing, as between the<lb break="yes"/>Gulf of Florida and the bank of New-<lb break="no"/>foundland; at other times augmenting,<lb break="yes"/>as in the neighbourhood of the Straits of<lb break="yes"/>Gibraltar, and near the Canary Islands,<lb break="yes"/>we cannot doubt but the same cause<lb break="yes"/>which drives the waters to make the<lb break="yes"/>circuitous sweep of the Gulf of Mexi-<lb break="no"/>co, agitates them also near the Isle<lb break="yes"/>of Madeira.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">velocity of the currents.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Between the parallels of 11 and 43<lb break="yes"/>degrees, the waters of the Atlantic are<lb break="yes"/>drawn by the currents into a continual<lb break="yes"/>whirlpool. Supposing that a particle<lb break="yes"/>of water returns to the same place<lb break="yes"/>from which it departed, we can esti-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">mate,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="591" facs="#f0005"/>
                    <cb/> mate, from our present knowledge of<lb break="yes"/>the swiftness of the currents, that its cir-<lb break="no"/>cuit of 3800 leagues is not terminated<lb break="yes"/>in less than two years and ten months.<lb break="yes"/>A boat, which may be supposed to re-<lb break="no"/>ceive no impulsion from the winds,<lb break="yes"/>would require thirteen months from<lb break="yes" />the Canary islands to reach the coasts<lb break="yes"/>of Carracas, ten months to make the<lb break="yes"/>tour of the gulf of Mexico and reach<lb break="yes" />Tortoise Shoals opposite the port of<lb break="yes"/>the Havannah, while forty or fifty days<lb break="yes"/>might be sufficient to carry it from the<lb break="yes"/>straits of Florida to the bank of New-<lb break="no" />foundland. It would be difficult to<lb break="yes"/>fix the rapidity of the retrograde cur-<lb break="no"/>rent from this bank to the coasts of<lb break="yes"/>Africa; estimating the mean velocity<lb break="yes"/>of the waters at seven or eight miles<lb break="yes"/>in twenty-four hours, we find ten or<lb break="yes"/>eleven months for this last distance.<lb break="yes" />Such are the effects of this slow but<lb break="yes"/>regular motion, which agitates the wa-<lb break="no"/>ters of the ocean. Those of the river<lb break="yes"/>of the Amazons take nearly forty-five<lb break="yes"/>days to flow from Tomependa to Grand<lb break="yes"/>Para.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">recorded phenomena.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In 1770 a small vessel laden with<lb break="yes"/>corn, and bound from the Island of<lb break="yes"/>Lancerotte to Santa Cruz, in Teneriff,<lb break="yes" />was driven to sea, while none of the<lb break="yes"/>crew were on board. The motion of<lb break="yes"/>the waters from east to west carried it<lb break="yes" />to America, where it went on shore at<lb break="yes"/>La Guayra, near Carracas.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Whilst the art of navigation was yet<lb break="yes"/>in its infancy, the gulf-stream furnish-<lb break="no"/>ed the genius of Christopher Columbus<lb break="yes"/>with certain indications of the existence<lb break="yes"/>of western regions. Two corpses, the<lb break="yes"/>features of which indicated a race of<lb break="yes"/>unknown men, were thrown on the coasts<lb break="yes" />of the Azores, towards the end of the<lb break="yes"/>15th century. Nearly at the same period,<lb break="yes"/>the brother-in-law of Columbus, Peter<lb break="yes"/>Correa, governor of Porto Santo, found<lb break="yes"/>on the strand of this island pieces of<lb break="yes"/>bamboo of an extraordinary size,<lb break="yes"/>brought thither by the western cur-<lb break="no" />rents. These corpses and the bamboos<lb break="yes"/>attracted the attention of the Genoese<lb break="yes"/>navigator, who conjectured that both<lb break="yes"/>came from a continent <choice>
                        <sic>situate</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">situated</corr>
                    </choice> towards<lb break="yes"/>the west; we know at present that in<lb break="yes"/>the torrid zone the trade-winds and the<lb break="yes"/>current of the tropics are in opposition<lb break="yes"/>to every motion of the waves in the di-<lb break="no"/>rection of the earth’s rotation. The<lb break="yes" />productions of the new world cannot<lb break="yes"/>reach the old but by the very high la-<lb break="no"/>titudes, and in following the direction<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>of the current of Florida. The fruit<lb break="yes"/>of several trees of the Antilles are of-<lb break="no"/>ten thrown on the coasts of the Isle of<lb break="yes"/>Ferro and Gomera. Before the disco-<lb break="no"/>very of America the Canarians consi-<lb break="no"/>dered these fruits as coming from the<lb break="yes"/>enchanted isle of St. Borondon, which,<lb break="yes" />according to the reveries of the pilots,<lb break="yes"/>and certain legends, was placed to-<lb break="no"/>wards the west in an unknown part of<lb break="yes"/>the ocean, buried, as was supposed, in<lb break="yes"/>eternal fogs.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The arm of the Gulf-stream, which<lb break="yes"/>in the 45th and 50th degrees of lati-<lb break="no"/>tude, runs from the south-west to the<lb break="yes" />north-east towards the coasts of Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope, deposits every year on the western<lb break="yes"/>coasts of Ireland and Norway the fruit<lb break="yes"/>of trees, which belong to the torrid<lb break="yes"/>zone of America. On the shores of<lb break="yes"/>the Hebrides we collect seeds of mi-<lb break="no"/>mosa scandens, of dolichos urens, of<lb break="yes" />guilandina bonduc, and several other<lb break="yes"/>plants of Jamaica, the isle of Cuba,<lb break="yes"/>and of the neighbouring continent.<lb break="yes" />The current carries thither also bar-<lb break="no"/>rels of French wine, well preserved,<lb break="yes"/>the remains of the cargoes of vessels<lb break="yes"/>wrecked in the West Indian seas. To<lb break="yes"/>these examples of the distant migra-<lb break="no"/>tion of the vegetable world, others no<lb break="yes"/>less striking may be added. The<lb break="yes"/>wreck of an English vessel, the Til-<lb break="no"/>bury, burnt near Jamaica, was found<lb break="yes"/>on the coasts of Scotland. On these<lb break="yes" />same coasts various kinds of tortoises<lb break="yes"/>are sometimes found, that inhabit the<lb break="yes"/>waters of the Antilles. When the<lb break="yes" />western winds are of long duration, a<lb break="yes"/>current is formed in the high latitudes,<lb break="yes"/>which runs directly towards the east-<lb break="maybe"/>south-east, from the coasts of Green-<lb break="no"/>land and Labrador, as far as the north<lb break="yes"/>of Scotland. Wallace relates, that<lb break="yes"/>twice, in 1682 and 1684, American<lb break="yes" />savages of the race of the Esquimaux,<lb break="yes"/>driven out to sea in their leathern ca-<lb break="no"/>noes, during a storm, and left to the<lb break="yes"/>guidance of the currents, reached the<lb break="yes"/>Orcades. This last example is so much<lb break="yes"/>the more worthy of attention, as it<lb break="yes"/>proves at the same time how, at a pe-<lb break="no"/>riod when the art of navigation was<lb break="yes"/>yet in its infancy, the motion of the<lb break="yes"/>waters of the ocean would contribute<lb break="yes"/>to disseminate the different races of<lb break="yes"/>men over the face of the globe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">the causes of currents.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In reflecting on the causes of the<lb break="yes"/>currents, we find that they are much<lb break="yes"/>more numerous than is generally be-<lb break="no" />lieved; for the waters of the sea may<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">be</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="592" facs="#f0006"/>
                    <cb/>be put in motion by an external im-<lb break="no"/>pulse, by a difference in heat and salt-<lb break="no"/>ness, by the periodical melting of the<lb break="yes"/>polar ice, or by the inequality of the<lb break="yes" />evaporation, which takes place in dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent latitudes. Sometimes several<lb break="yes"/>of these causes concur to the same ef-<lb break="no"/>fect, and sometimes they produce ef-<lb break="no"/>fects that are contrary. Winds that<lb break="yes"/>are light, but which, like the trade<lb break="yes"/>winds, are continually acting on the<lb break="yes"/>whole of a zone, cause a real move-<lb break="no"/>ment of transition, which we do not<lb break="yes"/>observe in the heaviest tempests, be-<lb break="no"/>cause these last are circumscribed<lb break="yes"/>within a small space. When, in a<lb break="yes"/>great mass of water, the particles<lb break="yes"/>placed at the surface acquire a different<lb break="yes"/>specific gravity, a superficial current is<lb break="yes"/>formed, which takes its direction to-<lb break="no" />wards the point where the water is<lb break="yes"/>coldest, or that which is most satu-<lb break="no"/>rated with muriat of soda, sulphat of<lb break="yes" />lime, and with muriate or sulphate of<lb break="yes"/>magnesia. In the seas of the tropics<lb break="yes"/>we find that at great depths the ther-<lb break="no" />mometer marks 7 or 8 centesimal de-<lb break="no"/>grees. Such is the result of the nu-<lb break="no"/>merous experiments of Commodore<lb break="yes"/>Ellis and of M. Peron. The tempe-<lb break="no"/>rature of the air in those latitudes being<lb break="yes"/>never below 19 or 20 degrees, it is not<lb break="yes" />at the surface that the waters can have<lb break="yes"/>acquired a degree of cold so near the<lb break="yes"/>point of congelation, and of the maxi-<lb break="no"/>mum of the density of water. The<lb break="yes"/>existence of this cold strata in the low<lb break="yes"/>latitudes is an evident proof of the ex-<lb break="no"/>istence of an inferior current, which<lb break="yes" />runs from the poles towards the equa-<lb break="no"/>tor; it also proves that the saline sub-<lb break="no"/>stances, which alter the specific gra-<lb break="no"/>vity of the water, are distributed in the<lb break="yes"/>ocean, so as not to annihilate the effect<lb break="yes"/>produced by the differences of tempe-<lb break="no"/>rature.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In fact, if the mean saltness of the<lb break="yes"/>sea was 0.005 greater under the equa-<lb break="no"/>tor than in the temperate zone, as se-<lb break="no" />veral naturalists pretend, a current at<lb break="yes"/>the bottom, from the equator towards<lb break="yes"/>the pole, would be the result: for<lb break="yes"/>0.005 produce a difference of density<lb break="yes"/>of 0.0017, while, according to the ta-<lb break="no"/>bles of Hallstrom, a refrigeration of 16<lb break="yes"/>centesimal degrees, between the 20th<lb break="yes"/>and 4th of temperature, causes only a<lb break="yes"/>change of 0.00015 in the specific gra-<lb break="no"/>vity. After attentive examination of<lb break="yes"/>the results of the experiments of Black,<lb break="yes" />reduced by Mr. Kirwan to the tempe-<lb break="no"/>rature of 16°, I find on the average<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> the density of the water of the<lb break="yes"/>sea,</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>from 0° to 14° latitude</cell>
                        <cell>at 1.0272</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>from 15° to 25°</cell>
                        <cell>1.0282</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>from 30° to 44°</cell>
                        <cell>0.0278</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>from 54° to 60°</cell>
                        <cell>1.0271</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The proportion of salt correspond-<lb break="no"/>ing to these four zones are, according<lb break="yes"/>to Bishop Watson, 0.0374, 0.0394,<lb break="yes" />0.0386, and 0.0372. Those numbers<lb break="yes"/>sufficiently prove that the experiments<lb break="yes"/>hitherto published do not in any way<lb break="yes"/>justify the renewed opinion, that the<lb break="yes"/>sea is <choice>
                        <sic>salter</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">saltier</corr>
                    </choice> under the equator than un-<lb break="no"/>der the 30th and 44th degrees of lati-<lb break="no"/>tude. It is not therefore a greater<lb break="yes"/>quantity of saline substance held in so-<lb break="no"/>lution, which opposes itself to this in-<lb break="no"/>ferior current, by which the equinoc-<lb break="no"/>tial ocean receives particles of water,<lb break="yes"/>which during the winter of the tempe-<lb break="no"/>rate zones have sunk towards the bot-<lb break="no"/>tom of the sea, from the 30th to the<lb break="yes"/>44th degree of southern and northern<lb break="yes" />latitude. Baume has analysed the sea-<lb break="no"/>water collected by M. Pagès in diffe-<lb break="no"/>rent latitudes, and found in this water<lb break="yes"/>0.005 less salt at 1° 16′ of latitude than<lb break="yes" />between the 25th and 40th degrees.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">falling meteors.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We were never wearied of admiring<lb break="yes"/>the beauty of the nights; nothing can<lb break="yes"/>be compared to the transparency and<lb break="yes" />serenity of an African sky. We were<lb break="yes"/>struck with the innumerable quantity<lb break="yes"/>of falling stars, which appeared at<lb break="yes"/>every instant. The farther progress<lb break="yes"/>we made towards the south the more<lb break="yes"/>frequent was this phenomenon, espe-<lb break="no"/>cially near the Canaries. I have ob-<lb break="no" />served during my excursions that these<lb break="yes"/>igneous meteors are in general more<lb break="yes"/>common and luminous in some regions<lb break="yes" />of the globe than in others; <hi rendition="#i">I have<lb break="yes"/>never beheld them so multiplied as in the vi-<lb break="no"/>cinity of the volcanoes of the province of<lb break="yes"/>Quito, and in the part of the Pacific Ocean<lb break="yes"/>which washes the volcanic coasts of Guati-<lb break="no"/>mala.</hi> The influence which place,<lb break="yes" />climate, and seasons, appear to have on<lb break="yes"/>the falling stars, distinguishes this<lb break="yes"/>class of meteors from those which give<lb break="yes"/>birth to stones that fall from the sky<lb break="yes" />(aerolites), and which probably exist<lb break="yes"/>beyond the boundaries of our atmos-<lb break="no"/>phere. According to the correspond-<lb break="no"/>ing observations of Messrs. Benzen-<lb break="no"/>berg and Brandes, <hi rendition="#i">many of the falling<lb break="yes"/>stars seen in Europe were only sixty thou-<lb break="no"/>sand yards high.</hi> One was even mea-<lb break="no"/>sured, which did not exceed twenty-<lb break="maybe"/>eight thousand yards, or fifteen miles.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">These</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="593" facs="#f0007"/>
                    <cb/>These measures, which can give no re-<lb break="no"/>sult but by approximation, deserve<lb break="yes"/>well to be repeated. In warm cli-<lb break="no"/>mates, especially under the tropics,<lb break="yes"/>the falling stars leave a tail behind<lb break="yes"/>them, which remains luminous 12 or<lb break="yes"/>16 seconds; at other times they seem<lb break="yes"/>to burst into sparks, and they are ge-<lb break="no"/>nerally lower than those in the north<lb break="yes"/>of Europe. We perceive them only<lb break="yes"/>in a serene and azure sky; they have<lb break="yes"/>perhaps never been seen below a cloud.<lb break="yes"/>Falling stars often follow the same di-<lb break="no" />rection for several hours, which di-<lb break="no"/>rection is then that of the wind. In<lb break="yes"/>the bay of Naples, M. Gay-Lussac and<lb break="yes" />myself observed luminous phenomena,<lb break="yes"/>very nearly analogous to those which<lb break="yes"/>fixed my attention during a long abode<lb break="yes"/>at Mexico and Quito. These meteors<lb break="yes"/>are perhaps modified by the nature of<lb break="yes"/>the soil and the air, like certain effects<lb break="yes"/>of the looming, and of the terrestrial<lb break="yes"/>refraction peculiar to the coasts of Ca-<lb break="no"/>labria and Sicily.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">flight of a swallow.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When we were forty leagues east of<lb break="yes"/>the island of Madeira, a common swal-<lb break="no"/>low came and perched on the topsail-<lb break="maybe" />yard. It was so fatigued that it suf-<lb break="no"/>fered itself to be easily taken. What<lb break="yes"/>could engage a bird, in that season,<lb break="yes" />and in calm weather, to fly so far? In<lb break="yes"/>the expedition of d’Entrecasteaux, a<lb break="yes"/>common swallow was seen at 60 leagues<lb break="yes"/>distance from Cape Blanc; but this<lb break="yes"/>was towards the end of October, and<lb break="yes"/>M. Labillardiere thought it had new-<lb break="no"/>ly arrived from Europe. We crossed<lb break="yes"/>these latitudes in June, at a period<lb break="yes"/>when the seas had not for a long time<lb break="yes"/>been agitated by tempests. I dwell<lb break="yes"/>on this last circumstance, because<lb break="yes"/>small birds, and even butterflies, are<lb break="yes"/>sometimes forced out to sea by the im-<lb break="no"/>petuosity of the winds, as we observed<lb break="yes"/>in the southern ocean, when we were<lb break="yes"/>on the western coasts of Mexico.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">apparent attraction.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As we were prevented by the fall of<lb break="yes"/>the wind, and by the currents, from<lb break="yes"/>repassing the channel of Alegranza,<lb break="yes"/>we resolved on tacking during the<lb break="yes"/>night between the Isle Clara and the<lb break="yes"/>West Rock. This resolution had<lb break="yes"/>nearly proved fatal. A calm is very<lb break="yes"/>dangerous near this last rock, towards<lb break="yes"/>which the current drives with con-<lb break="no"/>siderable force. We began to feel the<lb break="yes" />effects of this current at midnight. The<lb break="yes"/>proximity of the stony masses, which<lb break="yes"/>rise perpendicularly above the water,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>deprived us of the little wind which<lb break="yes"/>blew: the sloop no longer obeyed the<lb break="yes"/>helm, and we dreaded striking every<lb break="yes"/>instant. It is difficult to conceive how<lb break="yes"/>a mass of basalt, insulated in the vast<lb break="yes"/>expanse of the ocean, can cause so con-<lb break="no"/>siderable a motion in the waters.<lb break="yes"/>These phenomena, well worthy the<lb break="yes"/>attention of naturalists, are neverthe-<lb break="no"/>less well known to Mariners; they are<lb break="yes"/>extremely to be dreaded in the Pacific<lb break="yes"/>Ocean, particularly in the small Ar-<lb break="no"/>chipelago of the islands of Gallipagos.<lb break="yes"/>The difference of temperature which<lb break="yes"/>exists between the fluid and the mass<lb break="yes"/>of rocks cannot explain the direction<lb break="yes"/>which these currents take; and how<lb break="yes"/>can we admit that the water is engulf-<lb break="no"/>ed at the base of these rocks, which<lb break="yes"/>often are not of volcanic origin; and<lb break="yes"/>that this continual engulphing deter-<lb break="no" />mines the particles of water to fill up<lb break="yes"/>the vacuum that takes place?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">top of teneriffe.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Towards three in the morning, by<lb break="yes"/>the sombrous light of a few fir torches,<lb break="yes"/>we began our expedition for the sum-<lb break="no" />mit of the Piton. We scaled the vol-<lb break="no"/>cano on the north-east, where the de-<lb break="no"/>clivities are extremely steep; and we<lb break="yes"/>came, after two hours toil, to a small<lb break="yes"/>plain, which, on account of its isolated<lb break="yes"/>situation, bears the name of Alta Vis-<lb break="no"/>ta. It is the station also of the Neve-<lb break="no" />ros, those natives, whose occupation it<lb break="yes"/>is to collect ice and snow, which they<lb break="yes"/>sell in the neighbouring towns. Their<lb break="yes"/>mules, better practised in climbing<lb break="yes"/>mountains than those hired by travel-<lb break="no"/>lers, reach Alta Vista, and the Neve-<lb break="no"/>ros are obliged to transport the snow<lb break="yes" />to this place on their backs. Above<lb break="yes"/>this point the Malpays begins, a term<lb break="yes"/>by which is designated here, as well<lb break="yes"/>as in Mexico, Peru, and every other<lb break="yes"/>country subject to volcanoes, a ground<lb break="yes"/>destitute of vegetable mould, and co-<lb break="no"/>vered with fragments of lavas.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We observed during the twilight a<lb break="yes"/>phenomenon which is not unusual on<lb break="yes"/>high mountains, but which the posi-<lb break="no"/>tion of the volcano that we were<lb break="yes"/>scaling, rendered very striking. A<lb break="yes"/>layer of white and fleecy clouds con-<lb break="no" />cealed from us the sight of the ocean,<lb break="yes"/>and the lower region of the island.<lb break="yes"/>This layer did not appear above 1600<lb break="yes" />yards high; the clouds were so uni-<lb break="no"/>formly spread, and kept so perfect a<lb break="yes"/>level, that they wore the appearance<lb break="yes" />of a vast plain covered with snow.<lb break="yes"/>The colossal pyramid of the peak, the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">volcanic</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="594" facs="#f0008"/>
                    <cb/> volcanic summits of Lanzerota, of<lb break="yes"/>Fortaventura, and the isle of Palma,<lb break="yes"/>were like rocks amidst this vast sea of<lb break="yes"/>vapours, and their black tints were in<lb break="yes"/>fine contrast with the whiteness of the<lb break="yes"/>clouds.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I was anxious to make an exact ob-<lb break="no"/>servation of the instant of sun-rising<lb break="yes"/>at an elevation so considerable as that<lb break="yes"/>we had reached on the Peak of Tene-<lb break="no"/>riffe. No traveller furnished with in-<lb break="no"/>struments had as yet taken such an ob-<lb break="no"/>servation. I had a telescope and a<lb break="yes" />chronometer, of which I knew the<lb break="yes"/>great exactness. In the part <choice>
                        <sic>were</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">where</corr>
                    </choice> the<lb break="yes"/>sun was to appear the horizon was free<lb break="yes"/>from vapours. We perceived the up-<lb break="no"/>per limb at 4h 48′ 55″ apparent time,<lb break="yes"/>and, what is very remarkable, the first<lb break="yes"/>luminous point of the disc was found<lb break="yes" />immediately in contact with the limit<lb break="yes"/>of the horizon, consequently we saw<lb break="yes"/>the true horizon, that is to say, a part<lb break="yes"/>of the sea farther than 43 leagues. It<lb break="yes"/>is proved by calculation that, under<lb break="yes"/>the same parallel in the plain, the<lb break="yes"/>rising would have begun at 5h. 1′<lb break="yes" />50.4″ or 11′ 51.3″ later than at the<lb break="yes"/>height of the Peak. The difference<lb break="yes"/>observed was 12′ 55″, which arose no<lb break="yes"/>doubt from the uncertainty of the re-<lb break="no"/>fraction for a zenith distance, of which<lb break="yes"/>observations are wanting.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We had yet to scale the steepest<lb break="yes"/>part of the mountain, the Piton, which<lb break="yes"/>forms the summit. The slope of this<lb break="yes" />small cone, covered with volcanic<lb break="yes"/>ashes, and fragments of pumice stone,<lb break="yes"/>is so steep, that it would have been al-<lb break="no"/>most impossible to reach the top, had<lb break="yes"/>we not ascended by an old current of<lb break="yes"/>lava, the wrecks of which have resist-<lb break="no"/>ed the ravages of time. These wrecks<lb break="yes" />form a wall of scorious rocks, which<lb break="yes"/>stretches itself into the midst of the<lb break="yes"/>loose ashes. We ascended the Piton<lb break="yes" />by grasping these half decomposed<lb break="yes"/>scoriæ, the sharp edges of which re-<lb break="no"/>mained often in our hands. We em-<lb break="no"/>ployed nearly half an hour to scale a<lb break="yes"/>hill, the perpendicular height of which<lb break="yes"/>is scarcely 180 yards.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When we gained the summit of the<lb break="yes"/>Piton, we were surprised to find<lb break="yes"/>scarcely room enough to seat ourselves<lb break="yes" />conveniently. We were stopped by a<lb break="yes"/>small circular wall of porphyritic lava,<lb break="yes"/>with base of pitchstone, which con-<lb break="no"/>cealed from us the view of the crater.<lb break="yes"/>The west wind blew with such vio-<lb break="no"/>lence that we could scarcely stand.<lb break="yes"/>It was eight in the morning, and we<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>were frozen with the cold, though the<lb break="yes"/>thermometer kept a little above the<lb break="yes"/>freezing point.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The brink of the crater of the Peak<lb break="yes"/>bears no resemblance to those of the<lb break="yes"/>greater part of the other volcanoes<lb break="yes"/>which I have visited: for instance,<lb break="yes"/>the craters of Vesuvius, Jorullo, and<lb break="yes"/>Pichincha. In these the Piton pre-<lb break="no"/>serves its conic figure to the very<lb break="yes"/>summit: the whole of their declivity<lb break="yes"/>is inclined the same number of degrees,<lb break="yes"/>and uniformly covered with a layer of<lb break="yes"/>pumice stone, very minutely divided;<lb break="yes"/>when we reach the top of these vol-<lb break="no"/>canoes, nothing obstructs the view of<lb break="yes" />the bottom of the crater. The Peak<lb break="yes"/>of Teneriffe, and Cotopaxi, on the<lb break="yes"/>contrary, are of very different con-<lb break="no" />struction. At their summit a circular<lb break="yes"/>wall surrounds the crater; which wall<lb break="yes"/>at a distance, has the appearance of a<lb break="yes"/>small cylinder placed on a truncated<lb break="yes"/>cone. On Cotopaxi this peculiar con-<lb break="no"/>struction is visible to the naked eye<lb break="yes"/>at more than 2000 toises distance;<lb break="yes"/>and no person has ever reached the<lb break="yes"/>crater of this volcano. On the Peak<lb break="yes"/>of Teneriffe, the wall which surrounds<lb break="yes" />the crater like a parapet, is so high,<lb break="yes"/>that it would be impossible to reach<lb break="yes"/>the Caldera, if on the eastern side<lb break="yes"/>there was not a breach, which seems<lb break="yes"/>to have been the effect of a flowing of<lb break="yes"/>very old lava. We descended through<lb break="yes"/>this breach toward the bottom of the<lb break="yes" />funnel, the figure of which is elliptic.<lb break="yes"/>Its greater axis has a direction from<lb break="yes"/>north-west to south-east, nearly N.<lb break="yes"/>35° W. The greatest breadth of the<lb break="yes"/>mouth appeared to us to be 300 feet,<lb break="yes"/>the smallest 200 feet.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We descended to the bottom of the<lb break="yes"/>crater on a train of broken lava, from<lb break="yes"/>the eastern breach of the enclosure.<lb break="yes" />The heat was perceptible only in a few<lb break="yes"/>crevices, which gave vent to aqueous<lb break="yes"/>vapours with a peculiar buzzing noise.<lb break="yes"/>Some of these funnels or crevices are<lb break="yes"/>on the outside of the enclosure, on the<lb break="yes"/>external brink of the parapet that<lb break="yes"/>surrounds the crater. We plunged<lb break="yes"/>the thermometer into them, and saw<lb break="yes"/>it rise rapidly to 68 and 75 degrees. It<lb break="yes"/>no doubt indicated a higher tempera-<lb break="no" />ture, but we could not observe the<lb break="yes"/>instrument till we had drawn it up,<lb break="yes"/>lest we should burn our hands. M.<lb break="yes" />Cordier found several crevices, the<lb break="yes"/>heat of which was that of boiling water.<lb break="yes"/>It might be thought that these va-<lb break="no" />pours which are emitted in gusts,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">contain</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="595" facs="#f0009"/>
                    <cb/>contain muriatic or sulphurous acid;<lb break="yes"/>but, when condensed, they have no<lb break="yes"/>particular taste; and experiments,<lb break="yes" />which several naturalists have made<lb break="yes"/>with reagents, prove, that the chim-<lb break="no"/>neys of the Peak exhale only pure<lb break="yes" />water. This phænomenon, analogous<lb break="yes"/>to what I observed in the crater of<lb break="yes"/>Jorullo, deserves the more attention,<lb break="yes" />as muriatic acid abounds in the greater<lb break="yes"/>part of volcanoes, and as M. Vauquelin<lb break="yes"/>has discovered it even in the porphy-<lb break="no"/>ritic lavas of Sarcouy in Auvergne.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We prolonged in vain our stay on<lb break="yes"/>the summit of the Peak, to wait the<lb break="yes"/>moment when we might enjoy the<lb break="yes"/>view of the whole of the Archipelago<lb break="yes"/>of the Fortunate Islands. We disco-<lb break="no"/>vered Palma, Gomera, and the Great<lb break="yes" />Canary at our feet. The mountains of<lb break="yes"/>Lanzerota, free from vapours at sun-<lb break="no"/>rise, were soon enveloped in thick<lb break="yes" />clouds. On a supposition only of an<lb break="yes"/>ordinary refraction, the eye takes in,<lb break="yes"/>in calm weather, from the summit of<lb break="yes" />the volcano, a surface of the globe of<lb break="yes"/>5700 square leagues, equal to a fourth<lb break="yes"/>of the surface of Spain. The question<lb break="yes"/>has often been agitated, if it were<lb break="yes"/>possible to perceive the coast of<lb break="yes"/>Africa from the top of this colossal<lb break="yes"/>pyramid; but the nearest parts of this<lb break="yes"/>coast are still farther from Teneriffe<lb break="yes"/>than 2° 49′, or 56 leagues. The visual<lb break="yes"/>ray of the horizon from the peak being<lb break="yes" />1° 57′, Cape Bojador can be seen only<lb break="yes"/>on the supposition of its height being<lb break="yes"/>400 yards above the level of the<lb break="yes" />ocean.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We could not withdraw our eyes,<lb break="yes"/>on the summit of the Peak, from be-<lb break="no"/>holding the color of the azure vault<lb break="yes"/>of the sky. Its intensity at the zenith<lb break="yes"/>appeared to correspond to 41° of the<lb break="yes"/>cyanometer. We know by Saussure’s<lb break="yes" />experiment, that this intensity increases<lb break="yes"/>with the rarity of the air, and that the<lb break="yes"/>same instrument indicated at the same<lb break="yes"/>period 20° at the priory of Camouni,<lb break="yes"/>and 40° at the top of Mont-Blanc.<lb break="yes"/>This last mountain is 540 toises higher<lb break="yes"/>than the volcano of Teneriffe; and if,<lb break="yes" />notwithstanding this difference, the<lb break="yes"/>sky is seen there of a less deep blue,<lb break="yes"/>we must attribute this phænomenon<lb break="yes" />to the dryness of the African air, and<lb break="yes"/>the proximity of the torrid zone.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We saw on the summit of the Peak<lb break="yes"/>no trace of psora, lecidea, or other<lb break="yes"/>cryptogamous plants; no insect flut-<lb break="no" />tered in the air. We found how-<lb break="no"/>ever a few hymenopteras adhering to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>masses of sulphur, moistened with sul-<lb break="no"/>phurous acid, and lining the mouths<lb break="yes"/>of the funnels. These are bees, which<lb break="yes"/>appear to have been attracted by the<lb break="yes"/>flowers of the spartium nubigenum,<lb break="yes"/>and which oblique currents of air had<lb break="yes"/>carried up to these high regions, like<lb break="yes"/>the butterflies found by M. Ramond,<lb break="yes"/>at the top of Mont Perdu. The but-<lb break="no"/>terflies perished from cold, while the<lb break="yes" />bees on the Peak were scorched, on<lb break="yes"/>imprudently approaching the crevices<lb break="yes"/>where they came in search of warmth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Notwithstanding the heat we felt in<lb break="yes"/>our feet on the edge of the crater, the<lb break="yes"/>cone of ashes remains covered with<lb break="yes" />snow during several months in the<lb break="yes"/>winter. It is probable, that under the<lb break="yes"/>cap of snow considerable hollows are<lb break="yes" />found, like those we find under the<lb break="yes"/>glaciers of Switzerland, the tempera-<lb break="no"/>ture of which is constantly less ele-<lb break="no" />vated than that of the soil on which<lb break="yes"/>they repose. The cold and violent<lb break="yes"/>wind which blew from the time of<lb break="yes" />sun-rise, engaged us to seek shelter at<lb break="yes"/>the foot of the Piton. Our hands and<lb break="yes"/>faces were frozen, while our boots<lb break="yes" />were burnt by the soil on which we<lb break="yes"/>walked. We descended in the space<lb break="yes"/>of a few minutes the Sugar Loaf which<lb break="yes" />we had scaled with so much toil; and<lb break="yes"/>this rapidity was in part involuntary,<lb break="yes"/>for we often rolled down on the ashes.<lb break="yes"/>It was with regret that we quitted<lb break="yes"/>this solitary place, this domain where<lb break="yes"/>Nature towers in all her majesty; we<lb break="yes"/>soothed ourselves with the hope of<lb break="yes" />once again visiting the Canary islands,<lb break="yes"/>but this, like many other plans which<lb break="yes"/>we then formed, has never been exe-<lb break="no"/>cuted.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">canary birds.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As we approached the town of<lb break="yes"/>Orotava, we met great flocks of ca-<lb break="no"/>naries. These birds, well known in<lb break="yes" />Europe, were in general uniformly<lb break="yes"/>green; some had a yellow tint on their<lb break="yes"/>backs; their note was the same as that<lb break="yes"/>of the tame canary. It is nevertheless<lb break="yes" />remarked, that those which have been<lb break="yes"/>taken in the isle of the Great Canary,<lb break="yes"/>and in the islet of Monte Clara, near<lb break="yes"/>Lanzerota, have a stronger, and at the<lb break="yes"/>same time the most harmonious song.<lb break="yes"/>Under every zone, among birds of the<lb break="yes"/>same species, each flock has its pecu-<lb break="no" />liar note. The yellow canaries are a<lb break="yes"/>variety which has taken birth in Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope; and those we saw in cages at<lb break="yes" />Orotava and Santa Cruz had been<lb break="yes"/>bought at Cadiz and in other ports of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">Spain</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="596" facs="#f0010"/>
                    <cb/>Spain. But of all the birds of the<lb break="yes"/>Canary islands, that which has the<lb break="yes"/>most heart-soothing song is unknown<lb break="yes" />in Europe; this is the capirote, which<lb break="yes"/>no effort has been able to tame, so<lb break="yes"/>sacred to his soul is liberty. I have<lb break="yes" />stood in admiration at his soft and<lb break="yes"/>melodious warbling, in a garden at<lb break="yes"/>Orotava; but I have never seen him<lb break="yes" />sufficiently near, to know to what<lb break="yes"/>family he belongs.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">volcanic philosophy.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Not to interrupt the narrative of the<lb break="yes"/>excursion to the top of the Peak, I<lb break="yes"/>have said nothing of the geological<lb break="yes" />observations I made on the structure<lb break="yes"/>of this colossal mountain, and on the<lb break="yes"/>nature of the volcanic rocks of which<lb break="yes"/>it is composed. Before we quit the<lb break="yes"/>Archipelago of the Canaries, I shall<lb break="yes"/>delay a moment, and bring into one<lb break="yes"/>point of view what relates to the phy-<lb break="no"/>sical picture of these countries.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Is the conical mountain of a volcano<lb break="yes"/>entirely formed of a liquified matter,<lb break="yes"/>heaped together by successive erup-<lb break="no"/>tions; or does it contain in its centre a<lb break="yes" />nucleus of primitive rocks covered<lb break="yes"/>with lavas which are these same rocks<lb break="yes"/>altered by fire? What are the affinities<lb break="yes"/>which unite the productions of modern<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes with the basaltes, the pho-<lb break="no"/>nolites, and those porphyries with<lb break="yes"/>basis of feldspar, which are without<lb break="yes"/>quartz, and which cover the Cordil-<lb break="no"/>leras of Peru and Mexico, as well as<lb break="yes"/>the small groups of the Monts d’Or,<lb break="yes"/>of Cantal, and of Mézen in France?<lb break="yes"/>Has the central nucleus of volcanoes<lb break="yes"/>been heated in its primitive position,<lb break="yes"/>and raised up in a softened state by<lb break="yes"/>the force of the elastic vapours, before<lb break="yes"/>these fluids communicated, by means<lb break="yes"/>of a crater, with the external air?<lb break="yes" />What is the substance which, for<lb break="yes"/>thousands of years, keeps up this com-<lb break="no"/>bustion, which is sometimes so slow,<lb break="yes" />and at other times so active? Does<lb break="yes"/>this unknown cause act at an immense<lb break="yes"/>depth; or does this chemical action<lb break="yes" />take place in secondary rocks lying on<lb break="yes"/>granite?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The farther we are from finding a<lb break="yes"/>solution of these problems in the nu-<lb break="no"/>merous works hitherto published on<lb break="yes"/>Etna and Vesuvius, the greater is the<lb break="yes"/>desire of the traveller to see with his<lb break="yes"/>own eyes. He hopes to be more for-<lb break="no" />tunate than those who have preceded<lb break="yes"/>him; he wishes to form a precise idea<lb break="yes"/>of the geological relations the volcano<lb break="yes"/>and the neighbouring mountains bear<lb break="yes"/>to each other: but, how often is he dis-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/> appointed, when, on the limits of the<lb break="yes"/>primitive soil, enormous banks of tufa<lb break="yes"/>and puzzolana render every observa-<lb break="no"/>tion on the position and stratification<lb break="yes" />impossible! We reach the inside of<lb break="yes"/>the crater with less difficulty than we<lb break="yes"/>at first expected, we examine the cone<lb break="yes"/>from its summit to its basis; we are<lb break="yes"/>struck with the difference in the pro-<lb break="no"/>duce of each eruption, and with the<lb break="yes"/>analogy which still exists between the<lb break="yes" />lavas of the same volcano: but, not-<lb break="no"/>withstanding the care with which we<lb break="yes"/>interrogate nature, and the number of<lb break="yes" />partial observations which are pre-<lb break="no"/>sented at every step, we return from<lb break="yes"/>the summit of a burning volcano less<lb break="yes" />satisfied, than when we were preparing<lb break="yes"/>to go thither. It is after we have<lb break="yes"/>studied them on the spot, that the<lb break="yes" />volcanic phænomena appear still more<lb break="yes"/>isolated, more variable, more obscure,<lb break="yes"/>than we figure them when consulting<lb break="yes" />the narratives of travellers.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These reflections occurred to me on<lb break="yes"/>returning from the summit of the Peak<lb break="yes"/>of Teneriffe, the first unextinct vol-<lb break="no" />cano I had yet visited. They returned<lb break="yes"/>anew, whenever in South America, or<lb break="yes"/>in Mexico, I had occasion to examine<lb break="yes" />volcanic mountains. If we reflect on<lb break="yes"/>the little progress, which the labours<lb break="yes"/>of mineralogists, and the discoveries<lb break="yes"/>in chemistry, have made toward the<lb break="yes"/>knowledge of the physical geology of<lb break="yes"/>mountains, we cannot help being af-<lb break="no"/>fected with a painful sentiment; and<lb break="yes"/>this is felt still more strongly by those,<lb break="yes"/>who, questioning nature under different<lb break="yes"/>climates, are more occupied by the<lb break="yes" />problems they have not been able to<lb break="yes"/>solve, than with the small number of<lb break="yes"/>results they have obtained.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Peak of Teyde forms a pyra-<lb break="no"/>midal mass like Etna, Tungurahua,<lb break="yes"/>and Popocatepetl. This physiognomic<lb break="yes"/>character is very far from being com-<lb break="no"/>mon to all volcanoes. We have seen<lb break="yes"/>some in the southern hemisphere,<lb break="yes"/>which, instead of having the form of a<lb break="yes"/>cone or a bell, are lengthened in one<lb break="yes"/>direction, having the ridge sometimes<lb break="yes"/>smooth, and at others rough with small<lb break="yes"/>pointed rocks. This structure is pe-<lb break="no"/>culiar to Antisana and Pichincha, two<lb break="yes"/>burning mountains of the province of<lb break="yes"/>Quito; and the absence of the conic<lb break="yes"/>form ought never to be considered as<lb break="yes"/>a reason excluding a volcanic origin.<lb break="yes"/>It is here sufficient to observe in ge-<lb break="no"/>neral that the summits, which are still<lb break="yes"/>subject to eruptions of the greatest<lb break="yes"/>violence, and at the nearest periods to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">each</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="597" facs="#f0011"/>
                    <cb/>each other, are slender peaks of a conic<lb break="yes"/>form; that the mountains with length-<lb break="no"/>ened summits, and rugged with small<lb break="yes"/>stony masses, are very old volcanoes,<lb break="yes"/>and near being extinguished; and that<lb break="yes"/>rounded tops in the form of domes, or<lb break="yes"/>bells, indicate those problematic por-<lb break="no" />phyries, which are supposed to have<lb break="yes"/>been heated in their primitive place,<lb break="yes"/>penetrated by vapours, and forced up<lb break="yes"/>in a softened state, without having<lb break="yes"/>ever flowed as real lithoidal lavas. To<lb break="yes"/>the first of these distinctions belong<lb break="yes"/>Cotopaxi, the Peak of Teneriffe, and<lb break="yes" />that of Orizava in Mexico. The se-<lb break="no"/>cond is common to Cargueirazo and<lb break="yes"/>Pichincha, in the province of Quito;<lb break="yes"/>to the volcano of Puracey, near Po-<lb break="no"/>payan; and perhaps also to Hecla, in<lb break="yes"/>Iceland. The third and last is found<lb break="yes"/>in the majestic figure of Chimborazo,<lb break="yes" />and, if it be permitted to place by the<lb break="yes"/>side of this colossus a hill of Europe,<lb break="yes"/>in the Great Sarcouy in Auvergne.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">slopes of hills.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If the slope of these three volcanoes<lb break="yes"/>were uniform from the summit to its<lb break="yes"/>basis, the Peak of Teyde would have<lb break="yes" />an inclination of 12° 29′, Vesuvius<lb break="yes"/>12° 41′, and Etna 10° 13′; a result<lb break="yes"/>which must astonish those who do not<lb break="yes" />reflect on what constitutes an average<lb break="yes"/>slope. In a very long ascent, slopes<lb break="yes"/>of three or four degrees alternate with<lb break="yes"/>others which are inclined from twenty-<lb break="maybe"/>five to thirty degrees; and the latter<lb break="yes"/>only strike our imagination, because<lb break="yes"/>we think all the slopes of mountains<lb break="yes" />more steep than they really are.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The reader versed in the practice of<lb break="yes"/>levelling will not be astonished at the<lb break="yes"/>very gentle slope which these profiles<lb break="yes"/>seem to indicate. In nature an in-<lb break="no"/>clined plane of an angle of 35° appears<lb break="yes"/>to be 50°; we scarcely dare go down<lb break="yes"/>a hill of 22° slope in a carriage; and<lb break="yes" />the parts of the volcanic cones that<lb break="yes"/>are inclined 40° or 42°, are almost in-<lb break="no"/>accessible, though the foot may form<lb break="yes"/>steps by plunging it in the ashes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In places where there were at the<lb break="yes"/>same time slopes covered with tufted<lb break="yes"/>grass and loose sands, I took the fol-<lb break="no" />lowing measures:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>5°, slope already of a very marked in-<lb break="no"/>clination. In France the high roads<lb break="yes"/>must not exceed 4° 46′ by law;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>15°, slope extremely steep, and which<lb break="yes"/>we cannot descend in a carriage;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>37°, slope almost inaccessible on foot,<lb break="yes"/>if the bottom be a naked rock, or a<lb break="yes"/>turf too thick to form steps. The<lb break="yes"/>
                            <cb/>body falls backwards, when the ti-<lb break="no"/>bia makes a smaller angle than 53°,<lb break="yes"/>with the sole of the foot;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>42°, the steepest slope that can be<lb break="yes"/>climbed on foot in a ground that is<lb break="yes"/>sandy, or covered with volcanic<lb break="yes"/>ashes.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When the slope is 44° it is almost<lb break="yes"/>impossible to scale it, though the<lb break="yes"/>ground permits the forming of steps<lb break="yes"/>by thrusting in the foot. The cones<lb break="yes"/>of volcanoes have a medium slope from<lb break="yes"/>33° to 40°. The steepest parts of<lb break="yes" />these cones, either of Vesuvius, the<lb break="yes"/>Peak of Teneriffe, the volcano of Pi-<lb break="no"/>chincha, or Jorullo, are from 40° to<lb break="yes"/>42°. A slope of 55° is quite inacces-<lb break="no"/>sible. If seen from above it would be<lb break="yes"/>estimated at 75°.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">geological phenomena.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>No enlightened observer has hither-<lb break="no"/>to found at Teneriffe primitive strata,<lb break="yes"/>or even those trappean and ambigu-<lb break="no"/>ous porphyries, which constitute the<lb break="yes"/>basis of Etna, and of several volcanoes<lb break="yes"/>of the Andes; but we must not con-<lb break="no"/>clude from this isolated fact, that the<lb break="yes" />whole of the Archipelago of the Ca-<lb break="no"/>naries is the production of submarine<lb break="yes"/>fires. The island of Gomera contains<lb break="yes"/>mountains of granite and mica-slate,<lb break="yes"/>and it is undoubtedly in these very an-<lb break="no"/>cient rocks, that we must here seek,<lb break="yes"/>as well as on all other parts of the<lb break="yes" />globe, the centre of the volcanic ac-<lb break="no"/>tion. Hornblende, sometimes pure<lb break="yes"/>and forming intermediate strata, at<lb break="yes"/>other times mixed with granite, as in<lb break="yes"/>the basanites or basalt of the ancients,<lb break="yes"/>may by itself furnish all the iron con-<lb break="no"/>tained in the black and stony lavas.<lb break="yes" />This quantity amounts in the basalt<lb break="yes"/>of the modern mineralogists only to<lb break="yes"/>0.20, while in hornblende it exceeds<lb break="yes"/>0.30.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Were these granites and these mica-<lb break="no"/>slates of Gomera anciently united to<lb break="yes"/>the chain of Atlas, as the primitive<lb break="yes" />mountains of Corsica appear to be the<lb break="yes"/>central nucleus of Bochetta and the<lb break="yes"/>Apennines? This question can never<lb break="yes"/>be solved, till mineralogists shall have<lb break="yes" />visited the islands that surround the<lb break="yes"/>Peak, and the mountains of Morocco<lb break="yes"/>covered with eternal snows.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Though Teneriffe belongs to a group<lb break="yes"/>of islands of considerable extent, the<lb break="yes"/>Peak exhibits nevertheless all the cha-<lb break="no"/>racters of a mountain placed on a soli-<lb break="no"/>tary islet. As at St. Helena, the lead<lb break="yes"/>finds no bottom at a little distance<lb break="yes"/>from the ports of Santa Cruz, Orotava,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">and</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="598" facs="#f0012"/>
                    <cb/>and Garachico. The ocean, as well as<lb break="yes"/>the continents, has its mountains and<lb break="yes"/>its plains; and, if we except the Andes,<lb break="yes"/>the volcanic cones are formed every<lb break="yes"/>where in the regions of the globe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As the Peak rises amid a system of<lb break="yes"/>basalts and old lava, and as the whole<lb break="yes"/>part which is visible above the surface<lb break="yes" />of the waters exhibits burnt sub-<lb break="no"/>stances, it has been supposed, that this<lb break="yes"/>immense pyramid, is the effect of a<lb break="yes"/>progressive accumulation of lavas; or<lb break="yes"/>that it contains in its centre a nucleus<lb break="yes"/>of primitive rocks. Both of these<lb break="yes"/>suppositions appear to me improbable.<lb break="yes" />I think that there as little existed<lb break="yes"/>mountains of granite gneiss, or pri-<lb break="no"/>mitive calcareous stone, where we at<lb break="yes"/>present see the tops of the Peak, of<lb break="yes"/>Vesuvius, and of Etna, as in the plains<lb break="yes"/>where almost in our own time has been<lb break="yes"/>formed the volcano of Jorullo, which<lb break="yes"/>is more than a third of the height of<lb break="yes"/>Vesuvius. On examining the circum-<lb break="no"/>stances, which accompanied the form-<lb break="no" />ation of the new island in the Archi-<lb break="no"/>pelago of the Azores; on carefully<lb break="yes"/>reading the minute and ingenious nar-<lb break="no"/>rative, which the Jesuit Bourguignon<lb break="yes"/>gave of the slow appearance of the<lb break="yes"/>islet of the little Kameni, near Santo-<lb break="no"/>rino; we find, that these extraordinary<lb break="yes" />eruptions are generally preceded by<lb break="yes"/>a swelling of the softened crust of the<lb break="yes"/>globe. Rocks appear above the waters<lb break="yes" />before the flames force their way, and<lb break="yes"/>lava can issue from the crater: we<lb break="yes"/>must distinguish between the nucleus<lb break="yes" />raised up, and the mass of lavas and<lb break="yes"/>scoriæ, which successively increase its<lb break="yes"/>dimensions.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is true, in all the revolutions of<lb break="yes"/>this kind, which have taken place<lb break="yes"/>since the time that their history has<lb break="yes" />been written, the perpendicular height<lb break="yes"/>of the stony nucleus appears never to<lb break="yes"/>have exceeded one hundred and fifty<lb break="yes"/>or two hundred toises; even taking<lb break="yes"/>into the account the depth of the sea,<lb break="yes"/>the bottom of which had been lifted<lb break="yes"/>up: but when we are considering the<lb break="yes" />great effects of nature, and the inten-<lb break="no"/>sity of its forces, it is not the bulk of<lb break="yes"/>the masses, that ought to stop the<lb break="yes"/>geologist in his speculations. Every<lb break="yes"/>thing indicates, that the physical<lb break="yes"/>changes of which tradition has pre-<lb break="no"/>served the remembrance, exhibit but<lb break="yes"/>a feeble image of those gigantic catas-<lb break="no"/>trophes, which have given mountains<lb break="yes"/>their present form, changed the posi-<lb break="no"/>tions of the rocky strata, and buried<lb break="yes"/>sea shells on the summit of the higher<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>Alps. It was undoubtedly in those<lb break="yes"/>remote times, which preceded the ex-<lb break="no"/>istence of the human race, that the<lb break="yes"/>raised crust of the globe produced<lb break="yes"/>those domes of trappean porphyry,<lb break="yes"/>those hills of isolated basalt on vast<lb break="yes"/>elevated plains, those solid nuclei<lb break="yes"/>which are clothed in the modern lavas<lb break="yes"/>of the Peak, of Etna, and of Cotopaxi.<lb break="yes"/>The volcanic revolutions have suc-<lb break="no" />ceeded each other after long intervals,<lb break="yes"/>and at very different periods: of this<lb break="yes"/>we see the vestiges in the transition<lb break="yes"/>mountains, in the secondary strata,<lb break="yes"/>and in those of alluvion. Volcanoes<lb break="yes"/>of earlier date than the sandstone and<lb break="yes"/>calcareous rocks have been for ages<lb break="yes" />extinguished; those which are yet in<lb break="yes"/>activity are in general surrounded on-<lb break="no"/>ly with breccias and modern tufas;<lb break="yes" />but nothing hinders us from admitting<lb break="yes"/>that the Archipelago of the Canaries<lb break="yes"/>may exhibit some real rocks of secon-<lb break="no" />dary formation, if we recollect that<lb break="yes"/>subterraneous fires have been there re-<lb break="no"/>kindled in the midst of a system of ba-<lb break="no"/>salts and very ancient lavas.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have observed in another place<lb break="yes"/>that the whole of the mountainous<lb break="yes"/>part of the kingdom of Quito may be<lb break="yes"/>considered as an immense volcano,<lb break="yes"/>occupying more than seven hundred<lb break="yes"/>square leagues of surface, and throw-<lb break="no"/>ing out flames by different cones,<lb break="yes"/>known under the particular denomina-<lb break="no"/>tions of Cotopaxi, Tungurahua, and<lb break="yes"/>Pichincha. In like manner the whole<lb break="yes"/>group of the Canary Islands is placed,<lb break="yes"/>as it were, on the same submarine vol-<lb break="no"/>cano. The fire makes its way some-<lb break="no"/>times by one and sometimes by another<lb break="yes"/>of these islands. Teneriffe alone con-<lb break="no"/>tains in its centre an immense pyramid<lb break="yes" />terminated by a crater, and throwing<lb break="yes"/>out, from one century to another, lava<lb break="yes"/>by its flanks. In the other islands the<lb break="yes"/>different eruptions have taken place in<lb break="yes"/>various parts; and we no where find<lb break="yes"/>those isolated mountains, to which the<lb break="yes"/>volcanic effects are restrained. The<lb break="yes" />basaltic crust, formed by ancient vol-<lb break="no"/>canoes, seems every where under-<lb break="no"/>mined; and the currents of lava seen<lb break="yes" />at Lanzerota and Palma, remind us by<lb break="yes"/>every geological affinity of the erup-<lb break="no"/>tion, which took place in 1301 at the<lb break="yes" />isle of Ischia, amid the tufas of<lb break="yes"/>Epomeo.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">theory of volcanic fires.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I might terminate these geological<lb break="yes"/>sketches by discussing the nature of<lb break="yes"/>the combustible, which feeds, for so<lb break="yes" />many thousands of years, the fire of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="599" facs="#f0013"/>
                    <cb/>the Peak of Teneriffe; I might exa-<lb break="no"/>mine whether it be sodium or po-<lb break="no"/>tassium, the metallic basis of some<lb break="yes" />earth, carburet of hydrogen, or pure<lb break="yes"/>sulphur combined with iron, that<lb break="yes"/>burns in the volcano; but, wishing<lb break="yes"/>to limit myself to what may be the ob-<lb break="no"/>ject of direct observation, I will not<lb break="yes"/>take upon me to solve a problem, for<lb break="yes" />which we have not yet sufficient data.<lb break="yes"/>We are ignorant whether we should<lb break="yes"/>conclude from the enormous quantity<lb break="yes"/>of sulphur contained in the crater of<lb break="yes"/>the Peak, that it is this substance<lb break="yes"/>which keeps up the heat of the volca-<lb break="no"/>no; or whether the fire, fed by a com-<lb break="no"/>bustible of an unknown nature, effects<lb break="yes"/>merely the sublimation of the sulphur.<lb break="yes"/>What we learn from observation is,<lb break="yes" />that in craters which are still burning<lb break="yes"/>sulphur is very rare; while all the an-<lb break="no"/>cient volcanoes finish by remaining<lb break="yes"/>true sulphur pits. We might presume<lb break="yes"/>that in the former the sulphur is com-<lb break="no"/>bined with oxygen, while in the latter<lb break="yes"/>it is merely sublimed; for nothing hi-<lb break="no" />therto authorises us to admit, that it<lb break="yes"/>is formed in the interior of volcanoes,<lb break="yes"/>like ammonia and the neutral salts.<lb break="yes"/>When we were yet unacquainted with<lb break="yes"/>sulphur, but as disseminated in the<lb break="yes"/>muriatiferous gypsum, and in the Al-<lb break="no"/>pine limestone, we were almost obliged<lb break="yes"/>to suppose that in every part of the<lb break="yes"/>globe the volcanic fire acted on rocks<lb break="yes"/>of floetz or secondary formation; but<lb break="yes" />recent observations have proved that<lb break="yes"/>sulphur exists in great abundance in<lb break="yes"/>those primitive rocks, which so many<lb break="yes" />phenomena indicate as the centre of<lb break="yes"/>the volcanic action. Near Alausi, on<lb break="yes"/>the summit of the Andes of Quito, I<lb break="yes" />found an immense quantity in a bed of<lb break="yes"/>quartz, which formed a layer of mica-<lb break="no"/>slate; and this fact is so much the<lb break="yes" />more important, as it is in strict con-<lb break="no"/>formity with the observation of those<lb break="yes"/>fragments of ancient rocks, which are<lb break="yes"/>thrown out untouched by the volca-<lb break="no"/>noes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">progress of vegetation.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the northern part of the tempe-<lb break="no"/>rate zone the cryptogamous plants are<lb break="yes"/>the first that cover the stony crust of<lb break="yes"/>the globe. The lichens and mosses,<lb break="yes"/>that display their foliage beneath the<lb break="yes"/>snows, are succeeded by gramina, and<lb break="yes"/>other phanerogamous plants. This<lb break="yes"/>order of vegetation is different on the<lb break="yes"/>borders of the torrid zone, and in the<lb break="yes"/>countries between the tropics. We<lb break="yes" />there find, it is true, whatever some<lb break="yes"/>travellers may have asserted, not only<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> on the mountains, but also in humid<lb break="yes"/>and shady places, almost on a level<lb break="yes"/>with the ocean, funaria, dicranum, and<lb break="yes"/>bryum; and these genera, among their<lb break="yes"/>numerous species, exhibit several<lb break="yes"/>which are common to Lapland, the<lb break="yes"/>Peak of Teneriffe, and the Blue Moun-<lb break="no"/>tains of Jamaica. Nevertheless, in ge-<lb break="no"/>neral, it is not by mosses and lichens<lb break="yes"/>that vegetation in the countries near<lb break="yes" />the tropics begins. In the Canary<lb break="yes"/>islands, as well as in the Guinea, and on<lb break="yes"/>the rocky coasts of Peru, the first ve-<lb break="no"/>getables, that prepare the mould for<lb break="yes"/>others, are the succulent plants; the<lb break="yes"/>leaves of which, provided with an in-<lb break="no"/>finite number of orifices and cutaneous<lb break="yes" />vessels, deprive the ambient air of the<lb break="yes"/>water it holds in solution. Fixed in<lb break="yes"/>the crevices of volcanic rocks, they<lb break="yes"/>form, as it were, that first layer of ve-<lb break="no" />getable earth, with which the currents<lb break="yes"/>of lithoid lava are clothed. Wherever<lb break="yes"/>these lavas are scorified, and where<lb break="yes"/>they have a shining surface, as in the<lb break="yes"/>basaltic mounds to the north of Lan-<lb break="no"/>zerota, the unfolding of vegetation is<lb break="yes"/>extremely slow, and many ages may<lb break="yes"/>roll away before shrubs can take root.<lb break="yes"/>It is only when lavas are covered with<lb break="yes"/>tufa and ashes the volcanic islands<lb break="yes" />lose that appearance of nudity which<lb break="yes"/>marks their origin, and deck them-<lb break="no"/>selves with a rich and brilliant vegeta-<lb break="no" />tion.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In its present state the island of Te-<lb break="no"/>neriffe, the Chinerfe<note place="foot" n="*">Of Chinerfe the Europeans have form-<lb break="no"/>ed, by corruption, Tchineriffe and Teneriffe.</note> of the Guanches,<lb break="yes"/>exhibits five zones of plants, which<lb break="yes"/>we may distinguish by the names of<lb break="yes"/>region of vines, region of laurels, re-<lb break="no"/>gion of pines, region of the retama,<lb break="yes"/>and region of grasses. These zones<lb break="yes"/>are arranged in stages, one above the<lb break="yes"/>other, and occupy, on the steep decli-<lb break="no" />vity of the Peak, a perpendicular<lb break="yes"/>height of 1750 toises; while fifteen<lb break="yes"/>degrees farther north, on the Pyrenees,<lb break="yes"/>the snows already descend to thirteen<lb break="yes"/>or fourteen hundred toises of absolute<lb break="yes"/>elevation. If the plants of Teneriffe<lb break="yes"/>do not reach the summit of the volca-<lb break="no"/>no, it is not because the perpetual<lb break="yes"/>snows, and the cold of the surrounding<lb break="yes"/>atmosphere, lay down limits which<lb break="yes"/>they cannot pass; it is the scorified lava<lb break="yes"/>of the Malpays, the powdered and<lb break="yes"/>barren pumice stone of the Piton,<lb break="yes"/>which impede the migration of the<lb break="yes" />plants toward the brink of the crater.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The first zone, that of the vines,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">extends</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="600" facs="#f0014"/>
                    <cb/>extends from the sea-shore to four or<lb break="yes"/>six hundred yards of height; it is that<lb break="yes"/>which is most inhabited, and the only<lb break="yes"/>part carefully cultivated. The region<lb break="yes"/>of the vines exhibits, among its vege-<lb break="no"/>table productions, eight kinds of ar-<lb break="no"/>borescent euphorbia; mesembrianthe-<lb break="no"/>ma, which are multiplied from the<lb break="yes"/>Cape of Good Hope to the Pelopon-<lb break="no"/>nesus; the cacalia kleinia, the dracæ-<lb break="no" />na, and other plants, which in their<lb break="yes"/>naked and tortuous trunks, in their<lb break="yes"/>succulent leaves, and their tint of<lb break="yes"/>blueish green, exhibit features distin-<lb break="no"/>guishing the vegetation of Africa. It<lb break="yes"/>is in this zone that the date tree, the<lb break="yes"/>plantain, the sugar cane, the India fig,<lb break="yes" />the arum colocasia, the root of which<lb break="yes"/>furnishes the lower class with a nutri-<lb break="no"/>tive fecula, the olive tree, the fruit<lb break="yes"/>trees of Europe, the vine, and corn,<lb break="yes"/>are cultivated. The wheat is reaped<lb break="yes"/>from the end of March to the begin-<lb break="no"/>ning of May: and the culture of the<lb break="yes" />bread-fruit tree of Otaheite, that of<lb break="yes"/>the cinnamon tree of the Moluccas,<lb break="yes"/>the coffee tree of Arabia, and the co-<lb break="no"/>coa tree of America, have been tried<lb break="yes"/>with success.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The second zone, that of the laurels,<lb break="yes"/>contains the woody part of Teneriffe;<lb break="yes"/>this is the region of the springs, that<lb break="yes"/>rise up amidst a turf always verdant,<lb break="yes"/>and never parched with drought.<lb break="yes"/>Lofty forests crown the hills that lead<lb break="yes"/>to the volcano, and in them find four<lb break="yes"/>species of laurel, an oak nearly resem-<lb break="no"/>bling the quercus Turneri of the<lb break="yes"/>mountains of Thibet, the visnea moca-<lb break="no" />nera, the myrica faya of the Azores, a<lb break="yes"/>native olive (olea excelsa), which is<lb break="yes"/>the largest tree of this zone, two spe-<lb break="no"/>cies of sideroxylon, the leaves of which<lb break="yes"/>are extremely beautiful, the arbutus<lb break="yes"/>callicarpa, and other evergreen trees of<lb break="yes"/>the family of myrtles.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The third zone begins at a mile of<lb break="yes"/>absolute height, where the last group<lb break="yes"/>of arbutus, of myrica faya, and that<lb break="yes" />beautiful heath known to the natives<lb break="yes"/>under the name of texo, appears. This<lb break="yes"/>zone, half a mile in breadth, is en-<lb break="no" />tirely filled by a vast forest of pines.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The fourth and fifth zones, the re-<lb break="no"/>gions of the retama and the gramina,<lb break="yes"/>occupy heights equal to the most in-<lb break="no" />accessible summits of the Pyrenees. It<lb break="yes"/>is the sterile part of the island, where<lb break="yes"/>heaps of pumice stone, obsidian, and<lb break="yes"/>broken lava, form impediments to ve-<lb break="no"/>getation. We have already spoken of<lb break="yes"/>those flowery tufts of alpine broom<lb break="yes"/>(spartium nub genum), that form oases<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>amidst a vast sea of ashes. Two her-<lb break="no"/>baceous plants, the scrofularia gla-<lb break="no"/>brata, and the viola cheiranthifolia,<lb break="yes"/>advance even to the Malpays. Just<lb break="yes"/>above a turf scorched by the heat of an<lb break="yes"/>African sun, an arid soil is overspread<lb break="yes"/>by the cladonia paschalis, to which<lb break="yes"/>the herdsmen often set fire, that rolls<lb break="yes"/>to considerable distances. Toward<lb break="yes"/>the summit of the Peak, the urceolarca,<lb break="yes"/>and other plants of the family of the<lb break="yes"/>lichens, labour at the decomposition<lb break="yes"/>of the schorified matter. By this un-<lb break="no"/>ceasing action of organic forces the em-<lb break="no"/>pire of Flora extends itself over islands<lb break="yes" />ravaged by volcanoes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">trade winds.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Our course was such as is taken by<lb break="yes"/>all vessels destined for the Antilles<lb break="yes"/>since the first voyage of Columbus.<lb break="yes" />The latitude diminished rapidly, al-<lb break="no"/>most without gaining in longitude,<lb break="yes"/>from the parallel of Madeira to the<lb break="yes"/>tropic. When we reach the zone,<lb break="yes"/>where the trade winds are constant,<lb break="yes"/>we cross the ocean from east to west,<lb break="yes"/>on a calm and pacific sea, which Spa-<lb break="no"/>nish sailors call the Ladies’ Gulf, <hi rendition="#i">el<lb break="yes"/>Golfo de las Damas.</hi> We found, as all<lb break="yes"/>do who frequent those latitudes, that<lb break="yes"/>in proportion as we advance towards<lb break="yes"/>the west, the trade winds, which were<lb break="yes"/>at first east-north-east, fix to the east.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the passage from Santa Cruz to<lb break="yes"/>Cumana, as in that from Acapulco to<lb break="yes"/>the Philippine islands, the sailors are<lb break="yes"/>scarcely ever under the necessity of<lb break="yes"/>touching the sails. We pass those<lb break="yes"/>latitudes as if we were descending a<lb break="yes"/>river, and we might deem it no ha-<lb break="no"/>zardous undertaking, if we made the<lb break="yes"/>voyage in an open boat. Farther west,<lb break="yes"/>on the coast of St. Martha, and in the<lb break="yes" />Gulf of Mexico, the trade wind blows<lb break="yes"/>impetuously, and renders the sea very<lb break="yes"/>stormy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The wind fell gradually the farther<lb break="yes"/>we removed from the African coasts:<lb break="yes"/>it was sometimes smooth water for<lb break="yes" />several hours, and these short calms<lb break="yes"/>were regularly interrupted by elec-<lb break="no"/>trical phænomena. Black thick clouds<lb break="yes"/>with strong outlines rose on the east,<lb break="yes"/>and it seemed as if a squall would<lb break="yes"/>have forced us to hand our topsails;<lb break="yes"/>but the breeze freshened anew, there<lb break="yes"/>fell a few large drops of rain, and the<lb break="yes"/>storm was dispersed without our hear-<lb break="no"/>ing any thunder. It was curious to<lb break="yes"/>observe, during this time, the effect<lb break="yes"/>of several black, isolated, and very<lb break="yes"/>low clouds, which passed the zenith.<lb break="yes"/>We felt the force of the wind aug-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">ment</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="601" facs="#f0015"/>
                    <cb/>ment or diminish progressively, ac-<lb break="no"/>cording as small bodies of vesicular<lb break="yes"/>vapour approached or receded, while<lb break="yes" />the electrometers, furnished with a<lb break="yes"/>long metallic rod and lighted match,<lb break="yes"/>showed no change of electric tension<lb break="yes"/>in the lower strata of the air.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Nothing equals the beauty and mild-<lb break="no"/>ness of the climate of the equinoctial<lb break="yes"/>region on the ocean. While the trade<lb break="yes"/>wind blew strongly, the thermometer<lb break="yes"/>kept at 23 or 24 degrees in the day, and<lb break="yes"/>at 22 or 22·5 degrees during the night.<lb break="yes"/>To feel the full charm of these happy<lb break="yes" />climates bordering on the equator, the<lb break="yes"/>passage from Acapulco or the coasts<lb break="yes"/>of Chili to Europe should be under-<lb break="no" />taken in a very rough season. What<lb break="yes"/>a contrast between the tempestuous<lb break="yes"/>seas of the northern latitudes, and the<lb break="yes"/>regions where the calm of nature is<lb break="yes"/>never disturbed! If the return from<lb break="yes"/>Mexico or South America to the coasts<lb break="yes"/>of Spain were as expeditious and as<lb break="yes" />agreeable as the passage from the old<lb break="yes"/>to the new continent, the number of<lb break="yes"/>Europeans settled in the colonies<lb break="yes" />would be much less considerable than<lb break="yes"/>it is at present. The sea which sur-<lb break="no"/>rounds the Azores and the Bermuda<lb break="yes" />islands, and which is traversed in re-<lb break="no"/>turning to Europe by the high lati-<lb break="no"/>tudes, is called by the Spaniards by<lb break="yes" />the singular name of <hi rendition="#i">Golfo de las Yeguas</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(the Mares’ Gulf). Colonists who are<lb break="yes"/>not accustomed to the sea, and who<lb break="yes"/>have led solitary lives in the forests of<lb break="yes"/>Guiana, the Savannahs of the Caraccas,<lb break="yes" />or the Cordilleras of Peru, dread the<lb break="yes"/>neighbourhood of the Bermudas more<lb break="yes"/>than the inhabitants of Lima fear at<lb break="yes"/>present the passage round Cape Horn.<lb break="yes"/>They exaggerate the danger of a navi-<lb break="no"/>gation which is perilous only in the<lb break="yes"/>winter. They defer from one year to<lb break="yes" />another the execution of a project<lb break="yes"/>which appears hazardous, and death<lb break="yes"/>very often surprises them in the midst<lb break="yes" />of the preparations which they make<lb break="yes"/>for their return.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">southern constellation.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From the time we entered the torrid<lb break="yes"/>zone, we were never wearied with ad-<lb break="no"/>miring, every night, the beauty of the<lb break="yes" />southern sky, which, as we advanced<lb break="yes"/>towards the south, opened new con-<lb break="no"/>stellations to our view. We feel an<lb break="yes" />indescribable sensation, when, on ap-<lb break="no"/>proaching the equator, and particu-<lb break="no"/>larly on passing from one hemisphere<lb break="yes" />to the other, we see those stars which<lb break="yes"/>we have contemplated from our in-<lb break="no"/>fancy, progressively sink, and finally<lb break="yes"/>disappear. Nothing awakens in the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> traveller a livelier remembrance of the<lb break="yes"/>immense distance by which he is se-<lb break="no"/>parated from his country, than the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>aspec</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">aspect</corr>
                    </choice> of an unknown firmament. The<lb break="yes"/>grouping of the stars of the first mag-<lb break="no"/>nitude, some scattered nebulæ, rival-<lb break="no"/>ling in splendor the milky way, and<lb break="yes"/>tracks of space remarkable for their<lb break="yes"/>extreme blackness, give a particular<lb break="yes"/>physiognomy to the southern sky.<lb break="yes" />This sight fills with admiration even<lb break="yes"/>those, who, uninstructed in the<lb break="yes"/>branches of accurate science, feel the<lb break="yes" />same emotion of delight in the con-<lb break="no"/>templation of the heavenly vault, as<lb break="yes"/>in the view of a beautiful landscape,<lb break="yes" />or a majestic site. A traveller has no<lb break="yes"/>need of being a botanist, to recognize<lb break="yes"/>the torrid zone on the mere aspect of<lb break="yes"/>its vegetation; and without having<lb break="yes"/>acquired any notions of astronomy,<lb break="yes"/>without any acquaintance with the<lb break="yes"/>celestial charts of Flamstead and de la<lb break="yes"/>Caille, he feels he is not in Europe,<lb break="yes"/>when he sees the immense constel-<lb break="no"/>lation of the Ship, or the phosphores-<lb break="no" />cent clouds of Magellan, arise on the<lb break="yes"/>horizon. The heaven, and the earth,<lb break="yes"/>every thing in the equinoctial regions,<lb break="yes"/>assumes an exotic character.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We saw distinctly for the first time<lb break="yes"/>the Cross of the south only in the<lb break="yes"/>night of the 4th and 5th of July, in<lb break="yes"/>the sixteenth degree of latitude; it<lb break="yes"/>was strongly inclined, and appeared<lb break="yes"/>from time to time between the clouds,<lb break="yes"/>the centre of which, furrowed by un-<lb break="no"/>condensed lightnings, reflected a silver<lb break="yes"/>light.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The pleasure we felt on discovering<lb break="yes"/>the southern Cross was warmly shared<lb break="yes"/>by such of the crew as had lived in<lb break="yes" />the colonies. In the solitude of the<lb break="yes"/>seas, we hail a star as a friend, from<lb break="yes"/>whom we have long been separated.<lb break="yes" />Among the Portuguese and the Spa-<lb break="no"/>niards peculiar motives seem to in-<lb break="no"/>crease this feeling; a religious senti-<lb break="no" />ment attaches them to a constellation,<lb break="yes"/>the form of which recalls the sign of<lb break="yes"/>the faith planted by their ancestors in<lb break="yes"/>the deserts of the new world.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The two great stars which mark the<lb break="yes"/>summit and the foot of the Cross<lb break="yes"/>having nearly the same right ascen-<lb break="no" />sion, it follows hence, that the con-<lb break="no"/>stellation is almost perpendicular at<lb break="yes"/>the moment when it passes the meri-<lb break="no"/>dian. This circumstance is known to<lb break="yes"/>every nation that lives beyond the<lb break="yes"/>tropics, or in the southern hemisphere.<lb break="yes"/>It has been observed at what hour of<lb break="yes"/>the night, in different seasons, the<lb break="yes"/>Cross of the south is erect, or inclined.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">It</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="602" facs="#f0016"/>
                    <cb/>It is a time-piece that advances very<lb break="yes"/>regularly near four minutes a day, and<lb break="yes"/>no other group of stars exhibits to the<lb break="yes"/>naked eye, an observation of time so<lb break="yes"/>easily made. How often have we<lb break="yes"/>heard our guides exclaim in the sa-<lb break="no"/>vannas of Venezuela, or in the desert<lb break="yes"/>extending from Lima to Truxillo,<lb break="yes"/>“Midnight is past, the Cross begins<lb break="yes"/>to bend!” How often those words<lb break="yes"/>reminded us of that affecting scene,<lb break="yes"/>where Paul and Virginia, seated near<lb break="yes"/>the source of the river of Lataniers,<lb break="yes"/>conversed together for the last time,<lb break="yes"/>and where the old man, at the sight<lb break="yes"/>of the southern Cross, warns them<lb break="yes"/>that it is time to separate.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">tropical heats.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The extreme slowness with which<lb break="yes"/>the temperature increases during the<lb break="yes"/>passage from Spain to the New Con-<lb break="no" />tinent, is highly advantageous to the<lb break="yes"/>health of Europeans, who go to settle<lb break="yes"/>in the colonies. At Vera Cruz and at<lb break="yes" />Carthagena, the creoles who descend<lb break="yes"/>from the high savannas of Bogota,<lb break="yes"/>and the central elevated plain of New<lb break="yes" />Spain, are more exposed on the coasts<lb break="yes"/>to the attack of the yellow fever, or<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">vomito,</hi> than the inhabitants of the<lb break="yes" />north, who arrive by sea. In travel-<lb break="no"/>ling from Perote to Vera Cruz, the<lb break="yes"/>Mexicans descend in sixteen hours<lb break="yes"/>from the region of pines and oaks,<lb break="yes"/>from a mountainous country where<lb break="yes"/>the thermometer very often sinks at<lb break="yes" />noon to four or five degrees, to a<lb break="yes"/>burning plain covered with cocoa<lb break="yes"/>trees, with mimosa cornigera, and<lb break="yes" />other plants that vegetate only under<lb break="yes"/>the influence of a strong heat. These<lb break="yes"/>mountaineers feel a difference of tem-<lb break="no"/>perature of eighteen degrees; and this<lb break="yes" />difference produces the most fatal<lb break="yes"/>effects on the organs, by exciting their<lb break="yes"/>irritability. The European, on the<lb break="yes" />contrary, crosses the Atlantic Ocean<lb break="yes"/>in thirty-five or forty days; he pre-<lb break="no"/>pares himself gradually for the swel-<lb break="no" />tering heat of Vera Cruz, which,<lb break="yes"/>without being the direct cause of the<lb break="yes"/>yellow fever, do not the less contri-<lb break="no" />bute to the rapidity of its progress.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A very sensible decrement of heat<lb break="yes"/>is observed on the Globe, whether we<lb break="yes"/>go from the equator to the poles, as-<lb break="no" />cend from the surface of the earth into<lb break="yes"/>the highest regions of the air, or dive<lb break="yes"/>into the depth of the ocean. It is so<lb break="yes"/>much the more interesting to compare<lb break="yes"/>the rapidity of this three-fold decre-<lb break="no"/>ment, as this phænomenon has a great<lb break="yes"/>influence on the climatic distributions<lb break="yes" />of vegetable and animal productions<choice><sic>,</sic><corr type="editorial">.</corr></choice><lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>The mean temperature of the lower<lb break="yes"/>strata of the air, which corresponds to<lb break="yes"/>the sixty-fifth, forty-eighth, and twen-<lb break="no"/>tieth, degrees of north latitude, are,<lb break="yes"/>according to the most recent observa-<lb break="no"/>tions, 0·5°, 10·7°, and 25°; whence it<lb break="yes"/>results, that a centigrade degree cor-<lb break="no" />responds nearly to a change of latitude<lb break="yes"/>of 1°, 45′. Now the decrement of<lb break="yes"/>caloric is one degree every ninety<lb break="yes" />toises, when we raise ourselves per-<lb break="no"/>pendicularly into the atmosphere. It<lb break="yes"/>therefore follows, that under the tro-<lb break="no"/>pics, where the lowering of the tem-<lb break="no"/>perature is very regular on mountains<lb break="yes"/>of considerable height, 1000 yards of<lb break="yes"/>vertical elevation correspond to a<lb break="yes"/>change of latitude of 9° 45′. This<lb break="yes"/>result, conformable enough to those<lb break="yes"/>which other naturalists have adopted<lb break="yes" />before me, is very important to the<lb break="yes"/>geography of plants; for, though in<lb break="yes"/>the northern countries the distribution<lb break="yes" />of vegetables on the mountains and in<lb break="yes"/>the plains depends, like the height of<lb break="yes"/>the perpetual snows, more on the mean<lb break="yes"/>temperature of the months of summer<lb break="yes"/>than on that of the whole year, the<lb break="yes"/>latter does not less determine in south-<lb break="no"/>ern countries the limits, which the<lb break="yes" />species have not been able to pass in<lb break="yes"/>their distant migrations. The obser-<lb break="no"/>vation made by Tournefort on the<lb break="yes"/>summit of Ararat has been repeated<lb break="yes"/>by a great number of travellers. When<lb break="yes"/>we descend from a high chain of<lb break="yes"/>mountains and advance toward the<lb break="yes"/>poles, we find at first in plains of little<lb break="yes"/>height, and finally in the regions near<lb break="yes"/>the coast, the same arborescent plants<lb break="yes" />which in the low latitudes cover only<lb break="yes"/>the heights near the perennial snows.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <table>
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#c">
                            <hi rendition="#i">Table of the temperature of the Atlantic<lb break="yes"/>Ocean.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Latitude.</cell>
                        <cell>Temperature<lb break="yes"/>of the ocean.</cell>
                        <cell>Period.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>0° 58′ S.</cell>
                        <cell>27·2°</cell>
                        <cell>Nov.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>0 57 S.</cell>
                        <cell>27·7</cell>
                        <cell>April</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>0 33 S.</cell>
                        <cell>27·7</cell>
                        <cell>March</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>0 11 N.</cell>
                        <cell>28·0</cell>
                        <cell>Febr.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>0 13 N.</cell>
                        <cell>27·1</cell>
                        <cell>May</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>25° 15′ N.</cell>
                        <cell>20·0°</cell>
                        <cell>June</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>25 29 N.</cell>
                        <cell>21·6</cell>
                        <cell>April</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>25 49 N.</cell>
                        <cell>20·7</cell>
                        <cell>March</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>27 40 N.</cell>
                        <cell>21·6</cell>
                        <cell>Jan.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>28 47 N.</cell>
                        <cell>23·5</cell>
                        <cell>Octob.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>42° 34′ N.</cell>
                        <cell>11·1°</cell>
                        <cell>Febr.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>43 17 N.</cell>
                        <cell>15·5</cell>
                        <cell>May</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>43 58 N.</cell>
                        <cell>15 9</cell>
                        <cell>June</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>44 58 N.</cell>
                        <cell>12 7</cell>
                        <cell>Dec.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>45 13 N.</cell>
                        <cell>15·5</cell>
                        <cell>Nov.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>48 11 N.</cell>
                        <cell>14·3</cell>
                        <cell>June</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">
                    <hi rendition="#i">Temperature</hi>
                </fw>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="603" facs="#f0017"/>
                <cb/>
                <table>
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#c">
                            <hi rendition="#i">Temperature of the air in both hemispheres.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell rows="2">Latitude.</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">Correspondent<lb break="yes"/>months.</cell>
                        <cell cols="2">Mean temp of the Months.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Southern<lb break="yes"/>hemisphere.</cell>
                        <cell>Northern<lb break="yes"/>hemisphere.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>6°</cell>
                        <cell>December....</cell>
                        <cell>28·0°</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>June........</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                        <cell>28·5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>October .....</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                        <cell>26·5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>April .......</cell>
                        <cell>27·5</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>January .....</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                        <cell>19·3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>July ........</cell>
                        <cell>22·5</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>September ...</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                        <cell>20·5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>March ......</cell>
                        <cell>20·8</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>34</cell>
                        <cell>December....</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                        <cell>15·4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>June........</cell>
                        <cell>13·8</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>February ....</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                        <cell>17·0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>August ......</cell>
                        <cell>16·8</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>July ........</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                        <cell>18·2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>January .....</cell>
                        <cell>15·2</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>June........</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                        <cell>17·7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>December....</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                        <cell>July ........</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                        <cell>13·5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>January ......</cell>
                        <cell>6 2</cell>
                        <cell>........</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <table>
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#c">
                            <hi rendition="#g">
                                <hi rendition="#k">height of teneriffe.</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">
                            <hi rendition="#c">1. <hi rendition="#i">Geometrical measurements made on land.</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Toises.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>P. Feuillêe, in 1724 ‒ ‒ ‒ </cell>
                        <cell>2213</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>the same result modified by<lb break="yes"/>Bouguer ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ </cell>
                        <cell>2062</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Heberden and Cross, five opera-<lb break="no"/>tions, in 1752 ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ </cell>
                        <cell>2408</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Hernandez, in 1742 ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ </cell>
                        <cell>2658</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Borda and Pingrê, in 1771 ‒ ‒ </cell>
                        <cell>1742</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Borda, in 1776 ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ </cell>
                        <cell>1905</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">
                            <hi rendition="#c">
                                <hi rendition="#i">Made under sail.</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Mannevilette, in 1749 ‒ ‒ ‒ </cell>
                        <cell>2000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Borda and Pingré, in 1771 ‒ ‒ </cell>
                        <cell>1701</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Churruca, in 1788 ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ </cell>
                        <cell>2193</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Johnstone, ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ </cell>
                        <cell>2023</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">
                            <hi rendition="#c">2. <hi rendition="#i">Barometric measurements calculated after<lb break="yes"/>the formula of La Place.</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>toises.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Feuillée and Verguin, in 1724 </cell>
                        <cell>2025</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Borda, in 1776 ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ </cell>
                        <cell>1976</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Lamanon, in 1785 ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ </cell>
                        <cell>1902</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Cordier, in 1803 ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ ‒ </cell>
                        <cell>1920</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A toise is about two yards English.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The real height of the Peak of<lb break="yes"/>Teneriffe differs little probably from<lb break="yes"/>the mean between the three geome-<lb break="no"/>trical and barometrical measurements<lb break="yes"/>of Borda, Lamanon, and Cordier.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1905</cell>
                        <cell>toises</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1902</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rendition="#u">1920</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1909</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">west india landscape.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We anchored opposite the mouth of<lb break="yes"/>the river Manzanares on the 16th of<lb break="yes"/>July, at break of day: but we could<lb break="yes"/>not land till very late in the morning,<lb break="yes"/>because we were obliged to wait<lb break="yes"/>the visit of the officers of the port.<lb break="yes" />Our eyes were fixed on the groups of<lb break="yes"/>cocoa-trees that border the river, and<lb break="yes"/>the trunks of which, more than sixty<lb break="yes"/>feet high, towered over the landscape.<lb break="yes"/>The plain was covered with tufts of<lb break="yes"/>cassias, capers, and those arborescent<lb break="yes"/>mimosas, which, like the pine of Italy,<lb break="yes"/>extend their branches in the form of<lb break="yes"/>an umbrella. The pinnated leaves of<lb break="yes"/>the palms were conspicuous on the<lb break="yes"/>azure of a sky, the clearness of which<lb break="yes" />was unsullied by any trace of vapors.<lb break="yes"/>The sun was ascending rapidly toward<lb break="yes"/>the zenith. A dazzling light was<lb break="yes" />spread through the air, along the<lb break="yes"/>whitish hills strewed with cylindric<lb break="yes"/>cactuses, and over a sea ever calm, the<lb break="yes"/>shores of which were peopled with al-<lb break="no"/>catras, egrets, and flamingoes. The<lb break="yes"/>splendor of the day, the vivid colour-<lb break="no"/>ing of the vegetable world, the forms<lb break="yes" />of the plants, the varied plumage of<lb break="yes"/>the birds, every thing announced the<lb break="yes"/>grand aspect of nature in the equinoc-<lb break="no"/>tial regions.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">horrible rencountre.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We were conducted by the captain<lb break="yes"/>of the Pizarro to the governor of the<lb break="yes"/>province, Don Vincente Emparan, to<lb break="yes" />present to him the passports which<lb break="yes"/>had been given us by the first secre-<lb break="no"/>tary of state. He received us with<lb break="yes" />that frankness, and that noble simpli-<lb break="no"/>city, which has at all times characte-<lb break="no"/>rized the Biscayan nation. Before he<lb break="yes"/>was named governor of Portobello and<lb break="yes"/>Cumana, he had distinguished himself<lb break="yes"/>as a captain of a vessel in the royal<lb break="yes"/>navy. His name recalls to mind one<lb break="yes"/>of the most extraordinary and distress-<lb break="no"/>ing events recorded in the history of<lb break="yes"/>maritime wars. At the time of the<lb break="yes" />last rupture between Spain and Eng-<lb break="no"/>land, two brothers of M. d’Emparan<lb break="yes"/>fought during a whole night before<lb break="yes" />the port of Cadiz, taking each other’s<lb break="yes"/>ship for an enemy’s. The battle was<lb break="yes"/>so terrible that both vessels were sunk<lb break="yes"/>nearly at the same time. A very small<lb break="yes"/>part of the crew was saved, and the<lb break="yes"/>two brothers had the misfortune to re-<lb break="no"/>cognize each other a little before they<lb break="yes" />expired.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">city of cumana.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The city, placed at the foot of a<lb break="yes"/>hill destitute of verdure, is command-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">ed</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="604" facs="#f0018"/>
                    <cb/>ed by a castle. No steeple or dome<lb break="yes"/>attracts from afar the eye of the tra-<lb break="no"/>veller, but only a few trunks of tama-<lb break="no"/>rind, cocoa, and date trees, which rise<lb break="yes"/>above the houses, the roofs of which<lb break="yes"/>are flat. The surrounding plains,<lb break="yes"/>especially those on the coasts, wear a<lb break="yes"/>melancholy, dusty, and arid appear-<lb break="no"/>ance, while a fresh and luxuriant ve-<lb break="no"/>getation points out from afar the wind-<lb break="no"/>ings of the river, which separates the<lb break="yes" />city from the suburbs, the population<lb break="yes"/>of European and mixed race from the<lb break="yes"/>natives with a coppery tint. The hill<lb break="yes"/>of fort St. Antonio, solitary, white,<lb break="yes"/>and bare, reflects a great mass of light,<lb break="yes"/>and of radiant heat; it is composed of<lb break="yes"/>breccia, the strata of which contain<lb break="yes" />pelagian petrifactions. In the distance,<lb break="yes"/>toward the south, a vast and gloomy<lb break="yes"/>curtain of mountains stretches along.<lb break="yes"/>These are the high calcareous Alps of<lb break="yes"/>New Andalusia, surmounted by sand-<lb break="no"/>stone, and other more recent forma-<lb break="no"/>tions. Majestic forests cover this<lb break="yes" />Cordillera of the interior, and are join-<lb break="no"/>ed by a woody vale to the open clayey<lb break="yes"/>lands and salt marshes of the environs<lb break="yes"/>of Cumana. A few birds of consider-<lb break="no"/>able size contribute to give a particu-<lb break="no"/>lar physiognomy to these countries.<lb break="yes"/>On the sea-shore, and in the gulf, we<lb break="yes"/>find flocks of fishing herons, and alca-<lb break="no"/>tras of a very unwieldy form, which<lb break="yes"/>swim, like the swan, raising their<lb break="yes"/>wings. Nearer the habitation of men,<lb break="yes" />thousands of galinazo vultures, the<lb break="yes"/>true jackals of the winged tribe, are<lb break="yes"/>ever busy in uncovering the carcases<lb break="yes" />of animals. A gulf, which contains<lb break="yes"/>hot and submarine springs, divides the<lb break="yes"/>secondary from the primary and schis-<lb break="no" />tose rocks of the peninsula of Araya.<lb break="yes"/>Each of these coasts is bathed by a<lb break="yes"/>tranquil sea, of an azure tint, and al-<lb break="no"/>ways gently agitated by the same wind.<lb break="yes"/>A bright and clear sky, with a few<lb break="yes"/>light clouds at sun-set, reposes on the<lb break="yes"/>ocean, on the peninsula destitute of<lb break="yes" />trees, and on the plains of Cumana,<lb break="yes"/>while we see the storms accumulate<lb break="yes"/>and descend in fertile showers among<lb break="yes"/>the inland mountains. Thus on these<lb break="yes"/>coasts, as well as at the foot of the<lb break="yes"/>Andes, the earth and the skies offer<lb break="yes"/>the extremes of clear weather and<lb break="yes" />fogs, of drought and torrents of rain,<lb break="yes"/>of absolute nudity and never ceasing<lb break="yes"/>verdure. In the New Continent, the<lb break="yes" />low regions on the sea-coasts differ as<lb break="yes"/>widely from the inland mountainous<lb break="yes"/>districts, as the plains of Lower Egypt<lb break="yes"/>from the high lands of Abyssinia.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">earthquakes.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is a very generally received opi-<lb break="no"/>nion on the coasts of Cumana, and in<lb break="yes"/>the island of Margaretta, that the gulf<lb break="yes" />of Cariaco owes its existence to a rent<lb break="yes"/>of the continent, attended by an irrup-<lb break="no"/>tion of the ocean. The remembrance<lb break="yes"/>of this great revolution was preserved<lb break="yes"/>among the Indians to the end of the<lb break="yes"/>fifteenth century; and it is related<lb break="yes"/>that, at the time of the third voyage<lb break="yes" />of Christopher Columbus, the natives<lb break="yes"/>mentioned it as a very recent event. In<lb break="yes"/>1530 the inhabitants were alarmed by<lb break="yes"/>new shocks on the coasts of Paria and<lb break="yes"/>Cumana. The lands were inundated<lb break="yes"/>by the sea, and the small fort, built<lb break="yes"/>by James Castellon at New Toledo,<lb break="yes"/>was entirely destroyed. At the same<lb break="yes"/>time an enormous opening was formed<lb break="yes"/>in the mountains of Cariaco, on the<lb break="yes" />shores of the gulf that bears this name,<lb break="yes"/>when a great body of salt water, mix-<lb break="no"/>ed with asphaltum, issued from the<lb break="yes"/>micaceous schist. Earthquakes were<lb break="yes"/>very frequent toward the end of the<lb break="yes"/>sixteenth century; and, according to<lb break="yes"/>the traditions preserved at Cumana,<lb break="yes"/>the sea often inundated the shores,<lb break="yes"/>rising from fifteen to twenty fathoms.<lb break="yes"/>The inhabitants fled to the Cerro of<lb break="yes" />San Antonio, and to the hill where<lb break="yes"/>now stands the small convent of St.<lb break="yes"/>Francis. It is even thought that these<lb break="yes"/>frequent inundations induced the inha-<lb break="no"/>bitants to build that quarter of the<lb break="yes"/>town, which is backed by the moun-<lb break="no"/>tain; and stands on a part of its de-<lb break="no" />clivity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As no record exists at Cumana, and<lb break="yes"/>its archives, on account of the continual<lb break="yes"/>devastations of the termites, or white<lb break="yes"/>ants, contain no document that goes<lb break="yes"/>back farther than a hundred and fifty<lb break="yes"/>years, we are unacquainted with the<lb break="yes"/>precise dates of the ancient earth-<lb break="no" />quakes. We only know that, in times<lb break="yes"/>nearer our own, the year 1776 was at<lb break="yes"/>the same time the most fatal to the co-<lb break="no"/>lonists, and the most remarkable for<lb break="yes"/>the natural history of the country.<lb break="yes"/>A drought, like those which are felt<lb break="yes"/>at times in the islands of Cape Verd,<lb break="yes"/>had reigned during fifteen months,<lb break="yes"/>when, on the 21st of October, 1766,<lb break="yes"/>the city of Cumana was entirely de-<lb break="no" />stroyed. The remembrance of this<lb break="yes"/>day is every year renewed by a religi-<lb break="no"/>ous festival, attended with a solemn<lb break="yes" />procession. The whole of the houses<lb break="yes"/>were overturned in the space of a few<lb break="yes"/>minutes, and the shocks were hourly<lb break="yes"/>repeated during fourteen months. In<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">several</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="605" facs="#f0019"/>
                    <cb/> several parts of the province the earth<lb break="yes"/>opened, and threw out sulphureous<lb break="yes"/>waters. These irruptions were very<lb break="yes"/>frequent in a plain extending toward<lb break="yes"/>Casanay, two leagues to the east of<lb break="yes"/>the town of Cariaco, and known by<lb break="yes"/>the name of the hollow ground, <hi rendition="#i">tierra<lb break="yes"/>hueca,</hi> because it appears entirely un-<lb break="no" />dermined by thermal springs. Du-<lb break="no"/>ring the years 1766 and 1767, the inha-<lb break="no"/>bitants of Cumana encamped in the<lb break="yes" />streets; and they began to rebuild<lb break="yes"/>their houses, when the earthquakes<lb break="yes"/>took place only once a month. What<lb break="yes"/>was felt at Quito, immediately after<lb break="yes"/>the great catastrophe of the 4th of Fe-<lb break="no"/>bruary, 1797, took place on these<lb break="yes"/>coasts. While the ground was in a<lb break="yes" />state of continual oscillation, the at-<lb break="no"/>mosphere seemed to dissolve itself<lb break="yes"/>into water. The rivers were swollen<lb break="yes"/>by these sudden torrents of rain, the<lb break="yes"/>year was extremely fertile, and the In-<lb break="no"/>dians, whose frail huts easily resist the<lb break="yes"/>strongest shocks, celebrated, from ideas<lb break="yes"/>of an old superstition, with feasting<lb break="yes"/>and dances, the destruction of the<lb break="yes"/>world, and the approaching <choice>
                        <sic>epocha</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">epochs</corr>
                    </choice> of<lb break="yes"/>its regeneration.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Tradition states, that in the earth-<lb break="no"/>quake of 1766, as well as in another<lb break="yes"/>very remarkable one in 1794, the<lb break="yes" />shocks were mere horizontal oscilla-<lb break="no"/>tions; it was only on the disastrous<lb break="yes"/>day of the 14th of December, 1797,<lb break="yes" />that for the first time at Cumana the<lb break="yes"/>motion was felt by the raising up of<lb break="yes"/>the ground. More than four-fifths of<lb break="yes"/>the city were then entirely destroyed;<lb break="yes"/>and the shock, attended by a very loud<lb break="yes"/>subterraneous noise, resembled, as at<lb break="yes"/>Riobamba, the explosion of a mine at<lb break="yes"/>a great depth. Happily the most<lb break="yes"/>violent shock was preceded by a slight<lb break="yes"/>undulating motion, so that the greater<lb break="yes" />part of the inhabitants could escape<lb break="yes"/>into the streets, and a small number<lb break="yes"/>only perished of those who had assem-<lb break="no" />bled in the churches. It is a generally<lb break="yes"/>received opinion at Cumana, that the<lb break="yes"/>most destructive earthquakes are an-<lb break="no"/>nounced by very feeble oscillations,<lb break="yes"/>and by a hollow sound, which does<lb break="yes"/>not escape the observation of persons<lb break="yes"/>habituated to this kind of phenome-<lb break="no" />non. In this fatal moment the cries<lb break="yes"/>of <hi rendition="#i" >misericordia, tembla, tembla,</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">Mercy! the earth trembles.</note> are<lb break="yes" />every where heard; and it is very<lb break="yes"/>rarely that a false alarm is given by a<lb break="yes"/>native. Those who are most fearful<lb break="yes" />attentively observe the motions of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>dogs, goats, and swine. The last of<lb break="yes"/>these animals, endowed with delicate<lb break="yes"/>olfactory nerves, and accustomed to<lb break="yes" />turn up the earth, give warning of<lb break="yes"/>approaching danger, by their restless-<lb break="no"/>ness and their cries. We shall not<lb break="yes" />decide, whether, placed nearer the<lb break="yes"/>surface of the ground, they are the<lb break="yes"/>first that hear the subterraneous noise;<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">or whether their organs receive the impres-<lb break="no" />sion of some gaseous emanation, which issues<lb break="yes"/>from the earth.</hi> We cannot deny the<lb break="yes"/>possibility of this latter cause. During<lb break="yes"/>my abode at Peru, a fact was observed<lb break="yes"/>in the inland country, which has an<lb break="yes"/>analogy with this kind of phænomenon,<lb break="yes"/>and which is not unfrequent. At the<lb break="yes"/>end of violent earthquakes, the herbs<lb break="yes" />that cover the savannahs of Tucuman<lb break="yes"/>acquired noxious properties; an epi-<lb break="no"/>demic disorder took place among the<lb break="yes"/>cattle, and <hi rendition="#i">a great number among them<lb break="yes"/>appeared stupified or suffocated by the dele-<lb break="no" />terious vapours exhaled from the ground.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At Cumana, half an hour before the<lb break="yes"/>catastrophe of the 14th of December,<lb break="yes"/>1797, a strong smell of sulphur was<lb break="yes" />perceived near the hill of the convent<lb break="yes"/>of St. Francis; and on the same spot<lb break="yes"/>a subterraneous noise, which seemed<lb break="yes" />to proceed from the south east to the<lb break="yes"/>north-west, was heard the loudest.<lb break="yes"/>At the same time flames appeared on<lb break="yes" />the banks of the Manzanares, near the<lb break="yes"/>hospice of the Capuchins, and in the<lb break="yes"/>gulf of Cariaco, near Mariguitar. This<lb break="yes"/>last phænomenon, so extraordinary in<lb break="yes"/>a country not volcanic, is pretty fre-<lb break="no"/>quent in the Alpine calcareous moun-<lb break="no"/>tains near Cumanacoa, in the valley<lb break="yes"/>of Bordones, in the island of Marga-<lb break="no"/>retta, and amidst the <hi rendition="#i">Llanos,</hi> or savan-<lb break="no"/>nahs of New Andalusia. In these<lb break="yes"/>savannahs flakes of fire rise to a con-<lb break="no" />siderable height; they are seen for<lb break="yes"/>hours together in the dryest places;<lb break="yes"/>and it is asserted, that, on examining<lb break="yes"/>the ground which furnishes the inflam-<lb break="no"/>mable matter, no crevice is to be<lb break="yes"/>found. This fire, which resembles the<lb break="yes"/>sources of hydrogen, or <hi rendition="#i">Salse,</hi> of Mo-<lb break="no"/>dena, or what is called the Will-o’-the-<lb break="maybe" />wisp of our marshes, does not burn<lb break="yes"/>the grass; because, no doubt the co-<lb break="no"/>lumn of gas, which developes itself,<lb break="yes" />is mixed with azot, and carbonic<lb break="yes"/>acid, and does not burn at its basis.<lb break="yes"/>The people, although less supersti-<lb break="no" />tious here than in Spain, call these<lb break="yes"/>reddish flames by the singular name<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i">soul of the tyrant Aguirre</hi>; ima-<lb break="no"/>gining, that the spectre of Lopez<lb break="yes"/>Aguirre, harassed by remorse, wan-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">ders</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="606" facs="#f0020"/>
                    <cb/>ders over these countries sullied by<lb break="yes"/>his crimes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">causes.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We can scarcely doubt, that the<lb break="yes"/>earth, when opened and agitated by<lb break="yes"/>shocks, spreads occasionally gaseous<lb break="yes" />emanations through the atmosphere,<lb break="yes"/>in places remote from the mouths of<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes not extinct. At Cumana,<lb break="yes"/>as we have already observed, flames<lb break="yes"/>and vapors mixed with sulphurous<lb break="yes"/>acid spring up from the most arid soil.<lb break="yes"/>In other parts of the same province,<lb break="yes"/>the earth ejects water and petroleum.<lb break="yes"/>At Riobamba, a muddy and inflam-<lb break="no"/>mable mass, which is called <hi rendition="#i">moya,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>issues from crevices that close again,<lb break="yes"/>and accumulates into elevated hills.<lb break="yes"/>At seven leagues from Lisbon, near<lb break="yes"/>Colares, during the terrible earth-<lb break="no" />quake of the first of November, 1755,<lb break="yes"/>flames and a column of thick smoke<lb break="yes"/>were seen to issue from the flanks of<lb break="yes" />the rocks of Alvidras, and, according<lb break="yes"/>to some witnesses, from the bosom of<lb break="yes"/>the sea. This smoke lasted several<lb break="yes" />days, and it was the more abundant<lb break="yes"/>in proportion as the subterraneous<lb break="yes"/>noise, which accompanied the shocks,<lb break="yes"/>was louder.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I am inclined to think, that in the<lb break="yes"/>greater part of earthquakes nothing<lb break="yes"/>escapes from the agitated earth; and<lb break="yes" />that, where gaseous emanations and<lb break="yes"/>vapours take place, they oftener ac-<lb break="no"/>company, or follow, than precede the<lb break="yes" />shocks. This last circumstance ex-<lb break="no"/>plains a fact, which seems indubitable;<lb break="yes"/>I mean that mysterious influence, in<lb break="yes"/>equinoctial America, of earthquakes<lb break="yes"/>on the climate, and on the order of<lb break="yes"/>the dry and rainy seasons. If the earth<lb break="yes"/>generally acts on the air only at the<lb break="yes" />moment of the shocks, we can con-<lb break="no"/>ceive why it is so rare, that a sensible<lb break="yes"/>meteorological change becomes the<lb break="yes" />presage of these great revolutions of<lb break="yes"/>nature.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The hypothesis according to which,<lb break="yes"/>in the earthquakes of Cumana, elastic<lb break="yes"/>fluids tend to escape from the surface<lb break="yes"/>of the soil, seems confirmed by the<lb break="yes"/>observation of the dreadful noise,<lb break="yes"/>which is heard during the shocks at<lb break="yes"/>the borders of the wells in the <hi rendition="#i">plain of<lb break="yes"/>Charas.</hi> Water and sand are sometimes<lb break="yes" />thrown out twenty feet high. Similar<lb break="yes"/>phænomena have not escaped the ob-<lb break="no"/>servation of the ancients, who inha-<lb break="no"/>bited parts of Greece and Asia Minor<lb break="yes"/>abounding with caverns, crevices, and<lb break="yes"/>subterraneous rivers. Nature, in its<lb break="yes"/>uniform progress, every where sug-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/> gests the same ideas of the causes of<lb break="yes"/>earthquakes, and the means by which<lb break="yes"/>man, forgetting the measure of his<lb break="yes" />strength, pretends to diminish the<lb break="yes"/>effect of the subterraneous explosions.<lb break="yes"/>What a great Roman naturalist has<lb break="yes" />said of the utility of wells and caverns,<lb break="yes"/>is repeated in the New World by the<lb break="yes"/>most ignorant Indians of Quito, when<lb break="yes"/>they show travellers the <hi rendition="#i">guaicos,</hi> or<lb break="yes"/>crevices of Pichincha.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The subterraneous noise, so frequent<lb break="yes"/>during earthquakes, is generally not<lb break="yes"/>in the ratio of the strength of the<lb break="yes" />shocks. At Cumana it constantly<lb break="yes"/>precedes them, while at Quito, and<lb break="yes"/>for a short time past at Caracas, and<lb break="yes"/>in the West India Islands, a noise like<lb break="yes"/>the discharge of a battery was heard,<lb break="yes"/>a long time after the shocks had ceased.<lb break="yes"/>A third kind of phænomenon, the<lb break="yes"/>most remarkable of the whole, is the<lb break="yes"/>rolling of those subterraneous thun-<lb break="no"/>ders, which last several months, with-<lb break="no"/>out being accompanied by the least<lb break="yes"/>oscillating motion of the ground.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In every country subject to earth-<lb break="no"/>quakes, the point where, probably by<lb break="yes"/>a particular disposition of the stony<lb break="yes" />strata, the effects are the most sen-<lb break="no"/>sible is considered as the cause and<lb break="yes"/>the focus of the shocks. Thus at Cu-<lb break="no" />mana the hill of the castle of St. An-<lb break="no"/>tonio, and particularly the eminence<lb break="yes"/>on which the convent of St. Francis is<lb break="yes"/>placed, are believed to contain an<lb break="yes"/>enormous quantity of sulphur, and<lb break="yes"/>other inflammable matter. We for-<lb break="no"/>get, that the rapidity with which the<lb break="yes" />undulations are propagated to great<lb break="yes"/>distances, even across the basin of the<lb break="yes"/>ocean, proves, that the centre of ac-<lb break="no" />tion is very remote from the surface<lb break="yes"/>of the globe. From this same cause,<lb break="yes"/>no doubt, earthquakes are not re-<lb break="no" />strained to certain species of rocks, as<lb break="yes"/>some naturalists pretend, but all are<lb break="yes"/>fitted to propagate the movement.<lb break="yes"/>In order to keep within the limits of<lb break="yes"/>my own experience, I shall here cite the<lb break="yes"/>granites of Lima and Acapulco; the<lb break="yes"/>gneiss of Caracas; the mica-slate of<lb break="yes"/>the peninsula of Araya; the primi-<lb break="no"/>tive <choice>
                        <sic>thouschiefer</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">thonschiefer</corr>
                    </choice> of Tepecuacuilco, in<lb break="yes"/>Mexico; the secondary lime-stones of<lb break="yes"/>the Apennines, Spain, and new Anda-<lb break="no"/>lusia; and finally the trappean por-<lb break="no"/>phyries of the provinces of Quito and<lb break="yes"/>Popayan. In these different places<lb break="yes"/>the ground is frequently agitated by<lb break="yes"/>the most violent shocks; but some-<lb break="no"/>times, in the same rock, the superior<lb break="yes" />strata form invincible obstacles to the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">propagation</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="607" facs="#f0021"/>
                    <cb/>propagation of the motion. Thus,<lb break="yes"/>in the mines of Saxony, we have seen<lb break="yes"/>workmen hasten up affrighted by oscil-<lb break="no" />lations, which were not felt at the<lb break="yes"/>surface of the ground.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If, in regions the most remote from<lb break="yes"/>each other, primitive, secondary, and<lb break="yes"/>volcanic rocks, share equally in the<lb break="yes"/>convulsive movements of the globe,<lb break="yes"/>we cannot but admire also, that, in<lb break="yes"/>ground of little extent, certain classes<lb break="yes"/>of rocks oppose themselves to the<lb break="yes" />propagation of the shocks. At Cu-<lb break="no"/>mana, for instance, before the great<lb break="yes"/>catastrophe of 1797, the earthquakes<lb break="yes" />were felt only along the southern and<lb break="yes"/>calcareous coast of the gulf of Caria-<lb break="no"/>co, as far as the town of this name;<lb break="yes"/>while in the peninsula of Araya, and<lb break="yes"/>at the village of Maniquarez, the<lb break="yes"/>ground did not partake of the same<lb break="yes"/>agitation. The inhabitants of this<lb break="yes"/>northern coast, which is composed of<lb break="yes"/>mica-slate, built their huts on a mo-<lb break="no"/>tionless earth; a gulf three or four<lb break="yes" />thousand toises in breadth separated<lb break="yes"/>them from a plain covered with ruins,<lb break="yes"/>and overturned by earthquakes. This<lb break="yes" />security, founded on the experience of<lb break="yes"/>several ages, has vanished; and, since<lb break="yes"/>the 14th of December, 1797, new<lb break="yes"/>communications appear to have been<lb break="yes"/>opened in the interior of the globe.<lb break="yes"/>At present the peninsula of Araya is<lb break="yes"/>not merely subject to the agitations of<lb break="yes" />the soil of Cumana, the promontory<lb break="yes"/>of mica-slate is become in its turn a<lb break="yes"/>particular centre of the movements.<lb break="yes" />The earth is sometimes strongly shaken<lb break="yes"/>at the village of Maniquarez, when<lb break="yes"/>on the coast of Cumana the inhabitants<lb break="yes"/>enjoy the most perfect tranquillity.<lb break="yes"/>The gulf of Cariaco nevertheless is<lb break="yes"/>only sixty or eighty fathoms deep.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The earthquakes of Cumana are<lb break="yes"/>connected with those of the West In-<lb break="no"/>dia islands; and it has even been sus-<lb break="no" />pected, that they have some connec-<lb break="no"/>tion with the volcanic phænomena of<lb break="yes"/>the Cordilleras of the Andes. On<lb break="yes" />the 4th of November, 1797, the soil<lb break="yes"/>of the province of Quito underwent<lb break="yes"/>such a destructive commotion, that,<lb break="yes" />notwithstanding the extreme feeble-<lb break="no"/>ness of the population of that country,<lb break="yes"/>near 40,000 natives perished, buried<lb break="yes"/>under the ruins of their houses, swal-<lb break="no"/>lowed up in the crevices, or drowned<lb break="yes"/>in lakes that were suddenly formed.<lb break="yes"/>At the same period, the inhabitants of<lb break="yes"/>the eastern Antilles were alarmed by<lb break="yes"/>shocks, which continued during eight<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> months, when the volcano of <choice>
                        <sic>Gauda-<lb break="no"/>loupe</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Guada-<lb break="no"/>loupe</corr>
                    </choice> threw out pumice stones, ashes,<lb break="yes"/>and gusts of sulphureous vapors. This<lb break="yes"/>eruption of the 27th of September,<lb break="yes"/>during which very long-continued sub-<lb break="no"/>terraneous noises were heard, was fol-<lb break="no"/>lowed on the 14th of December by<lb break="yes"/>the great earthquake of Cumana.<lb break="yes"/>Another volcano of the West India<lb break="yes"/>islands, that of St. Vincents, has lately<lb break="yes"/>given a fresh instance of these extra-<lb break="no"/>ordinary connections. This volcano<lb break="yes"/>had not emitted flames since 1718,<lb break="yes"/>when they burst forth anew, in 1812.<lb break="yes"/>The total ruin of the city of Caracas<lb break="yes"/>preceded this explosion thirty-five<lb break="yes"/>days, and violent oscillations of the<lb break="yes"/>ground were felt, both in the islands,<lb break="yes"/>and on the coasts of Terra Firma.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Every thing in earthquakes seems to<lb break="yes"/>indicate the action of elastic fluids<lb break="yes"/>seeking an outlet to spread themselves<lb break="yes"/>in the atmosphere. Often, on the<lb break="yes"/>coasts of the South Sea, the action is<lb break="yes"/>almost instantaneously communicated<lb break="yes"/>from Chili to the gulf of Guayaquil,<lb break="yes"/>a distance of six hundred leagues;<lb break="yes"/>and, what is very remarkable, the<lb break="yes"/>shocks appear to be so much the<lb break="yes"/>stronger, as the country is more dis-<lb break="no"/>tant from burning volcanoes. The<lb break="yes"/>granitic mountains of Calabria, cover-<lb break="no"/>ed with very recent breccia, the cal-<lb break="no"/>careous chain of the Apennines, the<lb break="yes"/>country of Pignerol, the coasts of Por-<lb break="no" />tugal and Greece, those of Peru and<lb break="yes"/>Terra Firma, afford striking proofs of<lb break="yes"/>this assertion. The globe, it may be<lb break="yes"/>said, is agitated with greater force,<lb break="yes"/>in proportion as the surface has a<lb break="yes"/>smaller number of funnels communi-<lb break="no"/>cating with the caverns of the interior.<lb break="yes"/>At Naples and at Messina, at the foot<lb break="yes"/>of Cotopaxi and of Tunguragua, earth-<lb break="no"/>quakes are dreaded only when vapours<lb break="yes"/>and flames do not issue from the cra-<lb break="no" />ter. In the kingdom of Quito, the<lb break="yes"/>great catastrophe of Riobamba, which<lb break="yes"/>we have before mentioned, has led<lb break="yes" />several well-informed persons to think,<lb break="yes"/>that this unfortunate country would<lb break="yes"/>be less often desolate, if the subter-<lb break="no"/>raneous fire should break the porphy-<lb break="no"/>ritic dome of Chimborazo; and if this<lb break="yes"/>colossal mountain should become a<lb break="yes"/>burning volcano. At all times ana-<lb break="no"/>logous facts have led to the same hy-<lb break="no"/>pothesis. The Greeks, who, like<lb break="yes"/>ourselves, attributed the oscillations<lb break="yes"/>of the ground to the tension of elastic<lb break="yes"/>fluids, cited in favour of their opinion<lb break="yes"/>the total cessation of the shocks at<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="608" facs="#f0022"/>
                    <cb/> the island of Eubœa, by the opening<lb break="yes"/>of a crevice in the Lelantine plain.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We have endeavoured to collect at<lb break="yes"/>the end of this chapter, the general<lb break="yes"/>phænomena of earthquakes under dif-<lb break="no" />ferent climates. We have shown,<lb break="yes"/>that subterraneous vapours are sub-<lb break="no"/>jected to laws as uniform as the mix-<lb break="no" />ture of gaseous fluids, which con-<lb break="no"/>stitutes our atmosphere. We have<lb break="yes"/>abstained from all discussion of the<lb break="yes" />nature of the chemical agents, which<lb break="yes"/>are the causes of the great derange-<lb break="no"/>ments that the surface of the earth un-<lb break="no"/>dergoes from time to time. It is suffi-<lb break="no"/>cient here to observe, that these causes<lb break="yes"/>are concealed at immense depths; and<lb break="yes"/>that we must seek them in the rocks<lb break="yes" />which we call primitive, perhaps even<lb break="yes"/>below the earthy and oxided crust of<lb break="yes"/>the globe, in the abysses that contain<lb break="yes"/>the metalloidal bases of silex, lime,<lb break="yes"/>soda, and potash.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">slave market.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The slaves exposed to sale were<lb break="yes"/>young men from fifteen to twenty<lb break="yes"/>years of age. Every morning cocoa-<lb break="no"/>nut oil was distributed among them,<lb break="yes"/>with which they rubbed their bodies,<lb break="yes"/>to give their skin a black polish. The<lb break="yes"/>persons who came to purchase exami-<lb break="no"/>ned the teeth of these slaves, to judge<lb break="yes"/>of their age and health; forcing open<lb break="yes"/>their mouths as we do those of horses<lb break="yes" />in a market. This degrading custom<lb break="yes"/>dates from Africa, as is proved by the<lb break="yes"/>faithful picture, which, in one of his<lb break="yes"/>dramatic pieces, Cervantes, released<lb break="yes"/>from his long captivity among the<lb break="yes"/>Moors, has drawn of the sale of the<lb break="yes"/>Christian slaves at Algiers. It is dis-<lb break="no"/>tressing to think, that even at this day<lb break="yes"/>there exist European colonists in the<lb break="yes"/>West Indies, who mark their slaves<lb break="yes"/>with a hot iron, to know them again<lb break="yes"/>if they escape. This is the treatment<lb break="yes"/>bestowed on those, “who save other<lb break="yes" />men the trouble of sowing, tilling, and<lb break="yes"/>reaping, in order to live.”</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">phosphorescent insects.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The night was delightfully cool;<lb break="yes"/>swarms of phosphorescent insects glit-<lb break="no"/>tered in the air, and over a soil cover-<lb break="no" />ed with sesuvium, and groves of mi-<lb break="no"/>mosa, that bordered the river. We<lb break="yes"/>know how common the glow-worm is<lb break="yes"/>in Italy, and in all the south of Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope; but the picturesque effect it<lb break="yes"/>produces cannot be compared to those<lb break="yes" />innumerable, scattered, and moving<lb break="yes"/>lights, that embellish the nights of the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone, and seem to repeat on<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>the earth, along the vast extent of the<lb break="yes"/>savannahs, the spectacle of the starry<lb break="yes"/>vault of the sky.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 