<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.1" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.1" when="2018-10-10" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung für Verlag.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="272" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Earthquakes in</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Cumana.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">(From the same.)</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">I</hi>T is a very generally received opi-<lb break="no" />nion on the coasts of Cumana, and<lb break="yes"/>in the island of Margaretta, that the<lb break="yes"/>gulf of Cariaco owes its existence to a<lb break="yes" />rent of the continent, attended by an<lb break="yes"/>irruption of the ocean. The remem-<lb break="no"/>brance of this great revolution was<lb break="yes" />preserved among the Indians to the<lb break="yes"/>end of the fifteenth century; and it is<lb break="yes"/>related that, at the time of the third<lb break="yes"/>voyage of Christopher Columbus, the<lb break="yes"/>natives mentioned it as a very recent<lb break="yes"/>event. In 1530 the inhabitants were<lb break="yes"/>alarmed by new shocks on the coasts<lb break="yes"/>of Paria and Cumana. The lands<lb break="yes"/>were inundated by the sea, and the<lb break="yes"/>small fort, built by James Castellon at<lb break="yes" />New Toledo, was entirely destroyed.<lb break="yes"/>At the same time an enormous open-<lb break="no"/>ing was formed in the mountains of<lb break="yes" />Cariaco, on the shores of the gulf that<lb break="yes"/>bears this name, when a great body<lb break="yes"/>of salt water, mixed with asphaltum,<lb break="yes" />issued from the micaceous schist.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Earthquakes were very frequent to-<lb break="no"/>ward the end of the sixteenth century;<lb break="yes"/>and, according to the traditions pre-<lb break="no"/>served at Cumana, the sea often inun-<lb break="no"/>dated the shores, rising from fifteen to<lb break="yes"/>twenty fathoms. The inhabitants fled<lb break="yes"/>to the Cerro of San Antonia, and to<lb break="yes"/>the hill where now stands the small<lb break="yes"/>convent of St Francis. It is even<lb break="yes" />thought that these frequent inunda-<lb break="no"/>tions induced the inhabitants to build<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>that quarter of the town, which is<lb break="yes"/>backed by the mountain, and stands<lb break="yes"/>on a part of its declivity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As no record exists at Cumana, and<lb break="yes"/>its archives, on account of the conti-<lb break="no"/>nual devastations of the termites, or<lb break="yes" />white ants, contain no document that<lb break="yes"/>goes back further than a hundred and<lb break="yes"/>fifty years, we are unacquainted with<lb break="yes" />the precise dates of the ancient earth-<lb break="no"/>quakes. We only know that, in times<lb break="yes"/>nearer our own, the year 1776 was at<lb break="yes"/>the same time the most fatal to the<lb break="yes"/>colonists, and the most remarkable<lb break="yes"/>for the natural history of the country.<lb break="yes"/>A drought, like those which are felt<lb break="yes" />at times in the islands of Cape Verd,<lb break="yes"/>had reigned during fifteen months,<lb break="yes"/>when, on the 21st of October, 1766,<lb break="yes"/>the city of Cumana was entirely de-<lb break="no"/>stroyed. The remembrance of this<lb break="yes"/>day is every year renewed by a religi-<lb break="no"/>ous festival, attended with a solemn<lb break="yes"/>procession. The whole of the houses<lb break="yes"/>were overturned in the space of a few<lb break="yes"/>minutes, and the shocks were hourly<lb break="yes"/>repeated during fourteen months. In<lb break="yes"/>several parts of the province the earth<lb break="yes"/>opened, and threw out sulphureous<lb break="yes" />waters. These eruptions were very<lb break="yes"/>frequent in a plain extending toward<lb break="yes"/>Casanay, two leagues to the east of<lb break="yes"/>the town of Cariaco, and known by<lb break="yes"/>the name of the hollow ground, <hi rendition="#i">tierra<lb break="yes"/>hueca,</hi> because it appears entirely un-<lb break="no"/>dermined by thermal springs. During<lb break="yes"/>the years 1766 and 1767, the inhabi-<lb break="no"/>tants of Cumana encamped in the<lb break="yes"/>streets; and they began to rebuild<lb break="yes"/>their houses, when the earthquakes<lb break="yes"/>took place only once a month. What<lb break="yes"/>was felt at Quito, immediately after<lb break="yes"/>the great catastrophe of the fourth of<lb break="yes" />February, 1797, took place on these<lb break="yes"/>coasts. While the ground was in a<lb break="yes"/>state of continual oscillation, the at-<lb break="no" />mosphere seemed to dissolve itself in-<lb break="no"/>to water. The rivers were swollen<lb break="yes"/>by these sudden torrents of rain, the<lb break="yes"/>year was extremely fertile, and the<lb break="yes"/>Indians, whose frail huts easily resist<lb break="yes"/>the strongest shocks, celebrated from<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">ideas</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="273" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>ideas of an old superstition, with feast-<lb break="no"/>ing and dances, the destruction of the<lb break="yes"/>world, and the approaching epocha of<lb break="yes"/>its regeneration.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Tradition states, that in the earth-<lb break="no"/>quake of 1766, as well as in another<lb break="yes"/>very remarkable one in 1794, the<lb break="yes" />shocks were mere horizontal oscilla-<lb break="no"/>tions; it was only on the disastrous<lb break="yes"/>day of the 14th of December, 1797,<lb break="yes" />that, for the first time at Cumana, the<lb break="yes"/>motion was felt by the raising up of<lb break="yes"/>the ground. More than four-fifths of<lb break="yes"/>the city were then entirely destroyed;<lb break="yes"/>and the shock, attended by a very loud<lb break="yes"/>subterraneous noise, resembled, as at<lb break="yes"/>Riobamba, the explosion of a mine at<lb break="yes"/>a great depth. Happily the most<lb break="yes"/>violent shock was preceded by a slight<lb break="yes"/>undulating motion, so that the greater<lb break="yes" />part of the inhabitants could escape<lb break="yes"/>into the streets, and a small number<lb break="yes"/>only perished of those who had assem-<lb break="no" />bled in the churches. It is a generally<lb break="yes"/>received opinion at Cumana, that the<lb break="yes"/>most destructive earthquakes are an-<lb break="no"/>nounced by very feeble oscillations,<lb break="yes"/>and by a hollow sound, which does<lb break="yes"/>not escape the observation of persons<lb break="yes"/>habituated to this kind of phenome-<lb break="no" />non. In this fatal moment the cries<lb break="yes"/>of <hi rendition="#i" >misericordia, trembla, trembla</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">Mercy! the earth trembles.</note>,<lb break="yes"/>are every where heard; and it is very<lb break="yes"/>rarely that a false alarm is given by a<lb break="yes"/>native. Those who are most fearful,<lb break="yes"/>attentively observe the motions of<lb break="yes"/>dogs, goats, and swine. The last of<lb break="yes"/>these animals, endowed with delicate<lb break="yes"/>olfactory nerves, and accustomed to<lb break="yes"/>turn up the earth, give warning of<lb break="yes"/>approaching danger, by their restless-<lb break="no"/>ness and their cries. We shall not<lb break="yes"/>decide, whether, placed nearer the<lb break="yes"/>surface of the ground, they are the<lb break="yes"/>first that hear the subterraneous noise;<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">or whether their organs receive the<lb break="yes" />impression of some gaseous emanation,<lb break="yes"/>which issues from the earth.</hi> We<lb break="yes"/>cannot deny the possibility of this<lb break="yes"/>latter cause. During my abode at<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>Peru, a fact was observed in the in-<lb break="no"/>land country, which has an analogy<lb break="yes"/>with this kind of ph&#x00E6;nomenon, and<lb break="yes" />which is not unfrequent. At the end<lb break="yes"/>of violent earthquakes, the herbs that<lb break="yes"/>cover the savannahs of Tucuman ac-<lb break="no" />quired noxious properties; an epide-<lb break="no"/>mic disorder took place among the<lb break="yes"/>cattle, and <hi rendition="#i">a great number among<lb break="yes"/>them appeared stupified, or suffocated,<lb break="yes"/>by the deleterious vapours exhaled<lb break="yes"/>from the ground.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At Cumana, half an hour before<lb break="yes"/>the catastrophe of the 14th December,<lb break="yes"/>1797, a strong smell of sulphur was<lb break="yes" />perceived near the hill of the convent<lb break="yes"/>of St Francis; and on the same spot<lb break="yes"/>a subterraneous noise, which seemed<lb break="yes" />to proceed from the south-east to the<lb break="yes"/>north-west, was heard the loudest.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>At the same time flames appeared on<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the Manzanares, near the<lb break="yes"/>hospice of the Capuchins, and in the<lb break="yes"/>gulf of Cariaco, near Mariguitar.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>This last ph&#x00E6;nomenon, so extraordi-<lb break="no"/>nary in a country not volcanic, is pret-<lb break="no"/>ty frequent in the alpine calcareous<lb break="yes"/>mountains near Cumanacoa, in the<lb break="yes"/>valley of Bordones, in the island of<lb break="yes" />Margaretta, and amidst the <hi rendition="#i">Llanos,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>or savannahs of New Andalusia. In<lb break="yes"/>these savannahs flakes of fire rise consi-<lb break="no"/>derably high; they are seen for hours<lb break="yes"/>together in the dryest places; and it<lb break="yes" />is asserted, that, on examining the<lb break="yes"/>ground which furnishes the inflamma-<lb break="no"/>ble matter, no crevice is to be found.<lb break="yes"/>This fire, which resembles the sources<lb break="yes"/>of hydrogen, or <hi rendition="#i">Salse,</hi> of Modena, or<lb break="yes"/>what is called the Will-o&#x2019;-the-wisp of<lb break="yes"/>our marches, does not burn the grass;<lb break="yes"/>because, no doubt, the column of gas<lb break="yes" />which developes itself, is mixed with<lb break="yes"/>azot, and carbonic acid, and does not<lb break="yes"/>burn at its basis. The people, altho&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>less superstitious here than in Spain,<lb break="yes"/>call these reddish flames by the singu-<lb break="no"/>lar name of the <hi rendition="#i">soul of the tyrant A-<lb break="no"/>guirre;</hi> imagining, that the spectre of<lb break="yes"/>Lopez Aguirre, harrassed by remorse,<lb break="yes"/>wanders over these countries sullied by<lb break="yes"/>his crimes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">We</fw>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="274" facs="#f0003"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>We can scarcely doubt, that the<lb break="yes"/>earth, when opened and agitated by<lb break="yes"/>shocks, spreads occasionally gaseous<lb break="yes" />emanations through the atmosphere,<lb break="yes"/>in places remote from the mouths of<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes not extinct. At Cumana,<lb break="yes"/>as we have already observed, flames<lb break="yes"/>and vapours mixed with sulphurous<lb break="yes"/>acid spring up from the most arid soil.<lb break="yes"/>In other parts of the same province,<lb break="yes"/>the earth ejects water and petroleum.<lb break="yes"/>At Riobamba, a muddy and inflam-<lb break="no"/>mable mass, which is called <hi rendition="#i">moya,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>issues from crevices that close again,<lb break="yes"/>and accumulates into elevated hills.<lb break="yes"/>At seven leagues from Lisbon, near<lb break="yes"/>Colares, during the terrible earth-<lb break="no" />quake of the first of November 1755,<lb break="yes"/>flames and a column of thick smoke<lb break="yes"/>were seen to issue from the flanks of<lb break="yes" />the rocks of Alvidras, and, according<lb break="yes"/>to some witnesses, from the bosom of<lb break="yes"/>the sea. This smoke lasted several<lb break="yes" />days, and it was the more abundant<lb break="yes"/>in proportion as the subterraneous<lb break="yes"/>noise, which accompanied the shocks,<lb break="yes"/>was louder.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I am inclined to think, that in the<lb break="yes"/>greater part of earthquakes nothing<lb break="yes"/>escapes from the agitated earth; and<lb break="yes" />that, where gaseous emanations and<lb break="yes"/>vapours take place, they oftener ac-<lb break="no"/>company, or follow, than precede the<lb break="yes" />shocks. This last circumstance ex-<lb break="no"/>plains a fact, which seems indubitable;<lb break="yes"/>I mean that mysterious influence, in<lb break="yes"/>equinoctial America, of earthquakes<lb break="yes"/>on the climate, and on the order of<lb break="yes"/>the dry and rainy seasons. If the earth<lb break="yes"/>generally act on the air only at the<lb break="yes" />moment of the shocks, we can con-<lb break="no"/>ceive why it is so rare, that a sensible<lb break="yes"/>meteorological change becomes the<lb break="yes" />presage of these great revolutions of<lb break="yes"/>nature.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The hypothesis according to which,<lb break="yes"/>in the earthquakes of Cumana, elastic<lb break="yes"/>fluids tend to escape from the surface<lb break="yes"/>of the soil, seems confirmed by the<lb break="yes"/>observation of the dreadful noise,<lb break="yes"/>which is heard during the shocks at<lb break="yes"/>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>he</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">the</corr> 
                    </choice>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>bord ers</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">borders</corr>
                    </choice> of the wells in the <hi rendition="#i">plain of</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Charas.</hi> Water and sand are sometimes<lb break="yes" />thrown out twenty feet high. Similar<lb break="yes"/>ph&#x00E6;nomena have not escaped the ob-<lb break="no"/>servation of the ancients, who inha-<lb break="no"/>bited parts of Greece and Asia Minor,<lb break="yes"/>abounding with caverns, crevices, and<lb break="yes"/>subterraneous rivers. Nature, in its<lb break="yes"/>uniform progress, every where sug-<lb break="no"/>gests the same ideas of the causes of<lb break="yes"/>earthquakes, and the means by which<lb break="yes"/>man, forgetting the measure of his<lb break="yes" />strength, pretends to diminish the<lb break="yes"/>effect of the subterraneous explosions.<lb break="yes"/>What a great Roman naturalist has<lb break="yes" />said of the utility of wells and caverns,<lb break="yes"/>is repeated in the New World by the<lb break="yes"/>most ignorant Indians of Quito, when<lb break="yes"/>they show travellers the <hi rendition="#i">guaicos,</hi> or<lb break="yes"/>crevices of Pichincha.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The subterraneous noise, so frequent<lb break="yes"/>during earthquakes, is generally not<lb break="yes"/>in the ratio of the strength of the<lb break="yes" />shocks. At Cumana it constantly<lb break="yes"/>precedes them, while at Quito, and<lb break="yes"/>for a short time past at Caracas, and<lb break="yes"/>in the West India Islands, a noise like<lb break="yes"/>the discharge of a battery was heard,<lb break="yes"/>a long time after the shocks had cea-<lb break="no" />sed. A third kind of ph&#x00E6;nomenon,<lb break="yes"/>the most remarkable of the whole, is<lb break="yes"/>the rolling of those subterraneous<lb break="yes" />thunders, which last several months,<lb break="yes"/>without being accompanied by the<lb break="yes"/>least oscillating motion of the ground.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In every country subject to earth-<lb break="no"/>quakes, the point where, probably by<lb break="yes"/>a particular disposition of the stony<lb break="yes" />strata, the effects are the most sen-<lb break="no"/>sible, is considered as the cause and<lb break="yes"/>the focus of the shocks. Thus at Cu-<lb break="no" />mana the hill of the castle of St An-<lb break="no"/>tonio, and particularly the eminence<lb break="yes"/>on which the convent of St Francis is<lb break="yes"/>placed, are believed to contain an<lb break="yes"/>enormous quantity of sulphur, and<lb break="yes"/>other inflammable matter. We for-<lb break="no"/>get, that the rapidity with which the<lb break="yes" />undulations are propagated to great<lb break="yes"/>distances, even across the basin of the<lb break="yes"/>ocean, proves, that the centre of ac-<lb break="no" />tion is very remote from the surface<lb break="yes"/>of the globe. From this same cause,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">no</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="275" facs="#f0004"/>
                    <cb/> no doubt, earthquakes are not re-<lb break="no"/>strained to certain species of rocks, as<lb break="yes"/>some naturalists pretend, but all are<lb break="yes"/>fitted to propagate the movement.<lb break="yes"/>In order to keep within the limits of<lb break="yes"/>my own experience, I shall here cite<lb break="yes"/>the granites of Lima and Acapulco;<lb break="yes"/>the gneiss of Caracas; the mica-slate<lb break="yes"/>of the peninsula of Araya; the primi-<lb break="no"/>tive <choice>
                        <sic>thouschiefer</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">thonschiefer</corr>
                    </choice> of Tepecuacuilco, in<lb break="yes"/>Mexico; the secondary lime-stones of<lb break="yes"/>the Apennines, Spain, and new Anda-<lb break="no"/>lusia; and, finally, the trappean por-<lb break="no"/>phyries of the provinces of Quito and<lb break="yes"/>Popayan. In these different places<lb break="yes"/>the ground is frequently agitated by<lb break="yes"/>the most violent shocks; but some-<lb break="no"/>times, in the same rock, the superior<lb break="yes" />strata form invincible obstacles to the<lb break="yes"/>propagation of the motion. Thus,<lb break="yes"/>in the mines of Saxony, we have seen<lb break="yes"/>workmen hasten up affrighted by os-<lb break="no"/>cillations, which were not felt at the<lb break="yes"/>surface of the ground.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If, in regions the most remote from<lb break="yes"/>each other, primitive, secondary, and<lb break="yes"/>volcanic rocks, share equally in the<lb break="yes"/>convulsive movements of the globe,<lb break="yes"/>we cannot but admire also, that, in<lb break="yes"/>ground of little extent, certain classes<lb break="yes"/>of rocks oppose themselves to the<lb break="yes" />propagation of the shocks. At Cu-<lb break="no"/>mana, for instance, before the great<lb break="yes"/>catastrophe of 1797, the earthquakes<lb break="yes" />were felt only along the southern and<lb break="yes"/>calcareous coast of the gulf of Caria-<lb break="no"/>co, as far as the town of this name;<lb break="yes"/>while in the peninsula of Araya, and<lb break="yes"/>at the village of Maniquarez, the<lb break="yes"/>ground did not partake of the same<lb break="yes"/>agitation. The inhabitants of this<lb break="yes"/>northern coast, which is composed of<lb break="yes"/>mica-slate, built their huts on a mo-<lb break="no"/>tionless earth; a gulf three or four<lb break="yes" />thousand toises in breadth separated<lb break="yes"/>them from a plain covered with ruins,<lb break="yes"/>and overturned by earthquakes. This<lb break="yes" />security, founded on the experience<lb break="yes"/>of several ages, has vanished; and,<lb break="yes"/>since the 14th of December, 1797,<lb break="yes" />new communications appear to have<lb break="yes"/>been opened in the interior of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>globe. At present, the peninsula of<lb break="yes"/>Araya is not merely subject to the<lb break="yes"/>agitations of the soil of Cumana, the<lb break="yes"/>promontory of mica-slate is become,<lb break="yes"/>in its turn, a particular centre of the<lb break="yes"/>movements. The earth is sometimes<lb break="yes"/>strongly shaken at the village of Ma-<lb break="no"/>niquarez, when on the coast of Cuma-<lb break="no"/>na the inhabitants enjoy the most per-<lb break="no"/>fect tranquillity. The gulf of Cariaco,<lb break="yes"/>nevertheless, is only sixty or eighty<lb break="yes"/>fathoms deep.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The earthquakes of Cumana are<lb break="yes"/>connected with those of the West In-<lb break="no"/>dia islands; and it has even been sus-<lb break="no" />pected, that they have some connec-<lb break="no"/>tion with the volcanic ph&#x00E6;nomena of<lb break="yes"/>the Cordilleras of the Andes. On<lb break="yes" />the 4th of November, 1797, the soil<lb break="yes"/>of the province of Quito underwent<lb break="yes"/>such a destructive commotion, that,<lb break="yes" />notwithstanding the extreme feeble-<lb break="no"/>ness of the population of that country,<lb break="yes"/>near 40,000 natives perished, buried<lb break="yes"/>under the ruins of their houses, swal-<lb break="no"/>lowed up in the crevices, or drowned<lb break="yes"/>in lakes that were suddenly formed.<lb break="yes"/>At the same period, the inhabitants of<lb break="yes"/>the eastern Antilles were alarmed by<lb break="yes"/>shocks, which continued during eight<lb break="yes"/>months, when the volcano of Guada-<lb break="no"/>loupe threw out pumice stones, ashes,<lb break="yes" />and gusts of sulphureous vapours.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>This eruption of the 27th of Sept.,<lb break="yes"/>during which very long-continued<lb break="yes" />subterraneous noises were heard, was<lb break="yes"/>followed on the 14th of December<lb break="yes"/>by the great earthquake of Cumana.<lb break="yes" />Another volcano of the West India<lb break="yes"/>islands, that of St Vincents, has lately<lb break="yes"/>given a fresh instance of these extra-<lb break="no"/>ordinary connections. This volcano<lb break="yes"/>had not emitted flames since 1718,<lb break="yes"/>when they burst forth anew, in 1812.<lb break="yes"/>The total ruin of the city of Caracas<lb break="yes" />preceded this explosion thirty-five<lb break="yes"/>days, and violent oscillations of the<lb break="yes"/>ground were felt, both in the islands<lb break="yes"/>and on the coasts of Terra Firma.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Every thing in earthquakes seems<lb break="yes"/>to indicate the action of elastic fluids<lb break="yes"/>seeking an outlet to spread themselves<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">in</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="276" facs="#f0005"/>
                    <cb/>in the atmosphere. Often, on the<lb break="yes"/>coasts of the South Sea, the action is<lb break="yes"/>almost instantaneously communicated<lb break="yes" />from Chili to the gulf of Guayaquil,<lb break="yes"/>a distance of six hundred leagues;<lb break="yes"/>and, what is very remarkable, the<lb break="yes" />shocks appear to be so much the<lb break="yes"/>stronger, as the country is more dis-<lb break="no"/>tant from burning volcanoes. The<lb break="yes" />granitic mountains of Calabria, cover-<lb break="no"/>ed with very recent breccia, the cal-<lb break="no"/>careous chain of the Apennines, the<lb break="yes"/>country of Pignerol, the coasts of Por-<lb break="no"/>tugal and Greece, those of Peru and<lb break="yes"/>Terra Firma, afford striking proofs of<lb break="yes"/>this assertion. The globe, it may be<lb break="yes" />said, is agitated with greater force,<lb break="yes"/>in proportion as the surface has a<lb break="yes"/>smaller number of funnels communi-<lb break="no" />cating with the caverns of the interior.<lb break="yes"/>At Naples and at Messina, at the foot<lb break="yes"/>of Cotopaxi and of Tunguragus, earth-<lb break="no"/>quakes are dreaded only when vapours<lb break="yes"/>and flames do not issue from the cra-<lb break="no"/>ter. In the kingdom of Quito, the<lb break="yes"/>great catastrophe of Riobamba, which<lb break="yes"/>we have before mentioned, has led<lb break="yes"/>several well-informed persons to think,<lb break="yes"/>that this unfortunate country would<lb break="yes" />be less often desolate, if the subter-<lb break="no"/>raneous fire should break the porphy-<lb break="no"/>ritic dome of Chimborazo; and if this<lb break="yes"/>colossal mountain should become a<lb break="yes"/>burning volcano. At all times ana-<lb break="no"/>logous facts have led to the same hy-<lb break="no"/>pothesis. The Greeks, who, like<lb break="yes" />ourselves, attributed the oscillations<lb break="yes"/>of the ground to the tension of elastic<lb break="yes"/>fluids, cited in favour of their opinion<lb break="yes"/>the total cessation of the shocks at<lb break="yes"/>the island of Eub&#x0153;a, by the opening<lb break="yes"/>of a crevice in the Lelantine plain.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 