<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Description of the Ascent of the Peak of Teneriffe</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:50</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.20</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1815-Description_of_the-1-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1815-Description_of_the-1-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1815-Description_of_the-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1815-Description_of_the-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1815-Description_of_the-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1815-Description_of_the-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1815-Description_of_the-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1815-Description_of_the-7-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Personal Narrative&lt;/i&gt;, London 1814, Band 1, S. 154, 157, 159–160, 164–165, 168, 168–169, 171–172, 183, 188, 189–190, 196–197, 197–199, 201–203.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent&lt;/i&gt;, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 1, S. 123–124, 125, 126–127, 129–151.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Description of the Ascent of the Peak of Teneriffe</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1815</date>
          <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Scots Magazine, and Edinburgh Literary Miscellany&lt;/i&gt; 77 (1815), S. 268–272.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Schmuck: Initialen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="268" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Description of the Ascent of the Peak<lb break="yes"/>of</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Teneriffe.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">From</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt’s</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Travels in South<lb break="yes"/>America.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>OWARDS three in the morning,<lb break="yes"/>by the sombrous light of a few fir<lb break="yes"/>torches, we began our expedition for<lb break="yes"/>the summit of the Piton. We sca-<lb break="no"/>led the volcano on the north-east,<lb break="yes"/>where the declivities are extremely<lb break="yes"/>steep; and we came, after two hours<lb break="yes" />toil, to a small plain, which, on ac-<lb break="no"/>count of its isolated situation, bears<lb break="yes"/>the name of Alta Vista. It is the<lb break="yes"/>station also of the Neveros, those na-<lb break="no"/>tives, whose occupation it is to col-<lb break="no"/>lect ice and snow, which they sell in<lb break="yes"/>the neighbouring towns. Their mules,<lb break="yes" />better practised in climbing mountains<lb break="yes"/>than those hired by travellers, reach<lb break="yes"/>Alta Vista, and the Neveros are ob-<lb break="no"/>liged to transport the snow to this<lb break="yes"/>place on their backs. Above this<lb break="yes"/>point the Malpays begin, a term by<lb break="yes"/>which is designated here, as well as<lb break="yes"/>in Mexico, Peru, and every other<lb break="yes"/>country subject to volcanoes, a ground<lb break="yes"/>destitute of vegetable mould, and co-<lb break="no"/>vered with fragments of lavas.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We observed during the twilight<lb break="yes"/>a phenomenon which is not unusual<lb break="yes"/>on high mountains, but which the po-<lb break="no" />sition of the volcano that we were<lb break="yes"/>scaling rendered very striking. A<lb break="yes"/>layer of white and fleecy clouds con-<lb break="no" />cealed from us the sight of the ocean,<lb break="yes"/>and the lower region of the island.<lb break="yes"/>This layer did not appear above 1600<lb break="yes" />yards high; the clouds were so uni-<lb break="no"/>formly spread, and kept so perfect a<lb break="yes"/>level, that they wore the appearance<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>of a vast plain covered with snow.<lb break="yes"/>The colossal pyramid of the peak,<lb break="yes"/>the volcanic summits of Lanzerota,<lb break="yes"/>of Fortaventura, and the isle of Pal-<lb break="no"/>ma, were like rocks amidst this vast<lb break="yes"/>sea of vapours, and their black tints<lb break="yes" />were in fine contrast with the white-<lb break="no"/>ness of the clouds.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I was anxious to make an exact ob-<lb break="no"/>servation of the instant of sun-rising<lb break="yes"/>at an elevation so considerable as that<lb break="yes"/>we had reached on the Peak of Te-<lb break="no"/>neriffe. No traveller furnished with<lb break="yes"/>instruments had as yet taken such an<lb break="yes"/>observation. I had a telescope and a<lb break="yes" />chronometer, of which I knew the<lb break="yes"/>great exactness. In the part where<lb break="yes"/>the sun was to appear the horizon was<lb break="yes" />free from vapours. We perceived<lb break="yes"/>the upper limb at 4h. 48′ 55″ ap-<lb break="no"/>parent time, and, what is very re-<lb break="no" />markable, the first luminous point of<lb break="yes"/>the disc was found immediately in con-<lb break="no"/>tact with the limit of the horizon,<lb break="yes"/>consequently we saw the true hori-<lb break="no"/>zon, that is to say, a part of the sea<lb break="yes"/>farther than 43 leagues. It is pro-<lb break="no"/>ved by calculation, that, under the<lb break="yes"/>same parallel in the plain, the rising<lb break="yes"/>would have begun at 5h. 1′ 50.4″,<lb break="yes"/>or 11′ 51.3″ later than at the height<lb break="yes" />of the Peak. The difference observ-<lb break="no"/>ed was 12′ 55″, which arose no doubt<lb break="yes"/>from the uncertainty of the refrac-<lb break="no"/>tion for a zenith distance, of which<lb break="yes"/>observations are wanting.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We had yet to scale the steepest<lb break="yes"/>part of the mountain, the Piton,<lb break="yes"/>which forms the summit. The slope<lb break="yes"/>of this small cone, covered with vol-<lb break="no"/>canic ashes, and fragments of pumice<lb break="yes"/>stone, is so steep, that it would have<lb break="yes" />been almost impossible to reach<choice><sic>,</sic><corr type="editorial"></corr></choice> the<lb break="yes"/>top, had we not ascended by an old<lb break="yes"/>current of lava, the wrecks of which<lb break="yes" />have resisted the ravages of time.<lb break="yes"/>These wrecks form a wall of scorious<lb break="yes"/>rocks, which stretches itself into the<lb break="yes"/>midst of the loose ashes. We ascend-<lb break="no"/>ed the Piton by grasping these half<lb break="yes"/>decomposed scoriæ, the sharp edges<lb break="yes"/>of which remained often in our hands.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">We</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="269" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>We employed nearly half an hour to<lb break="yes"/>scale a hill, the perpendicular height<lb break="yes"/>of which is scarcely 180 yards.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When we gained the summit of<lb break="yes"/>the Piton, we were surprised to find<lb break="yes"/>scarcely room enough to seat ourselves<lb break="yes" />conveniently. We were stopped by<lb break="yes"/>a small circular wall of porphyritid<lb break="yes"/>lava, with base of pitchstone, which<lb break="yes"/>concealed from us the view of the<lb break="yes"/>crater. The west wind blew with<lb break="yes"/>such violence that we could scarcely<lb break="yes"/>stand. It was eight in the morning,<lb break="yes"/>and we were frozen with the cold,<lb break="yes"/>though the thermometer kept a little<lb break="yes"/>above the freezing point.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The brink of the crater of the<lb break="yes"/>Peak bears no resemblance to those<lb break="yes"/>of the greater part of the other vol-<lb break="no" />canoes which I have visited: for in-<lb break="no"/>stance, the craters of Vesuvius, Jo-<lb break="no"/>rullo, and Pichincha. In these the<lb break="yes" />Piton preserves its conic figure to the<lb break="yes"/>very summit: the whole of their de-<lb break="no"/>clivity is inclined the same number<lb break="yes" />of degrees, and uniformly covered<lb break="yes"/>with a layer of pumice stone, very<lb break="yes"/>minutely divided; when we reach the<lb break="yes" />top of these volcanoes, nothing ob-<lb break="no"/>structs the view of the bottom of the<lb break="yes"/>crater. The Peak of Teneriffe, and<lb break="yes" />Cotopaxi, on the contrary, are of very<lb break="yes"/>different construction. At their sum-<lb break="no"/>mit a circular wall surrounds the cra-<lb break="no"/>ter; which wall, at a distance, has the<lb break="yes" />appearance of a small cylinder placed<lb break="yes"/>on a truncated cone. On Cotopaxi<lb break="yes"/>this peculiar construction is visible to<lb break="yes"/>the naked eye at more than 2000<lb break="yes"/>toises distance; and no person has<lb break="yes"/>ever reached the crater of this vol-<lb break="no"/>cano. On the Peak of Teneriffe,<lb break="yes"/>the wall which surrounds the crater<lb break="yes"/>like a parapet, is so high, that it<lb break="yes"/>would be impossible to reach the<lb break="yes"/>caldera, if on the eastern side there<lb break="yes"/>was not a breach, which seems to have<lb break="yes"/>been the effect of a flowing of very<lb break="yes" />old lava. We descended through<lb break="yes"/>this breach toward the bottom of the<lb break="yes"/>funnel, the figure of which is elliptic.<lb break="yes" />Its greater axis has a direction from<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>north-west to south-east, nearly N.<lb break="yes"/>35° W. The greatest breadth of the<lb break="yes"/>mouth appeared to us to be 300 feet,<lb break="yes"/>the smallest 200 feet.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We descended to the bottom of the<lb break="yes"/>crater on a train of broken lava, from<lb break="yes"/>the eastern breach of the inclosure.<lb break="yes" />The heat was perceptible only in a<lb break="yes"/>few crevices, which gave vent to<lb break="yes"/>aqueous vapours with a peculiar buz-<lb break="no"/>zing noise. Some of these funnels or<lb break="yes"/>crevices are on the outside of the in-<lb break="no"/>closure, on the external brink of the<lb break="yes" />parapet that surrounds the crater.<lb break="yes"/>We plunged the thermometer into<lb break="yes"/>them, and saw it rise rapidly to 68<lb break="yes"/>and 75 degrees. It no doubt indica-<lb break="no"/>ted a higher temperature, but we<lb break="yes"/>could not observe the instrument till<lb break="yes"/>we had drawn it up, lest we should<lb break="yes"/>burn our hands. M. Cordier found<lb break="yes"/>several crevices, the heat of which<lb break="yes" />was that of boiling water. It might<lb break="yes"/>be thought that these vapours, which<lb break="yes"/>are emitted in gusts, contain muria-<lb break="no"/>tic or sulphurous acid; but, when<lb break="yes"/>condensed, they have no particular<lb break="yes"/>taste; and experiments, which seve-<lb break="no"/>ral naturalists have made with re-<lb break="no"/>agents, prove, that the chimneys of<lb break="yes"/>the Peak exhale only pure water. This<lb break="yes"/>phænomenon, analogous to what I<lb break="yes"/>observed in the crater of Jorullo, de-<lb break="no"/>serves the more attention, as muriatic<lb break="yes"/>acid abounds in the greater part of<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes, and as M. Vauquelin has<lb break="yes"/>discovered it even in the porphyritic<lb break="yes"/>lavas of Sarcouy in Auvergne.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We prolonged in vain our stay on<lb break="yes"/>the summit of the Peak, to wait the<lb break="yes"/>moment when we might enjoy the<lb break="yes"/>view of the whole of the Archipe-<lb break="no"/>lago of the Fortunate Islands. We<lb break="yes"/>discovered Palma, Gomera, and the<lb break="yes"/>Great Canary at our feet. The<lb break="yes"/>mountains of Lanzerota, free from<lb break="yes"/>vapours at sun-rise, were soon enve-<lb break="no"/>loped in thick clouds. On a suppo-<lb break="no"/>sition only of an ordinary refraction,<lb break="yes"/>the eye takes in, in calm weather,<lb break="yes"/>from the summit of the volcano, a<lb break="yes"/>surface of the globe of 5700 square<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">leagues,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="270" facs="#f0003"/>
                    <cb/>leagues, equal to a fourth of the sur-<lb break="no"/>face of Spain. The question has of-<lb break="no"/>ten been agitated, if it were possible<lb break="yes"/>to perceive the coast of Africa from<lb break="yes"/>the top of this colossal pyramid; but<lb break="yes"/>the nearest parts of this coast are still<lb break="yes"/>farther from Teneriffe than 2° 49′,<lb break="yes"/>or 56 leagues. The visual ray of<lb break="yes"/>the horizon from the peak being<lb break="yes"/>1° 57′, Cape Bojador can be seen on-<lb break="no"/>ly on the supposition of its height be-<lb break="no"/>ing 400 yards above the level of the<lb break="yes"/>ocean.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We could not withdraw our eyes,<lb break="yes"/>on the summit of the Peak, from be-<lb break="no"/>holding the colour of the azure vault<lb break="yes"/>of the sky. Its intensity at the<lb break="yes"/>zenith appeared to correspond to 41°<lb break="yes"/>of the cyanometer. We know by<lb break="yes"/>Saussure’s experiment, that this in-<lb break="no"/>tensity increases with the rarity of<lb break="yes"/>the air, and that the same instrument<lb break="yes"/>indicated at the same period 20° at<lb break="yes"/>the priory of Camouni, and 40° at<lb break="yes"/>the top of Mont-Blanc. This last<lb break="yes"/>mountain is 540 toises higher than<lb break="yes"/>the volcano of Teneriffe; and if, not-<lb break="no"/>withstanding this difference, the sky<lb break="yes"/>is seen there of a less deep blue, we<lb break="yes"/>must attribute this phænomenon to<lb break="yes"/>the dryness of the African air, and<lb break="yes"/>the proximity of the torrid zone.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We saw on the summit of the<lb break="yes"/>Peak no trace of psora, lecidea, or<lb break="yes"/>other cryptogamous plants; no insect<lb break="yes" />fluttering in the air. We found, how-<lb break="no"/>ever, a few hymenopteras adhering to<lb break="yes"/>masses of sulphur, moistened with<lb break="yes" />sulphurous acid, and lining the mouths<lb break="yes"/>of the funnels. These are bees,<lb break="yes"/>which appear to have been attracted<lb break="yes"/>by the flowers of the spartium nubi-<lb break="no"/>genum, and which oblique currents<lb break="yes"/>of air had carried up to these high<lb break="yes" />regions, like the butterflies found by<lb break="yes"/>M. Ramond at the top of Mont Per-<lb break="no"/>du. The butterflies perished from<lb break="yes"/>cold, while the bees on the Peak<lb break="yes"/>were scorched, on imprudently ap-<lb break="no"/>proaching the crevices where they<lb break="yes"/>came in search of warmth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Notwithstanding the heat we felt<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> in our feet on the edge of the crater,<lb break="yes"/>the cone of ashes remains covered<lb break="yes"/>with snow during several months in<lb break="yes"/>the winter. It is probable, that un-<lb break="no"/>der the cap of snow considerable hol-<lb break="no"/>lows are found, like those we find<lb break="yes"/>under the glaciers of Switzerland,<lb break="yes"/>the temperature of which is constant-<lb break="no"/>ly less elevated than that of the soil<lb break="yes"/>on which they repose. The cold and<lb break="yes" />violent wind which blew from the<lb break="yes"/>time of sun-rise, engaged us to seek<lb break="yes"/>shelter at the foot of the Piton. Our<lb break="yes" />hands and faces were frozen, while<lb break="yes"/>our boots were burnt by the soil on<lb break="yes"/>which we walked. We descended<lb break="yes"/>in the space of a few minutes the<lb break="yes"/>Sugar Loaf which we had scaled with<lb break="yes"/>so much toil; and this rapidity was<lb break="yes"/>in part involuntary, for we often rol-<lb break="no"/>led down on the ashes. It was with<lb break="yes"/>regret that we quitted this solitary<lb break="yes" />place, this domain, where Nature<lb break="yes"/>towers in all her majesty; we sooth-<lb break="no"/>ed ourselves with the hope of once<lb break="yes" />again visiting the Canary islands; but<lb break="yes"/>this, like many other plans which we<lb break="yes"/>then formed, has never been execu-<lb break="no" />ted.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Not to interrupt the narrative of<lb break="yes"/>the excursion to the top of the Peak,<lb break="yes"/>I have said nothing of the geological<lb break="yes" />observations I made on the structure<lb break="yes"/>of this colossal mountain, and on the<lb break="yes"/>nature of the volcanic rocks of which<lb break="yes"/>it is composed. Before we quit the<lb break="yes"/>Archipelago of the Canaries, I shall<lb break="yes"/>delay a moment, and bring into one<lb break="yes"/>point of view what relates to the phy-<lb break="no"/>sical picture of these countries.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Is the conical mountain of a vol-<lb break="no"/>cano entirely formed of a liquified<lb break="yes"/>matter, heaped together by successive<lb break="yes"/>eruptions; or, does it contain in its<lb break="yes"/>centre a nucleus of primitive rocks<lb break="yes"/>covered with lavas, which are these<lb break="yes"/>same rocks altered by fire? What<lb break="yes"/>are the affinities which unite the pro-<lb break="no"/>ductions of modern volcanoes with the<lb break="yes"/>basaltes, the phonolites, and those por-<lb break="no" />phyries with basis of feldspar, which<lb break="yes"/>are without quartz, and which cover<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="271" facs="#f0004"/>
                    <cb/>the Cordilleras of Peru and Mexico,<lb break="yes"/>as well as the small groupes of the<lb break="yes"/>Monts d’Or, of Cantal, and of Mê-<lb break="no" />zen in France? Has the central nu-<lb break="no"/>cleus of volcanoes been heated in its<lb break="yes"/>primitive position, and raised up in a<lb break="yes"/>softened state by the force of the e-<lb break="no"/>lastic vapours, before these fluids com-<lb break="no"/>municated, by means of a crater, with<lb break="yes"/>the external air? What is the sub-<lb break="no" />stance which, for thousands of years,<lb break="yes"/>keeps up this combustion, which is<lb break="yes"/>sometimes so slow, and at other times<lb break="yes"/>so active? Does this unknown cause<lb break="yes"/>act at an immense depth; or does<lb break="yes"/>this chemical action take place in se-<lb break="no"/>condary rocks lying on granite?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The farther we are from finding a<lb break="yes"/>solution of these problems in the nu-<lb break="no"/>merous works hitherto published on<lb break="yes"/>Etna and Vesuvius, the greater is the<lb break="yes"/>desire of the traveller to see with his<lb break="yes"/>own eyes. He hopes to be more for-<lb break="no" />tunate than those who have preceded<lb break="yes"/>him; he wishes to form a precise idea<lb break="yes"/>of the geological relations the volcano<lb break="yes"/>and the neighbouring mountains bear<lb break="yes"/>to each other: but how often is he dis-<lb break="no"/>appointed, when, on the limits of the<lb break="yes"/>primitive soil, enormous banks of tufa<lb break="yes" />and puzzolana render every observa-<lb break="no"/>tion on the position and stratification<lb break="yes"/>impossible! We reach the inside of<lb break="yes"/>the crater with less difficulty than we<lb break="yes"/>at first expected, we examine the cone<lb break="yes"/>from its summit to its basis; we are<lb break="yes"/>struck with the difference in the pro-<lb break="no"/>duce of each eruption, and with the<lb break="yes"/>analogy which still exists between the<lb break="yes"/>lavas of the same volcano: but, not-<lb break="no"/>withstanding the care with which we<lb break="yes" />interrogate nature, and the number of<lb break="yes"/>partial observations which are present-<lb break="no"/>ed at every step, we return from the<lb break="yes"/>summit of a burning volcano less sa-<lb break="no"/>tisfied than when we were preparing<lb break="yes"/>to go thither. It is after we have stu-<lb break="no"/>died them on the spot, that the vol-<lb break="no" />canic phænomena appear still more<lb break="yes"/>isolated, more variable, more obscure,<lb break="yes"/>than we figure them when consulting<lb break="yes" />the narratives of travellers.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>These reflections occurred to me on<lb break="yes"/>returning from the summit of the Peak<lb break="yes"/>of Teneriffe, the first unextinct vol-<lb break="no" />cano I had yet visited. They returned<lb break="yes"/>anew, whenever in South America, or<lb break="yes"/>in Mexico, I had occasion to examine<lb break="yes" />volcanic mountains. If we reflect on<lb break="yes"/>the little progress, which the labours<lb break="yes"/>of mineralogists, and the discoveries<lb break="yes"/>in chemistry, have made toward the<lb break="yes"/>knowledge of the physical geology of<lb break="yes"/>mountains, we cannot help being af-<lb break="no"/>fected with a painful sentiment; and<lb break="yes"/>this is felt still more strongly by those,<lb break="yes"/>who, questioning nature under differ-<lb break="no"/>ent climates, are more occupied by the<lb break="yes" />problems they have not been able to<lb break="yes"/>solve, than with the small number of<lb break="yes"/>results they have obtained.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Peak of Teyde forms a pyra-<lb break="no"/>midical mass, like Etna, Tungurahua,<lb break="yes"/>and Popocatepetl. This physiogno-<lb break="no" />mic character is very far from being<lb break="yes"/>common to all volcanoes. We have<lb break="yes"/>seen some in the southern hemisphere,<lb break="yes" />which, instead of having the form of<lb break="yes"/>a cone or bell, are lengthened in one<lb break="yes"/>direction, having the ridge sometimes<lb break="yes"/>smooth, and at others rough with small<lb break="yes"/>pointed rocks. This structure is pe-<lb break="no"/>culiar to Antisana and Pichincha, two<lb break="yes"/>burning mountains of the province of<lb break="yes" />Quito; and the absence of the conic<lb break="yes"/>form ought never to be considered as<lb break="yes"/>a reason excluding a volcanic origin.<lb break="yes"/>It is here sufficient to observe in ge-<lb break="no"/>neral, that the summits, which are still<lb break="yes"/>subject to eruptions of the greatest<lb break="yes"/>violence, and at the nearest periods to<lb break="yes"/>each other, are slender peaks of a conic<lb break="yes"/>form; that the mountains with length-<lb break="no"/>ened summits, and rugged with small<lb break="yes"/>stony masses, are very old volcanoes,<lb break="yes" />and near being extinguished; and that<lb break="yes"/>rounded tops, in the form of domes, or<lb break="yes"/>bells, indicate those problematic por-<lb break="no"/>phyries, which are supposed to have<lb break="yes"/>been heated in their primitive place,<lb break="yes"/>penetrated by vapours, and forced up<lb break="yes"/>in a softened state, without having<lb break="yes"/>ever flowed as real lithoidal lavas. To<lb break="yes"/>the first of these distinctions belong<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">Coto-</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="272" facs="#f0005"/>
                    <cb/> Cotopaxi, the Peak of Teneriffe, and<lb break="yes"/>that of Orizava in Mexico. The se-<lb break="no"/>cond is common to Cargueirazo, and<lb break="yes" />Pichincha, in the province of Quito;<lb break="yes"/>to the volcano of Puracey, near Po-<lb break="no"/>payan; and perhaps also to Hecla, in<lb break="yes"/>Iceland. The third and last is found<lb break="yes"/>in the majestic figure of Chimborazo,<lb break="yes"/>and, if it be permitted to place by the<lb break="yes"/>side of this colossus, a hill of Europe<lb break="yes" />in the Great Sarcouy in Auvergne.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 