<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Teneriffe</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:50</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.20</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1815-Description_of_the-4-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1815-Description_of_the-1-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1815-Description_of_the-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1815-Description_of_the-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1815-Description_of_the-4-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1815-Description_of_the-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1815-Description_of_the-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1815-Description_of_the-7-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 1, S. 137–144.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Teneriffe</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1850</date>
          <pubPlace>Belfast</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: The Belfast Man’s Journal 9 (2. März 1850), S. 141–143.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Schmuck: Kapitälchen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="141" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">TENERIFFE.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">An</hi> expedition to the summit of the volcano of<lb break="yes"/>Teneriffe, is interesting, not solely on account of the<lb break="yes"/>great number of phenomena which are the objects of<lb break="yes"/>research; it has still greater attractions from the<lb break="yes"/>picturesque beauties which it lays open to those<lb break="yes" />who are feelingly alive to the majesty of nature. It<lb break="yes"/>is a difficult task to describe those sensations, which<lb break="yes"/>act with so much the more force as they have some-<lb break="no"/>thing undefined, produced by the immensity of the<lb break="yes"/>space as well as by the greatness, the novelty, and<lb break="yes"/>the multitude of the objects, amidst which we find<lb break="yes"/>ourselves transported. When a traveller attempts<lb break="yes"/>to furnish descriptions of the loftiest summits of the<lb break="yes"/>globe, the cataracts of the great rivers, the tortuous<lb break="yes"/>vallies of the Andes, he is exposed to the danger of<lb break="yes"/>fatiguing his readers by the monotonous expression<lb break="yes"/>of his admiration. It appears to me more conform-<lb break="no" />able to the plan which I have proposed to myself in<lb break="yes"/>this narrative, to indicate the peculiar character that<lb break="yes"/>distinguishes each zone; we exhibit, with more<lb break="yes"/>clearness, the physiognomy of the landscape, in pro-<lb break="no"/>portion as we endeavour to sketch its individual<lb break="yes"/>features, to compare them with each other, and dis-<lb break="no"/>cover, by this kind of analysis, the sources of those<lb break="yes"/>enjoyments, which are offered us by the great<lb break="yes" />picture of nature.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Travellers have learnt, by experience, that views<lb break="yes"/>from the summits of very lofty mountains are neither<lb break="yes"/>so beautiful, picturesque, nor varied, as those from<lb break="yes"/>heights which do not exceed that of Vesuvius,<lb break="yes"/>Rigi, and the Puy-de-D&#x00F4;me. Collossal mountains,<lb break="yes"/>such as Chimborazo, Antisana, or Mount Rose, com-<lb break="no"/>pose so large a mass, that the plains covered with<lb break="yes"/>rich vegetation are seen only in the immensity of<lb break="yes"/>distance, where a blue and vapoury tint is uniformly<lb break="yes"/>spread over the landscape. The Peak of Teneriffe,<lb break="yes"/>from its slender form and local position, unites the<lb break="yes"/>advantages of less lofty summits to those which arise<lb break="yes"/>from very great heights. We not only discover,<lb break="yes" />from its top, a vast expanse of sea, but we see also<lb break="yes"/>the forests of Teneriffe, and the inhabited parts of<lb break="yes"/>the coasts, in a proximity fitted to produce the most<lb break="yes"/>beautiful contrasts of form and colour. We might<lb break="yes"/>say, that the volcano crushes with its mass the<lb break="yes"/>little isle which forms its basis, and shoots up from<lb break="yes"/>the waters to a height three times loftier than the<lb break="yes"/>region where the clouds float in the summer. If<lb break="yes" />its crater, half extinguished for ages past, shot<lb break="yes"/>forth flakes of fire like that of Stromboli in the<lb break="yes"/>&#x00C6;olian islands, the Peak of Teneriffe, resembling a<lb break="yes"/>lighthouse, would furnish a direction to the mariner<lb break="yes"/>in a circuit of more than 260 leagues.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When seated on the external edge of the crater,<lb break="yes"/>we turned our eyes towards the north-west, where<lb break="yes"/>the coasts are decked with villages and hamlets. At<lb break="yes"/>our feet, masses of vapour, constantly driven by the<lb break="yes"/>winds, afforded us the most variable spectacle. A<lb break="yes"/>uniform stratum of clouds, the same as we have just<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> described, and which separated us from the lower<lb break="yes"/>regions of the island, had been pierced in several<lb break="yes"/>places by the effect of the small currents of air,<lb break="yes"/>which the earth, heated by the sun, began to send<lb break="yes"/>towards us. The port of Orotava, its vessels at<lb break="yes"/>anchor, the gardens and the vineyards which encircle<lb break="yes"/>the town, exhibited themselves through <choice><sic>on</sic><corr type="editorial">an</corr></choice> opening,<lb break="yes"/>which seemed to enlarge every instant. From the<lb break="yes" />summit of these solitary regions, our eyes hovered<lb break="yes"/>over an inhabited world; we enjoyed the striking<lb break="yes"/>contrast between the bare sides of the Peak, its<lb break="yes"/>steep declivities covered with scori&#x00E6;, its elevated<lb break="yes"/>plains, destitute of vegetation, and the smiling<lb break="yes"/>aspect of the cultured country beneath; we beheld<lb break="yes"/>the plants divided by zones, as the temperature of<lb break="yes"/>the atmosphere diminished with the height of the<lb break="yes" />site. Below the Piton, lichens begin to cover the<lb break="yes"/>scorious lava with lustered surface; a violet, akin to<lb break="yes"/>the viola decumbens, rises on the slope of the volcano<lb break="yes"/>at 1740 toises of height; it takes the lead not only of<lb break="yes"/>the other herbaceous plants, but even of the gramina,<lb break="yes"/>which, in the Alps and on the ridge of the Cordil-<lb break="no"/>leras, form close neighbourhood with the plants of<lb break="yes"/>the family of cryptogamia. Tufts of retama, loaded<lb break="yes"/>with flowers, make gay the vallies hollowed out by<lb break="yes"/>the torrents, and which are encumbered with the<lb break="yes" />effects of the lateral eruptions; below the spartium,<lb break="yes"/>or retama, lies the region of ferns, bordered by the<lb break="yes"/>tract of the arborescent heaths. Forests of laurel,<lb break="yes"/>rhamnus, and arbutus, divide the ericas from the<lb break="yes"/>rising grounds planted with vines and fruit trees.<lb break="yes"/>A rich carpet of verdure extends from the plain of<lb break="yes"/>Spartium, and the zone of the Alpine plants even to<lb break="yes"/>the group of the date trees and the musa, at the feet<lb break="yes"/>of which the ocean appears to roll.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The seeming proximity, in which, from the summit<lb break="yes"/>of the Peak, we behold the hamlets, the vineyards,<lb break="yes"/>the gardens on the coast, is increased by the prodi-<lb break="no"/>gious transparency of the atmosphere. Notwith-<lb break="no"/>standing the great distance, we distinguished not only<lb break="yes"/>the houses, the sails of the vessels, and the trunks of<lb break="yes"/>trees, our eyes dwelt on the rich vegetation of the<lb break="yes"/>plains, enamelled with the most vivid colouring.<lb break="yes" />These phenomena are owing not only to the height<lb break="yes"/>of the site, but to the peculiar modiflcations of the<lb break="yes"/>air in warm climates. Under every zone, an object<lb break="yes"/>placed on a level with the sea, and viewed in a hori-<lb break="no"/>zontal direction, appears less luminous, than when<lb break="yes"/>seen from the top of a mountain, where vapours<lb break="yes"/>arrive across strata of air of decreasing density.<lb break="yes"/>Differences equally striking are produced by the in-<lb break="no"/>fluence of climates; the surface of a lake or large<lb break="yes"/>river is less resplendant, when we see it at an equal<lb break="yes"/>distance, from the top of the higher Alps of Switzer-<lb break="no"/>land, than when we view it from the summit of the<lb break="yes" />Cordilleras of Peru or Mexico. In proportion as<lb break="yes"/>the air is pure and serene, the solution of the vapours<lb break="yes"/>becomes more perfect, and the light loses less in its<lb break="yes"/>passage. When, from the coast of the South Sea, we<lb break="yes"/>reach the elevated plain of Quito, or that of Antisana,<lb break="yes"/>we are struck for some days at the nearness at which<lb break="yes"/>we think we see objects which are seven or eight<lb break="yes"/>leagues distant.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="142" facs="#f0002"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>The Peak of Teyde has not the advantage of being<lb break="yes"/>situate in the equinoctial region; but the dryness of<lb break="yes"/>the columns of air which rise perpetually above the<lb break="yes"/>neighbouring plains of Africa, and which the<lb break="yes"/>eastern winds bring with rapidity, gives the atmo-<lb break="no"/>sphere of the Canary Islands a transparency, which<lb break="yes"/>surpasses not only that of the air of Naples and Si-<lb break="no"/>cily, but, perhaps, also the purity of the sky of<lb break="yes" />Quito and Peru. This transparency may be regard-<lb break="no"/>ed as one of the chief causes of the beauty of the<lb break="yes"/>landscape under the torrid zone; it is this which<lb break="yes"/>heightens the splendour of the vegetable colouring,<lb break="yes"/>and contributes to the magical effect of their har-<lb break="no"/>monies and their contrasts. If a mass of light, which<lb break="yes"/>circulates about objects, fatigues the external senses<lb break="yes"/>during a part of the day, the inhabitant of the<lb break="yes" />southern climates has his compensations in moral<lb break="yes"/>enjoyments. A lucid clearness in the conceptions,<lb break="yes"/>a serenity of mind, correspond with the transparency<lb break="yes"/>of the surrounding atmosphere. We feel these im-<lb break="no"/>pressions without overstepping the limits of Europe.<lb break="yes"/>I appeal to travellers who have visited countries<lb break="yes"/>rendered famous by prodigies of the imagination and<lb break="yes"/>the arts, the favoured climates of Italy and Greece.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We prolonged in vain our stay on the summit of<lb break="yes"/>the Peak, to wait the moment when we might enjoy<lb break="yes"/>the view of the whole of the Archipelago of the<lb break="yes"/>Fortunate Islands. We discovered Palma, Gomera,<lb break="yes"/>and the Great Canary, at our feet. The mountains<lb break="yes"/>of Lanzerota, free from vapors at sunrise, were soon<lb break="yes"/>enveloped in thick clouds. On a supposition, only<lb break="yes"/>of an ordinary refraction, the eye takes in, in calm<lb break="yes"/>weather, from the summit of the volcano, a surface<lb break="yes"/>of the globe of 5700 square leagues, equal to a fourth<lb break="yes"/>of the surface of Spain. The question has often been<lb break="yes"/>agitated, if it were possible to perceive the coast of<lb break="yes"/>Africa from the top of this colossal pyramid; but<lb break="yes"/>the nearest parts of this coast are still farther from<lb break="yes"/>Teneriffe than 2&#x00B0; 49&#x2032;, or 56 leagues. The visual<lb break="yes"/>ray of the horizon from the Peak, being 1&#x00B0; 57&#x2032;,<lb break="yes"/>Cape Bojador can be seen only on the supposition of<lb break="yes"/>its height being 200 toises above the level of the ocean.<lb break="yes"/>We are absolutely ignorant of the height of the<lb break="yes" />Black Mountains near Cape Bojador, as well as that<lb break="yes"/>of the Peak, called by navigators <hi rendition="#i">Pennon grande</hi>,
                    <lb break="yes"/>farther south of this promontory. If the summit of<lb break="yes"/>the volcano of Teneriffe was more accessible, we<lb break="yes" />should observe, without doubt, with certain winds,<lb break="yes"/>the effects of an extraordinary refraction. In looking<lb break="yes"/>over what the Spanish and Portugese authors relate<lb break="yes"/>respecting the existence of the fabulous isle of San<lb break="yes"/>Borondon, or Antillia, we find that it is particularly<lb break="yes"/>the humid wind of the west-south-west, which pro-<lb break="no"/>duces, in these latitudes, the phenomena of the<lb break="yes"/>mirage. We shall not, however, admit with Mr.<lb break="yes" />Vieyra, &#x201C;that the play of the terrestrial refractions,<lb break="yes" />may render visible to the inhabitants of the Canaries<lb break="yes"/>the islands of Cape Verd, and even the Apalachian<lb break="yes"/>Mountains of America.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The cold, which we felt on the top of the Peak,<lb break="yes"/>was very considerable for the season. The centi-<lb break="no"/>grade thermometer, at a distance from the ground,<lb break="yes"/>and from the apertures that emitted the hot vapours,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> descended in the shade to 2&#x00B7;7&#x00B0;. The wind was west,<lb break="yes" />and consequently opposite to that which brings to<lb break="yes"/>Teneriffe, during a great part of the year, the warm<lb break="yes"/>air, that rises above the burning desert of Africa.<lb break="yes"/>As the temperature of the atmosphere, observed at<lb break="yes"/>the port of Oratava, by Mr. Savagi, was 22&#x00B7;8&#x00B0;, the<lb break="yes"/>decrement of caloric was one degree every 94 toises.<lb break="yes"/>This result perfectly coresponds with those ob-<lb break="no"/>tained by Lamanon and Saussure on the summits of<lb break="yes" />the Peak and Etna, though in very different seasons.<lb break="yes"/>The tall slender forms of these mountains facilitates<lb break="yes"/>the means of comparing the temperature of two<lb break="yes"/>strata of the atmosphere, which are nearly in the<lb break="yes"/>same perpendicular plane; and under this point of<lb break="yes"/>view, the observations made in an excursion to the<lb break="yes"/>volcano of Teneriffe, resemble those of an ascent in<lb break="yes"/>a balloon. We must, nevertheless, remark, that the<lb break="yes"/>ocean, on account of its transparency and evapora-<lb break="no"/>tion, reflects less caloric than the plains into the<lb break="yes"/>upper regions of the air; the summits, also, which<lb break="yes"/>are surrounded by the sea, are colder in the summer<lb break="yes"/>than the mountains which rise from a continent; but<lb break="yes"/>this circumstance has very little influence on the<lb break="yes"/>decrement of the atmospherical heat, the tempera-<lb break="no" />ture of the low regions being equally diminished by<lb break="yes"/>the proximity of the ocean.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is not the same with respect to the influence<lb break="yes"/>exereised by the direction of the wind, and the ra-<lb break="no"/>pidity of the ascending current; the latter some-<lb break="no"/>times increases in an astonishing manner the tem-<lb break="no"/>perature of the loftiest mountains. I have seen the<lb break="yes"/>thermometer rise, on the slope of the volcano of<lb break="yes"/>Antisana, in the kingdom of Quito, to 19&#x00B0;, when we<lb break="yes"/>were 2837 toises high. Mr. Labillardiére has seen<lb break="yes"/>it remain, on the edge of the crater of the Peak of<lb break="yes"/>Teneriffe, at 18&#x00B7;7&#x00B0;, though he had used every pos-<lb break="no"/>sible precaution to avoid the effect of accidental<lb break="yes"/>causes. The temperature of the road of Santa<lb break="yes" />Cruz being then at 28&#x00B0;, the difference between the<lb break="yes"/>air of the coast and on the summit of the Peak was<lb break="yes"/><choice><sic>9 3&#x00B0;</sic><corr type="editorial">9&#x00B7;3&#x00B0;</corr></choice>, instead of 20&#x00B0;, which corresponds to a decre-<lb break="no"/>ment of caloric 94 toises to each degree. I find in<lb break="yes"/>the journal of the expedition of d&#x2019;Entrecasteaux,<lb break="yes"/>that at this period the wind at Santa Cruz was<lb break="yes"/>south-south-east. The same wind blew, perhaps,<lb break="yes"/>more impetuously in the higher regions of the at-<lb break="no" />mosphere, and forced back, in an oblique direction,<lb break="yes"/>the hot air of the neigbouring continent toward the<lb break="yes"/>summit of the Piton. Besides, the visit of Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Labillardiére took place on the 17th October, 1791;<lb break="yes"/>and, in the Alps of Switzerland, we have observed,<lb break="yes"/>that the difference of temperature between the<lb break="yes"/>mountains and the plains is considerably less in<lb break="yes" />autumn, than in summer. All these variations of<lb break="yes"/>the rapidity with which caloric decreases, have<lb break="yes"/>their influence on the measures taken by the baro-<lb break="no"/>meter, only in as much as the decrement is not uni-<lb break="no"/>form in the intermediate strata, and as it differs from<lb break="yes"/>the arithmetical or harmonic progression, which is<lb break="yes"/>presumed in the formul&#x00E6; employed.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We saw on the summit of the Peak no trace of<lb break="yes"/>psora, lecidea, or other cryptogamous plants; no<lb break="yes"/>insect fluttered in the air. We found, however, a<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="143" facs="#f0003"/>
                    <cb/> few hymenopteras adhering to masses of sulphur<lb break="yes"/>moistened with sulphurous acid, and lining the<lb break="yes"/>mouths of the funnels. These are bees, which ap-<lb break="no"/>pear to have been attracted by the flowers of the<lb break="yes"/>spartium nubigenum, and which oblique currents of<lb break="yes"/>air had carried up to these high regions, like the<lb break="yes"/>butterflies found by Mr. Ramond at the top of Mont<lb break="yes"/>Perdu. The butterflies perished from cold, while<lb break="yes" />the bees on the Peak were scorched on imprudently<lb break="yes"/>approaching the crevices where they came in search<lb break="yes"/>of warmth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Notwithstanding the heat we felt in our feet on the<lb break="yes"/>edge of the crater, the cone of ashes remains covered<lb break="yes"/>with snow during several months in the winter. It<lb break="yes"/>is probable, that under the cap of snow considerable<lb break="yes"/>hollows are found, like those we find under the gla-<lb break="no"/>ciers of Switzerland, the temperature of which is<lb break="yes"/>constantly less elevated than that of the soil on<lb break="yes"/>which they repose. The cold and violent wind<lb break="yes" />which blew from the time of sunrise, engaged us to<lb break="yes"/>shelter at the foot of the Piton. Our hands and faces<lb break="yes"/>were frozen, while our boots were burnt by the soil<lb break="yes"/>on which we walked. We descended in the space of<lb break="yes"/>a few minutes the Sugar Loaf which we had scaled<lb break="yes"/>with so much toil; and this rapidity was, in part,<lb break="yes"/>involuntary, for we often rolled down in the ashes.<lb break="yes"/>It was with regret that we quitted this solitary place,<lb break="yes"/>this domain where Nature towers in all her majesty;<lb break="yes"/>we soothed ourselves with the hope of once again<lb break="yes" />visiting the Canary Islands; but this, like many<lb break="yes"/>other plans which we then formed, has never been<lb break="yes"/>executed. &#x2014;</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Humboldt.</hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 