<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="446" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Laws observed in the Distribution of vegetable<lb break="yes"/>Forms. By</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Alexander</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Count</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">Extracted from a paper read to the French Institute, Feb. 5, 1816.</note>.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#in">B</hi>otany,</hi> long confined to the simple description of the external<lb break="yes"/>forms of plants and their artificial classification, now presents<lb break="yes"/>several branches of study, which place it more on a footing with<lb break="yes"/>the other sciences. Such are the distribution of vegetables ac-<lb break="no"/>cording to a natural method founded upon the whole part of<lb break="yes"/>their structure; physiology, which displays their internal organi-<lb break="no"/>zation; botanical geography, which assigns to each tribe of plants<lb break="yes"/>their height, limits, and climate. The terms <hi rendition="#i">alpine plants,<lb break="yes" />plants of hot countries, plants of the sea-shore,</hi> are to be found<lb break="yes"/>in all languages, even in those of the most savage nations on the<lb break="yes"/>banks of the Oronoko. They prove that the attention of men<lb break="yes"/>has been constantly fixed on the distribution of vegetables, and<lb break="yes"/>on their connexion with the temperature of the air, the elevation<lb break="yes"/>of the soil, and the nature of the ground which they inhabit.<lb break="yes"/>It does not require much sagacity to observe, that on the slope<lb break="yes"/>of the high mountains of Armenia, vegetables of a different lati-<lb break="no"/>tude follow each in succession, like the climates, superposed as it<lb break="yes"/>were upon each other. This idea of Tournefort, developed by<lb break="yes"/>Linn&#x00E6;us in two interesting dissertations, (<hi rendition="#i">Stationes et Coloni&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>Plantarum,</hi>) nevertheless contains the first seeds of botanical<lb break="yes"/>geography. Menzel, the author of an unpublished Flora of Ja-<lb break="no"/>pan, strongly recommends to travellers researches as to the dis-<lb break="no"/>tribution of species in the different regions of the globe. He<lb break="yes"/>had even pointed out the result before by the name of the Geo-<lb break="no"/>graphy of Plants. This appellation was again employed, and<lb break="yes"/>almost at the same time, about the year 1783, by the Abbé<lb break="yes"/>Giraud Soulavie, and by the celebrated author of the Studies of<lb break="yes"/>Nature; a work which, amid a great variety of very inaccurate<lb break="yes"/>ideas as to the <hi rendition="#i">physique</hi> of the globe, contains some profound<lb break="yes"/>and ingenious views as to the forms, relations, and habitudes of<lb break="yes"/>vegetables. Abbé Giraud Soulavie was occupied in preference<lb break="yes"/>with the plants already cultivated: he has distinguished the cli-<lb break="no"/>mates of the olive trees, the vines, and the chesnuts. He gives<lb break="yes"/>a vertical section of Mount Mezin, to which he has added the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">barometrical</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="447" facs="#f0002"/> barometrical heights, &#x201C;because,&#x201D; as he says, &#x201C;he has a great<lb break="yes"/>contempt for every result taken from barometrical measurement.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>His Geography of the Plants in the South of France was followed<lb break="yes"/>by the <hi rendition="#i">Tentamen Histori&#x00E6; geographic&#x00E6; Vegetabilium</hi> of the<lb break="yes"/>learned Professor Strohmayer, published in 1800 at Gottingen<lb break="yes"/>in the form of a dissertation; but this Tentamen exhibits rather<lb break="yes"/>the plan of a future work, and the catalogue of authors to be<lb break="yes"/>consulted, than information respecting the altitudes which spon-<lb break="no"/>taneous plants reach in different climates. The case is the same<lb break="yes"/>with the very philosophical views announced by M. Treviranus<lb break="yes"/>in his <hi rendition="#i">Essai de Biologie;</hi> we therein find general considerations,<lb break="yes"/>but no measurements of heights, and no thermometrical indica-<lb break="no"/>tions, which are the solid bases of the geography of plants. This<lb break="yes"/>study has not risen to the rank of a science, until men of science<lb break="yes" />have perfected both the measures of heights by barometrical<lb break="yes" />observations, and the determination of mean temperatures; or,<lb break="yes" />what is more important for the development of vegetation, the<lb break="yes" />determination of the differences between the temperature of<lb break="yes" />summer and winter and between that of day and night. Few<lb break="yes" />branches of study have in our day made more rapid progress; and<lb break="yes" />a long time has not intervened between the first efforts and the<lb break="yes"/>present period, when by the united observations of a great num-<lb break="no"/>ber of travellers, we have succeeded in fixing the limits of ve-<lb break="no"/>getables in Lapland, the Pyrenees, the Alps, Caucasus, and the<lb break="yes"/>Cordilleras of America.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The vegetables which cover the vast surface of the globe pre-<lb break="no" />sent, when we study by natural classes or families, striking dif-<lb break="no"/>ferences in the distribution of their forms: it is to the laws of this<lb break="yes"/>distribution that I have recently turned my attention. On li-<lb break="no"/>miting them to the countries in which the number of the species<lb break="yes"/>is exactly known <note place="foot" n="*">Lapland, France, England, &amp;c. according to Messrs. Wahlenberg,<lb break="yes" />Buch, Ramond, Decandolle, and Smith.</note>, and by dividing this number by that of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Glumace&#x00E6;</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">The Glumace&#x00E6; contain the three families of <hi rendition="#i">Grumine&#x00E6;, Cyperace&#x00E6;,</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Juncace&#x00E6;.</hi>
                    </note>, the leguminous plants, the labiated, and the com-<lb break="no"/>pound, we find numerical relations which form very regular<lb break="yes"/>series. We see certain forms become more common from the<lb break="yes"/>equator towards the pole, like the ferns, the glumace&#x00E6;, the eri-<lb break="no" />cine&#x00E6;, and the rhododendrons. Other forms on the contrary in-<lb break="no"/>crease from the poles towards the equator, and may be consi-<lb break="no"/>dered in our hemisphere as southern forms: such are the ru-<lb break="no"/>biace&#x00E6;, the malvace&#x00E6;, the euphorbia, the leguminous and the<lb break="yes"/>composite plants. Finally, others attain their maximum even<lb break="yes"/>in the temperate zone, and diminish also towards the equator<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">and</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="448" facs="#f0003"/> and the poles. Such are the labiated plants, the amentace&#x00E6;,<lb break="yes"/>the crucifer&#x00E6;, and the umbellifer&#x00E6;. Part of these data long since<lb break="yes"/>struck botanical travellers, and all those who have looked into<lb break="yes" />herbals. It was known that the crucifer&#x00E6; and umbellifer&#x00E6; dis-<lb break="no"/>appeared almost entirely in the plains of the torrid zone, and<lb break="yes"/>that none of the malvace&#x00E6; were found beyond the polar circle.<lb break="yes"/>It is the same with the geography of the plants as with meteoro-<lb break="no"/>logy. The results of those sciences are so simple that in all ages<lb break="yes"/>general ideas have been formed of them: but it is only after la-<lb break="no"/>borious researches, and after having collected a great number of<lb break="yes"/>accurate observations, that numerical results were attained, and<lb break="yes"/>an acquaintance with the partial modifications undergone by <hi rendition="#i">the<lb break="yes"/>law of the distribution of forms.</hi> A table which we have drawn<lb break="yes"/>up exhibits this law with respect to sixteen families of plants<lb break="yes" />distributed over the equatorial, temperate, and glacial zones. We<lb break="yes"/>there see with satisfaction mixed with surprise, how in organic<lb break="yes"/>nature, the forms present constant relations under the same <hi rendition="#i">iso-<lb break="no"/>thermal parallels, i. e.</hi> on curves traced by points of the globe<lb break="yes"/>which receive an equal quantity of heat. The grasses form in<lb break="yes"/>England 1-12th, in France 1-13th, in North America 1-10th,<lb break="yes"/>of all the phanerogamous plants. The glumace&#x00E6; form in Ger-<lb break="no"/>many 1-7th; in France 1-8th; in North America 1-8th; in<lb break="yes"/>New Holland, according to the researches of Mr. Brown, 1-8th;<lb break="yes"/>of the known phanerogamous plants. The composite plants in-<lb break="no"/>crease a little in the northern part of the new continent; for,<lb break="yes"/>according to the new Flora of Pursch, there is between the pa-<lb break="no"/>rallels of Georgia and Boston 1-6th; whereas in Germany we<lb break="yes"/>find 1-8th; and in France 1-7th, of the total number of the species<lb break="yes"/>with visible fructification. In the whole temperate zone, the<lb break="yes"/>glumace&#x00E6; and the composite plants form together; nearly one-<lb break="no"/>fourth of the phanerogamous plants; the glumace&#x00E6;, the com-<lb break="no"/>posit&#x00E6;, the crucifer&#x00E6; and the leguminos&#x00E6;, together nearly one-<lb break="no" />third. It results from these researches that the forms of or-<lb break="no" />ganized beings are in a mutual dependence, and that the unity<lb break="yes" />of nature is such that the forms are limited, the one after the<lb break="yes" />other, according to constant laws easy of determination. When<lb break="yes" />we know upon any point of the globe the number of species pre-<lb break="no" />sented by one of the great families of the glumace&#x00E6;, the com-<lb break="no"/>posite, the cruciferous, or the leguminous plants, we may estimate<lb break="yes"/>with considerable probability both the total number of the pha-<lb break="no"/>nerogamous plants, and the number of species which compose<lb break="yes"/>the other vegetable families. It is thus that, by knowing under<lb break="yes"/>the temperate zone the number of the cyperace&#x00E6; or composite<lb break="yes"/>plants, we may guess at that of the gramineous or leguminous<lb break="yes"/>plants.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">The</fw>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="449" facs="#f0004"/>
                <p>The number of vegetable species described by botanists, or ex-<lb break="no" />isting in European herbals, extends to 44000, of which 6000<lb break="yes" />are agamous. In this number we had already included 3000<lb break="yes"/>new phanerogamous species enumerated by M. Bonpland and<lb break="yes"/>myself. France, according to M. Decandolle, possesses 3645<lb break="yes"/>phanerogamous plants, of which 460 are glumace&#x00E6;, 490 com-<lb break="no"/>posite, and 230 leguminous, &amp;c. In Lapland there are only<lb break="yes"/>497 phanerogamous plants; among which are 124 glumace&#x00E6;,<lb break="yes"/>58 composite, 14 leguminous, 23 amentaceous, &amp;c. See my<lb break="yes"/>Essay on the Geography of Plants published in 1806, and of<lb break="yes"/>which I am preparing a new edition.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In order to account for the differences which exist sometimes<lb break="yes" />between the relations exhibited by Germany, North America,<lb break="yes"/>and France, we must take into consideration the more or less<lb break="yes" />temperate climates of those regions. France extends from 42<formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{2}</formula>°<lb break="yes"/>to 51° of latitude, On this extent the mean annual heat is 16° 7&#x2032;<lb break="yes"/>to 11°: the mean heats of the summer months are 24° to 19°.<lb break="yes"/>Germany, comprised between 46° and 54° of latitude, pre-<lb break="no"/>sents at its extremities mean annual temperatures of 12° 5&#x2032; and<lb break="yes"/>8° 5&#x2032;. The mean heats of the summer months there are 21°<lb break="yes"/>and 18°. North America, in its immense extent, presents the<lb break="yes"/>most varied climates. Mr. Pursch has made us acquainted with<lb break="yes"/>2000 phanerogamous plants which grow between the parallels<lb break="yes"/>of 35° and 44°; consequently under mean annual temperatures<lb break="yes"/>of 16° and 7°. The Flora of North America is a mixture of<lb break="yes"/>several Floras. The southern regions give it an abundance of<lb break="yes"/>malvace&#x00E6; and composite plants; the northern regions, colder than<lb break="yes"/>Europe under the same parallel, furnish to this Flora abundance<lb break="yes"/>of rhododendrons, amentace&#x00E6;, and conifer&#x00E6;. The caryophylle&#x00E6;,<lb break="yes"/>the umbellifer&#x00E6;, and the crucifer&#x00E6; are in general more rare in<lb break="yes"/>North America than in the temperate zone of the old conti-<lb break="no"/>nent <note place="foot" n="*">For the sake of those who are not much conversant in descriptive bo-<lb break="no"/>tany, we shall here enumerate the plants which serve as a type to the forms<lb break="yes"/>or principal families: <hi rendition="#i">Glumace&#x00E6;,</hi> rushes, tares; <hi rendition="#i" >orchide&#x00E6;,</hi> orchis, satyrion,<lb break="yes"/>vanilla; <hi rendition="#i">labiat&#x00E6;,</hi> sage; <hi rendition="#i" >ericine&#x00E6;,</hi> broom; <hi rendition="#i">composit&#x00E6;,</hi> coltsfoot, tussilago; <hi rendition="#i">ru-<lb break="no" />biace&#x00E6;,</hi> madder, quinquina; <hi rendition="#i" >umbellifer&#x00E6;,</hi> fennel; <hi rendition="#i" >crucifer&#x00E6;,</hi> radish, cab-<lb break="no"/>bage; <hi rendition="#i">malvace&#x00E6;,</hi> cotton; <hi rendition="#i" >leguminos&#x00E6;,</hi> furze, truffles, sensitive plant;<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">euphorbiace&#x00E6;,</hi> milky thistle; <hi rendition="#i">amentace&#x00E6;,</hi> willow, oak; <hi rendition="#i" >conifer&#x00E6;,</hi> pine, yew,<lb break="yes"/>juniper.</note>.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These constant relations observed on the surface of the globe,<lb break="yes"/>in the plains from the equator to the pole, are again traced in<lb break="yes"/>the midst of perpetual snows on the summits of mountains. We<lb break="yes"/>may admit, in general, that on the cordilleras of the torrid zone<lb break="yes" />the boreal forms become more frequent. It is thus that we see<lb break="yes" />prevail at Quito on the summit of the Andes, the ericine&#x00E6;, the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">rhodo-</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="450" facs="#f0005"/> rhododendrons, and the gramineous plants. On the contrary,<lb break="yes"/>the labiat&#x00E6;, the rubiace&#x00E6;, the malvace&#x00E6;, and the euphorbiace&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>then become as rare as they are in Lapland. But this analogy<lb break="yes"/>is not supported in the ferns and the composite plants. The<lb break="yes"/>latter abound on the Andes, whereas the former gradually dis-<lb break="no"/>appear when they rise above 1800 fathoms in height. Thus the<lb break="yes"/>climate of the Andes resembles that of northern Europe only<lb break="yes"/>with respect to the mean temperature of the year. The repar-<lb break="no"/>tition of heat into the different seasons is entirely different, and<lb break="yes"/>powerfully influences the ph&#x00E6;nomena of vegetation. In general,<lb break="yes"/>the forms which prevail among the Alpine plants are, according<lb break="yes"/>to my researches, <hi rendition="#k">under the torrid zone,</hi> the <hi rendition="#i">gramine&#x00E6;</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(&#x00E6;gopogon, podos&#x00E6;mum, deyeuxia, avena); the <hi rendition="#i">composit&#x00E6;</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(culcitium, espeletia, aster, baccharis); and the <hi rendition="#i">caryophylle&#x00E6;</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(arenaria, stellaria). <hi rendition="#k">Under the temperate zone,</hi> the <hi rendition="#i">com-<lb break="no"/>posit&#x00E6;</hi> (senecio, leontodon, aster); the <hi rendition="#i">caryophylle&#x00E6;</hi> (ceras-<lb break="no"/>tium, cherleria, silene); and the <hi rendition="#i" >crucifer&#x00E6;</hi> (draba, lepidium).<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Under the frozen zone,</hi> the <hi rendition="#i" >caryophylle&#x00E6;</hi> (stellaria, alsine);<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">ericine&#x00E6;</hi> (andromeda) and the <hi rendition="#i" >ranunculace&#x00E6;.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These researches into the law of the distribution of forms, na-<lb break="no" />turally lead to the question whether there exist plants common<lb break="yes" />to both continents? a question which inspires the more interest,<lb break="yes"/>as it belongs to one of the most important problems in Zoonomia.<lb break="yes"/>It has been long known, and it is one of the most interesting<lb break="yes"/>results from the <hi rendition="#i">geography of animals,</hi> that no quadruped, no<lb break="yes"/>terrestrial bird, and, as appears from the researches of M. La-<lb break="no"/>treille, almost no insect, is common to the equatorial regions of<lb break="yes"/>the two worlds. M. Cuvier is convinced by precise inquiries<lb break="yes"/>that this rule applies even to reptiles. He has ascertained that<lb break="yes"/>the true boa constrictor is peculiar to America, and that the<lb break="yes"/>boas of the old continent were pytons. As to the regions beyond<lb break="yes"/>the tropics, Buffon has multiplied beyond measure the number<lb break="yes"/>of the animals common to America, to Europe, and the north of<lb break="yes"/>Asia. We are assured that the bison, the stag, and the goat of<lb break="yes"/>America, the rabbit and the musk rat, the bear, &amp;c. &amp;c. are<lb break="yes"/>species entirely different from those of Europe, although Buffon<lb break="yes"/>had affirmed the contrary. There remain only the glutton, the<lb break="yes"/>wolf, the white bear, the red fox, perhaps also the elau, which<lb break="yes"/>have not characters sufficient to entitle them to be specific.<lb break="yes"/>Among the plants, we must distinguish between the agam&#x00E6; and<lb break="yes"/>the cotyledone&#x00E6;; and by considering the latter between the mo-<lb break="no" />nocotylodens and the dicotyledons. There remains no doubt<lb break="yes"/>that many of the mosses and lichens are to be found at once in<lb break="yes" />equinoctial America and in Europe: our herbals show this. But<lb break="yes" />the case is not the same with the vascular agam&#x00E6; as with the<lb break="yes"/>agam&#x00E6; of a cellular texture. The ferus and the lycopodiace&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">do</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="451" facs="#f0006"/> do not follow the same laws with the mosses and the lichens.<lb break="yes"/>The former, in particular, exhibit very few species universally to<lb break="yes"/>be found; and the examples cited are frequently doubtful. As<lb break="yes"/>to the phanerogamous plants (with the exception of the rhizo-<lb break="no"/>phora, the avicennia, and some other littoral plants), the law of<lb break="yes"/>Buffon seems to be exact with respect to the species furnished<lb break="yes"/>with two cotyledons. It is absolutely false, although it has been<lb break="yes"/>often affirmed, that the ridges of the cordilleras of Peru, the<lb break="yes"/>climate of which has some analogy with the climate of France<lb break="yes"/>or Sweden, produce similar plants. The oaks, the pines, the<lb break="yes"/>yews, the ranunculi, the rose-trees, the alchemilla, the valerians,<lb break="yes"/>the stellaria, the draba of the Peruvian and Mexican Andes, have<lb break="yes"/>nearly the same physiognomy with the species of the same ge-<lb break="no"/>nera of North America, Siberia, or Europe. But all these al-<lb break="no"/>pine plants of the Cordilleras, without excepting one among<lb break="yes"/>three or four thousand which we have examined, differ specifi-<lb break="no"/>cally from the analogous species of the temperate zone of the old<lb break="yes"/>continent. In general, in that part of America situated between<lb break="yes"/>the tropies, the monocotyledontal plants alone, and among the<lb break="yes"/>latter almost solely the cyperace&#x00E6; and the gramine&#x00E6;, are com-<lb break="no"/>mon to the two worlds. These two families form an exception<lb break="yes"/>to the general law which we are here examining,&#x2014;a law which is<lb break="yes"/>so important for the history of the catastrophes of our planet,<lb break="yes"/>and according to which the organized beings of the equinoctial<lb break="yes"/>regions differ essentially in the two continents. I have given in<lb break="yes"/>my <hi rendition="#i">Prolegomena</hi> a precise catalogue of those monocotyledontal<lb break="yes"/>plants common to the shores of the Oronoko, Germany, and the<lb break="yes"/>East Indies. Their number does not exceed 20 or 24 species,<lb break="yes"/>among which it is sufficient to cite the cyperus mucronatus,<lb break="yes"/>c. hydra, hyp&#x00E6;lyptum argenteum, poa eragrostis, andropogon,<lb break="yes"/>allioni, &amp;c.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In North America placed beyond the tropics, we find nearly<lb break="yes" />one-seventh of monocotyledontal and dicotyledontal plants com-<lb break="no" />mon to the two continents. Of 2900 phanerogamous species<lb break="yes" />collected in the New Flora of Pursch, 390 are European. It is<lb break="yes" />true that we may hazard some doubts, as well with respect to<lb break="yes" />the number of the plants which have accompanied Europeans<lb break="yes"/>from one hemisphere to the other, as upon those which, when<lb break="yes"/>better examined, will be recognised subsequently as new species:<lb break="yes"/>but it is impossible that this state of uncertainty should extend<lb break="yes"/>to all; and it is to be presumed that, even after a careful exami-<lb break="no" />nation, the number of the species common to the temperate<lb break="yes" />zones of the two worlds will still remain very considerably ana-<lb break="no" />logous. Mr. Brown recently undertook some researches on the<lb break="yes" />plants of New Holland. A twenty-eighth part of all the mono-<lb break="no" />cotyledons hitherto found in the austral continent are common<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">to</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="452" facs="#f0007"/> to it with England, France, and Germany. Among the dicoty-<lb break="no"/>ledons the ratio is only 1 in 200; which proves once more how,<lb break="yes"/>in the two hemispheres, the grasses and the cyperace&#x00E6; are the<lb break="yes"/>most diffused, on account of the extreme flexibility of their or-<lb break="no"/>ganization. It would be desirous that learned zoologists should<lb break="yes"/>endeavour to examine the analogous numerical ratios presented<lb break="yes"/>by the distribution of the different families of animals on the<lb break="yes"/>globe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the austral hemisphere the vegetable forms of the torrid<lb break="yes"/>zone advance more towards the pole than in the boreal hemi-<lb break="no"/>sphere. The fern-trees in Asia and America are rarely to be<lb break="yes"/>found beyond the tropic of Cancer; whereas in the austral part<lb break="yes"/>of our globe the <hi rendition="#i">Dicksonia antarctica,</hi> the trunk of which is six<lb break="yes"/>metres in height, pushes its migrations as far as Van Diemen&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>Land under the latitude of 42°: it has even been found in New<lb break="yes"/>Zealand, in Dusky Gulph, under the parallel of Lyons.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Other forms not less majestic, and which were thought to be-<lb break="no"/>long exclusively to the equinoctial Flora, the parasite orchide&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>(epidendra, dendrobia) are found mixed with the arborescent<lb break="yes"/>ferus far beyond the tropic of Capricorn, in the centre of the<lb break="yes"/>austral temperate zone. These ph&#x00E6;nomena of the geography of<lb break="yes"/>plants prove how vague is what has been generally said of the<lb break="yes"/>great diminution of temperature in the southern hemisphere,<lb break="yes"/>without distinguishing between the parallels more or less near<lb break="yes"/>the pole, and without any regard to the division of heat among<lb break="yes"/>the different seasons of the year. Those regions towards which<lb break="yes"/>the equinoctial forms extend, possess, on account of the immen-<lb break="no"/>sity of the seas which surround them, a true <hi rendition="#i">island climate.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>From the tropic of Capricorn to the parallel of 34°, and per-<lb break="no"/>haps still further, the mean heats of the year (<hi rendition="#i">i. e.</hi> the quantity<lb break="yes"/>of heat received by any given point of the globe) do not differ<lb break="yes"/>considerably in the two hemispheres. On casting our eyes over<lb break="yes"/>the three continents, New Holland, Africa, and America, we find<lb break="yes"/>that the mean annual temperature of Port Jackson (lat. 33° 51&#x2032;)<lb break="yes"/>is 19° 3&#x2032; of the centigrade thermometer: that of the Cape of<lb break="yes" />Good Hope (lat. 33° 55&#x2032;) 19° 4&#x2032;; that of the town of Buenos<lb break="yes"/>Ayres (lat. 34° 36&#x2032;) 19° 7&#x2032;. We may be surprised at this great<lb break="yes"/>equality in the distribution of heat by the 34° of austral latitude.<lb break="yes"/>Meteorological observations, still more precise, prove that in the<lb break="yes"/>boreal hemisphere, under this very parallel of 34°, we find a mean<lb break="yes"/>temperature of 19° 8&#x2032;. On advancing towards the antarctic pole,<lb break="yes"/>perhaps even to the parallel of 57°, the temperatures of the two<lb break="yes"/>hemispheres differ less in winter than summer. The Malouine<lb break="yes"/>Islands, situated in 51° and a half of south latitude, have less in-<lb break="no"/>tense cold in winter than is experienced at London. The mean<lb break="yes"/>temperature of Van Diemen&#x2019;s Land seems to be 10°; it freezes<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">during</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="453" facs="#f0008"/> during winter, but not so much as to destroy the fern-trees and<lb break="yes"/>the parasite orchide&#x00E6;. In the adjoining seas Capt. Cook, in<lb break="yes"/>42° of austral latitude, did not see the thermometer fall below<lb break="yes"/>+ 6°, 6 in the midst of winter (July). To these very mild win-<lb break="no"/>ters, summers succeed remarkable for an extraordinary coolness.<lb break="yes"/>At the southern extremity of New Holland (lat. 42° 41&#x2032;) the<lb break="yes"/>temperature of the air rarely rises in the midst of summer at<lb break="yes"/>noon-day higher than 12° or 14°; and in Patagonia, as in the<lb break="yes"/>adjoining ocean (lat. 48° &#x2014; 58°), the mean heat of the warmest<lb break="yes"/>month is only 7° &#x2014; 8°; whereas in the boreal hemisphere at Pe-<lb break="no"/>tersburg and Umeo (lat. 59° 56&#x2032; and 63° 50&#x2032;) this heat exceeds<lb break="yes"/>17 &#x2014; 19. It is this mild temperature of the islands, which<lb break="yes"/>the southern countries enjoy between 30° and 40° of latitude,<lb break="yes"/>which permits the vegetable forms to pass beyond the tropic of<lb break="yes" />Capricorn. They embellish a great part of the temperate zone;<lb break="yes" />and the genera which the inhabitant of the northern hemisphere<lb break="yes" />regards as exclusively belonging to the tropical climates, present<lb break="yes"/>numerous species between the parallels of 35° and 38° of south<lb break="yes"/>latitude.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 