<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.1" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.1" when="2018-10-10" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung für Verlag.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="401" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Account of the Spermaceti Fishery on the Western Shore<lb break="yes"/>of America.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>By M. von Humboldt.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>HE western coast of Mexico, especially that part of the<lb break="yes"/>great ocean, situated between the gulph of Bayonna, the<lb break="yes"/>three Mary Islands, and Cape St. Lucas, abounds in spermaceti<lb break="yes"/>whales, or cachalots, of which the fishery is one of the most<lb break="yes"/>important objects of mercantile speculation, on account of the<lb break="yes"/>extremely high prices given for spermaceti (adipocire) by the<lb break="yes"/>English and the inhabitants of the United States. Were it<lb break="yes"/>not for the cachalot fishery, and the trade in furs of sea otters,<lb break="yes"/>at Noutka, the great ocean would scarcely ever be frequented<lb break="yes"/>by the Anglo-Americans and Europeans. Of all the oily li-<lb break="no"/>quids which enter into trade, there are few so dear as sperma-<lb break="no"/>ceti, or the particular substance contained in the enormous<lb break="yes"/>caverns of the snout of the cachalot. A single individual of<lb break="yes"/>these cetaceous giants yields as much as 125 English barrels<lb break="yes"/>(of 32½ gallons each) of spermaceti. A tun, containing eight<lb break="yes"/>of these barrels, or 1024 pints of Paris, used to sell in London<lb break="yes"/>before the peace of Amiens at 70l. or 80l. and during the war<lb break="yes"/>at 95l. and 100l. sterling. ’Till 1788 the whale fishers only fre-<lb break="no"/>quented the coasts of Chili and Peru. Only twelve or fifteen<lb break="yes"/>vessels then doubled Cape Horn annually for the cachalot<lb break="yes"/>fishery, while at the period when I was in the South Sea, there<lb break="yes"/>were more than sixty under the English flag alone.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The great ocean unites all the circumstances that render the<lb break="yes" />cachalot fishery both easy and lucrative. It is richer in mol-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">luscus</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="402" facs="#f0002"/>luscus fish, porpoises, tortoises, and sea calves of every species,<lb break="yes"/>and offers more nourishment to cetaceous animals than the At-<lb break="no"/>lantic Ocean. Hence these last are there in greater numbers,<lb break="yes"/>as well fatter as larger. The calm, which prevails during so<lb break="yes"/>great a part of the year in the equinoctial region of the south<lb break="yes"/>sea, facilitates very much the pursuit of cachalots and whales.<lb break="yes"/>It is a general rule that the cachalot avoids shallows, whereas<lb break="yes"/>they are sought after by the whale.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The greatest number of English and Anglo-American ves-<lb break="no"/>sels, which enter the great ocean, have the double object in<lb break="yes"/>view of carrying on the cachalot fishery and an illicit com-<lb break="no"/>merce with the Spanish colonies. The whale fishers can easily<lb break="yes"/>distinguish at a distance the cachalots from the whales, by the<lb break="yes"/>manner in which the former spout up the brine through their<lb break="yes"/>spiracles. The cachalots can remain longer under water, than<lb break="yes"/>the true whale. When they come to the surface, their respi-<lb break="no"/>ration is more frequently interrupted. The female of the ca-<lb break="no"/>chalot is four or five times smaller than the male; and its head<lb break="yes"/>does not yield more than 25 English barrels of <choice>
                        <sic>adipocire</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">adipocire.</corr>
                    </choice> A<lb break="yes"/>great number of females go generally together, led by two or<lb break="yes"/>three males, which are perpetually describing circles round<lb break="yes"/>their flock. This fishery, to be profitable, must be conducted<lb break="yes"/>on the most economical principles. Vessels from 180 to 300<lb break="yes"/>tons are employed in it, and the crew consists only of 16 or 24<lb break="yes"/>individuals. The expences of equipment of a vessel of 180<lb break="yes"/>tons, lined with copper, and provisioned for a voyage of two<lb break="yes"/>years, is estimated in London at 7000l. sterling. The fitter-out<lb break="yes"/>gives the sailors only their food, and a very small sum of money<lb break="yes"/>under the name of advance. Their pay depends on the pro-<lb break="no"/>duce of the fishery; for as the whole crew contribute to it,<lb break="yes"/>every individual has a right to the profit. It is not the want<lb break="yes"/>of hands which prevents the inhabitants of Mexico from ap-<lb break="no"/>plying to the cachalot fishery. In the present state of the Spa-<lb break="no"/>nish colonies, the sloth of the inhabitants is inimical to the<lb break="yes"/>execution of similar projects; and it would be impossible to<lb break="yes"/>procure sailors willing to embrace so rude a business, and so<lb break="yes"/>miserable a life, as that of cachalot fishers. How could they<lb break="yes"/>be found in a country, where, according to the ideas of the<lb break="yes"/>common people, all that is necessary to happiness is, bananas,<lb break="yes"/>salted flesh, a hammock, and a guitar? The hope of gain is<lb break="yes"/>too weak a stimulus under a zone where beneficent nature pro-<lb break="no"/>vides man a thousand means of procuring an easy and peace-<lb break="no"/>ful existence without quitting his country, and without strug-<lb break="no"/>gling with the monsters of the ocean.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 