<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="354" facs="#f0001"/><cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Humboldt on the Geography of Plants.</hi>&#x2014;</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Alexander</hi> Count Humboldt has submit-<lb break="no"/>ted to the Institute a curious paper, on the<lb break="yes"/>laws observed in the distribution of vegetable<lb break="yes"/>forms over the globe. Botany, long con-<lb break="no"/>fined to the simple description of the exter-<lb break="no"/>nal forms of plants, and their artificial clas-<lb break="no" />sification, now presents several branches of<lb break="yes"/>study, which place it more on a footing with<lb break="yes"/>the other sciences. Such are the distribu-<lb break="no"/>tion of vegetables, according to a natural<lb break="yes"/>method founded upon the whole part of<lb break="yes"/>their structure; physiology, which displays<lb break="yes"/>their internal organization; botanical geo-<lb break="no"/>graphy, which assigns to each tribe of plants<lb break="yes"/>their height, limits, and climate. The<lb break="yes" />terms alpine plants, plants of hot countries,<lb break="yes"/>plants of the sea-shore, are to be found in<lb break="yes"/>all languages, even in those of the most sa-<lb break="no"/>vage nations on the banks of the Oronoko.<lb break="yes"/>They prove that the attention of men has<lb break="yes"/>been constantly fixed on the distribution of<lb break="yes"/>vegetables, and on their connexion with the<lb break="yes"/>temperature of the air, the elevation of the<lb break="yes"/>soil, and the nature of the ground which<lb break="yes" />they inhabit. It does not require much sa-<lb break="no"/>gacity to observe, that on the slope of the<lb break="yes"/>high mountains of Armenia, vegetables of<lb break="yes"/>a different latitude follow each in succession,<lb break="yes"/>like the climates, superposed, as it were,<lb break="yes"/>upon each other.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The vegetables, says he, which cover the<lb break="yes"/>vast surface of the globe, present, when we<lb break="yes"/>study by natural classes or families, striking<lb break="yes"/>differences in the distribution of their forms.<lb break="yes"/>On limiting them to the countries in which<lb break="yes"/>the number of the species is exactly known,<lb break="yes"/>and by dividing this number by that of the<lb break="yes"/>glumace&#x00E6;, the leguminous plants, the la-<lb break="no"/>biated, and the compound, we find nume-<lb break="no" />rical relations which form very regular se-<lb break="no"/>ries. We see certain forms become more<lb break="yes"/>common, from the equator towards the pole,<lb break="yes"/>like the ferns, the glumace&#x00E6;, the ericine&#x00E6;,<lb break="yes"/>and the rhododendrons. Other forms, on<lb break="yes"/>the contrary, increase from the poles to-<lb break="no"/>wards the equator, and may be considered<lb break="yes"/>in our hemisphere as southern forms: such<lb break="yes"/>are the rubiace&#x00E6;, the malvace&#x00E6;, the eu-<lb break="no"/>phorbia, the leguminous, and the compo-<lb break="no"/>site plants. Finally, others attain their<lb break="yes"/>maximum even in the temperate zone, and<lb break="yes"/>diminish also towards the equator and the<lb break="yes" />poles; such are the labiated plants, the<lb break="yes"/>amentace&#x00E6;, the crucifer&#x00E6;, and the umbel-<lb break="no"/>lifer&#x00E6;. The grasses form in England 1-12th,<lb break="yes"/>in France 1-13th, in North America 1-10th,<lb break="yes"/>of all the phanerogamous plants. The glu-<lb break="no"/>mace&#x00E6; form in Germany 1-7th, in France<lb break="yes"/>1-8th, in North America 1-8th, in New<lb break="yes"/><cb/>Holland, according to the researches of Mr<lb break="yes" />Brown, 1-8th, of the known phanerogamous<lb break="yes"/>plants. The composite plants increase a<lb break="yes"/>little in the northern part of the new con-<lb break="no"/>tinent; for, according to the new Flora of<lb break="yes" />Pursch, there is between the parallels of<lb break="yes"/>Georgia and Boston 1-6th, whereas in Ger-<lb break="no"/>many we find 1-8th, and in France 1-7th,<lb break="yes"/>of the total number of the species, with vi-<lb break="no"/>sible fructification. In the whole temperate<lb break="yes" />zone, the glumace&#x00E6; and the composite<lb break="yes"/>plants, form together, nearly one-fourth of<lb break="yes"/>the phanerogamous plants; the glumace&#x00E6;,<lb break="yes"/>the composit&#x00E6;, the crucifer&#x00E6;, and the legu-<lb break="no" />minos&#x00E6;, together, nearly one-third. It re-<lb break="no"/>sults from these researches, that the forms<lb break="yes"/>of organized beings are in a mutual de-<lb break="no"/>pendence; and that the unity of nature is<lb break="yes" />such, that the forms are limited, the one<lb break="yes"/>after the other, according to constant laws<lb break="yes"/>easy of determination.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The number of vegetable species describ-<lb break="no"/>ed by botanists, or existing in European<lb break="yes"/>herbals, extends to 44,000, of which 6000<lb break="yes"/>are agamous. In this number we had al-<lb break="no" />ready included 3000 new phanerogamous<lb break="yes"/>species enumerated by M. Bompland and<lb break="yes"/>myself. France, according to M. Decan-<lb break="no"/>dolle, possesses 3645 phanerogamous plants,<lb break="yes"/>of which 460 are glumace&#x00E6;, 490 composite,<lb break="yes"/>and 230 leguminous, &amp;c. In Lapland there<lb break="yes"/>are only 497 phanerogamous plants; among<lb break="yes"/>which are 124 glumace&#x00E6;, 58 composite, 14<lb break="yes"/>leguminous, 23 amentaceous, &amp;c.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mr Pursch has made us acquainted with<lb break="yes"/>2000 phanerogamous plants which grow be-<lb break="no"/>tween the parallels of 35&#x00B0; and 44&#x00B0;; con-<lb break="no"/>sequently, under mean annual temperatures<lb break="yes"/>of 16&#x00B0; and 7&#x00B0;. The flora of North Ame-<lb break="no"/>rica is a mixture of several floras. The<lb break="yes"/>southern regions give it an abundance of<lb break="yes"/>malvace&#x00E6; and composite plants; the north-<lb break="no"/>ern regions, colder than Europe, under the<lb break="yes"/>same parallel, furnish to this flora abund-<lb break="no"/>ance of rhododendrons, amentace&#x00E6;, and co-<lb break="no"/>nifer&#x00E6;. The caryophylle&#x00E6;, the umbellifer&#x00E6;,<lb break="yes"/>and the crucifer&#x00E6;, are in general more rare<lb break="yes"/>in North America, than in the temperate<lb break="yes"/>zone of the old continent.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These constant relations observed on the<lb break="yes"/>surface of the globe, in the plains from the<lb break="yes"/>equator to the pole, are again traced in the<lb break="yes"/>midst of perpetual snows on the summits of<lb break="yes"/>mountains. We may admit, in general,<lb break="yes"/>that on the cordilleras of the torrid zone,<lb break="yes"/>the boreal forms become more frequent. It<lb break="yes"/>is thus that we see prevail at Quito, on the<lb break="yes"/>summit of the Andes, the ericine&#x00E6;, the rho-<lb break="no" />dodendrons, and the gramineous plants. On<lb break="yes"/>the contrary, the labiat&#x00E6;, the rubiace&#x00E6;, the<lb break="yes"/>malvace&#x00E6;, and the euphorbiace&#x00E6;, then be-<lb break="no"/>come as rare as they are in Lapland. But<lb break="yes" />this analogy is not supported in the ferns<lb break="yes"/>and the composite plants. The latter a-<lb break="no"/>bound on the Andes, whereas the former<lb break="yes"/>gradually disappear when they rise above<lb break="yes"/>1800 fathoms in height. Thus the climate<lb break="yes"/>of the Andes resembles that of northern Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope only with respect to the mean tem-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="355" facs="#f0002"/><cb/>perature of the year. The repartition of<lb break="yes"/>heat into the different seasons is entirely<lb break="yes" />different, and powerfully influences the phe-<lb break="no"/>nomena of vegetation. In general, the<lb break="yes"/>forms which prevail among the alpine plants,<lb break="yes"/>are, according to my researches, under the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone, the gramin&#x00E6; (&#x00E6;gopogon, podo-<lb break="no"/>s&#x00E6;mum, deyeuxia, avena); the composit&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>(calcitium, espeletia, aster, baccharis); and<lb break="yes"/>the caryophylle (arenaria, stellaria.) Under<lb break="yes"/>the temperate zone, the composit&#x00E6; (senecio,<lb break="yes" />leontodon, aster); the caryophylle&#x00E6; (ceras-<lb break="no"/>tium, cherleria, silene); and the crucifer&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>(draba, lepidium.) Under the frozen zone,<lb break="yes"/>the caryophyll&#x00E6; (stellaria, alsine); the eri-<lb break="no"/>cine&#x00E6; (andromeda), and the ranunculace&#x00E6;.<lb break="yes"/>It has been long known, and it is one of<lb break="yes"/>the most interesting results from the geo-<lb break="no"/>graphy of animals, that no quadruped, no<lb break="yes"/>terrestrial bird, and, as appears from the<lb break="yes" />researches of M. Latreille, almost no insect<lb break="yes"/>is common to the equatorial regions of the<lb break="yes"/>two worlds. M. Cuvier is convinced, by<lb break="yes"/>precise inquiries, that this rule applies even<lb break="yes"/>to reptiles. He has ascertained, that the<lb break="yes"/>true boa constrictor is peculiar to America;<lb break="yes"/>and that the boas of the old continent, were<lb break="yes"/>pytons. Among the plants, we must dis-<lb break="no"/>tinguish between the agam&#x00E6; and the cotyle-<lb break="no"/>done&#x00E6;: and by considering the latter be-<lb break="no"/>tween the monocotylodens and the dicotyle-<lb break="no"/>dons. There remains no doubt that many<lb break="yes"/>of the mosses and lichens are to be found at<lb break="yes" />once in equinoctial America and in Europe.<lb break="yes"/>But the case is not the same with the vascu-<lb break="no"/>lar agam&#x00E6; as with the agam&#x00E6; of a cellular<lb break="yes"/>texture. The ferns and the lycopodiace&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>do not follow the same laws with the mosses<lb break="yes"/>and the lichens. The former, in particular,<lb break="yes"/>exhibit very few species universally to be<lb break="yes"/>found; and the examples cited are fre-<lb break="no"/>quently doubtful. As to the phanerogamous<lb break="yes"/>plants (with the exception of the rhizophora,<lb break="yes"/>the avicennia, and some other littoral<lb break="yes"/>plants), the law of Buffon seems to be exact<lb break="yes"/>with respect to the species furnished with<lb break="yes"/>two cotyledons. It is absolutely false, al-<lb break="no"/>though it has been often affirmed, that the<lb break="yes"/>ridges of the cordilleras of Peru, the climate<lb break="yes"/>of which has some analogy with the climate<lb break="yes"/>of France or Sweden, produce similar plants.<lb break="yes" />The oaks, the pines, the yews, the ranun-<lb break="no"/>culi, the rose-trees, the alchemilla, the va-<lb break="no"/>lerians, the stellaria, the draba of the<lb break="yes"/>Peruvian and Mexican Andes, have<lb break="yes"/>nearly the same physiognomy with the<lb break="yes"/>species of the same genera of North A-<lb break="no"/>merica, Siberia, or Europe. But all<lb break="yes" />these alpine plants of the cordilleras, with-<lb break="no"/>out excepting one among three or four<lb break="yes"/>thousand which we have examined, differ<lb break="yes"/>specifically from the analogous species of the<lb break="yes" />temperate zone of the old continent. In<lb break="yes"/>general, in that part of America situated be-<lb break="no"/>tween the tropics, the monocotyledontal<lb break="yes"/>plants alone, and among the latter almost<lb break="yes"/>solely the cyperace&#x00E6; and the gramine&#x00E6;, are<lb break="yes"/>common to the two worlds. These two fa-<lb break="no"/>milies form an exception to the general law<lb break="yes"/><cb/>which we are here examining,&#x2014;a law which<lb break="yes"/>is so important for the history of the catas-<lb break="no"/>trophes of our planet, and according to<lb break="yes" />which, the organized beings of the equi-<lb break="no"/>noctial regions differ essentially in the two<lb break="yes"/>continents.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 