<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.1" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.1" when="2018-10-10" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung für Verlag.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="46" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>The Southern Constellations.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">(From Humboldt’s Personal Narrative.)</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From the time we entered the torrid zone,<lb break="yes"/>we were never wearied with admiring, every<lb break="yes"/>night, the beauty of the southern sky, which, as<lb break="yes"/>we advanced towards the south, opened new<lb break="yes"/>constellations to our view. We feel an indescri-<lb break="no" />bable sensation, when, on approaching the equa-<lb break="no"/>tor, and particularly on passing from one hemis-<lb break="no"/>phere to the other, we see those stars, which we<lb break="yes"/>have contemplated from our infancy, progressive-<lb break="no"/>ly sink, and finally disappear. Nothing awa-<lb break="no"/>kens in the traveller a livelier remembrance, of the<lb break="yes"/>immense distance by which he is separated from<lb break="yes" />his country, than the aspect of an unknown fir-<lb break="no"/>mament. The grouping of the stars of the first<lb break="yes"/>magnitude, some scattered nebulæ, rivalling in<lb break="yes"/>splendour the milky way, and tracts of space re-<lb break="no"/>markable for their extreme blackness, give a par-<lb break="no"/>ticular physiognomy to the southern sky. This<lb break="yes" />sight fills with admiration even those, who, unin-<lb break="no"/>structed in the branches of accurate science, feel<lb break="yes"/>the same emotion of delight in the contemplation<lb break="yes"/>of the heavenly vault, as in the view of a beautiful<lb break="yes"/>landscape, or a majestick site. A traveller has<lb break="yes"/>no need of being a botanist, to recognize the tor-<lb break="no"/>rid zone on the mere aspect of its vegetation: and<lb break="yes"/>without having acquired any notions of astrono-<lb break="no" />my, without any acquaintance with the celestial<lb break="yes"/>charts of Flamstead and de la Caille, he feels he<lb break="yes"/>is not in Europe, when he sees the immense con-<lb break="no"/>stellation of the Ship, or the phosporescent clouds<lb break="yes"/>of Magellan, arise on the horizon. The heaven,<lb break="yes"/>and the earth, every thing in the equinoctial re-<lb break="no"/>gions, assumes an exotic character.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The lower regions of the air were loaded with<lb break="yes"/>vapours for some days. We saw distinctly for<lb break="yes"/>the first time the cross of the south only in the<lb break="yes"/>night of the 4th and 5th of July, in the sixteenth<lb break="yes"/>degree of latitude<hi rendition="#i">;</hi> it was strongly inclined to,<lb break="yes"/>&amp; appeared from time to time between the clouds,<lb break="yes"/>the centre of which furrowed by uncondensed<lb break="yes"/>lightnings, reflected a silver light. If a traveller<lb break="yes"/>may be permitted to speak of his personal emo-<lb break="no" />tions, I shall add that in this night I saw one of<lb break="yes"/>the reveries of my earliest youth accomplished.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When we begin to fix our eyes on geographical<lb break="yes"/>maps, &amp; read the narratives of navigators, we feel<lb break="yes"/>for certain countries and climates a sort of predi-<lb break="no"/>lection, for which we know not how to account at<lb break="yes"/>a more advanced period of life. These impres-<lb break="no"/>sions, however, exercise a considerable influence<lb break="yes" />over our determinations<hi rendition="#i">;</hi> and from a sort of in-<lb break="no"/>stinct we endeavour to connect ourselves with ob-<lb break="no" />jects, on which the mind has long been fixed as<lb break="yes"/>by a secret charm. At a period when I studied<lb break="yes"/>the heavens, not with the intention of devoting<lb break="yes"/>myself to astronomy, but only to acquire a know-<lb break="no"/>ledge of the stars, I was agitated by a fear unknown<lb break="yes"/>to those who love a sedentary life. It seemed<lb break="yes" />painful to me to renounce the hope of beholding<lb break="yes"/>those beautiful constellations, which border the<lb break="yes"/>southern pole. Impatient to rove in the equinoc-<lb break="no"/>tial regions, I <choice>
                        <sic>couuld</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">could</corr>
                    </choice> not raise my eyes towards<lb break="yes"/>the starry vault without thinking of the Cross of<lb break="yes"/>the South, and without recalling the sublime pas-<lb break="no"/>sage of Dante, which the most celebrated com-<lb break="no"/>mentators have applied to this constellation<hi rendition="#i" >:</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <lg type="poem">
                    <l>Io mi volsi a man destra e <choice><sic>posi</sic><corr type="editorial">puosi</corr></choice> mente</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>All’altro polo e vidi quattro stelle</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Non viste mai fuor ch’alla prima gente.</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Goder <choice><sic>pare lo ceil</sic><corr type="editorial">pareva il ciel</corr></choice> di lor <choice><sic>fammelle</sic><corr type="editorial">fiammelle</corr></choice><choice><sic>;</sic><corr type="editorial">:</corr></choice></l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>O <choice><sic>settrentrional</sic><corr type="editorial">settentrional</corr></choice> vedovo sito</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Poi che privato <choice><sic>se’</sic><corr type="editorial">sei</corr></choice> di mirar quelle!</l>
                </lg>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The pleasure we felt on discovering the south-<lb break="no"/>ern Cross was warmly shared by such of the crew<lb break="yes"/>as had lived in the colonies. In the solitude of<lb break="yes"/>the seas we hail a star as a friend, from whom we<lb break="yes"/>have long been separated. Among the Portu-<lb break="no" />guese and the Spaniards peculiar motives seem<lb break="yes"/>to increase this feeling; a religious sentiment at-<lb break="no"/>taches them to a constellation, the form of which<lb break="yes"/>recalls the sign of the faith planted by their ances-<lb break="no"/>tors in the deserts of the new world.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The two great stars which mark the summit<lb break="yes"/>and the foot of the Cross having nearly the same<lb break="yes"/>right ascension, it follows hence, that the constel-<lb break="no"/>lation is almost perpendicular at the moment<lb break="yes"/>when it passes the meridian. This circumstance<lb break="yes" />is known to every nation, that lives beyond the<lb break="yes"/>tropics, or in the southern hemisphere. It has<lb break="yes"/>been observed at what hour of the night, in differ-<lb break="no"/>ent seasons, the Cross of the south is erect or incli-<lb break="no"/>ned. It is a time-piece that advances very regu-<lb break="no"/>larly near four minutes a day, and no other<lb break="yes"/>group of stars exhibits to the naked eye, an ob-<lb break="no" />servation of time so easily made. How often<lb break="yes"/>have we heard our guides exclaim in the savan-<lb break="no"/>nas of Venezuela, or in the desert extending from<lb break="yes"/>Lima to Truxillo, “Midnight is past, the Cross<lb break="yes"/>begins to bend!” How often those words remind-<lb break="no" />ed us of that affecting scene, where Paul and<lb break="yes"/>Virginia seated near the source of the river of<lb break="yes"/>Lataniers, conversed together for the last time,<lb break="yes"/>and where the old man, at the sign of the south-<lb break="no"/>ern Cross, warns them that it is time to sepa-<lb break="no"/>rate.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 