<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="4" facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>For several nights past the Southern Cross has been clear-<lb break="no"/>ly visible, and, of course, called up all my poetical senti-<lb break="no"/>ment; but, as Baron Von Humboldt has clothed this con-<lb break="no"/>stellation in such divine language, I will here give you an<lb break="yes"/>extract from his journal;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;From the time,&#x201D; says M. de Humboldt, &#x201C;we entered the<lb break="yes"/>Torrid Zone, we were never wearied with admiring, every<lb break="yes"/>night, the beauty of the southern sky, which, as we advan-<lb break="no"/>ced towards the South, opened new constellations to our<lb break="yes"/>view. Nothing awakens in the traveller a livelier remem-<lb break="no"/>brance of the immense distance by which he is separated<lb break="yes"/>from his country than an aspect of an unknown firmament.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;A traveller feels that he is not in Europe when he sees<lb break="yes"/>the immense constellation of the ship, or the phosphorescent<lb break="yes"/>clouds of Magellan arise on the horizon. The heaven and<lb break="yes"/>the earth, everything in the equinoctial regions, assume an<lb break="yes"/>exotic character.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;When we begin to fix our eyes on geographical maps, and<lb break="yes"/>read the narratives of navigators, we feel for certain countries<lb break="yes"/>and climates a sort of predilection, for which we know not<lb break="yes"/>how to account, at a more advanced period of life. These<lb break="yes"/>impressions, however, exercise a considerable influence over<lb break="yes"/>our determinations; and, from a sort of instinct, we en-<lb break="no"/>deavor to connect ourselves with objects, on which<lb break="yes"/>the mind has long been fixed, as by a secret charm. At a<lb break="yes"/>period when I studied the heavens, not with the intention<lb break="yes"/>of devoting myself to astronomy, but only to acquire a<lb break="yes"/>knowledge of the stars, I was agitated by a fear unknown to<lb break="yes"/>those who love a sedentary life. It seemed painful to me to<lb break="yes"/>renounce the hope of beholding those beautiful constella-<lb break="no"/>tions which border the Southern pole. Impatient to rove in<lb break="yes"/>the equinoctial regions, I could not raise my eyes toward<lb break="yes"/>the starry vault without thinking of the <hi rendition="#i">Cross of the South,</hi>
                <lb break="yes"/>and without recalling the sublime passage of Dante, which<lb break="yes"/>the most celebrated commentators have applied to this con-<lb break="no"/>stellation:</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <lg type="poem">
                <l>&#x201C;I turned me to right; my spirit flew</l>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <l>To the other pole; four stars shone sweetly bright,</l>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <l>Ne&#x2019;er seen but by the primal privileged few</l>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <l>The heavens seemed revelling in their glorious light;</l>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <l>O desolate North! thy melancholy clime</l>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <l>Looked never on their gladdening ray sublime!&#x201D;</l>
            </lg>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;In the solitude of the seas we hail a star as a friend from<lb break="yes"/>whom we have been long separated. Among the Portu-<lb break="no"/>guese and the Spanish, peculiar motives seem to increase<lb break="yes"/>this feeling; a religious sentiment attaches them to a con-<lb break="no"/>stellation, the form of which recalls the sign of the faith<lb break="yes"/>planted by their ancestors in the deserts of the new world.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;The two great stars which mark the summit, and the foot<lb break="yes"/>of the Cross, having nearly the same right ascension, it fol-<lb break="no"/>lows hence that the constellation is almost perpendicular at<lb break="yes"/>the moment when it passes the meridian.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;This circumstance is known to every nation that lies be-<lb break="no"/>yond the tropics, or in the Southern hemisphere. It has<lb break="yes"/>been observed at what hour of the night, in different sea-<lb break="no"/>sons, the Cross of the South is erect or inclined. It is a<lb break="yes"/>time-piece that advances very regularly four minutes a day,<lb break="yes"/>and no other group of stars exhibits, to the naked eye, an<lb break="yes"/>observation of time so easily made. A traveller says: &#x201C;How<lb break="yes"/>often have we heard our guides exclaim, in the savannas of<lb break="yes"/>Venezuela, or in the desert extending from Lima to Truxillo,<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;Midnight is past, the Cross begins to bend.&#x2019;&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 