<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">[Sur les Lois que l’on observe dans la distribution des formes végétales]</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:51</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.33</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1816-Sur_les_lois-5-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1816-Sur_les_lois-1.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1816-Sur_les_lois-2.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1816-Sur_les_lois-3.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1816-Sur_les_lois-4.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1816-Sur_les_lois-5-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1816-Sur_les_lois-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1816-Sur_les_lois-7-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1816-Sur_les_lois-8-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1816-Sur_les_lois-9-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">[Sur les Lois que l’on observe dans la distribution des formes végétales]</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1819</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Monthly Magazine; or, British Register&lt;/i&gt; 47:5:326 (1. Juni 1819), S. 438–440.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Schmuck: Kapitälchen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="438" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#c">II.</hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#k">
                    Alexander Count Humboldt</hi> has<lb break="yes" />submitted to the Institute a curious<lb break="yes"/>paper, on the laws observed in the distri-<lb break="no"/>bution of vegetable forms over the globe.<lb break="yes"/>Botany, long confined to the simple de-<lb break="no"/>scription of the external forms of plants,<lb break="yes"/>and their artificial classification, now<lb break="yes"/>presents several branches of study,<lb break="yes"/>which place it more on a footing with<lb break="yes"/>the other sciences. Such are the distri-<lb break="no"/>bution of vegetables, according to a<lb break="yes" />natural method founded upon the whole<lb break="yes"/>part of their structure; physiology,<lb break="yes"/>which displays their internal <choice>
                    <sic>organiza-<lb break="no"/>zation</sic>
                    <corr type="editorial">organiza-<lb break="no"/>tion</corr>
                </choice>; botanical geography, which<lb break="yes"/>assigns to each tribe of plants their<lb break="yes"/>height, limits, and climate. The terms<lb break="yes" />alpine plants, plants of hot countries,<lb break="yes"/>
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">plants</fw>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="439" facs="#f0002"/><cb/>plants of the sea-shore, are to be found in<lb break="yes"/>all languages, even in those of the most<lb break="yes"/>savage nations on the banks of the<lb break="yes"/>Oronoko. They prove that the atten-<lb break="no"/>tion of men has been constantly fixed on<lb break="yes"/>the distribution of vegetables, and on<lb break="yes"/>their connexion with the temperature of<lb break="yes"/>the air, the elevation of the soil, and the<lb break="yes"/>nature of the ground which they inhabit.<lb break="yes"/>It does not require much sagacity to ob-<lb break="no"/>serve, that on the slope of the high<lb break="yes"/>mountains of Armenia, vegetables of a<lb break="yes" />different latitude follow each in succes-<lb break="no"/>sion, like the elimates, superposed, as it<lb break="yes"/>were, upon each other.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>The vegetables, says he, which cover<lb break="yes"/>the vast surface of the globe, present,<lb break="yes"/>when we study by natural classes or<lb break="yes" />families, striking differences in the dis-<lb break="no"/>tribution of their forms. On limiting<lb break="yes"/>them to the countries in which the num-<lb break="no"/>ber of the species is exactly known, and<lb break="yes"/>by dividing this number by that of the<lb break="yes"/>glumace&#x00E6;, the leguminous plants, the<lb break="yes"/>labiated, and the compound, we find<lb break="yes"/>numerical relations which form very<lb break="yes"/>regular series. We see certain forms<lb break="yes"/>become more common, from the equator<lb break="yes"/>towards the pole, like the ferns, the<lb break="yes"/>glumace&#x00E6;, the ericine&#x00E6;, and the rhodo-<lb break="no"/>dendrons. Other forms, on the contrary,<lb break="yes"/>increase from the poles towards the<lb break="yes"/>equator, and may be considered in our<lb break="yes"/>hemisphere as southern forms: such are<lb break="yes"/>the rubiace&#x00E6;, the malvace&#x00E6;, the eu-<lb break="no"/>phorbia, the leguminous, and the com-<lb break="no"/>posite, plants. Finally, others attain<lb break="yes"/>their maximum even in the temperate<lb break="yes"/>zone, and diminish also towards the<lb break="yes"/>equator and the poles; such are the<lb break="yes"/>labiated plants, the amentace&#x00E6;, the<lb break="yes"/>crucifer&#x00E6;, and the umbellifer&#x00E6;. The<lb break="yes"/>grasses form in England 1-12th, in<lb break="yes"/>France 1-13th, in North America 1-10th,<lb break="yes"/>of all the phanerogamous plants. The<lb break="yes"/>glumace&#x00E6; form in Germany 1-7th, in<lb break="yes"/>France 1-8th, in North America 1-8th,<lb break="yes"/>in New Holland, according to the re-<lb break="no"/>searches of Mr. Brown, 1-8th, of the<lb break="yes"/>known phanerogamous plants. The<lb break="yes"/>composite plants increase a little in the<lb break="yes"/>northern part of the new continent; for,<lb break="yes" />according to the new Flora of Pursch,<lb break="yes"/>there is between the parallels of<lb break="yes"/>Georgia and Boston 1-6th, whereas in<lb break="yes" />Germany we find 1-8th, and in France<lb break="yes"/>1-7th, of the total number of the species,<lb break="yes"/>with visible fructification. In the whole<lb break="yes"/>temperate zone, the glumace&#x00E6; and the<lb break="yes"/>composite plants, form together, nearly<lb break="yes"/>one-fourth of the phanerogamous plants;<lb break="yes"/>the glumace&#x00E6;, the composit&#x00E6;, the<lb break="yes" />crucifer&#x00E6;, and the leguminos&#x00E6;, together,<cb/>nearly one-third. It results from these<lb break="yes"/>researches, that the forms of organized<lb break="yes" />beings are in a mutual dependence; and<lb break="yes"/>that the unity of nature is such, that the<lb break="yes"/>forms are limited, the one after the<lb break="yes" />other, according to constant laws easy<lb break="yes"/>of determination.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>The number of vegetable species de-<lb break="no"/>scribed by botanists, or existing in Eu-<lb break="no"/>ropean herbals, extends to 44,000, of<lb break="yes"/>which 6000 are agamous. In this num-<lb break="no"/>ber we had already included 3000 new<lb break="yes"/>phanerogamous species enumerated by<lb break="yes"/>M. Bompland and myself. France, ac-<lb break="no"/>cording to M. Decandolle, possesses<lb break="yes"/>3645 phanerogamous plants, of which<lb break="yes" />460 are glumace&#x00E6;, 490 composite, and<lb break="yes"/>230 leguminous, &amp;c. In Lapland there<lb break="yes"/>are only 497 phanerogamous plants;<lb break="yes" />among which are 124 glumace&#x00E6;, 58<lb break="yes"/>composite, 14 leguminous, 23 amentace-<lb break="no"/>ous, &amp;c.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>Mr. Pursch has made us acquainted<lb break="yes"/>with 2000 phanerogamous plants which<lb break="yes"/>grow between the parallels of 35&#x00B0; and<lb break="yes"/>44&#x00B0;; consequently, under mean annual<lb break="yes"/>temperatures of 16&#x00B0; and 7&#x00B0;. The flora<lb break="yes"/>of North America is a mixture of several<lb break="yes" />floras. The southern regions give it an<lb break="yes"/>abundance of malvace&#x00E6; and composite<lb break="yes"/>plants; the northern regions, colder than<lb break="yes"/>Europe, under the same parallel, furnish<lb break="yes"/>to this flora abundance of rhodonden-<lb break="no"/>drons, amentace&#x00E6;, and conifer&#x00E6;. The<lb break="yes"/>caryophylle&#x00E6;, the umbellifer&#x00E6;, and the<lb break="yes"/>crucifer&#x00E6;, are in general more rare in<lb break="yes"/>North America, than in the temperate<lb break="yes"/>zone of the old continent.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>These constant relations observed on<lb break="yes"/>the surface of the globe, in the plains<lb break="yes"/>from the equator to the pole, are again<lb break="yes" />traced in the midst of perpetual snows<lb break="yes"/>on the summits of mountains. We may<lb break="yes"/>admit, in general, that on the cordilleras<lb break="yes"/>of the torrid zone, the boreal forms be-<lb break="no"/>come more frequent. It is thus that we<lb break="yes"/>see prevail at Quito, on the summit of<lb break="yes"/>the Andes, the ericine&#x00E6;, the rhododen-<lb break="no"/>drons, and the gramineous plants. On<lb break="yes"/>the contrary, the labiat&#x00E6;, the rubiace&#x00E6;,<lb break="yes"/>the malvace&#x00E6;, and the euphorbiace&#x00E6;,<lb break="yes" />then become as rare as they are in<lb break="yes"/>Lapland. But this analogy is not sup-<lb break="no"/>ported in the ferns and the composite<lb break="yes" />plants. The latter abound on the<lb break="yes"/>Andes, whereas the former gradually<lb break="yes"/>disappear when they rise above 1800<lb break="yes" />fathoms in height. Thus the climate of<lb break="yes"/>the Andes resembles that of northern<lb break="yes"/>Europe only with respect to the mean<lb break="yes" />temperature of the year. The reparti-<lb break="no"/>tion of heat into the different seasons is<lb break="yes"/>entirely different, and powerfully influ-<lb break="no"/>
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">ences</fw>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="440" facs="#f0003"/> ences the phenomena of vegetation. In<lb break="yes" />general, the forms which prevail among<lb break="yes"/>the alpine plants, are, according to my<lb break="yes"/>researches, under the torrid zone, the<lb break="yes"/>gramine&#x00E6; (&#x00E6;gopogon, podos&#x00E6;mum,<lb break="yes"/>deyeuxia, avena); the composit&#x00E6; (cul-<lb break="no"/>citium, espeletia, aster, baccharis): and<lb break="yes"/>the caryophylle&#x00E6; (arenaria, stellaria.)<lb break="yes"/>Under the temperate zone, the com-<lb break="no"/>posit&#x00E6; (senecio, leontodon, aster); the<lb break="yes"/>caryophylle&#x00E6; (cerastium, cherleria, si-<lb break="no"/>lene); and the crucifer&#x00E6; (draba,<lb break="yes"/>lepidium.) Under the frozen zone, the<lb break="yes"/>caryophylle&#x00E6; (stellaria, alsine); the<lb break="yes"/>ericine&#x00E6; (andromeda), and the ranun-<lb break="no"/>enlace&#x00E6;. It has been long known, and<lb break="yes"/>it is one of the most interesting results<lb break="yes"/>from the geography of animals, that<lb break="yes"/>no quadruped, no terrestrial bird, and,<lb break="yes"/>as appears from the researches of M.<lb break="yes" />Latreille, almost no insect, is common<lb break="yes"/>to the equatorial regions of the two<lb break="yes"/>worlds. M. Cuvier is convinced, by<lb break="yes" />precise inquiries, that this rule applies<lb break="yes"/>even to reptiles. He has ascertained,<lb break="yes"/>that the true boa constrictor is peculiar<lb break="yes"/>to America; and that the boas of the old<lb break="yes"/>continent, were pytons. Among the<lb break="yes"/>plants, we must distinguish between the<lb break="yes"/>agam&#x00E6; and the cotyledone&#x00E6;; and by<lb break="yes"/>considering the latter between the mo-<lb break="no"/>nocotylodens and the dicotyledons.<lb break="yes"/>There remains no doubt that many of the<lb break="yes"/>mosses and lichens are to be found at<lb break="yes"/>once in equinoctial America and in Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope. But the case is not the same with<lb break="yes"/>the vascular agam&#x00E6; as with the agam&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>of a cellular texture. The ferns and the<lb break="yes"/>lycopodiace&#x00E6; do not follow the same<lb break="yes"/>laws with the mosses and the lichens.<cb/>The former, in particular, exhibit very<lb break="yes" />few species universally to be found; and<lb break="yes"/>the examples cited are frequently doubt-<lb break="no"/>ful. As to the phanerogamous plants<lb break="yes" />(with the exception of the rhizophora,<lb break="yes"/>the avicennia, and some other littoral<lb break="yes"/>plants), the law of Buffon seems to be<lb break="yes" />exact with respect to the species fur-<lb break="no"/>nished with two cotyledons. It is abso-<lb break="no"/>lutely false, although it has been often<lb break="yes" />affirmed, that the ridges of the cordilleras<lb break="yes"/>of Peru, the climate of which has some<lb break="yes"/>analogy with the climate of France or<lb break="yes"/>Sweden, produce similar plants. The<lb break="yes"/>oaks, the pines, the yews, the ranunculi,<lb break="yes"/>the rose-trees, the alchemilla, the<lb break="yes"/>valerians, the stellaria, the draba of the<lb break="yes" />Peruvian and Mexican Andes, have<lb break="yes"/>nearly the same physiognomy with the<lb break="yes"/>species of the same genera of North<lb break="yes"/>America, Siberia, or Europe. But all<lb break="yes"/>these alpine plants of the cordilleras,<lb break="yes"/>without excepting one among three or<lb break="yes" />four thousand which we have examined,<lb break="yes"/>differ specifically from the analogous<lb break="yes"/>species of the temperate zone of the old<lb break="yes"/>continent. In general, in that part of<lb break="yes"/>America situated between the tropics,<lb break="yes"/>the monocotyledontal plants alone, and<lb break="yes"/>among the latter almost solely the<lb break="yes"/>cyperace&#x00E6; and the gramine&#x00E6;, are com-<lb break="no"/>mon to the two worlds. These two<lb break="yes"/>families form an exception to the general<lb break="yes"/>law which we are here examining,&#x2014;a<lb break="yes"/>law which is so important for the history<lb break="yes"/>of the catastrophes of our planet, and<lb break="yes" />according to which, the organized beings<lb break="yes"/>of the equinoctial regions differ essen-<lb break="no"/>tially in the two continents.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 