<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="4" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>BARON HUMBOLDT<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">ON THE BAMBOOS OF AMERICA.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(From &#x201C;The New Monthly Magazine.&#x201D;</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Messrs Humboldt and Bonpland were so for-<lb break="no"/>tunate as to meet with two specimens of the<lb break="yes"/>bamboo tree in flower; the one on the bank of<lb break="yes"/>the river Cassaquiar, which is a branch of the<lb break="yes"/>Oronoko, and the other at the village of El<lb break="yes" />Muerto, in the province of Popayan. These<lb break="yes"/>reed-like trees, though they cover damp and<lb break="yes"/>swampy tracts of great extent, and attain the<lb break="yes"/>height of from 50 to 80 feet, are nevertheless<lb break="yes"/>very rarely seen in blossom in America. Vari-<lb break="no" />ous observant travellers who have visited the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">guadales</hi>&#x2014;as the swamps occupied by the bam-<lb break="no"/>boos are termed by the inhabitants&#x2014;never had<lb break="yes"/>the good fortune to obtain a sight of the flowers<lb break="yes"/>or fruit, either in Peru or New Granada. In<lb break="yes"/>the East Indies, on the other hand, the gigantic<lb break="yes"/>grasses blossom so abundantly, that the seeds of<lb break="yes"/>the bamboo mixed with honey are a common<lb break="yes"/>dish with the people of Mysore. According to<lb break="yes"/>a notion prevalent there, the plant does not bear<lb break="yes"/>fruit till it is fifteen years old, and soon after-<lb break="no"/>wards dies. There, too, a distinction is made<lb break="yes" />between the bamboo with a solid stem, which<lb break="yes"/>the natives call <hi rendition="#i">chitter,</hi> and which grows<lb break="yes"/>in a dry soil, and the bamboo with a hollow<lb break="yes"/>stem, termed <hi rendition="#i">doda,</hi> which grows more rapidly,<lb break="yes"/>and in moist situations.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The <hi rendition="#i">guadua</hi> bamboo was found by Messrs<lb break="yes" />Humboldt and Bonpland, on mountains to the<lb break="yes"/>height of 860 fathoms; and what is still more<lb break="yes"/>remarkable, these mountain trees, though grow-<lb break="no"/>ing upon a soil equally damp, contained more<lb break="yes"/>water than those of the level country. In more<lb break="yes"/>elevated regions the tree grows separately in the<lb break="yes"/>thickets; but in the plains, and to the height of<lb break="yes"/>400 fathoms, it forms extensive woods. The<lb break="yes" />bamboo belongs to the plants that grow in so-<lb break="no"/>ciety.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The American bamboos render the same ser-<lb break="no"/>vices in the New World as those of the East In-<lb break="no"/>dies in the Old. Whole houses are built of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">bambus guadia.</hi> The oldest and thickest trunks<lb break="yes"/>are employed for the walls; the roof is formed<lb break="yes" />with the smaller, and these are covered with the<lb break="yes"/>young branches that have leaves. The doors<lb break="yes"/>and household furniture also are made of bamboo.<lb break="yes"/>The advantages which cause the Americans to<lb break="yes"/>prefer the use of bamboo to that of the hard<lb break="yes"/>wood of the lofty trees which every where grow<lb break="yes" />in the vicinity of their habitations, consist in the<lb break="yes"/>facility with which it may be felled and wrought,<lb break="yes"/>in its durability, and the coolness enjoyed in<lb break="yes"/>houses constructed with it, owing to the free<lb break="yes"/>current of air which they afford.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The water contained in the American bamboo<lb break="yes"/>has a somewhat saline but not disagreeable taste.<lb break="yes"/>The inhabitants assert, that it acts powerfully on<lb break="yes"/>the urinary passages. Of the sweet bamboo-<lb break="no"/>honey, M. Von Humboldt could discover no<lb break="yes"/>traces in the New World; but in the kingdom of<lb break="yes"/>Quito he met with the <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir,</hi> differing but<lb break="yes"/>little from that of the East Indies. A piece of<lb break="yes"/>it, given by him to M. Vauquelin, was found by<lb break="yes"/>that chemist to be composed of 70-100ths of si-<lb break="no"/>liceous earth, and 30-100ths of potash, lime,<lb break="yes"/>and water. The American <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir</hi> is called<lb break="yes"/>by the Spaniards bamboo-fat. &#x201C;I cannot con-<lb break="no"/>ceive,&#x201D; says the traveller, &#x201C;how writers, who<lb break="yes" />have made the sugar of the ancients a subject<lb break="yes"/>of their inquiry, can compare the <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>which is white and brittle like starch, with ho-<lb break="no" />ney. For my own part, I could not perceive<lb break="yes"/>any sweet taste in the <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir</hi> of Quito, though<lb break="yes"/>it was yet moist and viscid; <choice><sic>aad</sic><corr type="editorial">and</corr></choice> I have some<lb break="yes"/>doubts whether the tree-like reeds of America<lb break="yes"/>contain a sweet juice at all. The <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir,</hi> in-<lb break="no"/>deed, before it becomes by desiccation as hard<lb break="yes"/>as stone, is clammy, white, and milky; when it<lb break="yes"/>has been kept five months, it emits an extreme-<lb break="no"/>ly fetid animal odour. The same was observed<lb break="yes"/>by Russel respecting the salt of the Asiatic bam-<lb break="no"/>boo, and Garcias ab Orto, who long resided at<lb break="yes"/>Goa as physician to the Viceroy, has alone ascri-<lb break="no"/>bed a sweet taste to the juice of the bamboo. It<lb break="yes"/>appears, however, that the ancients mistook the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir</hi> for real sugar; partly because both are<lb break="yes"/>the produce of reed-like plants, and partly be-<lb break="no" />cause the Sanscrit word <hi rendition="#i">scharkara,</hi> which at<lb break="yes"/>the present day is used like the Persian <hi rendition="#i" >schakar</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and the Hindostanee <hi rendition="#i">schukar</hi> to denote our su-<lb break="no"/>gar, does not properly imply something sweet,<lb break="yes"/>but something stony or sandy, and even the uri-<lb break="no" />nary calculus. It is therefore probable that the<lb break="yes"/>word <hi rendition="#i">scharkara</hi> was at first used for the <hi rendition="#i" >tabaschir</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>alone, and in the sequel transferred to our sugar<lb break="yes"/>from the smaller sugar-cane on account of its si-<lb break="no" />milar figure. The word <hi rendition="#i">bamboo</hi> is derived from<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">mambu,</hi> and from <hi rendition="#i">canda</hi> comes our term <hi rendition="#i">sugar-<lb break="no"/>candy</hi>, as does <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir</hi> from the Persian word<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">schir,</hi> which signifies milk.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Under the name of <hi rendition="#i">saccharum,</hi> Pliny cer-<lb break="no" />tainly described the <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir</hi> of the bamboo as<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;a honey collected from the stems of reeds,<lb break="yes" />which is white like gum, breaks between the<lb break="yes"/>teeth, is of the size of a nut, and is applicable<lb break="yes"/>to medicinal purposes alone.&#x2019; The ancients had,<lb break="yes"/>nevertheless, some knowledge of our sugar,<lb break="yes"/>which was said to be produced in India without<lb break="yes" />bees. Several writers of antiquity believed that<lb break="yes"/>a sweet honey-like juice was expressed from the<lb break="yes"/>roots of lofty reeds, thus confounding the root<lb break="yes"/>with the stem, and the comparatively low sugar-<lb break="no"/>cane with the tall bamboo tree. Some of them<lb break="yes"/>even had a notion that the genuine cane-sugar<lb break="yes" />was a dew which settled upon the leaves of those<lb break="yes"/>plants. The sugar-cane indeed grows wild and<lb break="yes"/>in a natural state near Almansura, in the East<lb break="yes"/>Indies, on the banks of Euphrates, and at Siraf;<lb break="yes"/>yet I presume that in the regions of Asia, visited<lb break="yes"/>by the Greeks, the juice of the cane was express-<lb break="no" />ed only for the purpose of an immediate beve-<lb break="no"/>rage, and that the ancients had not consequent-<lb break="no"/>ly any knowledge of solid sugar, so that where-<lb break="no"/>ever the term is employed by them it signifies<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir</hi> of the bamboo.
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;It is almost superfluous to observe, that be-<lb break="no"/>fore the Spaniards opened the way to America,<lb break="yes"/>the inhabitants of that continent and the adja-<lb break="no"/>cent islands were strangers to the sugar-cane, as<lb break="yes"/>well as to our different kinds of corn and rice.<lb break="yes" />The Spanish writers on America, indeed, give<lb break="yes"/>the name of <hi rendition="#i">little rice</hi> to the <hi rendition="#i">chenopodium quino,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>which is common in Bogota and Quito, as the<lb break="yes" />Anglo-Americans term a species of <hi rendition="#i">zizania,</hi> wild<lb break="yes"/>rice of Canada. Maize or Turkey corn, like<lb break="yes" />other plants of ancient cultivation, does not<lb break="yes"/>grow wild in any part of the new Continent. It<lb break="yes"/>were to be wished that some future traveller<lb break="yes"/>would furnish more particular information re-<lb break="no"/>specting the <hi rendition="#i">magu</hi>-corn and <hi rendition="#i">tuca</hi>-barley, of which<lb break="yes"/>Molini makes very brief mention in his history<lb break="yes"/>of Chili, and of which the Araucanians former-<lb break="no"/>ly made their Covque bread. From maize and<lb break="yes"/>the agave the Americans prepared the honey<lb break="yes"/>not produced by bees, which, as Hernando Cor-<lb break="no"/>tez informs us, was carried for sale to their mar-<lb break="no"/>kets.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 