<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Characteristic sketches of american vegetables</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:52</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.41</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1817-Pflanzenbilder_die_Orchiden-2-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1817-Pflanzenbilder_die_Orchiden-1-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1817-Pflanzenbilder_die_Orchiden-2-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1817-Pflanzenbilder_die_Orchiden-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1817-Pflanzenbilder_die_Orchiden-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1817-Pflanzenbilder_die_Orchiden-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1817-Pflanzenbilder_die_Orchiden-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Characteristic sketches of american vegetables</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1817</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in:&lt;i&gt; The New Monthly Magazine and Universal Register&lt;/i&gt; 7:41 (1. Juni 1817), S. 397–398, 8:43 (1. August 1817), S. 20–21, 8:44 (1. September 1817), S. 109–110.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="397" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <opener><salute>
                <hi rendition="#et">
                    <hi rendition="#k">mr. editor,</hi>
                </hi>
            </salute></opener>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>THE following characteristic sketches<lb break="yes"/>of remarkable families of the vegetable<lb break="yes"/>kingdom, extracted from the magnificent<lb break="yes"/>botanical work of Messrs. <hi rendition="#g">
                    <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi>
                </hi>
                <lb break="yes"/>and <hi rendition="#g">
                    <hi rendition="#k">Bonpland,</hi>
                </hi>
                <note place="foot" n="*">
                    <hi rendition="#i">Nova Genera et Species Plantarum<lb break="yes"/>quas in Peregrinatione ad Plagam œquinoc-<lb break="no"/>tialem Orbis novi colligerunt.</hi> fol.</note> completed last year at<lb break="yes"/>Paris, will I trust be acceptable to many<lb break="yes"/>more of your readers than those who<lb break="yes"/>have made that department of nature<lb break="yes"/>the object of their particular study.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <div n="2">
                    <head>I. <hi rendition="#i">The Palms.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The family of the <hi rendition="#i">Palms</hi> thrives best<lb break="yes"/>between the tropics, in the plains, and<lb break="yes"/>to the height of 500 fathoms, in places<lb break="yes"/>where the mean temperature in summer<lb break="yes"/>is from 19° to 28° of the centigrade<lb break="yes"/>thermometer, and—excepting the island<lb break="yes"/>of Cuba, to which the north wind from<lb break="yes"/>Canada brings a colder air—where the<lb break="yes"/>cold in winter is not below 15°. Only<lb break="yes"/>very few of their mountain varieties<lb break="yes"/>grow in the equinoctial region on the<lb break="yes"/>acclivities of the Andes up to the height<lb break="yes"/>of 1300 fathoms and more, as the <hi rendition="#i">Oreo-<lb break="no"/>doxa frigida</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i">Ceroxylon andicola.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>Beyond the tropics the <hi rendition="#i">Phœnix dactyli-<lb break="no"/>fera,</hi> the <hi rendition="#i">Chamœrops humilis</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Palmet-<lb break="no"/>ta,</hi> together with <hi rendition="#i">Areca Novæ Zeelandiæ,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>are found in tracts where the average<lb break="yes"/>warmth does not exceed 15° or 16°, and<lb break="yes"/>where the ground is sometimes covered<lb break="yes"/>for several days with snow.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>In the time of Linnæus no more than<lb break="yes"/>fifteen varieties of the palm were known:<lb break="yes"/>to these Ruiz and Pavon have added<lb break="yes"/>eight; Willdenow and Bredemeyer, six;<lb break="yes"/>and Humboldt and Bonpland twenty<lb break="yes"/>more. From a list collected by Kunth,<lb break="yes"/>from the later botanists it appears that<lb break="yes"/>at least 87 kinds of palms from America<lb break="yes"/>alone were known at that time; and<lb break="yes"/>these added to the 50 species of the old<lb break="yes"/>continent discovered up to April, 1816,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> make the total family amount to 137 va-<lb break="no"/>rieties. In Willdenow’s <hi rendition="#i">System of Bo-<lb break="no"/>tany,</hi> 70 palms are enumerated; and<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt and Bonpland saw, during<lb break="yes"/>their travels, more than 45. We may,<lb break="yes"/>however, venture to assume, that in the<lb break="yes"/>whole torrid zone the number of the va-<lb break="no"/>rieties of the palm must be much more<lb break="yes"/>extensive, if we consider that, on the<lb break="yes"/>one hand, the greatest part of Africa,<lb break="yes"/>Asia, and New Holland, is yet unex-<lb break="no"/>plored; and that, on the other, accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to authentic observations which<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt and Bonpland themselves<lb break="yes"/>had occasion to make during their five<lb break="yes"/>years’ peregrinations, the plants of this<lb break="yes"/>family are confined within such narrow<lb break="yes"/>limits that almost every fifty leagues new<lb break="yes"/>species of them are met with.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>In regard to port and form the palms<lb break="yes"/>present the greatest diversity. Some<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">(Kunthea montana, Aiphanes praga,<lb break="yes"/>Oreodoxa frigida)</hi> have only a weak,<lb break="yes"/>reed-like stem; while that of others<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">(Jubæa spectabilis, Cocos butyracea)</hi> mea-<lb break="no"/>sures from three to five feet in diameter.<lb break="yes"/>Some <hi rendition="#i">(Mauritia flexuosa, Chamœrops<lb break="yes"/>humilis)</hi> grow sociably together; while<lb break="yes"/>others <hi rendition="#i">(Oreodoxa regia, Martinezia ca-<lb break="no"/>ryotæfolia)</hi> occur but singly. This <hi rendition="#i">(Ac-<lb break="no"/>talea amygdalina)</hi> has a very low trunk;<lb break="yes"/>that <hi rendition="#i">(Ceroxylon andicola)</hi> attains the<lb break="yes"/>height of 160 or 180 feet. These <hi rendition="#i">(Co-<lb break="no"/>rypha tectorum, Alfonsia oleifera)</hi> inha-<lb break="no"/>bit the plains only of the tropical re-<lb break="no"/>gions, or the mountain-slopes to the ele-<lb break="no"/>vation of 300 fathoms, while others—<lb break="yes"/>which the travellers believe to have been<lb break="yes"/>wholly unknown previously to their<lb break="yes"/>visit to the Andes—approach the limits<lb break="yes"/>of everlasting snow. To the alpine and<lb break="yes"/>sub-alpine vegetables belong the follow-<lb break="no"/>ing species:</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Kunthia montana</hi> grows at the eleva-<lb break="no"/>tion of from 250 to 800 and even 1000<lb break="yes"/>fathoms, in the temperate region of the<lb break="yes"/>heart-leafed cinchona, on the declivity<lb break="yes"/>of the Bater, in the neighbourhood of the<lb break="yes"/>valley of Hato Viejo and the village of<lb break="yes"/>St. Paul, whence the plant bears like-<lb break="no"/>wise the name of <hi rendition="#i">Canna de San Pablo,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>or, <hi rendition="#i">de la Vibora;</hi> in the woods of the<lb break="yes"/>Alps of Pastoens between Chilanquer<lb break="yes"/>and Barbacoas, as also on the mountains<lb break="yes"/>of the province of Mocoa, which have a<lb break="yes"/>moderate temperature.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Oreodoxa frigida,</hi> at the elevation of<lb break="yes"/>from 1000 to 1400 fathoms, on the Alps<lb break="yes"/>of Quito, in company with the walnut-<lb break="no"/>tree and <hi rendition="#i">Podokarpos.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Ceroxylon andicola,</hi> at 920 to 1500<lb break="yes"/>fathoms, on the Alps of Tolimen and<lb break="yes"/>Mount St. John, in company with the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="398" facs="#f0002"/>
                        <cb/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Oreodoxa frigida</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i">Quercus grana-<lb break="no"/>tensis:</hi> it can endure a nocturnal cold of<lb break="yes"/>at farthest 6° to 8°. This beautiful<lb break="yes"/>palm, remarkable for having its whole<lb break="yes"/>stem overgrown with foliage, is most fre-<lb break="no"/>quently met with on the eastern declivity<lb break="yes"/>of the Andes of Quito, between Nevados<lb break="yes"/>de San Juan and Tolima, in the vicinity<lb break="yes"/>of Passo del Machin, Alto de las Sepul-<lb break="no"/>turas and Los Galiegos. It is found also<lb break="yes"/>of very large size near El Inciencial, at<lb break="yes"/>an elevation of 1240 fathoms. In the<lb break="yes"/>environs of Los Volcanitos and La Garita<lb break="yes"/>del Paramo, the <hi rendition="#i">Ceroxylon anaicola</hi> was<lb break="yes"/>not found higher than 1500 fathoms; it<lb break="yes"/>grows in company with the <hi rendition="#i">Escalloniæ</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>and <hi rendition="#i">Thibaudiæ.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Joseph de Caldas and George Thad-<lb break="no"/>dæus Lozano, two celebrated botanists of<lb break="yes"/>New Grenada, have found three other<lb break="yes"/>alpine palms on the mountains of Guana<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">(Paramo de Guanacas)</hi> not far from the<lb break="yes"/>region of everlasting snow.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>For a long time botanists knew of no<lb break="yes"/>other palms than those with six pistils.<lb break="yes"/>More recently we have been made ac-<lb break="no"/>quainted with six varieties having many<lb break="yes"/>pistils; three of which <hi rendition="#i">(Caryota, Mani-<lb break="no"/>curia,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Latania,)</hi> belong to the old<lb break="yes"/>world; and the other three, described by<lb break="yes"/>Ruiz, Pavon, and Humboldt <hi rendition="#i">(Ceroxylon,<lb break="yes"/>Jubæa,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Attalæa)</hi> to the Andes. Those<lb break="yes"/>species the pith of which furnishes a kind of<lb break="yes"/>sago-flour that forius an excellent article<lb break="yes"/>of food for the inhabitants of the new<lb break="yes"/>world, deserve to be particularly recom-<lb break="no"/>mended to the notice of future travellers<lb break="yes"/>in America.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It would lead me too far were I to at-<lb break="no"/>tempt to enumerate the various uses to<lb break="yes"/>which the palm-trees are applied. All<lb break="yes"/>your readers know that they furnish arti-<lb break="no"/>cles of the most dissimilar nature—wine,<lb break="yes"/>oil, wax, flour, sugar, and salt.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>In the tracts to the north of the line,<lb break="yes"/>between the mountains of Caraccas and<lb break="yes"/>the River of Amazons, traversed by<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt and Bonpland, they found the<lb break="yes"/>palms in general in blossom in January<lb break="yes"/>and February, but some of them flower<lb break="yes"/>at other seasons of the year.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>If the family of the palms is distin-<lb break="no"/>guished by beauty of form and its<lb break="yes"/>large size from almost all the other fami-<lb break="no"/>lies of vegetables, so likewise does it sur-<lb break="no"/>pass them in fecundity and abundance of<lb break="yes"/>fruit; and the powerful action of the sap<lb break="yes"/>is developed not only in thick umbra-<lb break="no"/>geous foliage, but also in an innumerable<lb break="yes"/>multitude of flowers and fruit. Not only<lb break="yes"/>the fields planted with palm-trees, but<lb break="yes"/>even the soil that has never been culti-<lb break="no"/>vated by man is frequently covered to<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> the depth of three inches with the fruit<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i">Alfonsia, Cocos butyracea, Seje,<lb break="yes"/>Pihiguao,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Mauritia.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Every flower capsule of the date-tree<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">(Phœnix dactylifera)</hi> contains, accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to Kämpfer <hi rendition="#i">(Amœn. exot.</hi> p. 699),<lb break="yes"/>above 12,000 male flowers. Humboldt<lb break="yes"/>and Bonpland have found a much greater<lb break="yes"/>number upon the <hi rendition="#i">Alfonsia amygdalina.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>In one single catkin-shaped bunch of<lb break="yes"/>flowers, of which each capsule contains<lb break="yes"/>from 110 to 120, they counted 1800<lb break="yes"/>male flowers; so that the total number<lb break="yes"/>in each capsule may be computed at<lb break="yes"/>207,000 flowers. According to a similar<lb break="yes"/>calculation every branch of the <hi rendition="#i">Seje,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>which furnishes an excellent aliment on<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the Oroonoko, produces<lb break="yes"/>8000 fruits, many of which indeed drop<lb break="yes"/>off before maturity. In the palm-grounds<lb break="yes"/>planted with the <hi rendition="#i">l’ihiguao</hi> each tree<lb break="yes"/>yields annually upon an average 400<lb break="yes"/>fruits of the shape of apples; and the<lb break="yes"/>Franciscans on the Oroonoko and Guai-<lb break="no"/>nia know from experience that whenever<lb break="yes"/>there is an uncommonly abundant crop<lb break="yes"/>of palm fruit the Indians grow remark-<lb break="no"/>ably fat.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rendition="#et">
                                <hi rendition="#k">Selector.</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#c">
                            <hi rendition="#i">(To be continued.)</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </closer>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <pb n="20" facs="#f0003" />
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">characteristic sketches of american<lb break="yes"/>vegetables.</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">By</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">alexander von humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">(Continued from</hi> Vol. VII. p. 398.)</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>II.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">The Orchides.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>THE <hi rendition="#i">monocotyledons</hi>, or plants that<lb break="yes"/>grow with one seed-lobe only, present the<lb break="yes"/>greatest diversity as well in regard to the<lb break="yes"/>beauty of their forms as to the variety of<lb break="yes"/>their colours. In the family of the Orchides,<lb break="yes"/>the flower-sheath, which, in the grasses, the<lb break="yes"/>cyperus-grasses, the families of the junce&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>and the palms, is pale, small, and nowise<lb break="yes"/>remarkable, is adorned with the most di-<lb break="no"/>versified colours, so as to surpass even<lb break="yes"/>the superb flowers of the amaryllis, the<lb break="yes"/>iris, and the banana genus. The or-<lb break="no"/>chides, in fact, are the chief ornament of<lb break="yes"/>the vegetable kingdom in the equinoctial<lb break="yes"/>regions; and if, according to the testi-<lb break="no"/>mony of Brown, fewer plants of that<lb break="yes"/>family occur between the tropics in New<lb break="yes"/>Holland (where so many unusual and<lb break="yes"/>extraordinary things are met with), than<lb break="yes"/>between the 33d and 35th degree of lati-<lb break="no"/>tude, this circumstance must be consi-<lb break="no"/>dered as an exception: but their pre-<lb break="no"/>ference of a damp and mild atmosphere<lb break="yes"/>explains the reason why the epidendron-<lb break="no"/>orchides extend in the southern hemi-<lb break="no"/>sphere so far towards the south pole,<lb break="yes"/>since they there find in winter a mode-<lb break="no"/>rate temperature similar to that of the<lb break="yes"/>vallies among the mountains of the tro-<lb break="no"/>pical regions.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It is impossible to calculate&#x2014;as the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> celebrated authors of the Flora of Peru<lb break="yes"/>also attest&#x2014;how abundant a harvest of<lb break="yes"/>orchides the mild climate of the deep<lb break="yes"/>and shady vallies in the range of the<lb break="yes"/>Andes still reserve for future travellers;<lb break="yes"/>for it may be confidently asserted, that<lb break="yes"/>we are not acquainted with more than<lb break="yes"/>the twentieth part of them. In all Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope we find but from 70 to 80 species<lb break="yes"/>of orchis; whereas in the equinoctial re-<lb break="no"/>gions of America, whose mountainous<lb break="yes"/>parts are yet so little known, 244 species<lb break="yes"/>have already been observed by botanists,<lb break="yes"/>and 61 of these are new ones discovered<lb break="yes"/>by Humboldt and Bonpland. The known<lb break="yes"/>orchides of the Old and New World do<lb break="yes"/>not amount to 700: Willdenow has enu-<lb break="no"/>merated only 394, of which 152 are Ame-<lb break="no"/>rican.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Though the plants of the orchis family<lb break="yes"/>are found scattered in both worlds from<lb break="yes"/>the sea-coast to the height of 1800 or<lb break="yes"/>1900 fathoms; still we are justified in<lb break="yes"/>asserting, that, from the multitude of<lb break="yes"/>their varieties, from the profusion of their<lb break="yes"/>foliage and the brilliancy and fragrance<lb break="yes"/>of their flowers, the vallies of the Andes<lb break="yes"/>of Mexico, New Grenada, Quito and<lb break="yes"/>Peru may be properly called their native<lb break="yes"/>country, where they thrive best in the<lb break="yes"/>moist shade, in a mild air, at an eleva-<lb break="no"/>tion of between 800 and 1100 fathoms,<lb break="yes"/>and in a mean temperature of 17° to 19°.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The species of orchis with spur-shaped<lb break="yes"/>flowers are very rare in the torrid zone,<lb break="yes"/>and with few exceptions their forms in<lb break="yes"/>the temperate and frigid zones are es-<lb break="no"/>sentially different, so that in the northern<lb break="yes"/>hemisphere we find the varieties of the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Orchis Habenaria, Cypripedium, Ophrys,<lb break="yes"/>Serapius, Epipactes, &amp;c.</hi>; but in the<lb break="yes"/>southern those of the <hi rendition="#i">Satyrium, Pteripo-<lb break="no"/>dium, Disperis, Corycium, Stilidium,<lb break="yes"/>Disa, Pterostylis, Acianthus, &amp;c.</hi> The<lb break="yes"/>orchides of the equinoctial regions be-<lb break="no"/>long chiefly to the epidendron genus.<lb break="yes"/>They are distinguished from the orchides<lb break="yes"/>of the temperate and frigid zones by a<lb break="yes"/>different appearance, and more especially<lb break="yes"/>by this circumstance, that the former<lb break="yes"/>almost always grow in society and upon<lb break="yes"/>trees, while the latter spring up singly<lb break="yes"/>without support. Very few species,<lb break="yes"/>which, if I may so express myself, dis-<lb break="no"/>play the physiognomy of the north, as<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">Ophrys, Habenaria, Altensteinia</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>occur between the tropics, and not<lb break="yes"/>merely on the ridges of the loftiest<lb break="yes"/>mountains, but sometimes also in the<lb break="yes"/>plains. The temperate zone of the two<lb break="yes"/>great continents possesses no more than<lb break="yes"/>four species in common: these are:<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Satyrium viride, Orchis hyperborea</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="21" facs="#f0004" />
                        <cb/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Neottia repens, Neottia tortilis.</hi> It is<lb break="yes"/>remarkable that the <hi rendition="#i">Dendrobium poly-<lb break="no"/>stachion</hi>, which grows on the mountains<lb break="yes"/>of Jamaica and in the woods of Guiana,<lb break="yes"/>has been found also in the island of St.<lb break="yes"/>Maurice. (Schwartz, <hi rendition="#i">Flor. Ind. occ.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>T. 3. p. 1433). Whether it be actually<lb break="yes"/>the same species seems however to be<lb break="yes"/>doubtful. Most of the orchides of the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone contain in their roots a white<lb break="yes"/>floury substance, which not unfre-<lb break="no"/>quently possesses alimentary properties;<lb break="yes"/>some, as the <hi rendition="#i">Pleurothallis sagittifera</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>contain also in their bulbs a viscid juice<lb break="yes"/>which may be employed as glue.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The monocotyledons in general con-<lb break="no"/>tain a large proportion of starch (<hi rendition="#i">amylum</hi>)<lb break="yes"/>partly in the fruit (the grasses, the un-<lb break="no"/>ripe fruit of the <hi rendition="#i">Musa</hi>, the <hi rendition="#i">Palma Pihi-<lb break="no"/>guao</hi>) partly in the stem (<hi rendition="#i">Sagus Mauri-<lb break="no"/>tius</hi>) partly in the roots (the arums, the<lb break="yes"/>orchides, the families of the Lilies and<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Dioscore&#x0153;, Maranta Indica</hi>). The juice<lb break="yes"/>of the Grasses and of the Agaves, the<lb break="yes"/>Areng palm, and the ripe fruit of the<lb break="yes"/>Pisang on the other hand contain sugar.<lb break="yes"/>That starch and sugar should occur at<lb break="yes"/>once in the same plant, and often in the<lb break="yes"/>same parts of it, will appear the less ex-<lb break="no"/>traordinary, when we consider, that mo-<lb break="no"/>dern chemists have found in both nearly<lb break="yes"/>the same proportions of oxygen, hydro-<lb break="no"/>gen and carbon, and that sweet beer is<lb break="yes"/>produced by sprouted barley. The an-<lb break="no"/>cients themselves seem to have had some<lb break="yes"/>notion of the conversion of the starch<lb break="yes"/>into sugar. Among others, Prosper Al-<lb break="no"/>pinus relates, that the Pisang (<hi rendition="#i">Musa pa-<lb break="no"/>radisiaca</hi>) sprung from the engrafting of<lb break="yes"/>the sugar-cane upon the Colocasia: and<lb break="yes"/>in like manner Abd Allatif assures us<lb break="yes"/>that when a date-stone germinates in a<lb break="yes"/>Colocasia root the produce is a pisang-<lb break="no"/>plant. The glutinous juice secreted by<lb break="yes"/>nature in the bulbous roots of the or-<lb break="no"/>chides differs from the genuine viscid<lb break="yes"/>matter of corn, as does the latter from<lb break="yes"/>that made of bird-lime berries, and the<lb break="yes"/>bark of the holly. An aroma which ex-<lb break="no"/>cites the nerves is found in the flower of<lb break="yes"/>the lily, asphodel and narcissus, in the<lb break="yes"/>bulb of the crocus, in the fruit of the<lb break="yes"/>vanilla and cardamom, in the roots of<lb break="yes"/>the varieties of <hi rendition="#i">Canna</hi>, and in the whole<lb break="yes"/>family of the <hi rendition="#i">Peperomi&#x0153;.</hi> Acids, astrin-<lb break="no"/>gent matter, resins, camphor, poisons,<lb break="yes"/>tannin, and vegetable milk occur but<lb break="yes"/>very rarely among the monocotyledons.<lb break="yes"/>The <hi rendition="#i">Colchica</hi>, and some species of <hi rendition="#i">ama-<lb break="no"/>ryllis</hi> alone furnish a poison, the only<lb break="yes"/>antidote to which is the juice of the palm<lb break="yes"/>that Humboldt calls <hi rendition="#i">Kunthia.</hi> The<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Smilax</hi>, and varieties of <hi rendition="#i">Scilla</hi> contain<lb break="yes"/>astringent matter; and resin is found in<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">Aloe.</hi> An astringent principle, which<lb break="yes"/>has not yet been duly examined, is con-<lb break="no"/>tained in the <hi rendition="#i">Drac&#x0153;na Draco</hi> and in the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Agave</hi>, the juice of which is used as a<lb break="yes"/>caustic in wounds. It is inconceivable<lb break="yes"/>how the celebrated Fourcroy could as-<lb break="no"/>sert that the monocotyledons, without<lb break="yes"/>exception, are destitute of oil, since the<lb break="yes"/>coco is planted in the tropical regions<lb break="yes"/>for the same purpose as our olive. De-<lb break="no"/>candolle <hi rendition="#i">(Essai sur les Proprietés medi-<lb break="no"/>cales des Plantes)</hi> has already made the<lb break="yes"/>ingenious remark, that the monocotyle-<lb break="no"/>dons, because their returning sap vessels<lb break="yes"/>are distributed through the whole stem<lb break="yes"/>and not collected together into a mass of<lb break="yes"/>bark, want nearly all that which, as the<lb break="yes"/>proper cortical substance, is found in the<lb break="yes"/>plants that germinate with two-seed<lb break="yes"/>lobes (dicotyledons), as Knight&#x2019;s experi-<lb break="no"/>ments (<hi rendition="#i">Phil. Trans.</hi> 1801, p. 337) une-<lb break="no"/>quivocally demonstrate.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="109" facs="#f0005" />
                    <cb/>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">characteristic sketches of american<lb break="yes"/>vegetables.<lb break="yes"/>by alexander von humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">Concluded from p.</hi> 21.)</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>III.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">The Grasses.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>MESSRS. HUMBOLDT and Bon-<lb break="no"/>pland were so fortunate as to meet with<lb break="yes"/>two specimens of the <hi rendition="#i">Bamboo tree</hi> in<lb break="yes"/>flower; the one on the bank of the river<lb break="yes"/>Cassaquiar, which is a branch of the Oro-<lb break="no"/>noko, and the other at the village of El<lb break="yes"/>Muerto, in the province of Popayan.<lb break="yes"/>These reed-like trees, though they cover<lb break="yes"/>damp and swampy tracts of great ex-<lb break="no"/>tent, and attain the height of from 50 to<lb break="yes"/>80 feet, are nevertheless very rarely seen<lb break="yes"/>in blossom in America. Various obser-<lb break="no"/>vant travellers who have visited the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">guadales</hi>&#x2014;as the swamps occupied by<lb break="yes"/>bamboos are termed by the inhabitants&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>never had the good fortune to obtain a<lb break="yes"/>sight of the flowers or fruit either in<lb break="yes"/>Peru or New Granada. In the East<lb break="yes"/>Indies, on the other hand, the gigantic<lb break="yes"/>grasses blossom so abundantly, that the<lb break="yes"/>seeds of the bamboo mixed with honey<lb break="yes"/>are a common dish with the people of<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> Mysore. According to a notion preva-<lb break="no"/>lent there, the plant does not bear fruit<lb break="yes"/>till it is fifteen years old, and soon after-<lb break="no"/>wards dies. There too a distinction is<lb break="yes"/>made between the bamboo with a solid<lb break="yes"/>stem, which the natives call <hi rendition="#i">chitter</hi>, and<lb break="yes"/>which grows in a dry soil, and the bam-<lb break="no"/>boo with a hollow stem, termed <hi rendition="#i">doda</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>which grows more rapidly, and in moist<lb break="yes"/>situations.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The <hi rendition="#i">guadua</hi> bamboo was found by<lb break="yes"/>Messrs. Humboldt and Bonpland on<lb break="yes"/>mountains to the height of 860 fathoms;<lb break="yes"/>and what is still more remarkable, these<lb break="yes"/>mountain trees, though growing upon a<lb break="yes"/>soil equally damp, contained more<lb break="yes"/>water than those of the level country. In<lb break="yes"/>more elevated regions the tree grows se-<lb break="no"/>parately in the thickets; but in the<lb break="yes"/>plains, and to the height of 400 fathoms,<lb break="yes"/>it forms extensive woods. The bamboo<lb break="yes"/>belongs to the plants that grow in society.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The American bamboos render the<lb break="yes"/>same services in the New World as those<lb break="yes"/>of the East Indies in the old. Whole<lb break="yes"/>houses are built of the <hi rendition="#i">Bambus guadia.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>The oldest and thickest trunks are em-<lb break="no"/>ployed for the walls; the roof is formed<lb break="yes"/>with the smaller, and these are covered<lb break="yes"/>with the young branches that have<lb break="yes"/>leaves. The doors and household fur-<lb break="no"/>niture also are made of bamboo. The<lb break="yes"/>advantages which cause the Americans<lb break="yes"/>to prefer the use of bamboo to that of<lb break="yes"/>the hard wood of the lofty trees which<lb break="yes"/>every where grow in the vicinity of their<lb break="yes"/>habitations, consist in the facility with<lb break="yes"/>which it may be felled and wrought, in<lb break="yes"/>its durability and the coolness enjoyed<lb break="yes"/>in houses constructed with it, owing to<lb break="yes"/>the free current of air which they afford.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The water contained in the American<lb break="yes"/>bamboo has a somewhat saline but not<lb break="yes"/>disagreeable taste. The inhabitants as-<lb break="no"/>sert that it acts powerfully on the urinary<lb break="yes"/>passages. Of the sweet bamboo-honey<lb break="yes"/>M. von Humboldt could discover no<lb break="yes"/>traces in the New World; but in the<lb break="yes"/>kingdom of Quito he met with the <hi rendition="#i">ta-<lb break="no"/>baschir</hi>, differing but little from that of<lb break="yes"/>the East Indies. A piece of it, given by<lb break="yes"/>him to M. Vauquelin, was found by that<lb break="yes"/>chemist to be composed of <formula notation="TeX">\frac{70}{100}</formula> of siliceous<lb break="yes"/>earth, and <formula notation="TeX">\frac{30}{100}</formula> of potash, lime and water.<lb break="yes"/>The American <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir</hi> is called by the<lb break="yes"/>Spaniards bamboo-fat. &#x201C;I cannot con-<lb break="no"/>ceive,&#x201D; says the traveller, &#x201C;how writers<lb break="yes"/>who have made the sugar of the ancients<lb break="yes"/>a subject of their enquiry, can compare<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir</hi>, which is white and brittle<lb break="yes"/>like starch, with honey. For my own<lb break="yes"/>part, I could not perceive any sweet taste<lb break="yes"/>in the <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir</hi> of Quito, though it was<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="sig" place="bottom">
                            <hi rendition="#k">New Montmly Mag.&#x2014;No. 44. Vol.</hi> VIII. Q</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="110" facs="#f0006" />
                        <cb/> yet moist and viscid: and I have some<lb break="yes"/>doubts whether the tree-like reeds of<lb break="yes"/>America contain a sweet juice at all.<lb break="yes"/>The <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir</hi>, indeed, before it becomes<lb break="yes"/>by desiccation as hard as stone, is<lb break="yes"/>clammy, white, and milky: when it has<lb break="yes"/>been kept five months it emits an ex-<lb break="no"/>tremely fetid animal odour. The same<lb break="yes"/>was observed by Russel respecting the<lb break="yes"/>salt of the Asiatic bamboo, and Garcias<lb break="yes"/>ab Orto, who long resided at Goa as<lb break="yes"/>physician to the viceroy, has alone as-<lb break="no"/>cribed a sweet taste to the juice of the<lb break="yes"/>bamboo. It appears, however, that the<lb break="yes"/>ancients mistook the <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir</hi> for real<lb break="yes"/>sugar; partly because both are the pro-<lb break="no"/>duce of reed-like plants, and partly be-<lb break="no"/>cause the Sanscrit word <hi rendition="#i">scharkara</hi>, which<lb break="yes"/>at the present day is used like the Per-<lb break="no"/>sian <hi rendition="#i">schakar</hi>, and the Hindustanee<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">schukar</hi> to denote our sugar, does not<lb break="yes"/>properly imply something sweet, but<lb break="yes"/>something stony or sandy, and even the<lb break="yes"/>urinary calculus. It is therefore proba-<lb break="no"/>ble that the word <hi rendition="#i">scharkara</hi> was at first<lb break="yes"/>used for the <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir</hi> alone, and in the<lb break="yes"/>sequel transferred to our sugar from the<lb break="yes"/>smaller sugar-cane on account of its simi-<lb break="no"/>lar figure. The word <hi rendition="#i">bamboo</hi> is derived<lb break="yes"/>from <hi rendition="#i">mambu</hi>, and from <hi rendition="#i">canda</hi> comes our<lb break="yes"/>term <hi rendition="#i">sugar-candy</hi>, as does <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>from the Persian word <hi rendition="#i">schir</hi>, which sig-<lb break="no"/>nifies milk.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Under the name of <hi rendition="#i">saccharum</hi> Pliny<lb break="yes"/>certainly described the <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir</hi> of the<lb break="yes"/>bamboo as&#x201C; a honey collected from the<lb break="yes"/>stems of reeds, which is white like gum,<lb break="yes"/>breaks between the teeth, is of the size<lb break="yes"/>of a nut, and is applicable to medicinal<lb break="yes"/>purposes alone.&#x201D; The ancients had,<lb break="yes"/>nevertheless, some knowledge of our<lb break="yes"/>sugar, which was said to be produced<lb break="yes"/>in India without bees. Several writers<lb break="yes"/>of antiquity believed that a sweet honey-<lb break="no"/>like juice was expressed from the roots<lb break="yes"/>of lofty reeds, thus confounding the root<lb break="yes"/>with the stem, and the comparatively low<lb break="yes"/>sugar-cane with the tall bamboo-tree.<lb break="yes"/>Some of them even had a notion that the<lb break="yes"/>genuine cane-sugar was a dew which set-<lb break="no"/>tled upon the leaves of those plants.<lb break="yes"/>The sugar-cane indeed grows wild and<lb break="yes"/>in a natural state near Almansura in the<lb break="yes"/>East Indies, on the banks of the Eu-<lb break="no"/>phrates, and at Siraf; yet I presume that<lb break="yes"/>in the regions of Asia visited by the<lb break="yes"/>Greeks the juice of the cane was ex-<lb break="no"/>pressed only for the purpose of an imme-<lb break="no"/>diate beverage, and that the ancients had<lb break="yes"/>not consequently any knowledge of solid<lb break="yes"/>sugar, so that wherever the term is em-<lb break="no"/>ployed by them it signifies the <hi rendition="#i">tabaschir</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>of the bainboo.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>
                    <p>&#x201C;It is almost superfluous to observe<lb break="yes"/>that before the Spaniards opened the<lb break="yes"/>way to America, the inhabitants of that<lb break="yes"/>continent and the adjacent islands were<lb break="yes"/>strangers to the sugar cane as well as to<lb break="yes"/>our different kinds of corn and rice.<lb break="yes"/>The Spanish writers on America, indeed,<lb break="yes"/>give the name of <hi rendition="#i">little rice</hi> to the <hi rendition="#i">cheno-<lb break="no"/>podium quino</hi>, which is common in Bogota<lb break="yes"/>and Quito, as the Anglo-Americans term<lb break="yes"/>a species of <hi rendition="#i">zizania</hi>, wild rice of Canada.<lb break="yes"/>Maize or Turkey corn, like other plants<lb break="yes"/>of ancient cultivation, does not grow<lb break="yes"/>wild in any part of the new continent.<lb break="yes"/>It were to be wished that some future<lb break="yes"/>traveller would furnish more particular<lb break="yes"/>information respecting the <hi rendition="#i">magu</hi>-corn<lb break="yes"/>and <hi rendition="#i">tuca</hi>-barley, of which Molini makes<lb break="yes"/>very brief mention in his History of<lb break="yes"/>Chili, and of which the Araucanians<lb break="yes"/>formerly made their Covque bread.<lb break="yes"/>From maize and the agave the Ameri-<lb break="no"/>cans prepared the honey not produced<lb break="yes"/>by bees, which, as Hernando Cortez in-<lb break="no"/>forms us, was carried for sale to their<lb break="yes"/>markets.&#x201D;</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>