<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="67" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Art.</hi> IX. <hi rendition="#i">Observations on the Orchide&#x00E6;. From the Latin<lb break="yes"/>of</hi> Alexander Baron Von Humboldt.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">
                            <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>he</hi>
                    </hi> distinction among the vegetables of the Monocotyledo-<lb break="no"/>nous division, in regard to beauty of form and variation of hue<lb break="yes"/>in the inflorescence, is immense. Thus flowers, which in the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Gramine&#x00E6;, Cyperace&#x00E6;, Junce&#x00E6;,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Palm&#x00E6;,</hi> are minute, colour-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="68" facs="#f0002"/>less, and inconspicuous; in the <hi rendition="#i" >Orchide&#x00E6;,</hi> on the other hand, are<lb break="yes"/>so rich in the variety of their tints, that they even exceed in this<lb break="yes"/>point of view the more showy beauty of the <hi rendition="#i">Amaryllide&#x00E6;, Iride&#x00E6;,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and <hi rendition="#i">Scitamine&#x00E6;.</hi> It is, however, in tropical regions that the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Orchide&#x00E6;</hi> form the principal decoration of the vegetable king-<lb break="no"/>dom; and although in the continent of New Holland (where all<lb break="yes"/>things are reported to be extraordinary) we find from Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Brown&#x2019;s account, that fewer species of this order are found<lb break="yes"/>within the tropics than between the latitudes of 33&#x00B0; and 35&#x00B0;;<lb break="yes"/>this must be accounted an exception to the general rule. But<lb break="yes"/>when we are aware that the <hi rendition="#i">Epidendrous Orchide&#x00E6;</hi> delight in<lb break="yes"/>moisture and a mild climate, it is not difficult to conceive why<lb break="yes"/>they should have extended themselves in the southern hemis-<lb break="no"/>phere, so much towards the antarctic circle; for there they<lb break="yes"/>find in the winter season an atmosphere as temperate as on the<lb break="yes"/>declivities of the mountains within the tropics.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is not easy to estimate the harvest of <hi rendition="#i">Orchide&#x00E6;</hi> that awaits<lb break="yes"/>the botanist in the sequestered and shady vallies of the Andés,<lb break="yes"/>where the climate is mild; as yet scarcely a twentieth part have<lb break="yes"/>unfolded themselves to science. The whole of Europe does not<lb break="yes"/>present us with more than from 70 to 80 species; while on the<lb break="yes"/>other hand, the tropical portion of America, though so slightly<lb break="yes"/>explored in its mountainous tracts, has already afforded to the<lb break="yes"/>naturalist 244 species, of which 61 that were unrecorded have<lb break="yes"/>been observed by Bonpland and myself. The <hi rendition="#i">Orchide&#x00E6;</hi> of the New<lb break="yes"/>and the Old World <choice>
                        <sic>rogether</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">together</corr>
                    </choice>, amount to about 700 species.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Though the <hi rendition="#i">Orchide&#x00E6;</hi> are dispersed through the equatorial<lb break="yes"/>regions of both the New and the Old Continent, from the level of<lb break="yes"/>the sea up to the height of from 1800 to 1900 fathoms, yet we<lb break="yes"/>may safely assert, that in regard to number of species, colour of<lb break="yes"/>blossom, fragrance, as well as fullness and brilliancy of foliage,<lb break="yes"/>that it is in the gorges of the Andés of Mexico, New Grenada,<lb break="yes"/>Quito, and Peru, between the heights of 800 and 1100 fathoms,<lb break="yes"/>where the mean annual temperature is 19&#x00B0;-17&#x00B0; of the centrigade<lb break="yes"/>thermometer, and soft breezes continually prevail, that they<lb break="yes"/>excel those of all the world besides.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There are hardly any <hi rendition="#i">Orchide&#x00E6;</hi> with spurred labels, in the<lb break="yes"/>equatorial regions; the types of such are peculiar to the temperate<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="69" facs="#f0003"/>and the frozen zones. To the northern hemisphere belong the genera<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Orchis, Habenaria, Cypripedium, Ophrys, Serapias,<lb break="yes"/>Epipactis,</hi>
                    </hi> &amp;c.; to the southern, those of <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Satyrium, Ptery-<lb break="no"/>godium, Disperis, Corycium, Disa, Pterostylis, Cala-<lb break="no"/>denia,</hi>
                    </hi> &amp;c. The equatorial <hi rendition="#i">Orchide&#x00E6;</hi> are chiefly of the Epiden-<lb break="no"/>drous section, of a peculiar appearance, and differing from those<lb break="yes"/>of the temperate and frigid regions, in being usually gregarious,<lb break="yes"/>and in growing upon trees, while in the latter regions they are<lb break="yes"/>found insulated, and upon the ground. Some few species of the<lb break="yes"/>northern type, for instance, some belonging to <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Ophrys, Habe-<lb break="no"/>naria,</hi>
                    </hi> and <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Alstenteinia,</hi>
                    </hi> are found within the tropics, not<lb break="yes"/>only on the chines of the loftiest mountains, but sometimes like-<lb break="no"/>wise in the plains. We know of only four species which are<lb break="yes"/>common to both the New and the Old World within the tem-<lb break="no"/>perate zone; these are <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Satyrium</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">viride,</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Orchis</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">hyperborea,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Neottia</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">repens,</hi> and <hi rendition="#k">Neottia</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">tortilis.</hi> It seems very astonish-<lb break="no"/>ing to us that <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Dendrobium</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">polystachion,</hi> should prove common<lb break="yes"/>to the mountainous parts of Jamaica, the forests of Cayenne,<lb break="yes"/>and the Isle of France. Can these plants be really of the<lb break="yes"/>same species? In the bulbs of most of the <hi rendition="#i">Orchide&#x00E6;</hi> of hot<lb break="yes"/>climates, a white starchy substance, generally of a nutritious<lb break="yes"/>nature, is found; in some, as for instance, in <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Pleurothallis</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">sagittifera,</hi> a viscous substance, applicable to the same purposes<lb break="yes"/>as carpenter&#x2019;s glue.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In general, the Monocotyledons abound in starch, which re-<lb break="no"/>sides either in the fruit (as for example, in the <hi rendition="#i">Gramine&#x00E6;,</hi> unripe<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Mus&#x00E6;,</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Palma</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Pihiguao</hi>) in the stem, (as in <hi rendition="#i" >Sagus,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Mauritia,</hi>)<lb break="yes"/>or in the root (as in the <hi rendition="#i">Aroide&#x00E6;, Tacc&#x00E6;, Orchide&#x00E6;,</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Maranta</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">indica, Liliace&#x00E6;, Dioscoride&#x00E6;</hi>). On the other hand, sugar is con-<lb break="no"/>tained in the juices of the <hi rendition="#i" >Gramine&#x00E6;,</hi> of the <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Argave</hi>
                    </hi> of <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Palma</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Areng,</hi> and the unripe fruit of the <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Musa</hi>
                    </hi> or plantain. And when<lb break="yes"/>we reflect that the chymists of the present day have ascertained<lb break="yes"/>that the proportions of oxygen, hydrogen, and carbon, are nearly<lb break="yes"/>the same in both sugar and starch, and that malted barley forms<lb break="yes"/>a sweet wort, we shall not be surprised to find them component<lb break="yes"/>parts of the same plant, nor even of the same parts of a plant.<lb break="yes"/>The older writers should seem to have had a kind of presentiment<lb break="yes"/>of the transmutation of starch into sugar, as when Prosper<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="70" facs="#f0004"/>Alpinus broached the idea, that the plantain derived its origin<lb break="yes"/>from a sugar-cane ingrafted on the root of the Colocasia; and<lb break="yes"/>Abd-Allatif, that it sprung from a stone of the date which<lb break="yes"/>had germinated in the root of the Colocasia. Gluten is asso-<lb break="no"/>ciated with the starch in the seed of the corn-plants, and is the<lb break="yes"/>principal cause of their being in the shape of bread, the staff of<lb break="yes"/>human life. The glutinous liquid deposited in the bulbs of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Orchide&#x00E6;,</hi> is as distinct from the true gluten of the corn-plants,<lb break="yes"/>as the bird-lime produced from the bark of the holly and the<lb break="yes"/>misletoe berries is from that. A very pungent aroma is found in<lb break="yes"/>the flowers of the <hi rendition="#i">Lilia, Asphodeli,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Narcissi;</hi> as in the stigma<lb break="yes"/>of the Crocus or Saffron, in the fruit of <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Vanilla</hi>
                    </hi> and <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Amomum</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Cardomomum;</hi> in the root of the <hi rendition="#i" >Cann&#x00E6;</hi> (ginger;) and in<lb break="yes"/>the whole tribe of <hi rendition="#i">Peperomi&#x00E6;.</hi> Acids, bitters, resin, camphor,<lb break="yes"/>poisons, tanning matter, and vegetable milk are seldom or ever<lb break="yes"/>found in the Monocotyledons. Poisonous matters in this pri-<lb break="no"/>mary division of vegetables are confined to the <hi rendition="#i">Colchicace&#x00E6;</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Amaryllide&#x00E6;:</hi> while the antidote is found only in the juice of<lb break="yes"/>that genus of palm which we have named <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Kunthia;</hi>
                    </hi> the<lb break="yes"/>bitter principle to <hi rendition="#k">Scilla</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i">Smilace&#x00E6;;</hi> gum-resin to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Aloe.</hi>
                    </hi> An astringent principle, not yet well determined, be-<lb break="no"/>longs to <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Drac&#x00E6;na</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Draco</hi> and the <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Agave</hi>
                    </hi> called <hi rendition="#i">Cocuiza</hi> in<lb break="yes"/>the Caraccas, and their juices are used as a caustic in surgery.<lb break="yes"/>I cannot conceive how it could have occurred to Fourcroy to<lb break="yes"/>affirm, that the Monocotyledons never produced any oil, when<lb break="yes"/>we see that within the tropics the Cocoa-palm is cultivated for the<lb break="yes"/>same purpose as the olive tree with us. It was acutely observed<lb break="yes"/>by Decandolle, and confirmed by the experiments of Mr. An-<lb break="no"/>drew Knight, that in the Monocotyledons, where the reducent<lb break="yes"/>vessels are dispersed throughout the entire trunk of the plant, and<lb break="yes"/>do not coalesce into a bark or rind, that nearly all those qualities<lb break="yes" />are wanting, with which nature has usually endowed the bark of<lb break="yes" />the Dicotyledons.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 