<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="74" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">the milk tree.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Amid</hi> the great number of curious<lb break="yes" />phenomena which have presented<lb break="yes"/>themselves to me in the course of<lb break="yes"/>my travels, I confess there are few<lb break="yes"/>that have so powerfully affected my<lb break="yes"/>imagination as the aspect of the cow-<lb break="no"/>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>tree</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">tree.</corr>
                    </choice> Whatever relates to milk,<lb break="yes"/>whatever regards corn, inspires an<lb break="yes"/>interest, which is not merely that of<lb break="yes" />the physical knowledge of things,<lb break="yes"/>but is connected with another order<lb break="yes"/>of ideas and sentiments. We can<lb break="yes" />scarcely conceive how the human<lb break="yes"/>race could exist without farinaceous<lb break="yes"/>substances, and without that nourish-<lb break="no"/>ing juice which the breast of the<lb break="yes"/>mother contains, and which is appro-<lb break="no"/>priated to the long feebleness of the<lb break="yes"/>infant. The amylaceous matter of<lb break="yes"/>corn, the object of religious venera-<lb break="no"/>tion among so many nations, ancient<lb break="yes"/>and modern, is diffused in the seeds,<lb break="yes" />and deposited in the roots of vege-<lb break="no"/>tables; milk, which serves us as an<lb break="yes"/>aliment, appears to us exclusively<lb break="yes"/>the produce of animal organization.<lb break="yes"/>Such are the impressions we have<lb break="yes"/>received in our earliest infancy; such<lb break="yes" />is also the source of that astonish-<lb break="no"/>ment which seizes us at the aspect<lb break="yes"/>of the tree just described. It is not<lb break="yes" />here the solemn shades of forests,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>the majestic course of rivers, the<lb break="yes"/>mountains wrapped in eternal frost,<lb break="yes"/>that excite our emotion. A few<lb break="yes" />drops of vegetable juice recal to our<lb break="yes"/>minds all the powerfulness and the<lb break="yes"/>fecundity of nature. On the barren<lb break="yes"/>flank of a rock grows a tree with co-<lb break="no"/>riaceous and dry leaves. Its large<lb break="yes"/>woody roots can scarcely penetrate<lb break="yes"/>into the stone. For several months<lb break="yes"/>of the year not a single shower<lb break="yes"/>moistens its foliage. Its branches<lb break="yes"/>appear dead and dried; but when<lb break="yes"/>the trunk is pierced, there flows<lb break="yes"/>from it a sweet and nourishing milk.<lb break="yes"/>It is at the rising of the sun that this<lb break="yes" />vegetable fountain is most abundant.<lb break="yes"/>The blacks and natives are then seen<lb break="yes"/>hastening from all quarters, furnish-<lb break="no"/>ed with large bowls to receive the<lb break="yes"/>milk, which grows yellow, and thick-<lb break="no"/>ens at its surface. Some employ<lb break="yes"/>their bowls under the tree itself,<lb break="yes"/>others carry the juice home to their<lb break="yes"/>children. We seem to see the fa-<lb break="no"/>mily of a shepherd who distributes<lb break="yes"/>the milk of his flock.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have described the sensations<lb break="yes"/>which the <hi rendition="#i" >cow-tree</hi> awakens in the<lb break="yes"/>mind of the traveller at the first<lb break="yes"/>view. In examining the physical<lb break="yes" />properties of animal and vegetable<lb break="yes"/>products, science displays them as<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="75" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>closely linked together; but it strips<lb break="yes"/>them of what is marvellous, and per-<lb break="no"/>haps also of a part of their charms,<lb break="yes"/>of what excited our astonishment.<lb break="yes"/>Nothing appears isolated; the che-<lb break="no"/>mical principles that were believed<lb break="yes"/>to be peculiar to animals are found<lb break="yes"/>in plants; a common chain links to-<lb break="no"/>gether all organic nature.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Long before chemists had recog-<lb break="no"/>nised small portions of wax in the<lb break="yes"/>pollen of flowers, the varnish of<lb break="yes" />leaves, and the whitish dust of our<lb break="yes"/>plums and grapes, the inhabitants of<lb break="yes"/>the Andes of Quindiu fabricated ta-<lb break="no" />pers with the thick layer of wax that<lb break="yes"/>covers the trunk of a palm-tree.<note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Ceroxylon andicola,</hi> which we have de-<lb break="no" />scribed in our Plantes Equinoctionales, vol. i.<lb break="yes"/>p. 9. pl. i. and ii.</note> It<lb break="yes"/>is but a few years since we have dis-<lb break="no"/>covered in Europe <hi rendition="#i">caseum,</hi> the basis<lb break="yes"/>of cheese, in the emulsion of al-<lb break="no" />monds;<note place="foot" n="†">Proust in the Journ. de Physique, vol. liv.<lb break="yes"/>p. 430. Boullay and Vogel, in the Annales de<lb break="yes"/>Chimie et de Physique, vol. vi. p. 403.</note> yet for ages past, in the<lb break="yes"/>mountains of the coast of Venezuela,<lb break="yes" />the milk of a tree, and the cheese<lb break="yes"/>separated from that vegetable milk,<lb break="yes"/>have been considered as a salutary<lb break="yes"/>aliment. What is the cause of this<lb break="yes"/>singular course in the unfolding of<lb break="yes"/>our knowledge? How have the vulgar<lb break="yes"/>in one hemisphere recognised what<lb break="yes"/>in the other has so long escaped the<lb break="yes"/>sagacity of chemists, accustomed to<lb break="yes"/>interrogate nature, and seize her in<lb break="yes"/>her mysterious progress? It is that<lb break="yes"/>a small number of elements and<lb break="yes"/>principles differently combined are<lb break="yes" />spread through several families of<lb break="yes"/>plants; it is that the genera and spe-<lb break="no"/>cies of these natural families are not<lb break="yes"/>equally distributed in the torrid, the<lb break="yes"/>frigid, and the temperate zones: it<lb break="yes"/>is that tribes, excited by want, and<lb break="yes"/>deriving almost all their subsistence<lb break="yes" />from the vegetable kingdom, discover<lb break="yes"/>nourishing principles, farinaceous<lb break="yes"/>and alimentary substances, wherever<lb break="yes"/>nature has deposited them, in the sap,<lb break="yes"/>the bark, the roots, or the fruits of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>vegetables. That amylaceous fecu-<lb break="no"/>la which the seeds of the cereal<lb break="yes"/>plants furnish in all its purity, is<lb break="yes" />found united with an acrid, and, some-<lb break="no"/>times, even poisonous juice, in the<lb break="yes"/>roots of the arums, the tacca pinna-<lb break="no" />tifida, and the iatropha manihot.<lb break="yes"/>The savage of America, like the sa-<lb break="no"/>vage of the islands in the Pacific<lb break="yes"/>Ocean, has learned to <hi rendition="#i">dulcify</hi> the fe-<lb break="no"/>cula, by pressing and separating it<lb break="yes"/>from its juice. In the milk of<lb break="yes"/>plants, and in the milky emulsions,<lb break="yes"/>matter extremely nourishing, albu-<lb break="no"/>men, <hi rendition="#i">caseum,</hi> and sugar, are found<lb break="yes"/>mixed with caoutchouc, and with de-<lb break="no"/>leterious and caustic principles, such<lb break="yes"/>as <hi rendition="#i">morphin</hi> and the hydrocyanic acid.<note place="foot" n="*">Opium contains <hi rendition="#i">morphin,</hi> caoutchouc, &amp;c.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>These mixtures vary not only in the<lb break="yes"/>different families, but also in the spe-<lb break="no"/>cies which belong to the same ge-<lb break="no"/>nus. Sometimes it is the <hi rendition="#i">morphin,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>or narcotic principle, that charac-<lb break="no"/>terizes the vegetable milk as in some<lb break="yes"/>papaverous plants; sometimes it is<lb break="yes"/>caoutchouc, as in the hevea, and the<lb break="yes"/>castilloa; sometimes albumen and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">caseum,</hi> as in the <hi rendition="#i">cow-tree.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#et">
                            <hi rendition="#i">Humboldt,</hi> vol. iv.</hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 