<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="159" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>CAVERN OF THE GUACHARO.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">What</hi> gives most celebrity to the valley of Caripe,<lb break="yes"/>besides the extraordinary coolness of the climate, is the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Cueva,</hi> or Cavern of the <hi rendition="#i">Guacharo.</hi> In a country where<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="160" facs="#f0002"/>the people love what is marvellous, a cavern that gives<lb break="yes"/>birth to a river, and is inhabited by thousands of noc-<lb break="no"/>turnal birds, the fat of which is employed in the missions<lb break="yes"/>to dress food, is an everlasting object of conversation and<lb break="yes"/>discussion. A lively interest in the phenomena of nature<lb break="yes"/>is preserved wherever society may be said to be without<lb break="yes"/>life; where in dull monotony it presents only simple<lb break="yes"/>relations little fitted to excite the ardour of curiosity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The cavern which the natives call <hi rendition="#i">a mine of fat,</hi> is not<lb break="yes"/>in the valley of Caripe itself, but at three short leagues<lb break="yes"/>distance from the convent, toward the West-south-west.<lb break="yes"/>It opens into a lateral valley, which terminates at the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Sierra del Guacharo.</hi> We set out toward the Sierra on the<lb break="yes"/>18th September, accompanied by the Alcaids, or Indian<lb break="yes"/>magistrates, and the greater part of the monks of the con-<lb break="no"/>vent. A narrow path led us at first during an hour and a<lb break="yes"/>half, towards the south, across a fine plain, covered with a<lb break="yes"/>beautiful turf. We then turned toward the West, along<lb break="yes"/>a small river, which issues from the mouth of the cavern.<lb break="yes"/>We ascended during three quarters of an hour, walking<lb break="yes"/>sometimes in the water, which was shallow, sometimes<lb break="yes"/>between the torrent and a wall of rocks on a soil extremely<lb break="yes"/>slippery and miry. The falling down of the earth, the<lb break="yes"/>scattered trunks of trees, over which the mules could<lb break="yes"/>scarcely pass, the creeping plants that covered the ground,<lb break="yes"/>rendered this part of the road fatiguing. We were<lb break="yes"/>surprised to find here, at scarcely 500 toises<note place="foot" n="*">3,200 feet English.</note> of elevation<lb break="yes" />above the level of the sea, a cruciferous plant, <hi rendition="#i">raphanus<lb break="yes"/>pinnatus.</hi> It is well known how scarce the plants of this<lb break="yes"/>family are between the tropics; they display in some<lb break="yes"/>sort a northern form, and as such we never expected to<lb break="yes"/>see it on the plain of Caripe at so little an elevation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the foot of the lofty mountain of Guacharo, we were<lb break="yes"/>only four hundred steps from the cavern, without yet<lb break="yes"/>perceiving the entrance. The torrent runs in a crevice,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="161" facs="#f0003"/>which has been hollowed out by the waters; and we<lb break="yes"/>went on under a cornice the projection of which pre-<lb break="no"/>vented us from seeing the sky. The path winds like<lb break="yes"/>the river: at the last turning we came suddenly before<lb break="yes"/>the immense opening of the grotto. The aspect of this<lb break="yes"/>spot is majestic even to the eye of a traveller accustom-<lb break="no"/>ed to the picturesque scenes of the higher Alps. Na-<lb break="no"/>ture in every zone follows immutable laws in the dis-<lb break="no"/>tribution of rocks, in the exterior forms of mountains,<lb break="yes"/>and even in those tumultuous changes which the ex-<lb break="no"/>terior crust of our planet has undergone. So great a<lb break="yes"/>uniformity led me to believe, that the aspect of the ca-<lb break="no"/>vern of Caripe would differ little from what I had ob-<lb break="no"/>served in my preceding travels. The reality far ex-<lb break="no"/>ceeded my expectations. If the configuration of the<lb break="yes"/>grottoes, the splendor of the stalactites, and all the<lb break="yes"/>phenomena of inorganic nature, present striking analo-<lb break="no"/>gies, the majesty of equinoxial vegetation gives at the<lb break="yes"/>same time an individual character to the aperture of<lb break="yes"/>the cavern.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Cueva del Guacharo is pierced in the vertical<lb break="yes"/>profile of a rock. The entrance is toward the south,<lb break="yes"/>and forms a vault eighty feet broad and seventy-two<lb break="yes"/>feet high. This elevation is but a fifth less than that<lb break="yes"/>of the colonnade of the Louvre. The rock that sur-<lb break="no"/>mounts the grotto is covered with trees of gigantic<lb break="yes"/>height. The mammee-tree, and the genipa with large<lb break="yes"/>and shining leaves, raise their branches vertically to-<lb break="no"/>ward the sky; while those of the courbaril and the<lb break="yes"/>erythrina form, as they extend themselves, a thick<lb break="yes"/>vault of verdure. Plants of the family of pothos, with<lb break="yes"/>succulent stems, oxalises, and orchide&#x00E6; with a golden<lb break="yes"/>flower spotted with black, three inches long, rise in<lb break="yes"/>the driest clefts of the rocks; while creeping plants,<lb break="yes"/>waving in the winds, are interwoven in festoons before<lb break="yes"/>the opening of the cavern. We distinguished in these<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="162" facs="#f0004"/>festoons a bignonia of a violet blue, the purple dolichos,<lb break="yes"/>and, for the first time, that magnificent solandra, the<lb break="yes"/>orange flower of which has a fleshy tube more than<lb break="yes"/>four inches long. The entrance of grottoes, like the<lb break="yes"/>view of cascades, derive their principal charm from the<lb break="yes"/>situation, more or less majestic, in which they are placed,<lb break="yes"/>and which in some sort determines the character of the<lb break="yes"/>landscape. What a contrast between the Cueva of Ca-<lb break="no"/>ripe, and those caverns of the north crowned with oaks<lb break="yes"/>and gloomy larch trees!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But this luxury of vegetation embellishes not only<lb break="yes"/>the outside of the vault; it appears even in the vestibule<lb break="yes"/>of the grotto. We saw with astonishment plantain-<lb break="no"/>leaved heliconias eighteen feet high, the praga palm-<lb break="no"/>tree, and arborescent arums, follow the banks of the<lb break="yes"/>river, even to those subterranean places. The vegeta-<lb break="no"/>tion continues in the cave of Caripe, as in those deep<lb break="yes"/>crevices of the Andes, half excluded from the light of<lb break="yes"/>day; and does not disappear, till, advancing in the<lb break="yes"/>interior, we reach thirty or forty paces from the en-<lb break="no"/>trance. We measured the way by means of a cord:<lb break="yes" />and we went on about four hundred and thirty feet<lb break="yes"/>without being obliged to light our torches. Daylight<lb break="yes"/>penetrates even into this region, because the grotto<lb break="yes"/>forms but one single channel, which keeps the same<lb break="yes"/>direction from south-east to north-west. Where the<lb break="yes"/>light begins to fail, we heard from afar the hoarse<lb break="yes"/>sounds of the nocturnal birds&#x2014;sounds which the na-<lb break="no"/>tives think belong exclusively to those subterraneous<lb break="yes"/>places.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Guacharo is of the size of our fowls, has the<lb break="yes"/>mouth of the goatsuckers and procnias, and the port of<lb break="yes"/>those vultures, the crooked beak of which is surrounded<lb break="yes"/>with stiff silky hairs. It forms a new genus, very diffe-<lb break="no"/>rent from the goat-sucker by the force of its voice, by<lb break="yes"/>the considerable strength of its beak, containing a<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="163" facs="#f0005"/>double tooth, and by its feet without the membranes<lb break="yes"/>that unite the anterior phalanxes of the claws. The<lb break="yes"/>plumage of the Guacharo is of a dark bluish gray, mix-<lb break="no"/>ed with small streaks and specks of black. Large white<lb break="yes"/>spots, which have the form of a heart, and which are<lb break="yes"/>bordered with black, mark the head, the wings, and<lb break="yes"/>the tail. The eyes of the bird are hurt by the blaze of<lb break="yes"/>day; they are blue, and smaller than those of the goat-<lb break="no"/>sucker. The spread of the wings, which are compo-<lb break="no" />sed of seventeen or eighteen quill-feathers, is three feet<lb break="yes"/>and a half. The Guacharo quits the cavern at night-fall,<lb break="yes"/>especially when the moon shines. It is almost the only<lb break="yes"/>frugiverous nocturnal bird that is yet known; the con-<lb break="no"/>formation of its feet sufficiently shows that it does not hunt<lb break="yes"/>like our owls. It is difficult to form an idea of the hor-<lb break="no"/>rible noise occasioned by thousands of these birds in the<lb break="yes"/>dark part of the cavern, and which can only be com-<lb break="no"/>pared to the croaking of crows, which, in the pine<lb break="yes"/>forests of the north, live in society, and construct their<lb break="yes"/>nests upon trees, the tops of which touch each other.<lb break="yes"/>The shrill and piercing cries of the Guacharoes strike<lb break="yes"/>upon the vaults of the rocks, and are repeated by the<lb break="yes"/>echo in the depth of the cavern. The Indians showed<lb break="yes"/>us the nests of these birds, by fixing torches to the end<lb break="yes"/>of a long pole. These nests were fifty or sixty feet<lb break="yes"/>high above our heads, in holes in the shape of funnels,<lb break="yes"/>with which the roof of the grotto is pierced like a sieve.<lb break="yes"/>The noise increased as we advanced, and the birds were<lb break="yes"/>affrighted by the light of the torches of Copal. When<lb break="yes"/>this noise ceased a few minutes around us, we heard at a<lb break="yes"/>distance the plaintive cries of the birds roosting in other<lb break="yes"/>ramifications of the cavern. It seemed as if those bands<lb break="yes"/>answered each other alternately.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Indians enter into the Cueva del Guacharo once<lb break="yes"/>a year, near midsummer, armed with poles, and des-<lb break="no"/>troy the greater part of the nests. At this season, seve-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="164" facs="#f0006"/>ral thousands of birds are killed; and the old ones, as<lb break="yes"/>if to defend their brood, hover over the heads of the<lb break="yes"/>Indians, uttering terrible cries. The young, which fall<lb break="yes"/>to the ground, are opened upon the spot. Their caul<lb break="yes"/>is extremely loaded with fat, a layer of which is conti-<lb break="no"/>nued, so as to form a kind of cushion between the legs<lb break="yes"/>of the bird. This quantity of fat in frugiverous ani-<lb break="no"/>mals, not exposed to the light, and exerting very little<lb break="yes"/>muscular motion, reminds us of what has been long<lb break="yes"/>since observed in the fattening of geese and oxen. It<lb break="yes"/>is well known how favourable darkness and repose are<lb break="yes"/>to this process. The nocturnal birds of Europe are<lb break="yes"/>lean, because instead of feeding on fruits, like the Gua-<lb break="no"/>charo, they live on the scanty produce of their prey.<lb break="yes"/>At the period which is commonly called, at Caripe, <hi rendition="#i">the<lb break="yes"/>oil harvest,</hi> the Indians build huts with palm leaves,<lb break="yes"/>near the entrance, and even in the porch of the cavern.<lb break="yes"/>Of these we still saw some remains. There, with a fire<lb break="yes"/>of brushwood, they melt, in pots of clay, the fat of the<lb break="yes"/>young birds just killed. This fat is known by the<lb break="yes"/>name of butter, or oil of the Guacharo. It is half li-<lb break="no"/>quid, transparent, without smell, and so pure, that it<lb break="yes"/>may be kept above a year without becoming rancid.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>At the convent of Caripe, no other oil is used in the<lb break="yes"/>kitchen of the monks but that of the cavern, and we<lb break="yes"/>never observed that it gave the aliments a disagreeable<lb break="yes"/>taste or smell.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The quantity of this oil collected, little corresponds<lb break="yes"/>with the carnage made every year in the grotto by the<lb break="yes"/>Indians. It appears that they do not get above 150 or<lb break="yes"/>160 bottles<note place="foot" n="*">Sixty cubic inches, or rather more than two English pints each.</note> of very pure butter; the rest, less trans-<lb break="no"/>parent, is preserved in large earthern vessels. This<lb break="yes"/>branch of industry reminds us of the harvest of pi-<lb break="no"/>geon&#x2019;s oil, of which some thousands of barrels were<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="165" facs="#f0007"/>formerly collected in Carolina. At Caripe, the use of<lb break="yes"/>the oil of the Guacharo is very ancient, and the mission-<lb break="no"/>aries have only regulated the method of extracting it.<lb break="yes"/>The members of an Indian family, which bears the<lb break="yes"/>name of Morocoymas, pretend, as the descendants of<lb break="yes"/>the first colonists of the valley, to be the lawful pro-<lb break="no"/>prietors of the cavern, and arrogate to themselves the<lb break="yes"/>monopoly of the fat: but, thanks to the monastic in-<lb break="no"/>stitutions, their rights at present are merely honorary.<lb break="yes"/>In conformity to the system of the missionaries, the<lb break="yes"/>Indians are obliged to furnish Guacharo-oil for the<lb break="yes"/>church lamp: the rest, we were assured, is purchased of<lb break="yes"/>them. We shall not decide either on the legitimacy of<lb break="yes"/>the rights of the Morocoymas, or on the origin of the<lb break="yes"/>obligation imposed on the natives by the monks. It<lb break="yes"/>would seem natural that the produce of the chace should<lb break="yes"/>belong to those who hunt; but in the forests of the New<lb break="yes"/>World, as in the centre of European cultivation, public<lb break="yes"/>right is modified according to the relations which are<lb break="yes"/>established between the strong and the weak, the vic-<lb break="no"/>tors and the vanquished.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The race of the Guacharoes would have been long<lb break="yes"/>ago extinct, had not several circumstances contributed<lb break="yes"/>to its preservation. The natives, restrained by their<lb break="yes"/>superstitious ideas, have seldom the courage to pene-<lb break="no"/>trate far into the grotto. It appears, also, that birds of<lb break="yes"/>the same species dwell in the neighbouring caverns,<lb break="yes"/>which are too narrow to be accessible to man. Perhaps<lb break="yes"/>the great cavern is repeopled by colonies that abandon<lb break="yes"/>the small grottoes; for the missionaries assured us, that<lb break="yes"/>hitherto no sensible diminution of the birds had been<lb break="yes"/>observed. Young Guacharoes have been sent to the<lb break="yes"/>port of Cumana, and have lived there several days<lb break="yes"/>without taking any nourishment; the seeds offered to<lb break="yes"/>them not suiting their taste. When the crops and giz-<lb break="no"/>zards of the young birds are opened in the cavern, they<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="166" facs="#f0008"/>are found to contain all sorts of hard and dry fruits, which<lb break="yes"/>furnish, under the singular name of <hi rendition="#i">Guacharo seed,</hi> a<lb break="yes"/>very celebrated remedy against intermittent fevers.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>The old birds carry these seeds to their young. They<lb break="yes"/>are carefully collected, and sent to the sick at Cariaco,<lb break="yes"/>and other places of the low regions, where fevers are<lb break="yes"/>prevalent.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We followed, as we continued our progress through<lb break="yes"/>the cavern, the banks of the small river which issued<lb break="yes"/>from it, and is from twenty-eight to thirty feet wide.<lb break="yes"/>We walked on the banks, ar far as the hills formed of<lb break="yes"/>calcareous incrustations permitted us. When the tor-<lb break="no"/>rent winds among very high masses of stalactites, we<lb break="yes"/>were often obliged to descend into its bed, which is<lb break="yes"/>only two feet in depth. We learnt, with surprise, that<lb break="yes"/>this subterraneous rivulet is the origin of the river Ca-<lb break="no"/>ripe, which at a few leagues distance, after having join-<lb break="no"/>ed the small river Santa Maria, is navigable for canoes.<lb break="yes"/>It enters into the river Areo under the name of <hi rendition="#i">Canno<lb break="yes"/>de Terezen.</hi> We found on the banks of the subterra-<lb break="no"/>neous rivulet a great quantity of palm-tree wood, the<lb break="yes"/>remains of trunks, on which the Indians climb to reach<lb break="yes"/>the nests hanging to the roofs of the cavern. The rings<lb break="yes"/>formed by the vestiges of the old footstalks of the leaves<lb break="yes"/>furnish, as it were, the footsteps of a ladder perpendi-<lb break="no"/>cularly placed.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Grotto of Caripe preserves the same direction,<lb break="yes"/>the same breadth, and its primitive height of sixty or<lb break="yes"/>seventy feet, to the distance of 472 metres, or 1458 feet,<lb break="yes"/>accurately measured. I have never seen a cavern, in<lb break="yes"/>either continent, of so uniform and regular a construction.<lb break="yes"/>We had great difficulty in persuading the Indians to<lb break="yes"/>pass beyond the outer part of the Grotto, the only part<lb break="yes"/>of which they annually visit to collect the fat. The<lb break="yes"/>whole authority of the missionaries was necessary to<lb break="yes"/>induce them to advance as far as the spot, where the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="167" facs="#f0009"/>soil rises abruptly at an inclination of sixty degrees, and<lb break="yes"/>where the torrent forms a small subterraneous cascade.<lb break="yes"/>The natives connect mystic ideas with this cave, inha-<lb break="no"/>bited by nocturnal birds; they believe, that the souls<lb break="yes"/>of their ancestors sojourn in the deep recesses of the<lb break="yes"/>cavern. &#x201C;Man,&#x201D; say they, &#x201C;should avoid places which<lb break="yes"/>are enlightened neither by the Sun <hi rendition="#i">(Zis),</hi> nor by the<lb break="yes"/>Moon <hi rendition="#i">(Numa).</hi>&#x201D; To go and join the Guacharoes, is to<lb break="yes"/>rejoin their fathers&#x2014;is to die. The magicians <hi rendition="#i">(piaches)</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and the poisoners <hi rendition="#i">(imorons)</hi> perform their nocturnal<lb break="yes"/>tricks at the entrance of the cavern, to conjure the<lb break="yes"/>chief of the evil spirits <hi rendition="#i" >(ivorokiamo).</hi> Thus, in every<lb break="yes"/>climate, the first fictions of nations resemble each other,<lb break="yes"/>those especially which relate to two principles govern-<lb break="no"/>ing the world, the abode of souls after death, the hap-<lb break="no"/>piness of the virtuous and the punishment of the guilty.<lb break="yes"/>The most different and most barbarous languages pre-<lb break="no"/>sent a certain number of images, which are the same,<lb break="yes"/>because they have their source in the nature of our in-<lb break="no"/>tellect and our sensations. Darkness is every where<lb break="yes"/>connected with the idea of death. The Grotto of Ca-<lb break="no"/>ripe is the Tartarus of the Greeks, and the Guacharoes,<lb break="yes"/>which hover over the rivulet, uttering plaintive cries,<lb break="yes"/>remind us of the Stygian birds.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the point where the rivulet forms the subterran-<lb break="no"/>eous cascade, a hill covered with vegetation, which is<lb break="yes"/>opposite the opening of the grotto, presents itself in a<lb break="yes"/>very picturesque manner. It appears at the extremity<lb break="yes"/>of a straight passage, 240 toises<note place="foot" n="*">1,534 English feet.</note> in length. The stal-<lb break="no"/>actites, which descend from the vault, and which re-<lb break="no"/>semble columns suspended in the air, display them-<lb break="no" />selves on a back-ground of verdure. The opening of<lb break="yes"/>the cavern appeared singularly contracted, when we<lb break="yes"/>saw it about the middle of the day, illumined by the<lb break="yes"/>vivid light reflected at once from the sky, the plants,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="168" facs="#f0010"/>and the rocks. The distant light of day formed some-<lb break="no"/>what of a magical contrast with the darkness, that sur-<lb break="no"/>rounded us in those vast caverns. We discharged our<lb break="yes"/>pieces at a venture, wherever the cries of the nocturnal<lb break="yes"/>birds, and the flapping of their wings, led us to suspect<lb break="yes"/>that a great number of nests were crowded together.<lb break="yes"/>After several fruitless attempts, Mr Bonpland succeed-<lb break="no"/>ed in killing a couple of guacharoes, which, dazzled by<lb break="yes"/>the light of the torches, seemed to pursue us. This cir-<lb break="no"/>cumstance afforded me the means of drawing this bird,<lb break="yes"/>which hitherto had remained unknown to naturalists.<lb break="yes"/>We climbed, not without some difficulty, the small hill,<lb break="yes"/>whence the subterraneous rivulet descends. We saw<lb break="yes"/>that the grotto was perceptibly contracted, retaining<lb break="yes"/>only forty feet in height; and that it continued stretch-<lb break="no"/>ing to the North-east, without deviating from its primi-<lb break="no"/>tive direction, which is parallel to that of the great val-<lb break="no"/>ley of Caripe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We walked in a thick mud to a spot, where we be-<lb break="no"/>held with astonishment the progress of subterraneous<lb break="yes"/>vegetation. The seeds, which the birds carry into the<lb break="yes"/>grotto to feed their young, spring up wherever they can<lb break="yes"/>fix in the mould, that covers the calcareous incrusta-<lb break="no"/>tions. Blanched stalks, with some half formed leaves,<lb break="yes"/>had risen to the height of two feet. It was impossible<lb break="yes"/>to ascertain the species of plants, the form, colour, and<lb break="yes"/>aspect of which had been changed by the absence of light.<lb break="yes"/>Those traces of organization amid darkness forcibly ex-<lb break="no"/>cited the curiosity of the natives, in general so stupid,<lb break="yes"/>and difficult to be moved. They examined them in<lb break="yes"/>that silent meditation inspired by a place they seemed<lb break="yes"/>to dread. It might be thought, that these subterran-<lb break="no"/>eous vegetables, pale and disfigured, appeared to them<lb break="yes"/>phantoms banished from the face of the Earth. To me<lb break="yes"/>the scene recalled one of the happiest scenes of my early<lb break="yes"/>youth, a long abode in the mines of Freiberg, where I<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="169" facs="#f0011"/>made experiments on the effects of blanching, which are<lb break="yes"/>very different, according as the air is pure, or over-<lb break="no"/>changed with hydrogen or azote.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The missionaries with all their authority, could not<lb break="yes"/>prevail on the Indians to penetrate farther into the<lb break="yes"/>cavern. As the vault grew lower, the cries of the gua-<lb break="no"/>charoes became more shrill. We were obliged to yield<lb break="yes"/>to the pusillanimity of our guides, and retrace our steps.<lb break="yes"/>The appearance of the cavern was indeed very uniform.<lb break="yes"/>We find that a bishop of St Thomas of Guiana, had<lb break="yes"/>gone farther than ourselves. He had measured nearly<lb break="yes"/>2500 feet from the mouth to the spot where he stopped,<lb break="yes"/>though the cavern reached farther. The remembrance<lb break="yes"/>of this fact was preserved in the convent of Caripe,<lb break="yes"/>without the exact period being noted. The bishop had<lb break="yes"/>provided himself with great torches of white wax of<lb break="yes"/>Castille. We had torches composed only of the bark<lb break="yes"/>of trees, and native resin. The thick smoke which<lb break="yes"/>issued from these torches, in a narrow subterranean<lb break="yes"/>passage, hurts the eyes, and obstructs the respiration.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We followed the course of the torrent to go out of<lb break="yes"/>the cavern. Before our eyes were dazzled with the<lb break="yes"/>light of day, we saw, without the grotto, the water of<lb break="yes"/>the river sparkling amid the foliage of the trees that<lb break="yes"/>concealed it. It was like a picture placed in the dis-<lb break="no"/>tance, and to which the mouth of the cavern served as<lb break="yes"/>a frame. Having at length reached the entrance, and<lb break="yes"/>seated ourselves on the banks of the rivulet, we rested<lb break="yes"/>after our fatigues. We were glad to be beyond the<lb break="yes"/>hoarse cries of the birds, and to leave a place where<lb break="yes"/>darkness does not offer even the charm of silence and<lb break="yes"/>tranquillity. We could scarcely persuade ourselves<lb break="yes"/>that the name of the Grotto of Caripe had hitherto<lb break="yes"/>remained unknown in Europe. The Guacharoes alone<lb break="yes" />would have been sufficient to have rendered it cele-<lb break="no"/>brated. These nocturnal birds have been nowhere yet<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="170" facs="#f0012"/>discovered, except in the mountains of Caripe and Cu-<lb break="no"/>manacoa.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The missionaries had prepared a repast at the entry<lb break="yes"/>of the cavern. Leaves of bananas and vijao, which<lb break="yes"/>have a silky lustre, served us as a table cloth, accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to the custom of the country. Nothing was want-<lb break="no"/>ing to our enjoyment, not even remembrances, which<lb break="yes"/>are so rare in those countries, where generations dis-<lb break="no"/>appear without leaving a trace of their existence. Our<lb break="yes"/>hosts took pleasure in reminding us, that the first monks<lb break="yes"/>who came into these mountains to found the little vil-<lb break="no"/>lage of Santa Maria, had lived during a month in the<lb break="yes"/>cavern; and there, on a stone, by the light of torches,<lb break="yes"/>had celebrated the mysteries of their religion. This<lb break="yes"/>solitary retreat served as a refuge to the missionaries<lb break="yes"/>against the persecutions of a warlike chief of the Tua-<lb break="no"/>copans, encamped on the banks of the river Caripe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#et">
                            <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 