<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.1" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. Markup.<note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe. Seitenzahl eingefügt.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="7" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/> MILK, BREAD, AND BUTTER TREES.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We had heard several weeks before of a tree, the<lb break="yes"/>sap of which is a nourishing milk. It is called &#x201C;the<lb break="yes"/>cow-tree,&#x201D; and we were assured that the negroes of the<lb break="yes"/>farm, who drink plentifully of this vegetable milk,<lb break="yes"/>consider it a wholesome aliment. All the milky juices<lb break="yes"/>of plants being acrid, bitter, and more or less poisonous,<lb break="yes"/>this account appeared to us very extraordinary; but we<lb break="yes"/>found by experience during our stay at Barbula, that<lb break="yes"/>the virtues of this tree had not been exaggerated. This<lb break="yes"/>fine tree rises like the broad-leaved star-apple. Its<lb break="yes"/>oblong and pointed leaves, rough and alternate, are<lb break="yes"/>marked by lateral ribs, prominent at the lower surface,<lb break="yes"/>and parallel. Some of them are ten inches long. We<lb break="yes"/>did not see the flower; the fruit is somewhat fleshy,<lb break="yes"/>and contains one and sometimes two nuts. When inci-<lb break="no"/>sions are made in the trunk of this tree, it yields abun-<lb break="no"/>dance of a glutinous milk, tolerably thick, devoid of all<lb break="yes"/>seridity, and of an agreeable and balmy smell. It was<lb break="yes"/>offered to us in the shell of a calabash. We drank<lb break="yes"/>considerable quantities of it in the evening before we<lb break="yes"/>went to bed, and very early in the morning, without<lb break="yes"/>feeling the least injurious effect. The viscocity of this<lb break="yes"/>milk alone renders it a little disagreeable. The negroes<lb break="yes"/>and the free people who work in the plantations drink<lb break="yes"/>it, dipping into it their bread of maixe or cassava. The<lb break="yes"/>overseer of the farm told us that the negroes grow sen-<lb break="no"/>sibly fatter during the season when the palo de vaca<lb break="yes"/>furnishes them with most milk. This juice, exposed to<lb break="yes"/>the air, presents at its surface (perhaps in consequence of<lb break="yes"/>the absorption of the atmospheric oxygen) membranes<lb break="yes"/>of a strongly animalised substance, yellowish, stringy, and<lb break="yes"/>resembling cheese. These membranes, separated from<lb break="yes"/>the rest of the more aqueous liquid, are clastic, almost<lb break="yes"/>like caoutchouc; but they undergo, in time, the same<lb break="yes"/>phenomena of putrefaction as gelatine. The people call<lb break="yes"/>the coagulum that separates by the contact of the air,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> cheese. The coagulum grows sour in the space of five<lb break="yes"/>or six days. Amidst the great number of curious phe-<lb break="no"/>nomena which I have obeerved in the course of my<lb break="yes"/>travels, I confess there are few that have made so<lb break="yes"/>powerful an impression on me as the aspect of the cow-<lb break="no"/>tree. Whatever relates to milk or to corn inspires an<lb break="yes"/>interest which is not merely that of the physical know-<lb break="no"/>ledge of things, but is connected with another order of<lb break="yes"/>ideas and sentiments. We can scarcely conceive how<lb break="yes"/>the human race could exist without farinaceous sub-<lb break="no"/>atances, and without that nourishing juice which the<lb break="yes"/>breast of the mother contains, and which is appropriated<lb break="yes"/>to the long feebleness of the infant. The amylaceous<lb break="yes"/>matter of corn, the object of religious veneration among<lb break="yes"/>so many nationa, ancient and modern, is diffused in the<lb break="yes"/>seeds, and deposited in the roots of vegetables; milk,<lb break="yes"/>which serves as an aliment, appears to us exclusively<lb break="yes"/>the produce of animal organisation. Such are the im-<lb break="no"/>pressions we have received in our earliest infancy: such<lb break="yes"/>is also the source of that astonishment created by the<lb break="yes"/>aspect of the tree just described. It is not here the<lb break="yes"/>solemn shades of forests, the majestic course of rivers,<lb break="yes"/>the mountains wrapped in eternal snow, that excite our<lb break="yes"/>emotion. A few drops of vegetable juice recall to our<lb break="yes"/>minds all the powerfulness and the fecundity of nature.<lb break="yes"/>On the barren flank of a rock grows a tree with coria-<lb break="no"/>ceous and dry leaves. Its large woody roots can scarcely<lb break="yes"/>penetrate into the stone. For several months of the<lb break="yes"/>year not a single shower moistens its foliage. Its<lb break="yes"/>branches appear dead and dried; but when the trunk is<lb break="yes"/>pierced there flows from it a sweet and nourishing milk.<lb break="yes"/>It is at the rising of the sun that this vegetable fountain<lb break="yes"/>is most abundant. The negroes and natives are then<lb break="yes"/>seen hastening from all quarters, furnished with large<lb break="yes"/>bowls to receive the milk, which grows yellow, and<lb break="yes"/>thickens at its surface. Some empty their bowls under<lb break="yes"/>the tree itself, others carry the juice home to their<lb break="yes"/>children. &#x2014; <hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels in the Equinoctial<lb break="yes"/>Regions of America.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 