<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="26" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">The Cow-Tree.</hi>&#x2014;</head>
                <p>The following interesting ac-<lb break="no"/>count of this wonder of the vegetable world is<lb break="yes"/>from the 4th volume of the Travels of M. de<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Amid the great number of curious pheno-<lb break="no"/>mena which have presented themselves to me in<lb break="yes"/>the course of my travels, I confess there are few<lb break="yes"/>that have so powerfully affected my imagination<lb break="yes"/>as the aspect of the cow-tree. Whatever relates<lb break="yes" />to milk, whatever regards corn, inspires an in-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="27" facs="#f0002"/>terest, which is not merely that of the physical<lb break="yes"/>knowledge of things, but it is connected with<lb break="yes" />another order of ideas and sentiments. We can<lb break="yes"/>scarcely conceive how the human race could exist<lb break="yes"/>without farinaceous substances, and without that<lb break="yes"/>nourishing juice which the breast of the mother<lb break="yes"/>contains, and which is appropriated to the long<lb break="yes"/>feebleness of the infant. The amylaceous matter<lb break="yes" />of corn, the object of religious veneration among<lb break="yes"/>so many nations, ancient and modern, is diffused<lb break="yes"/>in the seeds, and deposited in the roots of vege-<lb break="no"/>tables; milk, which serves us as an aliment, ap-<lb break="no"/>pears to us exclusively the produce of animal<lb break="yes"/>organization. Such are the impressions we have<lb break="yes" />received in our earliest infancy; such is also the<lb break="yes"/>source of that astonishment which seizes us at<lb break="yes"/>the aspect of the tree just described. It is not<lb break="yes"/>here the solemn shades of forests, the majestic<lb break="yes"/>course of rivers, the mountains wrapped in eter-<lb break="no"/>nal frost, that excite our emotion. A few drops<lb break="yes" />of vegetable juice recall to our minds all the<lb break="yes"/>powerfulness and fecundity of nature. On the<lb break="yes"/>barren flank of rock grows a tree with coriaceous<lb break="yes"/>and dry leaves. Its large woody roots can<lb break="yes"/>scarcely penetrate into the stone. For several<lb break="yes"/>months of the year not a single shower moistens its<lb break="yes"/>foliage. Its branches appear dead and dried; but<lb break="yes" />when the trunk is pierced, there flows from it a<lb break="yes"/>sweet and nourishing milk. It is at the rising of<lb break="yes"/>the sun that this vegetable fountain is most abun-<lb break="no"/>dant. The Blacks and natives are then seen<lb break="yes"/>hastening from all quarters, furnished with large<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="28" facs="#f0003"/>bowls to receive the milk, which grows yellow,<lb break="yes"/>and thickens at its surface. Some employ their<lb break="yes" />bowls under the tree itself, others carry the juice<lb break="yes"/>home to their children. We seem to see the<lb break="yes"/>family of a shepherd, who distributes the milk of<lb break="yes"/>his flock.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;I have described the sensations which the<lb break="yes"/>cow-tree awakens in the mind of the traveller at<lb break="yes"/>the first view. In examining the physical pro-<lb break="no"/>perties of animal and vegetable products, science<lb break="yes"/>displays them as closely linked together: but it<lb break="yes"/>strips them of what is marvellous, and perhaps<lb break="yes" />also of a part of their charms, of what excited<lb break="yes"/>our astonishment. Nothing appears isolated;<lb break="yes"/>the chymical principles that were believed to be<lb break="yes"/>peculiar to animals are found in plants; a common<lb break="yes"/>chain links together all organic nature.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 