<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="509" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">A man giving suck.</hi>
                </head>
                <p>&#x2014;In the village<lb break="yes"/>of Arenas, @n the road from San Fer-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="510" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>nando to Cumana, lives a labourer,<lb break="yes"/>Francisco Lozano, who presented a<lb break="yes"/>physiological phenomenon, highly cal-<lb break="no" />culated to strike the imagination,<lb break="yes"/>though it is very conformable to the<lb break="yes"/>known laws of organized nature. This<lb break="yes"/>man has suckled a child with his own<lb break="yes"/>milk. The mother having fallen sick,<lb break="yes"/>the father, to quiet the infant, took it<lb break="yes"/>into his bed, and pressed it to his bo-<lb break="no" />som. Lozano, then thirty-two years of<lb break="yes"/>age, had never remarked till that day<lb break="yes"/>that he had milk: but the irritation of<lb break="yes"/>the nipple, sucked by the child, caused<lb break="yes"/>the accumulation of that liquid. The<lb break="yes"/>milk was thick and very sweet. The<lb break="yes"/>father, astonished at the increased size<lb break="yes" />of his breast, suckled his child two or<lb break="yes"/>three times a day during five months.<lb break="yes"/>He drew on himself the attention of his<lb break="yes"/>neighbours, but he never thought, as he<lb break="yes" />probably would in Europe, of deriving<lb break="yes"/>any advantage from the curiosity he<lb break="yes"/>excited. We saw the certificate which<lb break="yes"/>had been drawn up on the spot, to attest<lb break="yes"/>this remarkable fact, eye-witnesses of<lb break="yes"/>which are still living. They assured<lb break="yes"/>us, that, during this suckling, the child<lb break="yes"/>had no other nourishment than the milk<lb break="yes"/>of his father. Lozano, who was not at<lb break="yes"/>Arenas during our journey in the Mis-<lb break="no"/>sions, came to us at Cumana. He was<lb break="yes" />accompanied by his son, who was then<lb break="yes"/>thirteen or fourteen years of age. Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Bonpland examined with attention the<lb break="yes"/>father&#x2019;s breast, and found it wrinkled<lb break="yes" />like those of women who have given<lb break="yes"/>suck. He observed, that the left breast<lb break="yes"/>in particular was much enlarged;<lb break="yes" />which Lozano explained to us from the<lb break="yes"/>circumstance, that the two breasts did<lb break="yes"/>not furnish milk in the same abundance.<lb break="yes"/>Don Vicente Emparan, governor of the<lb break="yes"/>province, sent a circumstantial account<lb break="yes"/>of this phenomenon to Cadiz.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is not a very uncommon circum-<lb break="no"/>stance, to find, both among human-<lb break="no"/>kind and animals, males whose breasts<lb break="yes" />contain milk; and the climate does not<lb break="yes"/>appear to exert any marked influence<lb break="yes"/>on the more or less abundance of this<lb break="yes"/>secretion. The ancients cite the milk<lb break="yes"/>of the he goats of Lemnos and Corsica.<lb break="yes"/>In our own time, we have seen in the<lb break="yes"/>country of Hanover, a he goat, which<lb break="yes"/>for a great number of years was milked<lb break="yes"/>every other day, and yielded more<lb break="yes"/>milk than a female goat. Among the<lb break="yes" />signs of the pretended weakness of the<lb break="yes"/>Americans, travellers have mentioned<lb break="yes"/>the milk contained in the breasts of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>men. It is however improbable, that<lb break="yes"/>it has ever been observed in a whole<lb break="yes"/>tribe, in some part of America unknown<lb break="yes"/>to modern travellers; and I can affirm,<lb break="yes"/>that at present it is not more common<lb break="yes"/>in the new continent, than in the old.<lb break="yes"/>The labourer of Arenas, whose history<lb break="yes" />we have just related, is not of the cop-<lb break="no"/>per-coloured race of Chayma Indians:<lb break="yes"/>he is a white man, descended from Eu-<lb break="no"/>ropeans. Moreover, the anatomists of<lb break="yes"/>Petersburg have observed, that among<lb break="yes"/>the lower orders of the people in Rus-<lb break="no"/>sia, milk in the breasts of men is much<lb break="yes" />more freqnent than among the more<lb break="yes"/>southern nations; and the Russians<lb break="yes"/>have never been deemed weak and ef-<lb break="no" />feminate.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There exists among the varieties of<lb break="yes"/>our kind a race of men, whose breasts<lb break="yes"/>at the age of puberty acquire a consi-<lb break="no" />derable bulk. Lozano did not belong<lb break="yes"/>to this class; and he often repeated to<lb break="yes"/>us, that it was only the irritation of the<lb break="yes"/>nipple, in consequence of the suction,<lb break="yes"/>which caused the flow of the milk. This<lb break="yes"/>confirms the ohservation of the anci-<lb break="no"/>ents, &#x201C;that men, who have a small<lb break="yes" />quantity of milk, yield it in abundance,<lb break="yes"/>when their breasts are sucked.&#x201D; These<lb break="yes"/>singular effects of a nervous stimulant<lb break="yes"/>were known to the shepherds of<lb break="yes" />Greece; those of Mount Oeta rubbed<lb break="yes"/>the dugs of the young goats, that had<lb break="yes"/>not yet conceived, with nettles, to<lb break="yes"/>make them produce milk.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When we reflect on the whole of the<lb break="yes"/>vital phenomena, we find, that no one<lb break="yes"/>of them is entirely isolated. In every<lb break="yes"/>age examples are cited of young girls<lb break="yes"/>not marriageable, or women withered<lb break="yes"/>by age, who have suckled children.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Among men these examples are infi-<lb break="no"/>nitely more rare; and after numerous<lb break="yes"/>researches, I have not found above two<lb break="yes"/>or three. One is cited by the anato-<lb break="no"/>mist of Verona, Alexander Benedictus,<lb break="yes" />who lived toward the end of the fif-<lb break="no"/>teenth century. He relates the history<lb break="yes"/>of an inhabitant of Syria, who, to calm<lb break="yes"/>the uneasiness of his child, after the<lb break="yes"/>death of the mother, pressed it to his<lb break="yes"/>bosom. The milk immediately came<lb break="yes"/>with such abundance, that the father<lb break="yes" />could take on himself the nourishment<lb break="yes"/>of his child, without assistance. Other<lb break="yes"/>examples are related by Santorellus,<lb break="yes"/>Paria, and Robert, bishop of Cork.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>The greater part of these phenomena<lb break="yes"/>having been noticed in times very re-<lb break="no"/>mote, it is not uninteresting to physi-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="511" facs="#f0003"/>
                    <cb/>ology, that we can confirm them in our<lb break="yes"/>own days. Besides, they bear very<lb break="yes"/>strongly on the long disputed question<lb break="yes"/>respecting final causes. The existence<lb break="yes"/>of the nipple in men has long puzzled<lb break="yes"/>philosophers; and it has even been re-<lb break="no"/>cently affirmed, &#x201C;that nature has re-<lb break="no"/>fused to one of the sexes the faculty of<lb break="yes" />sucking, because this faculty would<lb break="yes"/>not accord with the dignity of man.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 