<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="327" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>MILK AND BUTTER TREES.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">We</hi> had heard several weeks before of a tree, the sap<lb break="yes"/>of which is a nourishing milk. It is called &#x201C;the cow<lb break="yes"/>tree,&#x201D; and we were assured that the negroes of the farm,<lb break="yes"/>who drink plentifully of this vegetable milk, consider<lb break="yes"/>it a wholesome aliment. All the milky juices of plants<lb break="yes"/>being acrid, bitter, and more or less poisonous, this<lb break="yes"/>account appeared to us very extraordinary; but we<lb break="yes"/>found by experience, during our stay at Barbula, that<lb break="yes"/>the virtues of this tree had not been exaggerated.<lb break="yes"/>This fine tree rises like the broad leaved star-apple.<lb break="yes"/>Its oblong and pointed leaves, rough and alternate, are<lb break="yes"/>marked by lateral ribs, prominent at the lower surface<lb break="yes"/>and parallel. Some of them are ten inches long. We<lb break="yes"/>did not see the flower: the fruit is somewhat fleshy,<lb break="yes"/>and contains one and sometimes two nuts. When in-<lb break="no" />cisions are made in the trunk of this tree, it yields<lb break="yes" />abundance of a glutinous milk, tolerably thick, devoid<lb break="yes"/>of all acridity, and of an agreeable and balmy smell.<lb break="yes"/>It was offered to <choice><sic>as</sic><corr type="editorial">us</corr></choice> in the shell of a calabash. We<lb break="yes"/>drank considerable quantities of it in the evening<lb break="yes"/>before we went to bed, and very early in the morning,<lb break="yes"/>without feeling the least injurious effect. The viscosity<lb break="yes"/>of this milk alone renders it a little disagreeable.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The negroes and the free people who work in the<lb break="yes"/>plantations drink it, dipping into it their bread of<lb break="yes"/>maize or cassava. The overseer of the farm told us<lb break="yes"/>that the negroes grow sensibly fatter during the season<lb break="yes"/>when the palo de vaca furnishes them with most milk.<lb break="yes"/>This juice, exposed to the air, presents at its surface<lb break="yes"/>(perhaps in consequence of the absorption of the<lb break="yes"/>atmospheric oxygen) membranes of a strongly animal-<lb break="no"/>ized substance, yellow, somewhat resembling cheese.<lb break="yes"/>These membranes, separated from the rest of the more<lb break="yes"/>aqueous liquid, are elastic, almost like caoutchouc;<lb break="yes"/>but they undergo, in time, the same phenomena of<lb break="yes" />putrefaction as gelatine. The people call the coagulum,<lb break="yes"/>that separates by the contact of the air, cheese. The<lb break="yes"/>coagulum grows sour in the space of five or six<lb break="yes"/>days.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Amidst the great number of curious phenomena<lb break="yes"/>which I have observed in the course of my travels, I<lb break="yes"/>confess there are few that have made so powerful<lb break="yes"/>an impression on me as the aspect of this tree. What-<lb break="no"/>ever relates to milk or to corn inspires an interest<lb break="yes"/>which is not merely that of the physical knowledge of<lb break="yes"/>things, but is connected with another order of ideas<lb break="yes"/>and sentiments. We can scarcely conceive how the<lb break="yes" />human race could exist without farinaceous substances,<lb break="yes"/>and without that nourishing juices which is appro-<lb break="no"/>priated to the long feebleness of the infant. The<lb break="yes"/>amylaceous matter of corn, the object of religious<lb break="yes"/>veneration among so many nations, ancient and mo-<lb break="no"/>dern, is diffused in the seeds, and deposited in the<lb break="yes"/>roots of vegetables; milk, which serves as an aliment,<lb break="yes"/>appears to us exclusively the produce of animal orga-<lb break="no"/>nization.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Such are the impressions we have received in our<lb break="yes"/>earliest infancy: such is also the source of that asto-<lb break="no"/>nishment created by the aspect of the tree just de-<lb break="no"/>scribed. It is not here the solemn shades of forests,<lb break="yes"/>the majestic course of rivers, the mountains wrapped<lb break="yes"/>in eternal snow, that excite our emotion. A few drops<lb break="yes"/>of vegetable juice recall to our minds all the powerful-<lb break="no"/>ness and the fecundity of nature. On the barren flank<lb break="yes"/>of a rock grows a tree with coriaceous and dry leaves.<lb break="yes"/>Its large woody roots can scarcely penetrate into the<lb break="yes"/>stone.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>For several months of the year not a single shower<lb break="yes"/>moistens its foliage. Its branches appear dead and<lb break="yes"/>dried; but when the trunk is pierced there flows from<lb break="yes"/>it a sweet and nourishing milk. It is at the rising of<lb break="yes"/>the sun that this vegetable fountain is most abundant;<lb break="yes"/>the negroes and natives are then seen hastening from<lb break="yes"/>all quarters, furnished with large bowls to receive the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>milk, which grows yellow, and thickens at its surface.<lb break="yes" />Some empty their bowls under the tree itself, others<lb break="yes"/>carry the juice home to their children.&#x2014;</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Humboldt.</hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 