<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Personal Narrative of Travels, &amp;c. by Alexander de Humboldt. (Translated by Helen Maria Williams)</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:52</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.47</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1818-Curious_Circumstance-06-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-06-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Genaue Textstelle aus dem "Personal Narrative" aus Zeitgründen noch nicht überprüft und präzisiert.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 1, S. 372–475. [Nur Anfang und Schluss gesucht – noch nicht kontrolliert, ob alles durchgehend oder fragmentarisch]</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Personal Narrative of Travels, &amp;c. by Alexander de Humboldt. (Translated by Helen Maria Williams)</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1819</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Annual Register, or a View of the History, Politics, and Literature, for the Year 1818&lt;/i&gt; 60 (1819), S. 438–464.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Fußnoten mit Asterisken und Kreuzen; Schmuck: Initialen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="438" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">personal narrative of tra-<lb break="no"/>vels, &amp;c. by alexander de<lb break="yes"/>humboldt.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">Translated by Helen Maria Wil-<lb break="no"/>liams).</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>HE road skirted with bam-<lb break="no"/>boos led us to the small vil-<lb break="no"/>lage of San Fernando, which is<lb break="yes" />situate in a narrow plain, sur-<lb break="no"/>rounded by very steep calca-<lb break="no"/>reous rocks. This was the first<lb break="yes"/>mission <note place="foot" n="*">A certain number of habitations<lb break="yes"/>collected round a church, a mis-<lb break="no"/>sionary monk performing the minis-<lb break="no"/>terial duties, is called in the Spanish<lb break="yes" />colonies <hi rendition="#i">Mision</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">Pueblo de mision.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>Indian villages, governed by a priest,<lb break="yes"/>are called <hi rendition="#i">Pueblos de doctrina.</hi> They<lb break="yes" />make a distinction between the <hi rendition="#i">Cura<lb break="yes" />doctrinero,</hi> who is the priest of an<lb break="yes"/>Indian parish, and the <hi rendition="#i">Cura rector,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>priest of a village inhabited by whites<lb break="yes"/>and men of mixed race.</note> we saw in America.<lb break="yes"/>The houses, or rather the huts of<lb break="yes"/>the Chayma Indians, separated<lb break="yes" />from each other, are not sur-<lb break="no"/>rounded by gardens. The streets,<lb break="yes"/>which are wide and very straight,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>cross each other at right angles.<lb break="yes"/>The walls, which are very thin<lb break="yes"/>and slight, are made of clay,<lb break="yes" />strengthened by lianas. The uni-<lb break="no"/>formity of this construction, the<lb break="yes"/>grave and taciturn air of the in-<lb break="no" />habitants, and the extreme neat-<lb break="no"/>ness that reigns throughout their<lb break="yes"/>habitations, reminded us of the<lb break="yes" />establishments of the Moravian<lb break="yes"/>brethren. Every Indian family<lb break="yes"/>cultivates, at some distance from<lb break="yes"/>the village, besides its own gar-<lb break="no"/>den, the <hi rendition="#i">conuco</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Conuco de la communidad.</hi>
                    </note> of the commu-<lb break="no"/>nity. In this the adults of each<lb break="yes"/>sect work one hour in the morn-<lb break="no"/>ing, and one in the evening. In<lb break="yes"/>the missions nearest the coast, the<lb break="yes"/>garden of the community is gene-<lb break="no"/>rally a sugar or indigo plantation,<lb break="yes"/>under the direction of the mis-<lb break="no"/>sionary; and the produce of<lb break="yes"/>which, were the law strictly ob-<lb break="no"/>served, can be employed only for<lb break="yes"/>the support of the church, and<lb break="yes"/>the purchase of the sacerdotal or-<lb break="no"/>naments. The great square of<lb break="yes"/>San Fernando, in the centre of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="439" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>the village, contains the church,<lb break="yes"/>the dwelling of the missionary,<lb break="yes"/>and that humble edifice, which is<lb break="yes" />pompously called the king&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>house&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Casa del Rey.</hi> This is a<lb break="yes"/>real caravanserai, destined to<lb break="yes"/>lodge travellers; and, as we often<lb break="yes" />experienced, infinitely valuable<lb break="yes"/>in a country, where the name of<lb break="yes"/>an inn is still unknown. The<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Casas del Rey</hi> are to be found in<lb break="yes"/>all the Spanish colonies, and may<lb break="yes"/>be deemed an imitation of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">tamboes</hi> of Peru, established ac-<lb break="no"/>cording to the laws of Manco<lb break="yes"/>Capac.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We had been recommended to<lb break="yes"/>the friars, who govern the Mis-<lb break="no"/>sions of the Chayma Indians, by<lb break="yes"/>their syndic, who resides at Cu-<lb break="no"/>mana. This recommendation was<lb break="yes" />so much the more useful to us,<lb break="yes"/>as the missionaries, either from<lb break="yes"/>zeal for the purity of the morals<lb break="yes"/>of their parishioners, or to con-<lb break="no"/>ceal the monastic system from<lb break="yes"/>the indiscreet curiosity of stran-<lb break="no"/>gers, often adhere with rigor to<lb break="yes"/>an old regulation, by which a<lb break="yes"/>white man of the secular state is<lb break="yes"/>not permitted to sojourn more<lb break="yes"/>than one night in an Indian vil-<lb break="no"/>lage. In order to travel agree-<lb break="no"/>ably in the Spanish Missions, it<lb break="yes"/>would be in general imprudent,<lb break="yes"/>to trust solely to a passport issued<lb break="yes"/>by the secretary of state&#x2019;s office<lb break="yes"/>at Madrid, or that of the civil<lb break="yes" />governors. A traveller must pro-<lb break="no"/>vide himself with recommenda-<lb break="no"/>tions from the ecclesiastical au-<lb break="no" />thorities, particularly from the<lb break="yes"/>guardians of the convents, or the<lb break="yes"/>generals of the orders, residing<lb break="yes"/>at Rome; who are infinitely more<lb break="yes"/>respected by the missionaries,<lb break="yes"/>than are the bishops. The Mis-<lb break="no"/>sions form, I will not say accord-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/>ing to their primitive and cano-<lb break="no"/>nical institutions, but in fact, a<lb break="yes"/>distinct and nearly independent<lb break="yes" />hierarchy, the views of which<lb break="yes"/>seldom accord with those of the<lb break="yes"/>secular clergy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The missionary of San Fer-<lb break="no"/>nando was a capuchin, a native<lb break="yes"/>of Arragon, far advanced in<lb break="yes"/>years, but strong and healthy.<lb break="yes"/>His extreme corpulency, his hi-<lb break="no" />larity, the interest he took in<lb break="yes"/>battles and sieges, ill accorded<lb break="yes"/>with the ideas we form in our<lb break="yes" />northern countries of the melan-<lb break="no"/>choly reveries, and the con-<lb break="no"/>templative life of missionaries.<lb break="yes"/>Though extremely busy about a<lb break="yes"/>cow, which was to be killed the<lb break="yes"/>next day, the old monk received<lb break="yes"/>us with kindness, and permitted<lb break="yes"/>us to hang up our hammocks in<lb break="yes"/>a gallery of his house. Seated,<lb break="yes"/>without doing any thing, the<lb break="yes"/>greater part of the day, in an arm<lb break="yes" />chair of red wood, he bitterly<lb break="yes"/>complained of what he called the<lb break="yes"/>indolence and ignorance of his<lb break="yes" />countrymen. He asked a thou-<lb break="no"/>sand questions on the real object<lb break="yes"/>of our journey, which appeared<lb break="yes"/>to him hazardous, and at all<lb break="yes"/>events useless. Here, as at Oro-<lb break="no"/>noko, we were fatigued by that<lb break="yes"/>restless curiosity, which the Eu-<lb break="no"/>ropeans preserve in the forests of<lb break="yes"/>America, respecting the wars and<lb break="yes"/>political convulsions of the Old<lb break="yes"/>World.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Our missionary, however, seem-<lb break="no"/>ed well satisfied with his situation.<lb break="yes"/>He treated the Indians with mild-<lb break="no" />ness; he beheld his mission pro-<lb break="no"/>sper, and he praised with enthu-<lb break="no"/>siasm the waters, the bananas,<lb break="yes"/>and the dairy produce of the<lb break="yes"/>canton. The sight of our instru-<lb break="no"/>ments, our books, and our dried<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">plants,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="440" facs="#f0003"/>
                    <cb/>plants, drew from him a sarcastic<lb break="yes"/>smile; and he acknowledged, with<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">naïveté</hi> peculiar to those cli-<lb break="no"/>mates, that of all the enjoyments<lb break="yes" />of life, without excepting sleep,<lb break="yes"/>none was comparable to the plea-<lb break="no"/>sure of eating good beef (<hi rendition="#i">carne de<lb break="yes"/>vacca</hi>); so true it is, that sensua-<lb break="no"/>lity obtains an ascendancy, where<lb break="yes"/>there is no occupation for the<lb break="yes"/>mind. Our host often engaged<lb break="yes" />us to pay a visit with him to his<lb break="yes"/>cow, which he had just purchased;<lb break="yes"/>and on the morrow, at sunrise, he<lb break="yes" />would not dispense with our see-<lb break="no"/>ing it killed after the fashion of<lb break="yes"/>the country, that is, by ham-<lb break="no" />stringing the animal, and then<lb break="yes"/>plunging a large knife into the<lb break="yes"/>vertebr&#x00E6; of the neck. This dis-<lb break="no"/>gusting operation served to show<lb break="yes"/>us the great address of the<lb break="yes"/>Chayma Indians, eight of whom,<lb break="yes"/>in less than twenty minutes, cut<lb break="yes"/>up the animal into small pieces.<lb break="yes"/>The price of the cow was only<lb break="yes"/>seven piastres; but this price<lb break="yes"/>seemed to be thought very con-<lb break="no" />siderable. The same day the<lb break="yes"/>missionary had paid eighteen<lb break="yes"/>piastres to a soldier of Cumana,<lb break="yes"/>for having succeeded, after many<lb break="yes"/>fruitless attempts, in bleeding him<lb break="yes"/>in the foot. This fact, though<lb break="yes"/>seemingly very unimportant, is a<lb break="yes"/>striking proof how greatly, in<lb break="yes" />uncultivated countries, the price<lb break="yes"/>of things differs from that of<lb break="yes"/>labour.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Mission of San Fernando<lb break="yes"/>was founded toward the end of<lb break="yes"/>the 17th century, near the junc-<lb break="no"/>tion of the small rivers of the<lb break="yes"/>Manzanarès and Lucasperez.<note place="foot" n="*">Caulin, Hist. corogr. de la Nueva<lb break="yes"/>Andalusia, p. 309.</note> A<lb break="yes"/>fire, which consumed the church,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>and the huts of the Indians,<lb break="yes"/>induced the capuchins to place<lb break="yes"/>the village in its present fine<lb break="yes" />situation. The number of families<lb break="yes"/>is increased to one hundred, and<lb break="yes"/>the missionary observed to us,<lb break="yes"/>that the custom of marrying as<lb break="yes"/>thirteen or fourteen years of age<lb break="yes"/>contributes greatly to this rapid<lb break="yes"/>increase of population. He denied<lb break="yes"/>that old age was so premature<lb break="yes"/>among the Chaymas, as is com-<lb break="no"/>monly believed in Europe. The<lb break="yes"/>government of these Indian<lb break="yes"/>parishes is very complicated;<lb break="yes"/>they have their governor, their<lb break="yes"/>major-alguazils, and their militia<lb break="yes"/>commanders, who are all copper-<lb break="no"/>coloured natives. The company<lb break="yes" />of archers have their colours, and<lb break="yes"/>perform their exercise with the<lb break="yes"/>bow and arrow, in shooting at a<lb break="yes"/>mark; this is the <hi rendition="#i">national guard</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>[militia] of the country. This<lb break="yes"/>military establishment, under a<lb break="yes"/>purely monastic system, seemed<lb break="yes"/>to us very singular.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In this village lives a labourer,<lb break="yes"/>Fran&#x00E7;isco Lozano, who presented<lb break="yes"/>a physiological phenomenon,<lb break="yes"/>highly calculated to strike the<lb break="yes"/>imagination, though it is very<lb break="yes"/>conformable to the known laws<lb break="yes"/>of organized nature. This man<lb break="yes"/>has suckled a child with his own<lb break="yes" />milk. The mother having fallen<lb break="yes"/>sick, the father, to quiet the<lb break="yes"/>infant, took it into his bed, and<lb break="yes" />pressed it to his bosom. Lozano,<lb break="yes"/>then thirty-two years of age, had<lb break="yes"/>never remarked till that day that<lb break="yes"/>he had milk: but the irritation of<lb break="yes"/>the nipple, sucked by the child,<lb break="yes"/>caused the accumulation of that<lb break="yes"/>liquid. The milk was thick and<lb break="yes"/>very sweet. The father, astonished<lb break="yes"/>at the increased size of his breast,<lb break="yes"/>suckled his child two or three<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">times</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="441" facs="#f0004"/>
                    <cb/>times a day during five months.<lb break="yes"/>He drew on himself the attention<lb break="yes"/>of his neighbours, but he never<lb break="yes" />thought, as he probably would<lb break="yes"/>have done in Europe, of deriving<lb break="yes"/>any advantage from the curiosity<lb break="yes"/>he excited. We saw the certifi-<lb break="no"/>cate, which had been drawn up<lb break="yes"/>on the spot, to attest this remark-<lb break="no"/>able fact, eye-witnesses of which<lb break="yes"/>are still living. They assured us,<lb break="yes"/>that, during this suckling, the<lb break="yes"/>child had no other nourishment<lb break="yes"/>than the milk of his father.<lb break="yes" />Lozano, who was not at Arenas<lb break="yes"/>during our journey in the Missions,<lb break="yes"/>came to us at Cumana. He was<lb break="yes" />accompanied by his son, who was<lb break="yes"/>then thirteen or fourteen years of<lb break="yes"/>age. Mr. Bonpland examined<lb break="yes"/>with attention the father&#x2019;s breast,<lb break="yes"/>and found it wrinkled like those<lb break="yes"/>of women who have given suck.<lb break="yes"/>He observed, that the left breast<lb break="yes"/>in particular was much enlarged;<lb break="yes"/>which Lozano explained to us<lb break="yes"/>from the circumstance, that the<lb break="yes"/>two breasts did not furnish milk<lb break="yes"/>in the same abundance. Don Vi-<lb break="no"/>cente Emparan, governor of the<lb break="yes"/>province, sent a circumstantial<lb break="yes" />account of this phenomenon to<lb break="yes"/>Cadiz.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is not a very uncommon<lb break="yes"/>circumstance, to find, both among<lb break="yes"/>humankind and animals,<note place="foot" n="*">Athanas. Joannides de Mam-<lb break="no"/>marum Struct. 1801, p. 6. Haller,<lb break="yes"/>Elem. Physiol, T. 7, P. II, page 18.</note> males<lb break="yes"/>whose breasts contain milk; and<lb break="yes"/>the climate does not appear to<lb break="yes"/>exert any marked influence on<lb break="yes" />the more of less abundance of<lb break="yes"/>this secretion. The ancients cite<lb break="yes"/>the milk of the he goats of<lb break="yes"/>Lemnos and Corsica. In our own<lb break="yes"/>time, we have seen in the country<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>of Hanover, a he goat, which for<lb break="yes"/>a great number of years was<lb break="yes"/>milked every other day, and<lb break="yes"/>yielded more milk than a female<lb break="yes"/>goat.<note place="foot" n="*">Blumenbach, Vergleich. Anat.<lb break="yes"/>1805, p. 504. Han&#x0153;vrisches Magaz.<lb break="yes"/>1787, page 753. Reil. Arch. der<lb break="yes"/>Physiol. T. 3, p. 449. Montegre,<lb break="yes"/>Gazette de Santé, 1812, p. 110.</note> Among the signs of the<lb break="yes"/>pretended weakness of the Ame-<lb break="no"/>ricans, travellers have mentioned<lb break="yes"/>the milk contained in the breasts<lb break="yes"/>of men.<note place="foot" n="†">It has even been seriously re-<lb break="no"/>lated, that in a part of Brazil it is the<lb break="yes"/>men, and not the women, that suckle<lb break="yes" />children. Clavigero, Storia di Mes-<lb break="no"/>sico. T. 4. 169.</note> It is however impro-<lb break="no"/>bable, that it has ever been ob-<lb break="no"/>served in a whole tribe, in some<lb break="yes"/>part of America unknown to<lb break="yes"/>modern travellers; and I can<lb break="yes"/>affirm, that at present it is not<lb break="yes"/>more common in the new con-<lb break="no"/>tinent, than in the old. The<lb break="yes"/>labourer of Arenas, whose history<lb break="yes"/>we have just related, is not of the<lb break="yes" />copper-coloured race of Chayma<lb break="yes"/>Indians: he is a white man, de-<lb break="no"/>scended from Europeans. More-<lb break="no"/>over, the anatomists of Peters-<lb break="no"/>burg<note place="foot" n="‡">Comment. Petrop. Tom. 3, p.<lb break="yes"/>278.</note> have observed, that among<lb break="yes"/>the lower orders of the people in<lb break="yes"/>Russia, milk in the breasts of men<lb break="yes"/>is much more frequent, than<lb break="yes" />among the more southern nations;<lb break="yes"/>and the Russians have never been<lb break="yes"/>deemed weak and effeminate.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There exists among the varie-<lb break="no"/>ties of our kind a race of men,<lb break="yes"/>whose breasts at the age of puberty<lb break="yes"/>acquire a considerable bulk. Lo-<lb break="no"/>zano did not belong to this class;<lb break="yes"/>and he often repeated to us, that<lb break="yes"/>it was only the irritation of the nip-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">ple,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="442" facs="#f0005"/>
                    <cb/>ple in consequence of the suction,<lb break="yes"/>which caused the flow of the milk.<lb break="yes"/>This confirms the observation of<lb break="yes"/>the ancients, &#x201C;that men, who<lb break="yes"/>have a small quantity of milk,<lb break="yes"/>yield it in abundance, when their<lb break="yes"/>breasts are sucked.&#x201D;<note place="foot" n="*">Arist. Hist. Anim. lib. 3, cap.<lb break="yes"/>20, ed. Duval, 1639, Tom. 2, p. 259.</note> These<lb break="yes"/>singular effects of a nervous<lb break="yes"/>stimulant were known to the<lb break="yes"/>shepherds of Greece; those of<lb break="yes"/>Mount Oeta rubbed the dugs of<lb break="yes"/>the young goats, that had not<lb break="yes"/>yet conceived, with nettles, to<lb break="yes"/>make them produce milk.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When we reflect on the whole<lb break="yes"/>of the vital phenomena, we find,<lb break="yes"/>that no one of them is entirely<lb break="yes"/>isolated. In every age examples<lb break="yes"/>are cited of young girls not<lb break="yes" />marriageable, or women withered<lb break="yes"/>by age, who have suckled chil-<lb break="no"/>dren. Among men these exam-<lb break="no"/>ples are infinitely more rare; and<lb break="yes"/>after numerous researches, I have<lb break="yes"/>not found above two or three.<lb break="yes"/>One is cited by the anatomist of<lb break="yes"/>Verona, Alexander Benedictus,<lb break="yes" />who lived toward the end of the<lb break="yes"/>fifteenth century. He relates the<lb break="yes"/>history of an inhabitant of Syria,<note place="foot" n="†">Maripetrus sacri ordinis eques-<lb break="no"/>tris tradidit, Syrum quemdam, cui<lb break="yes"/>filius infans, mortua conjuge, supe-<lb break="no"/>rerat, ubera s&#x00E6;pius admovisse, ut<lb break="yes"/>famem filii ragientis frustraret, con-<lb break="no"/>tinuatoque suctu lacte manasse pa-<lb break="no"/>pillam; quo exinde nutritus est,<lb break="yes" />magno totius urbis miraculo. Alex.<lb break="yes"/>Benedicti hum. Corp. Anatome, Bas.<lb break="yes"/>1549, lib. 3, cap. 4, p. 595. Barthol.<lb break="yes"/>Vindic. Anatom. 1648, p. 32.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>who, to calm the uneasiness of<lb break="yes"/>his child, after the death of the<lb break="yes"/>mother, pressed it to his bosom.<lb break="yes" />The milk immediately came with<lb break="yes"/>such abundance, that the father<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>could take on himself the nourish-<lb break="no"/>ment of his child, without as-<lb break="no"/>sistance. Other examples are<lb break="yes"/>related by Santorellus, Paris, and<lb break="yes"/>Robert, bishop of Cork.<note place="foot" n="*">Gabr. Rzaczynski, Hist. natur.<lb break="yes"/>Cur. Sandomir. 1721, p. 332, Misc.<lb break="yes"/>Acad. Nat. Cur. 1688, p. 219. Phil.<lb break="yes"/>Trans. 1741, p. 810.</note> The<lb break="yes" />greater part of these phenomena<lb break="yes"/>having been noticed in times very<lb break="yes"/>remote, it is not uninteresting to<lb break="yes" />physiology, that we can confirm<lb break="yes"/>them in our own days. Besides,<lb break="yes"/>they bear very strongly on the<lb break="yes"/>long disputed question respecting<lb break="yes"/>final causes. The existence of<lb break="yes"/>the nipple in men has long puzzled<lb break="yes" />philosophers; and it has even<lb break="yes"/>been recently affirmed, &#x201C;that<lb break="yes"/>nature has refused to one of the<lb break="yes"/>sexes the faculty of suckling,<lb break="yes"/>because this faculty would not<lb break="yes"/>accord with the dignity of<lb break="yes"/>man.&#x201D; <note place="foot" n="†">Comment. Petrop. Tom. 3, p.<lb break="yes"/>277.</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Our host had visited the new<lb break="yes"/>world with an expedition, which<lb break="yes"/>was to form establishments for<lb break="yes"/>cutting wood for the Spanish navy<lb break="yes"/>on the shores of the gulf of Paria.<lb break="yes"/>In these vast forests of mahogany,<lb break="yes"/>cedar, and brasil-wood, which<lb break="yes"/>border the sea of the West Indies,<lb break="yes"/>they reckoned on choosing the<lb break="yes"/>trunks of the largest trees, giving<lb break="yes"/>them in a rough way the shape<lb break="yes"/>adapted to the building of ships,<lb break="yes"/>and sending them every year to<lb break="yes"/>the dock-yard of the Caraccas,<lb break="yes" />near Cadiz. White men, unac-<lb break="no"/>customed to the climate, could<lb break="yes"/>not support the fatigue of labour,<lb break="yes"/>the heat, and the effect of the<lb break="yes"/>noxious air exhaled by the forests.<lb break="yes"/>The same winds that are loaded<lb break="yes"/>with the perfume of flowers,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">leaves,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="443" facs="#f0006"/>
                    <cb/>leaves, and woods, infuse also, as<lb break="yes"/>we may say, the germes of disso-<lb break="no"/>lution into the vital organs. De-<lb break="no" />structive fevers carried off not<lb break="yes"/>only the ship-carpenters, but the<lb break="yes"/>persons who had the management<lb break="yes"/>of the establishment: and this<lb break="yes"/>bay, which the first Spaniards<lb break="yes"/>named <hi rendition="#i">Golfo Tristo, Melancholy<lb break="yes"/>Bay,</hi> on account of the mournful<lb break="yes"/>and savage aspect of its coasts,<lb break="yes"/>became the grave of European<lb break="yes"/>seamen. Our host had the rare<lb break="yes"/>good fortune to escape these dan-<lb break="no"/>gers. After having witnessed the<lb break="yes"/>death of a great number of his<lb break="yes"/>friends, he withdrew far from the<lb break="yes"/>coasts to the mountains of Co-<lb break="no"/>collar. Without neighbours, the<lb break="yes"/>quiet possessor of five leagues of<lb break="yes"/>savannahs, he enjoyed at once<lb break="yes"/>that independence, which belongs<lb break="yes"/>to solitude, and that serenity of<lb break="yes"/>mind, which a pure and bracing<lb break="yes"/>air produces in men who live<lb break="yes"/>agreeably to the simplicity of<lb break="yes" />nature.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Nothing can be compared to<lb break="yes"/>the impression of majestic tran-<lb break="no"/>quillity, which the aspect of the<lb break="yes"/>firmament inspires in this solitary<lb break="yes"/>region. Following with the eye,<lb break="yes"/>at the entrance of the night, those<lb break="yes"/>meadows that bound the horizon,<lb break="yes"/>that plain covered with verdure,<lb break="yes"/>and gently undulated, we thought<lb break="yes"/>we saw from afar, as in the deserts<lb break="yes"/>of the Oronoko, the surface of the<lb break="yes"/>ocean supporting the starry vault<lb break="yes"/>of heaven. The tree under which<lb break="yes"/>we were seated, the luminous in-<lb break="no"/>sects flying in the air, the con-<lb break="no"/>stellations that shone toward the<lb break="yes"/>south; every object seemed to<lb break="yes"/>tell us, that we were far from our<lb break="yes"/>native soil. If amid this exotic<lb break="yes"/>nature the bell of a cow, or the<lb break="yes"/>roaring of a bull, were heard from<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>the depth of a valley, the remem-<lb break="no"/>brance of our country was awak-<lb break="no"/>ened suddenly in the sound. They<lb break="yes"/>were like distant voices resound-<lb break="no"/>ing from beyond the ocean, and<lb break="yes"/>with magical power transporting<lb break="yes"/>us from one hemisphere to the<lb break="yes"/>other. Strange mobility of the<lb break="yes" />imagination of man, eternal source<lb break="yes"/>of our enjoyments, and our pains!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We began in the cool of the<lb break="yes"/>morning to climb the Tumiriquiri.<lb break="yes"/>Thus is called the summit of the<lb break="yes"/>Cocollar, which, with the Brigan-<lb break="no"/>tine, forms one single mass of<lb break="yes"/>mountain, formerly called by the<lb break="yes"/>natives the <hi rendition="#i">Sierra de los Tigeres.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>We travelled along a part of the<lb break="yes"/>road on horses, which roam about<lb break="yes"/>these savannahs; but some of<lb break="yes"/>them are used to the saddle.<lb break="yes"/>Though their appearance is very<lb break="yes"/>heavy, they pass lightly over the<lb break="yes"/>most slippery turf. We first<lb break="yes"/>stopped at a spring, that issues<lb break="yes"/>not from the calcareous rock, but<lb break="yes"/>from a layer of quartzose sand-<lb break="no"/>stone.<note place="foot" n="*">Direction: hor. 4&#x00B7;3. Dip. 45&#x00B0;<lb break="yes" />south-east.</note> The temperature was 21&#x00B0;,<lb break="yes"/>consequently 1-5&#x00B0; less than the<lb break="yes"/>spring of Quetepe; hence the dif-<lb break="no"/>ference of the level is nearly 220<lb break="yes"/>toises. Wherever the sandstone<lb break="yes"/>appears above ground the soil is<lb break="yes"/>level, and constitutes as it were<lb break="yes"/>small platforms, which follow like<lb break="yes"/>steps. To the height of 700<lb break="yes"/>toises, and even beyond, this<lb break="yes"/>mountain, like those in its vicinity,<lb break="yes"/>is covered only with gramineous<lb break="yes"/>plants.<note place="foot" n="†">The most abundant species are<lb break="yes"/>the paspalus; the andropogon fasti-<lb break="no" />giatum, which forms the genus diec-<lb break="no"/>tomis of Mr. Palissot de Beauvois;<lb break="yes"/>and the panicum olyroides.</note> This failure of trees is<lb break="yes"/>attributed at Cumana to the great<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">elevation</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="444" facs="#f0007"/>
                    <cb/>elevation of the ground; but a<lb break="yes"/>slight reflection on the distribu-<lb break="no"/>tion of plants in the Cordilleras<lb break="yes" />of the torrid zone will lead us to<lb break="yes"/>conceive, that the summits of New<lb break="yes"/>Andalusia are very far from reach-<lb break="no"/>ing the superior limit of the trees,<lb break="yes"/>which in this latitude is at least<lb break="yes"/>1800 toises of absolute height.<lb break="yes"/>The smooth turf of the Cocollar<lb break="yes"/>begins to appear at 350 toises<lb break="yes"/>above the level of the sea, and the<lb break="yes"/>traveller may contrive to walk<lb break="yes"/>upon this turf, till he reaches a<lb break="yes"/>thousand toises of height. Far-<lb break="no"/>ther on, beyond this band covered<lb break="yes"/>with gramineous plants, we found,<lb break="yes"/>amidst peaks almost inaccessible<lb break="yes"/>to man, a small forest of cedrela,<lb break="yes"/>javillo,<note place="foot" n="*">Hura crepitans, of the family of<lb break="yes"/>the euphorbiums. The growth of its<lb break="yes"/>trunk is so enormous, that Mr. Bonp-<lb break="no" />land measured vats of javillo wood,<lb break="yes"/>14 feet long, and 8 wide. These vats,<lb break="yes"/>made out of one log of wood, are<lb break="yes"/>employed to keep the guarapo, or<lb break="yes"/>juice of the sugar-cane, and the me-<lb break="no"/>lasses. The seeds of javillo are a<lb break="yes"/>very active poison, and the milk that<lb break="yes" />issues from the petioles when broken<lb break="yes"/>frequently produced inflammation in<lb break="yes"/>our eyes, if by chance the least quan-<lb break="no"/>tity penetrated between the eyelids.</note> and mahogany. These<lb break="yes"/>local circumstances induce me to<lb break="yes" />think, that the mountainous sa-<lb break="no"/>vannahs of the Cocollar and Tu-<lb break="no"/>rimiquiri owe their existence only<lb break="yes"/>to the destructive custom the na-<lb break="no"/>tives have of setting fire to the<lb break="yes"/>woods, which they want to con-<lb break="no"/>vert into pasturage. Thus, where<lb break="yes"/>during three centuries grasses and<lb break="yes"/>alpine plants have covered the<lb break="yes"/>soil with a thick carpet, the seeds<lb break="yes"/>of trees can no longer germinate<lb break="yes"/>and fix themselves in the earth,<lb break="yes"/>though the birds and winds waft<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>them continually from the distant<lb break="yes"/>forests into the savannahs.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The climate of these mountains<lb break="yes"/>is so mild, that at the farm of Co-<lb break="no"/>collar the cotton and coffee-tree,<lb break="yes"/>and even the sugar-cane, are cul-<lb break="no"/>tivated with success. Whatever<lb break="yes"/>the inhabitants of the coasts may<lb break="yes"/>allege, hoar frost has never been<lb break="yes"/>found in the latitude of 10&#x00B0;, on<lb break="yes"/>heights scarcely exceeding those<lb break="yes"/>of the mount D&#x2019;Or, or the Puy de<lb break="yes"/>Dome. The pastures of Tumiri-<lb break="no" />quiri become less rich in propor-<lb break="no"/>tion to the elevation. Wherever<lb break="yes"/>scattered rocks afford shade, li-<lb break="no" />chens and some European mosses<lb break="yes"/>are found. The melastomah gua-<lb break="no"/>cito,<note place="foot" n="*">Melastoma xanthostachyum,<lb break="yes"/>called <hi rendition="#i">guacito</hi> at Caraccas.</note> and a shrub, the large and<lb break="yes"/>tough leaves of which rustle like<lb break="yes"/>parchment<note place="foot" n="†" >Paliscourea rigida, <hi rendition="#i">chaparro bovo.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>In the savannahs, or <hi rendition="#i">llanos,</hi> the same<lb break="yes"/>Castilian name is given to a tree of<lb break="yes" />the family of the proteace&#x00E6;.</note> when shaken by the<lb break="yes" />winds, rise here and there in the<lb break="yes"/>savannah. But the principal or-<lb break="no"/>nament of the turf of these moun-<lb break="no"/>tains is a liliaceous plant with<lb break="yes"/>golden flowers, the marica marti-<lb break="no"/>nicensis. It is generally observed<lb break="yes"/>in the province of Cumana, and<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas, only at four or five<lb break="yes"/>hundred toises of elevation.<note place="foot" n="‡">For example, in the Montanna<lb break="yes"/>de Avila, in the road from Caraccas<lb break="yes"/>to La Guayra, and in the Silla de<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas. The seeds of the marica<lb break="yes"/>are ripe at the end of December.</note> The<lb break="yes"/>whole rocky mass of the Turimi-<lb break="no"/>quiri is composed of an alpine<lb break="yes" />limestone, like that of Cumanacoa,<lb break="yes"/>and a pretty thin strata of marl<lb break="yes"/>and quartzose sandstone. The<lb break="yes"/>limestone contains masses of brown<lb break="yes"/>oxidated iron, and carbonat of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">iron.</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="445" facs="#f0008"/>
                    <cb/>iron. I have observed in several<lb break="yes"/>places, and very distinctly, that<lb break="yes"/>the sandstone not only reposes on<lb break="yes"/>the limestone, but that this last<lb break="yes"/>rock frequently includes and al-<lb break="no"/>ternates with the sandstone.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We distinguished clearly the<lb break="yes"/>round summit of the Turimiquiri,<lb break="yes"/>and the lofty peaks or <hi rendition="#i">Cucuruchos,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>covered with a thick vegetation,<lb break="yes"/>and inhabited by tigers, which are<lb break="yes"/>hunted on account of their size,<lb break="yes"/>and the beauty of their skin. This<lb break="yes"/>round summit, which is covered<lb break="yes"/>with turf, is 707 toises above the<lb break="yes"/>level of the ocean. A ridge of<lb break="yes"/>steep rocks stretches out toward<lb break="yes"/>the west, and is interrupted at the<lb break="yes"/>distance of a mile by an enormous<lb break="yes"/>crevice, that descends toward the<lb break="yes"/>gulf of Cariaco. At the point<lb break="yes" />where we might suppose the con-<lb break="no"/>tinuation of the ridge, two calca-<lb break="no"/>reous paps or peaks arise, the<lb break="yes" />northernmost of which is the most<lb break="yes"/>elevated. It is this last which is<lb break="yes"/>more particularly called the <hi rendition="#i">Cu-<lb break="no"/>curucho de Turimiquiri,</hi> and which<lb break="yes"/>is considered as higher than the<lb break="yes"/>mountain of the Brigantine,<note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn1-1" next="#fn1-2">This popular opinion on the<lb break="yes"/>height of the Brigantine favors the<lb break="yes" />supposition, that the distance from<lb break="yes"/>the port of Cumana to the mountain<lb break="yes"/>is much less than twenty-four nau-<lb break="no"/>tical miles. For we have seen already<lb break="yes"/>(vol. ii, p. 206), that the angles of<lb break="yes"/>elevation measured at Cumana give<lb break="yes"/>1255 toises for the height of the Bri-<lb break="no"/>gantine, if we admit the exactness of<lb break="yes"/>the distance indicated in the map of<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">Deposito hydrografico</hi> at Madrid.<lb break="yes"/>I find, that to make the observed<lb break="yes"/>angle agree with a supposed eleva-<lb break="no"/>tion of a thousand toises, the summit<lb break="yes"/>of the Brigantine cannot be more<lb break="yes"/>than nineteen miles distant from<lb break="yes"/>Cumana. The chain of the moun-<lb break="no"/>tains of New Andalusia is in the</note> so<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>well known by the sailors who<lb break="yes"/>frequent the coasts of Cumana.<lb break="yes"/>We measured by angles of ele-<lb break="no"/>vation, and a basis, rather short,<lb break="yes"/>traced on the round summit bare<lb break="yes"/>of trees, the peak, or <hi rendition="#i">Cucurucho,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>which was about 350 toises higher<lb break="yes"/>than our station, so that its abso-<lb break="no"/>lute height exceeded 1050 toises.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The view we enjoyed on the<lb break="yes"/>Turimiquiri is of vast extent, and<lb break="yes"/>highly picturesque. From the<lb break="yes"/>summit to the ocean we perceived<lb break="yes"/>chains of mountains extended in<lb break="yes"/>parallel lines from east to west,<lb break="yes"/>and bounding longitudinal valleys.<lb break="yes"/>These valleys are intersected at<lb break="yes"/>right angles by an infinite number<lb break="yes"/>of small ravines, scooped out by<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1">same direction as the neighbouring<lb break="yes"/>coast, nearly from east to west; and,<lb break="yes"/>admitting a distance more consi-<lb break="no"/>derable than nineteen miles, the Bri-<lb break="no"/>gantine would be more south than<lb break="yes"/>the parallel of Cocollar. But the in-<lb break="no" />habitants of Cumana wanted to lay<lb break="yes"/>out a road to Nueva Barcelona over<lb break="yes"/>the Brigantine, and I did not find the<lb break="yes"/>latitude of this town less than 10&#x00B0;<lb break="yes"/>6&#x2032; 52″. This circumstance confirms<lb break="yes"/>the result of a trigonometrical calcu-<lb break="no"/>lation made at the Salado de Cu-<lb break="no" />mana; while on the other side the<lb break="yes"/>magnetic bearing of the Brigantine,<lb break="yes"/>taken at the summit of the <hi rendition="#i">Impos-<lb break="no"/>sible,</hi> gives a greater distance. This<lb break="yes"/>bearing would be highly important,<lb break="yes"/>if we were perfectly certain of the<lb break="yes" />longitude of the <hi rendition="#i">Impossible,</hi> and of<lb break="yes" />the variation of the needle in a place,<lb break="yes"/>where the sandstone is strongly im-<lb break="no"/>pregnated with iron. It is the duty<lb break="yes"/>of the traveller, to declare with can-<lb break="no"/>dour the doubts he may still enter-<lb break="no"/>tain respecting points, the position<lb break="yes"/>of which is not yet sufficiently as-<lb break="no"/>certained. On making land on the<lb break="yes"/>coast of Cumana, the pilot reckoned<lb break="yes"/>the distance of the Tataraqual fifteen<lb break="yes"/>or sixteen miles.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="446" facs="#f0009"/>
                    <cb/>the torrents: the result of which<lb break="yes"/>is, that the lateral ranges are<lb break="yes"/>transformed into so many rows of<lb break="yes" />paps, some round, and others py-<lb break="no"/>ramidal. The ground in general<lb break="yes"/>is a gentle slope, as far as the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Impossible;</hi> farther on, the preci-<lb break="no"/>pices become bold, and continue<lb break="yes"/>so to the shore of the gulf of<lb break="yes"/>Cariaco. The form of this mass<lb break="yes"/>of mountains reminded us of the<lb break="yes"/>chain of the Jura; and the only<lb break="yes"/>plain, that presents itself, is the<lb break="yes"/>valley of Cumanacoa. We seemed<lb break="yes"/>to see the bottom of a funnel, in<lb break="yes"/>which we distinguished, amidst<lb break="yes"/>tufts of scattered trees, the Indian<lb break="yes"/>village of Aricagua. Toward the<lb break="yes"/>north, a narrow slip of land, the<lb break="yes"/>peninsula of Araya, formed a dark<lb break="yes"/>stripe on the sea, which, illumined<lb break="yes"/>by the rays of the sun, reflected<lb break="yes"/>a strong light. Beyond the pen-<lb break="no"/>insula the horizon was bounded by<lb break="yes"/>Cape Macanao, the black rocks<lb break="yes"/>of which rise amid the waters like<lb break="yes"/>an immense bastion.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>What gives most celebrity to<lb break="yes"/>the valley of Caripe, beside the<lb break="yes"/>extraordinary coolness of the cli-<lb break="no"/>mate, is the great <hi rendition="#i">Cueva,</hi> or cavern<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i">Guacharo.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">The province of Guacharucu,<lb break="yes"/>which Delgado visited in 1534, in<lb break="yes"/>the expedition of Hieronimo de Ortal,<lb break="yes"/>appears to have been situate south,<lb break="yes"/>or south-east from Macarapana. Has<lb break="yes"/>its name any connexion with those<lb break="yes"/>of the cavern and the bird? or is this<lb break="yes"/>last of Spanish origin? (Laet, Nov.<lb break="yes" />Orb., p. 676). Guacharo means in<lb break="yes"/>Castilian &#x201C;one who cries and la-<lb break="no"/>ments himself;&#x201D; now the bird of the<lb break="yes" />cavern of Caripe, and the guacharaca<lb break="yes"/>(phasianus parraka), are very noisy<lb break="yes"/>birds.</note> In a country<lb break="yes" />where the people love what is<lb break="yes"/>marvellous, a cavern that gives<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>birth to a river, and is inhabited<lb break="yes"/>by thousands of nocturnal birds,<lb break="yes"/>the fat of which is employed in<lb break="yes" />the Missions to dress food, is an<lb break="yes"/>everlasting object of conversation<lb break="yes"/>and discussion. Scarcely has a<lb break="yes" />stranger arrived at Cumana, when<lb break="yes"/>he is told of the stone of Araya<lb break="yes"/>for the eyes; of the labourer of<lb break="yes" />Arenas, who suckled his child;<lb break="yes"/>and of the cavern of Guacharo,<lb break="yes"/>which is said to be several leagues<lb break="yes" />in length; till he is tired of hear-<lb break="no"/>ing of them. A lively interest in<lb break="yes"/>the phenomena of nature is pre-<lb break="no" />served wherever society may be<lb break="yes"/>said to be without life; where, in<lb break="yes"/>dull monotony, it presents only<lb break="yes"/>simple relations little fitted to ex-<lb break="no"/>cite the ardour of curiosity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The cavern, which the natives<lb break="yes"/>call <hi rendition="#i">a mine of fat,</hi> is not in the<lb break="yes"/>valley of Caripe itself, but at three<lb break="yes"/>short leagues distance from the<lb break="yes" />convent, toward the west-south-<lb break="no"/>west. It opens into a lateral<lb break="yes"/>valley, which terminates at the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Sierra del Guacharo.</hi> We set out<lb break="yes"/>toward the Sierra on the 18th of<lb break="yes"/>September, accompanied by the<lb break="yes"/>Alcaids, or Indian magistrates,<lb break="yes"/>and the greater part of the monks<lb break="yes"/>of the Convent. A narrow path<lb break="yes" />led us at first during an hour and<lb break="yes"/>a half toward the south, across a<lb break="yes"/>fine plain, covered with a beautiful<lb break="yes" />turf. We then turned toward the<lb break="yes"/>west, along a small river, which,<lb break="yes"/>issues from the mouth of the<lb break="yes"/>cavern. We ascended during<lb break="yes"/>three quarters of an hour, walking<lb break="yes"/>sometimes in the water, which<lb break="yes"/>was shallow, sometimes between<lb break="yes"/>the torrent and a wall of rocks,<lb break="yes"/>on a soil extremely slippery and<lb break="yes"/>miry. The falling down of the<lb break="yes"/>earth, the scattered trunks of<lb break="yes"/>trees over which the mules could<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">scarcely</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="447" facs="#f0010"/>
                    <cb/>scarcely pass, the creeping plants<lb break="yes"/>that covered the ground, rendered<lb break="yes"/>this part of the road fatiguing.<lb break="yes" />We were surprised to find here,<lb break="yes"/>at scarcely 500 toises of elevation<lb break="yes"/>above the level of the sea, a cru-<lb break="no" />ciferous plant, raphanus pinnatus.<lb break="yes"/>It is well known how scarce the<lb break="yes"/>plants of this family are between<lb break="yes"/>the tropics; they display in some<lb break="yes"/>sort a northern form, and as such<lb break="yes"/>we never expected to see it on<lb break="yes"/>the plain of Caripe at so little an<lb break="yes"/>elevation. Those northern forms<lb break="yes"/>seem also to appear in the galium<lb break="yes" />caripense, the valeriana scandens,<lb break="yes"/>and a sanicle not unlike the s. ma-<lb break="no"/>rilandica.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the foot of the lofty moun-<lb break="no"/>tain of Guacharo, we were only<lb break="yes"/>four hundred steps from the ca-<lb break="no"/>vern, without yet perceiving the<lb break="yes"/>entrance. The torrent runs in a<lb break="yes"/>crevice, which has been hollowed<lb break="yes"/>out by the waters; and we went<lb break="yes"/>on under a cornice, the projection<lb break="yes"/>of which prevented us from see-<lb break="no"/>ing the sky. The path winds<lb break="yes"/>like the river: at the last turning<lb break="yes" />we came suddenly before the im-<lb break="no"/>mense opening of the grotto. The<lb break="yes"/>aspect of this spot is majestic<lb break="yes"/>even to the eye of a traveller<lb break="yes"/>accustomed to the picturesque<lb break="yes"/>scenes of the higher Alps. I had<lb break="yes"/>before this seen the caverns of<lb break="yes"/>the peak of Derbyshire, where,<lb break="yes"/>extended in a boat, we traversed<lb break="yes"/>a subterranean river, under a<lb break="yes"/>vault of two feet high. I had<lb break="yes" />visited the beautiful grotto of<lb break="yes"/>Treshemienshiz, in the Carpathian<lb break="yes"/>mountains, the caverns of the<lb break="yes" />Hartz, and those of Franconia,<lb break="yes"/>which are vast cemeteries <note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn2-1" next="#fn2-2">The mould, that has covered for<lb break="yes"/>thousands of years the soil of the</note> of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>bones of tigers, hyenas, and bears,<lb break="yes"/>as large as our horses. Nature<lb break="yes"/>in every zone follows immutable<lb break="yes" />laws in the distribution of rocks,<lb break="yes"/>in the exterior form of mountains,<lb break="yes"/>and even in those tumultuous<lb break="yes" />changes, which the exterior crust<lb break="yes"/>of our planet has undergone. So<lb break="yes"/>great a uniformity led me to be-<lb break="no"/>lieve, that the aspect of the cavern<lb break="yes"/>of Caripe would differ little from<lb break="yes"/>what I had observed in my pre-<lb break="no"/>ceding travels. The reality far<lb break="yes"/>exceeded my expectations. If<lb break="yes"/>the configuration of the grottoes,<lb break="yes"/>the splendor of the stalactites,<lb break="yes"/>and all the phenomena of inor-<lb break="no" />ganic nature, present striking ana-<lb break="no"/>logies, the majesty of equinoxial<lb break="yes"/>vegetation gives at the same time<lb break="yes" />an individual character to the<lb break="yes"/>aperture of the cavern.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Cueva del Guacharo is<lb break="yes"/>pierced in the vertical profile of a<lb break="yes"/>rock. The entrance is toward<lb break="yes"/>the south, and forms a vault eighty<lb break="yes"/>feet broad, and seventy-two feet<lb break="yes"/>high. This elevation is but a<lb break="yes"/>fifth less than that of the colon-<lb break="no"/>nade of the Louvre. The rock,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn2-2" prev="#fn2-1">caverns of Gaylenreuth and Muggen-<lb break="no"/>dorf in Franconia, emits even now<lb break="yes" />choke-damps, or gazeous mixtures<lb break="yes"/>of hydrogen and nitrogen, that rise<lb break="yes"/>to the roof of their caves. This fact<lb break="yes"/>is known to all those who show<lb break="yes"/>these caverns to travellers; and<lb break="yes"/>when I had the direction of the<lb break="yes"/>mines of the Fichtelberg, I observed<lb break="yes" />it frequently in the summer time.<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Laugier found in the mould of<lb break="yes"/>Muggendorf, beside phosphate of<lb break="yes" />lime, 0&#x00B7;10 of animal matter. (Cuvier,<lb break="yes"/>Recherches sur les Ossemens fossiles,<lb break="yes"/>T. 4. Ours, p. 14). I was struck,<lb break="yes"/>during my stay at Steeben, with the<lb break="yes" />ammoniacal and fetid smell produced<lb break="yes"/>by it, when projected on a red hot<lb break="yes"/>iron.</note>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">that</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="448" facs="#f0011"/>
                    <cb/>that surmounts the grotto, is co-<lb break="no"/>vered with trees of gigantic height.<lb break="yes"/>The mammee-tree, and the ge-<lb break="no" />nipa<note place="foot" n="*">Caruto, genipa americana. The<lb break="yes" />flower, at Caripe, has sometimes five,<lb break="yes"/>sometimes six stamens.</note> with large and shining<lb break="yes"/>leaves, raise their branches ver-<lb break="no"/>tically toward the sky; while<lb break="yes"/>those of the courbaril and the<lb break="yes"/>erythrina form, as they extend<lb break="yes"/>themselves, a thick vault of ver-<lb break="no"/>dure. Plants of the family of<lb break="yes"/>pothos with succulent stems, oxa-<lb break="no" />lises, and orchide&#x00E6; of a singular<lb break="yes"/>structure,<note place="foot" n="†">A dendrobium, with a golden<lb break="yes"/>flower, spotted with black, three<lb break="yes"/>inches long.</note> rise in the driest clefts<lb break="yes"/>of the rocks; while creeping<lb break="yes"/>plants, waving in the winds, are<lb break="yes"/>interwoven in festoons before the<lb break="yes"/>opening of the cavern. We dis-<lb break="no"/>tinguished in these festoons a<lb break="yes"/>bignonia of a violet blue, the<lb break="yes" />purple dolichos, and for the first<lb break="yes"/>time that magnificent solandra,<note place="foot" n="‡">Solandra scandens. It is the<lb break="yes"/>gousaticha of the Chayma Indians.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>the orange flower of which has a<lb break="yes"/>fleshy tube more than four inches<lb break="yes"/>long. The entrance of grottoes,<lb break="yes"/>like the view of cascades, derive<lb break="yes"/>their principal charm from the<lb break="yes"/>situation, more or less majestic,<lb break="yes"/>in which they are placed, and<lb break="yes"/>which in some sort determines the<lb break="yes"/>character of the landscape. What<lb break="yes"/>a contrast between the Cueva of<lb break="yes"/>Caripe, and those caverns of the<lb break="yes"/>north crowned with oaks and<lb break="yes"/>gloomy larch-trees!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But this luxury of vegetation<lb break="yes"/>embellishes not only the outside<lb break="yes"/>of the vault, it appears even in<lb break="yes"/>the vestibule of the grotto. We<lb break="yes"/>saw with astonishment plantain-<lb break="no" />leaved heliconias eighteen feet<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>high, the praga palm-tree, and<lb break="yes"/>arborescent arums, follow the<lb break="yes"/>banks of the river, even to those<lb break="yes" />subterranean places. The vege-<lb break="no"/>tation continues in the cave of<lb break="yes"/>Caripe, as in those deep crevices<lb break="yes"/>of the Andes, half excluded from<lb break="yes"/>the light of day; and does not<lb break="yes"/>disappear, till, advancing in the<lb break="yes"/>interior, we reach thirty or forty<lb break="yes"/>paces from the entrance. We<lb break="yes" />measured the way by means of a<lb break="yes"/>cord: and we went on about four<lb break="yes"/>hundred and thirty feet, without<lb break="yes"/>being obliged to light our torches.<lb break="yes"/>Daylight penetrates even into<lb break="yes"/>this region, because the grotto<lb break="yes"/>forms but one single channel,<lb break="yes"/>which keeps the same direction,<lb break="yes" />from south-east to north-west.<lb break="yes"/>Where the light begins to fail, we<lb break="yes"/>heard from afar the hoarse sounds<lb break="yes"/>of the nocturnal birds; sounds,<lb break="yes"/>which the natives think belong<lb break="yes"/>exclusively to those subterraneous<lb break="yes"/>places.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The guacharo is of the size of<lb break="yes"/>our fowls, has the mouth of the<lb break="yes"/>goatsuckers and procnias, and the<lb break="yes"/>port of those vultures, the crooked<lb break="yes"/>beak of which is surrounded with<lb break="yes"/>stiff silky hairs. Suppressing, with<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Cuvier, the order of pic&#x00E6;, we<lb break="yes"/>must refer this extraordinary bird<lb break="yes"/>to the passeres, the genera of<lb break="yes"/>which are connected with each<lb break="yes"/>other by almost imperceptible<lb break="yes"/>transitions. I have noted it under<lb break="yes"/>the name of steatornis, in a parti-<lb break="no"/>cular monography, contained in<lb break="yes"/>the second volume of my obser-<lb break="no"/>vations on Zoology and Compa-<lb break="no"/>rative Anatomy. It forms a new<lb break="yes" />genus,<note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn3-1" next="#fn3-2">Its essential characters are:<lb break="yes"/>rostrum validum, lateribus compres-<lb break="no"/>sum, apice aduncum, mandibula, su-</note> very different from the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">goat-sucker</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="449" facs="#f0012"/>
                    <cb/>goat-sucker by the force of its<lb break="yes"/>voice, by the considerable strength<lb break="yes"/>of its beak, containing a double<lb break="yes" />tooth, by its feet without the<lb break="yes"/>membranes that unite the anterior<lb break="yes"/>phalanxes of the claws. It is the<lb break="yes" />first example of a nocturnal bird<lb break="yes"/>among the <hi rendition="#i" >passeres dentirostrati.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>In its manners it has analogies<lb break="yes"/>both with the goat-suckers and<lb break="yes"/>the alpine crow.<note place="foot" n="*">Corvus pyrrhocorax.</note> The plumage<lb break="yes"/>of the guacharo is of a dark<lb break="yes"/>bluish gray, mixed with small<lb break="yes"/>streaks and specks of black. Large<lb break="yes"/>white spots, which have the form<lb break="yes"/>of a heart, and which are bor-<lb break="no"/>dered with black, mark the head,<lb break="yes"/>the wings, and the tail. The eyes<lb break="yes" />of the bird are hurt by the blaze<lb break="yes"/>of day; they are blue, and smaller<lb break="yes"/>than those of the goat-suckers.<lb break="yes"/>The spread of the wings, which<lb break="yes"/>are composed of seventeen or<lb break="yes"/>eighteen quill feathers, is three<lb break="yes"/>feet and a half. The guacharo<lb break="yes"/>quits the cavern at night-fall,<lb break="yes"/>especially when the moon shines,<lb break="yes"/>It is almost the only frugiferous<lb break="yes"/>nocturnal bird, that is yet known;<lb break="yes"/>the conformation of its feet suffi-<lb break="no"/>ciently shows, that it does not<lb break="yes"/>hunt like our owls. It feeds on<lb break="yes"/>very hard fruits; as the nut-<lb break="no"/>cracker <note place="foot" n="†">Corvus caryocatactes, c. glan-<lb break="no"/>darius. Our alpine crow builds its<lb break="yes"/>nest, toward the top of Mount Liba-<lb break="no"/>nus, in subterranean caverns, nearly<lb break="yes" />like the guacharo; the horribly shrill<lb break="yes"/>voice of which it also has. (Labilla-<lb break="no"/>dière, Ann. du Musée, T. 18, p. 455).</note> and the pyrrhocorax.<lb break="yes"/>The latter nestles also in clefts of<lb break="yes"/>rocks, and is known under the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn3-2" prev="#fn3-1">periori subbidentata, dente anteriori<lb break="yes"/>acutiori. Rictus amplissimus. Pedes<lb break="yes"/>breves, digitis fissis, unguibus inte-<lb break="no" />gerrimis.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>name of <hi rendition="#i">night-crow.</hi> The Indians<lb break="yes" />assured us, that the guacharo<lb break="yes"/>does not pursue either the lamel-<lb break="no"/>licornous insects, or those pha-<lb break="no"/>l&#x00E6;n&#x00E6; which serve as food to the<lb break="yes"/>goat-suckers. It is sufficient to<lb break="yes"/>compare the beaks of the guacharo<lb break="yes"/>and goat-sucker, to conjecture<lb break="yes"/>how much their manners must<lb break="yes"/>differ. It is difficult to form an<lb break="yes"/>idea of the horrible noise occa-<lb break="no"/>sioned by thousands of these<lb break="yes" />birds in the dark part of the<lb break="yes"/>cavern, and which can only be<lb break="yes"/>compared to the croaking of our<lb break="yes"/>crows, which, in the pine forests<lb break="yes"/>of the north, live in society, and<lb break="yes"/>construct their nests upon trees,<lb break="yes"/>the tops of which touch each<lb break="yes"/>other. The shrill and piercing<lb break="yes" />cries of the guacharoes strike<lb break="yes"/>upon the vaults of the rocks, and<lb break="yes"/>are repeated by the echo in the<lb break="yes"/>depth of the cavern. The In-<lb break="no"/>dians showed us the nests of these<lb break="yes"/>birds, by fixing torches to the<lb break="yes"/>end of a long pole. These nests<lb break="yes"/>were fifty or sixty feet high above<lb break="yes"/>our heads, in holes in the shape<lb break="yes"/>of funnels, with which the roof<lb break="yes"/>of the grotto is pierced like a<lb break="yes"/>sieve. The noise increased as we<lb break="yes"/>advanced, and the birds were<lb break="yes"/>affrighted by the light of the<lb break="yes" />torches of copal. When this noise<lb break="yes"/>ceased a few minutes around us,<lb break="yes"/>we heard at a distance the plain-<lb break="no"/>tive cries of the birds roosting in<lb break="yes"/>other ramifications of the cavern.<lb break="yes"/>It seemed as if these bands an-<lb break="no" />swered each other alternately.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Indians enter into the<lb break="yes"/>Cueva del Guacharo once a year,<lb break="yes"/>near midsummer, armed with<lb break="yes"/>poles, by means of which they<lb break="yes"/>destroy the greater part of the<lb break="yes" />nests. At this season several<lb break="yes"/>thousands of birds are killed; and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="450" facs="#f0013"/>
                    <cb/>the old ones, as if to defend their<lb break="yes"/>brood, hover over the heads of<lb break="yes"/>the Indians, uttering terrible cries.<lb break="yes" />The young,<note place="foot" n="*">Los pollos del Guacharo.</note> which fall to the<lb break="yes"/>ground, are opened on the spot.<lb break="yes"/>Their peritoneum is extremely<lb break="yes"/>loaded with fat, and a layer of<lb break="yes"/>fat reaches from the abdomen to<lb break="yes"/>the anus, forming a kind of cushion<lb break="yes"/>between the legs of the bird. This<lb break="yes"/>quantity of fat in frugivorous ani-<lb break="no"/>mals, not exposed to the light,<lb break="yes"/>and exerting very little muscular<lb break="yes"/>motion, reminds us of what has<lb break="yes"/>been long since observed in the<lb break="yes"/>fattening of geese and oxen. It<lb break="yes" />is well known how favourable<lb break="yes"/>darkness and repose are to this<lb break="yes"/>process. The nocturnal birds of<lb break="yes"/>Europe are lean, because, instead<lb break="yes"/>of feeding on fruits, like the gua-<lb break="no"/>charo, they live on the scanty<lb break="yes"/>produce of their prey. At the<lb break="yes"/>period which is commonly called<lb break="yes"/>at Caripe <hi rendition="#i">the oil harvest,</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="†">La cosecha de la manteca.</note> the<lb break="yes" />Indians build huts with palm<lb break="yes"/>leaves, near the entrance, and<lb break="yes"/>even in the porch of the cavern.<lb break="yes"/>Of these we still saw some remains.<lb break="yes"/>There, with a fire of brush-wood,<lb break="yes"/>they melt in pots of clay the fat<lb break="yes"/>of the young birds just killed.<lb break="yes"/>This fat is known by the name of<lb break="yes"/>butter or oil <hi rendition="#i">(manteca</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">aceite)</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>of the guacharo. It is half liquid,<lb break="yes"/>transparent without smell, and so<lb break="yes"/>pure that it may be kept above a<lb break="yes"/>year without becoming rancid.<lb break="yes"/>At the convent of Caripe no other<lb break="yes"/>oil is used in the kitchen of the<lb break="yes" />monks but that of the cavern;<lb break="yes"/>and we never observed, that it<lb break="yes"/>gave the aliments a disagreeable<lb break="yes"/>taste or smell.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The quantity of this oil col-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/>lected little corresponds with the<lb break="yes"/>carnage made every year in the<lb break="yes"/>grotto by the Indians. It appears,<lb break="yes"/>that they do not get above 150 or<lb break="yes"/>160 bottles <note place="foot" n="*">Sixty cubic inches each.</note> of very pure <hi rendition="#i" >man-<lb break="no"/>teca;</hi> the rest, less transparent, is<lb break="yes"/>preserved in large earthen vessels.<lb break="yes"/>This branch of industry reminds<lb break="yes"/>us of the harvest of pigeons&#x2019; oil,<note place="foot" n="†">This <hi rendition="#i">pigeon oil</hi> comes from the<lb break="yes"/>columba migratoria (Pennant&#x2019;s Arctic<lb break="yes" />Zoology, T. 2, p. 13).</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>of which some thousands of barrels<lb break="yes"/>were formerly collected in Caro-<lb break="no"/>lina. At Caripe, the use of the<lb break="yes"/>oil of guacharoes is very ancient,<lb break="yes"/>and the missionaries have only re-<lb break="no"/>gulated the method of extracting<lb break="yes"/>it. The members of an Indian<lb break="yes"/>family, which bears the name of<lb break="yes"/>Morocoymas, pretend, as descend-<lb break="no" />ants of the first colonists of the<lb break="yes"/>valley, to be the lawful proprietors<lb break="yes"/>of the cavern, and arrogate to<lb break="yes" />themselves the monopoly of the<lb break="yes"/>fat; but, thanks to the monastic<lb break="yes"/>institutions, their rights at present<lb break="yes"/>are merely honorary. In confor-<lb break="no"/>mity to the system of the mis-<lb break="no"/>sionaries, the Indians are obliged<lb break="yes"/>to furnish guacharo-oil for the<lb break="yes"/>church lamp: the rest, we were<lb break="yes"/>assured, is purchased of them.<lb break="yes" />We shall not decide either on the<lb break="yes"/>legitimacy of the rights of the<lb break="yes"/>Morocoymas, or on the origin of<lb break="yes"/>the obligation imposed on the<lb break="yes"/>natives by the monks. It would<lb break="yes"/>seem natural, that the produce of<lb break="yes"/>the chace should belong to those<lb break="yes"/>who hunt: but in the forests of<lb break="yes"/>the New World, as in the centre<lb break="yes"/>of European cultivation, public<lb break="yes"/>right is modified according to<lb break="yes"/>the relations, which are esta-<lb break="no"/>blished between the strong and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="451" facs="#f0014"/>
                    <cb/>the weak, the victors and the van-<lb break="no"/>quished.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The race of the guacharoes<lb break="yes"/>would have been long ago extinct,<lb break="yes"/>had not several circumstances<lb break="yes"/>contributed to its preservation.<lb break="yes"/>The natives, restrained by their<lb break="yes"/>superstitious ideas, have seldom<lb break="yes"/>the courage to penetrate far into<lb break="yes"/>the grotto. It appears also, that<lb break="yes"/>birds of the same species dwell<lb break="yes"/>in neighbouring caverns, which<lb break="yes"/>are too narrow to be accessible to<lb break="yes" />man. Perhaps the great cavern<lb break="yes"/>is repeopled by colonies, that<lb break="yes"/>abandon the small grottoes; for<lb break="yes"/>the missionaries assured us, that<lb break="yes"/>hitherto no sensible diminution of<lb break="yes"/>the birds had been observed.<lb break="yes"/>Young guacharoes have been sent<lb break="yes"/>to the port of Cumana, and have<lb break="yes"/>lived there several days without<lb break="yes"/>taking any nourishment; the seeds<lb break="yes"/>offered to them not suiting their<lb break="yes"/>taste. When the crops and giz-<lb break="no"/>zards of the young birds are<lb break="yes"/>opened in the cavern, they are<lb break="yes" />found to contain all sorts of hard<lb break="yes"/>and dry fruits, which furnish,<lb break="yes"/>under the singular name of gua-<lb break="no" />charo seed, <hi rendition="#i">semilla del guacharo,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>a very celebrated remedy against<lb break="yes"/>intermittent fevers. The old birds<lb break="yes"/>carry these seeds to their young.<lb break="yes"/>They are carefully collected, and<lb break="yes"/>sent to the sick at Cariaco, and<lb break="yes"/>other places of the low regions,<lb break="yes"/>where fevers are prevalent.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We followed, as we continued<lb break="yes"/>our progress through the cavern,<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the small river, which<lb break="yes"/>issued from it, and is from twenty-<lb break="no"/>eight to thirty feet wide. We<lb break="yes"/>walked on the banks, as far as the<lb break="yes"/>hills formed of calcareous incrust-<lb break="no"/>ations permitted us. When the<lb break="yes"/>torrent winds among very high<lb break="yes"/>masses of stalactites, we were<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>often obliged to descend into its<lb break="yes"/>bed, which is only two feet in<lb break="yes"/>depth. We learnt, with surprise,<lb break="yes"/>that this subterraneous rivulet is<lb break="yes"/>the origin of the river Caripe,<lb break="yes"/>which, at a few leagues distance,<lb break="yes"/>after having joined the small river<lb break="yes"/>of Santa Maria, is navigable for<lb break="yes"/>canoes. It enters into the river<lb break="yes"/>Areo under the name of <hi rendition="#i">Canno de<lb break="yes"/>Terezen.</hi> We found on the banks<lb break="yes"/>of the subterraneous rivulet a<lb break="yes"/>great quantity of palm-tree wood,<lb break="yes"/>the remains of trunks, on which<lb break="yes"/>the Indians climb to reach the<lb break="yes"/>nests hanging to the roofs of the<lb break="yes"/>cavern. The rings, formed by the<lb break="yes" />vestiges of the old footstalks of<lb break="yes"/>the leaves, furnish as it were the<lb break="yes"/>footsteps of a ladder perpendicu-<lb break="no"/>larly placed.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Grotto of Caripe preserves<lb break="yes"/>the same direction, the same<lb break="yes"/>breadth, and its primitive height<lb break="yes"/>of sixty or seventy feet, to the<lb break="yes"/>distance of 472 metres, or 1458<lb break="yes"/>feet, accurately measured. I have<lb break="yes"/>never seen a cavern, in either<lb break="yes"/>continent, of so uniform and re-<lb break="no" />gular a construction. We had<lb break="yes"/>great difficulty in persuading the<lb break="yes"/>Indians to pass beyond the outer<lb break="yes"/>part of the grotto, the only part<lb break="yes"/>which they annually visit to collect<lb break="yes"/>the fat. The whole authority of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">los padres</hi> was necessary, to induce<lb break="yes"/>them to advance as far as the<lb break="yes"/>spot, where the soil rises abruptly<lb break="yes"/>at an inclination of sixty degrees,<lb break="yes"/>and where the torrent forms a<lb break="yes"/>small subterraneous cascade.<note place="foot" n="*">We find this phenomenon of a<lb break="yes"/>subterranean cascade, but on a much<lb break="yes"/>larger scale, in England at Yordas<lb break="yes"/>Cave, near Kingsdale, in Yorkshire.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>The natives connect mystic ideas<lb break="yes"/>with this cave, inhabited by noc-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">turnal</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="452" facs="#f0015"/>
                    <cb/>turnal birds; they believe, that<lb break="yes"/>the souls of their ancestors sojourn<lb break="yes"/>in the deep recesses of the cavern.<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Man,&#x201D; say they, &#x201C;should avoid<lb break="yes"/>places which are enlightened nei-<lb break="no"/>ther by the Sun <hi rendition="#i">(Zis),</hi> nor by the<lb break="yes"/>Moon <hi rendition="#i">(Nuna).</hi>&#x201D; To go and join<lb break="yes"/>the guacharoes, is to rejoin their<lb break="yes" />fathers, is to die. The magicians<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">(piaches)</hi> and the poisoners <hi rendition="#i">(imo-<lb break="no"/>rons)</hi> perform their nocturnal<lb break="yes"/>tricks at the entrance of the<lb break="yes"/>cavern, to conjure the chief of<lb break="yes"/>the evil spirits <hi rendition="#i">(ivorokiamo).</hi> Thus<lb break="yes"/>in every climate the first fictions<lb break="yes"/>of nations resemble each other,<lb break="yes"/>those especially which relate to<lb break="yes"/>two principles governing the<lb break="yes"/>world, the abode of souls after<lb break="yes"/>death, the happiness of the vir-<lb break="no" />tuous, and the punishment of the<lb break="yes"/>guilty. The most different and<lb break="yes"/>most barbarous languages present<lb break="yes"/>a certain number of images, which<lb break="yes"/>are the same, because they have<lb break="yes"/>their source in the nature of our<lb break="yes" />intellect and our sensations. Dark-<lb break="no"/>ness is every where connected<lb break="yes"/>with the idea of death. The<lb break="yes"/>Grotto of Caripe is the Tartarus<lb break="yes"/>of the Greeks; and the guacha-<lb break="no"/>roes, which hover over the rivu-<lb break="no"/>let, uttering plaintive cries, re-<lb break="no"/>mind us of the Stygian birds.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the point where the river<lb break="yes"/>forms the subterraneous cascade,<lb break="yes"/>a bill covered with vegetation,<lb break="yes"/>which is opposite the opening of<lb break="yes"/>the grotto, presents itself in a very<lb break="yes"/>picturesque manner. It appears<lb break="yes"/>at the extremity of a straight pas-<lb break="no"/>sage, 240 toises in length. The<lb break="yes" />stalactites, which descend from<lb break="yes"/>the vault, and which resemble<lb break="yes"/>columns suspended in the air,<lb break="yes" />display themselves on a back-<lb break="no"/>ground of verdure. The opening<lb break="yes"/>of the cavern appeared singularly<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>contracted, when we saw it about<lb break="yes"/>the middle of the day, illumined<lb break="yes"/>by the vivid light reflected at once<lb break="yes"/>from the sky, the plants, and the<lb break="yes"/>rocks. The distant light of day<lb break="yes"/>formed somewhat of magical con-<lb break="no"/>trast with the darkness, that sur-<lb break="no"/>rounded us in those vast caverns.<lb break="yes"/>We discharged our pieces at a<lb break="yes" />venture, wherever the cries of the<lb break="yes"/>nocturnal birds, and the flapping<lb break="yes"/>of their wings, led us to suspect,<lb break="yes" />that a great number of nests were<lb break="yes"/>crowded together. After several<lb break="yes"/>fruitless attempts, Mr. Bonpland<lb break="yes" />succeeded in killing a couple of<lb break="yes"/>guacharoes, which, dazzled by<lb break="yes"/>the light of the torches, seemed<lb break="yes"/>to pursue us. This circumstance<lb break="yes"/>afforded me the means of drawing<lb break="yes"/>this bird, which hitherto had re-<lb break="no"/>mained unknown to naturalists.<lb break="yes"/>We climbed, not without some<lb break="yes" />difficulty, the small hill whence<lb break="yes"/>the subterraneous rivulet descends.<lb break="yes"/>We saw, that the grotto was per-<lb break="no" />ceptibly contracted, retaining only<lb break="yes"/>forty feet in height; and that it<lb break="yes"/>continued stretching to the north-<lb break="no"/>east, without deviating from its<lb break="yes"/>primitive direction, which is pa-<lb break="no"/>rallel to that of the great valley<lb break="yes"/>of Caripe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In this part of the cavern, the<lb break="yes"/>rivulet deposes a blackish mould,<lb break="yes"/>very like the matter, which in the<lb break="yes" />grotto of Muggendorf, in Fran-<lb break="no"/>conia, is called the <hi rendition="#i">earth of sacri-<lb break="no"/>fice.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Opfer-erde</hi> of the cavern of <hi rendition="#i" >Hole<lb break="yes"/>Berg</hi> (mountain pierced entirely<lb break="yes"/>through).</note> We could not discover,<lb break="yes" />whether this fine and spongy<lb break="yes"/>mould fall through the cracks,<lb break="yes"/>which communicate with the sur-<lb break="no"/>face of the ground above; or be<lb break="yes"/>washed down by the rainwater,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">that</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="453" facs="#f0016"/>
                    <cb/>that penetrates into the cavern.<lb break="yes"/>It was a mixture of silex, alumin,<lb break="yes"/>and vegetable <hi rendition="#i">detritus.</hi> We walked<lb break="yes"/>in thick mud to a spot, where we<lb break="yes" />beheld with astonishment the pro-<lb break="no"/>gress of subterraneous vegetation.<lb break="yes"/>The seeds, which the birds carry<lb break="yes" />into the grotto to feed their young,<lb break="yes"/>spring up wherever they can fix<lb break="yes"/>in the mould, that covers the cal-<lb break="no" />careous incrustations. Blanched<lb break="yes"/>stalks, with some half formed<lb break="yes"/>leaves, had risen to the height of<lb break="yes" />two feet. It was impossible to<lb break="yes"/>ascertain the species of plants,<lb break="yes"/>the form, colour, and aspect of<lb break="yes" />which had been changed by the<lb break="yes"/>absence of light. Those traces of<lb break="yes"/>organization amid darkness for-<lb break="no"/>cibly excited the curiosity of the<lb break="yes"/>natives, in general so stupid, and<lb break="yes"/>difficult to be moved. They ex-<lb break="no"/>amined them in that silent medi-<lb break="no"/>tation inspired by a place they<lb break="yes"/>seemed to dread. It might be<lb break="yes"/>thought, that these subterraneous<lb break="yes"/>vegetables, pale and disfigured,<lb break="yes"/>appeared to them phantoms ba-<lb break="no"/>nished from the face of the earth.<lb break="yes"/>To me the scene recalled one of<lb break="yes"/>the happiest periods of my early<lb break="yes"/>youth, a long abode in the mines<lb break="yes"/>of Freiberg, where I made expe-<lb break="no" />riments on the effects of blanch-<lb break="no"/>ing <hi rendition="#i" >(étiolement),</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">Humboldt, Aphorismi ex Phy-<lb break="no"/>siologia chemica Plantarum (Flora<lb break="yes"/>Friberg, subterranea, p. 181).</note> which are very<lb break="yes"/>different, according as the air is<lb break="yes"/>pure, or overcharged with hydro-<lb break="no"/>gen or azot.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The missionaries, with all their<lb break="yes"/>authority, could not prevail on<lb break="yes"/>the Indians to penetrate farther<lb break="yes"/>into the cavern. As the vault<lb break="yes"/>grew lower, the cries of the gua-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/>charoes became more shrill. We<lb break="yes"/>were obliged to yield to the pusil-<lb break="no"/>lanimity of our guides, and trace<lb break="yes"/>back our steps. The appearance<lb break="yes"/>of the cavern was indeed very<lb break="yes"/>uniform. We find, that a bishop<lb break="yes"/>of St. Thomas of Guiana had<lb break="yes"/>gone farther than ourselves. He<lb break="yes" />had measured nearly 2500 feet <note place="foot" n="*">960 <hi rendition="#i" >varas.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>from the mouth to the spot where<lb break="yes"/>he stopped, though the cavern<lb break="yes"/>reached farther. The remem-<lb break="no" />brance of this fact was preserved<lb break="yes"/>in the convent of Caripe, without<lb break="yes"/>the exact period being noted.<lb break="yes"/>The bishop had provided himself<lb break="yes"/>with great torches of white wax<lb break="yes"/>of Castille. We had torches com-<lb break="no"/>posed only of the bark of trees,<lb break="yes"/>and native resin. The thick smoke<lb break="yes"/>which issued from these torches,<lb break="yes"/>in a narrow subterranean passage,<lb break="yes"/>hurts the eyes, and obstructs the<lb break="yes"/>respiration.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We followed the course of the<lb break="yes"/>torrent to go out of the cavern.<lb break="yes"/>Before our eyes were dazzled with<lb break="yes"/>the light of day, we saw, without<lb break="yes"/>the grotto, the water of the river<lb break="yes"/>sparkling amid the foliage of the<lb break="yes"/>trees that concealed it. It was<lb break="yes"/>like a picture placed in the dist-<lb break="no"/>ance, and to which the mouth of<lb break="yes"/>the cavern served as a frame.<lb break="yes"/>Having at length reached the en-<lb break="no"/>trance, and seated ourselves on<lb break="yes"/>the bank of the rivulet, we rested<lb break="yes"/>after our fatigues. We were glad<lb break="yes"/>to be beyond the hoarse cries of<lb break="yes"/>the birds, and to leave a place<lb break="yes"/>where darkness does not offer<lb break="yes" />even the charm of silence and<lb break="yes"/>tranquillity. We could scarcely<lb break="yes"/>persuade ourselves, that the name<lb break="yes" />of the Grotto of Caripe had hi-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">therto</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="454" facs="#f0017"/>
                    <cb/>therto remained unknown in Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope.<note place="foot" n="*" >We have reason to be surprised,<lb break="yes"/>that Father Gili, author of the Saggio<lb break="yes"/>di Storia Americana (Tom. 4, p. 414),<lb break="yes"/>did not mention it, though he had in<lb break="yes"/>his possession a manuscript com-<lb break="no"/>posed in 1780 at the convent of Ca-<lb break="no"/>ripe. I gave the first information<lb break="yes" />respecting the <hi rendition="#i">Cueva del Guacharo</hi> in<lb break="yes"/>1800, in my letters to Messrs. De-<lb break="no"/>lambre and Delamétherie, published<lb break="yes"/>in the Journal de Physique. See<lb break="yes"/>also my Geog. des Plantes, p. 84.</note> The guacharoes alone<lb break="yes"/>would have been sufficient, to<lb break="yes" />render it celebrated. These noc-<lb break="no"/>turnal birds have been no where<lb break="yes"/>yet discovered, except in the<lb break="yes" />mountains of Caripe and Cuma-<lb break="no"/>nacoa.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The mildness of the Spanish<lb break="yes"/>legislation compared with the<lb break="yes"/>Black Code of the greater part<lb break="yes"/>of other nations that have pos-<lb break="no"/>sessions in either India, cannot<lb break="yes" />be denied. But such is the state<lb break="yes"/>of the negroes, dispersed in places<lb break="yes"/>scarcely begun to be cultivated,<lb break="yes"/>that justice, far from efficaciously<lb break="yes"/>protecting them during their<lb break="yes"/>lives, cannot even punish acts of<lb break="yes"/>barbarity, that have caused their<lb break="yes"/>death. If an inquiry be attempted,<lb break="yes"/>the death of the slave is attributed<lb break="yes"/>to the bad state of his health, to<lb break="yes"/>the influence of a warm and<lb break="yes"/>humid climate, to the wounds<lb break="yes"/>which he has received, but which,<lb break="yes"/>it is asserted, were neither deep<lb break="yes"/>nor dangerous. The civil autho-<lb break="no"/>rity is powerless with respect to<lb break="yes"/>whatever constitutes domestic<lb break="yes"/>slavery; and nothing is more<lb break="yes"/>illusory than the effect so much<lb break="yes"/>vaunted of those laws, which pre-<lb break="no" />scribe the form of the whip, and<lb break="yes"/>the number of lashes which it is<lb break="yes"/>permitted to give <hi rendition="#i">at a time.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>Persons who have not lived in the<lb break="yes"/>colonies, or have inhabited only<lb break="yes"/>the West India islands, believe in<lb break="yes" />general, that the interest of the<lb break="yes"/>master in the preservation of his<lb break="yes"/>slaves must render their condition<lb break="yes"/>so much the milder as their<lb break="yes"/>number is less considerable.<lb break="yes"/>Nevertheless, even at Cariaco, a<lb break="yes"/>few weeks before my arrival in<lb break="yes"/>the province, a planter, who had<lb break="yes"/>only eight negroes, killed six by<lb break="yes"/>beating them in the most bar-<lb break="no"/>barous manner. He thus volun-<lb break="no" />tarily destroyed the greater part<lb break="yes"/>of his fortune. Two of his slaves<lb break="yes"/>expired on the spot. He embarked<lb break="yes"/>with four, who seemed more ro-<lb break="no"/>bust, for the port of Cumana, but<lb break="yes"/>they died on the passage. This<lb break="yes"/>act of cruelty had been preceded<lb break="yes"/>in the same year by another, the<lb break="yes"/>circumstances of which are equally<lb break="yes"/>horrible. Such great crimes re-<lb break="no"/>main almost always unpunished;<lb break="yes"/>the spirit, that dictated the laws,<lb break="yes"/>is not that which presides over<lb break="yes"/>their execution. The governor<lb break="yes" />of Cumana was a just and humane<lb break="yes"/>man; but the judiciary forms are<lb break="yes"/>prescribed, and the power of the<lb break="yes" />governor does not extend to a<lb break="yes"/>reform of abuses, which are<lb break="yes"/>almost inherent in every system<lb break="yes"/>of European colonization.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I shall begin by the nation of<lb break="yes"/>the Caymas, of whom more than<lb break="yes"/>fifteen thousand inhabit the<lb break="yes"/>Missions that have just been<lb break="yes"/>described. This nation, little<lb break="yes" />warlike, which father Francisco<lb break="yes"/>of Pamplona<note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn4-1" next="#fn4-2">The name of this monk, cele-<lb break="no"/>brated for his active intrepidity, is<lb break="yes"/>still revered in the province. He<lb break="yes"/>sowed the first seeds of civilization<lb break="yes"/>among these mountains. He had<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">long</fw>
                    </note> began to reduce<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="455" facs="#f0018"/>
                    <cb/>to subjection in the middle of<lb break="yes"/>the seventeenth century, has the<lb break="yes"/>Cumanagotoes toward the west,<lb break="yes"/>the Guaraounoes toward the east,<lb break="yes"/>and the Caribbees toward the<lb break="yes"/>south. It occupies a space along<lb break="yes"/>the elevated mountains of the<lb break="yes"/>Cocollar and the Guacharo, the<lb break="yes" />banks of the Guarapiche, of the<lb break="yes"/>Rio Colorado, of the Areo, and<lb break="yes"/>of the Cano of Caripe. Accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to a statistical survey made<lb break="yes"/>with great care by the father<lb break="yes"/>Prefect,<note place="foot" n="*">Fray Francisco de Chiprana<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">(manuscript memoir).</hi>
                    </note> there were in the Mis-<lb break="no"/>sions of the Arragonese Capuchins<lb break="yes"/>of Cumana&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Nineteen villages of <hi rendition="#i">Missions,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>of which the oldest was established<lb break="yes"/>in 1728; containing one thousand<lb break="yes"/>four hundred and sixty-five fami-<lb break="no"/>lies, and six thousand four hundred<lb break="yes"/>and thirty-three persons: sixteen<lb break="yes"/>villages <hi rendition="#i">de doctrina,</hi> of which the<lb break="yes"/>oldest dates in 1660; containing<lb break="yes"/>one thousand seven hundred and<lb break="yes" />sixty-six families, and eight thou-<lb break="no"/>sand one hundred and seventy<lb break="yes"/>persons.<note place="foot" n="†">Cultivated land <hi rendition="#i">(labranzas),</hi> be-<lb break="no"/>longing to these thirty-five villages,<lb break="yes"/>6554 <hi rendition="#i">almudas.</hi> The number of cows<lb break="yes"/>in 1792 amounted only to 1883.</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These Missions suffered greatly<lb break="yes"/>in 1681, 1697, and 1720, from<lb break="yes"/>the invasions of the Caribbees,<lb break="yes"/>then independent, who burnt<lb break="yes"/>whole villages. From 1730 to<lb break="yes"/>1736, the population diminished<lb break="yes"/>from the ravages of the small-<lb break="no"/>pox, a disease always more fatal<lb break="yes"/>to the copper-coloured Indians,<lb break="yes"/>than to the whites. Many of the<lb break="yes"/>Guaraounoes, who had been<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn4-2" prev="#fn4-1">long been captain of a ship; and be-<lb break="no"/>fore he became a monk, bore the<lb break="yes" />name of Tiburtio Redin.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>assembled together, fled back<lb break="yes"/>again to their marshes. Fourteen<lb break="yes"/>old Missions remained deserted,<lb break="yes"/>and have not been rebuilt. The<lb break="yes"/>Chaymas are in general short;<lb break="yes"/>and they appear so particularly,<lb break="yes"/>when compared, I shall not say<lb break="yes"/>with their neighbours the Car-<lb break="no" />ribbees, or with the Payaguas<lb break="yes"/>or Guayquilits <note place="foot" n="*">The ordinary stature of the<lb break="yes"/>Guayquilits or Mbayas, who live be-<lb break="no"/>tween the 20th and 22nd degrees of<lb break="yes"/>south latitude, is, according to Az-<lb break="no"/>zara 1.84, met. or five feet eight in-<lb break="no"/>ches [six feet and half an inch Eng.]<lb break="yes"/>The Payaguas, equally tall, have<lb break="yes" />given their name to Payaguay, or<lb break="yes"/>Paraguay.</note> of Paraguay,<lb break="yes"/>equally remarkable for their sta-<lb break="no" />ture, but with the ordinary natives<lb break="yes"/>of America. The common stature<lb break="yes"/>of a Chayma is 1&#x00B7;57 met. or four<lb break="yes" />feet ten inches [five feet two<lb break="yes"/>inches nearly], their body is<lb break="yes"/>thick set, shoulders extremely<lb break="yes"/>broad, and breast flat. All their<lb break="yes"/>limbs are round and fleshy. Their<lb break="yes"/>colour is that of the whole Ame-<lb break="no"/>rican race, from the cold table<lb break="yes"/>lands of Quito and New Grenada<lb break="yes"/>to the burning plains of the Ama-<lb break="no"/>zons. It is no longer changed<lb break="yes"/>by the varied influence of climate;<lb break="yes"/>it is connected with organic dis-<lb break="no"/>positions, which for ages past<lb break="yes"/>have been unalterably transmitted<lb break="yes"/>from generation to generation.<lb break="yes"/>If the uniform tint of the skin be<lb break="yes"/>more coppery and redder toward<lb break="yes"/>the north, it is on the contrary<lb break="yes"/>among the Chaymas of a dull<lb break="yes"/>brown inclining towards tawny.<lb break="yes" />The denomination of <hi rendition="#i">copper co-<lb break="no"/>loured</hi> [<hi rendition="#i">rouges-cuivrés</hi>] men could<lb break="yes"/>never have originated in equi-<lb break="no"/>noxial America to designate the<lb break="yes"/>natives.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">The</fw>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="456" facs="#f0019"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>The expression of the counte-<lb break="no"/>nance of the Chaymas, without<lb break="yes"/>being hard or stern, has some-<lb break="no"/>thing sedate and gloomy; the<lb break="yes"/>forehead is small, and but little<lb break="yes" />prominent. Thus in several lan-<lb break="no"/>guages of these countries, to<lb break="yes"/>express the beauty of a woman,<lb break="yes"/>they say &#x201C;that she is fat, and<lb break="yes"/>has a narrow forehead.&#x201D; The<lb break="yes" />eyes of the Chaymas are black,<lb break="yes"/>sunk, and very long; but they<lb break="yes"/>are neither so obliquely placed,<lb break="yes"/>nor so small, as in the people of<lb break="yes"/>the Mongul race, of whom Jor-<lb break="no"/>nandes says, that they have rather<lb break="yes"/>points, than eyes; <hi rendition="#i">magis puncta<lb break="yes"/>quam lumina.</hi> The corner of the<lb break="yes"/>eye is however sensibly raised up<lb break="yes" />toward the temples; the eyebrows<lb break="yes"/>are black, or dark brown, slender,<lb break="yes"/>and little arched; the eyelids are<lb break="yes" />furnished with very long eyelashes,<lb break="yes"/>and the habit of casting them<lb break="yes"/>down, as if they were lowered by<lb break="yes" />lassitude, softens the look of the<lb break="yes"/>women, and makes the eye thus<lb break="yes"/>veiled appear less than it really<lb break="yes"/>is. If the Chaymas, and in ge-<lb break="no"/>neral all the natives of South<lb break="yes"/>America and New Spain, resemble<lb break="yes"/>the Mongul race, by the form of<lb break="yes"/>the eye, their high cheek bones,<lb break="yes"/>their straight and flat hair, and<lb break="yes"/>the almost entire want of beard;<lb break="yes"/>they essentially differ from them<lb break="yes"/>in the form of the nose, which is<lb break="yes"/>pretty long, prominent throughout<lb break="yes"/>its whole length, and thick toward<lb break="yes"/>the nostrils, the openings of which<lb break="yes"/>are directed downward, as with all<lb break="yes"/>the nations of the Caucasian race.<lb break="yes"/>Their wide mouth, with lips but<lb break="yes"/>little protuberant, though broad,<lb break="yes"/>has often an expression of good-<lb break="no"/>ness. The passage from the nose<lb break="yes"/>to the mouth is marked in both<lb break="yes"/>sexes by two furrows, which run<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>diverging from the nostrils toward<lb break="yes"/>the corners of the mouth. The<lb break="yes"/>chin is extremely short and round;<lb break="yes" />and the jaws are remarkable for<lb break="yes"/>their strength and width.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Though the Chaymas have fine<lb break="yes"/>white teeth, like all people who<lb break="yes"/>lead a very simple life, they are<lb break="yes"/>however not so strong as those<lb break="yes"/>of the Negroes. The habit of<lb break="yes" />blackening the teeth, from the<lb break="yes"/>age of fifteen, by the juices of<lb break="yes"/>certain herbs <note place="foot" n="*">The first historians of the con-<lb break="no"/>quest attribute this effect to the<lb break="yes"/>leaves of a tree, that the natives call<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">hay,</hi> which resembled the myrtle.<lb break="yes" />Among nations very distant from<lb break="yes"/>each other, the pimento bears a<lb break="yes"/>similar name; among the Haytians<lb break="yes"/>(of the island of St. Domingo) <hi rendition="#i">aji</hi> or<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">ahi;</hi> among the Maypures of the<lb break="yes" />Oroonoko <hi rendition="#i">a-i.</hi> Some stimulant and<lb break="yes" />aromatic plants, which do not all<lb break="yes"/>belong to the genus capsicum, were<lb break="yes"/>designated by the same name.</note> and caustic lime,<lb break="yes"/>had engaged the attention of the<lb break="yes" />earliest travellers; but it is at<lb break="yes"/>present quite unknown. Such<lb break="yes"/>have been the migrations of the<lb break="yes" />different tribes in these countries,<lb break="yes"/>particularly since the incursions<lb break="yes"/>of the Spaniards, who carried on<lb break="yes" />the slave trade, it may be ad-<lb break="no"/>mitted, that the inhabitants of<lb break="yes"/>Paria, visited by Christopher Co-<lb break="no"/>lumbus, and by Ojeda, were not<lb break="yes"/>of the same race as the Chaymas.<lb break="yes"/>I doubt much, whether the cus-<lb break="no"/>tom of blackening the teeth were<lb break="yes"/>originally connected, as Gomara<lb break="yes" />affirmed,<note place="foot" n="†" xml:id="fn5-1" next="#fn5-2">Cap. 78, p. 101. The nations,<lb break="yes"/>that were seen by the Spaniards on<lb break="yes"/>the coast of Paria, had probably the</note> with extravagant ideas<lb break="yes"/>of beauty, or were practised with<lb break="yes"/>the view of preventing the <choice>
                        <sic>tooth-<lb break="no"/>ach</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">tooth-<lb break="no"/>ache</corr>
                    </choice>. This disorder is almost un-<lb break="no"/>known to the Indians; the whites<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">even</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="457" facs="#f0020"/>
                    <cb/>even suffer very seldom from it in<lb break="yes"/>the Spanish colonies, at least in<lb break="yes"/>the warm regions, where the<lb break="yes"/>temperature is so uniform. They<lb break="yes"/>are more exposed to it on the<lb break="yes" />back of the Cordilleras, at Santa-<lb break="no"/>Fe, and at Popayan.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Chaymas, like almost all<lb break="yes"/>the native nations I have seen,<lb break="yes"/>have small, slender hands. Their<lb break="yes"/>feet are large, and their toes<lb break="yes"/>retain an extraordinary mobility.<lb break="yes"/>All the Chaymas have a family<lb break="yes"/>look; and this analogy of form,<lb break="yes"/>so often observed by travellers, is<lb break="yes"/>so much the more striking, as<lb break="yes"/>between the years of twenty and<lb break="yes"/>fifty difference of age is no way<lb break="yes" />denoted by wrinkles of the skin,<lb break="yes"/>the colour of the hair, or decre-<lb break="no"/>pitude of the body. On entering<lb break="yes"/>a hut, it is often difficult among<lb break="yes"/>adult persons to distinguish the<lb break="yes"/>father from the son, and not to<lb break="yes"/>confound one generation with<lb break="yes"/>another. I attribute this family<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="†" xml:id="fn5-2" prev="#fn5-1">custom of stimulating the organs of<lb break="yes"/>taste by caustic lime, as others em-<lb break="no" />ployed tobacco, the chimo, the leaves<lb break="yes"/>of the cocca, or betel. This practice<lb break="yes"/>is found even in our days, but more<lb break="yes"/>toward the west, among the Gua-<lb break="no"/>jiroes, at the mouth of the Rio la<lb break="yes"/>Hacha. These Indians, still savage,<lb break="yes"/>carry small shells, calcined and<lb break="yes" />powdered, in the shell of a fruit, that<lb break="yes"/>serves them as a vessel for various<lb break="yes"/>purposes, suspended to their girdle.<lb break="yes"/>The powder of the Guajiroes is an<lb break="yes"/>article of commerce, as was an-<lb break="no"/>ciently, according to Gomara, that<lb break="yes"/>of the Indians of Paria. In Europe<lb break="yes"/>the immoderate habit of smoking<lb break="yes"/>also makes the teeth yellow and<lb break="yes"/>blackens them: but would it be just<lb break="yes" />to conclude from this fact, that they<lb break="yes"/>who smoke with us do it because we<lb break="yes"/>think yellow teeth handsomer than<lb break="yes"/>white?</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>look to two different causes, the<lb break="yes"/>local situation of the Indian<lb break="yes"/>tribes, and their inferior degree<lb break="yes"/>of intellectual culture. Savage<lb break="yes"/>nations are subdivided into an<lb break="yes"/>infinity of tribes, which, bearing<lb break="yes"/>a cruel hatred toward each other,<lb break="yes"/>form no intermarriages, even<lb break="yes"/>when their languages spring from<lb break="yes"/>the same root, and when only a<lb break="yes"/>small arm of a river, or a group of<lb break="yes"/>hills, separates their habitations.<lb break="yes"/>The less numerous are the tribes,<lb break="yes"/>the more the intermarriages,<lb break="yes"/>repeated for ages, between the<lb break="yes"/>same families, tend to fix a<lb break="yes"/>certain equality of conformation,<lb break="yes" />an organic type, which may be<lb break="yes"/>called national.<note place="foot" n="*">Nullis aliis aliarum nationem<lb break="yes"/>connubiis infecta, propria et sincera,<lb break="yes"/>et tantum sui similis gens. Unde<lb break="yes"/>habitus quoque corporum, quam-<lb break="no"/>quam in tanto hominum numero,<lb break="yes"/>idem omnibus. Tac. Germ. c. 4.</note> This type is<lb break="yes"/>preserved under the government<lb break="yes"/>of the Missions formed by a single<lb break="yes"/>horde. The isolated state is the<lb break="yes"/>same, and marriages are contract-<lb break="no"/>ed only between the inhabitants of<lb break="yes"/>the same hamlet. Those ties of<lb break="yes"/>blood, which unite almost a whole<lb break="yes"/>nation, are indicated in a simple<lb break="yes"/>manner in the language of the<lb break="yes"/>Indians born in the Mission, or<lb break="yes" />by those, who, taken from the<lb break="yes"/>woods, have learned Spanish. To<lb break="yes"/>designate the individuals, who<lb break="yes"/>belong to the same tribe, they<lb break="yes"/>employ the words <hi rendition="#i">mis parientes,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>my relations.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These causes, which depend<lb break="yes"/>only on the isolated state, and the<lb break="yes"/>effects of which are found among<lb break="yes"/>the Jews of Europe, among the<lb break="yes"/>different casts of India, and among<lb break="yes"/>mountaineer nations in general,<lb break="yes"/>are connected with causes hitherto<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">neglected.</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="458" facs="#f0021"/>
                    <cb/>neglected. I have observed else-<lb break="no"/>where, that it is intellectual cul-<lb break="no"/>ture which contributes most to<lb break="yes" />diversify the features. Barbarous<lb break="yes"/>nations have rather a physiog-<lb break="no"/>nomy of tribe or horde, than one<lb break="yes" />peculiar to such or such an<lb break="yes"/>individual. The savage and civi-<lb break="no"/>lized man are like those animals<lb break="yes"/>of the same species, several of<lb break="yes"/>which rove in the forest, while<lb break="yes"/>others, connected with us, share<lb break="yes"/>in the benefits and evils that<lb break="yes"/>accompany civilization. The<lb break="yes"/>varieties of form and colour are<lb break="yes"/>frequent only in domestic animals.<lb break="yes"/>How great is the difference, with<lb break="yes"/>respect to mobility of features<lb break="yes"/>and variety of physiognomy, be-<lb break="no"/>tween dogs again become savage<lb break="yes" />in the New World, and those the<lb break="yes"/>slightest caprices of which are<lb break="yes"/>indulged in the houses of the<lb break="yes"/>opulent! Both in men and animals<lb break="yes"/>the emotions of the soul are<lb break="yes"/>reflected in the features; and the<lb break="yes"/>features acquire the habit of<lb break="yes"/>mobility, in proportion as the<lb break="yes"/>emotions of the mind are more<lb break="yes"/>frequent, more varied, and more<lb break="yes"/>durable. But the Indian of the<lb break="yes" />Missions, distant from all cultiva-<lb break="no"/>tion, guided only by his physical<lb break="yes"/>wants, satisfying almost without<lb break="yes" />difficulty his desires, under a<lb break="yes"/>happy climate, drags on a dull<lb break="yes"/>monotonous life. The greatest<lb break="yes"/>equality reigns among the mem-<lb break="no"/>hers of the same community; and<lb break="yes"/>this uniformity, this invariable-<lb break="no"/>ness of situation, is pictured on<lb break="yes"/>the features of the Indians.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Under the system of the monks,<lb break="yes"/>violent passions, such as resent-<lb break="no"/>ment and anger, agitate the native<lb break="yes" />more rarely than when he lives in<lb break="yes"/>the forest. If the savage man<lb break="yes"/>give himself up to impetuous and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>quick emotions; his physiognomy,<lb break="yes"/>till then calm and motionless,<lb break="yes"/>changes instantly to convulsive<lb break="yes" />contortions. His passion is tran-<lb break="no"/>sient in proportion to its violence.<lb break="yes"/>With the Indians of the Missions,<lb break="yes" />as I have often observed on the<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko, anger is less furious,<lb break="yes"/>less frank, but of longer duration.<lb break="yes" />Besides, in every condition of<lb break="yes"/>man, it is not the energy or the<lb break="yes"/>transient bursts of the passions,<lb break="yes"/>which give expression to the<lb break="yes"/>features; it is rather that sensi-<lb break="no"/>bility of the soul, which brings us<lb break="yes"/>continually into contact with the<lb break="yes"/>external world, multiplies our<lb break="yes"/>sufferings and our pleasures, and<lb break="yes"/>reacts at once on the physiog-<lb break="no"/>nomy, the manners, and the<lb break="yes" />language. If the variety and<lb break="yes"/>mobility of the features embellish<lb break="yes"/>the domain of animated nature,<lb break="yes"/>we must admit also, that both<lb break="yes"/>increase by civilization, without<lb break="yes"/>being produced by it alone. In<lb break="yes"/>the great family of nations, no<lb break="yes"/>other race unites these advantages<lb break="yes" />to a higher degree than that of<lb break="yes"/>Caucasus, or the European. It<lb break="yes"/>is only in white men, that the<lb break="yes" />instantaneous penetration of the<lb break="yes"/>dermoidal system by the blood<lb break="yes"/>can take place; that slight change<lb break="yes"/>of the colour of the skin, which<lb break="yes"/>adds so powerful an expression to<lb break="yes"/>the emotions of the soul. &#x201C;How<lb break="yes"/>can those be trusted, who know<lb break="yes"/>not how to blush?&#x201D; says the<lb break="yes" />European, in his inveterate hatred<lb break="yes"/>to the Negro and the Indian. We<lb break="yes"/>must also admit, that this insen-<lb break="no" />sibility of the features is not<lb break="yes"/>peculiar to every race of men of<lb break="yes"/>a very dark complexion: it is<lb break="yes"/>much less apparent in the Af-<lb break="no"/>rican, than in the natives of<lb break="yes" />America.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">To</fw>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="459" facs="#f0022"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>To this physical sketch of the<lb break="yes"/>Chaymas we shall add a few<lb break="yes"/>summary remarks on their manner<lb break="yes"/>of living, and on their morals.<lb break="yes"/>Unacquainted with the language<lb break="yes" />of the people, I do not pretend to<lb break="yes"/>have penetrated their character<lb break="yes"/>during my short abode in the<lb break="yes" />Missions. Whenever I speak of<lb break="yes"/>the Indians, I shall add what we<lb break="yes"/>heard from the missionaries to<lb break="yes"/>the little we observed ourselves.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Chaymas, like all savage<lb break="yes"/>people, who dwell in regions<lb break="yes"/>excessively hot, have an insupe-<lb break="no"/>rable aversion to clothing. The<lb break="yes"/>writers of the middle age inform<lb break="yes" />us, that in the north of Europe<lb break="yes"/>the shirts and drawers, distributed<lb break="yes"/>by the missionaries, greatly con-<lb break="no" />tributed to the conversion of the<lb break="yes"/>Pagan. Under the torrid zone,<lb break="yes"/>on the contrary, the natives are<lb break="yes" />ashamed as they say to be clothed;<lb break="yes"/>and flee to the woods, when they<lb break="yes"/>are too soon compelled to give<lb break="yes"/>up their nakedness. Among the<lb break="yes"/>Chaymas, in spite of the remon-<lb break="no"/>strances of the monks, men and<lb break="yes"/>women remain naked within their<lb break="yes"/>houses. When they traverse the<lb break="yes" />village, they wear a kind of tunic<lb break="yes"/>of cotton, which scarcely reaches<lb break="yes"/>to the knees. It is furnished with<lb break="yes" />sleeves for the men; but the<lb break="yes"/>women, and the young boys to<lb break="yes"/>the age of ten or twelve, have the<lb break="yes"/>arms, shoulders, and upper part<lb break="yes"/>of the breast naked. The tunic<lb break="yes"/>is so cut, that the fore part is<lb break="yes"/>joined to the back by two narrow<lb break="yes"/>bands, which cross the shoulders.<lb break="yes"/>When we met the natives, with-<lb break="no"/>out the Mission, we saw them,<lb break="yes"/>especially in rainy weather,<lb break="yes" />stripped of their clothes, and<lb break="yes"/>holding their shirts rolled up<lb break="yes"/>under their arms. They preferred<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>receiving the rain on their body<lb break="yes"/>quite naked, to wetting their<lb break="yes"/>clothes. The oldest women hid<lb break="yes" />themselves behind trees, and<lb break="yes"/>laughed aloud when they saw<lb break="yes"/>us pass. The missionaries com-<lb break="no"/>plain in general, that the senti-<lb break="no"/>ments of decency are scarcely<lb break="yes" />more felt by young girls than by<lb break="yes"/>the men. Ferdinand Columbus<note place="foot" n="*">Life of the Admiral, cap. 71,<lb break="yes"/>(Churchill&#x2019;s Collection, 1723, vol. ii,<lb break="yes"/>p. 586). This Life, written after the<lb break="yes"/>year 1537, from original notes in the<lb break="yes"/>hand-writing of Christopher Colum-<lb break="no"/>bus, is the most valuable record of<lb break="yes"/>the history of his discoveries. It<lb break="yes"/>exists only in the Italian and Spanish<lb break="yes"/>translations of Alphonso de Ulloa<lb break="yes" />and Gonzales Barcia; for the ori-<lb break="no"/>ginal, carried to Venice in 1571 by<lb break="yes"/>the learned Fornari, has neither been<lb break="yes"/>published nor found since. <hi rendition="#i">Napione<lb break="yes"/>della Patria di Colombo,</hi> 1804, p. 109,<lb break="yes"/>and 295. <hi rendition="#i">Cancellieri sopra Chris.<lb break="yes"/>Colombo,</hi> 1809, p. 129.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>relates, that in 1498 his father<lb break="yes"/>found the women entirely naked<lb break="yes"/>in the island of Trinidad; while<lb break="yes"/>the men wore the <hi rendition="#i">guayuco,</hi> which<lb break="yes"/>is rather a narrow bandage than<lb break="yes"/>an apron. At the same period,<lb break="yes"/>on the coast of Paria, the girls<lb break="yes" />distinguished themselves from the<lb break="yes"/>married women, either, as cardinal<lb break="yes"/>Bembo asserts,<note place="foot" n="†">See the eloquent description of<lb break="yes"/>America, in the History of Venice,<lb break="yes"/>(Book 12). &#x201C;Femin&#x00E6; virum pass&#x00E6;<lb break="yes" />nullam partem, pr&#x00E6;ter muliebria;<lb break="yes"/>virgines ne illam quidem tegebant.&#x201D;</note> by being quite<lb break="yes"/>naked, or, according to Gomara,<note place="foot" n="‡">Las donzellas se conocen en el<lb break="yes"/>color y tamano del cordel, y traerlo<lb break="yes"/>asi, es senal certissima de virginidad.<lb break="yes"/>(Gomara, cap. 73, p. 96).</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>by the colour of the <hi rendition="#i">guayuco.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>This bandage, which is still in<lb break="yes"/>use among the Chaymas, and all<lb break="yes"/>the naked nations of the Oroo-<lb break="no"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">noko,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="460" facs="#f0023"/>
                    <cb/>noko, is only two or three inches<lb break="yes"/>broad, and is tied on both sides<lb break="yes"/>to a string, that encircles the<lb break="yes" />middle of the body. The girls<lb break="yes"/>are often married at the age of<lb break="yes"/>twelve years; until nine the mis-<lb break="no" />sionaries allow them to go to<lb break="yes"/>church naked, that is to say<lb break="yes"/>without a tunic. I need not<lb break="yes"/>repeat here, that among the<lb break="yes"/>Chaymas, as well as in all the<lb break="yes"/>Spanish Missions and the Indian<lb break="yes"/>villages, which I have visited, a<lb break="yes"/>pair of drawers, or shoes, or a<lb break="yes"/>hat, are objects of luxury unknown<lb break="yes"/>to the natives. A servant, who<lb break="yes"/>had been with us during our<lb break="yes"/>journey to Caripe and the Oroo-<lb break="no"/>noko, and whom I brought to<lb break="yes"/>France, was so much struck on<lb break="yes"/>landing, when he saw the ground<lb break="yes"/>tilled by a peasant with a hat on,<lb break="yes"/>that he thought himself in a<lb break="yes"/>miserable country, where even<lb break="yes"/>nobles <hi rendition="#i">(los mismos caballeros)</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>followed the plough. The Chayma<lb break="yes"/>women are not handsome, ac-<lb break="no"/>cording to the ideas that we annex<lb break="yes" />to beauty; yet the girls have<lb break="yes"/>something soft and melancholy<lb break="yes"/>in their looks, which forms an<lb break="yes"/>agreeable contrast with the ex-<lb break="no"/>pression of the mouth, which is<lb break="yes"/>somewhat austere and savage.<lb break="yes"/>They wear the hair plaited in two<lb break="yes"/>long tresses; they do not paint<lb break="yes" />their skin, and from their extreme<lb break="yes"/>poverty are acquainted with no<lb break="yes"/>other ornaments than necklaces<lb break="yes"/>and bracelets made of shells,<lb break="yes"/>birds&#x2019; bones, and seeds. Both<lb break="yes"/>men and women are very mus-<lb break="no"/>cular, but fleshy and plump. It<lb break="yes"/>is superfluous to add, that I saw<lb break="yes" />no person, who had any natural<lb break="yes"/>deformity; I might say the same<lb break="yes"/>of thousands of Caribs, Muyscas,<lb break="yes"/>and Mexican and Peruvian In-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/>dians, whom we observed during<lb break="yes"/>the course of five years. Bodily<lb break="yes"/>deformities, deviations from na-<lb break="no"/>ture, are infinitely rare among<lb break="yes"/>certain races of men, especially<lb break="yes"/>those nations, who have the<lb break="yes"/>dermoid system highly coloured.<lb break="yes"/>I cannot believe, that they depend<lb break="yes"/>solely on the progress of civiliza-<lb break="no"/>tion, a luxurious life, or the<lb break="yes"/>corruption of morals. In Europe<lb break="yes"/>a deformed or very ugly girl<lb break="yes"/>marries if she have a fortune, and<lb break="yes"/>the children often inherit the<lb break="yes"/>deformity of the mother. In the<lb break="yes"/>savage state, which is a state of<lb break="yes"/>equality, nothing can induce a<lb break="yes"/>man to unite himself to a deformed<lb break="yes"/>woman, or one who is very un-<lb break="no"/>healthy. If therefore such a<lb break="yes" />woman have had the misfortune<lb break="yes"/>of attaining an adult age, and<lb break="yes"/>have resisted the chances of a<lb break="yes"/>restless and disturbed life, she<lb break="yes"/>dies without children. We might<lb break="yes"/>be tempted to think, that savages<lb break="yes"/>all appear well made and vigorous,<lb break="yes"/>because feeble children die young<lb break="yes"/>for want of care; and that the<lb break="yes"/>strongest alone survive; but these<lb break="yes"/>causes cannot act on the Indians<lb break="yes"/>of the Missions, who have the<lb break="yes"/>manners of our peasants, and the<lb break="yes"/>Mexicans of Cholula and Tlas-<lb break="no" />cala, who enjoy wealth, that has<lb break="yes"/>been transmitted to them by<lb break="yes"/>ancestors more civilized than<lb break="yes"/>themselves. If in every state of<lb break="yes"/>cultivation, the copper-coloured<lb break="yes"/>race manifests the same inflexibi-<lb break="no"/>lity, the same resistance to devia-<lb break="no"/>tion from a primitive type, are we<lb break="yes"/>not forced to admit, that this<lb break="yes"/>property belongs in great measure<lb break="yes"/>to hereditary organization, to that<lb break="yes"/>which constitutes the race? I use<lb break="yes"/>intentionally the expression <hi rendition="#i">in<lb break="yes"/>great measure,</hi> not entirely to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">exclude</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="461" facs="#f0024"/>
                    <cb/>exclude the influence of civili-<lb break="no"/>zation. Besides, with copper-<lb break="no"/>coloured men, as with the whites,<lb break="yes" />luxury and effeminacy, by<lb break="yes"/>weakening the physical consti-<lb break="no"/>tution, had heretofore rendered<lb break="yes"/>deformities more common at<lb break="yes"/>Couzco and Tenochtitlan. It is<lb break="yes"/>not among the Mexicans of the<lb break="yes"/>present day, who are all labourers,<lb break="yes"/>and leading the most simple lives,<lb break="yes"/>that Montezuma would have<lb break="yes"/>found the dwarfs and hump-backs,<lb break="yes"/>that Bernal Diaz saw waiting at<lb break="yes"/>his table when he dined.<note place="foot" n="*">Bernal Diaz, Hist. verd. de la<lb break="yes" />Nueva Espana, 1630, cap. 91, p. 68.</note> The<lb break="yes"/>custom of marrying very young,<lb break="yes"/>according to the testimony of the<lb break="yes"/>monks, is no way detrimental to<lb break="yes"/>population. This precocious nu-<lb break="no"/>bility depends on the race, and<lb break="yes"/>not on the influence of a climate<lb break="yes"/>excessively warm. It is found on<lb break="yes"/>the north-west coast of America,<lb break="yes"/>among the Eskimoes, and in Asia,<lb break="yes"/>among the Kamtschadales, and<lb break="yes"/>the Coriacs, where girls of ten<lb break="yes"/>years old are often mothers. It<lb break="yes"/>may appear astonishing, that the<lb break="yes"/>time of gestation, the duration of<lb break="yes"/>pregnancy, is never altered in a<lb break="yes"/>state of health, with any race, or<lb break="yes"/>in any climate.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Chaymas are almost with-<lb break="no"/>out beard on the chin, like the<lb break="yes"/>Tungooses, and other nations of<lb break="yes"/>the Mongul race. They pluck<lb break="yes"/>out the few hairs that appear;<lb break="yes" />but it is not just to say in general,<lb break="yes"/>that they have no beard merely<lb break="yes"/>because they pluck out the hairs.<lb break="yes" />Independently of this custom, the<lb break="yes"/>greater part of the natives would<lb break="yes"/>be nearly beardless.<note place="foot" n="†" xml:id="fn6-1" next="#fn6-2">There would never have been<lb break="yes"/>any difference of opinion between</note> I say the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>greater part, for there exist<lb break="yes"/>tribes, which, appearing distinct<lb break="yes"/>among the others, are so much<lb break="yes"/>more worthy of fixing our atten-<lb break="no"/>tion. Such are in North America<lb break="yes"/>the Chippeways,<note place="foot" n="*">Between latitude 60&#x00B0; and 65&#x00B0;<lb break="yes"/>north.</note> visited by Mac-<lb break="no"/>kenzie, and the Yabipaees,<note place="foot" n="†">Humb., Nouv. Esp. T. ii, p. 410.</note> near<lb break="yes"/>the Toltec ruins at Moqui, with<lb break="yes"/>bushy beards; in South America,<lb break="yes"/>the Patagonians, and the Gua-<lb break="no"/>ranies. Among these last indivi-<lb break="no"/>duals are found, some of whom<lb break="yes"/>have hairs on the breast. When<lb break="yes"/>the Chaymas, instead of extracting<lb break="yes" />the little hair they have on the<lb break="yes"/>chin, attempt to shave themselves<lb break="yes"/>frequently, their beard grows. I<lb break="yes" />have seen this experiment tried<lb break="yes"/>with success by young Indians, who<lb break="yes"/>served at mass, and who anxiously<lb break="yes"/>wished to resemble the Capuchin<lb break="yes"/>Fathers, their missionaries, and<lb break="yes"/>masters. The greater part of the<lb break="yes"/>people, however, have as great an<lb break="yes"/>antipathy to the beard, as the<lb break="yes"/>Eastern nations hold it in rever-<lb break="no"/>ence. This antipathy is derived<lb break="yes"/>from the same source as the<lb break="yes" />predilection for flat foreheads,<lb break="yes"/>which is seen in so singular a<lb break="yes"/>manner in the statues of the<lb break="yes"/>Azteck heroes and divinities.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="†" xml:id="fn6-2" prev="#fn6-1">physiologists upon the existence of<lb break="yes"/>the beard among the Americans, if<lb break="yes"/>they had paid attention to what the<lb break="yes"/>first historians of the Conquest of<lb break="yes"/>their country have said on this sub-<lb break="no"/>ject; for example, Pigafetta, in 1519,<lb break="yes"/>in his journal preserved in the Am-<lb break="no"/>brosian Library at Milan, and pub-<lb break="no"/>lished (in 1800) by Amoretti, p. 18;<lb break="yes"/>Benzoni, Hist. del Mundo Nuovo,<lb break="yes" />1572, p. 35; Bembo, Hist. Venet.,<lb break="yes"/>1557, p. 86.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">Nations</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="462" facs="#f0025"/>
                    <cb/>Nations attach the idea of beauty<lb break="yes"/>to every thing, which particularly<lb break="yes"/>characterizes their own physical<lb break="yes" />conformation, their natural phy-<lb break="no"/>siognomy.<note place="foot" n="*">Thus, in their finest statues, the<lb break="yes"/>Greeks exaggerated the form of the<lb break="yes"/>forehead, by elevating beyond pro-<lb break="no"/>portion the facial line. (Cuv., Anat.<lb break="yes"/>Comp. T. ii, p. 6. Humb., Monum.<lb break="yes"/>Americ., T. i. p. 158).</note> Thence it results,<lb break="yes"/>that, if Nature have bestowed<lb break="yes" />very little beard, a narrow fore-<lb break="no"/>head, or a brownish-red skin,<lb break="yes"/>every individual thinks himself<lb break="yes" />beautiful, in proportion as his<lb break="yes"/>body is destitute of hairs, his<lb break="yes"/>head flattened, his skin more<lb break="yes"/>covered with <hi rendition="#i">annotto,</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">chica,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>or some other coppery or red-<lb break="no"/>colour.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Chaymas lead a life of the<lb break="yes"/>greatest uniformity. They go to<lb break="yes"/>rest very regularly at seven in the<lb break="yes"/>evening; and rise long before<lb break="yes"/>day-light, at half after four in<lb break="yes"/>the morning. Every Indian has<lb break="yes"/>a fire near his hammock. The<lb break="yes"/>women are so chilly, that I have<lb break="yes" />seen them shiver at church when<lb break="yes"/>the centigrade thermometer was<lb break="yes"/>not below 18&#x00B0;. The inside of the<lb break="yes"/>huts of the Indians is extremely<lb break="yes"/>clean. Their hammocks, their<lb break="yes"/>mat of reeds, their pots to hold<lb break="yes"/>cassava and fermented maize,<lb break="yes"/>their bows and arrows, every<lb break="yes" />thing is arranged in the greatest<lb break="yes"/>order. Men and women bathe<lb break="yes"/>every day, and being almost con-<lb break="no" />stantly naked, they are exempted<lb break="yes"/>from that want of cleanliness, of<lb break="yes"/>which the garments are the prin-<lb break="no" />cipal cause among the lower<lb break="yes"/>people in cold countries. Beside<lb break="yes"/>a house in the village, they have<lb break="yes" />generally in their <hi rendition="#i">conucos,</hi> near<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>some spring, or at the entrance<lb break="yes"/>of some solitary valley, a small<lb break="yes"/>hut, covered with the leaves of the<lb break="yes" />palm or plaintain-tree. Though<lb break="yes"/>they live less commodiously in<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">conuco,</hi> they love to retire<lb break="yes"/>thither as often as they can. We<lb break="yes"/>have already spoken of that<lb break="yes"/>irresistible desire of fleeing from<lb break="yes"/>society, and of entering again on<lb break="yes"/>a savage life. The youngest<lb break="yes"/>children sometimes leave their<lb break="yes" />parents, and wander four or five<lb break="yes"/>days in the forests, living on fruits,<lb break="yes"/>palm-cabbage, and roots. When<lb break="yes" />travelling in the Missions, it is<lb break="yes"/>not uncommon, to find the villages<lb break="yes"/>almost deserted, because the in-<lb break="no" />habitants are in their gardens, or<lb break="yes"/>in the forests, <hi rendition="#i">al monte.</hi> Among<lb break="yes"/>civilized nations, the passion for<lb break="yes"/>hunting is owing perhaps in part<lb break="yes"/>to the same sentiments, to the<lb break="yes"/>charm of solitude, to the innate<lb break="yes"/>desire of independence, to the<lb break="yes"/>deep impression made by Nature,<lb break="yes"/>whenever man finds himself in<lb break="yes" />contact with her alone.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The condition of the women<lb break="yes"/>among the Chaymas, like that in<lb break="yes"/>all semibarbarous nations, is a<lb break="yes"/>state of privation and suffering.<lb break="yes"/>The hardest labour is their share.<lb break="yes"/>When we saw the Chaymas return<lb break="yes"/>in the evening from their gardens,<lb break="yes"/>the man carried nothing but the<lb break="yes"/>knife <hi rendition="#i">(machette),</hi> with which he<lb break="yes"/>clears his way among the under-<lb break="no"/>wood. The woman however bent<lb break="yes"/>under a great load of plantains;<lb break="yes" />she held a child in her arms; and<lb break="yes"/>sometimes two other children<lb break="yes"/>were placed upon the load.<lb break="yes" />Notwithstanding this inequality<lb break="yes"/>of condition, the wives of the<lb break="yes"/>Indians of South America appear<lb break="yes"/>to be in general happier than<lb break="yes"/>those of the savages of the North.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">Between</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="463" facs="#f0026"/>
                    <cb/>Between the Alleghany moun-<lb break="no"/>tains and the Mississippi, wherever<lb break="yes"/>the natives do not live in great<lb break="yes" />part on the produce of the chace,<lb break="yes"/>the women cultivate the maize,<lb break="yes"/>beans, and gourds; and the men<lb break="yes"/>take no share in the labours of<lb break="yes"/>the field. Under the torrid zone,<lb break="yes"/>the hunting nations are extremely<lb break="yes"/>scarce, and, in the Missions, the<lb break="yes"/>men work in the fields like the<lb break="yes"/>women.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Nothing can exceed the diffi-<lb break="no"/>culty with which the Indians<lb break="yes"/>learn Spanish. They have an<lb break="yes"/>absolute aversion to it, while,<lb break="yes"/>living separate from the whites,<lb break="yes" />they have not the ambition to be<lb break="yes"/>called polished Indians, or, as it is<lb break="yes"/>termed in the Missions, <hi rendition="#i">latinized<lb break="yes"/>Indians, Indios muy latinos.</hi> But<lb break="yes"/>what struck me most, not only<lb break="yes"/>among the Chaymas, but in all<lb break="yes"/>the very distant Missions, which<lb break="yes"/>I afterwards visited, is the extreme<lb break="yes"/>difficulty, which the Indians have<lb break="yes"/>to arrange and express the most<lb break="yes"/>simple ideas in Spanish, even<lb break="yes"/>when they perfectly understand<lb break="yes"/>the meaning of the words, and<lb break="yes"/>the turn of the phrases. When a<lb break="yes"/>white questions them concerning<lb break="yes"/>objects which surround them from<lb break="yes"/>their cradle, they seem to discover<lb break="yes"/>an imbecility, which exceeds that<lb break="yes"/>of infancy. The missionaries as-<lb break="no"/>sert, that this embarrassment is<lb break="yes"/>not the effect of timidity; that in<lb break="yes"/>the Indians who daily visit the<lb break="yes"/>missionary&#x2019;s house, and who<lb break="yes" />regulate the public works, it does<lb break="yes"/>not arise from natural stupidity,<lb break="yes"/>but from the obstacles they find<lb break="yes" />in the structure of a language<lb break="yes"/>so different from their native<lb break="yes"/>tongues. The more remote man<lb break="yes"/>is from cultivation, the greater<lb break="yes"/>his stiffness and moral inflexibility.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>We must not then be surprised,<lb break="yes"/>to find obstacles among the iso-<lb break="no"/>lated Indians in the Missions,<lb break="yes"/>which are unknown to those, who<lb break="yes"/>inhabit the same parish with the<lb break="yes"/>mestizoes, the mulattoes, and the<lb break="yes"/>whites, in the neighbourhood of<lb break="yes"/>towns. I have often been surprised<lb break="yes"/>at the volubility, with which, at<lb break="yes"/>Caripe, the <hi rendition="#i">alcalde,</hi> the <hi rendition="#i">gover-<lb break="no" />nador,</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i">sargento mayor,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>harangue for whole hours the<lb break="yes"/>Indians assembled before the<lb break="yes"/>church; regulating the labours<lb break="yes"/>of the week, reprimanding the<lb break="yes"/>idle, threatening the disobedient.<lb break="yes"/>Those chiefs, who are equally of<lb break="yes"/>the Chayma race, and who trans-<lb break="no"/>mit the orders of the missionary,<lb break="yes"/>speak all at the same time, with<lb break="yes"/>a loud voice, with marked em-<lb break="no"/>phasis, but almost without action.<lb break="yes" />Their features remain motionless;<lb break="yes"/>but their look is imperious and<lb break="yes"/>severe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These same men, who displayed<lb break="yes"/>quickness of intellect, and who<lb break="yes"/>were tolerably well acquainted<lb break="yes"/>with the Spanish, could no longer<lb break="yes"/>connect their ideas, when, accom-<lb break="no"/>panying us in our excursions<lb break="yes"/>around the convent, we put<lb break="yes"/>questions to them through the<lb break="yes" />intervention of the monks. They<lb break="yes"/>were made to affirm or deny,<lb break="yes"/>whatever the monks pleased:<lb break="yes"/>and indolence, attended with that<lb break="yes"/>wily politeness, to which the least<lb break="yes"/>cultivated Indian is no stranger,<lb break="yes" />induced them sometimes to give<lb break="yes"/>to their answers the turn, that<lb break="yes"/>seemed to be suggested by our<lb break="yes" />questions. Travellers cannot be<lb break="yes"/>enough on their guard against<lb break="yes"/>this officious assent, when they<lb break="yes" />wish to support their opinions by<lb break="yes"/>the testimony of the natives. To<lb break="yes"/>put an Indian Alcalde to the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">proof,</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="464" facs="#f0027"/>
                    <cb/>proof, I asked him one day, if<lb break="yes"/>he did not think the little river of<lb break="yes"/>Caripe, which issues from the<lb break="yes"/>cavern of the Guacharo, returned<lb break="yes"/>into it on the opposite side by some<lb break="yes"/>unknown entrance, after having<lb break="yes"/>ascended the slope of the moun-<lb break="no"/>tain. After appearing gravely to<lb break="yes"/>reflect on the subject, he an-<lb break="no"/>swered, by way of supporting my<lb break="yes"/>hypothesis: &#x201C;How else, if it<lb break="yes"/>were not so, would there always<lb break="yes"/>be water in the bed of the river<lb break="yes"/>at the mouth of the cavern?&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI> 