<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="45" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#b">THE COW-TREE OF SOUTH<lb break="yes"/>AMERICA.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We had heard of a tree, the juice of which is a<lb break="yes"/>nourishing milk; it is called the Cow-Tree; and<lb break="yes"/>we were assured that the negroes of the farm, who<lb break="yes"/>drink plentifully of this vegetable milk, consider<lb break="yes"/>it as a wholesome aliment. All the milky juices of<lb break="yes"/>plants being acrid, bitter, and more or less poison-<lb break="no"/>ous, this assertion appeared to us very extraordi-<lb break="no" />nary; but we found, by experience, during our<lb break="yes"/>stay at Barbula, that the virtues of the <hi rendition="#i">palo de vaca</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>had not been exaggerated. This fine tree rises<lb break="yes" />like the broad-leaved star-apple. Its oblong and<lb break="yes"/>pointed leaves, tough and alternate, are marked by<lb break="yes"/>lateral ribs, prominent at the lower surface, and<lb break="yes"/>parallel; they are some of them ten inches long.<lb break="yes"/>We did not see the flower: the fruit is somewhat<lb break="yes"/>fleshy, and contains one, or sometimes two nuts.<lb break="yes"/>When incisions are made in the trunk of the Cow-<lb break="no" />Tree, it yields abundance of a glutinous milk,<lb break="yes"/>tolerably thick, destitute of all acrimony, and of<lb break="yes"/>an agreeable and balmy smell. It was offered to<lb break="yes"/>us in the shell of the <hi rendition="#i">tutumo,</hi> or calabash-tree.<lb break="yes"/>We drank considerable quantities of it in the<lb break="yes"/>evening before we went to bed, and very early in<lb break="yes"/>the morning, without feeling the least injurious<lb break="yes"/>effect. The ropiness of this milk alone renders it<lb break="yes"/>a little disagreeable. The negroes and the free<lb break="yes"/>people, who work in the plantations, drink it, dip-<lb break="no"/>ping into it their bread of maize or cassava. The<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">major domo</hi> of the farm <choice><sic>farm</sic><corr type="editorial"></corr></choice> told us, that the<lb break="yes"/>negroes grow sensibly fatter during the season<lb break="yes" />when the <hi rendition="#i">palo de vaca</hi> furnishes them with most<lb break="yes"/>milk.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This juice, exposed to the air, presents at its<lb break="yes"/>surface, perhaps in consequence of the absorption<lb break="yes"/>of the atmospheric oxygen, membranes of a<lb break="yes"/>strongly animalized substance, yellowish, stringy,<lb break="yes"/>and resembling a cheesy substance; these mem-<lb break="no"/>branes, separated from the rest of the more<lb break="yes" />aqueous liquid, are elastic, almost like <hi rendition="#i" >caoutchouc</hi>;<lb break="yes"/>but they undergo, in time, the same phenomena of<lb break="yes"/>putrefaction as gelatine. The people call the<lb break="yes"/>coagulum that separates by the contact of the air,<lb break="yes"/>cheese; this coagulum grows sour in the space of<lb break="yes" />five or six days, as I observed in the small portions<lb break="yes"/>which I carried to Nueva Valencia.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This extraordinary tree appears to be peculiar to<lb break="yes"/>the Cordillera of the coast, particularly from Bar-<lb break="no"/>bula to the lake of Maracaybo. Some stocks of it<lb break="yes"/>exist near the village of San Mateo, and in the<lb break="yes"/>valley of Caucagua, three days&#x2019; journey east of<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas. At Caucagua, the natives call the tree<lb break="yes"/>that furnishes this nourishing juice the Milk-Tree.<lb break="yes"/>They profess to recognise, from the thickness and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>colour of the foliage the trunks that yield the most<lb break="yes"/>juice, as the herdsman distinguishes, from ex-<lb break="no"/>ternal signs, a good milch cow. It seems, ac-<lb break="no"/>cording to Mr. Kunth, to belong to the <hi rendition="#i">Sapota</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>family.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Amid the great number of curious phenomena<lb break="yes"/>which have presented themselves to me in the<lb break="yes"/>course of my travels, I confess there are few which<lb break="yes"/>have so powerfully affected my imagination as the<lb break="yes"/>aspect of the Cow-Tree. On the barren flank of a<lb break="yes"/>rock grows a tree, with coriaceous and dry leaves;<lb break="yes"/>its large woody roots can scarcely penetrate into<lb break="yes"/>the stone; for several months in the year not a<lb break="yes" />single shower moistens its foliage; its branches<lb break="yes"/>appear dead and dried; but when the trunk is<lb break="yes"/>pierced there flows from it a sweet nourishing<lb break="yes"/>milk. It is at the rising of the sun that this vege-<lb break="no"/>table fountain is most abundant; the blacks and<lb break="yes"/>natives are then seen hastening from all quarters,<lb break="yes"/>furnished with large bowls to receive the milk,<lb break="yes" />which grows yellow, and thickens at its surface;<lb break="yes"/>some empty their bowls near the tree itself, others<lb break="yes"/>carry the juice home to their children. We seem<lb break="yes"/>to behold the family of a shepherd, who distributes<lb break="yes"/>the milk of his flock.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i" >Humbolt&#x2019;s Personal Narra-<lb break="no"/>tive.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 