<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Scenery of South America</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:52</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.47</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1818-Curious_Circumstance-04-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-04-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-xx1-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 1, S. 370, 531, 611. [Es scheinen kleinere Ausschnitte zu sein, die zusammengefügt worden sind. Gefunden habe ich bisher den Anfang und zwei Stellen. Der Rest ist eine Zeitfrage. BZ]</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Scenery of South America</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1819</date>
          <pubPlace>Boston, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in:&lt;i&gt; New-England Galaxy &amp;amp; Masonic Magazine&lt;/i&gt; 2:73 (5. März 1819), S. 84.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="84" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>SCENERY OF SOUTH AMERICA</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#i">From the third volume of Humboldt&#x2019;s Person-<lb break="no" />al Travels.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When a traveller newly arrived from Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope penetrates for the first time into the for-<lb break="no"/>ests of South America, nature presents her-<lb break="no"/>self to him under an unexpected aspect.<lb break="yes" />The objects that surround him recall but<lb break="yes"/>feebly those pictures, which celebrated wri-<lb break="no"/>ters have traced on the banks of the Missis-<lb break="no"/>sippi, in Florida, and in other temperate re-<lb break="no"/>gions of the new world. He feels at every<lb break="yes"/>step that he is not on the confines, but in the<lb break="yes"/>centre of the torrid zone: not in one of the<lb break="yes"/>West India Islands but on a vast continent,<lb break="yes"/>where every thing is gigantic, the mountains<lb break="yes"/>the rivers, and the mass of vegetation. If<lb break="yes"/>he feel strongly the beauty of picturesque<lb break="yes"/>scenery, he can scarcely define the various<lb break="yes"/>emotions, which crowd upon his mind; he<lb break="yes"/>can scarcely distinguish what most excites<lb break="yes"/>his admiration, the deep silence of those<lb break="yes"/>solitudes, the individual beauty and contrast<lb break="yes"/>of forms, or that vigour and freshness of <choice><sic>vege-<lb break="no"/>able</sic><corr type="editorial">vege-<lb break="no"/>table</corr></choice> life, which characterise the climate of<lb break="yes"/>the tropics. It might be said that the earth,<lb break="yes" />overloaded with plants, does not allow them<lb break="yes"/>space enough to unfold themselves.&#x2014;The<lb break="yes"/>trunks of the trees are every where con-<lb break="no"/>cealed under a thick carpet of verdure; and<lb break="yes"/>if we carefully transplanted the orchidae,<lb break="yes"/>the pipers, and the pothos, which a single<lb break="yes"/>courbaril or American fig tree nourishes, we<lb break="yes"/>should cover a vast extent of ground. By<lb break="yes"/>this singular assemblage, the forests, as well<lb break="yes" />as the flanks of the rocks and mountains, en-<lb break="no"/>large the domain of organic nature. The<lb break="yes"/>same lianas as creep on the ground, reach<lb break="yes"/>the tops of the trees, and pass from one to<lb break="yes"/>another at the height of more than a hund-<lb break="no"/>red feet. Thus by a continual interplacing<lb break="yes"/>of parasite plants, the botanist is often led to<lb break="yes"/>confound the flowers, the fruits and leaves,<lb break="yes"/>which belong to different species.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We walked under the shade of these ar-<lb break="no"/>cades, that scarcely admit a glimpse of the<lb break="yes"/>sky, which appeared to me of an indigo<lb break="yes"/>blue, so much the deeper as the green of<lb break="yes"/>the equinoctial plants is generally of a strong-<lb break="no"/>er hue, with somewhat of a brownish tint.<lb break="yes"/>A great fern tree, very different from the<lb break="yes"/>polypodium arboreum of the West Indies,<lb break="yes" />rose above masses of scattered rocks. In<lb break="yes"/>this place we were struck for the first time<lb break="yes"/>with the sight of those nests in the shape of<lb break="yes"/>bottles, or small pockets, which are suspend-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/>ed to the branches of the lowest trees, and<lb break="yes"/>which attest the admirable industry of the<lb break="yes"/>orioles that mingle their warblings with the<lb break="yes"/>hoarse cries of the parrots and the macaws.<lb break="yes"/>These last, so well known for vivid colors<lb break="yes"/>fly only in pairs, while the real parrots wand-<lb break="no" />er about in flocks of several hundreds. A<lb break="yes"/>man must have lived in those climates, par-<lb break="no"/>ticularly in the hot valleys of the Andes, to<lb break="yes"/>conceive how these birds sometimes drown<lb break="yes"/>with their voice the noise of the torrents,<lb break="yes" />which rush down from rock to rock.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There is something so great, so powerful,<lb break="yes"/>in the impression made by nature in the cli-<lb break="no"/>mate of the Indies, that after an abode of a<lb break="yes"/>few months we seemed to have lived there<lb break="yes" />during a long succession of years. In Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope, the inhabitant of the north, and of the<lb break="yes"/>plains feels an almost similar emotion, when<lb break="yes"/>he quits even after a short abode the shores<lb break="yes"/>of the bay of Naples, the delicious country<lb break="yes" />between Tivoli and the lake of Nemi, or the<lb break="yes"/>wild and solemn scenery of the higher Alps<lb break="yes"/>and the Pyrenees. Yet every where under<lb break="yes"/>the temperate zone, the effects of the physi-<lb break="no"/>ognomy of the vegetables afford little con-<lb break="no" />trast. The firs and the oaks that crown the<lb break="yes"/>mountains of Sweden, have a certain family<lb break="yes"/>air with those that vegetate in the fine cli-<lb break="no"/>mates of Greece and Italy. Between the<lb break="yes"/>tropics on the contrary, in the lower regions<lb break="yes" />of both Indies, every thing in nature appears<lb break="yes"/>new and marvellous. In the open plains and<lb break="yes"/>amid the gloom of forests, almost all the re-<lb break="no"/>membrances of Europe are effaced; for it<lb break="yes"/>is the vegetation that determines the char-<lb break="no" />acter of a landscape, and acts upon our im-<lb break="no"/>agination by it&#x2019;s mass, the contrast of it&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>forms, and the glow of it&#x2019;s colours. In pro-<lb break="no"/>portion as impressions are powerful and new,<lb break="yes"/>they weaken antecedent impressions, and<lb break="yes"/>their strength gives them the appearance of<lb break="yes"/>duration. I appeal to those, who, more sen-<lb break="no"/>sible of the beauties of nature than of the<lb break="yes"/>charms of social life, have long resided<lb break="yes" />in the torrid zone. How dear, how <choice>
                        <sic>mem-<lb break="no"/>able</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">memor-<lb break="no"/>able</corr>
                    </choice> during life, is the land where they first<lb break="yes"/>embarked! A vague desire to visit that spot<lb break="yes"/>roots itself in their minds to the most advan-<lb break="no"/>ced age. Cumana and it&#x2019;s dusty soil are<lb break="yes"/>still more frequently present to my imagina-<lb break="no" />tion, than all the wonders of the Cordilleras.<lb break="yes"/>Beneath the fine sky of the south, the light<lb break="yes"/>and the magic of the aerial hues, embellish a<lb break="yes"/>land almost destitute of vegitation. The sun<lb break="yes"/>does not merely enlighten, it colours the<lb break="yes" />objects, and wraps them in a thin vapour,<lb break="yes"/>which, without changing the transparency<lb break="yes"/>of the air, renders it&#x2019;s tints more harmonious,<lb break="yes"/>softens the effects of the light, and diffuses<lb break="yes"/>over nature that calm, which is reflected in<lb break="yes"/>our souls. To explain this vivid impression,<lb break="yes" />which the aspect of the scenery of the two<lb break="yes"/>Indias produces, even on coasts where there<lb break="yes"/>is little wood, it will be sufficient to recol-<lb break="no"/>lect, that the beauty of the sky augments<lb break="yes"/>from Naples toward the equator, almost as<lb break="yes"/>much as from Provence toward the south of<lb break="yes"/>Italy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>While we take in at one view the vast<lb break="yes"/>landscape, we feel little regret, that the soli-<lb break="no"/>tudes of the New World are not embellish-<lb break="no"/>ed with the images of past times&#x2014;Wherev-<lb break="no"/>er, under the torrid zone, the earth, studded<lb break="yes" />with mountains and overspread with plants,<lb break="yes"/>has preserved it&#x2019;s primitive characteristics,<lb break="yes"/>man no longer appears as the centre of the<lb break="yes"/>creation.&#x2014;Far from taming the elements,<lb break="yes"/>all his efforts tend to escape from their em-<lb break="no" />pire. The changes made by savage nations<lb break="yes"/>during the lapse of ages on the surface of<lb break="yes"/>the globe disappear before those, that are<lb break="yes"/>produced in a few hours by the actions of<lb break="yes" />volcanic fires, the inundations of mighty<lb break="yes"/>floods, and the impetuosity of tempests. It<lb break="yes"/>is the conflict of the elements, which char-<lb break="no"/>acterizes in the New World the aspect of<lb break="yes"/>nature. A country without population ap-<lb break="no"/>pears to the people of cultivated Europe like<lb break="yes"/>a city abandoned by its inhabitants. In A-<lb break="no"/>merica after having lived during several<lb break="yes"/>years in the forests of the low regions, or<lb break="yes"/>on the ridge of the cordilleras; after having<lb break="yes"/>surveyed countries as extensive as France,<lb break="yes"/>containing only a small number of scattered<lb break="yes"/>huts; a deep solitude no longer affrights the<lb break="yes"/>imagination. We become accustomed to<lb break="yes"/>the idea of a world, that supports only plants<lb break="yes"/>and animals; where the savage has never<lb break="yes"/>uttered either the shout of joy, on the plain-<lb break="no"/>tive accent of inocence.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 