<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="65" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>THE GREAT CAVERN OF GUACHARO<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">in south america.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">Abridged from the interesting Narrative of Humbolt, vol. iii.</note>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> Cueva del Guacharo is pierced in the vertical<lb break="yes"/>profile of a rock. The entrance is toward the<lb break="yes" />south, and forms a vault eighty feet broad, and<lb break="yes"/>seventy-two <choice>
                        <sic>feeet</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">feet</corr>
                    </choice> high. The rock, that surmounts<lb break="yes"/>the grotto, is covered with trees of gigantic height.<lb break="yes"/>The mammee-tree, and the genipa with large<lb break="yes"/>and shining leaves, raise their branches vertically<lb break="yes"/>toward the sky; while those of the courbaril and<lb break="yes"/>the erythrina form, as they extend themselves, a<lb break="yes"/>thick vault of verdure. Plants of the family of<lb break="yes" />Pothos with succulent stems, oxalises, and orchide&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>of a singular structure, rise in the driest clefts of<lb break="yes"/>the rocks; while creeping plants, waving in the<lb break="yes"/>winds, are interwoven in festoons before the open-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="66" facs="#f0002"/>ing of the cavern. We distinguished in these<lb break="yes"/>festoons a bignonia of a violet blue, the purple<lb break="yes" />dolichos, and for the first time that <choice>
                        <sic>magnificen</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">magnificent</corr>
                    </choice>
                    <lb break="yes"/>olandra, the orange flower of which has a fleshy<lb break="yes" />tube more than four inches long. The entrances<lb break="yes"/>of grottoes, like the view of cascades, derive their<lb break="yes"/>principal charm from the situation, more or less<lb break="yes"/>majestic, in which they are placed, and which in<lb break="yes"/>some sort determines the character of the land-<lb break="no"/>scape. What a contrast between the Cueva of<lb break="yes" />Caripe, and those caverns of the North crowned<lb break="yes"/>with oaks and gloomy larch trees!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But this luxury of vegetation embellishes not<lb break="yes"/>only the outside of the vaults, it appears even in<lb break="yes"/>the vestibule of the grotto. We saw with astonish-<lb break="no"/>ment plaintain-leaved heliconias eighteen feet high,<lb break="yes"/>the praga palm-tree, and arborescent arums, follow<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the river even to these subterranean<lb break="yes"/>places. The vegetation continues in the cave of<lb break="yes" />Caripe, as in those deep crevices of the Andes, half<lb break="yes"/>excluded from the light of day; and does not<lb break="yes"/>disappear, till, advancing in the interior, we reach<lb break="yes"/>thirty or forty paces from the entrance. We<lb break="yes"/>measured the way by means of a cord; and we<lb break="yes"/>went on about four hundred and thirty feet, without<lb break="yes"/>being obliged to light our torches.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="67" facs="#f0003"/>
                <p>Daylight penetrates into this region, because<lb break="yes"/>the grotto forms but one channel, which keeps the<lb break="yes"/>same direction from south-east to north-west.<lb break="yes"/>Where the light begins to fail, we heard from afar<lb break="yes"/>the hoarse sounds of the nocturnal birds, sounds<lb break="yes"/>which the natives think belong exclusively to those<lb break="yes"/>subterraneous places. The guacharo is the size of<lb break="yes"/>our fowls, has the mouth of the goatsuckers and<lb break="yes" />procnias, and the port of those vultures, the crooked<lb break="yes"/>beak of which is surrounded with stiff silky hairs.<lb break="yes"/>It is difficult to form an idea of the horrible noise<lb break="yes"/>occasioned by thousands of these birds in the dark<lb break="yes"/>part of the cavern, and which can only be compared<lb break="yes"/>to the croaking of our crows, which, in the pine<lb break="yes"/>forests of the north, live in society, and construct<lb break="yes"/>their nests upon trees, the tops of which touch each<lb break="yes"/>other. The shrill and piercing cries of the gua-<lb break="no" />charos strike upon the vaults of the rocks, and<lb break="yes"/>are repeated by the echo in the depth of the<lb break="yes"/>cavern. The Indians shewed us the nests of these<lb break="yes"/>birds, by fixing torches to the end of a long pole.<lb break="yes"/>These nests were fifty or sixty feet high above our<lb break="yes"/>heads, in holes in the shape of funnels, with which<lb break="yes"/>the roof of the grotto is pierced like a sieve. The<lb break="yes"/>noise increased as we advanced, and the birds were<lb break="yes"/>affrighted by the light of the torches of copal.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="68" facs="#f0004"/>When this noise ceased around us, we heard at a<lb break="yes"/>distance the plaintive cries of the birds roosting in<lb break="yes"/>other ramifications of the cavern.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Indians enter into the Cueva del Guacharo<lb break="yes"/>once a-year, near midsummer, armed with poles,<lb break="yes"/>by means of which they destroy the greater part of<lb break="yes"/>the nests. At this season several thousands of birds<lb break="yes"/>are killed; and the old ones to defend their brood,<lb break="yes"/>hover around the heads of the savage Indians,<lb break="yes" />uttering terrible cries, which would appal any heart<lb break="yes"/>but that of man in an untutored state.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We followed, as we continued our progress<lb break="yes"/>through the cavern, the bank of the small river<lb break="yes"/>which issued from it, and is from twenty-eight to<lb break="yes"/>thirty feet wide. We walked on the banks, as far<lb break="yes"/>as the hills formed of calcareous incrustations per-<lb break="no"/>mitted us. Where the torrent winds among very<lb break="yes" />high masses of stalactites, we were often obliged to<lb break="yes"/>descend into its bed, which is only two feet in<lb break="yes"/>depth. We learnt, with surprise, that this subterrane-<lb break="no"/>ous rivulet is the origin of the river Caripe, which,<lb break="yes"/>at a few leagues distance, after having joined the<lb break="yes"/>smaller river of Santa Maria, is navigable for<lb break="yes"/>canoes. It enters into the river Areo under the<lb break="yes" />name of <hi rendition="#i">Canno de Terezen.</hi> We found on the<lb break="yes"/>banks of the subterraneous rivulet a great quantity<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="69" facs="#f0005"/>of palm-tree wood, the remains of trunks, on which<lb break="yes"/>the Indians climb to reach the nests hanging to the<lb break="yes"/>roofs of the cavern. The rings formed by the<lb break="yes" />vestiges of the old foot-stalks of the leaves, furnished<lb break="yes"/>as it were the footsteps of a ladder perpendicularly<lb break="yes"/>placed.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Grotto of Caripe preserves the same direc-<lb break="no"/>tion, the same breadth, and its primitive height of<lb break="yes"/>sixty or seventy feet, to the distance of 1,458 feet,<lb break="yes"/>accurately measured. I have never seen a cavern<lb break="yes"/>in either continent, of so uniform and regular a con-<lb break="no"/>struction. We had great difficulty in persuading<lb break="yes"/>the Indians to pass beyond the outer part of the<lb break="yes" />grotto, the only part which they <choice>
                        <sic>anuually</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">annually</corr>
                    </choice> visit to<lb break="yes"/>collect the fat. The whole authority of <hi rendition="#i">los padres</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>was necessary, to induce them to proceed as far as<lb break="yes"/>the spot where the soil rises abruptly at an inclina-<lb break="no"/>tion of sixty degrees, and where the torrent forms a<lb break="yes"/>small subterraneous cascade. The natives connect<lb break="yes" />mystic ideas with this cave, inhabited with noctur-<lb break="no"/>nal birds; they believe, that the souls of their an-<lb break="no"/>cestors sojourn in the deep recesses of the cavern.<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Man,&#x201D; say they, &#x201C;should avoid places which are<lb break="yes"/>enlightened neither by the Sun nor by the Moon.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the point where the river forms the subter-<lb break="no"/>raneous cascade, a hill covered with vegetation,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="70" facs="#f0006"/>which is opposite the opening of the grotto, pre-<lb break="no"/>sents itself in a very picturesque manner. It ap-<lb break="no" />pears at the extremity of a straight passage, 240<lb break="yes"/>toises in length. The stalactites, which descend<lb break="yes"/>from the vault, and which resemble columns sus-<lb break="no"/>pended in the air, display themselves on a back-<lb break="no"/>ground of verdure. The opening of this cavern<lb break="yes"/>appeared singularly contracted, when we saw it<lb break="yes" />about the middle of the day, illumined by the<lb break="yes"/>vivid light reflected at once from the sky, the<lb break="yes"/>plants, and the rocks. The distant light of day<lb break="yes"/>formed somewhat of magical contrast with the<lb break="yes"/>darkness that surrounded us in those vast caverns.<lb break="yes"/>We climbed, not without some difficulty, the small<lb break="yes"/>hill, whence the subterraneous rivulet descends.<lb break="yes" />We saw that the grotto was perceptibly contracted,<lb break="yes"/>retaining only forty feet in height; and that it<lb break="yes"/>continued stretching to the north-east, without<lb break="yes"/>deviating from its primitive direction, which is<lb break="yes"/>parallel to that of the great valley of Caripe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The missionaries, with all their authority, could<lb break="yes"/>not induce the Indians to penetrate farther into the<lb break="yes"/>cavern. As the vaults grow lower, the cries of the<lb break="yes"/>guacharoes become more shrill. We were obliged<lb break="yes"/>to yield to the pusillanimity of our guides, and re-<lb break="no"/>trace our steps. We followed the course of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="71" facs="#f0007"/>torrent to go out of the cavern. Before our eyes<lb break="yes"/>were dazzled with the light of day, we saw, outside<lb break="yes"/>the grotto, the water of the river sparkling amid<lb break="yes"/>the foliage of the trees that concealed it. Having<lb break="yes"/>at length reached the entrance, and seated our-<lb break="no" />selves on the bank of the rivulet, we rested after<lb break="yes"/>our fatigues. We were glad to be beyond the<lb break="yes"/>hoarse cries of the birds, and to leave a place where<lb break="yes"/>darkness does not offer even the charm of silence<lb break="yes"/>and tranquillity.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 