<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">the palo de vaca or cow-tree.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We had heard, several weeks before, of a tree, the<lb break="yes"/>sap of which is a nourishing milk. It is called &#x2018;the<lb break="yes"/>cow-tree&#x2019;; and we were assured that the negroes of<lb break="yes"/>the farm, who drink plentifully of this vegetable milk,<lb break="yes"/>consider it a wholesome aliment. All the milky<lb break="yes"/>juices of plants being acrid, bitter, and more or less<lb break="yes"/>poisonous, this account appeared to us very extra-<lb break="no"/>ordinary; but we found by experience during our<lb break="yes"/>stay at Barbula, that the virtues of this tree had not<lb break="yes"/>been exaggerated. This fine tree rises like the broad-<lb break="no"/>leaved star-apple. Its oblong and pointed leaves,<lb break="yes" />rough and alternate, are marked by lateral ribs,<lb break="yes"/>prominent at the lower surface, and parallel<choice>
                        <sic/>
                        <corr type="editorial">.</corr>
                    </choice> Some<lb break="yes"/>of them are ten inches long. We did not see the<lb break="yes"/>flower: the fruit is somewhat fleshy, and contains<lb break="yes"/>one and sometimes two nuts. When incisions are<lb break="yes" />made in the trunk of this tree, it yields abundance<lb break="yes"/>of a glutinous milk, tolerably thick, devoid of all<lb break="yes"/>acridity, and of an agreeable and balmy smell.<lb break="yes"/>It was offered to us in the shell of a Calabash. We<lb break="yes"/>drank considerable quantities of it in the evening<lb break="yes"/>before we went to bed, and very early in the morn-<lb break="no"/>ing, without feeling the least injurious effect. The<lb break="yes"/>viscosity of this milk alone renders it a little dis-<lb break="no"/>agreeable. The negroes and the free people who<lb break="yes" />work in the plantations drink it, dipping into it<lb break="yes"/>their bread of maize or cassava. The overseer of the<lb break="yes"/>farm told us that the negroes grow sensibly fatter<lb break="yes"/>during the season when the <hi rendition="#i">palo de vaca</hi> furnishes<lb break="yes"/>them with most milk. This juice, exposed to the<lb break="yes"/>air, presents at its surface (perhaps in conse-<lb break="no"/>quence of the absorption of the atmospheric<lb break="yes"/>oxygen) membranes of a strongly animalised sub-<lb break="no" />stance, yellowish, stringy, and resembling cheese.<lb break="yes"/>These membranes, separated from the rest of the<lb break="yes"/>more aqueous liquid, are elastic, almost like caout-<lb break="no"/>chouc; but they undergo, in time, the same pheno-<lb break="no"/>mena of putrefaction as gelatine. The people call<lb break="yes"/>the coagulum that separates by the contact of the<lb break="yes"/>air, cheese. This coagulum grows sour in the space<lb break="yes"/>of five or six days, as I observed in the small por-<lb break="no"/>tions which I carried to Nueva Valencia. The milk<lb break="yes" />contained in a stopped phial, had deposited a litte<lb break="yes" />coagulum; and, far from becoming fetid, it exhaled<lb break="yes"/>constantly a balsamic odour. The fresh juice mixed<lb break="yes"/>with cold water was scarcely coagulated at all; but on<lb break="yes"/>the contact of nitric acid the separation of the viscous<lb break="yes"/>membranes took place. We sent two bottles of this milk to M. Fourcry at Paris: in one<choice>
                        <sic/>
                        <corr type="editorial">,</corr>
                    </choice> it was in its natu-<lb break="no"/>ral state, and in the other, mixed with a certain<lb break="yes"/>quantity of carbonate of soda. The French consul<lb break="yes"/>residing in the island of St. Thomas, undertook to<lb break="yes"/>convey them to him.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The extraordinary tree of which we have been<lb break="yes"/>speaking appears to be peculiar to the Cordillera<lb break="yes"/>of the coast, particularly from Barbula to the lake<lb break="yes"/>of Maracaybo. Some stocks of it exist near the<lb break="yes"/>village of San Mateo; and, according to M. Brede-<lb break="no"/>meyer, whose travels have so much enriched the<lb break="yes" />fine conservatories of Schonbrunn and Vienna, in the<lb break="yes"/>valley of Caucagua, 3 days journey east of Caracas.<lb break="yes"/>This naturalist found, like us, that the vegetable<lb break="yes"/>milk of the <hi rendition="#i">palo de vaca</hi> had an agreeable taste<lb break="yes"/>and an aromatic smell. At Caucagua, the natives<lb break="yes"/>call the tree that furnishes this nourishing juice, &#x2018;the<lb break="yes"/>milk tree&#x2019; (arbol del leche). They profess to recog-<lb break="no"/>nize, from the thickness and colour of the foliage,<lb break="yes"/>the trunks that yield the most juice; as the herds-<lb break="no"/>man distinguishes, from external signs, a good<lb break="yes"/>milch cow. No botanist has hitherto known the<lb break="yes" />existence of this plant. It seems, according to M.<lb break="yes"/>Kunth, to belong to the sapota family. Long after<lb break="yes"/>my return to Europe, I found in the Description<lb break="yes"/>of the East Indies by Laet, a Dutch Traveller, a<lb break="yes"/>passage that seems to have some relation to the cow-<lb break="no"/>tree. &#x201C;There exist trees,&#x201D; says Laet, &#x201C;in the province<lb break="yes"/>of Cumana, the sap of which much resembles curdled<lb break="yes"/>milk, and affords a salubrious nourishment.&#x201C;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Amidst the great number of curious phenomena<lb break="yes"/>which I have observed in the course of my travels,<lb break="yes"/>I confess there are few that have made so powerful<lb break="yes"/>an impression on me as the aspect of the cow-tree.<lb break="yes"/>Whatever relates to milk or to corn, inspires an inte-<lb break="no"/>rest which is not merely that of the physical know-<lb break="no"/>ledge of things, but is connected with another order<lb break="yes"/>of ideas and sentiments. We can scarcely conceive<lb break="yes"/>how the human race could exist without farinaceous<lb break="yes"/>substances, and without that nourishing juices which<lb break="yes"/>the breast of the mother contains, and which is <choice><sic>ap-<lb break="no"/>priated</sic><corr type="editorial">ap-<lb break="no"/>propriated</corr></choice> to the long feebleness of the infant. The<lb break="yes" />amylaceous matter of corn, the object of religious<lb break="yes"/>veneration among so many nations, ancient and<lb break="yes"/>modern, is diffused in the seeds, and deposited in<lb break="yes"/>the roots of vegetables; milk which serves as an<lb break="yes"/>aliment, appears to us exclusively the produce of<lb break="yes"/>animal organisation. Such are the impressions<lb break="yes"/>we have received in our earliest infancy: such is<lb break="yes"/>also the source of that astonishment created by the<lb break="yes"/>aspect of the tree just described. It is not here the<lb break="yes"/>solemn shades of forests, the majestic course of<lb break="yes" />rivers, the mountains wrapped in eternal snow, that<lb break="yes"/>excite our emotion. A few drops of vegetable<lb break="yes"/>juice recall to our minds all the powerfulness and the<lb break="yes"/>fecundity of nature. On the barren flank of a rock<lb break="yes"/>grows a tree with coriaceous and dry leaves. Its<lb break="yes"/>large woody roots can scarcely penetrate into the<lb break="yes"/>stone. For several months of the year not a single<lb break="yes"/>shower moistens its foliage. Its branches appear<lb break="yes" />dead and dried; but when the trunk is pierced there<lb break="yes"/>flows from it a sweet and nourishing milk. It is at<lb break="yes"/>the rising of the sun that this vegetable fountain is<lb break="yes"/>most abundant. The negroes and natives are then seen<lb break="yes"/>hastening from all quarters, furnished with large<lb break="yes"/>bowls to receive the milk, which grows yellow, and<lb break="yes"/>thickens at its surface. Some empty their bowls<lb break="yes" />under the tree itself, others carry the juice home to<lb break="yes"/>their children.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels, in Bohn&#x2019;s Scien-<lb break="no"/>tific Library.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 