<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="85" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">CHARACTER OF SOUTH AMERICAN POP-<lb break="no"/>ULATION.<lb break="yes"/>From Humboldt&#x2019;s Personal Travels.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Although</hi>
                    </hi> I had the advantage, which<lb break="yes"/>few Spaniards have shared with me, of hav-<lb break="no"/>ing successively visited Caraccas, the Ha-<lb break="no"/>vannah, Santa Fe de Bogota, Quito, Lima,<lb break="yes"/>and Mexico, and of having been connected<lb break="yes"/>in these six capitals of Spanish America<lb break="yes"/>with men of all ranks, I shall venture to de-<lb break="no"/>cide on the various degrees of civilization,<lb break="yes" />which society has attained in the different<lb break="yes"/>colonies. It is easier to indicate the differ-<lb break="no"/>ent shades of national improvement, and the<lb break="yes"/>point toward which the unfolding of the in-<lb break="no"/>tellect tends in preference, than to compare<lb break="yes"/>and class things that cannot be investigated<lb break="yes" />under the same point of view. It appeared<lb break="yes"/>to me, that a strong tendency toward the<lb break="yes"/>study of the sciences prevailed at Mexico<lb break="yes"/>and Santa Fe de Bogota; more taste for lit-<lb break="no" />erature, and whatever can charm an ardent<lb break="yes"/>and lively imagination, at Quito and Lima;<lb break="yes"/>more accurate notions of the political rela-<lb break="no"/>tions of countries, and more enlarged views<lb break="yes"/>on the state of colonies and their mother<lb break="yes" />countries, at the Havannah and Caraccas.<lb break="yes"/>The numerous communications with com-<lb break="no"/>mercial Europe, with that sea of the West<lb break="yes"/>Indies, which we have described as a medi-<lb break="no"/>terranean with many outlets, have had a pow-<lb break="no" />erful influence on the progress of society in<lb break="yes"/>the island of Cuba, and in the five provinces<cb/>of Venezuela. Civilization has in no other<lb break="yes"/>part of Spanish America assumed a more<lb break="yes"/>European physiognomy. The great number<lb break="yes"/>of Indian cultivaters who inhabit Mexico and<lb break="yes"/>the interior of New Grenada, have impressed<lb break="yes"/>a peculiar, I might say an exotic character,<lb break="yes"/>on those vast countries. Notwithstanding<lb break="yes"/>the increase of the black population, we<lb break="yes"/>seem to be nearer Cadiz and the United<lb break="yes"/>States at Caraccas and the Havannah, than in<lb break="yes"/>any other part of the New World.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Caraccas being situate on the continent,<lb break="yes"/>and its population less mutable than that of<lb break="yes"/>the islands, the national manners have been<lb break="yes"/>better preserved than at the Havannah. So-<lb break="no"/>ciety does not present very animated and<lb break="yes"/>varied pleasures; but that feeling of com-<lb break="no"/>fort is experienced in domestic life, which<lb break="yes"/>leads to uniform cheerfulness and cordiality<lb break="yes"/>united with politeness of manners. There<lb break="yes"/>exists at Caraccas, as in every place where<lb break="yes"/>a great change in the ideas is preparing, two<lb break="yes"/>races of men, we might say two distinct gen-<lb break="no"/>erations; one of which, but a small number<lb break="yes"/>remains, preserves a strong attachment for<lb break="yes"/>ancient customs, simplicity of manners, and<lb break="yes" />moderation in their desires. They live only<lb break="yes"/>in the images of the past. America appears<lb break="yes"/>to them a property conquered by their an-<lb break="no"/>cestors. Abhorring what is called the en-<lb break="no" />lightened state of the age, they carefully<lb break="yes"/>preserve hereditary prejudices as a part of<lb break="yes"/>their patrimony. The other class, less oc-<lb break="no"/>cupied even by the present than by the fu-<lb break="no"/>ture, have a propensity, often ill-judged, for<lb break="yes"/>new habits and ideas. When this tendency<lb break="yes"/>is allied to the love of solid instruction, re-<lb break="no"/>strained and guided by a strong and enlight-<lb break="no"/>ened reason, its effects become beneficial to<lb break="yes" />society. I knew at Caraccas, among the<lb break="yes"/>second generation, several men equally dis-<lb break="no"/>tinguished by their taste for study, the mild-<lb break="no"/>ness of their manners, and the elevation of<lb break="yes"/>their sentiments. I have also known men,<lb break="yes"/>who, disdaining all that is excellent in the<lb break="yes"/>character, the literature, and the arts of the<lb break="yes"/>Spaniards, have lost their national individu-<lb break="no"/>ality, without having acquired from their<lb break="yes"/>connexions with foreigners any just ideas of<lb break="yes" />the real bases of happiness and social order.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Since the reign of Charles V. the corpo-<lb break="no"/>ration spirit and municipal habits having<lb break="yes"/>passed from the mother country to the col-<lb break="no"/>onies, men take a pleasure at Cumana, and<lb break="yes" />in other commercial towns of Terra Firma,<lb break="yes"/>in exaggerating the pretensions to nobility<lb break="yes"/>of the most illustrious families of Caraccas,<lb break="yes"/>known by the name of <hi rendition="#i">los Mantuanos.</hi> I am<lb break="yes"/>ignorant in what manner these pretensions<lb break="yes"/>were formerly manifested; but it appeared<lb break="yes"/>to me, that the progress of knowledge, and<lb break="yes"/>the change effected in manners, have grad-<lb break="no"/>ually and pretty generally destroyed what-<lb break="no"/>ever is offensive in those distinctions among<lb break="yes"/>the whites. In all the colonies there exist<lb break="yes"/>two kinds of nobility. One is composed of<lb break="yes"/>the Creoles, whose ancestors have very re-<lb break="no"/>cently filled great stations in America. Their<lb break="yes"/>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>perogatives</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">prerogatives</corr>
                    </choice> are partly founded on the dis-<lb break="no"/>tinction they enjoy in the mother country;<lb break="yes"/>and they imagine they can retain them be-<lb break="no"/>yond the sea, whatever may be the date of<lb break="yes"/>their settlement in the colonies. The other<lb break="yes"/>nobility <choice>
                        <sic>hss</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">has</corr>
                    </choice> more of an American cast. It<lb break="yes"/>is composed of the descendants of the <hi rendition="#i">Con-<lb break="no"/>quistadores,</hi> that is to say, of the Spaniards<lb break="yes"/>who served in the army at the time of the<lb break="yes"/>first conquest. Among the warriors who<lb break="yes" />fought with Cortez, Losada, and Pizarro, se-<lb break="no"/>veral belonged to the most distinguished<lb break="yes"/>families of the peninsula; others, born in<lb break="yes"/>the inferior classes of the people, have il-<lb break="no"/>lustrated their names by that chivalrous<lb break="yes"/>spirit, which prevailed at the beginning of<lb break="yes"/>the sixteenth century. I have elsewhere<lb break="yes"/>observed, that in the records of those times<lb break="yes"/>of religious and military enthusiasm, we find<lb break="yes" />among the followers of the great captains,<lb break="yes"/>many simple, virtuous, and generous char-<lb break="no"/>acters, who reprobated the cruelties that<lb break="yes"/>stained the glory of the Spanish name, but<lb break="yes"/>who, confounded in the mass, have not es-<lb break="no"/>caped the general proscription. The name<lb break="yes"/>of <hi rendition="#i">Conquistadores</hi> remains the more odious,<lb break="yes"/>as the greater number of them, after having<lb break="yes"/>outraged peaceful nations, and lived in the<lb break="yes"/>midst of opulence, did not experience to-<lb break="no"/>ward the end of their career, those long mis-<lb break="no" />fortunes, which appease the hatred of man-<lb break="no"/>kind, and sometimes soften the severity of<lb break="yes"/>the historian.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But it is not only the progress of ideas,<lb break="yes"/>and the conflict between two classes of dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent origin, which have induced the priv-<lb break="no"/>ileged casts to abandon their pretensions, or<lb break="yes"/>at least to conceal them carefully. Aris-<lb break="no" />tocracy in the Spanish colonies has a coun-<lb break="no"/>terpoise of another kind, and of which the<lb break="yes"/>action becomes every day more powerful. A<lb break="yes"/>sentiment of equality among the whites has<lb break="yes" />penetrated every bosom. Wherever men of<lb break="yes"/>colour are either considered as slaves, or<lb break="yes"/>as having been enfranchised, what constitutes<lb break="yes"/>nobility is hereditary liberty, is the proud<lb break="yes"/>boast of having never reckoned among an-<lb break="no"/>cestors any but freemen. In the colonies,<lb break="yes"/>the colour of the skin is the real badge of<lb break="yes"/>nobility, In Mexico, as well as Peru, at<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas as in the island of Cuba, a barefoot-<lb break="no" />ed fellow is often heard exclaiming: &#x201C;Does<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="86" facs="#f0002"/>that rich white man think himself whiter than<lb break="yes"/>I am?&#x201D; The population which Europe pours<lb break="yes"/>into America, being very considerable, it<lb break="yes"/>may easily be supposed, that the axiom, ev-<lb break="no"/>ery white man is noble, <hi rendition="#i">toto blanco es cabal-<lb break="no"/>ero,</hi> must singularly wound the pretensions<lb break="yes"/>of a great number of ancient and illustrious<lb break="yes"/>European familes. But we may observe<lb break="yes"/>farther that the truth of this axiom has long<lb break="yes"/>since been recognized in Spain, among a<lb break="yes"/>people justly celebrated for probity, industry<lb break="yes"/>and national spirit. Every Biscayan calls<lb break="yes" />himself noble; and there being a greater<lb break="yes"/>number of Biscayans in America and the<lb break="yes"/>Philippine Islands, than in the peninsula, the<lb break="yes"/>whites of this race have contributed in no<lb break="yes"/>small degree, to propagate in the colonies<lb break="yes"/>the system of equality among all men, whose<lb break="yes"/>blood has not been contaminated by the Af-<lb break="no"/>rican race.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Moreover, the countries of which the in-<lb break="no"/>habitants, even without a representative<lb break="yes"/>government, or any institution of peerage,<lb break="yes"/>annex so much importance to genealogy, and<lb break="yes"/>the advantages of birth, are not always those<lb break="yes"/>where the aristocracy of families is the most<lb break="yes"/>offensive. We should seek in vain among<lb break="yes"/>the natives of Spanish origin that cold and<lb break="yes"/>assuming air, which the character of modern<lb break="yes" />civilization seems to have rendered more<lb break="yes"/>common in the rest of Europe. Conviviality,<lb break="yes"/>candour, and a great simplicity of manners,<lb break="yes"/>unite the different classes of society in the<lb break="yes"/>colonies, as well as in the mother country.<lb break="yes"/>We might even venture to say, that the ex-<lb break="no"/>pressions of vanity and self-love are less of-<lb break="no"/>fensive, when they retain something of sim-<lb break="no"/>plicity and frankness.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I found in several families at Caraccas, a<lb break="yes"/>taste for instruction, a knowledge of the<lb break="yes"/>master-pieces of French and Italian litera-<lb break="no"/>ture, and a particular <choice>
                        <sic>predeliction</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">predilection</corr>
                    </choice> for music,<lb break="yes"/>which is cultivated with success, and which,<lb break="yes"/>as it always happens in the pursuit of the<lb break="yes"/>fine arts, serves to bring the different classes<lb break="yes" />of society nearer each other. The mathe-<lb break="no"/>matical sciences, drawing, painting, cannot<lb break="yes"/>here boast of any of those establishments,<lb break="yes"/>with which royal munificence, and the pa-<lb break="no"/>triotic zeal of the inhabitants have enriched<lb break="yes" />Mexico. In the midst of the marvels of<lb break="yes"/>Nature, so rich in productions, no person<lb break="yes"/>on this coast was devoted to the study of<lb break="yes"/>plants and minerals. In a convent of St.<lb break="yes" />Francis alone, I met with a respectable old<lb break="yes"/>gentleman, who calculated the almanac for<lb break="yes"/>all the provinces of Venezuela, and who<lb break="yes"/>possessed some precise ideas on the state<lb break="yes" />of modern astronomy. Our instruments in-<lb break="no"/>terested him deeply, and one day our house<lb break="yes"/>was filled with all the monks of St. Francis,<lb break="yes"/>begging to see a dipping-needle. The cu-<lb break="no"/>riosity that dwells on physical phenomena is<lb break="yes" />augmented in countries undermined by vol-<lb break="no"/>canic fires, and in a climate where nature is<lb break="yes"/>at once so overwhelming, and so mysterious-<lb break="no"/>ly agitated.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 