<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="286" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>MILK, BREAD AND BUTTER TREES.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We had heard several weeks before of a tree,<lb break="yes"/>the sap of which is a nourishing milk. It is<lb break="yes"/>called “the cow tree,” and we were assured<lb break="yes"/>that the negroes of the farm, who drink plenti-<lb break="no"/>fully of this vegetable milk, consider it a whole-<lb break="no" />some aliment. All the milky juices of plants<lb break="yes"/>being acrid, bitter, and more or less poisonous,<lb break="yes"/>this account seemed to us very extraordinary;<lb break="yes"/>but we found, by experience, during our stay<lb break="yes"/>at Barbula, that the virtues of this tree had not<lb break="yes"/>been exaggerated. This fine tree rises like the<lb break="yes" />broad-leaved star-apple. Its oblong and pointed<lb break="yes"/>leaves, rough and alternate, are marked by late-<lb break="no"/>ral ribs, prominent at the lower surface and<lb break="yes"/>parallel. Some of them are ten inches long.<lb break="yes"/>We did not see the flower; the fruit is some-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/>what fleshy, and contains one and sometimes<lb break="yes"/>two nuts. When incisions are made in the<lb break="yes"/>trunk of this tree, it yields an abundance of a<lb break="yes"/>glutinous milk, tolerably thick, devoid of all<lb break="yes"/>acridity, and of an agreeable and balmy smell.<lb break="yes" />It was offered to us in the shell of a calabash.<lb break="yes"/>We drank considerable quantities of it in the<lb break="yes"/>evening before we went to bed, and very early<lb break="yes"/>in the morning, without feeling the least inju-<lb break="no"/>rious effect. The viscosity of this milk alone<lb break="yes"/>renders it a little disagreeable. The negroes<lb break="yes" />and the free people who work in the plantations<lb break="yes"/>drink it, dipping into it their bread of maize or<lb break="yes"/>cassava. The overseer of the farm told us that<lb break="yes"/>the negroes grow sensibly fatter during the<lb break="yes"/>season when the palo de vaca furnishes them<lb break="yes"/>with most milk. This juice, exposed to the air,<lb break="yes" />presents at its surface (perhaps in consequence<lb break="yes"/>of the absorption of the atmospherie oxygen)<lb break="yes"/>membranes of a strongly animalized substance,<lb break="yes"/>yellow, somewhat resembling cheese. These<lb break="yes"/>membranes, separated from the rest of the<lb break="yes"/>more aqueous liquid, are elastic, almost like<lb break="yes" />caoutchouc; but they undergo the same phe-<lb break="no"/>nomena of putrefaction as gelatine. The people<lb break="yes"/>call the coagulum, that separates by the contact<lb break="yes"/>of the air, cheese. The coagulum grows sour<lb break="yes"/>in the space of five or six days. Amidst the<lb break="yes"/>great number of curicus phenomena which I<lb break="yes"/>have observed in the course of my travels, I<lb break="yes"/>confess there are few that have made so power-<lb break="no"/>ful an impression on me as the aspect of the<lb break="yes"/>cow tree. Whatever relates to milk or to corn<lb break="yes"/>inspires an interest which is not merely that of<lb break="yes" />the physical knowledge of things, but is con-<lb break="no"/>nected with another order of ideas and senti-<lb break="no"/>ments. We can scarcely conceive how the human<lb break="yes"/>race could exist without farinaceous substances,<lb break="yes"/>and without that nourishing juice which the<lb break="yes"/>breast of the mother contains, and which is ap-<lb break="no" />propriated to the long feebleness of the infant.<lb break="yes"/>The amylaccous matter of corn, the object of<lb break="yes"/>religious veneration among so many nations,<lb break="yes"/>ancient and modern, is diffused in the seeds,<lb break="yes"/>and deposited in the roots of vegetables; milk<lb break="yes"/>which serves as an aliment, appears to us ex-<lb break="no" />clusively the produce of animal organization.<lb break="yes"/>Such are the impressions we have received in<lb break="yes"/>our earliest infancy; such is also the source of<lb break="yes"/>that astonishment created by the aspect of the<lb break="yes"/>tree just described. It is not here the solemn<lb break="yes"/>shades of forests, the majestic course of rivers,<lb break="yes"/>the mountains wrapped in eternal snow, that<lb break="yes" />excite our emotion. A few drops of vegetable<lb break="yes"/>juice recal to our minds all the powerfulness<lb break="yes"/>and the fecundity of nature. On the barren<lb break="yes"/>flank of a rock grows a tree with coriaceous and<lb break="yes"/>dry leaves. Its large woody roots can scarcely<lb break="yes" />penetrate into the stone. For several months<lb break="yes"/>of the year, not a single shower moistens its<lb break="yes"/>foliage. Its branches appear dead and dried;<lb break="yes"/>but when the trunk is pierced, there flows from<lb break="yes"/>it a sweet and nourishing milk. It is at the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="287" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>rising of the sun that this vegetable fountain is<lb break="yes"/>most abundant; the negroes and natives are<lb break="yes"/>then seen hastening from all quarters, furnished<lb break="yes"/>with large bowls to receive the milk, which<lb break="yes"/>grows yellow, and thickens at its surface. Some<lb break="yes"/>empty their bowls under the tree itself, others<lb break="yes" />carry the juice home to their children.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt’s Travels in the Equinoctial Regions of<lb break="yes" />America.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 