<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent, During the Years 1799–1804</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:53</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.54</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1818-Personal_Narrative_of-1-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Personal_Narrative_of-1-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Personal_Narrative_of-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent&lt;/i&gt;, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 1, S. 512–594.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent, During the Years 1799–1804</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1818</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;Monthly Magazine, or, British Register&lt;/i&gt; 44:307 (Januar 1818), S. 590–600.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="590" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>PERSONAL NARRATIVE<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">of</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>TRAVELS<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">to the</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#i">EQUINOCTIAL REGIONS</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">of</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>THE NEW CONTINENT,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">During the Years</hi> 1799-1804,<lb break="yes"/>BY ALEXANDER DE HUMBOLDT,<lb break="yes"/>AND AIMÉ BONPLAND;<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">with maps, plans,</hi> &amp;c.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Written in French</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">By</hi> ALEXANDER DE HUMBOLDT,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">And translated into English</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">By</hi> HELEN MARIA WILLIAMS.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">vol. iii.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                </head>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#k">earthquake at cumana.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#in">F</hi>ROM the 28th of October to the<lb break="yes"/>3d of November, the reddish fog<lb break="yes"/>was thicker than it had yet been. The<lb break="yes"/>heat of the night seemed stifling, though<lb break="yes"/>the thermometer rose only to 26°. The<lb break="yes" />breeze, which generally cooled the air<lb break="yes"/>from eight or nine o’clock in the even-<lb break="no"/>ing, was no longer felt. The atmosphere<lb break="yes"/>appeared as if it were on fire. The<lb break="yes"/>ground, parched and dusty, was cracked<lb break="yes"/>on every side. On the fourth of Novem-<lb break="no"/>ber, about two in the afternoon, large<lb break="yes"/>clouds, of an extraordinary blackness,<lb break="yes"/>enveloped the high mountains of the<lb break="yes" />Brigantine and Tataraqual. They ex-<lb break="no"/>tended, by degrees, as far as the zenith.<lb break="yes"/>About four in the afternoon, thunder<lb break="yes"/>was heard over our heads, but at an im-<lb break="no"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">mense</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="591" facs="#f0002"/>
                        <cb/>mense height, without rolling, and with<lb break="yes"/>a hoarse and often interrupted sound.<lb break="yes"/>At the moment of the strongest electric<lb break="yes"/>explosion, at 4h. 12m. there were two<lb break="yes"/>shocks of an earthquake, which follow-<lb break="no"/>ed at fifteen seconds distance from each<lb break="yes"/>other. The people in the streets filled<lb break="yes"/>the air with their cries. Mr. Bonpland,<lb break="yes"/>who was leaning over a table examining<lb break="yes" />plants, was almost thrown on the floor.<lb break="yes"/>I felt the shock very strongly, though I<lb break="yes"/>was lying in a hammock. Its direction<lb break="yes"/>was from north to south, which is rare<lb break="yes"/>at Cumana. Slaves, who were drawing<lb break="yes"/>water from a well, more than eighteen<lb break="yes"/>or twenty feet deep, near the river<lb break="yes"/>Manzanares, heard a noise like the ex-<lb break="no"/>plosion of a strong charge of gunpowder.<lb break="yes"/>The noise seemed to come from the bot-<lb break="no"/>tom of the well, a very singular pheno-<lb break="no"/>menon, though very common in the<lb break="yes"/>greater part of the countries of America<lb break="yes" />exposed to earthquakes.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A few minutes before the first shock,<lb break="yes"/>there was a very violent blast of wind,<lb break="yes"/>followed by an electrical rain, in great<lb break="yes"/>drops. I immediately tried the atmos-<lb break="no"/>pherical electricity by the electrometer<lb break="yes"/>of Volta. The small balls separated<lb break="yes"/>four lines; the electricity often changed<lb break="yes"/>from positive to negative, as is the case<lb break="yes"/>during storms; and, in the north of<lb break="yes"/>Europe, even sometimes in a fall of snow.<lb break="yes"/>The sky remained cloudy, and the blast<lb break="yes"/>of wind was followed by a dead calm,<lb break="yes"/>which lasted all night. The setting of<lb break="yes"/>the sun presented a scene of extraordi-<lb break="no"/>nary magnificence. The thick veil of<lb break="yes"/>the clouds was rent asunder as in shreds,<lb break="yes"/>quite near the horizon: the sun appear-<lb break="no"/>ed at 12 degrees of altitude, on a firma-<lb break="no"/>ment of indigo-blue. Its disk was enor-<lb break="no"/>mously enlarged, distorted, and undulat-<lb break="no"/>ed toward the edges. The clouds were<lb break="yes"/>gilded; and fasciculi of divergent rays,<lb break="yes" />which reflected the most brilliant colours<lb break="yes"/>of the rainbow, extended even to the<lb break="yes"/>midst of the heavens. There was a great<lb break="yes"/>crowd in the public square. This phe-<lb break="no"/>nomenon, the earthquake, the clap of<lb break="yes"/>thunder which had accompanied it, the<lb break="yes"/>red vapour seen during so many days,<lb break="yes"/>all was regarded as the effect of the<lb break="yes"/>eclipse.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>About nine in the evening there was<lb break="yes"/>a third shock, much slighter than the<lb break="yes"/>former two, but attended evidently with<lb break="yes"/>a subterraneous noise. The barometer<lb break="yes"/>was a little lower than usual; but the<lb break="yes"/>progress of the horary variations or small<lb break="yes"/>atmospheric tides, was no way interrupt-<lb break="no"/>ed. The mercury was precisely at the<lb break="yes"/>minimum of height at the moment of the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/>earthquake; it continued rising till ele-<lb break="no"/>ven in the evening, and sunk again till<lb break="yes"/>half after four in the morning, conform-<lb break="no"/>ably to the law which regulates the baro-<lb break="no"/>metrical variations In the night be-<lb break="no"/>tween the 3d and 4th of November, the<lb break="yes"/>reddish vapour was so thick, that I<lb break="yes"/>could not distinguish the place of the<lb break="yes" />moon, except by a beautiful halo of 20°<lb break="yes"/>diameter.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It was scarcely twenty-two months<lb break="yes"/>since the town of Cumana had been al-<lb break="no"/>most totally destroyed by an earthquake.<lb break="yes"/>The people look on the vapours which<lb break="yes"/>darken the horizon, and the failure of the<lb break="yes"/>breeze during the night, as prognostics<lb break="yes"/>infallibly disastrous. We had frequent<lb break="yes"/>visits from persons, who wished to know<lb break="yes"/>if our instruments indicated new shocks<lb break="yes"/>for the next day. The inquietude was<lb break="yes"/>particularly great and general, when on<lb break="yes"/>the 5th of November, exactly at the same<lb break="yes" />hour as the preceding day, there was a<lb break="yes"/>violent gust of wind, attended by thun-<lb break="no"/>der, and a few drops of rain. No shock<lb break="yes"/>was felt. The wind and storm returned<lb break="yes"/>for five or six days at the same hour, al-<lb break="no" />most at the same minute. The inhabi-<lb break="no"/>tants of Cumana, and of many other<lb break="yes"/>places between the tropics, have long<lb break="yes"/>ago, made the observation, that those<lb break="yes" />atmospherical changes, which appear the<lb break="yes"/>most accidental, follow for whole weeks<lb break="yes"/>a certain type with astonishing regulari-<lb break="no"/>ty. The same phenomenon exists in<lb break="yes"/>summer, under the temperate zone;<lb break="yes"/>nor has it escaped the sagacity of astro-<lb break="no"/>nomers, who often see clouds form in a<lb break="yes"/>serene sky, during three or four days to-<lb break="no"/>gether, at the same part of the firma-<lb break="no" />ment, take the same direction, and dis-<lb break="no"/>solve at the same height; sometimes be-<lb break="no"/>fore, sometimes after, the passage of a<lb break="yes"/>star over the meridian, consequently<lb break="yes" />within a few minutes of the same point<lb break="yes"/>of apparent time.<note place="foot" n="*">Mr. Arago and I paid a great deal<lb break="yes"/>of attention to this phenomenon during<lb break="yes" />a long series of observations made in the<lb break="yes"/>years 1809 and 1810, at the Observatory at<lb break="yes"/>Paris, to verify the declination of the stars.</note>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The earthquake of the 4th of Novem-<lb break="no"/>ber, the first I had felt, made so much<lb break="yes"/>the more lively an impression on me, as<lb break="yes"/>it was accompanied with remarkable<lb break="yes" />meteorological variations. It was, more-<lb break="no"/>over, a real lifting-up, and not a shock<lb break="yes"/>by undulations. I did not then<lb break="yes"/>imagine, that, after a long abode on<lb break="yes" />the table-lands of Quito, and the coasts<lb break="yes"/>of Peru, I should become almost as<lb break="yes"/>familiar with the abrupt movements of<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="592" facs="#f0003"/>
                        <cb/>the ground, as we are in Europe with<lb break="yes"/>the noise of thunder. We did not think<lb break="yes"/>of rising at night, in the city of Quito,<lb break="yes"/>when subterraneous rumblings (<hi rendition="#i" >bramidos</hi>),<lb break="yes"/>which seem always to come from the<lb break="yes"/>volcano of Pichincha, announced, (two<lb break="yes"/>or three, and sometimes seven or eight<lb break="yes"/>minutes beforehand) a shock; the force<lb break="yes"/>of which is seldom in proportion to the<lb break="yes"/>intensity of the noise. The carelessness<lb break="yes"/>of the inhabitants, who recollect that, for<lb break="yes"/>three centuries past, their city has not<lb break="yes"/>been overwhelmed, communicates itself<lb break="yes"/>easily to the least intrepid traveller.<lb break="yes"/>In general, it is not so much the fear of<lb break="yes" />the danger, as the novelty of the sensa-<lb break="no"/>tion, that strikes so forcibly, when the<lb break="yes"/>effect of the slightest earthquake is felt<lb break="yes"/>for the first time.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>From our infancy, the idea of certain<lb break="yes"/>contrasts fixes itself in our minds: wa-<lb break="no"/>ter appears to us an element that moves;<lb break="yes"/>earth, a motionless and inert mass.<lb break="yes"/>These ideas are the effect of daily ex-<lb break="no"/>perience; they are connected with every<lb break="yes"/>thing that is transmitted to us by the<lb break="yes"/>senses. When a shock is felt, when the<lb break="yes"/>earth is shaken on its old foundations,<lb break="yes" />which we had deemed so stable, one in-<lb break="no"/>stant is sufficient to destroy long illu-<lb break="no"/>sions. It is like awakening from a<lb break="yes"/>dream; but a painful awakening. We<lb break="yes"/>feel, that we have been deceived by<lb break="yes"/>the apparent calm of nature; we be-<lb break="no"/>come attentive to the least noise: we<lb break="yes" />mistrust, for the first time, a soil on<lb break="yes"/>which we had so long placed our feet<lb break="yes"/>with confidence. If the shocks be re-<lb break="no"/>peated, if they become frequent during<lb break="yes" />several successive days, the uncertainty<lb break="yes"/>quickly disappears. In 1784, the inha-<lb break="no"/>bitants of Mexico were accustomed to<lb break="yes"/>hear the thunder roll beneath their feet,<lb break="yes"/>as it is heard by us in the region of the<lb break="yes" />clouds. Confidence easily springs up<lb break="yes"/>in the human breast, and we end by ac-<lb break="no"/>customing ourselves on the coast of Peru<lb break="yes"/>to the undulations of the ground, like<lb break="yes"/>the sailor to the tossings of the ship,<lb break="yes"/>caused by the motion of the waves.</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#k">meteors.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The night of the 11th of November,<lb break="yes"/>was cool and extremely beautiful. To-<lb break="no"/>ward the morning, from half after two,<lb break="yes"/>the most extraordinary luminous meteors<lb break="yes" />were seen towards the east. Mr. Bonp-<lb break="no"/>land, who had risen to enjoy the fresh-<lb break="no"/>ness of the air in the gallery, perceived<lb break="yes"/>them first. Thousands of bolides and<lb break="yes"/>falling stars, succeeded each other during<lb break="yes" />four hours. Their direction was very<lb break="yes"/>regularly from north to south. They<lb break="yes"/>filled a space in the sky extending from<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/>the true east 30° toward the north and<lb break="yes"/>south. In an amplitude of 60° the me-<lb break="no"/>teors were seen to rise above the horizon<lb break="yes"/>at E.N.E., and at E. describe arcs more<lb break="yes"/>or less extended, and fall toward the<lb break="yes" />south, after having followed the direction<lb break="yes"/>of the meridian. Some of them attained<lb break="yes"/>a height of 40°, and all exceeded 25° or<lb break="yes"/>30°. There was very little wind in the<lb break="yes"/>low regions of the atmosphere, and this<lb break="yes" />blew from the east. No trace of clouds<lb break="yes"/>was to be seen. Mr. Bonpland relates,<lb break="yes"/>that from the beginning of the phenome-<lb break="no"/>non, there was not a space in the firma-<lb break="no"/>ment equal in extent to three diameters<lb break="yes"/>of the moon, that was not filled at every<lb break="yes"/>instant with bolides and falling stars.<lb break="yes"/>The first were fewer in number, but as<lb break="yes"/>they were seen of different sizes, it was<lb break="yes"/>impossible to fix the limit between these<lb break="yes"/>two classes of phenomena. All these<lb break="yes"/>meteors left luminous traces from five to<lb break="yes" />ten degrees in length, as often happens<lb break="yes"/>in the equinoctial regions. The phos-<lb break="no"/>phorescence of these traces, or luminous<lb break="yes"/>bands, lasted seven or eight seconds.<lb break="yes"/>Many of the falling stars had a very dis-<lb break="no" />tinct nucleus, as large as the disk of<lb break="yes"/>Jupiter, from which darted sparks of vi-<lb break="no"/>vid light. The bolides seem to burst as<lb break="yes"/>by explosion; but the largest, those<lb break="yes" />from 1° to 1° 15′ in diameter, disap-<lb break="no"/>peared without scintillation, leaving be-<lb break="no"/>hind them phosphorescent bands (<hi rendition="#i">trabes</hi>)<lb break="yes"/>exceeding in breadth fifteen or twenty<lb break="yes"/>minutes. The light of these meteors<lb break="yes"/>was white, and not reddish, which must<lb break="yes"/>be attributed, no doubt, to the absence<lb break="yes"/>of vapours, and the extreme transpa-<lb break="no"/>rency of the air. For the same reason,<lb break="yes"/>under the tropics, the stars of the first<lb break="yes" />magnitude have at their rising, a light<lb break="yes"/>evidently whiter than in Europe.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Almost all the inhabitants of Cumana<lb break="yes"/>were witnesses of this phenomenon, be-<lb break="no"/>cause they leave their houses before four<lb break="yes"/>o’clock, to attend the first morning mass.<lb break="yes" />They did not behold these bolides with<lb break="yes"/>indifference; the oldest among them re-<lb break="no"/>membered, that the great earthquakes of<lb break="yes"/>1766, were preceded by similar pheno-<lb break="no" />mena. The Guaiqueries in the Indian<lb break="yes"/>suburb, came out and asserted, “that<lb break="yes"/>the fire-work had begun at one o’clock;<lb break="yes"/>and that as they returned from fishing in<lb break="yes" />the Gulf, they had already perceived<lb break="yes"/>very small falling stars toward the east.”<lb break="yes"/>They affirmed at the same time, that<lb break="yes"/>igneous meteors were extremely rare on<lb break="yes"/>those coasts after two in the morning.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The phenomenon ceased by degrees<lb break="yes"/>after four o’clock, and the bolides and<lb break="yes"/>falling stars became less frequent; but<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">we</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="593" facs="#f0004"/>
                        <cb/>we still distinguished some toward the<lb break="yes"/>north-east by their whitish light, and the<lb break="yes"/>rapidity of their movement, a quarter of<lb break="yes"/>an hour after sun-rise. This circum-<lb break="no"/>stance will appear less extraordinary,<lb break="yes"/>when I bring to the reader’s recollection,<lb break="yes"/>that in full day-light, in 1788, the inte-<lb break="no"/>rior of the houses in the town of Popayan<lb break="yes"/>was brightly illuminated by an aërolite<lb break="yes"/>of immense magnitude. It passed over<lb break="yes"/>the town when the sun was shining<lb break="yes"/>clearly, about one o’clock. Mr. Bonp-<lb break="no"/>land and myself, during our second resi-<lb break="no"/>dence at Cumana, after having observed<lb break="yes"/>on the 26th of September, 1800, the<lb break="yes"/>immersion of the first satellite of Jupiter,<lb break="yes"/>succeeded in seeing the planet distinctly<lb break="yes"/>with the naked eye, eighteen minutes<lb break="yes"/>after the disk of the sun had appeared in<lb break="yes" />the horizon. There was a very slight va-<lb break="no"/>pour in the east, but Jupiter appeared<lb break="yes"/>on an azure sky. These facts prove the<lb break="yes"/>extreme purity and transparency of the<lb break="yes"/>atmosphere under the torrid zone. The<lb break="yes"/>mass of diffused light is so much less, as<lb break="yes"/>the vapours are more perfectly dissolved.<lb break="yes"/>The same cause, that weakens the diffu-<lb break="no"/>sion of the solar light, diminishes the ex-<lb break="no"/>tinction of that which emanates either<lb break="yes"/>from a <hi rendition="#i">bolis,</hi> Jupiter, or the moon, seen<lb break="yes" />on the second day after her conjunction.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The researches of Mr. Chladni having<lb break="yes"/>singularly fixed the attention of the sci-<lb break="no"/>entific world upon the bolides and falling<lb break="yes"/>stars at my departure from Europe, we<lb break="yes"/>did not neglect, during the course of our<lb break="yes" />journey from Caraccas to the Rio Negro,<lb break="yes"/>to enquire every where, whether the<lb break="yes"/>meteors of the 12th of November had<lb break="yes"/>been perceived. In a savage country,<lb break="yes"/>where the greater number of the inhabit-<lb break="no"/>ants sleep out in the air, so extraordinary<lb break="yes"/>a phenomenon could not fail to be re-<lb break="no"/>marked, except when concealed by<lb break="yes"/>clouds from the eye of observation. The<lb break="yes"/>Capuchin missionary at San Fernando de<lb break="yes"/>Apura, a village situate amid the savan-<lb break="no"/>nahs of the province of Varinas; the Fran-<lb break="no" />ciscan monks stationed near the cataracts<lb break="yes"/>of the Oroonoko, and at Maroa, on the<lb break="yes"/>banks of the Rio Negro; had seen number-<lb break="no"/>less falling stars and bolides illumine the<lb break="yes"/>vault of heaven. Maroa is south-west<lb break="yes"/>of Cumana, at one hundred and seventy-<lb break="maybe"/>four leagues distance. All these ob-<lb break="no"/>servers compared the phenomenon to a<lb break="yes"/>beautiful fire-work, which had lasted<lb break="yes"/>from three till six in the morning. Some<lb break="yes"/>of the monks had marked the day upon<lb break="yes"/>their ritual; others had noted it by the<lb break="yes"/>nearest festivals of the church. Unfor-<lb break="no" />tunately, none of them could recollect<lb break="yes"/>the direction of the meteors, or their ap-<lb break="no"/>
                        <cb/>parent height. From the position of the<lb break="yes"/>mountains and thick forests, which sur-<lb break="no"/>round the Missions of the Cataracts and<lb break="yes"/>the little village of Maroa, I presume that<lb break="yes"/>the bolides were still visible at 20° above<lb break="yes" />the horizon. On my arrival at the<lb break="yes"/>southern extremity of Spanish Guiana, at<lb break="yes"/>the little fort of San Carlos, I found some<lb break="yes"/>Portugueze, who had gone up the Rio<lb break="yes" />Negro from the Mission of St. Joseph of<lb break="yes"/>the Marivitains; who assured me, that<lb break="yes"/>in that part of Brazil, the phenomenon<lb break="yes"/>had been perceived, at least as far as<lb break="yes"/>San Gabriel das Cachoeiras, conse-<lb break="no"/>quently as far as the equator itself.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I was powerfully struck at the im-<lb break="no"/>mense height, which these bolides muss<lb break="yes"/>have attained, to have been visible at<lb break="yes"/>the same time at Cumana, and on the<lb break="yes" />frontiers of Brazil, in a line of two hun-<lb break="no"/>dred and thirty leagues in length. But<lb break="yes"/>what was my astonishment, when, at my<lb break="yes"/>return to Europe, I learnt, that the<lb break="yes" />same phenomenon had been perceived<lb break="yes"/>on an extent of the globe of 64° of lati-<lb break="no"/>tude, and 91° of longitude; at the equa-<lb break="no"/>tor, in South America, at Labrador, and<lb break="yes"/>in Germany! I found accidentally during<lb break="yes"/>my passage from Philadelphia to Bor-<lb break="no"/>deaux (in the Memoirs of the Pennsylva-<lb break="no"/>nian Society) the corresponding observa-<lb break="no"/>tion of Mr. Ellicott (lat 30° 42′); and,<lb break="yes" />upon my return from Naples to Berlin,<lb break="yes"/>I read the account of the Moravian Mis-<lb break="no"/>sionaries among the Eskimaux, in the<lb break="yes"/>Bibliothek of Gottingen. Several philo-<lb break="no" />sophers had already discussed at this pe-<lb break="no"/>riod the coincidence of the observations<lb break="yes"/>in the north with those at Cumana,<lb break="yes"/>which Mr. Bonpland and I had publish-<lb break="no"/>ed in 1800.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The following is a succinct enumera-<lb break="no"/>tion of facts: 1st, the fiery meteors were<lb break="yes"/>seen in the east, and the east-north-east,<lb break="yes"/>to 40° of elevation, from 2 h. to 6 h. at<lb break="yes"/>Cumana (lat. 10° 27′ 52″, long. 66° 30′);<lb break="yes"/>at Porto Cabello (lat. 10° 6′ 52″, long.<lb break="yes" />67° 5′); and on the frontiers of Brazil,<lb break="yes"/>near the equator, in the longitude of 70°<lb break="yes"/>west of the meridian of Paris. 2d, In<lb break="yes"/>French Guiana (lat. 4° 56′, long. 54° 35′),<lb break="yes"/>“the northern part of the sky was seen<lb break="yes"/>all on fire. Innumerable falling stars<lb break="yes"/>traversed the heavens during an hour<lb break="yes"/>and a half, and diffused so vivid a light,<lb break="yes"/>that those meteors might be compared<lb break="yes"/>to the blazing sheaves shot out from a<lb break="yes"/>fire-work.” The knowledge of this fact<lb break="yes"/>rests upon highly respectable testimony,<lb break="yes"/>that of the Count of Marbois, at that<lb break="yes"/>time transported to Cayenne, a victim<lb break="yes"/>to his love of justice and of rational con-<lb break="no"/>stitutional liberty. 3d, Mr. Ellicott,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">astronomer</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="594" facs="#f0005"/>
                        <cb/>astronomer to the United States, having<lb break="yes"/>terminated his trigonometric operations<lb break="yes"/>for the rectification of the limits on the<lb break="yes"/>Ohio, being on the 12th of November in<lb break="yes" />the Gulf of Florida, in the latitude of<lb break="yes"/>25°, and longitude 81° 50′, saw, in all<lb break="yes"/>parts of the sky, “as many meteors as<lb break="yes"/>stars, moving in all directions: some ap-<lb break="no"/>peared to fall perpendicularly; and it<lb break="yes"/>was expected every minute that they<lb break="yes"/>would drop into the vessel.” The same<lb break="yes"/>phenomenon was perceived upon the<lb break="yes" />American continent as far as the latitude<lb break="yes"/>of 30° 42′. 4th, In Labrador, at Nain<lb break="yes"/>(lat. 56° 55′), and Hoffenthal (lat. 58° 4′);<lb break="yes"/>in Greenland, at Lichtenau (lat. 61° 5′),<lb break="yes"/>and at New Herrenhut (lat. 64° 14′,<lb break="yes"/>long. 52° 20′); the Eskimaux were<lb break="yes"/>frightened at the enormous quantity of<lb break="yes"/>bolides, that fell during twilight toward<lb break="yes"/>all points of the firmament, and “some<lb break="yes"/>of which were a foot broad. 5th, In<lb break="yes"/>Germany, Mr. Zeissing, vicar of Itter-<lb break="no"/>stadt near Weimar (lat. 50° 59′, long.<lb break="yes"/>9° 1′ east), perceived, on the 12th of<lb break="yes" />November, between the hours of six and<lb break="yes"/>seven in the morning, when it was half<lb break="yes"/>after two at Cumana, some falling stars,<lb break="yes"/>which shed a very white light. “Soon<lb break="yes"/>after, toward the south and south-west,<lb break="yes" />luminous rays appeared from four to six<lb break="yes"/>foot long; they were reddish, and resem-<lb break="no"/>bled the luminous track of a sky-rocket.<lb break="yes"/>During the morning twilight, between<lb break="yes"/>the hours of seven and eight, the south-<lb break="no" />west part of the sky was seen, from time<lb break="yes"/>to time, strongly illuminated by white<lb break="yes"/>lightning, which ran in serpentine lines<lb break="yes"/>along the horizon. At night the cold<lb break="yes"/>increased, and the barometer had risen.”<lb break="yes"/>It is very probable, that the meteor<lb break="yes"/>might have been observed more to the<lb break="yes"/>east, in Poland and in Russia. If Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Ritter had not taken a particular account<lb break="yes" />of them from the Vicar of Itterstadt’s<lb break="yes"/>papers, we should have supposed, that<lb break="yes"/>the bodies had not been visible beyond<lb break="yes"/>the limits of the New Continent.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The distance from Weimar to the Rio<lb break="yes"/>Negro, is 1800 sea leagues; and from<lb break="yes"/>Rio Negro to Herrenhut in Greenland,<lb break="yes"/>1300 leagues. Admitting that the same<lb break="yes"/>fiery meteors were seen at points so dis-<lb break="no"/>tant from each other, we must also ad-<lb break="no"/>mit, that their height was at least 411<lb break="yes"/>leagues. Near Weimar, the appear-<lb break="no"/>ance like sky-rockets was seen in the<lb break="yes"/>south, and south-east; at Cumana, in<lb break="yes"/>the east, and in the east-north-east. We<lb break="yes"/>may therefore conclude, that numberless<lb break="yes" />aërolites must have fallen into the sea,<lb break="yes"/>between Africa and South-America, to<lb break="yes"/>the west of the Cape-Verde Islands.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> But, since the direction of the bolides<lb break="yes"/>was not the same at Labrador and at<lb break="yes"/>Cumana, why were they not perceived in<lb break="yes"/>the latter place towards the north, as at<lb break="yes"/>Cayenne? We can scarcely be too cau-<lb break="no"/>tious on a subject, on which good ob-<lb break="no"/>servations made in very distant places<lb break="yes"/>are still wanting. I am rather inclined<lb break="yes"/>to think, that the Chayma Indians of<lb break="yes"/>Cumana did not see the same bolides<lb break="yes"/>as the Portugueze in Brazil, and the<lb break="yes"/>missionaries in Labrador; but, at the<lb break="yes" />same time, it cannot be doubted, and this<lb break="yes"/>fact appears to me very remarkable, that<lb break="yes"/>in the New World, between the meri-<lb break="no"/>dians of 46° and 82°, between the equa-<lb break="no"/>tor and 64° north, at the same hour, an<lb break="yes" />immense number of bolides and falling<lb break="yes"/>stars were perceived; and that those<lb break="yes"/>meteors had every where the same bril-<lb break="no"/>liancy throughout a space of 921,000<lb break="yes" />square leagues.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The scientific men, who have lately<lb break="yes"/>made such laborious <choice>
                            <sic>reseaches</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">researches</corr>
                        </choice> on fall-<lb break="no"/>ing stars and their parallaxes, considered<lb break="yes"/>them, as meteors belonging to the far-<lb break="no"/>thest limits of our atmosphere, between<lb break="yes"/>the region of the Aurora Borealis and that<lb break="yes"/>of the lightest clouds. Some have been<lb break="yes"/>seen, which had not more than 14,000<lb break="yes"/>toises, or about five leagues, of elevation.<lb break="yes"/>The highest do not appear to exceed thirty<lb break="yes" />leagues. They have often more than a<lb break="yes"/>hundred feet diameter; and their swift-<lb break="no"/>ness is such, that they dart, in a few se-<lb break="no"/>conds, over a space of two leagues.<lb break="yes" />Some of these have been measured, the<lb break="yes"/>direction of which was almost perpendi-<lb break="no"/>cularly upward, or forming an angle of<lb break="yes"/>50° with the vertical line. This ex-<lb break="no" />tremely remarkable circumstance has<lb break="yes"/>led to the conclusion, that falling stars<lb break="yes"/>are not aërolites, which, after having<lb break="yes"/>hovered about a long time in space,<lb break="yes"/>take fire on entering accidentally into<lb break="yes"/>our atmosphere, and fall toward the<lb break="yes"/>earth.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Whatever may be the origin of these lu-<lb break="no"/>minous meteors, it is difficult to conceive<lb break="yes"/>any instantaneous inflammation taking<lb break="yes"/>place in a region, where there is less air<lb break="yes"/>than in the vacuum of our air-pumps;<lb break="yes"/>and where (at 25,000 toises high) the<lb break="yes"/>mercury in the barometer would not rise<lb break="yes"/>to 0·012 of a line. We have ascertain-<lb break="no"/>ed the uniform mixture of atmospheric<lb break="yes"/>air to 0·003 nearly, only to an elevation<lb break="yes"/>of 3000 toises; consequently not be-<lb break="no"/>yond the last stratum of fleecy clouds.<lb break="yes"/>It might be admitted, that, in the first<lb break="yes"/>revolutions of the globe, gaseous sub-<lb break="no" />stances, which yet remain unknown to<lb break="yes"/>us, may have risen toward that region,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">through</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="595" facs="#f0006"/>
                        <cb/>through which the falling stars pass: but<lb break="yes"/>accurate experiments, made upon mix-<lb break="no"/>tures of gasses which have not the same<lb break="yes"/>specific gravity, prove, that we cannot<lb break="yes"/>admit a superior stratum of the atmos-<lb break="no"/>phere entirely different from the inferior<lb break="yes"/>strata. Gaseous substances mix and<lb break="yes"/>penetrate each other with the least mo-<lb break="no"/>tion, and a uniformity of their mixture<lb break="yes"/>would have taken place in the lapse of<lb break="yes" />ages, unless we suppose in them the effects<lb break="yes"/>of a repulsive action unexampled in those<lb break="yes"/>substances which we can subject to our<lb break="yes"/>observations. Farther, if we admit the<lb break="yes" />existence of particular aërial fluids in the<lb break="yes"/>inaccessible regions of luminous meteors,<lb break="yes"/>falling stars, bolides, and the Aurora<lb break="yes"/>Borealis; how can we conceive why the<lb break="yes"/>whole stratum of those fluids does not at<lb break="yes" />once take fire, but that the gaseous<lb break="yes"/>emanations, like the clouds, occupy only<lb break="yes"/>limited spaces? How can we suppose<lb break="yes"/>an electrical explosion without some va-<lb break="no" />pours collected together, capable of<lb break="yes"/>containing unequal charges of electrici-<lb break="no"/>ty, in air, the mean temperature of which<lb break="yes"/>is, perhaps, 25° below the freezing point<lb break="yes"/>of the centigrade thermometer, and<lb break="yes"/>the rarefaction of which is so consider-<lb break="no"/>able, that the compression of the elec-<lb break="no"/>trical shock could scarcely disengage<lb break="yes"/>any heat? These difficulties would, in<lb break="yes"/>great part, be removed, if the direction<lb break="yes"/>of the motion of falling stars allowed<lb break="yes"/>us to consider them as bodies with a<lb break="yes"/>solid nucleus, as cosmic phenomena (be-<lb break="no"/>longing to space beyond the limits of our<lb break="yes" />atmosphere), and not as telluric pheno-<lb break="no"/>mena (belonging to our planet only).</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Supposing that the meteors of Cumana<lb break="yes"/>were only at the usual height, at which<lb break="yes"/>falling stars in general move, the same<lb break="yes"/>meteors were seen above the horizon in<lb break="yes" />places more than 310 leagues distant<lb break="yes"/>from each other. Now, what an extra-<lb break="no"/>ordinary disposition to incandescence<lb break="yes"/>must have reigned on the 12th of No-<lb break="no"/>vember, in the higher regions of the at-<lb break="no"/>mosphere, to have furnished, during<lb break="yes"/>four hours, myriads of bolides and falling<lb break="yes"/>stars, visible at the equator, in Green-<lb break="no" />land, and in Germany.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Mr. Benzenberg judiciously observes,<lb break="yes"/>that the same cause, which renders the<lb break="yes"/>phenomenon more frequent, has also an<lb break="yes"/>influence on the largeness of the meteors,<lb break="yes" />and the intensity of their light. In<lb break="yes"/>Europe, the nights when there are the<lb break="yes"/>greatest number of falling stars, are those<lb break="yes"/>in which very bright ones are mixed with<lb break="yes"/>very small ones. The periodicalness of<lb break="yes"/>the phenomenon augments the interest<lb break="yes"/>which it excites. There are months, in<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/>which Mr. Brandes has reckoned in our<lb break="yes"/>temperate zone, only sixty or eighty fall-<lb break="no"/>ing stars in one night; and in other<lb break="yes"/>months their number has risen to two<lb break="yes"/>thousand. Whenever one is observed,<lb break="yes"/>which has the diameter of Sirius or of<lb break="yes"/>Jupiter, we are sure of seeing so bril-<lb break="no"/>liant a meteor, succeeded by a great<lb break="yes"/>number of smaller meteors. If the<lb break="yes"/>falling stars be very frequent during<lb break="yes"/>one night, it is very probable, that this<lb break="yes"/>frequency will continue during several<lb break="yes"/>weeks. It would seem, that, in the<lb break="yes"/>higher regions of the atmosphere, near<lb break="yes"/>that extreme limit where the centrifugal<lb break="yes"/>force is balanced by gravity, there exists,<lb break="yes"/>at regular periods, a particular disposi-<lb break="no"/>tion for the production of bolides, falling<lb break="yes"/>stars, and the Aurora Borealis. Does<lb break="yes"/>the periodicalness of this great pheno-<lb break="no"/>menon depend upon the state of the<lb break="yes"/>atmosphere? or upon something which<lb break="yes"/>this atmosphere receives from without,<lb break="yes" />while the earth advances in the ecliptic?<lb break="yes"/>Of all this we are still ignorant, as men<lb break="yes"/>were in the days of Anaxagoras.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>With respect to the falling stars them-<lb break="no"/>selves, it appears to me, from my own<lb break="yes"/>experience, that they are more frequent<lb break="yes"/>in the equinoctial regions than in the<lb break="yes" />temperate zone; more frequent over the<lb break="yes"/>continents, and near certain coasts, than<lb break="yes"/>in the middle of the ocean. Do the radia-<lb break="no"/>tion of the surface of the globe, and the<lb break="yes"/>electric charge of the lower regions of<lb break="yes"/>the atmosphere, which varies according<lb break="yes"/>to the nature of the soil, and the positions<lb break="yes"/>of the continents and seas, exert their<lb break="yes"/>influence as far as those heights, where<lb break="yes"/>eternal winter reigns? The total absence<lb break="yes" />even of the smallest clouds, at certain<lb break="yes"/>seasons, or above some barren plains<lb break="yes"/>destitute of vegetation, seem to prove,<lb break="yes"/>that this influence can be felt at least as<lb break="yes"/>far as five or six thousand toises high.<lb break="yes"/>A phenomenon analogous to that of the<lb break="yes"/>12th of November, was observed thirty<lb break="yes"/>years before, on the table land of the<lb break="yes"/>Andes, in a country studded with volca-<lb break="no" />noes. At the city of Quito, there was<lb break="yes"/>seen, in one part of the sky, above the<lb break="yes"/>volcano of Cayambo, so great a number<lb break="yes"/>of falling stars, that the mountain was<lb break="yes" />thought to be in flames. This singular<lb break="yes"/>sight lasted more than an hour. The<lb break="yes"/>people assembled in the plain of Exico,<lb break="yes"/>where a magnificent view presents itself<lb break="yes"/>of the highest summits of the Cordilleras.<lb break="yes"/>A procession was already on the point<lb break="yes"/>of setting out from the Convent of St.<lb break="yes"/>Francis, when it was perceived, that the<lb break="yes"/>blaze on the horizon was caused by fiery<lb break="yes" />meteors, which ran along the skies in all<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">directions,</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="596" facs="#f0007"/>
                        <cb/>directions, at the altitude of twelve or<lb break="yes"/>thirteen degrees.</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#k">la guayra.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I landed in the port of La Guayra,<lb break="yes"/>and the same evening made preparations<lb break="yes"/>for transporting my instruments to Ca-<lb break="no"/>raccas. The persons for whom I had<lb break="yes" />recommendation, advised me not to<lb break="yes"/>sleep in the town, where the yellow<lb break="yes"/>fever had only ceased a few weeks, but in<lb break="yes"/>a house on a little hill, above the village<lb break="yes" />of Maiquetia, more exposed to fresh<lb break="yes"/>winds than La Guayra.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>La Guayra is rather a roadstead than<lb break="yes"/>a port. The sea is constantly agitated,<lb break="yes"/>and the ships suffer at once by the ac-<lb break="no"/>tion of the wind, the tideways, the bad<lb break="yes"/>anchorage, and the worms. The land-<lb break="no"/>ing is taken in with difficulty, and the<lb break="yes"/>height of the swell prevents embarking<lb break="yes"/>mules here, as at New Barcelona and<lb break="yes"/>Porto Cabello. The free Mulattoes and<lb break="yes" />Negroes, who carry the cacao on board<lb break="yes"/>the ships, are a class of men of very re-<lb break="no"/>markable muscular strength. They go<lb break="yes"/>up to their middles through the water;<lb break="yes" />and, what is well worthy of attention,<lb break="yes"/>they have nothing to fear from the<lb break="yes"/>sharks, which are so frequent in this har-<lb break="no"/>bour. The fact seems connected with what<lb break="yes"/>I have often observed between the tro-<lb break="no"/>pics, relatively to other classes of animals,<lb break="yes"/>that live in society; for instance, monkeys<lb break="yes"/>and crocodiles. In the missions of the<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko, and the river of Amazons,<lb break="yes"/>the Indians who catch monkeys to sell<lb break="yes"/>them, know very well, that they can easily<lb break="yes"/>succeed in taming those which inhabit<lb break="yes"/>certain islands; while monkeys, of the<lb break="yes"/>same species, caught on the neighbour-<lb break="no"/>ing continent, die of terror or rage,<lb break="yes"/>when they find themselves in the power<lb break="yes"/>of man. The crocodiles of one pool in<lb break="yes"/>the Llanos are cowardly, and flee even<lb break="yes"/>in the water; while those of another at-<lb break="no"/>tack with extreme intrepidity. It would<lb break="yes"/>be difficult to explain this difference of<lb break="yes"/>manners and habits, by the aspect of<lb break="yes"/>their respective localities. The sharks<lb break="yes"/>of the port of La Guayra seem to fur-<lb break="no"/>nish an analogous example. They are<lb break="yes"/>dangerous and blood-thirsty, at the<lb break="yes" />island opposite the coast of Caraccas,<lb break="yes"/>at the Roques, at Bonayre, and at Cu-<lb break="no"/>rassao: while they forbear to attack per-<lb break="no"/>sons swimming in the ports of La Guayra<lb break="yes"/>and Santa Martha. The people, who,<lb break="yes"/>in order to simplify the explanation of<lb break="yes"/>natural phenomena, have always recourse<lb break="yes"/>to the marvellous, affirm, that, in both<lb break="yes"/>places, a bishop gave his benediction to<lb break="yes" />the sharks.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The situation of La Guayra is very<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/>singular, and can only be compared to that<lb break="yes"/>of <choice><sic>SantaCruz</sic><corr type="editorial">Santa-Cruz</corr></choice> in Teneriffe. The chain of<lb break="yes"/>mountains, that separates the port from<lb break="yes"/>the high valley of Caraccas, descends<lb break="yes"/>almost directly into the sea; and the<lb break="yes" />houses of the town are backed by a wall<lb break="yes"/>of steep rocks. There scarcely remains<lb break="yes"/>one hundred or one hundred and forty<lb break="yes"/>toises breadth of flat ground between<lb break="yes"/>the wall and the ocean. The town has<lb break="yes"/>six or eight thousand inhabitants, and<lb break="yes"/>contains only two streets, running pa-<lb break="no"/>rallel to each other east and west. It<lb break="yes"/>is commanded by a battery of <hi rendition="#i">Cerro co-<lb break="no"/>lorado</hi>; and its fortifications along the<lb break="yes"/>seaside are well disposed, and kept in<lb break="yes" />repair. The aspect of this place has<lb break="yes"/>something solitary and gloomy; we<lb break="yes"/>seemed not to be on a continent, cover-<lb break="no"/>ed with vast forests, but in a rocky<lb break="yes"/>island, destitute of mould and vegeta-<lb break="no"/>tion. With the exception of Cape<lb break="yes"/>Blanco, and the cocoa-trees of Maique-<lb break="no"/>tia, no view meets the eye but that of<lb break="yes"/>the horizon, the sea, and the azure<lb break="yes"/>vault of heaven. The heat is stifling<lb break="yes"/>during the day, and most frequently<lb break="yes"/>during the night. The climate of La<lb break="yes"/>Guayra is justly considered as more ar-<lb break="no"/>dent than that of Cumana, Porto Ca-<lb break="no"/>bello, and Coro; because the sea-<lb break="no" />breeze is less felt, and the air is heated<lb break="yes"/>by the radiant caloric, which the per-<lb break="no"/>pendicular rocks emit from the time the<lb break="yes"/>sun sets.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The examination of the thermometric<lb break="yes"/>observations, made during nine months<lb break="yes"/>at La Guayra by a distinguished physi-<lb break="no"/>cian, enabled me to compare the climate<lb break="yes"/>of this port, and that of Cumana, the<lb break="yes"/>Havannah, and Vera Cruz.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>These four places are considered as the<lb break="yes"/>hottest on the shores of the New World.<lb break="yes"/>The mean of the observations made at<lb break="yes"/>noon, from the 27th of June to the 16th<lb break="yes"/>of November, were, at La Guayra, 31·6°<lb break="yes"/>of the centigrade thermometer; at Cu-<lb break="no"/>mana, 29·3°; at Vera Cruz, 28·7°; at<lb break="yes"/>the Havannah, 29·5°. The daily differ-<lb break="no"/>ence, at the same hour, scarcely ex-<lb break="no"/>ceeded 0·8° or 1·4°. During this pe-<lb break="no"/>riod it rained but four times, and then<lb break="yes"/>only for seven or eight minutes. At this<lb break="yes" />season, the yellow fever prevails; which<lb break="yes"/>usually disappears at La Guayra, as at<lb break="yes"/>Vera Cruz, and the island of St. Vincent,<lb break="yes"/>when the temperature of the day de-<lb break="no"/>scends below twenty-three or twenty-<lb break="no"/>four degrees. The mean temperature<lb break="yes"/>of the hottest month was, at La Guayra,<lb break="yes"/>nearly 29·3°; at Cumana, 29·1°; at<lb break="yes" />Vera Cruz, 27·7°; at Cairo, according to<lb break="yes"/>Nouet, 29·9°; at Rome, 25°. From<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="597" facs="#f0008"/>
                        <cb/>the 16th of November to the 19th of<lb break="yes"/>December, the mean temperature of<lb break="yes"/>noon, at La Guayra, was only 24·3°; at<lb break="yes"/>night, 21·6°. This is the time at which<lb break="yes"/>the sufferings from heat are the least;<lb break="yes"/>and yet I do not believe, that the ther-<lb break="no"/>mometer ever falls (and it is lowest a<lb break="yes"/>little before sunrise) below 21°. It<lb break="yes" />sometimes descends at Cumana, to 21·2°;<lb break="yes"/>at Vera Cruz, to 16°; at the Havannah<lb break="yes"/>(always when the north wind blows), to<lb break="yes"/>8°, and even lower. The mean tempe-<lb break="no" />rature of the coldest month is in these<lb break="yes"/>four places, 23·2°, 26·8°, 21·1°, 21·0°.<lb break="yes"/>At Cairo, it is 13·4°. The mean of<lb break="yes"/>the whole year, according to good ob-<lb break="no" />servations carefully calculated, is, at La<lb break="yes"/>Guayra nearly 28·1°; at Cumana, 27·7°;<lb break="yes"/>at Vera Cruz, 25·4°; at the Havannah,<lb break="yes"/>25·6°; at Rio Janeiro, 23·5°; at Santa<lb break="yes"/>Cruz in Teneriffe, in the latitude of 28°<lb break="yes" />28′, but backed like La Guayra, by a wall<lb break="yes"/>of rocks, 21·9°: at Cairo, 22·4°; at<lb break="yes"/>Rome, 15·8°.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>From the whole of these observations<lb break="yes"/>it follows, that La Guayra is one of the<lb break="yes"/>hottest places on the earth<note place="foot" n="*">In Asia, the mean temperature of<lb break="yes" />Abushar, of Madras, and of Batavia, are<lb break="yes"/>not above 25° and 27°; but the hottest<lb break="yes"/>month at Madras rises to 32°, according<lb break="yes"/>to Roxburgh; and at Abushar, on the Per-<lb break="no"/>sian Gulf, according to Mr. Jukes, to<lb break="yes"/>33·90°; which is from two to four degrees<lb break="yes"/>higher than at Cairo.</note>, that the<lb break="yes" />quantity of heat which it receives in the<lb break="yes"/>course of a year, is a little greater than<lb break="yes"/>that felt at Cumana; but that, in the<lb break="yes"/>months of November, December, and<lb break="yes"/>January, (at equal distance from the<lb break="yes"/>two passages of the sun through the ze-<lb break="no"/>nith of the town), the atmosphere cools<lb break="yes"/>more at La Guayra.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>At the time of my abode at La Guayra,<lb break="yes"/>the scourge of yellow fever, or <hi rendition="#i">calentura<lb break="yes"/>amarilla,</hi> had been known only two<lb break="yes"/>years; and the mortality had not been<lb break="yes"/>considerable, because the confluence of<lb break="yes" />strangers on the coast of Caraccas was<lb break="yes"/>less than at the Havannah and Vera Cruz.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I found the latitude of La Guayra to<lb break="yes"/>be 10° 36′ 19″; and the longitude<lb break="yes"/>69° 26′ 13″. The dip of the needle on<lb break="yes"/>the 24th of January, 1800, was 42·20°;<lb break="yes"/>and its variation 4° 20′ 35″ east. The<lb break="yes"/>intensity of the magnetic forces was<lb break="yes"/>found proportional to 237 oscillations.</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#k">caraccas.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>After having described the scenery,<lb break="yes"/>and the atmospheric constitution of La<lb break="yes"/>Guayra, we shall now leave the coasts<lb break="yes"/>of the Caribbean Sea. The road that<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/>leads from the port to Caraccas, the ca-<lb break="no"/>pital of a government of near 90,000<lb break="yes"/>inhabitants, resembles, as I have already<lb break="yes"/>observed, the passages over the Alps,<lb break="yes"/>the road of St. Gothard, and of the Great<lb break="yes" />St. Bernard. Taking the level of the<lb break="yes"/>road had never been attempted before<lb break="yes"/>my arrival in the province of Venezuela.<lb break="yes"/>No precise idea had even been formed of<lb break="yes"/>the elevation of the valley of Caraccas.<lb break="yes"/>It had indeed been long observed, that<lb break="yes"/>the descent was much less from La<lb break="yes"/>Cumbre and La Vueltas, which is the<lb break="yes" />culminating point of the road toward the<lb break="yes"/>Pastora at the entrance of the valley of<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas, than toward the port of La<lb break="yes"/>Guayra: but the mountain of Avila, hav-<lb break="no" />ing a very considerable bulk, the eye can-<lb break="no"/>not discover, at the same time, the points<lb break="yes"/>to be compared. It is even impossible<lb break="yes"/>to form a precise idea of the elevation of<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas from the climate of the valley.<lb break="yes" />The air in it is cooled by the descending<lb break="yes"/>currents of air; and by the fogs, which<lb break="yes"/>envelop the lofty summit of the Silla<lb break="yes"/>during a great part of the year. I have<lb break="yes"/>often gone on foot from La Guayra to<lb break="yes" />Caraccas; and I sketched a profile of<lb break="yes"/>the road, founded on twelve points, the<lb break="yes"/>heights of which were determined by ba-<lb break="no"/>rometric measurements.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>When in the season of the great heats<lb break="yes"/>we breathe the burning atmosphere of<lb break="yes"/>La Guayra, and turn our eyes toward<lb break="yes"/>the mountains, we are strongly affected<lb break="yes"/>by the idea, that, at the direct distance<lb break="yes"/>of five or six thousand toises, a popula-<lb break="no"/>tion of forty thousand souls, assembled<lb break="yes"/>in a narrow valley, enjoys all the cool-<lb break="no"/>ness of spring, of a temperature which,<lb break="yes"/>at night, descends to 12° of the centesi-<lb break="no"/>mal thermometer. This near approach<lb break="yes"/>of different climates is common in the<lb break="yes"/>Cordilleras of the Andes; but every<lb break="yes"/>where, at Mexico, at Quito, in Peru,<lb break="yes"/>and in New Grenada, a long journey<lb break="yes"/>must be made into the interior, either<lb break="yes"/>by the plains, or by proceeding up the<lb break="yes" />rivers, in order to reach the great cities,<lb break="yes"/>which are the centres of civilization.<lb break="yes"/>The height of Caraccas is but a third of<lb break="yes"/>that of Mexico, Quito, and Santa Fe de<lb break="yes"/>Bogota; yet, among all the capitals of<lb break="yes" />Spanish America, which enjoy a cool<lb break="yes"/>and delicious climate in the midst of the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone, Caraccas stands nearest to<lb break="yes"/>the coast. What a privilege, to possess<lb break="yes"/>a sea-port at three leagues distance, and<lb break="yes" />to be situate among mountains, on a ta-<lb break="no"/>ble-land, which would produce wheat,<lb break="yes"/>if the cultivation of the coffee-tree were<lb break="yes"/>not preferred!</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The road from La Guayra to the Val-<lb break="no"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">ley</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="598" facs="#f0009"/>
                        <cb/>ley of Caraccas, is infinitely finer than<lb break="yes"/>that from Honda to Santa Fe, or that<lb break="yes"/>from Guayaquil to Quito. It is even<lb break="yes"/>kept in better order than the ancient<lb break="yes"/>road, which led from the port of Vera<lb break="yes"/>Cruz to Perote, on the eastern declivity<lb break="yes"/>of the mountains of New Spain. With<lb break="yes"/>good mules, it requires but three hours<lb break="yes"/>to go from the port of La Guayra to Ca-<lb break="no" />raccas; and only two hours to return.<lb break="yes"/>With loaded mules, or on foot, the<lb break="yes"/>journey is from four to five hours. The<lb break="yes"/>ascent begins with a ridge of rocks ex-<lb break="no" />tremely steep, and stations that bear the<lb break="yes"/>name of Torrequemada, Curucuti, and<lb break="yes"/>Salto, to a large inn (La Venta) built at<lb break="yes"/>six hundred toises above the level of the<lb break="yes"/>sea. The denomination of the Burnt<lb break="yes"/>Tower indicates the sensation that is<lb break="yes"/>felt in descending toward La Guayra. A<lb break="yes"/>suffocating heat is reflected by the walls<lb break="yes"/>of rock, and still more by the barren<lb break="yes" />plains, on which the traveller looks<lb break="yes"/>down.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>When I passed for the first time that<lb break="yes"/>table-land, on my way to the capital of<lb break="yes"/>Venezuela, I found several travellers as-<lb break="no"/>sembled round the little inn of Guayavo,<lb break="yes"/>to rest their mules. They were inhabit-<lb break="no"/>ants of Caraccas, and were disputing on<lb break="yes"/>the efforts toward independence, which<lb break="yes"/>had been made a short time before. Jo-<lb break="no"/>seph Espana had perished on the scaf-<lb break="no" />fold; and his wife groaned in a prison,<lb break="yes"/>because she had given an asylum to her<lb break="yes"/>husband when a fugitive, and had not de-<lb break="no"/>nounced him to the government. I was<lb break="yes" />struck with the agitation which prevailed<lb break="yes"/>in every mind, and the bitterness with<lb break="yes"/>which questions were debated, on which<lb break="yes"/>men of the same country ought not to<lb break="yes"/>have differed in opinion. While they<lb break="yes" />descanted on the hatred of the Mulattoes<lb break="yes"/>against the free negroes and whites, on<lb break="yes"/>the wealth of the monks, and the diffi-<lb break="no"/>culty of holding slaves in obedience, a<lb break="yes"/>cold wind, that seemed to descend from<lb break="yes"/>the lofty summit of the Silla of Caraccas,<lb break="yes"/>enveloped us in a thick fog, and put an<lb break="yes"/>end to this animated conversation. We<lb break="yes"/>sought for shelter, in the Venta del<lb break="yes" />Guayavo. When we entered the inn,<lb break="yes"/>an old man, who had spoken with the<lb break="yes"/>most calmness, reminded the others how<lb break="yes"/>imprudent it was, in a time of denuncia-<lb break="no" />tion, on the mountain as well as in the<lb break="yes"/>city, to engage in political discussions.<lb break="yes"/>These words, uttered in a spot of so wild<lb break="yes"/>an aspect, made a lively impression on<lb break="yes"/>my mind; which was often renewed dur-<lb break="no"/>ing our journeys in the Andes of New<lb break="yes"/>Grenada and Peru. In Europe, where<lb break="yes"/>nations decide their quarrels in the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/>plains, we climb the mountains in search<lb break="yes"/>of solitude and liberty. In the New<lb break="yes"/>World, the Cordilleras are inhabited to<lb break="yes"/>the height of twelve thousand feet; and<lb break="yes"/>thither men carry with them their poli-<lb break="no" />tical dissentions, and their little and<lb break="yes"/>hateful passions.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Caraccas is the capital of a country,<lb break="yes"/>which is nearly twice as large as Peru at<lb break="yes"/>present, and which yields little in ex-<lb break="no"/>tent to the kingdom of New Grenada.<lb break="yes" />This country, which the Spanish govern-<lb break="no"/>ment designates by the name of <hi rendition="#i">Capita-<lb break="no"/>nia General de Caraccas,</hi> or of the<lb break="yes"/>(united) provinces of Venezuela, has<lb break="yes"/>nearly a million of inhabitants, among<lb break="yes"/>whom are sixty thousand slaves. It con-<lb break="no" />tains, along the coast, New Andalusia,<lb break="yes"/>or the province of Cumana (with the<lb break="yes"/>island of Margaretta), Barcelona, Ve-<lb break="no"/>nezuela or Caraccas, Coro, and Mara-<lb break="no"/>caybo; in the interior, the provinces of<lb break="yes"/>Varinas and Guiana, the first along the<lb break="yes"/>rivers of Santo Domingo and the Apure,<lb break="yes"/>the second along the Oroonoko, the Casi-<lb break="no" />quiare, the Atabapo, and the Rio Ne-<lb break="no"/>gro. In a general view of the seven<lb break="yes"/>united provinces of Terra Firma, we per-<lb break="no"/>ceive, that they form three distinct zones,<lb break="yes" />extending from east to west.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Caraccas is the seat of an <hi rendition="#i">audiencia</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>(high court of justice) and one of the<lb break="yes" />eight archbishoprics, into which Spanish<lb break="yes"/>America is divided. Its population in<lb break="yes"/>1800, according to the researches I<lb break="yes"/>made into the number of births, was<lb break="yes" />nearly 40,000; the best informed inha-<lb break="no"/>bitants believed it even to be 45,000, of<lb break="yes"/>which 18,000 are whites, and 27,000<lb break="yes"/>free men of colour. Computations made<lb break="yes"/>in 1778, had already given from 30,000<lb break="yes"/>to 32,000. All the direct numberings<lb break="yes"/>have remained a quarter, and more, be-<lb break="no"/>low the effective number. In 1766, the<lb break="yes" />population of Caraccas, and the fine val-<lb break="no"/>ley in which that city is placed, suffered<lb break="yes"/>immensely by a severe attack of the<lb break="yes"/>small-pox. The mortality rose in the<lb break="yes" />town to six or eight thousand. Since<lb break="yes"/>that memorable period, inoculation is<lb break="yes"/>become general, and I have seen it prac-<lb break="no"/>tised without the aid of physicians. In<lb break="yes"/>the province of Cumana, where the<lb break="yes" />communications with Europe are less<lb break="yes"/>frequent, there had not been, in my<lb break="yes"/>time, one instance of the small-pox dur-<lb break="no"/>ing fifteen years; while, at Caraccas,<lb break="yes"/>that cruel malady was constantly dread-<lb break="no"/>ed, because it always showed itself spo-<lb break="no"/>radically on several points at a time. I<lb break="yes"/>say sporadically, for in Equinoctial Ame-<lb break="no"/>rica, where the changes of the atmo-<lb break="no"/>sphere, and the phenomena of organic<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">life,</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="599" facs="#f0010"/>
                        <cb/>life, seem subject to a remarkable pe-<lb break="no"/>riodicalness, the small-pox, before the<lb break="yes"/>benevolent introduction of the vaccine<lb break="yes"/>disease, exerted its ravages only, if we<lb break="yes"/>may place confidence in general belief,<lb break="yes" />every fifteen or twenty years. Since my<lb break="yes"/>return to Europe, the population of Ca-<lb break="no"/>raccas has continued to augment. It<lb break="yes"/>amounted to 50,000 souls; when, at the<lb break="yes" />great earthquake of the 26th of March,<lb break="yes"/>1812, twelve thousand inhabitants pe-<lb break="no"/>rished beneath the ruins of their houses.<lb break="yes"/>The political events, which have suc-<lb break="no"/>ceeded this catastrophe, have reduced<lb break="yes"/>the number of inhabitants to less than<lb break="yes"/>20,000; but these losses will soon be<lb break="yes"/>repaired, if the fertile and commercial<lb break="yes"/>country, of which Caraccas is the centre,<lb break="yes" />should have the happiness of enjoying<lb break="yes"/>repose, and a wise administration, for a<lb break="yes"/>few years.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The town is seated at the entrance of<lb break="yes"/>the plain of Chacao, which extend<lb break="yes"/>three leagues east towards Caurimare<lb break="yes"/>and the Cuesta de Auyamas, and which<lb break="yes"/>is two leagues and a half in breadth.<lb break="yes"/>This plain, through which runs the Rio<lb break="yes"/>Guayra, is four hundred and fourteen<lb break="yes"/>toises in height above the level of the<lb break="yes" />sea. The ground, which the town of<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas occupies, is uneven, and has<lb break="yes"/>a steep slope from N.N.W. to S.S.E. In<lb break="yes"/>order to form an exact idea of the situa-<lb break="no" />tion of Caraccas, we must recollect the<lb break="yes"/>general disposition of the mountains of<lb break="yes"/>the coast, and the great longitudinal val-<lb break="no"/>leys, by which they were traversed. The<lb break="yes"/>Guayra rises in the group of primitive<lb break="yes" />mountains of Higuerota, which separates<lb break="yes"/>the valley of Caraccas from that of Ara-<lb break="no"/>gua. It is formed near Las Ajuntas by<lb break="yes"/>the junction of the little rivers of San Pe-<lb break="no"/>dro and Macarao, and runs first to the<lb break="yes"/>east as far as the Cuesta of Auyamas,<lb break="yes"/>and then to the south, to unite its waters<lb break="yes"/>with those of Rio Tuy, below Yare. The<lb break="yes"/>Rio Tuy is the only considerable river in<lb break="yes" />the northern and mountainous part of<lb break="yes"/>the province.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The climate of Caraccas has often been<lb break="yes"/>called a perpetual spring. It is found<lb break="yes"/>every where, half way up the Cordilleras<lb break="yes"/>of Equinoctial America, between four<lb break="yes"/>hundred and nine hundred toises of ele-<lb break="no" />vation, unless the great breadth of the<lb break="yes"/>valley, joined to an arid soil, causes an<lb break="yes"/>extraordinary intensity of radiant caloric.<lb break="yes"/>What indeed can we imagine more de-<lb break="no"/>lightful than a temperature, which in<lb break="yes"/>the day keeps between 20° and 26°;<lb break="yes"/>and at night, between 16° and 18°,<lb break="yes"/>which is equally favourable to the plan-<lb break="no"/>tain (cambury), the orange-tree, the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/>coffee-tree, the apple, the apricot, and<lb break="yes"/>corn? A national writer compares the<lb break="yes"/>situation of Caraccas to the terrestrial<lb break="yes"/>Paradise, and recognizes in the Anauco<lb break="yes"/>and the neighbouring torrents, the four<lb break="yes" />rivers of the Garden of Eden.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It is to be regretted, that such a tem-<lb break="no"/>perate climate is generally inconstant<lb break="yes"/>and variable. The inhabitants of Ca-<lb break="no"/>raccas complain of having several seasons<lb break="yes"/>in the same day; and of the rapid<lb break="yes"/>change from one season to another. In<lb break="yes"/>the month of January for instance, a<lb break="yes"/>night, of which the mean temperature is<lb break="yes" />16°, is followed by a day, when the ther-<lb break="no"/>mometer, during eight successive hours,<lb break="yes"/>keeps above 22° in the shade. In the<lb break="yes"/>same day, we find the temperature of 24°<lb break="yes"/>and 18°.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The cool and delightful climate we<lb break="yes"/>have been describing, agrees also with<lb break="yes"/>the culture of equinoctial productions.<lb break="yes"/>The sugar-cane is cultivated with success,<lb break="yes" />even at heights exceeding that of Carac-<lb break="no"/>cas; but in the valley, on account of the<lb break="yes"/>dryness of the climate, and the stony<lb break="yes"/>soil, the cultivation of the coffee-tree is<lb break="yes"/>preferred; which there yields little fruit<lb break="yes" />indeed, but of the finest quality. When<lb break="yes"/>the shrub is in blossom, the plain ex-<lb break="no"/>tending beyond Chacao presents a de-<lb break="no"/>lightful aspect. The banana-tree, which<lb break="yes"/>is seen in the plantations near the town,<lb break="yes" />is not the great <hi rendition="#i">platano harton;</hi> but the<lb break="yes"/>varieties <hi rendition="#i">camburi</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">dominico,</hi> which<lb break="yes"/>require less heat. The great plantations<lb break="yes"/>are brought to the market of Caraccas<lb break="yes"/>from the haciendos of Turiamo, situate<lb break="yes"/>on the coast between Burburata and<lb break="yes"/>Porto Cabello. The highest flavoured<lb break="yes"/>pine-apples are those of Baruto, of Em-<lb break="no"/>pedrado, and of the heights of Buena-<lb break="no"/>vista, on the road to Victoria. When a<lb break="yes" />traveller ascends, for the first time, to<lb break="yes"/>the valley of Caraccas, he is agreeably<lb break="yes"/>surprised to find the culinary plants of<lb break="yes"/>our climate, the strawberry, the vine,<lb break="yes"/>and almost all the fruit-trees of the tem-<lb break="no" />perate zone, growing by the side of the<lb break="yes"/>coffee and banana-tree. The apples and<lb break="yes"/>peaches esteemed the best come from<lb break="yes"/>Macaroa, or from the western extre-<lb break="no" />mity of the valley. There, the quince-<lb break="maybe"/>tree, the trunk of which attains only<lb break="yes"/>four or five feet in height, is so common,<lb break="yes"/>that it has almost become wild. Pre-<lb break="no"/>served apples and quinces, particularly<lb break="yes"/>the latter, are much used in a country,<lb break="yes"/>where it is thought, that, to drink water,<lb break="yes"/>thirst must previously be excited by<lb break="yes"/>sweetmeats. In proportion as the envi-<lb break="no" />rons of the town have been cultivated<lb break="yes"/>with coffee; and the establishment of<lb break="yes"/>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">plantations,</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="600" facs="#f0011"/>
                        <cb/>plantations, which dates only from the<lb break="yes"/>year 1795, has increased the num-<lb break="no"/>ber of agricultural negroes; the apple<lb break="yes"/>and quince trees, scattered in the savan-<lb break="no" />nahs, have given place, in the valley of<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas, to maize and pulse.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I remained two months at Caraccas,<lb break="yes"/>where Mr. Bonpland and I lived in a<lb break="yes"/>large and nearly solitary house, in the<lb break="yes"/>highest part of the town. From a gal-<lb break="no"/>lery, we could survey at once the sum-<lb break="no"/>mit of the Silla, the serrated ridge of<lb break="yes"/>the Gallipano, and the charming valley<lb break="yes"/>of the Guayra, the rich cultivation of<lb break="yes" />which, formed a pleasing contrast with<lb break="yes"/>the gloomy curtain of the surrounding<lb break="yes"/>mountains. It was the season of drought,<lb break="yes"/>and, in order to improve the pasturage,<lb break="yes"/>the savannahs, and the turf that covers<lb break="yes"/>the steepest rocks, were set on fire.<lb break="yes"/>These vast conflagrations, viewed from<lb break="yes"/>a distance, produce the most singular ef-<lb break="no"/>fects of light. Wherever the savannahs,<lb break="yes" />following the undulating slope of the<lb break="yes"/>rocks, have filled up the furrows hollow-<lb break="no"/>ed out by the waters, the inflamed land<lb break="yes"/>appears, in a dark night, like currents of<lb break="yes"/>lava suspended over the valley. Their<lb break="yes"/>vivid but steady light assumes a reddish<lb break="yes"/>tint, when the wind, descending from the<lb break="yes"/>Silla, accumulates streams of vapour in<lb break="yes"/>the low regions. At other times, and<lb break="yes" />this aspect is still more solemn, these<lb break="yes"/>luminous bands, enveloped in thick<lb break="yes"/>clouds, appear only at intervals, where<lb break="yes"/>it is clear; and as the clouds ascend,<lb break="yes"/>their edges reflect a splendid light.<lb break="yes"/>These various phenomena, so common<lb break="yes"/>under the tropics, become still more in-<lb break="no"/>teresting from the form of the mountain,<lb break="yes"/>the disposition of the slopes, and the<lb break="yes" />height of the savannahs covered with<lb break="yes"/>alpine grasses. During the day, the<lb break="yes"/>wind of Petare, blowing from the east,<lb break="yes"/>drives the smoke toward the town, and<lb break="yes"/>diminishes the transparency of the air.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Civilization has in no other part of<lb break="yes"/>Spanish America, assumed a more Eu-<lb break="no"/>ropean physiognomy. The great num-<lb break="no" />ber of Indian cultivators, who inhabit<lb break="yes"/>Mexico and the interior of New Grena-<lb break="no"/>da, have impressed a peculiar, I might<lb break="yes"/>also say an exotic character, on those<lb break="yes"/>vast countries. Notwithstanding the<lb break="yes" />increase of the black population, we<lb break="yes"/>seem to be nearer Cadiz and the United<lb break="yes"/>States at Caraccas and the Havannah,<lb break="yes"/>than in any other part of the New<lb break="yes" />World.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I found in several families at Caraccas<lb break="yes"/>a taste for instruction, a knowledge of<lb break="yes"/>the master-pieces of French and Italian<lb break="yes"/>literature, and a particular predilection<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/>for music, which is cultivated with suc-<lb break="no"/>cess, and which, as it always happens<lb break="yes"/>in the pursuit of the fine arts, serves to<lb break="yes"/>bring the different classes of society near-<lb break="no"/>er to each other. The mathematical sci-<lb break="no" />ences, drawing, painting, cannot here<lb break="yes"/>boast of any of those establishments,<lb break="yes"/>with which royal munificence, and the<lb break="yes"/>patriotic zeal of the inhabitants, have<lb break="yes"/>enriched Mexico. In the midst of the<lb break="yes" />marvels of nature, so rich in productions,<lb break="yes"/>no person on this coast was devoted to<lb break="yes"/>the study of plants and minerals. In a<lb break="yes"/>convent of St. Francis alone I met with<lb break="yes" />a respectable old gentleman, who calcu-<lb break="no"/>lated the almanac for all the provinces of<lb break="yes"/>Venezuela, and who possessed some pre-<lb break="no"/>cise ideas on the state of modern astro-<lb break="no"/>nomy.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 