<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Account of the Great Cavern of the Guacharo</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:52</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.46</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-02</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-02.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-03.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent&lt;/i&gt;, 7 Bände, übersetzt von Helen Maria Williams, London 1814–1829, Band 3, London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, and Brown/J. Murray/H. Colburn 1818, S. 119–137, 152.; Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Relation historique du Voyage aux régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent&lt;/i&gt;, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 1, S. 413–422, 429–430.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Account of the Great Cavern of the Guacharo</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1820</date>
          <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Edinburgh Philosophical Journal&lt;/i&gt; 3:5 (Juli 1820), S. 83–92.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <relatedItem type="reprint">
            <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Ueber die Urvölker von Amerika und die Denkmähler welche von ihnen übrig geblieben sind. Anthropologische und ethnographische Schriften&lt;/i&gt;, herausgegeben von Oliver Lubrich, Hannover: Wehrhahn 2009, S. 35–44.</bibl>
          </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Fußnoten mit Asterisken; Schmuck: Initialen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="83" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Art.</hi> XV.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Account of the Great <placeName>Cavern of the Guacharo</placeName>.</hi> By<lb break="yes" />Baron <hi rendition="#k">Alexander de Humboldt</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">Abridged from his Personal Narrative, vol. iii.</note>.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#in">W</hi>hat</hi> gives most celebrity to the valley of <placeName>Caripe</placeName>, be-<lb break="no"/>side the extraordinary coolness of the climate, is the great <hi rendition="#i">Cueva</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>or <placeName>Cavern of the <hi rendition="#i">Guacharo.</hi>
                    </placeName> In a country where the people<lb break="yes"/>love what is marvellous, a cavern that gives birth to a river,<lb break="yes"/>and is inhabited by thousands of nocturnal birds, the fat of<lb break="yes"/>which is employed in the Missions to dress food, is an everlast-<lb break="no"/>ing object of conversation and discussion. Scarcely has a stranger<lb break="yes" />arrived at <placeName>Cumana</placeName>, when he is told of the stone of <placeName>Araya</placeName> for<lb break="yes"/>the eyes; of the labourer of Arenas who suckled his child; and<lb break="yes"/>of the <placeName>cavern of Guacharo</placeName>, which is said to be several leagues in<lb break="yes" />length; till he is tired of hearing of them. A lively interest in<lb break="yes"/>the phenomena of nature is preserved wherever society may be<lb break="yes"/>said to be without life; where, in dull monotony, it presents on-<lb break="no"/>ly simple relations little fitted to excite the ardour of curiosity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="84" facs="#f0002"/>
                <p>The cavern, which the natives call <hi rendition="#i">a mine of fat,</hi> is not in<lb break="yes"/>the <placeName>valley of Caripe</placeName> itself, but at three short leagues distance<lb break="yes"/>from the convent, towards the west-south-west. It opens into a<lb break="yes"/>lateral valley, which terminates at the <placeName>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Sierra del Guacharo.</hi>
                    </placeName> We<lb break="yes"/>set out toward the Sierra on the 18th of September, accompa-<lb break="no"/>nied by the Alcaids, or Indian magistrates, and the greater part<lb break="yes"/>of the monks of the Convent. A narrow path led us at first<lb break="yes"/>during an hour and a half toward the south, across a fine plain,<lb break="yes"/>covered with a beautiful turf. We then turned toward the<lb break="yes"/>west, along a small river, which issues from the mouth of the<lb break="yes"/>cavern. We ascended during three quarters of an hour, walk-<lb break="no"/>ing sometimes in the water, which was shallow, sometimes be-<lb break="no"/>tween the torrent and a wall of rocks, on a soil extremely slip-<lb break="no"/>pery and miry. The falling down of the earth, the scattered<lb break="yes"/>trunks of trees over which the mules could scarcely pass, and the<lb break="yes"/>creeping plants that covered the ground, rendered this part of<lb break="yes"/>the road fatiguing.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the foot of the lofty <placeName>mountain of Guacharo</placeName>, we were<lb break="yes"/>only four hundred steps from the cavern, without yet perceiving<lb break="yes"/>the entrance. The torrent runs in a crevice, which has been<lb break="yes"/>hollowed out by the waters; and we went on under a cornice,<lb break="yes"/>the projection of which prevented us from seeing the sky. The<lb break="yes"/>path winds like the river: at the last turning we came suddenly<lb break="yes"/>before the immense opening of the grotto. The aspect of this<lb break="yes"/>spot is majestic even to the eye of a traveller accustomed to the<lb break="yes"/>picturesque scenes of the higher <placeName>Alps</placeName>. I had before this seen<lb break="yes"/>the caverns of the Peak of <placeName>Derbyshire</placeName>, where, extended in a<lb break="yes"/>boat, we traversed a subterranean river, under a vault of two feet<lb break="yes"/>high. I had visited the beautiful grotto of <placeName>Treshemienshiz</placeName>, in<lb break="yes"/>the <placeName>Carpathian Mountains</placeName>, the caverns of the <placeName>Hartz</placeName>, and those<lb break="yes"/>of <placeName>Franconia</placeName>, which are vast cemeteries <note place="foot" n="*">The mould, that has covered for thousands of years the soil of the caverns of<lb break="yes"/>
                        <placeName>Gaylenreuth</placeName> and <placeName>Muggendorf</placeName> in <placeName>Franconia</placeName>, emits even now choke-damps, or ga-<lb break="no"/>seous mixtures of hydrogen and nitrogen, that rise to the roof of these caves. This<lb break="yes"/>fact is known to all those who shew these caverns to travellers; and when I had<lb break="yes"/>the direction of the mines of the <placeName>Fichtelberg</placeName>, I observed it frequently in the sum-<lb break="no"/>mer time.</note> of bones of tygers,<lb break="yes"/>hyenas, and bears, as large as our horses. Nature in every zone<lb break="yes"/>follows immutable laws in the distribution of rocks, in the exte-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="85" facs="#f0003"/>rior form of mountains, and even in those tumultuous changes,<lb break="yes"/>which the exterior crust of our planet has undergone. So great<lb break="yes"/>a uniformity led me to believe, that the aspect of the cavern of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName>Caripe</placeName> would differ little from what I had observed in my pre-<lb break="no"/>ceding travels. The reality far exceeded my expectations. If<lb break="yes"/>the configuration of the grottoes, the splendor of the stalactites,<lb break="yes"/>and all the phenomena of inorganic nature, present striking ana-<lb break="no"/>logies, the majesty of equinoxial vegetation gives at the same<lb break="yes"/>time an individual character to the aperture of the cavern.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The <placeName>Cueva del Guacharo</placeName> is pierced in the vertical profile<lb break="yes"/>of a rock. The entrance is toward the south, and forms a vault<lb break="yes"/>eighty feet broad, and seventy-two feet high. This elevation is<lb break="yes"/>but a fifth less than that of the colonnade of the <placeName>Louvre</placeName>. The<lb break="yes"/>rock, that surmounts the grotto, is covered with trees of gigan-<lb break="no"/>tic height. The mammee-tree, and the genipa with large and<lb break="yes"/>shining leaves, raise their branches vertically toward the sky;<lb break="yes"/>while those of the courbaril and the erythrina form, as they ex-<lb break="no"/>tend themselves, a thick vault of verdure. Plants of the family<lb break="yes"/>of pothos with succulent stems, oxalises, and orchideæ of a sin-<lb break="no"/>gular structure, rise in the driest clefts of the rocks; while creep-<lb break="no" />ing plants, waving in the winds, are interwoven in festoons be-<lb break="no" />fore the opening of the cavern. We distinguished in these fes-<lb break="no" />toons a bignonia of a violet-blue, the purple dolichos, and for<lb break="yes" />the first time that magnificent olandra, the orange flower of<lb break="yes" />which has a fleshy tube more than four inches long. The en-<lb break="no" />trances of grottoes, like the view of cascades, derive their prin-<lb break="no"/>cipal charm from the situation, more or less majestic, in which<lb break="yes"/>they are placed, and which in some sort determines the charac-<lb break="no"/>ter of the landscape. What a contrast between the Cueva of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName>Caripe</placeName>, and those caverns of the North crowned with oaks and<lb break="yes"/>gloomy larch-trees!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But this luxury of vegetation embellishes not only the out-<lb break="no"/>side of the vault, it appears even in the vestibule of the grotto.<lb break="yes"/>We saw with astonishment plantain-leaved heliconias eighteen<lb break="yes"/>feet high, the praga palm-tree, and arborescent arums, follow<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the river even to those subterranean places. The<lb break="yes" />vegetation continues in the cave of <placeName>Caripe</placeName>, as in those deep cre-<lb break="no"/>vices of the <placeName>Andes</placeName>, half excluded from the light of day; and<lb break="yes"/>does not disappear, till, advancing in the interior, we reach thir-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="86" facs="#f0004"/> ty or forty paces from the entrance. We measured the way by<lb break="yes"/>means of a cord; and we went on about four hundred and thir-<lb break="no"/>ty feet, without being obliged to light our torches. Day-light<lb break="yes"/>penetrates even into this region, because the grotto forms but<lb break="yes"/>one single channel, which keeps the same direction from south-<lb break="no"/>east to north-west. Where the light begins to fail, we heard<lb break="yes"/>from afar the hoarse sounds of the nocturnal birds, sounds<lb break="yes"/>which the natives think belong exclusively to those subterrane-<lb break="no"/>ous places.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The guacharo is of the size of our fowls, has the mouth of<lb break="yes"/>the goatsuckers and procnias, and the port of those vultures,<lb break="yes"/>the crooked beak of which is surrounded with stiff silky hairs.<lb break="yes"/>It forms a new genus, very different from the goatsucker by<lb break="yes"/>the force of its voice, by the considerable strength of its beak,<lb break="yes" />containing a double tooth, by its feet without the membranes<lb break="yes" />that unite the anterior phalanxes of the claws. It is the first<lb break="yes" />example of a nocturnal bird among the <hi rendition="#i">passeres dentirostrati.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>In its manners it has analogies both with the goatsuckers and<lb break="yes"/>the alpine crow. The plumage of the guacharo is of a dark<lb break="yes"/>bluish-grey, mixed with small streaks and specks of black.<lb break="yes"/>Large white spots, which have the form of a heart, and which<lb break="yes"/>are bordered with black, mark the head, the wings, and the<lb break="yes"/>tail. The eyes of the bird are hurt by the blaze of day; they<lb break="yes"/>are blue, and smaller than those of the goatsuckers. The<lb break="yes"/>spread of the wings, which are composed of seventeen or eighteen<lb break="yes"/>quill feathers, is three feet and a half. The guacharo quits the<lb break="yes"/>cavern at night-fall, especially when the moon shines. It is al-<lb break="no"/>most the only frugiferous nocturnal bird that is yet known; the<lb break="yes"/>conformation of its feet sufficiently shows, that it does not hunt<lb break="yes"/>like our owls. It feeds on very hard fruits; as the nut-cracker<lb break="yes"/>and pyrrhocorax. The latter nestles also in clefts of rocks, and<lb break="yes"/>is known under the name of <choice>
                        <sic>
                            <hi rendition="#i">night-crow,</hi>
                        </sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">
                            <hi rendition="#i">night-crow</hi>.</corr>
                    </choice> The Indians assured<lb break="yes"/>us, that the guacharo does not pursue either the lamellicornous<lb break="yes"/>insects, or those phalænæ which serve as food to the goatsuck-<lb break="no"/>ers. It is sufficient to compare the beaks of the guacharo and<lb break="yes"/>goatsucker, to conjecture how much their manners must differ.<lb break="yes"/>It is difficult to form an idea of the horrible noise occasioned by<lb break="yes"/>thousands of these birds in the dark part of the cavern; and<lb break="yes"/>which can only be compared to the croaking of our crows, which,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="87" facs="#f0005"/>in the pine forests of the north, live in society, and construct<lb break="yes"/>their nests upon trees, the tops of which touch each other. The<lb break="yes"/>shrill and piercing cries of the guacharoes strike upon the vaults<lb break="yes"/>of the rocks, and are repeated by the echo in the depth of the<lb break="yes"/>cavern. The Indians showed us the nests of these birds, by<lb break="yes"/>fixing torches to the end of a long pole. These nests were fifty<lb break="yes"/>or sixty feet high above our heads, in holes in the shape of fun-<lb break="no"/>nels, with which the roof of the grotto is pierced like a sieve.<lb break="yes"/>The noise increased as we advanced, and the birds were affright-<lb break="no"/>ed by the light of the torches of copal. When this noise ceased<lb break="yes"/>around us, we heard at a distance the plaintive cries of the birds<lb break="yes"/>roosting in other ramifications of the cavern. It seemed as if<lb break="yes"/>these bands answered each other alternately.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Indians enter into the <placeName>Cueva del Guacharo</placeName> once a-<lb break="no"/>year, near midsummer, armed with poles, by means of which<lb break="yes"/>they destroy the greater part of the nests. At this season seve-<lb break="no"/>ral thousands of birds are killed; and the old ones, as if to de-<lb break="no"/>fend their brood, hover around the heads of the Indians, uttering<lb break="yes"/>terrible cries. The young, which fall to the ground, are open-<lb break="no"/>ed on the spot. Their peritoneum is extremely loaded with fat,<lb break="yes"/>and a layer of fat reaches from the abdomen to the anus, form-<lb break="no"/>ing a kind of cushion between the legs of the bird. This quan-<lb break="no"/>tity of fat in frugiferous animals, not exposed to the light, and<lb break="yes"/>exerting very little muscular motion, reminds us of what has<lb break="yes"/>been long since observed in the fattening of geese and oxen. It<lb break="yes"/>is well known how favourable darkness and repose are to this pro-<lb break="no"/>cess. The nocturnal birds of Europe are lean, because, instead<lb break="yes"/>of feeding on fruits like the guacharo, they live on the scanty pro-<lb break="no"/>duce of their prey. At the period which is commonly called at<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName>Caripe</placeName>
                    <hi rendition="#i">the oil harvest</hi>, the Indians build huts with palm leaves,<lb break="yes"/>near the entrance, and even in the porch of the cavern. Of<lb break="yes"/>these we still saw some remains. There, with a fire of brush-<lb break="no"/>wood, they melt in pots of clay the fat of the young birds just<lb break="yes"/>killed. This fat is known by the name of butter or oil <hi rendition="#i">(man-<lb break="no"/>teca</hi> or <hi rendition="#i" >aceite)</hi> of the guacharo. It is half liquid, transparent,<lb break="yes"/>without smell, and so pure that it may be kept above a year<lb break="yes"/>without becoming rancid. At the convent of <placeName>Caripe</placeName> no other<lb break="yes"/>oil is used in the kitchen of the monks but that of the cavern;<lb break="yes"/>and we never observed, that it gave the aliments a disagreeable<lb break="yes"/>taste or smell.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="88" facs="#f0006"/>
                <p>The quantity of this oil collected little corresponds with the<lb break="yes" />carnage made every year in the grotto by the Indians. It ap-<lb break="no" />pears that they do not get above 150 or 160 bottles (sixty cubic<lb break="yes"/>inches each) of very pure <hi rendition="#i">manteca;</hi> the rest, less transparent, is<lb break="yes"/>preserved in large earthen vessels. This branch of industry re-<lb break="no"/>minds us of the harvest of pigeon’s oil <note place="foot" n="*">This <hi rendition="#i">pigeon oil</hi> comes from the columba migratoria, (Pennant’s Arctic Zoo-<lb break="no"/>logy, vol. ii. p. 13.)</note>, of which some thou-<lb break="no"/>sands of barrels were formerly collected in Carolina. At <placeName>Caripe</placeName>,<lb break="yes" />the use of the oil of guacharoes is very ancient, and the mission-<lb break="no"/>aries have only regulated the method of extracting it. The mem-<lb break="no"/>bers of an Indian family, which bears the name of Morocomas, pre-<lb break="no"/>tend, as descendants of the first colonists of the valley, to be the<lb break="yes"/>lawful proprietors of the cavern, and arrogate to themselves the<lb break="yes"/>monopoly of the fat; but, thanks to the monastic institutions,<lb break="yes"/>their rights at present are merely honorary. In conformity to<lb break="yes"/>the system of the missionaries, the Indians are obliged to fur-<lb break="no"/>nish guacharo-oil for the church-lamp: the rest, we were as-<lb break="no"/>sured, is purchased of them. We shall not decide either on the<lb break="yes"/>legitimacy of the rights of the Morocomas, or on the origin of<lb break="yes"/>the obligation imposed on the natives by the monks. It would<lb break="yes"/>seem natural, that the produce of the chace should belong to<lb break="yes"/>those who hunt: but in the forests of the New World, as in the<lb break="yes"/>centre of European cultivation, public right is modified accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to the relations which are established between the strong<lb break="yes"/>and the weak, the victors and the vanquished.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The race of the guacharoes would have been long ago ex-<lb break="no"/>tinct, had not several circumstances contributed to its preserva-<lb break="no"/>tion. The natives, restrained by their superstitious ideas, have<lb break="yes"/>seldom the courage to penetrate far into the grotto. It appears,<lb break="yes"/>also, that birds of the same species dwell in neighbouring ca-<lb break="no"/>verns, which are too narrow to be accessible to man. Perhaps<lb break="yes"/>the great cavern is repeopled by colonies, that abandon the small<lb break="yes" />grottoes, for the missionaries assured us, that hitherto no sensible<lb break="yes"/>diminution of the birds had been observed. Young guacharoes<lb break="yes"/>have been sent to the port of <placeName>Cumana</placeName>, and have lived there se-<lb break="no"/>veral days without taking any nourishment; the seeds offered to<lb break="yes"/>them not suiting their taste. When the crops and gizzards of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="89" facs="#f0007"/>young birds are opened in the cavern, they are found to contain<lb break="yes"/>all sorts of hard and dry fruits, which furnish, under the singu-<lb break="no"/>lar name of guacharo seed, <hi rendition="#i" >semilla del guacharo,</hi> a very cele-<lb break="no"/>brated remedy against intermittent fevers. The old birds carry<lb break="yes"/>these seeds to their young. They are carefully collected, and<lb break="yes"/>sent to the sick at <placeName>Cariaco</placeName>, and other places of the low regions,<lb break="yes"/>where fevers are prevalent.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We followed, as we continued our progress through the<lb break="yes"/>cavern, the banks of the small river which issued from it, and<lb break="yes"/>is from twenty-eight to thirty feet wide. We walked on the<lb break="yes"/>banks, as far as the hills formed of calcareous incrustations per-<lb break="no"/>mitted us. When the torrent winds among very high masses<lb break="yes"/>of stalactites, we were often obliged to descend into its bed,<lb break="yes"/>which is only two feet in depth. We learnt, with surprise, that<lb break="yes"/>this subterraneous rivulet is the origin of the <placeName>river Caripe</placeName>,<lb break="yes" />which, at a few leagues distance, after having joined the small<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName>river of Santa Maria</placeName>, is navigable for canoes. It enters into the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName>river Areo</placeName> under the name of <hi rendition="#i">
                        <placeName>Canno de Terezen</placeName>.</hi> We found<lb break="yes"/>on the banks of the subterraneous rivulet a great quantity<lb break="yes"/>of palm-tree wood, the remains of trunks, on which the In-<lb break="no"/>dians climb to reach the nests hanging to the roofs of the ca-<lb break="no"/>vern. The rings, formed by the vestiges of the old footstalks<lb break="yes"/>of the leaves, furnish as it were the footsteps of a ladder perpen-<lb break="no" />dicularly placed.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <placeName>The Grotto of Caripe</placeName> preserves the same direction, the<lb break="yes"/>same breadth, and its primitive height of sixty or seventy feet,<lb break="yes"/>to the distance of 1458 feet, accurately measured. I have ne-<lb break="no"/>ver seen a cavern in either continent, of so uniform and regular<lb break="yes"/>a construction. We had great difficulty in persuading the In-<lb break="no"/>dians to pass beyond the outer part of the grotto, the only part<lb break="yes"/>which they annually visit to collect the fat. The whole autho-<lb break="no"/>rity of <hi rendition="#i">los padres</hi> was necessary, to induce them to advance as far<lb break="yes"/>as the spot where the soil rises abruptly at an inclination of sixty<lb break="yes" />degrees, and where the torrent forms a small subterraneous cas-<lb break="no" />cade <note place="foot" n="*">We find this phenomenon of a subterranean cascade, but on a much larger<lb break="yes"/>scale, in <placeName>England</placeName> at <placeName>Yordas Cave</placeName>, near <placeName>Kingsdale</placeName>, in <placeName>Yorkshire</placeName>.</note>. The natives connect mystic ideas with this cave, inhabited<lb break="yes"/>by nocturnal birds; they believe, that the souls of their ancestors<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="90" facs="#f0008"/> sojourn in the deep recesses of the cavern. “Man,” say they,<lb break="yes"/>“should avoid places which are enlightened neither by the Sun<lb break="yes"/>nor by the Moon.” To go and join the guacharoes, is to rejoin<lb break="yes"/>their fathers, is to die. The magicians and the poisoners per-<lb break="no"/>form their nocturnal tricks at the entrance of the cavern, to con-<lb break="no"/>jure the chief of the evil spirits.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the point where the river forms the subterraneous cas-<lb break="no"/>cade, a hill covered with vegetation, which is opposite the open-<lb break="no"/>ing of the grotto, presents itself in a very picturesque manner.<lb break="yes"/>It appears at the extremity of a straight passage, 240 toises in<lb break="yes" />length. The stalactites, which descend from the vault, and<lb break="yes" />which resemble columns suspended in the air, display themselves<lb break="yes" />on a back-ground of verdure. The opening of the cavern ap-<lb break="no" />peared singularly contracted, when we saw it about the middle<lb break="yes" />of the day, illumined by the vivid light reflected at once from<lb break="yes" />the sky, the plants, and the rocks. The distant light of day<lb break="yes" />formed somewhat of magical contrast with the darkness that<lb break="yes" />surrounded us in those vast caverns. We discharged our pieces<lb break="yes" />at a venture, wherever the cries of the nocturnal birds, and the<lb break="yes"/>flapping of their wings, led us to suspect that a great number<lb break="yes"/>of nests were crowded together. After several fruitless attempts,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">M. Bonpland</persName> succeeded in killing a couple of guacharoes, which,<lb break="yes"/>dazzled by the light of the torches, seemed to pursue us. This<lb break="yes"/>circumstance afforded me the means of drawing this bird, which<lb break="yes"/>hitherto had remained unknown to naturalists. We climbed,<lb break="yes"/>not without some difficulty, the small hill, whence the subterra-<lb break="no"/>neous rivulet descends. We saw that the grotto was perceptibly<lb break="yes"/>contracted, retaining only forty feet in height; and that it con-<lb break="no"/>tinued stretching to the north-east, without deviating from its<lb break="yes"/>primitive direction, which is parallel to that of the great valley<lb break="yes"/>of Caripe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In this part of the cavern, the rivulet deposits a blackish<lb break="yes" />mould, very like the matter which, in the grotto of <placeName>Muggen-<lb break="no"/>dorf</placeName> in <placeName>Franconia</placeName>, is called the <hi rendition="#i">earth of sacrifice.</hi> We could<lb break="yes" />not discover, whether this fine and spongy mould fall through<lb break="yes" />the cracks which communicate with the surface of the ground<lb break="yes" />above, or be washed down by the rain-water that penetrates in-<lb break="no" />to the cavern. It was a mixture of silex, alumen, and vegetable<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">detritus.</hi> We walked in thick mud to a spot, where we beheld<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="91" facs="#f0009"/>with astonishment the progress of subterraneous vegetation.<lb break="yes"/>The seeds, which the birds carry into the grotto to feed their<lb break="yes"/>young, spring up wherever they can fix in the mould, that co-<lb break="no"/>vers the calcareous incrustations. Blanched stalks, with some<lb break="yes"/>half-formed leaves, had risen to the height of two feet. It was<lb break="yes"/>impossible to ascertain the species of plants, the form, colour,<lb break="yes"/>and aspect of which had been changed by the absence of light.<lb break="yes"/>Those traces of organization amid darkness, forcibly excited the<lb break="yes"/>curiosity of the natives, in general so stupid, and difficult to be<lb break="yes"/>moved. They examined them in that silent meditation inspired<lb break="yes"/>by a place they seemed to dread. It might be thought, that<lb break="yes"/>these subterraneous vegetables, pale and disfigured, appear-<lb break="no"/>ed to them phantoms banished from the face of the earth.<lb break="yes"/>To me the scene recalled one of the happiest periods of my<lb break="yes"/>early youth, a long abode in the mines of <placeName>Freiberg</placeName>, where I<lb break="yes"/>made experiments on the effects of blanching, which are very<lb break="yes"/>different, according as the air is pure, or overcharged with hy-<lb break="no"/>drogen or azote.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The missionaries, with all their authority, could not prevail<lb break="yes"/>on the Indians to penetrate farther into the cavern. As the<lb break="yes"/>vault grew lower, the cries of the guacharoes became more shrill.<lb break="yes"/>We were obliged to yield to the pusillanimity of our guides,<lb break="yes"/>and trace back our steps. The appearance of the cavern was in-<lb break="no"/>deed very uniform. We find, that a bishop of St Thomas of <placeName>Gui-<lb break="no"/>ana</placeName> had gone farther than ourselves. He had measured nearly<lb break="yes"/>2500 feet from the mouth to the spot where he stopped, though<lb break="yes"/>the cavern reached farther. The remembrance of this fact was<lb break="yes"/>preserved in the convent of <placeName>Caripe</placeName>, without the exact period be-<lb break="no" />ing noted. The bishop had provided himself with great torches<lb break="yes" />of white wax of Castile. We had torches composed only of the<lb break="yes" />bark of trees and native resin. The thick smoke which issues<lb break="yes" />from these torches, in a narrow subterranean passage, hurts the<lb break="yes" />eye, and obstructs the respiration.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We followed the course of the torrent to go out of the ca-<lb break="no"/>vern. Before our eyes were dazzled with the light of day, we saw,<lb break="yes" />without the grotto, the water of the river sparkling amid the foliage<lb break="yes"/>of the trees that concealed it. It was like a picture placed in the<lb break="yes"/>distance, and to which the mouth of the cavern served as a frame.<lb break="yes"/>Having at length reached the entrance, and seated ourselves on<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="92" facs="#f0010"/>the bank of the rivulet, we rested after our fatigues. We were<lb break="yes"/>glad to be beyond the hoarse cries of the birds, and to leave a<lb break="yes"/>place where darkness does not offer even the charm of silence<lb break="yes"/>and tranquillity. We could scarcely persuade ourselves, that the<lb break="yes"/>name of the <placeName>Grotto of Caripe</placeName> had hitherto remained unknown<lb break="yes"/>in <placeName>Europe</placeName>. The guacharoes alone would have been sufficient to<lb break="yes"/>render it celebrated. These nocturnal birds have been nowhere<lb break="yes"/>yet discovered, except in the <placeName>mountains of Caripe</placeName> and <placeName>Cumana-<lb break="no" />coa</placeName>.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The <placeName>cavern of Caripe</placeName>, situated nearly in the latitude of<lb break="yes"/>10° 10′, consequently in the centre of the torrid zone, is elevated<lb break="yes"/>506 toises above the level of the water in the <placeName>Gulf of Cariaco</placeName>.<lb break="yes"/>We found in every part of it, in the month of September, the<lb break="yes"/>temperature of the interior air between 64°.6 and 66° of Fah-<lb break="no"/>renheit; the external atmosphere being at 61°.2. At the en-<lb break="no"/>trance of the cavern, the thermometer in the air was at 63°.7,<lb break="yes"/>but when immersed in the water of the little subterraneous river,<lb break="yes"/>it marked, even to the end of the cavern, 62°.2.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 