<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="631" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Milk of the Cow Tree, and on Vegetable Milk in<lb break="yes"/>general.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">by m. humboldt.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">M.</hi> Humboldt and his companions, in the course of their travels,<lb break="yes"/>heard an account of a tree which grows in the valleys of<lb break="yes"/>Aragua, the juice of which is a nourishing milk, and which, from<lb break="yes"/>that circumstance, has received the name of the cow tree. As the<lb break="yes"/>milky juices of plants are in general acrid, bitter, and even poisonous,<lb break="yes"/>M. Humboldt was at first scarcely disposed to credit the account,<lb break="yes"/>but experience proved it to be correct.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The tree in its general aspect resembles the chrysophyllum cainito;<lb break="yes"/>its leaves are oblong, pointed, leathery, and alternate, marked with<lb break="yes"/>lateral veins, projecting downwards, they are parallel, and are ten<lb break="yes"/>inches long. M. Humboldt had no opportunity of seeing the flower;<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="632" facs="#f0002"/>the fruit is somewhat fleshy, and contains one or sometimes two nuts.<lb break="yes"/>When incisions are made into the trunk, it discharges abundantly a<lb break="yes"/>glutinous milk, moderately thick, without any acridness, and exhal-<lb break="no"/>ing an agreeable balsamic odour. The travellers drank considerable<lb break="yes"/>quantities of it without experiencing any injurious effects: its viscidity<lb break="yes"/>only rendering it rather unpleasant. The superintendant of the<lb break="yes" />plantation assured them that the negroes acquire flesh during the<lb break="yes"/>season in which the cow tree yields the greatest quantity of milk.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When this fluid is exposed to the air, perhaps, in conquence of the<lb break="yes"/>absorption of the oxygen of the atmosphere, its surface becomes<lb break="yes"/>covered with membranes of a substance that appears to be of a decided<lb break="yes"/>animal nature, yellowish, thready, and of a cheesy consistence.<lb break="yes"/>These membranes, when separated from the more aqueous part of the<lb break="yes"/>fluid, are almost as elastic as caoutchouc; but at the same time they<lb break="yes"/>are as much disposed to become putrid as gelatine. The natives<lb break="yes"/>give the name of cheese to a coagulum, which is separated by the<lb break="yes"/>contact of the air; in the course of five or six days, it becomes sour.<lb break="yes"/>The milk, kept for some time in a corked phial, had deposited a little<lb break="yes" />coagulum, and still exhaled its balsamic odour. If the recent juice<lb break="yes"/>be mixed with cold water, the coagulum is formed in small<lb break="yes"/>quantity only; but the separation of the viscid membranes occurs<lb break="yes"/>when it is placed in contact with nitric acid.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This remarkable tree seems to be peculiar to the Cordilliere du<lb break="yes" />Littoral, especially from Barbula to the lake of Maracaybo. There<lb break="yes"/>are likewise some traces of it near the village of San Mateo; and,<lb break="yes"/>according to the account of M. Bredmeyer, in the valley of Caucagua,<lb break="yes"/>three days journey to the east of the Caraccas. This naturalist has<lb break="yes"/>likewise described the vegetable milk of the cow tree as possessing<lb break="yes"/>an agreeable flavour and an aromatic odour: the natives of Caucagua<lb break="yes"/>called it the milk tree.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. Humboldt offers some general observations upon the milky<lb break="yes" />juices of plants, and concludes with some particular observations<lb break="yes"/>upon the fluid which is procured from the carica papaya: this<lb break="yes"/>has been analyzed by M. Vauquelien; but the specimen which he<lb break="yes"/>examined had had its properties altered by having been conveyed to a<lb break="yes"/>great distance, and kept for a long time.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The younger is the fruit of the papaw, the more milk does it yield;<lb break="yes"/>in proportion as the fruit ripens, the milk, which is less abundant,<lb break="yes"/>becomes more watery: there is then less of that animal matter which<lb break="yes"/>coagulable by acids and by the absorption of oxygen. When<lb break="yes"/>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>pitric</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">nitric</corr>
                    </choice> acid is poured drop by drop into the milky juice procured from<lb break="yes"/>a very young fruit, a very extraordinary phenomenon is observed. In<lb break="yes"/>the centre of each drop there is formed a gelatinous pellicule, divided<lb break="yes"/>by greyish stri&#x00E6;; these stri&#x00E6; are merely the juice which is rendered<lb break="yes"/>more watery, because the contact of the acid has caused it to lose its<lb break="yes"/>albumen. At the same time the centre of the pellicule becomes opa-<lb break="no"/>que, and of the colour of the yolk of the egg; while it increases in<lb break="yes"/>bulk by the prolongation of the diverging fibres. The whole fluid at<lb break="yes"/>first has the appearance of an agate with milky clouds; and it appears<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="633" facs="#f0003"/>as if organic membranes were produced under the eye. When the coa-<lb break="no"/>gulum is moved, it becomes granulated like soft cheese; the yellow co-<lb break="no"/>lour is reproduced by adding a few more drops of nitric acid. The acid<lb break="yes"/>in this case acts in the same manner with the oxygen of the atmos-<lb break="no"/>phere, at the temperature of from 80&#x00B7;5 to 95 deg (Far.); for the white<lb break="yes"/>coagulum becomes yellow in two or three minutes by exposure to<lb break="yes"/>the sun. After some hours, the yellow colour turns brown, un-<lb break="no"/>doubtedly because the carbon is more liberated in proportion as the<lb break="yes"/>hydrogen, with which it was combined, is burned. The coagulum<lb break="yes"/>formed by the acid becomes viscid, and acquires the waxy odour,<lb break="yes"/>which is perceived when the muscular fibre or fungi are treated with<lb break="yes" />nitric acid. From the interesting experiments of Mr. Hatchett, it<lb break="yes"/>may be supposed that in this case the <choice>
                        <sic>ablumen</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">albumen</corr>
                    </choice> is partially converted<lb break="yes"/>to the state of gelatine.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When the coagulum of the papaw is thrown into water, it softens,<lb break="yes" />becomes partially dissolved, and gives the water a yellowish tinge;<lb break="yes"/>the milk, when placed in contact with water, also forms membranes;<lb break="yes"/>a tremulous jelly, similar to starch is immediately precipitated,<lb break="yes"/>and the appearance is more remarkable if we employ water at<lb break="yes"/>the temperature of from about 100 deg. <choice><sic>140 to</sic><corr type="editorial">to 140</corr></choice> deg. (Far.) If<lb break="yes"/>carbonate of soda be added to the fluid, the coagulum is not formed;<lb break="yes"/>but it is immediately produced by the addition of an acid. If we<lb break="yes"/>compare together the milky juices of the papaw, the cow tree, and<lb break="yes"/>the h&#x00E6;vea caoutchouc we find a striking <choice><sic>remblance</sic><corr type="editorial">resemblance</corr></choice> between the<lb break="yes"/>juices which abound in caseous matter, and those in which the<lb break="yes"/>caoutchouc predominates. According to the opinion of M. Gay-<lb break="no"/>Lussac, we may consider the caoutchouc as analogous to the oily<lb break="yes"/>part or the butter of the vegetable milk; in the vegetable <choice><sic>milky</sic><corr type="editorial">milk</corr></choice><lb break="yes"/>we find caseum and caoutchouc; in animal milk, caseum and butter.<lb break="yes"/>The albuminous and the oily principles, exist in different proportions<lb break="yes"/>in the different species of animals and milky plants; and in the<lb break="yes"/>last, they are frequently united to other substances which render them<lb break="yes" />injurious as articles of food.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 