<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">The Caraccas</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:52</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.47</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1818-Curious_Circumstance-02-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-02-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent&lt;/i&gt;, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 1, S. 370, 531, 611, 376–378, 381–383, 454–455, 535–536, 545–554, 590–594.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">The Caraccas</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1818</date>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The analectic magazine&lt;/i&gt; 12 (Juli–Dezember 1818), S. 508–517.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="508" facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#k">the caraccas.</hi><lb/><hi rendition="#i">From the third volume of Humboldt&#x2019;s Per-<lb/>sonal Travels.</hi></head><lb/>
                <head><hi rendition="#k">scenery of south america.</hi></head>
                <p>When a traveller newly arrived from<lb/>Europe penetrates for the first time into<lb/>the forests of South America, nature pre-<lb/>sents herself to him under an unexpect-<lb/>ed aspect. The objects that surround<lb/>him recall but feebly those pictures,<lb/>which celebrated writers have traced<lb/>on the banks of the Mississippi, in Flo-<lb/>rida, and in other temperate regions of<lb/>the new world. He feels at every step<lb/>that he is not on the confines, but in the<lb/>centre of the torrid zone: not in one of<lb/>the West India islands, but on a vast<lb/>continent, where every thing is gigan-<lb/>tic, the mountains, the rivers, and the<lb/>mass of vegetation. If he feel strongly<lb/>the beauty of picturesque scenery, he<lb/>can scarcely define the various emo-<lb/>tions, which crowd upon his mind; he<lb/>can scarcely distinguish what most ex-<lb/>cites his admiration, the deep silence of<lb/>those solitudes, the individual beauty<lb/>and contrast of forms, or that vigour<lb/>and freshness of vegetable life, which<lb/>characterize the climate of the tropics.<lb/>It might be said that the earth, over-<cb/>loaded with plants, does not allow them<lb/>space enough to unfold themselves.&#x2014;<lb/>The trunks of the trees are every<lb/>where concealed under a thick carpet<lb/>of verdure; and if we carefully trans-<lb/>planted the orchidae, the pipers, and the<lb/>pothos, which a single courbaril or A-<lb/>merican fig tree nourishes, we should<lb/>cover a vast extent of ground. By this<lb/>singular assemblage, the forests, as<lb/>well as the flanks of the rocks and<lb/>mountains, enlarge the domain of or-<lb/>ganic nature. The same lianas as<lb/>creep on the ground, reach the tops of<lb/>the trees, and pass from one to another<lb/>at the height of more than a hundred<lb/>feet. Thus by a continual interlacing<lb/>of parasite plants, the botanist is often<lb/>led to confound the flowers, the fruits<lb/>and leaves, which belong to different<lb/>species.</p>
                <p>We walked for some hours under the<lb/>shade of these arcades, that scarcely<lb/>admit a glimpse of the sky; which ap-<lb/>peared to me of an indigo blue, so much<lb/>the deeper as the green of the equi-<lb/>noctial plants is generally of a stronger<lb/>hue, with somewhat of a brownish tint.<lb/>A great fern tree, very different from<lb/>the pollypodium arboreum of the West<lb/>
  <pb n="509" facs="#f0002"/>Indies, rose above masses of scattered<lb/>rocks. In this place we were struck<lb/>for the first time with the sight of those<lb/>nests in the shape of bottles, or small<lb/>pockets, which are suspended to the<lb/>branches of the lowest trees, and which<lb/>attest the admirable industry of the<lb/>orioles, that mingle their warblings<lb/>with the hoarse cries of the parrots and<lb/>the macaws. These last, so well known<lb/>for their vivid colours, fly only in pairs,<lb/>while the real parrots wander about in<lb/>flocks of several hundreds. A man<lb/>must have lived in those climates, par-<lb/>ticularly in the hot valleys of the An-<lb/>des, to conceive how these birds some-<lb/>times drown with their voice the noise<lb/>of the torrents, which rush down from<lb/>rock to rock.</p>
     <p>There is something so great, so pow-<lb/>erful, in the impression made by nature<lb/>in the climate of the Indies, that after<lb/>an abode of a few months we seemed to<lb/>have lived there during a long succes-<lb/>sion of years. In Europe, the inhabi-<lb/>tant of the north and of the plains feels<lb/>an almost similar emotion, when he<lb/>quits even after a short abode the<lb/>shores of the bay of Naples, the delici-<lb/>ous country between Tivoli and the<lb/>Lake of Nemi, or the wild and solemn<lb/>scenery of the Higher Alps and the Py-<lb/>renees. Yet every where under the<lb/>temperate zone, the effects of the phy-<lb/>siognomy of the vegetables afford little<lb/>contrast. The firs and the oaks that<lb/>crown the mountains of Sweden, have<lb/>a certain family air with those, that ve-<lb/>getate in the fine climates of Greece<lb/>and Italy. Between the tropics on the<lb/>contrary, in the lower regions of both<lb/>Indies, every thing in nature appears<lb/>new and marvellous. In the open<lb/>plains, and amid the gloom of forests,<lb/>almost all the remembrances of Eu-<lb/>rope are effaced; for it is the vegetation<lb/>that determines the character of a<lb/>landscape, and acts upon our imagina-<lb/>tion by it&#x2019;s mass, the contrast of it&#x2019;s<lb/>forms, and the glow of it&#x2019;s colours. In<lb/>proportion as impressions are powerful<lb/>and new, they weaken antecedent im-<lb/>pressions, and their strength gives them<lb/>the appearance of duration. I appeal<lb/>to those, who, more sensible of the<lb/>beauties of nature than of the charms<lb/>of social life, have long resided in the<lb/>torrid zone. How dear, how memora-<lb/>ble during life, is the land where they<lb/>first disembarked! A vague desire to<lb/>revisit that spot roots itself in their<cb/>minds to the most advanced age. Cu-<lb/>mana and it&#x2019;s dusty soil are still more<lb/>frequently present to my imagination,<lb/>than all the wonders of the Cordilleras.<lb/>Beneath the fine sky of the south, the<lb/>light and the magic of the aerial hues,<lb/>embellish a land almost destitute of ve-<lb/>getation. The sun does not merely<lb/>enlighten, it colours the objects, and<lb/>wraps them in a thin vapour, which,<lb/>without changing the transparency of<lb/>the air, renders it&#x2019;s tints more harmo-<lb/>nious, softens the effects of the light,<lb/>and diffuses over nature that calm,<lb/>which is reflected in our souls. To ex-<lb/>plain this vivid impression, which the<lb/>aspect of the scenery of the two Indias<lb/>produces, even on coasts where there<lb/>is little wood, it will be sufficient to re-<lb/>collect, that the beauty of the sky aug-<lb/>ments from Naples toward the equator,<lb/>almost as much as from Provence to-<lb/>ward the south of Italy.</p>
                <p>While we take in at one view the<lb/>vast landscape, we feel little regret,<lb/>that the solitudes of the New World are<lb/>not embellished with the images of past<lb/>times. Wherever, under the torrid<lb/>zone, the earth, studded with mountains<lb/>and overspread with plants, has pre-<lb/>served it&#x2019;s primitive characteristics,<lb/>man no longer appears as the centre of<lb/>the creation. Far from taming the<lb/>elements, all his efforts tend to escape<lb/>from their empire. The changes made<lb/>by savage nations during the lapse of<lb/>ages on the surface of the globe disap-<lb/>pear before those, that are produced in<lb/>a few hours by the actions of volcanic<lb/>fires, the inundations of mighty floods,<lb/>and the impetuosity of tempests. It is<lb/>the conflict of the elements, which char-<lb/>acterizes in the New World the aspect<lb/>of nature. A country without popula-<lb/>tion appears to the people of cultivated<lb/>Europe like a city abandoned by its in-<lb/>habitants. In America, after having<lb/>lived during several years in the forests<lb/>of the low regions, or on the ridge of<lb/>the Cordilleras; after having surveyed<lb/>countries as extensive as France, con-<lb/>taining only a small number of scatter-<lb/>ed huts; a deep solitude no longer af-<lb/>frights the imagination. We become<lb/>accustomed to the idea of a world, that<lb/>supports only plants and animals; where<lb/>the savage has never uttered either the<lb/>shout of joy, or the plaintive accents of<lb/>sorrow.</p>
                <lb/>
<p><hi rendition="#i">A man giving suck.</hi>&#x2014;In the village<lb/>of Arenas, on the road from San Fer-</p>
   <pb n="510" facs="#f0003" />             
  <p>nando to Cumana, lives a labourer,<lb/>Francisco Lozano, who presented a<lb/>physiological phenomenon, highly cal-<lb/>culated to strike the imagination,<lb/>though it is very conformable to the<lb/>known laws of organized nature. This<lb/>man has suckled a child with his own<lb/>milk. The mother having fallen sick,<lb/>the father, to quiet the infant, took it<lb/>into his bed, and pressed it to his bo-<lb/>som. Lozano, then thirty-two years of<lb/>age, had never remarked till that day<lb/>that he had milk: but the irritation of<lb/>the nipple, sucked by the child, caused<lb/>the accumulation of that liquid. The<lb/>milk was thick and very sweet. The<lb/>father, astonished at the increased size<lb/>of his breast, suckled his child two or<lb/>three times a day during five months.<lb/>He drew on himself the attention of his<lb/>neighbours, but he never thought, as he<lb/>probably would in Europe, of deriving<lb/>any advantage from the curiosity he<lb/>excited. We saw the certificate which<lb/>had been drawn up on the spot, to attest<lb/>this remarkable fact, eye-witnesses of<lb/>which are still living. They assured<lb/>us, that, during this suckling, the child<lb/>had no other nourishment than the milk<lb/>of his father. Lozano, who was not at<lb/>Arenas during our journey in the Mis-<lb/>sions, came to us at Cumana. He was<lb/>accompanied by his son, who was then<lb/>thirteen or fourteen years of age. Mr.<lb/>Bonpland examined with attention the<lb/>father&#x2019;s breast, and found it wrinkled<lb/>like those of women who have given<lb/>suck. He observed, that the left breast<lb/>in particular was much enlarged;<lb/>which Lozano explained to us from the<lb/>circumstance, that the two breasts did<lb/>not furnish milk in the same abundance.<lb/>Don Vicente Emparan, governor of the<lb/>province, sent a circumstantial account<lb/>of this phenomenon to Cadiz.</p>
                <p>It is not a very uncommon circum-<lb/>stance, to find, both among human-<lb/>kind and animals, males whose breasts<lb/>contain milk; and the climate does not<lb/>appear to exert any marked influence<lb/>on the more or less abundance of this<lb/>secretion. The ancients cite the milk<lb/>of the he goats of Lemnos and Corsica.<lb/>In our own time, we have seen in the<lb/>country of Hanover, a he goat, which<lb/>for a great number of years was milked<lb/>every other day, and yielded more<lb/>milk than a female goat. Among the<lb/>signs of the pretended weakness of the<lb/>Americans, travellers have mentioned<lb/>the milk contained in the breasts of<cb/>men. It is however improbable, that<lb/>it has ever been observed in a whole<lb/>tribe, in some part of America unknown<lb/>to modern travellers; and I can affirm,<lb/>that at present it is not more common<lb/>in the new continent, than in the old.<lb/>The labourer of Arenas, whose history<lb/>we have just related, is not of the cop-<lb/>per-coloured race of Chayma Indians:<lb/>he is a white man, descended from Eu-<lb/>ropeans. Moreover, the anatomists of<lb/>Petersburg have observed, that among<lb/>the lower orders of the people in Rus-<lb/>sia, milk in the breasts of men is much<lb/>more <choice><sic>freqnent</sic><corr type="editorial">frequent</corr></choice> than among the more<lb/>southern nations; and the Russians<lb/>have never been deemed weak and ef-<lb/>feminate.</p>
                <p>There exists among the varieties of<lb/>our kind a race of men, whose breasts<lb/>at the age of puberty acquire a consi-<lb/>derable bulk. Lozano did not belong<lb/>to this class; and he often repeated to<lb/>us, that it was only the irritation of the<lb/>nipple, in consequence of the suction,<lb/>which caused the flow of the milk. This<lb/>confirms the ohservation of the anci-<lb/>ents, &#x201C;that men, who have a small<lb/>quantity of milk, yield it in abundance,<lb/>when their breasts are sucked.&#x201D; These<lb/>singular effects of a nervous stimulant<lb/>were known to the shepherds of<lb/>Greece; those of Mount Oeta rubbed<lb/>the dugs of the young goats, that had<lb/>not yet conceived, with nettles, to<lb/>make them produce milk.</p>
                <p>When we reflect on the whole of the<lb/>vital phenomena, we find, that no one<lb/>of them is entirely isolated. In every<lb/>age examples are cited of young girls<lb/>not marriageable, or women withered<lb/>by age, who have suckled children.&#x2014;<lb/>Among men these examples are infi-<lb/>nitely more rare; and after numerous<lb/>researches, I have not found above two<lb/>or three. One is cited by the anato-<lb/>mist of Verona, Alexander Benedictus,<lb/>who lived toward the end of the fif-<lb/>teenth century. He relates the history<lb/>of an inhabitant of Syria, who, to calm<lb/>the uneasiness of his child, after the<lb/>death of the mother, pressed it to his<lb/>bosom. The milk immediately came<lb/>with such abundance, that the father<lb/>could take on himself the nourishment<lb/>of his child, without assistance. Other<lb/>examples are related by Santorellus,<lb/>Paria, and Robert, bishop of Cork.&#x2014;<lb/>The greater part of these phenomena<lb/>having been noticed in times very re-<lb/>mote, it is not uninteresting to physi-</p>
  <pb n="511" facs="#f0004"/>
    <p>ology, that we can confirm them in our<lb/>own days. Besides, they bear very<lb/>strongly on the long disputed question<lb/>respecting final causes. The existence<lb/>of the nipple in men has long puzzled<lb/>philosophers; and it has even been re-<lb/>cently affirmed, &#x201C;that nature has re-<lb/>fused to one of the sexes the faculty of<lb/>sucking, because this faculty would<lb/>not accord with the dignity of man.&#x201D;</p>
<lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#i">Tobacco of Cumana.</hi>&#x2014;Next to the to-<lb/>bacco of the isle of Cuba, and of the Rio<lb/>Negro, that of Cumana is the most aro-<lb/>matic. It excels all the tobacco of<lb/>New Spain, and of the province of Va-<lb/>rinas. We shall give some particulars<lb/>of its culture, as it is essentially differ-<lb/>ent from that which is practised in Vir-<lb/>ginia. The prodigious expansion which<lb/>is remarked in the <hi rendition="#i">solaneous</hi> plants of<lb/>the valley of Cumanacoa, especially in<lb/>the abundant species of the solanum<lb/>arborescens, of aquartia, and of ces-<lb/>trum, seems to indicate how favourable<lb/>this spot is for plantations of tobacco.&#x2014;<lb/>The seed is sowed in the open ground,<lb/>at the beginning of September; though<lb/>sometimes not until the month of De-<lb/>cember, which is less favourable for the<lb/>harvest. The cotyledons appear on the<lb/>eighth day: and the young plants are<lb/>covered with large leaves of heliconia<lb/>or plantain to shelter them from the di-<lb/>rect action of the sun. Great care is<lb/>also taken to destroy the weeds,<lb/>which, between the tropics, spring up<lb/>with astonishing rapidity. The tobacco<lb/>is transplanted into a rich and well pre-<lb/>pared ground, a month or two after it<lb/>has risen from the seed. The plants<lb/>are disposed in regular rows, three or<lb/>four feet distant from each other. Care<lb/>is taken to weed them often, and the<lb/>principal stalk is several times <hi rendition="#i">topped,</hi><lb/>till greenish blue spots indicate to the<lb/>cultivator the maturity of the leaves.&#x2014;<lb/>They begin to gather them in the fourth<lb/>month, and this first gathering generally<lb/>terminates in the space of a few days.<lb/>It would be better to pluck the leaves<lb/>only as they dry. In good years, the<lb/>cultivators cut the plant when it is only<lb/>four feet high; and the shoot, which<lb/>springs from the root, throws out new<lb/>leaves with such rapidity, that they<lb/>may be gathered on the thirteenth or<lb/>fourteenth day. These last have the<lb/>cellular texture very much extended;<lb/>and they contain more water, more al-<cb/>bumen, and less of that acrid, volatile<lb/>principle, which is but little soluble in<lb/>water, and in which the stimulant pro-<lb/>perty of tobacco seems to reside.</p>
                <p>The preparation which the tobacco,<lb/>after being gathered, undergoes at Cu-<lb/>manacoa, is what the Spaniards call<lb/><hi rendition="#i">cura seca.</hi> Monsieur de Pons has very<lb/>well described it, as it is practised at<lb/>Uritucu, and in the valleys of Aragua.<lb/>The leaves are suspended by threads of<lb/>cocuiza: their ribs are taken out, and<lb/>they are twisted into cords. The pre-<lb/>pared tobacco should be carried to the<lb/>king&#x2019;s warehouses in the month of June:<lb/>but the laziness of the inhabitants, and<lb/>the preference they give to the cultiva-<lb/>tion of maize and cassava, commonly<lb/>prevent them from finishing the pre-<lb/>paration before the month of August.&#x2014;<lb/>It is easy to conceive, that the leaves,<lb/>so long exposed to very moist air, must<lb/>lose some of their flavour.</p>
                <p>The soil of Cumanacoa is so proper<lb/>for this branch of culture, that tobacco<lb/>grows wild, wherever the seed finds any<lb/>moisture. It grows thus spontaneously<lb/>at Cerro del Cuchivano, and around<lb/>the cavern of Caripe. Besides, the<lb/>only kind of tobacco cultivated at Cu-<lb/>manacoa, as well as in the neighbour-<lb/>ing districts of Aricagua and San Lor-<lb/>enzo, is the tobacco with large sestile<lb/>leaves, called Virginia tobacco. The<lb/>tobacco with petiolate leaves, which is<lb/>the yetl of the ancient Mexicans, is un-<lb/>known, though it is designated in Ger-<lb/>many under the singular name of <hi rendition="#i">Turk-<lb/>ish tobacco.</hi></p>
       <p>If the culture of tobacco were free,<lb/>the province of Cumana might furnish<lb/>a great part of Europe. It even ap-<lb/>pears that other districts would not be<lb/>less favourable to this branch of colo-<lb/>nial industry, than the valley of Cuma-<lb/>nacoa, in which the too great frequen-<lb/>cy of rains often injures the aromatic<lb/>property of the leaves.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#i">The Cocoa-Tree.</hi>&#x2014;The contrary<lb/>winds and rainy weather forced us to<lb/>go on shore at Pericantral, a small farm<lb/>situate on the south side of the gulf.&#x2014;<lb/>The whole of this coast covered with<lb/>beautiful vegetation, is almost without<lb/>cultivation. There are scarcely seven<lb/>hundred inhabitants: and, except the<lb/>village of Mariguitar, we saw only<lb/>plantations of cocoa-trees, which are<lb/>the olives of the country. This palm-</p>
      <pb n="512" facs="#f0005"/>
                <p>tree occupies on both continents a zone;<lb/>of which the mean temperature of the<lb/>year is not below 30&#x00B0;. It is, like the<lb/>cham&#x00E6;rops of the basin of the Medi-<lb/>terranean, a true palm-tree of the<lb/>coast. It prefers salt to fresh waters;<lb/>and flourishes less inland, where the air<lb/>is not loaded with saline particles, than<lb/>on the coasts. When cocoa-trees are<lb/>planted in Terra Firma, or in the Mis-<lb/>sions of the Oroonoko, at a distance<lb/>from the sea, a considerable quantity<lb/>of salt, sometimes as much as half a<lb/>bushel, is thrown into the hole that re-<lb/>ceives the cocoa-nut. Among the<lb/>plants cultivated by man, the sugar-<lb/>cane, the plantain, the mammee apple,<lb/>and alligator-pear (laurus persea), alone<lb/>have the property of the cocoa-tree;<lb/>that of being watered alike with fresh<lb/>and salt water. This circumstance is<lb/>favourable to their migrations; and if<lb/>the sugar-cane of the shore yield a sir-<lb/>up that is a little brackish, it is believed<lb/>at the same time to be better fitted for<lb/>the distillation of spirit, than the juice<lb/>produced from the canes in the interior.</p>
                <p>The cocoa-tree, in the rest of Ame-<lb/>rica, is in general cultivated around<lb/>farm-houses, to be eaten as fruit; in the<lb/>gulf of Cariaco, it forms real planta-<lb/>tions. At Cumana, they talk of a <hi rendition="#i">ha-<lb/>cienda de coco,</hi> as of a <hi rendition="#i">hacienda de can-<lb/>na</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">de cacao.</hi> In a fertile and moist<lb/>ground, the cocoa-tree begins to bear<lb/>fruit in abundance the fourth year; but<lb/>in dry soils it yields produce at the end<lb/>of ten years only. The duration of the<lb/>tree does not in general exceed eighty<lb/>or a hundred years; and it&#x2019;s mean<lb/>height at this period is from seventy to<lb/>eighty feet. This rapid growth is so<lb/>much the more remarkable, as other<lb/>palm-trees, for instance, the <hi rendition="#i">moriche,</hi><lb/>and the palm of Sombrero, the longe-<lb/>vity of which is very great, frequently<lb/>do not reach above fourteen or eigh-<lb/>teen feet in sixty years. In the first<lb/>thirty or forty years, a cocoa-tree of<lb/>the gulf of Cariaco bears every luna-<lb/>tion a cluster of ten or fourteen nuts,<lb/>all of which however do not ripen. It<lb/>may be reckoned that, on an average,<lb/>a tree produces annually a hundred<lb/>nuts, which yield eight <hi rendition="#i">flascos</hi> of oil.&#x2014;<lb/>The flasco is sold for two rials and a<lb/>half of plate, or sixteen pence. In Pro-<lb/>vence, an olive-tree thirty years old<lb/>yields twenty pounds, or seven flascoes<lb/>of oil, so that it produces something<lb/>less than a cocoa-tree. There are in<cb/>the gulf of Cariaco <hi rendition="#i">haciendas</hi> of eight<lb/>or nine thousand cocoa-trees. They<lb/>resemble, in their picturesque appear-<lb/>ance, those fine plantations of date-<lb/>trees, near Elche, in Murcia, where in<lb/>one square league are found upwards<lb/>of 70,000 palms. The cocoa-tree bears<lb/>fruit in abundance till it is thirty or<lb/>forty years old; after this age, the pro-<lb/>duce diminishes, and a trunk a hundred<lb/>years old, without being altogether<lb/>barren, yields very little produce. In<lb/>the town of Cumana a great quantity<lb/>of oil of cocoas is made, which is limpid,<lb/>without smell, and very fit for burning.<lb/>The trade in this oil is not less brisk<lb/>than that on the coast of Africa for<lb/>palm oil, which is obtained from the<lb/>elays guineensis, and is used for food.<lb/>At Cumana I have often witnessed the<lb/>arrival of canoes laden with 3000 cocoa<lb/>nuts. A tree in full bearing yields an<lb/>annual revenue of two piastres and half<lb/>(eleven shillings and tenpence half-<lb/>penny). But in the <hi rendition="#i">haciendas</hi> of cocoa,<lb/>trees of different ages being mixed, the<lb/>capital is estimated by appraisers only<lb/>at four piastres.</p>
<lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#i">Port of Barcelona.</hi>&#x2014;The port of<lb/>Barcelona, of which the name is scarce-<lb/>ly to be found on our maps, has had a<lb/>very active commerce ever since 1795.<lb/>From it is exported great part of the<lb/>produce of those vast steppes which ex-<lb/>tend from the south side of the chain of<lb/>the coast as far as the Oroonoko, and<lb/>which abound in cattle of every kind,<lb/>almost as much as the Pampas of Bue-<lb/>nos Ayres. The commercial industry<lb/>of these countries depends on the de-<lb/>mand in the great and little West India<lb/>islands for salted provision, oxen,<lb/>mules, and horses. The coasts of Ter-<lb/>ra Firma being opposite to those of the<lb/>Island of Cuba, at a distance of fifteen<lb/>or eighteen days&#x2019; sail, the merchants of<lb/>the Havannah prefer, especially in time<lb/>of peace, drawing their provision from<lb/>the port of Barcelona, to the risque of a<lb/>long voyage in another hemisphere to<lb/>the mouth of the Rio de la Plata. Of<lb/>a black population amounting to<lb/>1,300,000, which the archipelago of the<lb/>West India islands now contains, Cuba<lb/>alone has more than 230,000 slaves,<lb/>who are fed with vegetables, salt pro-<lb/>vision, and dried fish. Every vessel,<lb/>that trades in salt meat, or <hi rendition="#i">tasajo,</hi> from<lb/>Terra Firma, carries twenty or thirty<lb/>thousand arobas, the sale price of which</p>
          <pb n="513" facs="#f0006"/>      
                    <p>is more than forty-five thousand pias-<lb/>tres. The situation of Barcelona is<lb/>singularly advantageous for the trade<lb/>in cattle. The animals have only three<lb/>days&#x2019; journey from the Llanos to the<lb/>port, while it requires eight or nine<lb/>days to reach Cumana, on account of<lb/>the chain of mountains of the Brigan-<lb/>tine and the Impossible. According<lb/>to the best information I could obtain,<lb/>eight thousand mules were embarked<lb/>at Barcelona, six thousand at Porto-<lb/>Cabello, and three thousand at Caru-<lb/>pano, in 1799 and 1800, for the Span-<lb/>ish, English, and French islands. I am<lb/>ignorant of the precise exportation of<lb/>Burburata, Coro, and the mouths of the<lb/>Guarapiche and the Oroonoko; but I<lb/>believe, notwithstanding the causes<lb/>that have diminished the quantity of<lb/>cattle in the Llanos of Cumana, Bar-<lb/>celona, and Caraccas, those immense<lb/>steppes did not furnish less at that pe-<lb/>riod than thirty thousand mules a year<lb/>for the West India trade. Estimating<lb/>each mule at twenty-five piastres (the<lb/>cost price) we find that this branch of<lb/>trade alone produces nearly 3,700,000<lb/>francs, without reckoning the profits<lb/>on the freight of the vessels. Mr. de<lb/>Pons, in general very exact in his sta-<lb/>tistical computations, estimates them at<lb/>a much smaller number. But as he<lb/>could not himself visit the Llanos, his<lb/>place of agent to the French govern-<lb/>ment obliging him to reside constantly<lb/>at the town of Caraccas, the proprie-<lb/>tors of the <hi rendition="#i">Hatos</hi> perhaps communicat-<lb/>ed to him too low estimations.</p>
<lb/>
<p><hi rendition="#i">La Guayra.</hi>&#x2014;La Guayra is rather a<lb/>roadstead than a port. The sea is con-<lb/>stantly agitated, and the ships suffer<lb/>at once by the action of the wind, the<lb/>tideways, the bad anchorage, and the<lb/>worms. The lading is taken in with<lb/>difficulty, and the heights of the swell<lb/>prevents embarking mules here, as at<lb/>New Barcelona and Porto Cabello.<lb/>The free mulattos and negroes, who<lb/>carry the cocoa on board the ships, are<lb/>a class of men of very remarkable mus-<lb/>cular strength. They go up to their<lb/>middles through the water; and what<lb/>is well worthy of attention, they have<lb/>nothing to fear from the sharks, which<lb/>are so frequent in this harbour. This<lb/>fact seems connected with what I have<lb/>often observed between the tropics,<lb/>relatively to other classes of animals<cb/>that live in society, for instance, mon-<lb/>keys and crocodiles. In the missions<lb/>of the Oroonoko, and the river of Ama-<lb/>zons, the Indians, who catch monkeys<lb/>to sell them, know very well, that they<lb/>can easily succeed in taming those<lb/>which inhabit certain islands; while<lb/>monkeys of the same species, caught<lb/>on the neighbouring continent, die of<lb/>terror or rage when they find them-<lb/>selves in the power of man. The croc-<lb/>odiles of one pool in the Llanos are<lb/>cowardly, and flee even in the water;<lb/>while those of another attack with ex-<lb/>treme intrepidity. It would be difficult<lb/>to explain this difference of manners<lb/>and habits, by the aspect of their re-<lb/>spective localities. The sharks of the<lb/>port of La Guayra seem to furnish an<lb/>analogous example. They are dange-<lb/>rous and blood-thirsty at the island op-<lb/>posite the coast of Caraccas, at the<lb/>Roques, at Bonayre, and at Curassao;<lb/>while they forbear to attack persons<lb/>swimming in the ports of La Guayra<lb/>and Santa Martha. The people who,<lb/>in order to simplify the explanation of<lb/>natural phenomena, have always re-<lb/>course to the marvellous, affirm, that<lb/>in both places a bishop gave his bene-<lb/>diction to the sharks.</p>
                <p>The situation of La Guayra is very<lb/>singular, and can only be compared to<lb/>that of Santa Cruz, in Teneriffe. The<lb/>chain of mountains, that separates the<lb/>port from the high valley of Carracas,<lb/>descends almost directly into the sea;<lb/>and the houses of the town are backed<lb/>by a wall of steep rocks. There scarce-<lb/>ly remains one hundred or one hundred<lb/>and forty toises breadth of flat ground<lb/>between the wall and the ocean. The<lb/>town has six or eight thousand inhabi-<lb/>tants, and contains only two streets,<lb/>running parallel to each other, east<lb/>and west. It is commanded by the bat-<lb/>tery of <hi rendition="#i">Cerro colorado;</hi> and its fortifi-<lb/>cations along the sea-side are well dis-<lb/>posed, and kept in repair. The aspect<lb/>of this place has something solitary and<lb/>gloomy; we seemed not to be on a con-<lb/>tinent, covered with vast forests, but<lb/>in a rocky island, destitute of mould<lb/>and vegetation. With the exception of<lb/>Cape Blanco, and the cocoa-trees of<lb/>Maiqueta, no view meets the eye but<lb/>that of the horizon, the sea, and the<lb/>azure vault of heaven. The heat is<lb/>stifling during the day, and most fre-<lb/>quently during the night. The climate</p>
   <pb n="514" facs="#f0007"/>
                    <p>of La Guayra is justly considered as<lb/>more ardent than that of Cumana, Por-<lb/>to Cabello, and Coro; because the sea<lb/>breeze is less felt, and the air is heated<lb/>by the radiant caloric, which the per-<lb/>pendicular rocks emit from the time<lb/>the sun sets.</p>
                <p>At the time of my abode at La Gu-<lb/>ayra, the scourge of yellow fever, or<lb/><hi rendition="#i">calentura amarilla,</hi> had been known<lb/>only two years; and the mortality had<lb/>not been considerable, because the<lb/>confluence of strangers on the coast of<lb/>Caraccas was less than that at Havan-<lb/>nah and Vera Cruz. A few individu-<lb/>als, even Creoles and mulattos, were<lb/>sometimes taken off suddenly by cer-<lb/>tain irregular remittent fevers; which,<lb/>from being complicated with bilious<lb/>appearances, hemorrhages, and other<lb/>symptoms equally alarming, appeared<lb/>to have some analogy with the yellow<lb/>fever. They were generally men em-<lb/>ployed in the hard labour of cutting<lb/>wood; in the forests, for instance, in<lb/>the neighbourhood of the little port of<lb/>Carupano, or the gulf of Sante-Fe,<lb/>west of Cumana. Their death often<lb/>alarmed the unseasoned Europeans, in<lb/>towns that were regarded as eminent-<lb/>ly healthy; but the seeds of the spora-<lb/>dical malady by which they had been<lb/>attacked, were propagated no farther.<lb/>On the coast of Terra Firma, the real<lb/>typus of America, which is known by<lb/>the names <hi rendition="#i">vomito prieto</hi> (the black vo-<lb/>mit) and of yellow fever, and which<lb/>ought to be considered as a morbid af-<lb/>fection <hi rendition="#i">sui generis,</hi> was known only at<lb/>Porto Cabello, at Carthagena, and at<lb/>Santa Martha, where Gastelbondo had<lb/>observed and described it in 1729. The<lb/>Spaniards who had recently disem-<lb/>barked, and the inhabitants of the val-<lb/>ley of Caraccas, were not then afraid<lb/>to reside at La Guayra. They com-<lb/>plained only of the oppressive heat,<lb/>which prevailed during a great part of<lb/>the year. If they opposed themselves<lb/>to the immediate action of the sun,<lb/>they dreaded at most only those in-<lb/>flammations of the skin or eyes, which<lb/>are felt every where in the torrid zone,<lb/>and which are often accompanied by<lb/>a febrile affection, and powerful con-<lb/>gestions in the head. Many individuals<lb/>preferred the ardent but uniform cli-<lb/>mate of La Guayra, to the cool but<lb/>extremely variable climate of Carac-<cb/>cas; and scarcely any mention was<lb/>made of the insalubrity of that port.</p>
                <p>Since the year 1797, every thing has<lb/>changed. Commerce being opened to<lb/>other vessels than those of the mother<lb/>country, seamen born in colder cli-<lb/>mates than Spain, and consequently<lb/>more sensible to the impressions of the<lb/>climate of the torrid zone, began to<lb/>frequent La Guayra. The yellow fe-<lb/>ver declared itself; North Americans,<lb/>seized with the typhus, were received<lb/>in the Spanish hospitals; and it was<lb/>affirmed, that they had <hi rendition="#i">imported</hi> the<lb/>contagion, and that, before they enter-<lb/>ed the road, the disease had appeared<lb/>on board a brig, which came from<lb/>Philadelphia. The captain of the brig<lb/>denied the fact; and asserted, that, far<lb/>from having introduced this malady, his<lb/>sailors had caught it in the port. We<lb/>know from what happened in Cadiz, in<lb/>1800, how difficult it is to elucidate<lb/>facts, when their uncertainty serves to<lb/>favour theories, that are diametrically<lb/>opposite. The more enlightened in-<lb/>habitants of Caraccas and La Guayra,<lb/>divided in opinion, like the physicians<lb/>in Europe and the United States, on<lb/>the principle of contagion of the yellow<lb/>fever, cited the instance of the same<lb/>American vessel to prove, some, that<lb/>the typhus came from abroad, and<lb/>others, that it took birth in the coun-<lb/>try itself.</p>
                <p>Since the years 1797, and 1798, the<lb/>same in which there was a dreadful<lb/>mortality at Philadelphia, Santa Lucia,<lb/>and St. Domingo, the yellow fever has<lb/>continued its ravages at La Guayra.<lb/>It has proved fatal not only to the<lb/>troops newly arrived from Spain, but<lb/>also to those which had been raised<lb/>far from the coasts, in the Llanos be-<lb/>tween Calabozo and Uritucu, in a re-<lb/>gion almost as hot as La Guayra, but<lb/>favourable to health. This latter phe-<lb/>nomenon would surprise us more, if we<lb/>did not know, that even the natives<lb/>of Vera Cruz, who are not attacked<lb/>with the typhus in their own town,<lb/>sometimes sink under it in the epi-<lb/>demics of the Havannah and the United<lb/>States. As the black vomit finds an<lb/>insurmountable limit at the Encero,<lb/>(four hundred and seventy-six toises<lb/>high) on the declivity of the mountains<lb/>of Mexico, on the road to Xalapa,<lb/>where the oaks, and a cool and deli-</p>
                    <pb n="515" facs="#f0008"/>
                <p>cious climate begin; the yellow fever<lb/>scarcely ever passes beyond the ridge<lb/>of mountains that separates La Gu-<lb/>ayra from the valley of Caraccas. This<lb/>valley has been exempted from it for a<lb/>long time; for we must not confound<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i" >vomito</hi> and the yellow fever with<lb/>the irregular and bilious fevers.</p>
                <p>Since the yellow fever has made<lb/>such cruel ravages in La Guayra, the<lb/>want of cleanliness in that little town<lb/>has been exaggerated, like that of Ve-<lb/>ra Cruz, and of the quays or wharves<lb/>of Philadelphia. In a place where the<lb/>soil is extremely dry, destitute of ve-<lb/>getation, and where a few drops of<lb/>water scarcely fall in seven or eight<lb/>months, the causes that produce what<lb/>are called miasmata, cannot be very<lb/>frequent. The streets of La Guayra<lb/>appeared to me in general to be tole-<lb/>rably clean, with the exception of the<lb/>quarter of the slaughter-houses. The<lb/>sea-side has no beach, on which the<lb/>remains of fuci and of mollusc&#x00E6; are<lb/>heaped up; but the neighbouring coast,<lb/>which stretches to the east toward<lb/>Cape Codera, and consequently to the<lb/>windward of La Guayra, is extremely<lb/>unhealthy. Intermitting, putrid, and<lb/>bilious fevers often prevail at Macuto,<lb/>and at Caravalleda; and when, from<lb/>time to time, the breeze is interrupted<lb/>by a westerly wind, the little bay of<lb/>Cotia, which I shall often have occa-<lb/>sion to mention, sends an air loaded<lb/>with putrid emanations toward the<lb/>coast of La Guayra, notwithstanding<lb/>the rampart opposed by Cape Blanco.</p>
                <p>The irritability of the organs being<lb/>so different in the people of the north<lb/>and those of the south, it cannot be<lb/>doubted, that with a greater freedom<lb/>of commerce, and a more frequent<lb/>and intimate communication between<lb/>countries situate in different climates,<lb/>the yellow fever will extend its ra-<lb/>vages in the New World. It is even<lb/>probable, that the concurrence of so<lb/>many exciting causes, and their action<lb/>on individuals so differently organized,<lb/>may give birth to new forms of disease,<lb/>and new deviations of the vital powers.<lb/>This is one of the evils, that inevitably<lb/>attends a rising civilization. To point<lb/>it out is not to regret barbarism; it is<lb/>not to partake the opinions of those,<lb/>who would break the bands that unite<lb/>nations, not in order to render the<lb/>ports of the colonies more healthy, but<cb/>to thwart the introduction of know-<lb/>ledge, and slacken the progress of<lb/>reason.</p>
                <p>The yellow fever and the black vo-<lb/>mit, cease periodically at the Havan-<lb/>nah and Vera Cruz, when the north<lb/>winds bring the cold air of Canada to-<lb/>ward the Gulf of Mexico. But from<lb/>the extreme equality of temperature,<lb/>which characterizes the climates of<lb/>Porto Cabello, La Guayra, New Bar-<lb/>celona, and Cumana, it may be feared<lb/>that the typhus will there become per-<lb/>manent, whenever, from a great con-<lb/>course of strangers, it has acquired<lb/>a high degree of exacerbation.</p>
                <lb/>           
                <p><hi rendition="#i">Character of South American Popu-<lb/>lation.</hi>&#x2014;Although I had the advantage,<lb/>which few Spaniards have shared with<lb/>me of having successively visited Ca-<lb/>raccas, the Havannah, Santa Fe de<lb/>Bogota, Quito, Lima, and Mexico, and<lb/>of having been connected in these six<lb/>capitals of Spanish America with men<lb/>of all ranks, I shall not venture to de-<lb/>cide on the various degrees of civiliza-<lb/>tion, which society has attained in the<lb/>different colonies. It is easier to indi-<lb/>cate the different shades of national<lb/>improvement, and the point toward<lb/>which the unfolding of the intellect<lb/>tends in preference, than to compare<lb/>and class things that cannot be inves-<lb/>tigated under the same point of view.<lb/>It appeared to me, that a strong ten-<lb/>dency toward the study of the sciences<lb/>prevailed at Mexico and Santa Fe de<lb/>Bogota; more taste for literature, and<lb/>whatever can charm an ardent and<lb/>lively imagination, at Quito and Lima;<lb/>more accurate notions of the political<lb/>relations of countries, and more en-<lb/>larged views on the state of colonies<lb/>and their mother countries, at the Ha-<lb/>vannah and Caraccas. The numerous<lb/>communications with commercial Eu-<lb/>rope, with that sea of the West Indies,<lb/>which we have described as a medi-<lb/>terranean with many outlets, have had<lb/>a powerful influence on the progress of<lb/>society in the island of Cuba, and in<lb/>the five provinces of Venezuela. Civi-<lb/>lization has in no other part of Spanish<lb/>America assumed a more European<lb/>physiognomy. The great number of<lb/>Indian cultivators who inhabit Mexi-<lb/>co and the interior of New Grenada,<lb/>have impressed a peculiar, I might<lb/>almost say an exotic character, on</p>
                    <pb n="516" facs="#f0009"/>
                    <p>those vast countries. Notwithstanding<lb/>the increase of the black population,<lb/>we seem to be nearer Cadiz and the<lb/>United States at Caraccas and the<lb/>Havannah, than in any other part of<lb/>the New World.</p>
                <p>Caraccas being situate on the con-<lb/>tinent, and its population less mutable<lb/>than that of the islands, the national<lb/>manners have been better preserved<lb/>than at the Havannah. Society does<lb/>not present very animated and varied<lb/>pleasures; but that feeling of comfort<lb/>is experienced in domestic life, which<lb/>leads to uniform cheerfulness and cor-<lb/>diality, united with politeness of man-<lb/>ners. There exists at Caraccas, as in<lb/>every place where a great change in<lb/>the ideas is preparing, two races of<lb/>men, we might say two distinct gene-<lb/>rations; one of which, but a small num-<lb/>ber remains, preserves a strong at-<lb/>tachment for ancient customs, simpli-<lb/>city of manners, and moderation in<lb/>their desires. They live only in the<lb/>images of the past. America appears<lb/>to them a property conquered by their<lb/>ancestors. Abhorring what is called<lb/>the enlightened state of the age, they<lb/>carefully preserve hereditary preju-<lb/>dices as a part of their patrimony. The<lb/>other class, less occupied even by the<lb/>present than by the future, have a<lb/>propensity, often ill-judged, for new<lb/>habits and ideas. When this tendency<lb/>is allied to the love of solid instruction,<lb/>restrained and guided by a strong and<lb/>enlightened reason, its effects become<lb/>beneficial to society. I knew at Ca-<lb/>raccas, among the second generation,<lb/>several men equally distinguished by<lb/>their taste for study, the mildness of<lb/>their manners, and the elevation of<lb/>their sentiments. I have also known<lb/>men, who, disdaining all that is excel-<lb/>lent in the character, the literature,<lb/>and the arts of the Spaniards, have lost<lb/>their national individuality, without<lb/>having acquired from their connexions<lb/>with foreigners any just ideas of the<lb/>real bases of happiness and social or-<lb/>der.</p>
        <p>Since the reign of Charles V, the<lb/>corporation spirit and municipal habits<lb/>having passed from the mother coun-<lb/>try to the colonies, men take a plea-<lb/>sure at Cumana, and in other commer-<lb/>cial towns of Terra Firma, in exagge-<lb/>rating the pretensions to nobility of the<lb/>most illustrious families of Caraccas,<cb/>known by the name of <hi rendition="#i">los Mantuanos.</hi><lb/>I am ignorant in what manner these<lb/>pretensions were formerly manifested;<lb/>but it appeared to me, that the pro-<lb/>gress of knowledge, and the change<lb/>effected in manners, have gradually<lb/>and pretty generally destroyed what-<lb/>ever is offensive in those distinctions<lb/>among the whites. In all the colonies<lb/>there exist two kinds of nobility. One<lb/>is composed of the Creoles, whose an-<lb/>cestors have very recently filled great<lb/>stations in America. Their preroga-<lb/>tives are partly founded on the distinc-<lb/>tion they enjoy in the mother country;<lb/>and they imagine they can retain them<lb/>beyond the sea, whatever may be the<lb/>date of their settlement in the colonies.<lb/>The other nobility has more of an<lb/>American cast. It is composed of the<lb/>descendants of the <hi rendition="#i">Conquistadores,</hi> that<lb/>is to say, of the Spaniards who served in<lb/>the army at the time of the first con-<lb/>quest. Among the warriors who fought<lb/>with Cortez, Losada, and Pizarro, se-<lb/>veral belonged to the most distinguish-<lb/>ed families of the peninsula; others,<lb/>born in the inferior classes of the peo-<lb/>ple, have illustrated their names by<lb/>that chivalrous spirit, which prevailed<lb/>at the beginning of the sixteenth cen-<lb/>tury. I have elsewhere observed, that<lb/>in the records of those times of reli-<lb/>gious and military enthusiasm, we find<lb/>among the followers of the great cap-<lb/>tains, many simple, virtuous, and gene-<lb/>rous characters, who reprobated the<lb/>cruelties that stained the glory of the<lb/>Spanish name, but who, confounded in<lb/>the mass, have not escaped the general<lb/>proscription. The name of <hi rendition="#i">Conquista-<lb/>dores</hi> remains the more odious, as the<lb/>greater number of them, after having<lb/>outraged peaceful nations, and lived<lb/>in the midst of opulence, did not ex-<lb/>perience toward the end of their ca-<lb/>reer, those long misfortunes, which ap-<lb/>pease the hatred of mankind, and some-<lb/>times soften the severity of the histo-<lb/>rian.</p>
              <p>But it is not only the progress of<lb/>ideas, and the conflict between two<lb/>classes of different origin, which have<lb/>induced the privileged casts to aban-<lb/>don their pretensions, or at least to<lb/>conceal them carefully. Aristocracy<lb/>in the Spanish colonies has a counter-<lb/>poise of another kind, and of which<lb/>the action becomes every day more<lb/>powerful. A sentiment of equality</p>
                  <pb n="517" facs="#f0010"/>
                        <p>among the whites has penetrated every<lb/>bosom. Wherever men of colour are<lb/>either considered as slaves, or as hav-<lb/>ing been enfranchised, what consti-<lb/>tutes nobility is hereditary liberty, is<lb/>the proud boast of having never reck-<lb/>oned among ancestors any but free-<lb/>men. In the colonies, the colour of the<lb/>skin is the real badge of nobility. In<lb/>Mexico, as well as Peru, at Caraccas<lb/>as in the island of Cuba, a barefoot-<lb/>ed fellow is often heard exclaiming:<lb/>&#x2018;Does that rich white man think him-<lb/>self whiter than I am?&#x2019; The population<lb/>which Europe pours into America, be-<lb/>ing very considerable, it may easily<lb/>be supposed, that the axiom, every<lb/>white man is noble, <hi rendition="#i">toto blanco es ca-<lb/>balero,</hi> must singularly wound the pre-<lb/>tensions of a great number of ancient<lb/>and illustrious European families. But<lb/>we may observe farther, that the truth<lb/>of this axiom has long since been re-<lb/>cognized in Spain, among a people<lb/>justly celebrated for probity, industry,<lb/>and national spirit. Every Biscayan<lb/>calls himself noble; and there being a<lb/>greater number of Biscayans in Ame-<lb/>rica and the Philippine Islands, than<lb/>in the peninsula, the whites of this<lb/>race have contributed in no small de-<lb/>gree, to propagate in the colonies the<lb/>system of equality among all men,<lb/>whose blood has not been contami-<lb/>nated by the African race.</p>
                <p>Moreover, the countries of which<lb/>the inhabitants, even without a repre-<lb/>sentative government, or any institu-<lb/>tion of peerage, annex so much im-<lb/>portance to genealogy, and the ad-<lb/>vantages of birth, are not always those<lb/>where the aristocracy of families is the<lb/>most offensive. We should seek in vain<lb/>among the natives of Spanish origin<lb/>that cold and assuming air, which the<lb/>character of modern civilization seems<lb/>to have rendered more common in the<lb/>rest of Europe. Conviviality, candour,<lb/>and a great simplicity of manners,<lb/>unite the different classes of society in<lb/>the colonies, as well as in the mother<lb/>country. We might even venture to<lb/>say, that the expressions of vanity and<lb/>self-love are less offensive, when they<lb/>retain something of simplicity and<lb/>frankness.</p>
                <p>I found in several families at Ca-<lb/>raccas, a taste for instruction, a know-<lb/>ledge of the master-pieces of French<lb/>and Italian literature, and a particular<cb/>predilection for music, which is culti-<lb/>vated with success, and which, as it<lb/>always happens in the pursuit of the<lb/>fine arts, serves to bring the different<lb/>classes of society nearer to each other.<lb/>The mathematical sciences, drawing,<lb/>painting, cannot here boast of any<lb/>of those establishments, with which<lb/>royal munificence, and the patriotic<lb/>zeal of the inhabitants have enriched<lb/>Mexico. In the midst of the marvels<lb/>of Nature, so rich in productions, no<lb/>person on this coast was devoted to the<lb/>study of plants and minerals. In a con-<lb/>vent of St. Francis alone, I met with<lb/>a respectable old gentleman, who cal-<lb/>culated the almanac for all the pro-<lb/>vinces of Venezuela, and who pos-<lb/>sessed some precise ideas on the state<lb/>of modern astronomy. Our instruments<lb/>interested him deeply, and one day our<lb/>house was filled with all the monks of<lb/>St. Francis, begging to see a dipping-<lb/>needle. The curiosity that dwells on<lb/>physical phenomena is augmented in<lb/>countries undermined by volcanic fires,<lb/>and in a climate where nature is at<lb/>once so overwhelming, and so myste-<lb/>riously agitated.</p>   
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI> 