<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.1" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.1" when="2018-10-10" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung für Verlag.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-30" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>[<hi rendition="#i">From De Humboldt’s Travels, part</hi> 2.]</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Mission of San Fernando, by the regularity<lb break="yes"/>of the town, the uniformity of the buildings, the so-<lb break="no"/>ber and silent air of the inhabitants, and the extreme<lb break="yes"/>neatness of the houses, recalled to the recollection<lb break="yes"/>of our travellers the establishments of the Moravian<lb break="yes"/>brethren; and this is saying not a little in their favour.<lb break="yes"/>Every Indian family, besides its proper garden, as-<lb break="no"/>sists in the cultivation of the common garden; <hi rendition="#i">Co-<lb break="no"/>nuco de la communidad</hi>; every adult working <choice>
                        <sic>there-</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">there</corr>
                    </choice>
                    <lb break="yes"/>one hour in the morning and one in the evening.<lb break="yes" />The great square in the centre of the village con-<lb break="no"/>tains the church, the dwelling of the missionary,<lb break="yes"/>and the humble edifice on which is bestowed the<lb break="yes"/>pompous apellation of <hi rendition="#i">Casa del Rey</hi>, the house of<lb break="yes"/>the king: a sort of caravansera, intended to give<lb break="yes"/>shelter to travellers, and of infinite service in a<lb break="yes"/>country where the hotel or inn is utterly unknown.<lb break="yes"/>The following is the portrait of the good father of<lb break="yes"/>San Fernando:</p>
                <p>“The missionary of San Fernando was a Capuchin, a native<lb break="yes"/>of Aragon, very far advanced in years, but still vigorous and<lb break="yes" />cheerful. His great corpulency, his sprightly disposition, and<lb break="yes" />the interest which he took in battles and sieges, but ill accorded<lb break="yes"/>with the notion formed, in the northern countries, of the<lb break="yes"/>melancholic abstraction and contemplative life of a missionary.<lb break="yes"/>Though closely busied with a cow which was to be slaughtered<lb break="yes"/>the next morning, the old monk yet received us with good<lb break="yes"/>humour, and gave us leave to sling our hammocks in a gallery<lb break="yes"/>of his house. Seated, without employment, during the chief<lb break="yes"/>part of the day, in a great arm chair of reed wood, he complained<lb break="yes"/>bitterly of what he termed the idleness and ignorance of his<lb break="yes"/>countrymen. He asked us a thousand questions concerning<lb break="yes"/>the real motive of our travels which to him seemed hazardous<lb break="yes"/>and, at best, useless. Here, as on the Orinoco, we were<lb break="yes"/>harassed by that eager curiosity which, in the midst of the<lb break="yes"/>forests of America, Europeans retain respecting the wars and<lb break="yes"/>political storms of the Old World.</p>
                <p>“In other respects, our missionary appeared to be satisfied<lb break="yes"/>with his situation. He treated the Indians mildly; he saw his<lb break="yes"/>mission proper; and he extolled with enthusiasm the water,<lb break="yes"/>the bananas, and the milk diet of the district. He smiled con-<lb break="no"/>temptuously at the sight of our instruments, books, and dried<lb break="yes"/>plants; and acknowledged, with a frankness peculiar to these<lb break="yes"/>climates, that, of all the enjoyments of life, not excepting sleep,<lb break="yes"/>none was to be compared with the pleasure of eating good beef,<lb break="yes"/>so true is it, that sensuality springs from the absence of mental<lb break="yes" />occupation. Our host persuaded us repeatedly to visit a cow<lb break="yes"/>he had just purchased; and the next day, at sunrise, he insisted<lb break="yes"/>on our going to see the animal killed according to the custom<lb break="yes"/>of the country, namely, by cutting the ham-string, and plunging<lb break="yes"/>a large knife between the vertebrae of the neck. Disgusting<lb break="yes"/>as the operation was, we learnt from it the expertness of the<lb break="yes"/>Chaymas Indians, who, eight in number, cut the beast into<lb break="yes"/>small joints in less than twenty minutes. The cow had cost but<lb break="yes"/>seven piastres, yet this seemed to be considered a very high<lb break="yes"/>price. The same day the missionary paid eighteen piastres to a<lb break="yes"/>soldier of Cumana, for bleeding him in the foot. The fact, of<lb break="yes"/>little apparent importance, strikingly proves how much, in<lb break="yes"/>wild, uncultivated countries, the value of commodities differs<lb break="yes"/>from that of the labour.”</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 