<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="424" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Milk extracted from the Cow Tree (l’ Arbre de la<lb break="yes"/>Vache), and on Vegetable Milk in general.</hi>— By <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Annales de Chimie.</hi>—“</head>
                <p>We have given (say the editors of the<lb break="yes"/>Annales) the extract of a memoir read by M. Humboldt in one<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="425" facs="#f0002"/>of the last sittings of the Academy of Sciences. The readers<lb break="yes"/>who may desire a more extended detail on a subject so inte-<lb break="no"/>resting in vegetable chemistry, will find it in the sixth volume<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i">Relation Historique,</hi> by the author, which will be very<lb break="yes"/>shortly published.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>“We had for several weeks past heard mention made of a<lb break="yes"/>certain tree in the valleys of Aragua, the juice of which was<lb break="yes"/>said to be a nourishing milk; the tree, indeed, was called the<lb break="yes"/>cow tree, and we learnt that the negroes of the place, who<lb break="yes"/>drank it abundantly, looked upon it as a very wholesome spe-<lb break="no"/>cies of aliment. This account excited surprise in our minds,<lb break="yes"/>since the general characters attached to the milky juices of<lb break="yes"/>plants, are those of being acrid, bitter, and more or less poison-<lb break="no"/>ous. But since our residence in Barbula (province of the<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas), we have found that in this account of the <hi rendition="#i">Palo de<lb break="yes"/>vaca</hi> there was no exaggeration. The tree thus named, is one<lb break="yes"/>of a very beautiful appearance. Its flowers we had not an<lb break="yes"/>opportunity of seeing; the fruit of it is rather pulpy, and en-<lb break="no"/>closes sometimes one and sometimes two kernels. When in-<lb break="no"/>cisions are made into the trunk of this tree, which appears to<lb break="yes"/>belong to the sapota tribe of plants, it gives out an abundance<lb break="yes"/>of a glutinous thick kind of milk, void of all acrimony, and<lb break="yes"/>exhaling an odour by no means unpleasant. We drank consi-<lb break="no"/>derable quantities of it, both in the evening before we retired<lb break="yes"/>to rest and early in the morning, without experiencing the<lb break="yes"/>slightest inconvenience: it is only the glutinous nature of<lb break="yes"/>the fluid in question that occasions its taste to be at all un-<lb break="no"/>pleasant. Both the slaves and others employed upon the<lb break="yes"/>plantations drink it freely, and mix it with the maize and ca-<lb break="no"/>pada plant. The master of the plantation assured us that the<lb break="yes"/>slaves always thrived and gained flesh during the season in<lb break="yes"/>which the <hi rendition="#i">Palo de vaca</hi> furnished them with milk. When this<lb break="yes"/>milk is exposed to the air, its surface becomes covered with a<lb break="yes"/>strongly animalized substance of a yellowish hue, and fibrous<lb break="yes"/>stringy appearance, resembling a cheesy matter. This change<lb break="yes"/>in the juice is probably produced by an absorption of oxygen<lb break="yes"/>from the air. When the membranous substance of which we<lb break="yes"/>speak is separated from the more fluid part of the milk, it<lb break="yes"/>proves to be nearly as elastic as caoutchouc; but it undergoes<lb break="yes"/>in the course of time a like putrefaction with gelatine. The<lb break="yes"/>people of the place call this matter cheese. It becomes sour<lb break="yes"/>in about five or six days, according to the observation which I<lb break="yes"/>made on some portions of it which I took with me to Orenoque.<lb break="yes"/>The milk, enclosed in a well stopped vial, had thrown down a<lb break="yes"/>small quantity of <hi rendition="#i">coagulum,</hi> which, far from being fetid, con-<lb break="no"/>stantly exhaled a sort of balsamic odour. The fresh milk<lb break="yes"/>scarcely coagulated at all upon being mixed with cold water;<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="426" facs="#f0003"/>but a separation of this viscous matter took place when I<lb break="yes"/>heated it with nitric acid. We sent two bottles of this milk<lb break="yes"/>to M. Fourcroy, at Paris. The one bottle contained the juice<lb break="yes"/>pure, in the other it was mixed with a quantity of carbonate<lb break="yes"/>of soda.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This remarkable production, the Palo de vaca, appears to be<lb break="yes"/>confined to the Cordilleras (la Cordillière du Littoral), espe-<lb break="no"/>cially near the lake of Marakabo. It is found also near the<lb break="yes"/>town of San Mateo; and, according to M. Bredmeyer (whose<lb break="yes"/>voyages have so much contributed to enrich the beautiful green-<lb break="no"/>houses of Schônbrun and Vienna), it is to be seen in the vale<lb break="yes"/>of Caucagua, three days’ journey east of the Caraccas. This<lb break="yes"/>naturalist, like ourselves, found the vegetable juice in question<lb break="yes"/>of an agreeable taste and aromatic odour. The natives of Cau-<lb break="no"/>cagua call the tree which furnishes it, the milk tree <hi rendition="#i">arbol de<lb break="yes"/>loche.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The inhabitants of the Andes had been in the practice of<lb break="yes"/>fabricating wax lights from the wax which is found on the<lb break="yes"/>trunk of the palm tree long before the chemists of Europe had<lb break="yes"/>discovered quantities of wax in the pollen of flowers, varnish<lb break="yes"/>in leaves, and farina in fruits; in like manner the <hi rendition="#i">caseum,</hi> the<lb break="yes"/>basis of cheese, has but recently been detected in the emulsions<lb break="yes"/>of almonds; whereas we find that ages ago, in the mountains<lb break="yes"/>of Venezuela, the milk of a tree, and the cheese which sepa-<lb break="no"/>rates itself from such milk, were used as aliment. How are we<lb break="yes"/>to account for these singularities in regard to the developement<lb break="yes"/>of our knowledge of nature’s productions? How can we ex-<lb break="no"/>plain the fact, that the people of another hemisphere have dis-<lb break="no"/>covered and applied properties which had for so long a time<lb break="yes"/>escaped the penetration of men whose very occupation it is to<lb break="yes"/>search Nature’s laws, and penetrate her mysterious operations?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It would appear that the fact is to be explained partly from<lb break="yes"/>the circumstance of the elements and principles of plants<lb break="yes"/>being distributed among so many orders and families of the<lb break="yes"/>vegetable creation, partly from that difference of quantity, with<lb break="yes"/>respect to their essential principles, which is observed in the<lb break="yes"/>vegetable world, according as the particular plant is a native of<lb break="yes"/>equatorial, or of cold and temperate latitudes, and partly by an<lb break="yes"/>ingenuity derived from necessity, which impels uncultivated<lb break="yes"/>man to seek for his sustenance in the natural productions by<lb break="yes"/>which he is surrounded. Thus the juices, the bark, the roots,<lb break="yes"/>and the fruits of trees, become the subjects naturally of in-<lb break="no"/>stinctive investigation; and when poisonous productions are<lb break="yes"/>combined with those that are wholesome and nutritive, man is<lb break="yes"/>taught by the same necessity to separate the one principle from<lb break="yes"/>the other, as in the arum, tacca, &amp;c. The American savage,<lb break="yes"/>as well as the inhabitants of the South Sea islands, have thus<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="427" facs="#f0004"/>learnt the art to prepare the fecula of plants, by compressing<lb break="yes"/>it and separating its juice. In the milk of plants, as also in the<lb break="yes"/>milky emulsions, materials considerably nutrient, such as albu-<lb break="no"/>men, the caseous and the saccharine principles are intermixed<lb break="yes"/>with caoutchouc, and deleterious ingredients, such as morphine<lb break="yes"/>and hydrocyanic acid. These combinations vary not only in<lb break="yes"/>the different tribes of plants, but also in the respective species<lb break="yes"/>of the same genera. Sometimes it is the morphine or narcotic<lb break="yes"/>principle, which predominates in vegetable milk; in other in-<lb break="no"/>stances the caoutchouc is the characterizing ingredient; and<lb break="yes"/>lastly, as we have seen in the juice of the papaya, and cow<lb break="yes"/>tree, the caseous is the main principle.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The lactiferous plants belong principally to the three families<lb break="yes"/>of the Euphorbia, the Urticaria, and the Apocyna; and as upon<lb break="yes"/>investigating the different distribution of vegetable growth in<lb break="yes"/>the several parts of the world, we find that the species of these<lb break="yes"/>orders of plants are most numerous in the tropical regions, we<lb break="yes"/>infer that a very high temperature is necessary for the proper<lb break="yes"/>elaboration of the milky juices, as well at to the complete<lb break="yes"/>formation of the caoutchouc of albumen, and of the caseous<lb break="yes"/>principle. The juice of the <hi rendition="#i">Palo de vaca</hi> certainly presents<lb break="yes"/>one of the most striking examples of a vegetable milk in which<lb break="yes"/>the acrid and deleterious principles are not united to albumen,<lb break="yes"/>caseum, or caoutchouc; but the euphorbium and asclepias<lb break="yes"/>genera, so generally known by their caustic properties, had<lb break="yes"/>before furnished us with some species of which the juice is<lb break="yes"/>bland and innocent, as in the instance of the tabayba dulce,<lb break="yes"/>(euphorbia balsamifera) of the Canary Isles, and the asclepias<lb break="yes"/>lactifera of Ceylon. Bruman has told us, that the inhabitants<lb break="yes"/>of Ceylon make use of this last in lieu of milk, and that they<lb break="yes"/>mix its leaves in cookery with those articles of food that are<lb break="yes"/>generally prepared with milk. It is to be wished that Mr. John<lb break="yes"/>Davy may pay attention to this particular during his stay at<lb break="yes"/>Ceylon; for it appears probable, as has been suggested by M.<lb break="yes"/>Decandolle, that it is only the juice which exudes from the<lb break="yes"/>young plant, which is used for the purposes in question, viz.<lb break="yes"/>that which flows from the vegetable before the development of<lb break="yes"/>the acrid principle. Indeed, in some countries, the first shoots<lb break="yes"/>of even the apocyna are eaten.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have thus endeavoured to institute a general resemblance<lb break="yes"/>between the juices which circulate in plants, and the lactiferous<lb break="yes"/>emulsions which are yielded by the almond and palm tribe;<lb break="yes"/>and I may here add a few remarks respecting some experiments<lb break="yes"/>upon the carica papaya, which I made during my stay in the<lb break="yes"/>valleys of Aragua; not, of course, of so satisfactory a nature as they<lb break="yes"/>might have been, had I been furnished with the several reactîves<lb break="yes"/>necessary to conduct investigations of this kind. I ascertained<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="428" facs="#f0005"/>that the younger the fruit of the plant, the greater was the<lb break="yes"/>quantity of milk which it furnished: this juice, indeed, was<lb break="yes"/>found even in the germ of the fruit; and as it proceeded to<lb break="yes"/>maturity, its milk became not merely less abundant, but also<lb break="yes"/>more aqueous. In it was found less of the animal coagulable<lb break="yes"/>matter (matière animale coagulable), and it is conceivable that<lb break="yes"/>as the plant advances in growth, this matter, abstracted from<lb break="yes"/>the fruit, comes to constitute its pulpy or fleshy parts. The<lb break="yes"/>coagulum from the very young fruit, heated with nitric acid,<lb break="yes"/>becomes viscous, and exhales a waxy odour, similar to that<lb break="yes"/>which I have observed in muscular flesh and in small mush-<lb break="no"/>rooms (morilles), when the acid is added to them in the same<lb break="yes"/>manner. Following the hints of Fourcroy and Vauquelin, I<lb break="yes"/>mixed the milk of the papaya with a solution of carbonate of<lb break="yes"/>soda. The mixture did not run into coagulated lumps, even<lb break="yes"/>when water was added to it. The membranous substance did<lb break="yes"/>not show itself, until, by the addition of an acid to the solution,<lb break="yes"/>the soda became neutralized. The coagulum formed by the<lb break="yes"/>nitric acid, lemon juice, and hot water, I caused to disappear,<lb break="yes"/>by adding to the mixture the carbonate of soda. By this ad-<lb break="no"/>dition the juice resumed its milky and liquid appearance; but<lb break="yes"/>the experiments only answered when the addition was made to<lb break="yes"/>recently formed coagula.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In conclusion, it may be remarked, that a comparison of the<lb break="yes"/>milky juices of the papaya with those of the cow-tree and the<lb break="yes"/>hevea, offers a striking analogy between the juices which abound<lb break="yes"/>in the caseous, and those that contain the caoutchouc principle.<lb break="yes"/>All the productions in which the latter is predominant, as like-<lb break="no"/>wise the impenetrable garments (manteaux imperméables) that<lb break="yes"/>are fabricated in Spanish America, are made to exhale a like<lb break="yes"/>animal and disagreeable odour, by placing the milk of the<lb break="yes"/>hevea between two layers of them; a circumstance which would<lb break="yes"/>seem to argue that the caoutchouc in coagulating, attracts to<lb break="yes"/>itself the caseum, which is no other, perhaps, than albumen in<lb break="yes"/>a different form. The fruit of the bread-tree is not any more<lb break="yes"/>bread than are the bananas before their maturity, or the tube-<lb break="no"/>rous and amilaceous roots of the cassada, the convolvulus bat-<lb break="no"/>tatas, or the potatoe. On the contrary, the milk of the <hi rendition="#i">Palo<lb break="yes"/>de vaca</hi> contains the caseous principle in the same manner as<lb break="yes"/>does the milk from the mammalia. In pursuing these analogies<lb break="yes"/>between the animal and vegetable world, we may, with M.<lb break="yes"/>Gay-Lussac, consider the caoutchouc as the oily part, the butter<lb break="yes"/>as it were of the vegetable milk. In a word, we may find in<lb break="yes"/>vegetable milk, caseum and caoutchouc; in animal milk, caseum<lb break="yes"/>and butter. The two principles vary in their proportions in<lb break="yes"/>different animals, as they do in the various species of lactiferous<lb break="yes"/>plants. In these last, they are more generally mingled with<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="429" facs="#f0006"/>other materials which are not alimentary; but from such mate-<lb break="no"/>rials they may, perhaps, be always separated by chemical<lb break="yes"/>processes. Vegetable milk becomes wholesome and nourish-<lb break="no"/>ing when it is deprived of its acrid and narcotic principle, and<lb break="yes"/>when it abounds more in caseous matter than in caoutchouc.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>