<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">A man giving suck</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:52</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.47</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1818-Curious_Circumstance-09-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-09-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-xx1-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>&lt;i&gt;Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent, during the Years 1799–1804&lt;/i&gt;, übersetzt von Helen Maria Williams, Bd. 3, London 1818, ab S. 46.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 1, S. 376–378.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">A man giving suck</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1826</date>
          <pubPlace>Albany, New York</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in:&lt;i&gt; The Escritoir; Or, Masonic and Miscellaneous Album&lt;/i&gt; 1:21 (17. Juni 1826), S. 165.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="165" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>A MAN GIVING SUCK.<lb break="yes"/>[From Humboldt&#x2019;s Personal Travels.]</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the village of Arenas, on the road from San<lb break="yes"/>Fernando to Cumana, lives a labourer, Francisco<lb break="yes"/>Lozano, who presented a physiological phenomenon,<lb break="yes"/>highly calculated to strike the imagination, though<lb break="yes"/>it is very conformable to the known laws of organ-<lb break="no"/>ized nature. This man has suckled a child with his<lb break="yes"/>own milk. The mother having fallen sick, the fa-<lb break="no" />ther, to quiet the infant, took it into his bed, and<lb break="yes"/>pressed it to his bosom. Lozano, then thirty two<lb break="yes"/>years of age, had never remarked till that day that<lb break="yes"/>he had milk: but the irritation of the nipple, sucked<lb break="yes"/>by the child, caused the accumulation of that liquid.<lb break="yes"/>The milk was thick and very sweet. The father,<lb break="yes"/>astonished at the increased size of his breast, suck-<lb break="no"/>led his child two or three times a day during five<lb break="yes"/>months. He drew on himself the attention of his<lb break="yes" />neighbours, but he never thought, as he probably<lb break="yes"/>would in Europe, of deriving any advantage, from<lb break="yes"/>the curiosity he excited. We saw the certificate<lb break="yes"/>which had been drawn up on the spot, to attest this<lb break="yes"/>remarkable fact, eye-witnesses of which are still liv-<lb break="no"/>ing. They assured us, that, during this suckling,<lb break="yes"/>the child had no other nourishment than the milk of<lb break="yes"/>his father. Lozano, who was not at Arenas during<lb break="yes" />our journey in the Missions, came to us at Cumana.<lb break="yes"/>He was accompained by his son, who was then thir-<lb break="no"/>teen or fourteen years of age. <choice>
                        <sic>Mr. Benpland</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Mr. Bonpland</corr>
                    </choice> ex-<lb break="no"/>amined with attention the father&#x2019;s breast, and found<lb break="yes"/>it wrinkled like those of a woman who have given<lb break="yes"/>suck. He observed, that the left breast in particu-<lb break="no"/>lar was much enlarged; which Lozano explained to<lb break="yes" />us from the circumstance, that the two breasts did<lb break="yes"/>not furnish milk in the same abundance. Don<lb break="yes"/>Vicente Emparan, governor of the province, sent<lb break="yes"/>a circumstantial account of this phenomenon to<lb break="yes"/>Cadiz.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is not a very uncommon circumstance, to find,<lb break="yes"/>both among human kind and animals, males whose<lb break="yes"/>breasts contain milk; and the climate does not ap-<lb break="no"/>pear to exort any marked influence on the more or<lb break="yes"/>less abundance of this secretion. The ancients cite<lb break="yes"/>the milk of the he goats of Lemnos and Corsica.<lb break="yes" />In our own time, we have seen in the country of Ha-<lb break="no"/>nover, a he goat, which for a great number of years<lb break="yes"/>was milked every other day, and yielded more milk<lb break="yes"/>than a female goat. Among the signs of the pre-<lb break="no"/>tended weakness of the Americans, travellers have<lb break="yes"/>mentioned the milk contained in the breasts of <choice>
                        <sic>men</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">men.</corr>
                    </choice>
                    <lb break="yes"/>It is however improbable, that it has ever been ob-<lb break="no"/>served in a whole tribe, in some part of America<lb break="yes" />unknown to modern travellers; and I can affirm,<lb break="yes"/>that at present it is not more common in the new<lb break="yes"/>continent, <choice><sic>that</sic><corr type="editorial">than</corr></choice> in the old. The labourer of Arenas<lb break="yes"/>whose history we have just related, is not of the cop-<lb break="no"/>per coloured race of Chayma Indians: he is a white<lb break="yes"/>man, descended from Europeans. Moreover, the ana-<lb break="no"/>tomists of Petersburg have observed, that among the<lb break="yes"/>lower orders of the people in Russia, milk in the<lb break="yes"/>breasts of men is much more frequent than among<lb break="yes" />the more southern nations; and the Russians have<lb break="yes"/>never been deemed weak and effeminate.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There exists among the varieties of our kind a race<lb break="yes"/>of men, whose breasts at the age of puberty acquire<lb break="yes"/>a considerable bulk. Lozano did not belong to this<lb break="yes"/>class; and he often repeated to us, that it was only<lb break="yes"/>the irritation of the nipple, in consequence of the<lb break="yes"/>suction, which caused the flow of milk. This con-<lb break="no"/><cb/>firms the observation of the antients, &#x201C;that men,<lb break="yes"/>who have a small quantity of milk, yield it in abun-<lb break="no"/>dance, when their breasts are sucked.&#x201D; These sin-<lb break="no"/>gular effects of a nervous stimulant were known to<lb break="yes"/>the shepherds of Greece; those of Mount Octa rub-<lb break="no" />bed the dugs of the young goats, that had not yet<lb break="yes"/>conceived, with nettles, to make them produce milk.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When we reflect on the whole of the vital phe-<lb break="no"/>nomena, we find, that one of them is entirely iso-<lb break="no"/>lated. In every age examples are cited of young<lb break="yes"/>girls not marriageable, or women withered by age,<lb break="yes"/>who have suckled children: Among men these ex-<lb break="no"/>amples are infinitely more rare: after numerous<lb break="yes" />researches, I have not found above two or three.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>One is cited by the anatomist of Verona, Alex-<lb break="no"/>ander Benedictus, who lived toward the end<lb break="yes"/>of the fifteenth century. He relates the history<lb break="yes"/>of an inhabitant of Syria, who, to calm the<lb break="yes"/>uneasiness of his child, after the death of the<lb break="yes" />mother, pressed it to his bosom. The milk immedi-<lb break="no"/>ately came with such abundance, that the father<lb break="yes"/>could take on himself the nourishment of his child,<lb break="yes"/>without assistance. Other examples are related by<lb break="yes"/>Santorellus, Paria, and Robert, bishop of Cork.<lb break="yes"/>The greater part of the phenomena having been<lb break="yes" />noticed in times very remote, it is not uninter-<lb break="no"/>esting to phisiology that we can confirm them in our<lb break="yes"/>own days. Besides, they bear very strongly on the<lb break="yes"/>long disputed question respecting final causes. The<lb break="yes"/>existence of the nipple in men has long puzzled<lb break="yes"/>philosophers; and it has even been recently affirm-<lb break="no"/>ed, that nature has refused to one of the sexes the<lb break="yes"/>faculty of suckling because this faculty would not<lb break="yes"/>accord with the dignity of man.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 