<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="219" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>HUMBOLDT&#x2019;S AMERICAN TRAVELS.<note place="foot" n="*">Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial<lb break="yes"/>Regions of America, during the years 1799&#x2014;1804. By<lb break="yes"/>Alexander von Humboldt and Aimé Bonpland. Written<lb break="yes"/>in French by Alexander von Humboldt: translated and<lb break="yes"/>edited by Thomasina Ross. Vol. I. Bohn&#x2019;s Scientific<lb break="yes"/>Library. New York: Hangs, Brother &amp; Co.</note>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">There</hi> are two motives for this publication,<lb break="yes"/>either of which is sufficient to secure a<lb break="yes" />prompt support for the undertaking, apart<lb break="yes"/>from the intrinsic merits of the work itself,<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;the interest which is thrown back upon<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt&#x2019;s Central American researches by<lb break="yes"/>the present commercial development of those<lb break="yes" />regions; and the interest which is reflected<lb break="yes"/>across half a century from the brilliant gene-<lb break="no"/>ralization of the Cosmos upon the growing<lb break="yes"/>mind and materials of its author.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>How vividly this torch of present self-<lb break="no"/>interest lights up the dark regions of the<lb break="yes"/>past! A few years since, the researches of<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt were matters of scientific specula-<lb break="no"/>tion and of learned curiosity. To the people<lb break="yes"/>he was a great name and little more. Now,<lb break="yes"/>when the line of the surveyor is traversing<lb break="yes"/>the scene of his Mexican and other explora-<lb break="no"/>tions; when we are practically digging for<lb break="yes"/>gold in his mountains, and our perceptions of<lb break="yes" />the manners of the natives whom he de-<lb break="no"/>scribed is sharpened by the point of their<lb break="yes"/>weapons; when his meteorological tables<lb break="yes"/>are proving themselves upon the constitu-<lb break="no"/>tions of ourselves and our relations; when<lb break="yes"/>we are in danger of being poisoned by his<lb break="yes"/>plants or stung by his serpents;&#x2014;in fine,<lb break="yes"/>when the whole vast area of his science is<lb break="yes"/>brought home to us by the stock certificates<lb break="yes"/>in our pockets, we are prepared to drop our<lb break="yes"/>old listlessness, and turn over his pages with<lb break="yes"/>animation and enthusiasm.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is thus that the scholar, indefatigably<lb break="yes"/>working in advance of his times, prepares for<lb break="yes"/>the world, through difficulty and weariness,<lb break="yes"/>the charm and beneficence of knowledge.<lb break="yes"/>Happy if, like Humboldt, he survive to wit-<lb break="no"/>ness the fruitage of his fame with the great<lb break="yes"/>mutations of society and the practical realiza-<lb break="no"/>tion of his studies.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There is something heroic about Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt&#x2019;s Travels. He will be regarded by<lb break="yes"/>the coming generations as a modern Hero-<lb break="no"/>dotus.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This feeling is no doubt owing to the<lb break="yes"/>extent of his studies, and the rapid intellec-<lb break="no"/>tual perceptions of his mind, by which he<lb break="yes"/>enlivens a mass of facts by considerations<lb break="yes" />drawn from the distant relations of his sub-<lb break="no"/>ject. In reading his books, we have no such<lb break="yes"/>sensation as that which oppresses us with<lb break="yes"/>some scientific writers, of crawling slowly<lb break="yes"/>over a great heap of observations; but while<lb break="yes"/>we have the most accurate and even techni-<lb break="no"/>cal descriptions of science, we are treated to<lb break="yes"/>a candor and openness of suggestion which<lb break="yes"/>are as far removed as possible from the de-<lb break="no"/>scriptions of a pedant, and are like nothing<lb break="yes" />more than the bright intelligent conversation<lb break="yes"/>of a perfect gentleman, whom you always<lb break="yes"/>respect, by whom you are constantly taught,<lb break="yes"/>and by whom you are never bored!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>For an example of the best methods of<lb break="yes"/>ethnological study, where can we find nicer,<lb break="yes"/>more patient attention, interesting detail, or<lb break="yes"/>valuable results, than in the chapters on the<lb break="yes"/>Chaymas Indians about the missions in the<lb break="yes" />neighborhood of Cumana in Venezuela, in<lb break="yes"/>the then province of New Andalusia? What<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>a variety of information and perception opens<lb break="yes"/>upon us in these brief two pages of a visit to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#k">the monks of caripe.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;We were received with great hospitality<lb break="yes"/>by the monks of Caripe. The building has an<lb break="yes"/>inner court, surrounded by an arcade, like the<lb break="yes"/>convents in Spain. This inclosed place was<lb break="yes"/>highly convenient for setting up our instru-<lb break="no" />ments and making observations. We found a<lb break="yes"/>numerous society in the convent. Young<lb break="yes"/>monks, recently arrived from Spain, were just<lb break="yes"/>about to settle in the Missions, while old<lb break="yes"/>infirm missionaries sought for health in the<lb break="yes" />fresh and salubrious air of the mountains of<lb break="yes"/>Caripe. I was lodged in the cell of the supe-<lb break="no"/>rior, which contained a pretty good collection<lb break="yes"/>of books, I found there, to my surprise, the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Teatro Critico</hi> of Feijoo, the <hi rendition="#i">Lettres Edifiantes</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and the <hi rendition="#i">Traité d&#x2019;Electricité</hi> by Abbé Nollet.<lb break="yes"/>It seemed as if the progress of knowledge<lb break="yes"/>advanced even in the forests of America.<lb break="yes"/>The youngest of the Capuchin monks of the<lb break="yes"/>last Mission had brought with him a Spanish<lb break="yes"/>translation of Chaptal&#x2019;s Treatise on Chemistry,<lb break="yes"/>and he intended to study this work in the<lb break="yes"/>solitude where he was destined to pass the<lb break="yes" />remainder of his days. During our long abode<lb break="yes"/>in the Missions of South America we never<lb break="yes"/>perceived any sign of intolerance. The monks<lb break="yes"/>of Caripe were not ignorant that I was born<lb break="yes"/>in the Protestant part of Germany. Fur-<lb break="no"/>nished as I was with orders from the court of<lb break="yes"/>Spain, I had no motives to conceal from them<lb break="yes"/>this fact; nevertheless, no mark of distrust, no<lb break="yes"/>indiscreet question, no attempt at controversy,<lb break="yes"/>ever diminished the value of the hospitality<lb break="yes" />they exercised with so much liberality and<lb break="yes"/>frankness.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The convent is founded on a spot which<lb break="yes"/>was anciently called Arcocuar. Its height<lb break="yes"/>above the level of the sea is nearly the same<lb break="yes"/>as that of the town of Caracas, or of the<lb break="yes"/>inhabited part of the Blue Mountains of Ja-<lb break="no" />maica. Thus the mean temperatures of these<lb break="yes"/>three points, all situated within the tropics,<lb break="yes"/>are nearly the same. The necessity of being<lb break="yes"/>well clothed at night, and especially at sun-<lb break="no"/>rise, is felt at Caripe. We saw the centigrade<lb break="yes" />thermometer at midnight, between 16&#x00B0; and<lb break="yes"/>17&#x00B7;5&#x00B0;; in the morning, between 19&#x00B0; and 20&#x00B0;.<lb break="yes"/>About one o&#x2019;clock it had risen only to 21&#x00B0;, or<lb break="yes"/>22&#x00B7;5&#x00B0;. This temperature is sufficient for the<lb break="yes"/>development of the productions of the torrid<lb break="yes" />zone; though, compared with the excessive<lb break="yes"/>heat of the plains of Cumana, we might call it<lb break="yes"/>the temperature of spring. Water exposed to<lb break="yes"/>currents of air in vessels of porous clay, cools<lb break="yes"/>at Caripe, during the night, as low as 13&#x00B0;.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Experience has proved that the temperate<lb break="yes"/>climate and rarefied air of this spot are singu-<lb break="no"/>larly favorable to the cultivation of the coffee-<lb break="no"/>tree, which is well known to flourish on<lb break="yes"/>heights. The prefect of the capuchins, an<lb break="yes" />active and enlightened man, has introduced<lb break="yes"/>into the province this new branch of agricul-<lb break="no"/>tural industry. Indigo was formerly planted<lb break="yes"/>at Caripe, but the small quantity of fecula<lb break="yes"/>yielded by this plant, which requires great<lb break="yes" />heat, caused the culture to be abandoned.<lb break="yes"/>We found in the <hi rendition="#i">conuco</hi> of the community<lb break="yes"/>many culinary plants, maize, sugar cane, and<lb break="yes"/>five thousand coffee-trees, which promised a<lb break="yes"/>fine harvest. The friars were in hopes of<lb break="yes"/>tripling the number in a few years. We can-<lb break="no"/>not help remarking the uniform efforts for the<lb break="yes"/>cultivation of the soil which are manifested<lb break="yes"/>in the policy of the monastic hierarchy.<lb break="yes"/>Wherever convents have not yet acquired<lb break="yes"/>wealth in the New Continent, as formerly in<lb break="yes" />Gaul, in Syria, and in the north of Europe,<lb break="yes"/>they exercise a happy influence on the clearing<lb break="yes"/>of the ground and the introduction of exotic<lb break="yes"/>vegetation. At Caripe, the <hi rendition="#i">conuco</hi> of the com-<lb break="no"/>munity presents the appearance of an exten-<lb break="no"/>sive and beautiful garden. The natives are<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>obliged to work in it every morning from six<lb break="yes"/>to ten, and the alcaldes and alguazils of Indian<lb break="yes"/>race overlook their labors. These men are<lb break="yes"/>looked upon as great state functionaries, and<lb break="yes"/>they alone have the right of carrying a cane.<lb break="yes" />The selection of them depends on the superior<lb break="yes"/>of the convent. The pedantic and silent gra-<lb break="no"/>vity of the Indian alcaldes, their cold and<lb break="yes"/>mysterious air, their love of appearing in form<lb break="yes"/>at church and in the assemblies of the people,<lb break="yes" />force a smile from Europeans. We were not<lb break="yes"/>yet accustomed to these shades of the Indian<lb break="yes"/>character, which we found the same at the<lb break="yes"/>Orinoco, in Mexico, and in Peru, among people<lb break="yes"/>totally different in their manners and their<lb break="yes"/>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>lauguage.</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">language.</corr>
                    </choice> The alcaldes came daily to the<lb break="yes"/>convent, less to treat with the monks on the<lb break="yes"/>affairs of the Mission, than under the pretence<lb break="yes"/>of inquiring after the health of the newly-<lb break="no"/>arrived travellers. As we gave them brandy,<lb break="yes" />their visits became more frequent than the<lb break="yes"/>monks desired.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The personal account of the Indians is<lb break="yes"/>throughout in a fresh and living spirit of<lb break="yes"/>investigation. A man milliner who happens<lb break="yes"/>to be a poet will make a great deal out of<lb break="yes"/>the dress of fashionable life, but here is a<lb break="yes"/>philosopher who will tell you quite as inte-<lb break="no"/>resting a story of no dress at all.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#k">no clothing of the chaymas.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The Chaymas, like all savage people who<lb break="yes"/>dwell in excessively hot regions, have an<lb break="yes"/>insuperable aversion to clothing. The writers<lb break="yes"/>of the middle ages inform us, that in the north<lb break="yes"/>of Europe, articles of clothing distributed by<lb break="yes" />missionaries, greatly contributed to the con-<lb break="no"/>version of the pagan. In the torrid zone, on<lb break="yes"/>the contrary, the natives are ashamed (as they<lb break="yes"/>say) to be clothed; and flee to the woods<lb break="yes"/>when they are compelled to cover themselves.<lb break="yes" />Among the Chaymas, in spite of the remon-<lb break="no"/>strances of the monks, men and women<lb break="yes"/>remain unclothed within their houses. When<lb break="yes"/>they go into the villages they put on a kind<lb break="yes"/>of tunic of cotton, which scarcely reaches to<lb break="yes" />the knees. The men&#x2019;s tunics have sleeves;<lb break="yes"/>but women, and young boys to the age of ten<lb break="yes"/>or twelve, have the arms, shoulders, and<lb break="yes"/>upper part of the breast uncovered. The<lb break="yes" />tunic is so shaped, that the fore-part is joined<lb break="yes"/>to the back by two narrow bands, which<lb break="yes"/>cross the shoulders. When we met the natives<lb break="yes"/>out of the boundaries of the Mission, we saw<lb break="yes"/>them, especially in rainy weather, stripped of<lb break="yes" />their clothes, and holding their skirts rolled<lb break="yes"/>up under their arms. They preferred letting<lb break="yes"/>the rain fall on their bodies to wetting<lb break="yes"/>their clothes. The elder women hid them-<lb break="no"/>selves behind trees, and burst into loud fits of<lb break="yes" />laughter when they saw us pass. The mis-<lb break="no"/>sionaries complain that in general the young<lb break="yes"/>girls are not more alive to feelings of decency<lb break="yes"/>than the men. Ferdinand Columbus relates<lb break="yes"/>that, in 1498, his father found the women in<lb break="yes" />the island of Trinidad without any clothing;<lb break="yes"/>while the men wore the <hi rendition="#i">guayuco,</hi> which is<lb break="yes"/>rather a narrow bandage than an apron. At<lb break="yes"/>the same period, on the coast of Paria, young<lb break="yes"/>girls were distinguished from married women,<lb break="yes"/>either, as Cardinal Bembo states, by being<lb break="yes" />quite unclothed, or, according to Gomara, by<lb break="yes"/>the color of the <hi rendition="#i">guayuco.</hi> This bandage, which<lb break="yes"/>is still in use among the Chaymas, and all the<lb break="yes"/>naked nations of the Orinoco, is only two or<lb break="yes"/>three inches broad, and is tied on both sides<lb break="yes"/>to a string which encircles the waist. Girls<lb break="yes"/>are often married at the age of twelve; and<lb break="yes" />until they are nine years old, the missionaries<lb break="yes"/>allow them to go to church unclothed, that is<lb break="yes"/>to say, without a tunic. Among the Chaymas,<lb break="yes"/>as well as in all the Spanish Missions and the<lb break="yes"/>Indian villages, a pair of drawers, a pair of<lb break="yes" />shoes or a hat, are objects of luxury unknown<lb break="yes"/>to the natives. An Indian servant, who had<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="220" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>been with us during our journey to Caripe and<lb break="yes"/>the Orinoco, and whom I brought to France,<lb break="yes"/>was so much struck, on landing, when he saw<lb break="yes"/>the ground tilled by a peasant with his hat<lb break="yes"/>on, that he thought himself in a miserable<lb break="yes" />country, where even the nobles (los mismos<lb break="yes"/>caballeros) followed the plough.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This on the deformities of civilized and<lb break="yes"/>savage life is not without its moral.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The Chayma women are not handsome,<lb break="yes"/>according to the ideas we annex to beauty;<lb break="yes"/>yet the young girls have a look of softness and<lb break="yes"/>melancholy, contrasting agreeably with the<lb break="yes"/>expression of the mouth, which is somewhat<lb break="yes" />harsh and wild. They wear their hair plaited<lb break="yes"/>in two long tresses; they do not paint their<lb break="yes"/>skin; and wear no other ornaments than<lb break="yes"/>necklaces and bracelets made of shells, birds&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>bones, and seeds. Both men and women are<lb break="yes"/>very muscular, but at the same time fleshy<lb break="yes"/>and plump. I saw no person who had any<lb break="yes"/>natural deformity; and I may say the same of<lb break="yes"/>thousands of Caribs, Muyscas, and Mexican<lb break="yes"/>and Peruvian Indians, whom we observed<lb break="yes"/>during the course of five years. Bodily defor-<lb break="no"/>mities, and deviations from nature, are exceed-<lb break="no"/>ingly rare among certain races of men,<lb break="yes" />especially those who have the epidermis highly<lb break="yes"/>colored; but I cannot believe that they depend<lb break="yes"/>solely on the progress of civilization, a luxuri-<lb break="no"/>ous life, or the corruption of morals. In<lb break="yes"/>Europe, a deformed or very ugly girl marries,<lb break="yes"/>if she happen to have a fortune, and the chil-<lb break="no" />dren often inherit the deformity of the mother.<lb break="yes"/>In the savage state, which is a state of<lb break="yes"/>equality, no consideration can induce a man<lb break="yes"/>to unite himself to a deformed woman, or one<lb break="yes"/>who is very unhealthy. Such a woman, if<lb break="yes"/>she resist the accidents of a restless and<lb break="yes"/>troubled life, dies without children. We<lb break="yes"/>might be tempted to think, that savages all<lb break="yes"/>appear well made and vigorous, because feeble<lb break="yes"/>children die young for want of care, and only<lb break="yes" />the strongest survive; but these causes cannot<lb break="yes"/>operate among the Indians of the Missions,<lb break="yes"/>whose manners are like those of our peasants,<lb break="yes"/>or among the Mexicans of Cholula and Tlas-<lb break="no"/>cala, who enjoy wealth, transmitted to them<lb break="yes"/>by ancestors more civilized than themselves.<lb break="yes"/>If, in every state of cultivation, the copper-<lb break="no"/>colored race manifests the same inflexibility,<lb break="yes"/>the same resistance to deviation from a primi-<lb break="no"/>tive type, are we not forced to admit that this<lb break="yes"/>peculiarity belongs in great measure to here-<lb break="no" />ditary organization, to that which constitutes<lb break="yes"/>the race? With copper-colored men, as with<lb break="yes"/>whites, luxury and effeminacy weaken the<lb break="yes"/>physical constitution, and heretofore deformi-<lb break="no"/>ties were more common at Cuzco and Tenoch-<lb break="no" />titlan. Among the Mexicans of the present<lb break="yes"/>day, who are all laborers, leading the most<lb break="yes"/>simple lives, Montezuma would not have found<lb break="yes"/>those dwarfs and humpbacks whom Bernal<lb break="yes" />Diaz saw waiting at his table when he dined.<lb break="yes"/>The custom of marrying very young, according<lb break="yes"/>to the testimony of the monks, is no way<lb break="yes"/>detrimental to population. This precocious<lb break="yes" />nubility depends on the race, and not on the<lb break="yes"/>influence of a climate excessively warm. It is<lb break="yes"/>found on the north-west coast of America,<lb break="yes"/>among the Esquimaux, and in Asia, among the<lb break="yes"/>Kamtschatdales, and the Koriaks, where girls<lb break="yes"/>of ten years old are often mothers. It may<lb break="yes"/>appear astonishing, that the time of gestation<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;the duration of pregnancy, never alters in<lb break="yes"/>a state of health, in any race, or in any<lb break="yes"/>climate.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We might glean from every page passages<lb break="yes"/>like this, always bringing information from<lb break="yes"/>the subject and to the subject, always con-<lb break="no"/>ferring delight.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Is it unnatural that M. Humboldt should<lb break="yes"/>quit this, his first residence on the long-<lb break="no"/>desired tropical continent with a burst of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>enthusiasm, and that the reader should par-<lb break="no"/>ticipate in it?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#k">fascination of the tropics.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;We quitted the shore of Cumana, as if it<lb break="yes"/>had long been our home. This was the first<lb break="yes"/>land we had trodden in a zone, towards which<lb break="yes"/>my thoughts had been directed from earliest<lb break="yes"/>youth. There is a powerful charm in the<lb break="yes" />impression produced by the scenery and cli-<lb break="no"/>mate of these regions; and after an abode of<lb break="yes"/>a few months we seemed to have lived there<lb break="yes"/>during a long succession of years. In Europe,<lb break="yes"/>the inhabitant of the north feels an almost<lb break="yes" />similar emotion, when he quits even after a<lb break="yes"/>short abode the shores of the Bay of Naples,<lb break="yes"/>the delicious country between Tivoli and the<lb break="yes"/>lake of Nemi or the wild and majestic scenery<lb break="yes"/>of the Upper Alps and the Pyrenees. Yet<lb break="yes" />everywhere in the temperate zone, the effects<lb break="yes"/>of vegetable physiognomy afford little con-<lb break="no"/>trast. The firs and the oaks which crown the<lb break="yes"/>mountains of Sweden have a certain family air<lb break="yes"/>in common with those which adorn Greece<lb break="yes"/>and Italy. Between the tropics, on the con-<lb break="no"/>trary, in the lower regions of both Indies,<lb break="yes"/>everything in nature appears new and mar-<lb break="no"/>vellous. In the open plains and amid the<lb break="yes" />gloom of forests, almost all the remembrances<lb break="yes"/>of Europe are effaced; for it is vegetation that<lb break="yes"/>determines the character of a landscape, and<lb break="yes"/>acts upon the imagination by its mass, the<lb break="yes"/>contrast of its forms, and the glow of its<lb break="yes" />colors. In proportion as impressions are<lb break="yes"/>powerful and new, they weaken antecedent<lb break="yes"/>impressions, and their force imparts to them<lb break="yes"/>the character of duration. I appeal to those<lb break="yes"/>who, more sensible to the beauties of nature<lb break="yes" />than to the charms of society, have long<lb break="yes"/>resided in the torrid zone. How dear, how<lb break="yes"/>memorable during life, is the land on which<lb break="yes"/>they first disembarked! A vague desire to<lb break="yes"/>revisit that spot remains rooted in their minds<lb break="yes" />to the most advanced age. Cumana and its<lb break="yes"/>dusty soil are still more frequently present to<lb break="yes"/>my imagination than all the wonders of the<lb break="yes"/>Cordilleras. Beneath the bright sky of the<lb break="yes" />south, the light, and the magic of the aerial<lb break="yes"/>hues, embellish a land almost destitute of<lb break="yes"/>vegetation. The sun does not merely enlighten,<lb break="yes"/>it colors the objects, and wraps them in a thin<lb break="yes"/>vapor, which, without changing the trans-<lb break="no" />parency of the air, renders its tints more<lb break="yes"/>harmonious, softens the effects of the light,<lb break="yes"/>and diffuses over nature a placid calm, which<lb break="yes"/>is reflected in our souls. To explain this vivid<lb break="yes"/>impression which the aspect of the scenery in<lb break="yes" />the two Indies produces, even on coasts but<lb break="yes"/>thinly wooded, it is sufficient to recollect that<lb break="yes"/>the beauty of the sky augments from Naples<lb break="yes"/>to the equator, almost as much as from Pro-<lb break="no"/>vence to the south of Italy.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 