<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On the Geographical Distribution of Ferns</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:53</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.53</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1818-On_the_Geographical-1-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>&lt;i&gt;Nova genera et species plantarum&lt;/i&gt;, Bd. 1 1815</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>S. 33–37.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>auch enthalten in:</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>&lt;i&gt;De distributione geographica plantarum secundum coeli temperiem et altitudinem montium&lt;/i&gt;. MDCCCXVII [1817].</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>S. 169-186. [Diese Hinweise stammen von Rex.]</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On the Geographical Distribution of Ferns</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1818</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <pubPlace>New York City, New York</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Journal of Science and the Arts&lt;/i&gt; 4:7 (3. Januar 1818), S. [57–66].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <relatedItem type="reprint">
            <bibl>[Hinweis von Corinna Fiedler, bitte besorgen]: Hanno Beck, Studienausgabe, Band 1 (Schriften zur Geographie der Pflanzen), S. 247ff.</bibl>
          </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="57" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Geographical Distribution of Ferns.<lb break="yes" />From the Latin of</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Alexander,</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Baron</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">von Humboldt.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Paris,</hi> 1817.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">I</hi>T will not escape the studious observer of the natural sta-<lb break="no"/>tions of plants, that in the cryptogamous <note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn1-1" next="#fn1-2">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Phanogamous</hi> plants, are those in which the organs of fructification<lb break="yes"/>are apparent and determinate; <hi rendition="#i">cryptogamous</hi> plants, those where these</note> class of vegeta-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="58" facs="#f0002"/> bles, the Order of Ferns distinguishes itself from those of<lb break="yes"/>Mosses, Liverworts, and Mushrooms, in this particular, viz.<lb break="yes"/>that the latter have many species which are owned in common<lb break="yes"/>as well by the north of Europe as by the tropical regions of<lb break="yes"/>both the Old and New Continents, and not merely as peculiar<lb break="yes"/>to the mountains, but likewise as inhabitants of their plains;<lb break="yes"/>such are <hi rendition="#k">Funaria</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">hygrometrica</hi> (twisting cord moss,) <hi rendition="#k" >Dicra-<lb break="no"/>nium</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">glaucum</hi> (white fork moss,) <hi rendition="#k" >Polytrichum</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">juniperinum</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(juniper-leaved hair moss,) and the Lichens <hi rendition="#k" >Verrucaria</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Perella,</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Sticta</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">crocata,</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Parmelia</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">perlata,</hi> &amp;c. all which are<lb break="yes"/>found as well on the trees and rocks of the West Indian Islands,<lb break="yes"/>the chain of the Andés, the East Indies, and that part of New<lb break="yes" />Holland which stretches towards the North, as in the Forests<lb break="yes" />of Sweden and Great Britain. While among ferns a far nar-<lb break="no"/>rower range has been allotted to the species, for with very few<lb break="yes" />exceptions those of the new and old continents, not only differ<lb break="yes" />in the one from those in the other, but in the tropical regions<lb break="yes" />are manifestly distinct from their co-ordinates of the temperate<lb break="yes"/>and frigid zones.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In tracing the native stations of the ferns, and the plan of<lb break="yes" />their distribution over the face of the earth, I have ascertained<lb break="yes"/>that of the 1000 species that have been as yet observed, 760<lb break="yes"/>belong to the torrid zone, and 240 to the temperate and frigid<lb break="yes"/>zones. But when we speak generally of the number of these<lb break="yes"/>plants, the subject presents itself three ways; one, regarding<lb break="yes"/>the relative numbers of the species among themselves, another<lb break="yes"/>regarding their numbers in relation to the phænogamous<lb break="yes"/>portion of vegetation, and a third in regard to the quantity<lb break="yes"/>each species may of itself exist in. Thus Wahlenberg reckons<lb break="yes"/>19 species of fern in Lapland, Hoffmann, 40 in Germany,<lb break="yes"/>Swartz, 103 in Jamaica, making the proportions of the frigid,<lb break="yes"/>temperate, and torrid zones, as they relate to each other in this<lb break="yes"/>point, as 1, 2, and 5. But the amount of phænogamous plants<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1">are more or less clandestine and indeterminate; <hi rendition="#i">agamous</hi> plants,<lb break="yes"/>those in which those organs either are not present, or have not been<lb break="yes"/>detected.<space dim="horizontal"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">K</hi>
                    </note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="59" facs="#f0003"/>in these regions is greatly disproportionate; for in Lapland<lb break="yes"/>there are 514 known species, and in Germany 1884, making<lb break="yes"/>the proportions 1:25 and 1:48. Whether this relative dis-<lb break="no"/>proportion increases towards the equator or not, is unknown<lb break="yes"/>to me; but if it were 1:50, and if the ferns have come in-<lb break="no"/>completely within the view and observation of botanists as the<lb break="yes"/>phænogamous portion of the vegetable creation, (which has<lb break="yes"/>hardly been the case,<note place="foot" n="*">Swartz, who attended diligently to ferns, has only recorded 764 phæno-<lb break="no" />gamous plants in Jamaica. In Michaux’s Flora of North America 45 ferns<lb break="yes"/>and 1575 phænogamous plants have been described. The Isles of Bourbon<lb break="yes"/>and France comprehend 137 species of plants.</note>) the result would be, that 5000 phæno-<lb break="no"/>gamous species have been already discovered in Jamaica, and<lb break="yes"/>23,000 in the whole of the tropical extent of America. The<lb break="yes"/>degrees of abundance with which nature has sent forth parti-<lb break="no"/>cular species are manifestly various: at the extremity of Nor-<lb break="no"/>way, on the shores of the frozen sea, ferns, although but few<lb break="yes"/>in species, cover nearly the whole face of the land.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Of the 1000 species of ferns recorded by Willdenow, 470<lb break="yes"/>grow in the old world; viz. 170 in the temperate and frigid<lb break="yes"/>zones, 300 within the tropics; and 530 grow in the New<lb break="yes"/>World, viz. 70 in the temperate and frigid zones, and 460<lb break="yes"/>within the tropics.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have elsewhere attempted to show, that if we represent<lb break="yes"/>the land within the tropics by = 1000, we are to allot it in the<lb break="yes" />following proportions; to</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <list>
                    <item>Africa, .............. 461</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>America ............. 301</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>New Holland and the Islands in the Indian Sea, 124</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Asia ............... 114</item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>leaving the proportion which belongs to the New World in<lb break="yes"/>relation to that of the Old as 5 is to 7. So that if we did not<lb break="yes"/>know the New World to be of a more humid constitution with<lb break="yes"/>a more mountainous surface than the Old, and that the interior<lb break="yes"/>of Africa and New Holland have been far less explored than<lb break="yes"/>the regions that lie between the Orinoco and the river of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="60" facs="#f0004"/>Amazons, we might be led to wonder why the portion of<lb break="yes"/>America, being considerably the least, should have by ⅓ the<lb break="yes"/>largest proportion of ferns.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I am fully aware that too much reliance must not be placed<lb break="yes"/>on the exactness of the amounts, since it has not been ascer-<lb break="no"/>tained, what proportion of each of the various regions of the<lb break="yes"/>earth has been accurately explored; nor what proportion of the<lb break="yes"/>total of vegetation has escaped the notice of the botanist; nor<lb break="yes"/>whether all the different tribes of plants have been investigated<lb break="yes"/>with equal care. But independent of these doubts, it is clear<lb break="yes"/>that the number of species cannot at all events be less than<lb break="yes"/>that which I computed.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Although the phænogamous plants of tropical America<lb break="yes"/>are entirely different from the phænogamous ones of the Old<lb break="yes"/>World, yet the northern portion of America has many in<lb break="yes"/>common with Europe and the North of Asia. Whence it<lb break="yes"/>may be inferred, that at some period those continents have<lb break="yes"/>joined towards the North Pole; and it will be a matter<lb break="yes"/>of wonder, that so few European ferns are found in Canada,<lb break="yes"/>Pennsylvania, and California; for of such we do not hear of<lb break="yes"/>more than from 6 to 10 species, as for instance, <hi rendition="#k">Ophioglossum</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">vulgatum,</hi> (common adder’s-tongue,) <hi rendition="#k" >Polypodium</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">calcareum,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(rigid three-branched polypody.) <hi rendition="#k" >Aspidium</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">thelypteris,</hi> (marsh<lb break="yes"/>shield-fern, or Lady-fern,) <hi rendition="#i">Acristatum,</hi> (lesser crested shield-<lb break="no"/>fern) <hi rendition="#k">Pteris</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">aquilina,</hi> (common brake,) &amp;c.; but then Europe<lb break="yes"/>altogether does not contain more than 70 indigenous species of<lb break="yes"/>fern.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Towards the South Pole, the ferns, which grow at the extre-<lb break="no"/>mities of the two continents, differ more than those of the north-<lb break="no"/>ern temperate zone do from each other. The only instances<lb break="yes"/>of any common to all the continent in those regions, that I am<lb break="yes"/>aware of, are <hi rendition="#k">Davallia</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">pinnata,</hi> which grows in Chili and in the<lb break="yes" />Philippine Islands; and <hi rendition="#k">Osmunda</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">barbara,</hi> which grows in New<lb break="yes"/>Holland and at the Cape of Good Hope. Hence it is the more<lb break="yes"/>strange that <hi rendition="#k">Aspidium</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">aculeatum,</hi> (or common prickly shield-<lb break="no" />fern,) which is the only one among the ferns of the Old World<lb break="yes" />that ranges through several of the zones, extending itself<lb break="yes" />from England across Mount Atlas to the southernmost verge<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="61" facs="#f0005"/>of Africa, should not have yet been met with in America.<lb break="yes"/>According to Messrs. Forster and Brown, <hi rendition="#k">Botrychium</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Lunaria,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(common moonwort) familiar in every part of Germany, covers,<lb break="yes"/>in company with the <hi rendition="#k">Phleum</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">alpinum,</hi> (alpine cat’s-tail-grass)<lb break="yes"/>of our country, every rock in Tierra del Fuego. <hi rendition="#k">Hymeno-<lb break="no"/>phyllum</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">tunbridgense,</hi> (Tunbridge filmy-grass) grows in New<lb break="yes"/>Holland as well as in Ireland, Norway, and Italy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The only instance of a species of the fern-tribe growing both<lb break="yes"/>in the Old and in the New continents, in the torrid as well<lb break="yes"/>as in the frigid zone, in a northern and a southern hemi-<lb break="no"/>sphere, viz. in England, Jamaica, and the Isle of Bourbon, is<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#k">Adiantum</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Capillus Veneris,</hi> (true maiden-hair,) a plant<lb break="yes"/>which has been commemorated by Hippocrates, Theophrastus,<lb break="yes"/>and Dioscorides. It has however been surmised by some that<lb break="yes"/>the germs of this fern have adhered to the filtering stones used<lb break="yes"/>aboard ships in long voyages, and been thus carried along with<lb break="yes"/>them and disseminated over the world.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is not quite clear, that any fern has been found that is<lb break="yes" />common to the tropical regions of both the New and Old Con-<lb break="no" />tinents. Authors have as yet only suggested three such<lb break="yes" />instances, viz. <hi rendition="#k">Aspidium</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">punctulatum,</hi> A. <hi rendition="#i">coriaceum,</hi> and <hi rendition="#k">Asple-<lb break="no"/>nium</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">monanthemum,</hi> which are said to be spontaneous in the<lb break="yes"/>West Indies, the Andés of Peru, Guinea, New Holland, and<lb break="yes"/>the Cape of Good Hope. To these may be added <hi rendition="#k" >Asplenium</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">falcatum,</hi> and <hi rendition="#k">Blechnum</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">caudatum,</hi> supposed to belong to South<lb break="yes" />America and the Islands of Magindanao as well as Ceylon.<lb break="yes"/>But I doubt whether the statements concerning these instances<lb break="yes"/>are so well authenticated, as those mentioned above of <hi rendition="#k">Hyme-<lb break="no"/>nophyllum</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">tunbridgense,</hi> and <hi rendition="#k">Botrychium</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Lunaria.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>More than half of all the ferns yet observed belong to<lb break="yes"/>four genera only, viz. to <hi rendition="#k">Polypodium</hi>, (Polypody,) <hi rendition="#k">Aspidium,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(Shield-fern,) <hi rendition="#k">Pteris,</hi> (Brake,) and <hi rendition="#k">Asplenium,</hi> (Spleenwort.)<lb break="yes"/>Some types among them seem confined almost entirely to tro-<lb break="no"/>pical lands, as <hi rendition="#k">Meniscium, Anemia, Hydroglossum, Mer-<lb break="no" />tensia,</hi> and <hi rendition="#k">Schizea</hi>: but all the generic types of the northern<lb break="yes"/>temperate zone are found likewise between the tropics. The<lb break="yes"/>New World alone has no genus of the Fern-tribe peculiar to<lb break="yes"/>itself, although many of its phænogamous genera are so; for<lb break="yes"/>example, <hi rendition="#k">Cactus, Calceolaria, Alstrœmeria, Bromelia,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="62" facs="#f0006"/>and others. As for the fern-types <hi rendition="#k" >Polybotrya, Pleopeltis,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and <hi rendition="#k">Marattia,</hi> so few species of them have been found, that it<lb break="yes"/>is highly probable other congeners will be detected in our own<lb break="yes"/>continent, so that they can hardly be relied on as exceptions.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Ferns, which in the northern frigid zone grow along the<lb break="yes"/>ground in the shade, in the tropical regions, shoot up to the<lb break="yes"/>dimensions of trees, vying with the palms themselves in stature<lb break="yes"/>and comeliness. These tree-ferns constitute a principal orna-<lb break="no"/>ment of the torrid zone, giving that peculiar character to the<lb break="yes"/>spots where they grow, which strikes so forcibly the European<lb break="yes"/>stranger by its novelty. The Greek and Roman writers who<lb break="yes"/>have treated of plants, mention in several places, that many<lb break="yes"/>which in Europe creep along the ground, in hotter climates<lb break="yes"/>become trees, making it the more remarkable, that none<lb break="yes"/>should speak of a tree-fern; particularly as Megasthenes,<lb break="yes"/>Aristobulus, and Nearchus, recount among the wonders of<lb break="yes"/>Indian and Ethiopian lands, that there are trees having leaves<lb break="yes"/>as large as a shield, a fig-tree that takes root at the ends<lb break="yes"/>of its branches, and palms too high for the flight of an arrow<lb break="yes"/>to pass over. Theophrastus, Dioscorides, and Pliny, who has<lb break="yes"/>trodden over again the ground of the two first, mention only<lb break="yes"/>eight or ten species of ferns, none above a yard high. And<lb break="yes"/>when a certain sort of fern brought from India is noticed, as<lb break="yes"/>being known to the philosopher Eresius, no observation is<lb break="yes"/>offered concerning the stature of the stem, attention being only<lb break="yes"/>bestowed on certain medicinal qualities imputed to the plant.<lb break="yes"/>So that tree-ferns must have been left unnoticed by the Romans<lb break="yes"/>and Greeks, either because in that portion of India, which the<lb break="yes"/>arms of Alexander had opened to them, or in Ethiopia and<lb break="yes"/>Lybia, which they visited in the view of commerce, none are<lb break="yes"/>to be found; or because their writers, as was usual in former<lb break="yes"/>times, left unnoticed all plants which did not recommend<lb break="yes"/>themselves to their attention by the fruit they bore, or the fra-<lb break="no"/>grance of their wood, or their medicinal virtues. Oviedo,<lb break="yes"/>the Spaniard, in his history of the West Indies, is the first<lb break="yes"/>who mentions a tree-fern; for the <hi rendition="#i">Filix arborea</hi> of Tragus is<lb break="yes"/>nothing more than a variety of our common forked spleen-<lb break="no"/>wort, transplanted into a more fertile land.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>So late as the time of Linnæus scarcely 4 sorts of tree-fern<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="63" facs="#f0007"/>were known, and about 15 sorts of palms; at present we are<lb break="yes"/>acquainted with 25 of the former, and 100 of the latter. The<lb break="yes"/>tree-ferns of America are,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#et">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Cyathea</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#i">speciosa, C. arborea, C. Serra, C. muricata, C.<lb break="yes"/>multiflora, C. villosa, C. aspera,</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#k">Pteris</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#i">aculeata, P.<lb break="yes"/>villosa,</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#k">Meniscium</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#i">arboreum,</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#k">Aspidium</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#i">caducum, A. pro-<lb break="no"/>cerum, A. rostratum,</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#k">Asplenium</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#i">arboreum,</hi> cæt.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Of New Holland and the Islands of the Indian Sea;<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#et">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Cyathea</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#i">affinis, C. medullaris, C. dealbata, C. extensa,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#k">Dicksonia</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#i">squarrosa, D. antarctica,</hi> cæt.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Of Southern Africa, and the Islands of France and Bourbon.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#et">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Cyathea</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#i">excelsa, C. glauca, C. riparia,</hi> cæt.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The tree-ferns of the East Indies, Cochinchina, the Island<lb break="yes"/>of Madagascar, and the Cape of Good Hope have not yet been<lb break="yes" />accurately described. I have not included amongst the arbo-<lb break="no" />rescent species, <hi rendition="#k">Aspidium</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Arbuscula,</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Lomaria</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Boryana,</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Poly-<lb break="no"/>podium</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">rhizocaule, P. pruinatum,</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Pteris</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">marginata,</hi> &amp;c. because<lb break="yes"/>they are either climbers, or else shrubby or caulescent plants,<lb break="yes"/>with stems not more than three or four feet high. Of the<lb break="yes"/>five new species of tree-ferns observed by M. Bonpland and<lb break="yes"/>myself, <hi rendition="#k">Cyathea</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">speciosa</hi> is the one which makes the finest<lb break="yes"/>appearance, and has a stem 25 feet high. The <hi rendition="#i" >C. excelsa</hi> of<lb break="yes"/>the Isle of Bourbon is said by Messrs. Du Petit Thouars and<lb break="yes"/>Bory St. Vincent to grow to the same height.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In general, the tropical plants are further advanced towards<lb break="yes"/>the South Pole than towards the North Pole, a fact which<lb break="yes"/>seems inconsistent with the received opinion of the cold being<lb break="yes"/>greater in the Southern Hemisphere. In North America and<lb break="yes"/>New Spain, the tree-ferns hardly ever grow beyond the limits<lb break="yes"/>of the tropic of Cancer, while only one species of palm (<hi rendition="#k">Cha-<lb break="no" />mærops</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Palmetto</hi>) advances to Carolina, or the latitude of 37°.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the Southern Hemisphere, on the other hand, <hi rendition="#k">Dicksonia</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">antarctica,</hi> described by Labillardiére as having a stem near 20<lb break="yes"/>feet high, grows in Van Diemen’s Island; nay, another species<lb break="yes"/>of <hi rendition="#i">Dicksonia</hi> has been found at Dusky Bay in New Zealand, in<lb break="yes"/>the 46th degree of southern latitude, where in a parallel which<lb break="yes"/>corresponds with that of Lyons, the trees swarm with <hi rendition="#i">Epiden-<lb break="no"/>dra and Dendrobia,</hi> vegetable parasites, which constitute the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="64" facs="#f0008"/>most graceful ornaments of the tropical Flora. Phæno-<lb break="no"/>mena, which excite the more wonder, when we find from the<lb break="yes"/>observations of the celebrated navigators Cook, Entrecasteaux,<lb break="yes"/>and Flinders, that the mean annual temperature of this zone<lb break="yes"/>is scarcely equal to 12,5 of the centigrade thermometer.<lb break="yes"/>But the great expanse of water in the Southern Hemisphere<lb break="yes"/>cools the heat in summer and assuages the cold in winter; so<lb break="yes"/>that in the 52d and 53d degrees of southern latitude, corres-<lb break="no"/>ponding to that of Berlin in our hemisphere, the snow melts<lb break="yes"/>nearly every day of the winter, and the centigrade thermome-<lb break="no"/>ter very seldom rises to 11° in the months of January and De-<lb break="no"/>cember, the hot summer months of these regions. Even in the<lb break="yes"/>42d and 43d degrees of Southern latitude, owing to the cur-<lb break="no"/>rents of wind that blow from the South Pole, the summers are<lb break="yes"/>hardly hotter than at the sides of the mountains of Switzerland:<lb break="yes"/>these summers, on the other hand, are succeeded by winters<lb break="yes"/>even milder than those of Rome. Labillardiére never observed<lb break="yes"/>the centigrade thermometer in Van Diemen’s Island rise<lb break="yes"/>higher at mid-day than 15-17°,5 in the months of January and<lb break="yes"/>February; and Cook in the same parallel, during July, a winter<lb break="yes"/>month of those regions; never found the degree of cold below<lb break="yes"/>8° of the centigrade thermometer.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In tropical America, as I have shown in another work, the<lb break="yes" />herbaceous ferns grow in all parts, from the border of the sea,<lb break="yes" />and from the plains, up to the heights of the Andés, although<lb break="yes" />but little below the limits of eternal snow. There are certain<lb break="yes" />species peculiar to certain elevations, and each in its zone is<lb break="yes" />unable to transgress that boundary which has been allotted to<lb break="yes" />it. Thus in the mountains of Peru and New Spain, <hi rendition="#k">Cheil-<lb break="no"/>anthes</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">marginatus,</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Acrostichum</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">muscosum,</hi> and <hi rendition="#k">Hemionitis</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">rufa,</hi> grow between the elevations of 1200 and 1600 fathoms:<lb break="yes"/>in the same way the <hi rendition="#k">Pteris</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">crispa,</hi> (rock-brake or curled stone-<lb break="no" />fern) grows on Mount St. Gothard from above the region of<lb break="yes" />Pines up to the elevation of 1,100 fathoms; and in Lapland,<lb break="yes" />near Enontekies, to that of 300 fathoms; so that in Switzer-<lb break="no" />land, its highest station is scarcely 280 fathoms removed from<lb break="yes" />the limits of eternal snow, and in the North of Norway<lb break="yes" />scarcely 100 fathoms. <hi rendition="#k">Polypodium</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">hyperboreum,</hi> (hairy alpine<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="65" facs="#f0009"/>polypody) in latitude 68° advances still higher, to beyond<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Betula</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">nana,</hi> (dwarf birch) <hi rendition="#k">Draba</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">alpina</hi> (mountain whitlow<lb break="yes"/>grass) and <hi rendition="#k">Campanula</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">uniflora,</hi> (one-flowered bell-flower.) I<lb break="yes" />have elsewhere explained myself on the subject of the reason<lb break="yes" />why plants approach nearer to the boundary of eternal snow<lb break="yes" />towards the North Pole, than they do in the torrid zone.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the kingdom of Quito, M. Bonpland and myself saw moun-<lb break="no" />tain-ferns reaching into the elevated plain which engirds Mount<lb break="yes" />Antisana and along the sides of the Rucupichincha in the val-<lb break="no" />ley of Verdecuchu, both which spots are 2100 fathoms above<lb break="yes"/>the level of the sea; and also other herbaceous ferns on Mount<lb break="yes" />Chimborazo, growing on porphyritic rock, as high up as 2300<lb break="yes" />fathoms. But at heights so great, where the cold is so severe,<lb break="yes" />as well as in parched unshaded plains and spots, the quantity of<lb break="yes"/>ferns is plainly perceived to diminish from the want of moisture.<lb break="yes"/>Their main body is stationed in the temperate and sub-frigid<lb break="yes"/>zones, between the elevations of 300 and 1200 fathoms.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Tree-ferns in some regions occasionally grow down to<lb break="yes"/>the edge of the sea, and on lowlands in shady spots; but<lb break="yes"/>in those parts of tropical America where M. Bonpland and<lb break="yes"/>myself passed five years, they occupy a peculiar zone, in which<lb break="yes"/>the temperature is between 18 and 22 degrees of the centigrade<lb break="yes"/>thermometer. A delightful region, where vernal breezes<lb break="yes"/>prevail almost the year through, and which lies between the<lb break="yes"/>elevations of 400 and 800 fathoms from the level of the sea:<lb break="yes"/>though they sometimes descend as low as to the height of 200<lb break="yes"/>fathoms. This zone is called by the natives in the Spanish dia-<lb break="no"/>lect, <hi rendition="#i">tierra templada de los helechos,</hi> the temperate land of the<lb break="yes" />ferns. The chief part of the tree-ferns we met with, was in<lb break="yes" />New Andalusia, near the Convent of Caripa, and in New<lb break="yes"/>Granada near Ibague, Guaduas and Icononzo, and in the<lb break="yes"/>valleys of Peru between Loxa and the river of the Amazons<lb break="yes"/>also in New Spain near Xalapa. The region of fern-trees is<lb break="yes"/>not far from that of the <hi rendition="#k">Cinchonas,</hi> or bark-trees; for we<lb break="yes"/>find <hi rendition="#k">Cinchona</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">oblongifolia</hi> and C. <hi rendition="#i">multiflora,</hi> however fond<lb break="yes"/>they are of heat, mingling themselves with the tree-ferns<lb break="yes"/>in the Andès of Peru, and of the mountains of Quito and New<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="66" facs="#f0010"/>Granada. In New Spain they grow in company with the<lb break="yes"/>oaks* of that country; a strange association in the eye of the<lb break="yes"/>European.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 