<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="438" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">the caraccas.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#i">From the third volume of Humboldt&#x2019;s<lb break="yes" />Personal Travels.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>After having described the scenery<lb break="yes"/>and the atmospheric constitution of La<lb break="yes"/>Guayra, we shall now leave the coasts of<lb break="yes"/>the Carribbean sea. The road that<lb break="yes" />leads from the port to Caraccas, the ca-<lb break="no"/>pital of a government of near 900,000<lb break="yes"/>inhabitants, resembles the passages<lb break="yes"/>over the Alps, the road of St. Gothard<lb break="yes"/>and the Great St. Bernard. The height<lb break="yes"/>of Caraccas is but a third of that of<lb break="yes"/>Mexico, Quito, and <hi rendition="#i">Santa Fe de Ba-<lb break="no"/>gota</hi>; yet among all the capitals of<lb break="yes"/>Spanish America, which enjoy a cool<lb break="yes"/>and delicious climate in the midst of the<lb break="yes" />torrid zone, Caraccas stands nearest<lb break="yes"/>the coast. What a privilege, to possess<lb break="yes"/>a sea-port at three leagues, distance,<lb break="yes"/>and to be situate among mountains, on<lb break="yes"/>a table land, which would produce<lb break="yes"/>wheat, if the cultivation of the coffee<lb break="yes"/>tree were not preferred! The road<lb break="yes"/>from La Guayra to the valley of Car-<lb break="no" />accas, is infinitely finer than that from<lb break="yes"/>Quayaquil to Quito, or that from Hon-<lb break="no"/>da to Santa Fe. With good mules it<lb break="yes"/>requires but three hours to go from the<lb break="yes"/>port of La Guayra to the Caraccas; and<lb break="yes"/>only two hours to return.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>When I passed for the first time that<lb break="yes"/>table land, on my way to the capital of<lb break="yes"/>Venezuela, I found several travellers<lb break="yes"/>assembled around the little inn of<lb break="yes"/>Guayavo, to rest their mules. They<lb break="yes"/>were inhabitants of Caraccas, and were<lb break="yes"/>disputing on the efforts towards inde-<lb break="no"/>pendence, which had been made a short<lb break="yes"/>time before. Joseph Espana had per-<lb break="no"/>ished on the scaffold; and his wife<lb break="yes"/>groaned in prison, because she had<lb break="yes" />given an asylum to her husband when<lb break="yes"/>a fugitive, and had not denounced him<lb break="yes"/>to the government. I was struck with<lb break="yes"/>the agitation which prevailed in every<lb break="yes" />mind, and the bitterness with which<lb break="yes"/>questions were debated, on which men<lb break="yes"/>of the same country ought not to have<lb break="yes"/>differed in opinion. While they de-<lb break="no" />scanted on the hatred of the mulattoes<lb break="yes"/>against the free negroes and whites, on<lb break="yes"/>the wealth of the monks, and the diffi-<lb break="no"/>culty of holding slaves in obedience, a<lb break="yes"/>cold wind that seemed to descend from<lb break="yes"/>the lofty summit of the Silla of Carac-<lb break="no"/>cas, enveloped us in a thick fog, and<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/>put an end to this animated conversa-<lb break="no"/>tion.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Caraccas is the capital of a country<lb break="yes"/>which is nearly twice as large as Peru<lb break="yes"/>is at present, and which yields little in<lb break="yes"/>extent to the kingdom of Grenada.<lb break="yes"/>This country which the Spanish go-<lb break="no"/>vernment designates by the name of<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">captain generalship of Caraccas,</hi> or<lb break="yes"/>of the (<hi rendition="#i" >united</hi>) <hi rendition="#i">provinces of Venezuela,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>has nearly a million of inhabitants,<lb break="yes"/>among whom are sixty thousand slaves.<lb break="yes"/>It contains along the coast, New An-<lb break="no"/>dalusia, or the province of Cumana (with<lb break="yes"/>the island of Margaretta), Barcelona,<lb break="yes" />Venezuela or Caraccas, Coro and Ma-<lb break="no"/>ra-Caybo in the interior, the provin-<lb break="no"/>ces of Varinas and Guayana, the first<lb break="yes"/>along the rivers of Santa Domingo and<lb break="yes"/>Apere, the second along the Oroonoko,<lb break="yes"/>the Casiquiare, the Atabapo, and the rio<lb break="yes"/>Negro. In the general view of the seven<lb break="yes"/>united provinces of Terra, we perceive,<lb break="yes"/>that they form three distinct zones ex-<lb break="no" />tending from east to west. We find at<lb break="yes"/>first cultivated land along the shore, and<lb break="yes"/>near the chain of the mountains on the<lb break="yes"/>coast; next savannahs or pasturages, and<lb break="yes"/>finally beyond the Oroonoko, a third<lb break="yes"/>zone, that of forests, into which we can<lb break="yes"/>penetrate only by means of the rivers<lb break="yes"/>that traverse them. In the first zone are<lb break="yes"/>felt the preponderance of force, and the<lb break="yes" />abuse of power, which is the necessary<lb break="yes"/>consequence. The natives carry on a<lb break="yes"/>civil war, and sometimes devour one<lb break="yes"/>another. The monks endevour to<lb break="yes"/>augment the little villages of their mis-<lb break="no"/>sions, by availing themselves of the dis-<lb break="no"/>sensions of the natives. The military<lb break="yes"/>live in a state of hostility with the<lb break="yes" />monks, whom they were intended to<lb break="yes"/>protect. Every thing offers alike the<lb break="yes"/>melancholy picture of misery and priva-<lb break="no"/>tions. In the second region, in the plains<lb break="yes" />and the pasture grounds, food is ex-<lb break="no"/>tremely abundant, but has little variety.<lb break="yes"/>Although more advanced in civilization,<lb break="yes"/>men without the circle of some scat-<lb break="no"/>ered towns do not remain less isolated<lb break="yes"/>from one another. At the view of their<lb break="yes"/>dwellings, partly covered with skins and<lb break="yes"/>leather, it would seem that far from be-<lb break="no"/>ing fixed, they are scarcely encamped<lb break="yes"/>in those vast meadows, which extend<lb break="yes"/>to the horizon. Agriculture, which<lb break="yes"/>alone lays the basis, and draws closer<lb break="yes"/>the ties of society, occupies the third<lb break="yes" />zone, the shore, and especially the hot<lb break="yes"/>and temperate vallies in the mountains<lb break="yes"/>near the sea.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="439" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>
                    <p>If we examine the state of the cap-<lb break="no"/>tain-generalship of Caraccas, we per-<lb break="no"/>ceive that its agricultural industry,<lb break="yes"/>its great mass of population, its nu-<lb break="no"/>merous towns, and whatever is con-<lb break="no"/>nected with an advanced civiliza-<lb break="no"/>tion, are found near the coast. This<lb break="yes"/>coast extends farther than two hundred<lb break="yes" />leagues. It is bathed by the Little<lb break="yes"/>Carribbean sea, a sort of Mediterranean,<lb break="yes"/>on the shores of which almost all the<lb break="yes"/>nations of Europe have founded colo-<lb break="no"/>nies. The coasts of Venezuela, from<lb break="yes"/>their extent, their stretching towards<lb break="yes"/>the east, the number of their ports, and<lb break="yes"/>the safety of their anchorage at different<lb break="yes" />seasons, enjoy all the advantages of the<lb break="yes"/>interior Carribbean sea. The commu-<lb break="no"/>nications with the greater islands, and<lb break="yes"/>even with those that are to windward,<lb break="yes"/>can no where be more frequent than<lb break="yes"/>from the ports of Cumana, Barcelona,<lb break="yes"/>La Guayra, Porto Cabello, Coro, and<lb break="yes"/>Maraycaboa and no where has it been<lb break="yes" />found more difficult to restrain an illicit<lb break="yes"/>commerce with strangers. Can we<lb break="yes"/>wonder, that this facility of commercial<lb break="yes"/>intercourse with the inhabitants of free<lb break="yes"/>America, and the agitated nations of<lb break="yes" />Europe, should have augmented in con-<lb break="no"/>junction, in the provinces united under<lb break="yes"/>the captain generalship of Venezuela,<lb break="yes"/>opulence, knowledge, and that restless<lb break="yes"/>desire of local government, which is<lb break="yes" />blended with the love of liberty and<lb break="yes"/>republican forms?</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The copper-coloured natives, or In-<lb break="no"/>dians, constitute a very important mass<lb break="yes"/>of the agricultural population only in<lb break="yes"/>those places, where the Spaniards found<lb break="yes" />regular governments, a civil commu-<lb break="no"/>nity, and ancient and very complicated<lb break="yes"/>institutions at the conquest, as in New<lb break="yes"/>Spain, south of Durango; and in Peru,<lb break="yes"/>from Cusco to Potosi. In the captain-<lb break="no"/>generalship of Caraccas, the Indian<lb break="yes"/>population is inconsiderable, at least<lb break="yes"/>beyond the missions and in the culti-<lb break="no"/>vated zone. At the moments of great<lb break="yes"/>political dissensions, the natives excite<lb break="yes"/>no fear in the whites, or the mingled<lb break="yes"/>casts. Computing in 1809 the total<lb break="yes" />population of the seven united provin-<lb break="no"/>ces at 900,000 souls, it appeared to me<lb break="yes"/>that the Indians made only one ninth;<lb break="yes"/>while at Mexico, they form nearly one<lb break="yes"/>half of the inhabitants.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Among the casts that compose the<lb break="yes"/>population of Venezuela, that of the<lb break="yes"/>blacks, is not important from its num-<lb break="no"/>
                        <cb/>ber, but it is so from its accumulation<lb break="yes"/>on a small space of territory. In all<lb break="yes"/>the captain-generalship the slaves do<lb break="yes"/>not exceed a fifteenth of the whole po-<lb break="no"/>pulation. In the island of Cuba, of all<lb break="yes" />those in the West Indies where the ne-<lb break="no"/>groes bear the smallest proportion to the<lb break="yes"/>whites, they were, in 1811, as one to<lb break="yes"/>three. The seven united provinces of<lb break="yes" />Venezuela have sixty thousand slaves;<lb break="yes"/>Cuba, the extent of which is eight times<lb break="yes"/>less, has two hundred and twelve thou-<lb break="no"/>sand.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The sixty thousand slaves which the<lb break="yes"/>Seven United Provinces contain, are so<lb break="yes"/>unequally divided, that in the province<lb break="yes"/>of Caraccas alone, there are nearly for-<lb break="no"/>ty thousand, one fifth of which are mu-<lb break="no"/>lattoes; in that of Maracaybo, ten or<lb break="yes"/>twelve thousand; in those of Cumana<lb break="yes"/>and Barcelona, scarcely six thousand.<lb break="yes"/>To judge of the influence which the<lb break="yes"/>slaves and the men of colour exert in<lb break="yes"/>general, on the public tranquillity, it is<lb break="yes"/>not enough to know their number; we<lb break="yes" />must consider their accumulation at<lb break="yes"/>certain points, and their manner of life,<lb break="yes"/>as cultivators or inhabitants of towns.<lb break="yes"/>In the province of Venezuela, the slaves<lb break="yes"/>are assembled together on a space of<lb break="yes"/>no great extent, between the coast and<lb break="yes"/>a line that passes (at twelve leagues<lb break="yes"/>from the coast) through Panaquire,<lb break="yes"/>Yare, Sabana de Ocumare, Villa de<lb break="yes"/>Cura, and Nirgua. The <choice><sic>Leanos</sic><corr type="editorial">Llanos</corr></choice> or vast<lb break="yes"/>plains of Calaboso, San Carlos, Gua-<lb break="no"/>nare, and Barquecimeto contain only<lb break="yes" />four or five thousand, who are scatter-<lb break="no"/>ed among the farms, and employed in<lb break="yes"/>the care of cattle. The number of freed<lb break="yes"/>men is very considerable; the Spanish<lb break="yes"/>laws and customs are favourable to af-<lb break="no"/>franchisement.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>What is most interesting in the co-<lb break="no"/>lonies next to the state of the blacks, is<lb break="yes"/>to know the number of white creoles,<lb break="yes"/>whom I call Hispano-Americans, and<lb break="yes"/>that of the whites born in Europe. It<lb break="yes"/>is difficult to acquire notions sufficient-<lb break="no"/>ly exact on so delicate a point. The<lb break="yes"/>people in the new, as well as in the old<lb break="yes" />world, abhor numberings, suspecting<lb break="yes"/>them to be made in order to augment<lb break="yes"/>the weight of taxes. The men in office,<lb break="yes"/>on the other hand, sent by the mother-<lb break="no" />country to the colonies, dislike these<lb break="yes"/>statistical enumerations as much as the<lb break="yes"/>people, and this from motives of jealous<lb break="yes"/>policy.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>If we compare the Seven United Pro-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="440" facs="#f0003"/>
                        <cb/>vinces of Venezuela to the kingdom of<lb break="yes"/>Mexico, and the island of Cuba, we<lb break="yes"/>shall succeed in finding the approxi-<lb break="no"/>mate number of white creoles, and<lb break="yes"/>even of Europeans. The first, or Hi-<lb break="no"/>spano-Americans, form in Mexico near<lb break="yes"/>ly one fifth, and in the island of Cuba,<lb break="yes"/>according to the very accurate enume-<lb break="no"/>ration of 1801, a third of the whole po-<lb break="no"/>pulation. When we reflect, that the<lb break="yes"/>kingdom of Mexico is inhabited by two<lb break="yes"/>millions and a half of natives of the<lb break="yes" />copper-coloured race; when we consi-<lb break="no"/>der the state of the coasts that are bath-<lb break="no"/>ed by the Pacific ocean, and the small<lb break="yes"/>number of whites in the intendencies<lb break="yes"/>of Puebla and Oaxaca, comparatively<lb break="yes"/>with the natives; we cannot doubt, that<lb break="yes"/>the province of Venezuela, at least, if<lb break="yes"/>not the capitania-general, has a greater<lb break="yes"/>proportion than that of one to five. The<lb break="yes"/>island of Cuba, in which the whites are<lb break="yes" />even more numerous than in Chili, may<lb break="yes"/>furnish us with a limiting number, that<lb break="yes"/>is to say, the <hi rendition="#i" >maximum</hi> that can be sup-<lb break="no"/>posed in the capitania-general of Ca-<lb break="no"/>raccas. I believe we must stop at two<lb break="yes"/>hundred, or two hundred and ten thou-<lb break="no" />sand Hispano-Americans, in a total po-<lb break="no"/>pulation of nine hundred thousand souls.<lb break="yes"/>The number of Europeans included in<lb break="yes"/>the white race (not comprehending the<lb break="yes" />troops sent from the mother-country)<lb break="yes"/>does not exceed twelve or fifteen thou-<lb break="no"/>sand. It certainly is not greater at Mex-<lb break="no"/>ico than sixty thousand, and I find by<lb break="yes"/>several statements, that if we estimate<lb break="yes"/>the Spanish colonies at fourteen or fif-<lb break="no"/>teen millions of inhabitants, there are<lb break="yes"/>in this number, at most, three millions<lb break="yes"/>of creole whites, and two hundred thou-<lb break="no"/>sand Europeans.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It seems to excite surprise in Europe,<lb break="yes"/>that the Spaniards of the mother-coun-<lb break="no"/>try, of whom we have remarked the<lb break="yes"/>small number, have made during ages<lb break="yes"/>so long and so firm a resistance. Men<lb break="yes"/>forget that the European party in all<lb break="yes"/>the colonies is necessarily augmented<lb break="yes" />by a great mass of the natives. Family<lb break="yes"/>interests, the desire of uninterrupted<lb break="yes"/>tranquillity, the fear of engaging in an<lb break="yes"/>enterprise that might fail, prevent these<lb break="yes"/>latter from embracing the cause of in-<lb break="no" />dependence, or aspiring to establish a<lb break="yes"/>local and representative government,<lb break="yes"/>though dependant on the mother-coun-<lb break="no"/>try. Some shrink from violent mea-<lb break="no"/>sures, and flatter themselves, that a<lb break="yes" />gradual reform may render the colonial<lb break="yes"/>system less oppressive. They see in<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/>revolutions only the loss of their slaves,<lb break="yes"/>the spoliation of the clergy, and the in-<lb break="no"/>troduction of religious toleration, which<lb break="yes"/>they believe to be incompatible with<lb break="yes"/>the purity of the established worship.<lb break="yes" />Others belong to the small number of<lb break="yes"/>families, which, either from hereditary<lb break="yes"/>opulence, or having been long settled<lb break="yes"/>in the colonies, exercise a real muni-<lb break="no"/>cipal aristocracy. They would rather<lb break="yes"/>be deprived of certain rights, than share<lb break="yes"/>them with all; they would prefer even<lb break="yes"/>a foreign yoke to the exercise of au-<lb break="no"/>thority by the Americans of an inferior<lb break="yes" />cast; they abhor every constitution<lb break="yes"/>founded on an equality of rights, and<lb break="yes"/>above all, they dread the loss of these<lb break="yes"/>decorations and titles which they have<lb break="yes"/>with so much difficulty acquired, and<lb break="yes"/>which, as we have observed above,<lb break="yes"/>compose so essential a part of their<lb break="yes"/>domestic happiness.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>St. Thomas, in Guiana, will be ne-<lb break="no"/>cessarily, at some future day, a place<lb break="yes"/>of trade of high importance, eapecially<lb break="yes"/>when the flour of New Grenada, em-<lb break="no"/>barked above the confluence of the Rio<lb break="yes"/>Negro and the Umadea, and descend-<lb break="no"/>ing by the Meta and Oroonoko, shall<lb break="yes"/>be preferred at Caraccas and Guiana to<lb break="yes"/>the flour of New England. It is a great<lb break="yes"/>advantage to the provinces of Vene-<lb break="no"/>zuela, that their territorial wealth is<lb break="yes"/>not directed to one point, like that of<lb break="yes" />Mexico and New Granada, which flows<lb break="yes"/>to Vera Cruz and Carthagena; but that<lb break="yes"/>they possess a great number of towns<lb break="yes"/>equally well peopled, and forming so<lb break="yes"/>many various centres of commerce and<lb break="yes"/>civilization.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The climate of Caraccas has often<lb break="yes"/>been called a <hi rendition="#i">perpetual spring.</hi> It is<lb break="yes"/>found every where, half way up the<lb break="yes"/>Cordilleras of Equinoctial America, be-<lb break="no"/>tween four hundred and nine hundred<lb break="yes" />toises of elevation, unless the great<lb break="yes"/>breadth of the valley joined to an arid<lb break="yes"/>soil causes an extraordinary intensity<lb break="yes"/>of radiant caloric. What, indeed, can<lb break="yes"/>we imagine more delightful, than a<lb break="yes" />temperature, which in the day keeps<lb break="yes"/>between 20&#x00B0; and 26&#x00B0;; and at night be-<lb break="no"/>tween 16&#x00B0; and 18&#x00B0;, which is equally<lb break="yes"/>favourable to the plantain (cambury),<lb break="yes"/>the orange-tree, the coffee-tree, the<lb break="yes"/>apple, the apricot, and corn? A nation-<lb break="no"/>al writer compares the situation of Ca-<lb break="no"/>raccas to the terrestrial paradise, and<lb break="yes" />recognizes in the Anauco and the<lb break="yes"/>neighbouring torrents, the four rivers<lb break="yes"/>of the garden of Eden.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 