<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="59" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>A MAN GIVING SUCK.<lb break="yes"/>[From Humboldt&#x2019;s Personal Travels.]</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the village of Arenas, on the road from<lb break="yes"/>San Fernando to Cumana, lives a labourer,<lb break="yes"/>Francisco Lozano, who presented a physio-<lb break="no"/>logical phenomenon, highly calculated to<lb break="yes"/>strike the imagination, though it is very<lb break="yes" />conformable to the known laws of organized<lb break="yes"/>nature. This man has suckled a child with<lb break="yes"/>his own milk. The mother having fallen<lb break="yes"/>sick, the father, to quiet the infant, took it<lb break="yes"/>into his bed, and pressed it to his bosom.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Lozano, then thirty-two years of age, had<lb break="yes"/>never remarked till that day that he had<lb break="yes"/>milk: but the irritation of the nipple, sucked<lb break="yes"/>by the child, caused the accumulation of<lb break="yes"/>that liquid. The milk was thick and very<lb break="yes"/>sweet. The father, astonished at the in-<lb break="no"/>creased size of his breast, suckled his child<lb break="yes"/>two or three times a day during five months.<lb break="yes"/>He drew on himself the attention of his<lb break="yes"/>neighbors, but he never thought, as he pro-<lb break="no" />bably would in Europe, of deriving any ad-<lb break="no"/>vantage, from the curiosity he excited. We<lb break="yes"/>saw the certificate which had been drawn<lb break="yes"/>up on the spot, to attest this remarkable<lb break="yes"/>fact, eye-witnesses of which are still living.<lb break="yes" />They assured us, that during this suckling,<lb break="yes"/>the child had no other nourishment than the<lb break="yes"/>milk of his father. Lozano, who was not at<lb break="yes"/>Arenas during our journey in the Missions,<lb break="yes" />came to us at Cumana. He was accompan-<lb break="no"/>ied by his son, who was then thirteen or<lb break="yes"/>fourteen years of age. <choice>
                        <sic>Mr. Benpland</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Mr. Bonpland</corr>
                    </choice> exam-<lb break="no"/>ined with attention the father&#x2019;s breast, and<lb break="yes"/>found it wrinkled like those of a woman who<lb break="yes"/>had given suck. He observed, that the<lb break="yes"/>left breast in particular was much enlarged;<lb break="yes"/>which Lozano explained to us from the cir-<lb break="no"/>cumstance, that the two breasts did not fur-<lb break="no"/>nish milk in the same abundance. Don Vi-<lb break="no" />cente Emparan, governor of the province,<lb break="yes"/>sent a circumstantial account of this pheno-<lb break="no"/>menon to Cadiz.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is not a very uncommon circumstance,<lb break="yes"/>to find, both among human kind and animals,<lb break="yes"/>males whose breast contain milk; and the<lb break="yes"/>climate does not appear to extort any mark-<lb break="no"/>ed influence on the more or less abundance<lb break="yes"/>of this secretion. The ancients cite the<lb break="yes"/>milk of the he-goats of Lemnos and Corsica.<lb break="yes"/>In our own time we have in the county of<lb break="yes" />Hanover, a he-goat, which for a great num-<lb break="no"/>ber of years was milked every other day,<lb break="yes"/>and yielded more milk than a female goat.<lb break="yes"/>Among the signs of the pretended weakness<lb break="yes"/>of the Americans, travellers have mention-<lb break="no"/><cb/>ed the milk contained in the breasts of men.<lb break="yes"/>It is however improbable, that it has ever<lb break="yes"/>been observed in a whole tribe, in some part<lb break="yes"/>of America unknown to modern travellers;<lb break="yes"/>and I can affirm, that at present it is not<lb break="yes" />more common in the new continent, than in<lb break="yes"/><choice><sic>in</sic><corr type="editorial"></corr></choice> the old. The <choice><sic>labour</sic><corr type="editorial">labourer</corr></choice> of Arenas whose<lb break="yes"/>history we have just related, is not of the<lb break="yes"/>copper-coloured race of Chayma Indians,<lb break="yes" />he is a white man descended from Euro-<lb break="no"/>peans. Moreover, the anatomists of Peters-<lb break="no"/>burg have observed, that among the lower<lb break="yes"/>orders of the people in Russia, milk in the<lb break="yes" />breasts of men is much more frequent than<lb break="yes"/>among the more southern nations; and the<lb break="yes"/>Russians have never been deemed weak and<lb break="yes"/>effeminate.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There exists among the varieties of our kind<lb break="yes"/>a race of men, whose breasts at the age of pu-<lb break="no"/>berty acquire a considerable bulk. Lozano<lb break="yes"/>did not belong to this class; and he often<lb break="yes"/>repeated to us, that it was only the irritation<lb break="yes" />of the nipple, in consequence of the suction,<lb break="yes"/>which caused the flow of milk. This con-<lb break="no"/>firms the observation of the ancients, &#x201C;that<lb break="yes"/>men, who have a small quantity of milk,<lb break="yes"/>yield it in abundance, when their breasts are<lb break="yes" />sucked.&#x201D; These singular effects of a ner-<lb break="no"/>vous stimulant were known to the shepherds<lb break="yes"/>of Greece; those of Mount Octa rubbed the<lb break="yes"/>dugs of the young goats, that had not yet<lb break="yes"/>conceived, with nettles, to make them pro-<lb break="no"/>duce milk.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When we reflect on the whole of the vital<lb break="yes"/>phenomena, we find, that one of them is en-<lb break="no"/>tirely isolated. In every age examples are<lb break="yes"/>cited of young girls not marriageable, or<lb break="yes" />women withered by age, who have suckled<lb break="yes"/>children. Among men these examples are<lb break="yes"/>infinitely more rare: after numerous re-<lb break="no"/>searches, I have not found above two or<lb break="yes"/>three. One is cited by the anatomist of<lb break="yes"/>Verona, Alexander Benedictus, who lived<lb break="yes"/>toward the end of the fifteenth century. He<lb break="yes"/>relates the history of an inhabitant of Syria,<lb break="yes" />who, to calm the uneasiness of his child,<lb break="yes"/>after the death of the mother, pressed it to<lb break="yes"/>his bosom. The milk immediately came<lb break="yes"/>with such abundance, that the father could<lb break="yes"/>take on himself the nourishment of his child<lb break="yes" />without assistance. Other examples are<lb break="yes"/>related by Santorellus, Paria, and Robert,<lb break="yes"/>bishop of Cork. The greater part of the<lb break="yes"/>phenomena having been noted in times very<lb break="yes" />remote, it is not uninteresting to physiology<lb break="yes"/>that we can confirm them in our own days.<lb break="yes"/>Besides, they bear very strongly on the long<lb break="yes"/>disputed question respecting final causes.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>The existence of the nipple in men has long<lb break="yes"/>puzzled philosophers; and it has even been<lb break="yes"/>recently affirmed, that nature has refused to<lb break="yes" />one of the sexes the faculty of suckling be-<lb break="no"/>cause this faculty would not accord with the<lb break="yes"/>dignity of man.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 