<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="117" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">the great cavern of guacharo, in south america.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">Abridged from the Personal Narrative of Humboldt, vol. iii.</note>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In a country where the people love what is marvellous,<lb break="yes"/>a cavern that gives birth to a river, and is inhabited by<lb break="yes"/>thousands of nocturnal birds, the fat of which is employed<lb break="yes"/>in the Missions to dress food, is an everlasting object of<lb break="yes"/>conversation and discussion. Scarcely has a stranger ar-<lb break="no"/>rived at Cumana, when he is told of the stone of Araya<lb break="yes"/>for the eyes; of the labourer of Arenas who suckled his<lb break="yes"/>child; and of the <hi rendition="#k">Cavern</hi> of <hi rendition="#k">Guacharo,</hi> which is said to<lb break="yes"/>be several leagues in length; till he is tired of hearing of<lb break="yes"/>them.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Cueva del Guacharo is pierced in the vertical pro-<lb break="no"/>file of a rock. The entrance is toward the south, and<lb break="yes"/>forms a vault eighty feet broad, and seventy-two feet<lb break="yes"/>high. The rock, that surmounts the grotto, is covered<lb break="yes"/>with trees of gigantic height. The mammee-tree, and<lb break="yes"/>the genipa with large and shining leaves, raise their<lb break="yes"/>branches vertically toward the sky; while those of the<lb break="yes"/>courbaril and the erythrina form, as they extend them-<lb break="no"/>selves, a thick vault of verdure. Plants of the family of<lb break="yes"/>pothos with succulent stems, oxalises, and orchide&#x00E6; of a<lb break="yes"/>singular structure, rise in the driest clefts of the recks;<lb break="yes"/>while creeping plants, waving in the winds, are inter-<lb break="no"/>woven in festoons before the opening of the cavern. We<lb break="yes"/>distinguished in these festoons a bignonia of a violet-blue,<lb break="yes"/>the purple dolichos, and for the first time that magnificent<lb break="yes"/>olandra, the orange flower of which has a fleshy tube more<lb break="yes"/>than four inches long. The entrances of grottoes, like<lb break="yes"/>the view of cascades, derive their principal charm from<lb break="yes"/>the situation, more or less majestic, in which they are<lb break="yes"/>placed, and which in some sort determines the character<lb break="yes"/>of the landscape. What a contrast between the Cueva of<lb break="yes"/>Caripe, and those caverns of the North crowned with<lb break="yes"/><choice><sic>aks</sic><corr type="editorial">oaks</corr></choice> and gloomy larch-trees!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But this luxury of vegetation embellishes not only the<lb break="yes"/>outside of the vault, it appears even in the vestibule of the<lb break="yes"/>grotto. We saw with astonishment plantain-leaved heli-<lb break="no"/>conias eighteen feet high, the praga palm-tree, and ar-<lb break="no"/>borescent arums, follow the banks of the river even to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="118" facs="#f0002"/>those subterranean places. The vegetation continues in<lb break="yes"/>the cave of Caripe, as in those deep crevices of the Andes,<lb break="yes"/>half excluded from the light of day; and does not dis-<lb break="no"/>appear, till, advancing in the interior, we reach thirty or<lb break="yes"/>forty paces from the entrance. We measured the way by<lb break="yes"/>means of a cord: and we went on about four hundred and<lb break="yes"/>thirty feet, without being obliged to light our torches.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Day-light penetrates into this region, because the<lb break="yes"/>grotto forms but one single channel, which keeps the<lb break="yes"/>same direction from south-east to north-west. Where the<lb break="yes"/>light begins to fail, we heard from afar the hoarse sounds<lb break="yes"/>of the nocturnal birds, sounds which the natives think<lb break="yes"/>belong exclusively to those subterraneous places. The<lb break="yes"/>guacharo is of the size of our fowls, has the mouth of the<lb break="yes"/>goatsuckers and procnias, and the port of those vulture,<lb break="yes"/>the crooked beak of which is surrounded with stiff silky<lb break="yes"/>hairs. It forms a new genus, very different from the<lb break="yes"/>goatsucker by the force of its voice, by the considerable<lb break="yes"/>strength of its beak, containing a double tooth, by its<lb break="yes"/>feet without the membranes that unite the anterior pha-<lb break="no"/>lanxes of the claws. In its manners it has analogies both<lb break="yes"/>with the goatsuckers and the alpine crow. The plumage<lb break="yes"/>of the guacharo is of a dark bluish-grey, mixed with small<lb break="yes"/>streaks and specks of black. It is difficult to form an<lb break="yes"/>idea of the horrible noise occasioned by thousands of<lb break="yes"/>these birds in the dark part of the cavern, and which can<lb break="yes"/>only be compared to the croaking of our crows, which,<lb break="yes"/>in the pine forests of the north, live in society, and con-<lb break="no"/>struct their nests upon trees, the tops of which touch<lb break="yes"/>each other. The shrill and piercing cries of the guacha-<lb break="no"/>roes strike upon the vaults of the rocks, and are repeated<lb break="yes"/>by the echo in the depth of the cavern. The Indians<lb break="yes"/>shewed us the nests of these birds, by fixing torches to<lb break="yes"/>the end of a long pole. These nests were fifty or sixty<lb break="yes"/>feet high above our heads, in holes in the shape of fun-<lb break="no"/>nels, with which the roof of the grotto <choice><sic>pierced</sic><corr type="editorial">is pierced</corr></choice> like a<lb break="yes"/>sieve. The noise increased as we advanced, and the birds<lb break="yes"/>were affrighted by the light of the orches of copal.<lb break="yes"/>When this noise ceased around us, we heard at a distance<lb break="yes"/>the plaintive cries of the birds roosting in other ramifi-<lb break="no"/>cations of the cavern. It seemed as if these bands an-<lb break="no"/>swered each other alternately.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="119" facs="#f0003"/>
                <p>The Indians enter into the Cueva del Guacharo once<lb break="yes"/>a-year, near midsummer, armed with poles, by means of<lb break="yes"/>which they destroy the greater part of the nests. At this<lb break="yes"/>season several thousands of birds are killed; and the old<lb break="yes"/>ones, to defend their brood, hover around the heads of<lb break="yes"/>the savage Indians, uttering terrible cries, which would<lb break="yes"/>appal any heart but that of man in an untutored state.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We followed, as we continued our progress through the<lb break="yes"/>cavern, the banks of the small river which issued from it,<lb break="yes"/>and is from twenty-eight to thirty feet wide. We walked<lb break="yes"/>on the banks, as far as the hills formed of calcareous in-<lb break="no"/>crustations permitted us. When the torrent winds among<lb break="yes"/>very high masses of stalactites, we were often obliged to<lb break="yes"/>descend into its bed, which is only two feet in depth.<lb break="yes"/>We learnt, with surprise, that this subterraneous rivulet<lb break="yes"/>is the origin of the river Caripe, which, at a few leagues<lb break="yes"/>distance, after having joined the small river of Santa<lb break="yes"/>Maria, is navigable for canoes. It enters into the river<lb break="yes"/>Areo under the name of <hi rendition="#i">Canno de Terezen.</hi> We found<lb break="yes"/>on the banks of the subterraneous rivulet a great quantity<lb break="yes"/>of palm-tree wood, the remains of trunks, on which the<lb break="yes"/>Indians climb to reach the nests hanging to the roofs of<lb break="yes"/>the cavern. The rings, formed by the vestiges of the old<lb break="yes"/>footstalks of the leaves, furnish as it were the footsteps of<lb break="yes"/>a ladder perpendicularly placed.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Grotto of Caripe preserves the same direction, the<lb break="yes"/>same breadth, and its primitive height of sixty or seventy<lb break="yes"/>feet, to the distance of 1458 feet, accurately measured.<lb break="yes"/>I have never seen a cavern in either continent, of so uni-<lb break="no"/>form and regular a construction. We had great difficulty<lb break="yes"/>in persuading the Indians to pass beyond the outer part<lb break="yes"/>of the grotto, the only part which they annually visit to<lb break="yes"/>collect the fat. The whole authority of <hi rendition="#i">los padres</hi> was<lb break="yes"/>necessary, to induce them to advance as far as the spot<lb break="yes"/>where the soil rises abruptly at an inclination of sixty de-<lb break="no"/>grees, and where the torrent forms a small subterraneous<lb break="yes"/>cascade.<note place="foot" n="*">We find this phenomenon of a subterranean cascade, but on<lb break="yes"/>much large scale, in England, at Yordas Cave, near Kingsdale, in<lb break="yes" />Yorkshire.</note> The natives connect mystic ideas with this<lb break="yes"/>cave, inhabited by nocturnal birds; they believe, that the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="120" facs="#f0004"/>souls of their ancestors sojourn in the deep recesses of the<lb break="yes"/>cavern. &#x201C;Man,&#x201D; say they, &#x201C;should avoid places which<lb break="yes"/>are enlightened neither by the Sun nor by the Moon<choice><sic>,</sic><corr type="editorial">.</corr></choice>&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>To go and join the guacharoes, is to rejoin their fathers,<lb break="yes"/>is to die. The magicians and the poisoners perform their<lb break="yes"/>nocturnal tricks at the entrance of the cavern, to conjure<lb break="yes"/>the chief of the evil spirits.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the point where the river forms the subterraneous<lb break="yes"/>cascade, a hill covered with vegetation, which is opposite<lb break="yes"/>the opening of the grotto, presents itself in a very pic-<lb break="no"/>turesque manner. It appears at the extremity of a straight<lb break="yes"/>passage, 240 toises in length. The stalactites, which de-<lb break="no"/>scend from the vault, and which resemble columns sus-<lb break="no"/>pended in the air, display themselves on a back-ground<lb break="yes"/>of verdure. The opening of the cavern appeared singu-<lb break="no"/>larly contracted, when we saw it about the middle of the<lb break="yes"/>day, illumined by the vivid light reflected at once from<lb break="yes"/>the sky, the plants, and the rocks. The distant light of<lb break="yes"/>day formed somewhat of magical contrast with the dark-<lb break="no"/>ness that surrounded us in those vast caverns. We<lb break="yes" />climbed, not without some difficulty, the small hill, whence<lb break="yes" />the subterraneous rivulet descends. We saw that the<lb break="yes"/>grotto was <choice><sic>perceptibiy</sic><corr type="editorial">perceptibly</corr></choice> contracted, retaining only forty<lb break="yes"/>feet in height; and that it continued stretching to the<lb break="yes"/>north-east, without deviating from its primitive direction,<lb break="yes"/>which is parallel to that of the great valley of Caripe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The missionaries, with all their authority, could not<lb break="yes"/>prevail on the Indians to penetrate farther into the ca-<lb break="no"/>vern. As the vault grew lower, the cries of the guacha-<lb break="no"/>roes became more shrill. We were obliged to yield to the<lb break="yes"/>pusillanimity of our guides, and trace back our steps. We<lb break="yes"/>followed the course of the torrent to go out of the cavern.<lb break="yes"/>Before our eyes were dazzled with the light of day, we<lb break="yes"/>saw, without the grotto, the water of the river sparkling<lb break="yes"/>amid the foliage of the trees that concealed it. It was like<lb break="yes"/>a picture placed in the distance, and to which the mouth<lb break="yes"/>of the cavern served as a frame. Having at length reached<lb break="yes"/>the entrance, and seated ourselves on the bank of the ri-<lb break="no"/>vulet, we rested after our fatigues. We were glad to be<lb break="yes"/>beyond the hoarse cries of the birds, and to leave a place<lb break="yes"/>where darkness does not offer even the charm of silence<lb break="yes"/>and tranquillity.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 