<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="354" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>VEGETABLE SUBSTANCES&#x2014;THE COW TREE.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">Mr. Humboldt, in his Personal Narrative gives the following<lb break="yes"/>account of this wonder of the vegetable world.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Amid the great number of curious phenomena which<lb break="yes"/>have presented themselves to me in the course of my<lb break="yes"/>travels, I confess there are few that have so powerfully<lb break="yes"/>affected my imagination, as the aspect of the <hi rendition="#i">cow tree</hi>&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Whatever regards corn, inspires an interest, which is<lb break="yes"/>not merely that of the physical knowledge of things, but<lb break="yes"/>is connected with another order of ideas and sentiments.<lb break="yes"/>We can scarcely conceive how the human race could<lb break="yes"/>exist without farinaceous substances, and without that<lb break="yes"/>nourishing juice which the breast of the mother contains,<lb break="yes"/>and which is appropriated to the long feebleness of the<lb break="yes"/>infant. The amylaceous matter of corn, the object of<lb break="yes"/>religious veneration among so many nations, ancient and<lb break="yes"/>modern, is diffused in the seeds and deposited in the<lb break="yes"/>roots of vegetables&#x2014;milk, which serves us as an ali-<lb break="no"/>ment, appears to us exclusively the produce of animal<lb break="yes"/>organization. Such are the impressions we have receiv-<lb break="no"/>ed in our earliest infancy; such is also the source of<lb break="yes"/>that astonishment which seizes us at the aspect of the<lb break="yes"/>tree just described. It is not here the solemn shades of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="355" facs="#f0002"/>forests, the majestic course of rivers, the mountains<lb break="yes"/>wrapped in eternal frosts, that excite our emotion. A<lb break="yes"/>few drops of vegetable juice recall to our minds all the<lb break="yes"/>powerfulness and fecundity of nature. On the barren<lb break="yes"/>flank of a rock grows a tree with coriaceous and dry<lb break="yes"/>leaves. Its large woody roots can scarcely penetrate<lb break="yes"/>into the stone. For several months of the year not a<lb break="yes"/>single shower moistens its foliage. Its branches appear<lb break="yes"/>dead and dried; but when its trunk is pierced, there<lb break="yes"/>flows from it a sweet and nourishing milk. It is at the<lb break="yes"/>rising of the sun that this vegetable fountain is most<lb break="yes"/>abundant. The blacks and natives are then seen<lb break="yes" />hastening from all quarters; furnished with large bowls<lb break="yes"/>to receive the milk, which grows yellow, and thickens<lb break="yes"/>at its surface. Some employ their bowls under the<lb break="yes"/>tree itself, others carry the juice home to their children.<lb break="yes"/>We seem to see the family of a shepherd, who distri-<lb break="no"/>butes the milk to his flock.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have described the sensation which the cow tree<lb break="yes"/>awakes in the mind of the traveller, at the first view. In<lb break="yes"/>examining the physical properties of animal and vegeta-<lb break="no"/>ble products, science displays them as closely linked<lb break="yes"/>together; but it strips them of what is marvellous, and<lb break="yes"/>perhaps also of a part of their charms, of what excited<lb break="yes"/>our astonishment. Nothing appears isolated, the chemi-<lb break="no"/>cal principles that were believed to be peculiar to<lb break="yes"/>animals are found in plants, a common chain links<lb break="yes"/>together all organic nature.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 