<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="646" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Personal Narrative of Travels in the Equinoctial<lb break="yes"/>Regions of <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">South America,</hi>
                        </hi> during the Years</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>1799&#x2014;1804,</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">by <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">Alexander de Humboldt,</hi>
                        </hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>and <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">Aime Bonpland.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I <hi rendition="#k">landed</hi> (says M. de Humboldt,) in the Port of La<lb break="yes"/>Guayra, and the same evening made preparations for<lb break="yes"/>transporting my instruments to Caraccas. La Guayra<lb break="yes"/>is rather a roadstead than a port. The sea is con-<lb break="no"/>stantly agitated, and the ships suffer at once by the ac-<lb break="no"/>tion of the wind, the tideways, the bad anchorage, and<lb break="yes"/>the worms. The lading is taken in with difficulty, and<lb break="yes"/>the height of the swell prevents embarking mules here,<lb break="yes"/>as at New Barcelona and Porto Cabello. The free Mu-<lb break="no"/>lattoes and Negroes, who carry the cacao on-board the<lb break="yes"/>ships, are a class of men of very remarkable muscular<lb break="yes"/>strength. They go up to their middles through the<lb break="yes"/>water; and, what is well worthy of attention, they have<lb break="yes"/>nothing to fear from the sharks, which are so frequent in<lb break="yes"/>this harbour. The fact seems connected with what I<lb break="yes"/>have often observed between the tropics, relatively to<lb break="yes"/>other classes of animals, that live in society; for instance,<lb break="yes"/>monkeys and crocodiles. In the missions of the Oroo-<lb break="no"/>noko, and the river of Amazons, the Indians who catch<lb break="yes"/>monkeys to sell them, know very well, that they can easily<lb break="yes"/>succeed in taming those which inhabit certain islands;<lb break="yes"/>while monkeys, of the same species, caught on the<lb break="yes"/>neighbouring continent, die of terror or rage, when they<lb break="yes"/>find themselves in the power of man. The crocodiles<lb break="yes"/>of one pool in the Llanos are cowardly, and flee even in<lb break="yes"/>the water; while those of another attack with extreme<lb break="yes"/>intrepidity. It would be difficult to explain this dif-<lb break="no"/>ference of manners and habits, by the aspect of their<lb break="yes"/>respective localities. The sharks of the port La Guayra<lb break="yes"/>seem to furnish an analogous example. They are dange-<lb break="no"/>rous and blood-thirsty, at the island opposite the coast of<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas, at the Roques, at Bonayre, and at Curassao:<lb break="yes"/>while they forbear to attack persons swimming in the<lb break="yes"/>ports of La Guayra and Santa Martha.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="647" facs="#f0002"/>
                <p>The situation of La Guayra is very singular, and can<lb break="yes"/>only be compared to that of Santa Cruz in Teneriffe.<lb break="yes"/>The chain of mountains, that separates the port from the<lb break="yes"/>high valley of Caraccas, descends almost directly into<lb break="yes"/>the sea; and the houses of the town are backed by a wall<lb break="yes"/>of steep rocks. There scarcely remains one hundred or<lb break="yes"/>one hundred and forty toises breadth of flat ground be-<lb break="no"/>tween the wall and the ocean. The town has six or eight<lb break="yes"/>thousand inhabitants, and contains only two streets,<lb break="yes"/>running parallel to each other east and west. It is com-<lb break="no"/>manded by a battery of <hi rendition="#i">Cerro colorado;</hi> and its fortifi-<lb break="no"/>cations along the seaside are well disposed, and kept in<lb break="yes"/>repair. The aspect of this place has something solitary<lb break="yes"/>and gloomy; we seemed not to be on a continent, cover-<lb break="no"/>ed with vast forests, but in a rocky island, destitute of<lb break="yes"/>mould and vegetation. With the exception of Cape<lb break="yes"/>Blanco, and the cocoa-trees of Maiquetia, no view meets<lb break="yes"/>the eye but that of the horizon, the sea, and the azure<lb break="yes"/>vault of heaven. The heat is trifling during the day, and<lb break="yes"/>most frequently during the night. The climate of La<lb break="yes"/>Guayra is justly considered as more ardent than that of<lb break="yes"/>Cumana, Porto Cabello, and Coro; because the sea-<lb break="no" />breeze is less felt, and the air is heated by the radiant<lb break="yes" />caloric, which the perpendicular rocks emit from the<lb break="yes"/>time the sun sets.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The examination of the thermometric observations,<lb break="yes"/>made during nine months at La Guayra by a distinguish-<lb break="no"/>ed physician, enabled me to compare the climate of this<lb break="yes"/>port, and that of Cumana, the Havannah, and Vera Cruz.<lb break="yes"/>These four places are considered as the hottest on the<lb break="yes"/>shores of the New World. The mean of the observations<lb break="yes"/>made at noon, from the 27th of June to the 16th of<lb break="yes"/>November, were, at La Guayra, 103&#x00B0;; at Cumano, 98&#x00B0;;<lb break="yes"/>at Vera Cruz, 96&#x00B0;; at Havannah, 98.5&#x00B0;. The mean of<lb break="yes"/>the whole year, according to good observations, carefully<lb break="yes"/>calculated, is, at La Guayra nearly 95.5&#x00B0;; at Cumana,<lb break="yes"/>94&#x00B0;; at Vera Cruz, 89.5&#x00B0;; at the Havannah, 89.6&#x00B0;; at<lb break="yes"/>Cairo, 83.5&#x00B0;; at Rome, 67&#x00B0;. From the whole of these<lb break="yes"/>observations it follows, that La Guayra is one of the<lb break="yes"/>hottest places on the earth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The road that leads from La Guayra to Caraccas,<lb break="yes"/>resembles the passages over the Alps. It is even impossible<lb break="yes"/>to form a precise idea of the elevation of Caraccas from<lb break="yes"/>the climate of the valley. The air in it is cooled by the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="648" facs="#f0003"/>descending currents of air; and by the fogs, which envelop<lb break="yes"/>the lofty summit of the Silla during a great part of the<lb break="yes"/>year.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When in the seasons of the great heats we breathe the<lb break="yes"/>burning atmosphere of La Guayra, and turn our eyes<lb break="yes"/>toward the mountains, we are strongly affected by the idea,<lb break="yes"/>that, at the direct distance of 10 or 20 thousand yards, a<lb break="yes"/>population of forty thousand souls, assembled in a narrow<lb break="yes"/>valley, enjoys all the coolness of spring, of a temperature<lb break="yes"/>which, at night, descends to 59&#x00B0;. This near approach of<lb break="yes"/>different climates is common in the Cordilleras of the<lb break="yes"/>Andes; but every where at Mexico, at Quito, in Peru, and<lb break="yes"/>in New Grenada, a long journey must be made into the<lb break="yes"/>interior, either by the plains, or by proceeding up the<lb break="yes"/>rivers, in order to reach the great cities, which are the<lb break="yes"/>centres of the civilization. The height of Caraccas is but<lb break="yes"/>a third of that of Mexico, Quito, and Santa Fe de Bogota;<lb break="yes"/>yet, among all the capitals of Spanish America, which<lb break="yes"/>enjoy a cool and delicious climate in the midst of the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone, Caraccas stands nearest to the coast. What<lb break="yes"/>a privilege, to possess a sea-port at three leagues distance,<lb break="yes"/>and to be situate among mountains, on a table-land, which<lb break="yes"/>would produce wheat, if the cultivation of the coffee-tree<lb break="yes"/>were not preferred!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The road from La Guayra to the valley of Caraccas, is<lb break="yes"/>infinitely finer than that from Honda to Santa Fe, or that<lb break="yes"/>from Guayaquil to Quito. It is even kept in better<lb break="yes"/>order than the ancient road, which led from the port of<lb break="yes"/>Vera Cruz to Perote, on the eastern declivity of the moun-<lb break="no"/>tains of New Spain. With good mules, it requires but<lb break="yes"/>three hours to go from the port of La Guayra to Caraccas;<lb break="yes"/>and only two hours to return. With loaded mules, or on<lb break="yes"/>foot, the journey is from four to five hours. The ascent<lb break="yes"/>begins with a ridge of rocks extremely steep, and stations<lb break="yes"/>that bear the name of Torrequemada, Curucuti, and Salto,<lb break="yes"/>to a large inn (La Venta) built at six hundred toises above<lb break="yes"/>the level of the sea. The denomination of the burnt<lb break="yes"/>Tower indicates the sensation that is felt in descending<lb break="yes"/>toward La Guayra. A suffocating heat is reflected by the<lb break="yes"/>walls of rock, and still more by the barren plains, on which<lb break="yes"/>the traveller looks down.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When I passed for the first time that table-land, on my<lb break="yes"/>way to the capital of Venezuela, I found several travellers<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="649" facs="#f0004"/>assembled round the little inn of Guayavo, to rest their<lb break="yes"/>mules. They were inhabitants of Caraccas, and were dis-<lb break="no"/>puting on the efforts toward independence which had been<lb break="yes"/>made a short time before. Joseph Espana had perished on<lb break="yes"/>the scaffold; and his wife groaned in a prison, because she<lb break="yes"/>had given an asylum to her husband when a fugitive, and<lb break="yes"/>had not denounced him to the government. I was struck<lb break="yes"/>with the agitation which prevailed in every mind, and the<lb break="yes"/>bitterness with which questions were debated, on which<lb break="yes"/>men of the same country ought not to have differed in<lb break="yes"/>opinion. While they descanted on the hatred of the Mu-<lb break="no"/>lattoes against the free negroes and whites, on the wealth<lb break="yes"/>of the monks, and the difficulty of holding slaves in obe-<lb break="no"/>dience, a cold wind, that seemed to descend from the<lb break="yes"/>lofty summit of the Silla of Caraccas, enveloped us with a<lb break="yes"/>thick fog, and put an end to this animated conversation.<lb break="yes"/>We sought for shelter in the Venta del Guayavo. When<lb break="yes"/>we entered the inn, an old man, who had spoken with the<lb break="yes"/>utmost calmness, reminded the others how imprudent it was,<lb break="yes"/>in a time of denunciation, on the mountain as well as in the<lb break="yes"/>city, to engage in political discussions. These words,<lb break="yes"/>uttered in a spot of so wild an aspect, made a lively im-<lb break="no"/>pression on my mind; which was often renewed during<lb break="yes"/>our journeys in the Andes of New Grenada and Peru. In<lb break="yes"/>Europe, where nations decide their quarrels in the plains,<lb break="yes"/>we clime the mountains in search of solitude and liberty.<lb break="yes"/>In the New World, the Cordilleras are inhabited to the<lb break="yes"/>height of twelve thousand feet; and thither men carry<lb break="yes"/>with them their political dissentions, and their little and<lb break="yes"/>hateful passions.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Caraccas is the capital of a country, which is nearly<lb break="yes"/>twice as large as Peru at present, and which yields little in<lb break="yes"/>extent to the kingdom of New Grenada. This country,<lb break="yes"/>which the Spanish government designates by the name of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Capitania General de Caraccas,</hi> or of the (united) pro-<lb break="no"/>vinces of Venezuela, has nearly a million of inhabitants,<lb break="yes"/>among whom are sixty thousand slaves. It contains along<lb break="yes"/>the coast, New Andalusia, or the province of Cumana (with<lb break="yes"/>the island of Margaretta), Barcelona, Venezuela or Ca-<lb break="no"/>raccas, Coro, and Maracaybo; in the interior, the provin-<lb break="no"/>ces of Varinas and Guiana, the first along the rivers of<lb break="yes"/>Santo Domingo and the Apure, the second along the<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko, and Casiquiare, the Atabapo, and the Rio<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="650" facs="#f0005"/>Negro. In a general view of the seven united provinces of<lb break="yes"/>Terra Firma, we perceive, that they form three distinct<lb break="yes"/>zones, extending from east to west.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Caraccas is the seat of an <hi rendition="#i">audiencia</hi> (high court of justice)<lb break="yes"/>and one of the eight archbishoprics into which Spanish<lb break="yes"/>America is divided.<note place="foot" n="*">It is now (in 1822) the capital of the republic of Columbia.</note> Its population in 1800, according<lb break="yes"/>to the researches I made into the number of births, was<lb break="yes"/>nearly 40,000; the best informed inhabitants believed it<lb break="yes"/>even to be 45,000, of which 18,000 are whites, and 27,000<lb break="yes"/>free men of colour. Computations, made in 1778, had<lb break="yes"/>already given from 30,000 to 32,000. All the direct<lb break="yes"/>numberings have remained a quarter, and more, below the<lb break="yes"/>effective number. In 1766, the population of Caraccas,<lb break="yes"/>and the fine valley in which that city is placed, suffered<lb break="yes"/>immensely by a severe attack of the small-pox. The<lb break="yes"/>mortality rose in the town to six or eight thousand. Since<lb break="yes"/>that memorable period, inoculation is become general, and I<lb break="yes"/>have seen it practised without the aid of physicians. In<lb break="yes"/>the province of Cumana, where the communications with<lb break="yes"/>Europe are less frequent, there had not been, in my time,<lb break="yes"/>one instance of the small-pox during fifteen years; while,<lb break="yes"/>at Caraccas, that cruel malady was constantly dreaded,<lb break="yes"/>because it always showed itself sporadically on several<lb break="yes"/>points at a time. I say sporadically, for in Equinoctial<lb break="yes"/>America, where the changes of atmosphere, and the phe-<lb break="no"/>nomena of organic life, seem subject to a remarkable<lb break="yes"/>periodicalness, the small-pox, before the benevolent intro-<lb break="no"/>duction of the vaccine disease, exerted its ravages only, if<lb break="yes"/>we may place confidence in general belief, every fifteen or<lb break="yes"/>twenty years. Since my return to Europe, the population<lb break="yes"/>of Caraccas has continued to augment. It amounted to<lb break="yes"/>50,000 souls; when, at the great earthquake of the 26th<lb break="yes"/>of March, 1812, twelve thousand inhabitants perished be-<lb break="no"/>neath the ruins of their houses.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The town is seated at the entrance of the plain of Cha-<lb break="no"/>cao, which extends three leagues east towards Caurimare<lb break="yes"/>and the Cuesta de Auyamas, and which is two leagues and<lb break="yes"/>a half in breadth. This plain, through which runs the Rio<lb break="yes"/>Guayra, is four hundred and fourteen toises in height above<lb break="yes"/>the level of the sea. The ground, which the town of Ca-<lb break="no"/>raccas occupies, is uneven, and has a steep slope from<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="651" facs="#f0006"/>N. N. W. to S. S. E. In order to form an exact idea of the<lb break="yes"/>situation of Caraccas, we must recollect the general dis-<lb break="no"/>position of the mountains of the coast, and the great<lb break="yes"/>longitudinal valleys, by which they were traversed. The<lb break="yes"/>Guayra rises in the group of primitive mountains of Higue-<lb break="no"/>rota, which separates the valley of Caraccas from that of<lb break="yes"/>Aragua. It is formed near Las Ajuntas by the junction of<lb break="yes"/>the little rivers of San Pedro and Macarao, and runs first<lb break="yes"/>to the east as far as the Cuesta of Auyamas, and then to<lb break="yes"/>the south, to unite its waters with those of Rio Tuy, below<lb break="yes"/>Yare. The Rio Tuy is the only considerable river in the<lb break="yes"/>northern and mountainous part of the province.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The climate of Caraccas has often been called a per-<lb break="no"/>petual spring. It is found every where, half-way up the<lb break="yes"/>Cordilleras of Equinoctial America, between four hundred<lb break="yes"/>and nine hundred toises of elevation, unless the great<lb break="yes"/>breadth of the valley, joined to an arid soil, causes an ex-<lb break="no"/>traordinary intensity of radiant caloric. What indeed can<lb break="yes"/>we imagine more delightful than a temperature, which in<lb break="yes"/>the day keeps between 77&#x00B0; and 90.5&#x00B0;; and at night be-<lb break="no"/>tween 68&#x00B0; and 75&#x00B0;, which is equally favourable to the<lb break="yes"/>plantain (cambury), the orange-tree, the coffee-tree, the<lb break="yes"/>apple, the apricot, and corn! A national writer compares<lb break="yes"/>the situation of Caraccas to the terrestrial Paradise, and<lb break="yes"/>recognizes in the Anauco and the neighbouring torrents,<lb break="yes"/>the four rivers of the garden of Eden.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The cool and delightful climate we have been describ-<lb break="no"/>ing, agrees also with the culture of equinoctial productions.<lb break="yes"/>The sugar-cane is cultivated with success, even at heights<lb break="yes"/>exceeding that of Caraccas; but in the valley, on account<lb break="yes"/>of the dryness of the climate, and the stony soil, the cul-<lb break="no"/>tivation of the coffee-tree is preferred; which there yields<lb break="yes"/>little fruit indeed, but of the finest quality. When the<lb break="yes"/>shrub is in blossom, the plain extending beyond Chacao<lb break="yes"/>presents a delightful aspect. The banana-tree, which is<lb break="yes"/>seen in the plantations near the town, is not the great<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">plantano harton</hi>; but the varieties <hi rendition="#i">camburi</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">dominico,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>which require less heat. The great plantations are brought<lb break="yes"/>to the market of Caraccas from the haciendos of Turiamo,<lb break="yes"/>situate on the coast between Burburata and Porto Cabello.<lb break="yes"/>The highest flavoured pine-apples are those of Baruto, of<lb break="yes"/>Empedrado, and of the heights of Buenavista, on the road<lb break="yes"/>to Victoria. When a traveller ascends, for the first time,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="652" facs="#f0007"/>to the valley of Caraccas, he is agreeably surprised to find<lb break="yes"/>the culinary plants of our climate, the strawberry, the vine,<lb break="yes"/>and almost all the fruit-trees of the temperate zone, grow-<lb break="no"/>ing by the side of the coffee and banana-tree. The apples<lb break="yes"/>and peaches esteemed the best come from Macaroa, or<lb break="yes"/>from the western extremity of the valley. There, the<lb break="yes"/>quince-tree, the trunk of which attains only four or five<lb break="yes"/>feet in height, is so common, that it is almost become wild.<lb break="yes"/>Preserved apples and quinces, particularly the latter, are<lb break="yes"/>much used in a country, where it is thought that, to drink<lb break="yes"/>water, thirst must previously be excited by sweetmeats.<lb break="yes"/>In proportion as the environs of the town have been culti-<lb break="no"/>vated with coffee; and the establishment of plantations,<lb break="yes"/>which dates only from the year 1795, has increased the<lb break="yes"/>number of agricultural negroes; the apple and quince-trees,<lb break="yes"/>scattered in the savannahs, have given place, in the valley<lb break="yes"/>of Caraccas, to maize and pulse.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Civilization has in no other part of Spanish America as-<lb break="no"/>sumed a more European physiognomy. The great number<lb break="yes"/>of Indian cultivators, who inhabit Mexico and the interior<lb break="yes"/>of New Grenada, have impressed a peculiar, I might also<lb break="yes"/>say an exotic, character, on those vast countries. Notwith-<lb break="no"/>standing the increase of the black population, we seem to<lb break="yes"/>be nearer Cadiz and the United States at Caraccas and the<lb break="yes"/>Havannah, than in any other part of the New World.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I found in several families at Caraccas a taste for in-<lb break="no"/>struction, a knowledge of the master-pieces of French and<lb break="yes"/>Italian literature, and a particular predilection for music,<lb break="yes"/>which is cultivated with success, and which, as it always<lb break="yes"/>happen in the pursuit of the fine arts, serves to bring the<lb break="yes"/>different classes of society nearer to each other. The ma-<lb break="no"/>thematical sciences, drawing, and painting, cannot here boast<lb break="yes"/>of any of those establishments, with which royal munifi-<lb break="no"/>cence, and the patriotic zeal of the inhabitants, have<lb break="yes"/>enriched Mexico. In the midst of the marvels of nature,<lb break="yes"/>so rich in productions, no person on this coast was devoted<lb break="yes"/>to the study of plants and minerals. In a convent of St.<lb break="yes"/>Francis alone I met with a respectable old gentleman, who<lb break="yes"/>calculated the almanac for all the provinces of Venezuela,<lb break="yes"/>and who possessed some precise ideas on the state of modern<lb break="yes"/>astronomy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In describing the great earthquake at Cumana, Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt says, that, from the 28th of October to the 3d<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="653" facs="#f0008"/>of November, a reddish fog was thicker than it had yet<lb break="yes"/>been. The heat of the night seemed stifling, though the<lb break="yes"/>thermometer rose only to 91&#x00B0;. The breeze, which gene-<lb break="no"/>rally cooled the air from eight or nine o&#x2019;clock in the even-<lb break="no"/>ing, was no longer felt. The atmosphere appeared as if it<lb break="yes"/>were on fire. The ground, parched and dusty, was cracked<lb break="yes"/>on every side. On the fourth of November, about two<lb break="yes"/>in the afternoon, large clouds, of an extraordinary black-<lb break="no"/>ness, enveloped the high mountains of the Brigantine and<lb break="yes"/>Tataraqual. They extended, by degrees, as far as the<lb break="yes"/>zenith. About four in the afternoon, thunder was heard,<lb break="yes"/>over our heads, but at an immense height, without rolling,<lb break="yes"/>and with a hoarse and often interrupted sound. At the<lb break="yes"/>moment of the strongest electric explosion, at 4h. 12m.<lb break="yes"/>there were two shocks of an earthquake, which followed at<lb break="yes"/>fifteen seconds distance from each other. The people in<lb break="yes"/>the streets filled the air with their cries. M. Bonpland,<lb break="yes"/>who was leaning over a table examining plants, was almost<lb break="yes"/>thrown on the floor. I felt this shock very strongly,<lb break="yes"/>though I was lying in a hammock. Its direction was from<lb break="yes"/>north to south, which is rare at Cumana. Slaves, who<lb break="yes"/>were drawing water from a well, more than eighteen or<lb break="yes"/>twenty feet deep, near the river Manzanares, heard a noise<lb break="yes"/>like the explosion of a strong charge of gunpowder. The<lb break="yes"/>noise seemed to come from the bottom of the well. About<lb break="yes"/>nine in the evening there was another shock, attended with<lb break="yes"/>a subterraneous noise. The earthquake of the fourth of<lb break="yes"/>November, the first I had felt, made so much the more<lb break="yes"/>lively an impression on me, as it was accompanied with re-<lb break="no"/>markable meteorological variations. It was, moreover,<lb break="yes"/>a real lifting-up, and not a shock by undulations. I did<lb break="yes"/>not then imagine, that, after a long abode on the table-<lb break="no"/>lands of Quito, and the coasts of Peru, I should become<lb break="yes"/>almost as familiar with the abrupt movements of the ground,<lb break="yes"/>as we are in Europe with the noise of thunder. We did<lb break="yes"/>not think of rising at night, in the city of Quito, when<lb break="yes"/>subterraneous rumblings (<hi rendition="#i">bramidos</hi>), which seem always<lb break="yes"/>to come from the volcano of Pichincha, announced (two<lb break="yes"/>or three, and sometimes seven or eight, minutes before-<lb break="no"/>hand) a shock, the force of which is seldom in proportion<lb break="yes"/>to the (intensity of the noise. The carelessness of the in-<lb break="no"/>habitants, who recollect that, for three centuries past,<lb break="yes"/>their city has not been overwhelmed, communicates itself<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="654" facs="#f0009"/>easily to the least intrepid traveller. In general, it is not<lb break="yes"/>so much the fear of the danger, as the novelty of the sen-<lb break="no"/>sation, that strikes so forcibly, when the effect of the<lb break="yes"/>slightest earthquake is felt for the first time. In 1784,<lb break="yes"/>the inhabitants of Mexico were accustomed to hear the<lb break="yes"/>thunder roll beneath their feet, as it is heard by us in the<lb break="yes"/>region of the clouds. Confidence easily springs up in the<lb break="yes"/>human breast, and we end by accustoming ourselves on<lb break="yes"/>the coast of Peru to the undulations of the ground, like<lb break="yes"/>the sailor to the tossings of the ship, caused by the motion<lb break="yes"/>of the waves.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The night of the 11th of November was cool and ex-<lb break="no"/>tremely beautiful. Toward the morning, from half after<lb break="yes"/>two, the most extraordinary luminous meteors were seen<lb break="yes"/>towards the east. M. Bonpland, who had risen to enjoy<lb break="yes"/>the freshess of the air in the gallery, perceived them first.<lb break="yes"/>Thousands of bolides and falling stars succeeded each other<lb break="yes"/>during four hours. M. Bonpland relates, that, from the<lb break="yes"/>beginning of the phenomenon, there was not a space in the<lb break="yes"/>firmament, equal in extent to three diameters of the moon,<lb break="yes"/>that was not filled at every instant with bolides and falling<lb break="yes"/>stars. The first were fewer in number, but, as they were<lb break="yes"/>seen of different sizes, it was impossible to fix the limit be-<lb break="no"/>tween these two classes of phenomena. All these meteors<lb break="yes"/>left luminous traces from five to ten degrees in length, as<lb break="yes"/>often happens in the equinoctial regions. On my arrival<lb break="yes"/>at the southern extremity of Spanish Guiana, at the little<lb break="yes"/>fort of San Carlos, I found some Portugueze, who had gone<lb break="yes"/>up the Rio Negro from the mission of St. Joseph of the<lb break="yes"/>Marivitains; who assured me, that, in that part of Brazil,<lb break="yes"/>the phenomenon had been perceived; at least as far as San<lb break="yes"/>Gabriel das Cachoeiras, consequently as far as the equator<lb break="yes"/>itself. I was powerfully struck with the immense height<lb break="yes"/>which these bolides must have attained, to have been visi-<lb break="no"/>ble at the same time at Cumana, and on the frontiers of<lb break="yes"/>Brazil, in a line of two hundred and thirty leagues in length.<lb break="yes"/>But what was my astonishment, when, at my return to<lb break="yes"/>Europe, I learnt, that the same phenomenon had been<lb break="yes"/>perceived on an extent of the globe of 64&#x00B0; of latitude, and<lb break="yes"/>91&#x00B0; of longitude; at the equator, in South America, at<lb break="yes"/>Labrador, and in Germany. The distance from Weimar<lb break="yes"/>to the Rio Negro, is 1800 sea leagues; and, from Rio<lb break="yes"/>Negro to Herrenhut in Greenland, 4500 miles. Admitting<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="655" facs="#f0010"/>that the same fiery meteors were seen at points so distant<lb break="yes"/>from each other, we must also admit, that their height<lb break="yes"/>was at least 1200 miles; and that those meteors had every<lb break="yes"/>where the same brilliancy throughout a space of 2,500,000<lb break="yes"/>square miles.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We were never wearied of admiring the beauty of the<lb break="yes"/>nights, nothing can be compared to the transparency and<lb break="yes"/>serenity of an African sky. We were struck with the<lb break="yes"/>innumerable quantity of falling stars, which appeared at<lb break="yes"/>every instant. The farther progress we made towards the<lb break="yes"/>south the more frequent was this phenomenon, especially<lb break="yes"/>near the Canaries. I have observed during my excursions<lb break="yes"/>that these igneous meteors are in general more common<lb break="yes"/>and luminous in some regions of the globe than in others;<lb break="yes"/>I have never beheld them so multiplied as in the vicinity of<lb break="yes"/>the volcanoes of the province of Quito, and in the part of<lb break="yes"/>the Pacific Ocean which washes the volcanic coasts of<lb break="yes"/>Guatimala. In warm climates, especially under the tro-<lb break="no"/>pics, the falling stars leave a tail behind them, which<lb break="yes"/>remains luminous twelve or sixteen seconds; at other times<lb break="yes"/>they seem to burst into sparks, and they are generally<lb break="yes"/>lower than those in the north of Europe. We perceive<lb break="yes"/>them only in a serene and azure sky; they have perhaps<lb break="yes"/>never been seen below a cloud.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The natives near the cataracts of the Oroonoko, up<lb break="yes"/>which river Mr. de Humboldt made his way to a height<lb break="yes"/>little known to Europeans, are distinguished by several<lb break="yes"/>remarkable prejudices, among which, none are more fatal<lb break="yes"/>than those narrated in the following:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Among the causes of the depopulation of the Raudales, I<lb break="yes"/>have not reckoned the small-pox; that malady which, in<lb break="yes"/>other parts of America, makes such cruel ravages, that<lb break="yes"/>the natives, seized with dismay, burn their huts, kill their<lb break="yes"/>children, and renounce every kind of society. This<lb break="yes"/>scourge is almost unknown on the banks of the Oroonoko.<lb break="yes"/>What depopulates the Christian settlements is, the repug-<lb break="no"/>nance of the Indians for the regulations of the missions,<lb break="yes"/>the insalubrity of a climate at once hot and damp, bad<lb break="yes"/>nourishment, want of care in the diseases of children, and<lb break="yes"/>the guilty practice of mothers of preventing pregnancy<lb break="yes"/>by the use of deleterious herbs. Among the barbarous<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="656" facs="#f0011"/>people of Guyana, as well as those of the half-civilized<lb break="yes"/>islands of the South Sea, young wives will not become<lb break="yes"/>mothers. If they have children, their offspring are exposed,<lb break="yes"/>not only to the dangers of savage life, but also the dangers<lb break="yes"/>arising from the strangest popular prejudices. When twins<lb break="yes"/>are born, false notions of propriety and family honour re-<lb break="no"/>quire that one of them should be destroyed. &#x2018;To bring<lb break="yes"/>twins into the world, is to be exposed to public scorn; it<lb break="yes"/>is to resemble rats, opossums, and the vilest animals,<lb break="yes"/>which bring forth a great number of young at a time.&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>Nay more: &#x2018;two children born at the same time cannot<lb break="yes"/>belong to the same father.&#x2019; This is an axiom of<lb break="yes" />physiology of the Salivas; and in every zone, and in<lb break="yes"/>different states of society, when the vulgar seize upon<lb break="yes"/>an axiom, they adhere to it with more steadfastess<lb break="yes"/>than the better informed men, by whom it was first<lb break="yes"/>hazarded. To avoid a disturbance of conjugal tran-<lb break="no"/>quillity, the old female relations of the mother, or the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">mure japoic-nei</hi> (midwives), take care that one of the<lb break="yes"/>twins shall disappear. If the new born infant, though<lb break="yes"/>not a twin, have any physical deformity, the father instantly<lb break="yes"/>puts it to death.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Indians of Atures, says Mr. H., are mild and<lb break="yes"/>moderate; and are accustomed, as effects of their<lb break="yes"/>idleness, to the greatest privations. Formerly, excited<lb break="yes"/>to labour by the Jesuits, they did not want for food. The<lb break="yes"/>fathers cultivated maize, French beans, (<hi rendition="#i">frisoles,</hi>) and<lb break="yes"/>other European vegetables; they even planted sweet<lb break="yes"/>oranges and tamarinds round the villages; and they pos-<lb break="no"/>sessed twenty or thirty thousand head of cows and<lb break="yes"/>horses, in the savannahs of Atures and Carichana. They<lb break="yes"/>had at their service a great number of slaves and ser-<lb break="no"/>vants (<hi rendition="#i">peones</hi>), to take care of their herds. Nothing is<lb break="yes"/>now cultivated but a little cassava, and a few plantains.<lb break="yes"/>The fertility of the soil however is such that, at Atures,<lb break="yes"/>I counted on a single branch of musa 108 fruits, four or<lb break="yes"/>five of which would almost suffice for the daily nourish-<lb break="no"/>ment of a man. The culture of maize is entirely neg-<lb break="no"/>lected, and the horses and cows have disappeared. Near<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">raudal,</hi> a part of the village still bears the name of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Passo del ganado</hi> (ford of the cattle), while the de-<lb break="no"/>scendants of those very Indians, whom the Jesuits had<lb break="yes"/>assembled in a mission, speak of horned cattle as of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="657" facs="#f0012"/>animals of a race that is lost. In going up the Oroo-<lb break="no"/>noko, toward San Carlos del Rio Negro, we saw the<lb break="yes"/>last cow at Carichana. The fathers of the Observance,<lb break="yes"/>who now govern these vast countries, did not immediately<lb break="yes"/>succeed the Jesuits. During an interregnum of eighteen<lb break="yes"/>years the missions were visited only from time to time,<lb break="yes"/>and by Capuchin monks. The agents of the secular go-<lb break="no"/>vernment, under the title of <hi rendition="#i">Commissioners of the King,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>managed the <hi rendition="#i">hatos,</hi> or farms, of the Jesuits with culpable<lb break="yes"/>negligence. They killed the cattle in order to sell the<lb break="yes"/>hides. Many heifers were devoured by tigers, and a<lb break="yes"/>greater number perished in consequence of wounds made<lb break="yes"/>by the bats of the <hi rendition="#i">raudales,</hi> which are much less, but<lb break="yes"/>far bolder, than the bats of the Llanos. At the time of<lb break="yes"/>the expedition of the boundaries, the horses of Encara-<lb break="no"/>mada, Carichana, and Atures, were conveyed as far as<lb break="yes"/>San Jose of Maravitanos, where, on the banks of the<lb break="yes"/>Rio Negro, the Portuguese could only procure them after<lb break="yes"/>a long passage, and of a very inferior quality, by the<lb break="yes"/>river Amazon and Grand Para. Since the year 1795<lb break="yes" />the cattle of the Jesuits have entirely disappeared. There<lb break="yes"/>now remains in testimony of the ancient cultivation of<lb break="yes"/>these countries, and the industrious activity of the first<lb break="yes" />missionaries, only a few trunks of the orange and tama-<lb break="no"/>rind in the savannahs, surrounded by wild trees.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The tigers, or jaguars, which are less dangerous for<lb break="yes"/>the cattle than the bats, come into the village at Atures,<lb break="yes"/>and devour the pigs of the poor Indians.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Among the monkeys, the author continues, which<lb break="yes"/>we saw at the mission of Atures, we found one new<lb break="yes"/>species, of the tribe of <hi rendition="#i">sais</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">sajous,</hi> which the Creoles<lb break="yes"/>vulgarly call <hi rendition="#i">machis.</hi> It is the <hi rendition="#i">ouarapavi</hi> with grey hair<lb break="yes"/>and a bluish face. It has the orbits of the eyes and fore-<lb break="no"/>head as white as snow, which at first sight distinguish it<lb break="yes"/>from the <hi rendition="#i">simia capucina,</hi> the <hi rendition="#i">simia apella,</hi> the <hi rendition="#i">simia tre-<lb break="no"/>pida,</hi> and the other weeping monkeys hitherto so con-<lb break="no"/>fusedly described. This little animal is as gentle as it is<lb break="yes"/>ugly. Every day in the court-yard of the missionary it<lb break="yes"/>seized a pig, upon which it remained from morning till<lb break="yes"/>night, traversing the savannahs. We have also seen it<lb break="yes"/>upon the back of a large cat, which had been brought up<lb break="yes"/>with it in Father Zea&#x2019;s house.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It was among the cataracts that we began to hear of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="658" facs="#f0013"/>the hairy man of the woods, called <hi rendition="#i" >salvaje,</hi> that carries<lb break="yes"/>off women, constructs huts, and sometimes eats human<lb break="yes"/>flesh. The Tamanacks call it <hi rendition="#i">achi,</hi> and the Maypures<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">vasitri,</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">great devil.</hi> The natives and the missionaries<lb break="yes"/>have no doubt of the existence of this anthropomorphous<lb break="yes"/>monkey, which they singularly dread. Father Gili gravely<lb break="yes"/>relates the history of a lady in the town of San Carlos,<lb break="yes"/>who much praised the gentle character and attentions of<lb break="yes"/>the man of the woods. She lived several years with one<lb break="yes"/>in great domestic harmony, and only requested some<lb break="yes"/>hunters to take her back, &#x2018;because she was tired, she and<lb break="yes"/>her children (a little hairy also), of living far from the<lb break="yes"/>church and the sacraments.&#x2019; The same author, notwith-<lb break="no"/>standing his credulity, confesses, that he had not been<lb break="yes"/>able to find an Indian, who asserted positively that he<lb break="yes"/>had seen the <hi rendition="#i">salvaje</hi> with his own eyes. This fable,<lb break="yes"/>which the missionaries, the European planters, and the<lb break="yes"/>negroes of Africa, have no doubt embellished with many<lb break="yes"/>features taken from the description of the manners of<lb break="yes"/>the ourang-outang, the gibbon, the jocao or chimpanzee,<lb break="yes"/>and the pongo, pursued us during five years from the<lb break="yes"/>northern to the southern hemisphere; and we were every<lb break="yes"/>where blamed, in the most cultivated classes of society,<lb break="yes"/>for being the only persons to doubt the existence of the<lb break="yes"/>great anthropomorphous monkey of America. We shall<lb break="yes"/>first observe, that there are certain regions, where this<lb break="yes"/>belief is particularly prevalent among the people; such<lb break="yes"/>are the banks of the Upper Oroonoko, the valley of<lb break="yes"/>Upar near the lake of Maracaybo, the mountains of<lb break="yes"/>Santa Martha and of Merida, the provinces of Quixos,<lb break="yes"/>and the banks of the Amazon near Tomependa. In all<lb break="yes"/>these places so distant one from the other, it is repeated,<lb break="yes"/>that the <hi rendition="#i">salvaje</hi> is easily recognized by the traces of its<lb break="yes"/>feet, the toes of which are turned backward. But, if<lb break="yes"/>there exist a monkey of a large size in the New Conti-<lb break="no"/>nent, how has it happened that during three centuries no<lb break="yes"/>man worthy of belief has been able to procure the skin<lb break="yes"/>of one? Several hypotheses present themselves to the<lb break="yes"/>mind, in order to explain the source of so ancient an<lb break="yes"/>error or belief. Has the famous <hi rendition="#i" >capuchin</hi> monkey of<lb break="yes"/>Esmeralda, the canine teeth of which are more than six<lb break="yes"/>lines and a half long, the physiognomy much more like<lb break="yes"/>man&#x2019;s than that of the ourang-outang, and which, when<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="659" facs="#f0014"/>irritated, rubs its beard with its hand, given rise to the<lb break="yes"/>fable of the <hi rendition="#i">salvaje?</hi> It is not so large indeed as the<lb break="yes"/>coaita (<hi rendition="#i">simia paniscus</hi>); but when seen at the top of a<lb break="yes"/>tree, and the head only visible, it might easily be taken<lb break="yes"/>for a human being. It may be also (and this opinion ap-<lb break="no"/>pears to me the most probable), that the man of the<lb break="yes"/>woods was one of these large bears, the footsteps of<lb break="yes"/>which resemble those of a man, and which is believed in<lb break="yes"/>every country to attack women. The animal killed in<lb break="yes"/>my time at the foot of the mountains of Merida, and<lb break="yes"/>sent by the name of <hi rendition="#i">salvaje</hi> to Colonel Ungaro, the<lb break="yes"/>governor of the province Varinas, was in fact a bear,<lb break="yes"/>with black and smooth fur.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Persons who have not navigated the great rivers of<lb break="yes"/>equinoctial America, for instance, the Oroonoko and the<lb break="yes"/>Rio Magdalena, can scarcely conceive, how without inter-<lb break="no"/>ruption, at every instant of life, you may be tormented by<lb break="yes"/>insects flying in the air, and how the multitude of these<lb break="yes"/>little animals may render vast regions wholly uninhabitable.<lb break="yes"/>However accustomed you may be to endure pain without<lb break="yes"/>complaint, however lively an interest you may take in the<lb break="yes"/>objects of your researches, it is impossible not to be con-<lb break="no"/>stantly disturbed by the moschettoes, <hi rendition="#i"><choice><sic>zanchdoes</sic><corr type="editorial">zancudoes</corr></choice>, jejens,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and <hi rendition="#i">tempraneroes,</hi> that cover the face and hands, pierce<lb break="yes"/>the clothes with their long sucker in the form of a needle,<lb break="yes"/>and, getting into the mouth and nostrils, set you coughing<lb break="yes"/>and sneezing whenever you attempt to speak in the open<lb break="yes"/>air. In the missions of the Oroonoko, in the villages placed<lb break="yes"/>on the banks of the river, surrounded by immense forests,<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">plaga de las moscas,</hi> the plague of the flies, affords an<lb break="yes"/>inexhaustible subject of conversation. When two persons<lb break="yes"/>meet in the morning, the first questions they address to<lb break="yes"/>each other are, &#x2018;How did you find the zancudoes during<lb break="yes"/>the night? How are we to-day for the moschettoes?&#x2019; These<lb break="yes"/>questions remind us of a Chinese form of politeness, which<lb break="yes"/>indicates the ancient state of the country where it took<lb break="yes"/>birth. Salutations where made heretofore in the <hi rendition="#i">celestial<lb break="yes"/>empire,</hi> in the following words, <hi rendition="#i">vou-touhou,</hi> &#x2018;Have you<lb break="yes"/>been incommoded in the night by the serpents?&#x2019; We shall<lb break="yes"/>soon see, that on the banks of the Tuamini, in the river<lb break="yes"/>Magdalena, and still more at Choco, the country of gold<lb break="yes"/>and platina, the Chinese compliment on the serpents might<lb break="yes"/>be added to that of the moschettoes</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="660" facs="#f0015"/>
                <p>At Mandavaca we found an old missionary, who told<lb break="yes"/>us, with an air of sadness, that he had spent <hi rendition="#i">his twenty<lb break="yes" />years of moschettoes</hi> in America. He desired us to look<lb break="yes" />well at his legs, that we might be able to tell one day,<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;poor alla (beyond sea), that the poor monks suffer in the<lb break="yes"/>forests of Cassiquiare.&#x2019; Every sting leaving a small<lb break="yes"/>darkish brown point, his legs were so speckled, that it was<lb break="yes"/>difficult to recognize the whiteness of his skin through the<lb break="yes"/>spots of coagulated blood. If the insects of the simulium<lb break="yes"/>genus abound in the Cassiquiare, which has <hi rendition="#i">white waters,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>the culices, or <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes,</hi> are so much the more rare; you<lb break="yes"/>scarcely find any there, while on the rivers of <hi rendition="#i">black waters,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>in the Atabapo and the Rio Negro, there are generally<lb break="yes"/>some <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi> and no <hi rendition="#i">moschettoes.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From six in the morning till five in the afternoon, the air<lb break="yes"/>is filled with moschettoes: which have not, as we find re-<lb break="no"/>lated in some travels, the form of our knats, but that of a<lb break="yes"/>small fly. They are simuliums, of the family nemocer&#x00E6; of<lb break="yes"/>the system of Latreille. Their sting is as painful as that<lb break="yes"/>of <hi rendition="#i">stomoxes.</hi> It leaves a little reddish-brown spot, which<lb break="yes"/>is extravasated and coagulated blood, where their pro-<lb break="no"/>boscis has pierced the skin. An hour before sun-set a<lb break="yes"/>species of small knats, called <hi rendition="#i" >tempraneros,</hi> because they<lb break="yes"/>appear also at sun-rise, take the place of the moschettoes.<lb break="yes"/>Their presence scarcely lasts an hour and a half; they dis-<lb break="no"/>appear between six and seven in the evening, or, as they<lb break="yes"/>say here, after the <hi rendition="#i">Angelus (a la oracion).</hi> After a<lb break="yes"/>few minutes&#x2019; repose, you feel yourself stung by <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>another species of gnat (culex) with very long legs. The<lb break="yes"/>zancudo, the proboscis of which contains a sharp pointed<lb break="yes"/>sucker, causes the most acute pain, and a swelling that<lb break="yes"/>remains several weeks. Its hum resembles that of our<lb break="yes"/>gnats in Europe, but is louder and more prolonged. The<lb break="yes"/>Indians pretend to distinguish &#x2018;by their song&#x2019; the <hi rendition="#i">zancu-<lb break="no"/>does</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i" >tempraneroes;</hi> the latter of which are real<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">twilight insects,</hi> while the <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi> are most frequently<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">nocturnal insects,</hi> and disappear towards sun-rise.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The <hi rendition="#i">culices</hi> of South America have generally the<lb break="yes"/>wings, corselet, and legs, of an azure colour, annulated,<lb break="yes"/>and variable from a mixture of spots of a metallic lustre.<lb break="yes"/>Here, as in Europe, the males, which are distinguished<lb break="yes"/>by their feathered antenn&#x00E6;, are extremely rare; you are<lb break="yes"/>seldom stung except by females. The preponderance of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="661" facs="#f0016"/>this sex explains the immense increase of the species,<lb break="yes"/>each female laying several hundred eggs. In going up<lb break="yes"/>one of the great rivers of America, it is observed, that<lb break="yes"/>the appearance of a new species of <hi rendition="#i">culex</hi> denotes the ap-<lb break="no"/>proximity of a new stream flowing in.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The whites born in the torrid zone walk barefoot<lb break="yes"/>with impunity in the same apartment where a European<lb break="yes"/>recently landed is exposed to the attack of the <hi rendition="#i">niguas</hi> or<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">chegoes (pulex penetrans).</hi> These animals, almost in-<lb break="no"/>visible to the eye, get under the nails of the feet, and<lb break="yes"/>there acquire the size of a small pea by the quick increase<lb break="yes"/>of its eggs, which are placed in a bag under the belly of<lb break="yes"/>the insect. The <hi rendition="#i">nigua,</hi> therefore, distinguishes, what<lb break="yes"/>the most delicate chemical analysis could not distinguish,<lb break="yes"/>the cellular membrane and blood of a European from<lb break="yes"/>those of a Creole white. It is not so with the mos-<lb break="no"/>chettoes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is difficult not to smile at hearing the missionaries<lb break="yes"/>dispute on the size and voracity of the moschettoes at<lb break="yes"/>different parts of the same river. In the centre of a<lb break="yes"/>country ignorant of what is passing in the rest of the<lb break="yes"/>world, this is the favourite subject of conversation. &#x2018;How<lb break="yes"/>I pity your situation!&#x2019; said the missionary of the rau-<lb break="no"/>dales to the missionary of Cassiquiare, at our departure;<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;you are alone, like me, in this country of tigers and<lb break="yes"/>monkeys; with you fish is still more rare, and the heat<lb break="yes"/>more violent; but as for my flies, <hi rendition="#i" >(mia moscas,)</hi> I can<lb break="yes"/>boast, that with one of mine I would beat three of yours.&#x2019;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This voracity of insects in certain spots, the rage with<lb break="yes"/>which they attack man, the activity of the venom varying<lb break="yes"/>in the same species, are very remarkable facts; which<lb break="yes"/>find their analogy, however, in the classes of large animals.<lb break="yes"/>The crocodile of Angostura pursues men, while at Nueva-<lb break="no"/>Barcelona, in the Rio Neveri, you may bathe tranquilly in<lb break="yes"/>the midst of these carnivorous reptiles. The jaguars of<lb break="yes"/>Maturin, Cumanacoa, and the isthmus of Panama, are<lb break="yes"/>cowardly in comparison to those of the Upper Oroonoko.<lb break="yes"/>The Indians well know, that the monkeys of some valleys<lb break="yes"/>can easily be tamed, while others of the same species,<lb break="yes"/>caught elsewhere, will rather die of hunger, than submit<lb break="yes"/>to slavery.<choice><sic>&#x201D;</sic><corr type="editorial"></corr></choice><note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn1-1" next="#fn1-2">&#x201C;I might have added the example of the scorpion of Cumana,<lb break="yes"/>which it is very difficult to distinguish from that of the island of</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="662" facs="#f0017"/>
                <p>At Maypure, higher up, we heard much of the pottery<lb break="yes"/>of the Indians; in every part of the forests, far from any<lb break="yes"/>human habitations, on digging the earth, fragments of<lb break="yes"/>pottery and delft are found. The taste for this kind of<lb break="yes"/>fabrication seems to have been common heretofore to the<lb break="yes"/>natives of both Americas. To the north of Mexico&#x2014;on<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the Rio Gila&#x2014;among the ruins of an Azteck<lb break="yes"/>city&#x2014;in the United States&#x2014;near the <hi rendition="#i">tumuli</hi> of the Mia-<lb break="no"/>mis; in Florida&#x2014;and in every place where any trace of<lb break="yes"/>ancient civilization could be found, the soil covers frag-<lb break="no"/>ments of painted pottery; and the extreme resemblance<lb break="yes"/>of the ornaments they display is striking. Savage na-<lb break="no"/>tions, and those civilized people, who are condemmed by<lb break="yes"/>their political and religious institutions always to imitate<lb break="yes"/>themselves, strive, as if by instinct, to perpetuate the<lb break="yes"/>same forms, to preserve a peculiar type or style, and to<lb break="yes"/>follow the methods and processes which were employed<lb break="yes"/>by their ancestors. In North America, fragments of<lb break="yes"/>delft have been discovered in places where lines of forti-<lb break="no"/>fication are found, and the walls of towns constructed by<lb break="yes"/>an unknown nation, now entirely extinct. The paintings<lb break="yes"/>on these fragments have a great similitude to those which<lb break="yes"/>are executed in our days on earthenware by the natives of<lb break="yes"/>Louisiana and Florida. Thus too the Indians of Maypure<lb break="yes"/>often painted before our eyes the same ornaments as we<lb break="yes"/>had observed in the cavern of Ataroipe, on the vases<lb break="yes"/>containing human bones. They are real <hi rendition="#i">greeques,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>meandrites, and figures of crocodiles, of monkeys, and of<lb break="yes"/>a large quadruped, which I could not recognize, <choice><sic>through</sic><corr type="editorial">though</corr></choice><lb break="yes"/>it has always the same squat form.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Above Maypure this is indeed a &#x201C;New World.&#x201D; Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt says, when the traveller has <choice><sic>past</sic><corr type="editorial">passed</corr></choice> the great<lb break="yes"/>cataracts, he feels as if he were in a new world; and had<lb break="yes"/>overstepped the barriers which nature seems to have<lb break="yes"/>raised between the civilized countries of the coast and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1">Trinidad, Jamaica, Carthagena, and Guayaquil: yet the former is<lb break="yes"/>not more to be feared than the <hi rendition="#i">scorpio Europ&#x00E6;us</hi> (of the south of<lb break="yes"/>France), while the latter produces consequences far more alarming<lb break="yes"/>than the <hi rendition="#i">scorpio occitanus</hi> (of Spain and Barbary). At Carthagena<lb break="yes"/>and Guayaquil, the sting of the scorpion <hi rendition="#i">(alacran)</hi> instantly causes<lb break="yes"/>the loss of speech. Sometimes a singular torpor of the tongue is<lb break="yes"/>observed for fifteen or sixteen hours. The patient, when stung in<lb break="yes"/>the legs, stammers <choice><sic>at</sic><corr type="editorial">as</corr></choice> if he had been struck with apoplexy.&#x201D;</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="663" facs="#f0018"/>the savage and unknown interior. Towards the coast, in<lb break="yes"/>the bluish distance, appeared, for the last time, the high<lb break="yes"/>chain of the Cunavami mountains. Its long horizontal<lb break="yes"/>ridge reminded us of the Mesa of Bergantin, near Cu-<lb break="no"/>mana; but it terminates by a truncated summit. The<lb break="yes"/>peak of Calitamini (the name given to this summit) glows<lb break="yes"/>at sun-set as with a reddish fire. This appearance is<lb break="yes"/>every day the same. No one ever approached the sum-<lb break="no"/>mit of this mountain, the height of which does not exceed<lb break="yes"/>six hundred toises. I believe this splendor, commonly<lb break="yes"/>reddish and sometimes silvery, to be a reflexion produced<lb break="yes"/>by large plates of talc, or by gneiss passing into mica-<lb break="no"/>slate. The whole of this country contains granitic rocks,<lb break="yes"/>on which here and there, in little plains, an argillaceous<lb break="yes"/>grit-stone immediately reposes, containing fragments of<lb break="yes"/>quartz, and of brown iron ore.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In going to the <hi rendition="#i">embarcadere,</hi> he continues, we caught,<lb break="yes"/>on the trunk of a hevea, a new species of tree frog, re-<lb break="no"/>markable for its beautiful colours; it had a yellow belly,<lb break="yes"/>the back and head of a fine velvetty purple, and a very<lb break="yes"/>narrow stripe of white from the point of the nose to the<lb break="yes"/>hinder extremities. This frog was two inches long, and<lb break="yes"/>allied to the <hi rendition="#i">rana tinctoria,</hi> the blood of which, it is as-<lb break="no"/>serted, introduced into the skin of a parrot, in places<lb break="yes"/>where the feathers have been plucked out, occasions the<lb break="yes"/>growth of frizzled feathers of a yellow or red colour.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Every hemisphere produces plants of a different species;<lb break="yes"/>and it is not by the diversity of climates that we can<lb break="yes"/><choice><sic>a tempt</sic><corr type="editorial">attempt</corr></choice> to explain, why equinoctial Africa has no<lb break="yes"/>aturin&#x00E6;, and the New World no heaths; why the <choice><sic>cal-<lb break="no"/>cwolari&#x00E6;</sic><corr type="editorial">cal-<lb break="no"/>ceolari&#x00E6;</corr></choice> are found only in the southern hemisphere;<lb break="yes"/>why the birds of the continent of India glow with colours<lb break="yes"/>less splendid than the birds of the hot parts of America;<lb break="yes"/>finally, why the tiger is peculiar to Asia, and the orni-<lb break="no"/>thorincus to New-Holland. In the vegetable as well as in<lb break="yes"/>the animal kingdom, the causes of the distribution of the<lb break="yes"/>species are among the number of mysteries, which natural<lb break="yes"/>philosophy cannot reach. There are regions of America<lb break="yes"/>as barren and hot as the interior of Africa. The islands<lb break="yes"/>that produce the spices of India are scarcely remarkable<lb break="yes"/>for their dryness; and it is not on account of the humidity<lb break="yes"/>of the climate, as it has been affirmed in recent works, that<lb break="yes"/>the New Continent is deprived of those fine species of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="664" facs="#f0019"/>laurine&#x00E6; and myristic&#x00E6;, which are found united in one<lb break="yes"/>little corner of the earth in the Archipelago of India. For<lb break="yes"/>some years past, the real cinnamon has been cultivated<lb break="yes"/>with success in several parts of the New Continent; and<lb break="yes"/>a zone, that produces the coumarouna, the vanilla, the<lb break="yes"/>pucheri, the pineapple, the myrtus pimenta, the balsam<lb break="yes"/>of tolu, the myroxylon peruvianum, the crotons, the<lb break="yes"/>citrosmas, the pejoa, the <hi rendition="#i" >incienso</hi> of the Silla of Carac-<lb break="no"/>cas, the <hi rendition="#i">quereme,</hi> the pancratium, and so many majestic<lb break="yes"/>liliaceous plants, cannot be considered as destitute of<lb break="yes"/>aromatics.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The <hi rendition="#i">phiguao</hi> or pirajao palm has a trunk, armed with<lb break="yes"/>thorns more than 60 feet high; its leaves are pinnated, very<lb break="yes"/>thin, undulated, and frizzled towards the points. Nothing<lb break="yes"/>is more extraordinary than the fruit of this tree; every<lb break="yes"/>cluster contains from fifty to eighty: they are yellow like<lb break="yes"/>apples, grow purple in proportion as they ripen, two or<lb break="yes"/>three inches thick; and generally, from abortion, without<lb break="yes"/>a kernal. Among the eighty or ninety species of palm<lb break="yes"/>trees that are peculiar to the New Continent, adds Mr. H.,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;which I have enumerated in the <hi rendition="#i">Nova Genera Plan-<lb break="no"/>tarum &#x00E6;quinoctialium,</hi> there are none in which the sarco-<lb break="no"/>carp is developed in a manner so extraordinary. The<lb break="yes"/>fruit of the <hi rendition="#i">pirijao</hi> furnishes a farinaceous substance, as<lb break="yes"/>yellow as the yolk of an egg, slightly saccharine, and ex-<lb break="no"/>tremely nutritious. It is eaten like plantains or potatoes,<lb break="yes"/>boiled or roasted in the ashes, and affords an aliment as<lb break="yes"/>wholesome as it is agreeable. The Indians and the mis-<lb break="no"/>sionaries are unwearied in their praises of this noble palm-<lb break="no"/>tree, which might be called the <hi rendition="#i">peach palm,</hi> and which we<lb break="yes"/>found cultivated in abundance at San Fernando, San Bal-<lb break="no"/>thasar, Santa Barbara, and wherever we advanced toward<lb break="yes"/>the south or the east along the banks of the Atabapo and<lb break="yes"/>the Upper Oroonoko. In those wild regions are we invo-<lb break="no"/>luntarily reminded of the assertion of Linn&#x00E6;us, that the<lb break="yes"/>country of palm-trees was the first abode of our species,<lb break="yes"/>and that man is essentially <hi rendition="#i">palmivorous.</hi> On examining<lb break="yes" />the provisions accumulated in the huts of the Indians, we<lb break="yes" />perceive, that their subsistance, during several months of<lb break="yes"/>the year, depends as much on the farinaceous fruit of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">pirijao,</hi> as on the cassava and plantain. The tree bears<lb break="yes"/>fruit but once a year, but to the amount of three clusters,<lb break="yes"/>from one hundred and fifty to two hundred fruit. Here,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="665" facs="#f0020"/>also, is seen the gigantic bombax (<hi rendition="#i">bombax ceila</hi>) one <choice><sic>o</sic><corr type="editorial">of</corr></choice><lb break="yes"/>which, as they sailed along, attracted the notice of the<lb break="yes"/>travellers, and they landed to measure it. The height<lb break="yes"/>(we are told) was nearly one hundred and twenty feet,<lb break="yes"/>and the diameter between fourteen and fifteen.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Nor is animal inferior to vegetable life. The river<lb break="yes"/>Atabapo displays every where a peculiar aspect; you see<lb break="yes"/>nothing of its real banks, formed by flat lands eight or ten<lb break="yes"/>feet high; they are concealed by a row of palms, and small<lb break="yes"/>trees with slender trunks, the roots of which are bathed by<lb break="yes"/>the waters. There are many crocodiles from the point<lb break="yes"/>where you quit the Oroonoko to the mission of San Fer-<lb break="no"/>nando, and their presence indicates, as we have said above,<lb break="yes"/>that this part of the river belongs to the Rio Guaviare and<lb break="yes"/>not to the Atabapo. In the real bed of the latter river,<lb break="yes"/>above the mission of San Fernando, there are no longer any<lb break="yes"/>crocodiles: we find there are some <hi rendition="#i" >bavas,</hi> a great many<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">fresh-water dolphins,</hi> but no manatees. We also seek in<lb break="yes"/>vain on those banks the thick-nosed tapir, the araguates,<lb break="yes"/>or great howling monkeys, the zamuro, or vultur aura, and<lb break="yes"/>the crested pheasant, known by the name of <hi rendition="#i">guacharuca.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Enormous water snakes, in shape resembling the boa, are<lb break="yes"/>unfortunately very common, and are dangerous to the<lb break="yes"/>Indians who bathe. We saw them almost from the first<lb break="yes"/>day, swimming by the side of our canoe; they were at the<lb break="yes"/>most twelve or fourteen feet long. The jaguars of the<lb break="yes"/>banks of the Atabapo and the Temi are large and well fed:<lb break="yes"/>they are said, however, to be less daring than the jaguars<lb break="yes"/>of the Oroonoko.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following is a curious account of the <hi rendition="#i">Indian Rub-<lb break="no"/>ber</hi>:&#x2014;&#x201C;Here (says Mr. H. at the mission of St. Balthasar<lb break="yes"/>on the Atabapo) we saw, for the first time, that white and<lb break="yes"/>fungous substance, which I have made known by the name<lb break="yes"/>of <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">zapis.</hi> We immediately perceived, that it<lb break="yes" />was analogous to the <hi rendition="#i">elastic resin;</hi> but, as the Indians<lb break="yes"/>made us understand by signs, that it was found under-<lb break="no"/>ground, we were inclined to think, till we arrived at the<lb break="yes"/>mission of Javita, that the <hi rendition="#i" >dapicho</hi> was a fossil caoutchouc,<lb break="yes"/>though different from the elastic bitumen of <choice><sic>Derbyshire</sic><corr type="editorial">Derbyshire.</corr></choice><lb break="yes"/>A Poimisano Indian, seated by the fire, in the hut of the<lb break="yes"/>missionary, was <choice><sic>enployed</sic><corr type="editorial">employed</corr></choice> in reducing the <hi rendition="#i">depicho</hi> <choice><sic>in to</sic><corr type="editorial">into</corr></choice> black<lb break="yes"/>caoutchouc. He had spitted several bits on a slender<lb break="yes"/>stick, and was roasting them like meat. The <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="666" facs="#f0021"/>blackens in proportion as it grows softer, and gains in<lb break="yes"/>elasticity. The resinous and aromatic smell, which filled<lb break="yes"/>the hut, seemed to indicate, that this coloration is the<lb break="yes"/>effect of the decomposition of a carburet of hydrogen, and<lb break="yes"/>that the carbon appears in proportion as the hydrogen<lb break="yes"/>burns at a low heat. The Indian beat the softened and<lb break="yes"/>blackened mass with a piece of brazil wood, ending in form<lb break="yes"/>of a club; he then kneaded the <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> into balls of three<lb break="yes"/>or four inches in diameter, and let it cool. These balls<lb break="yes"/>exactly resemble the caoutchouc of the shops, but their<lb break="yes"/>surface remains in general slightly viscous. They are used<lb break="yes"/>at San Balthasar in the Indian game of tennis, which is so<lb break="yes"/>celebrated among the inhabitants of Uruana and En-<lb break="no"/>caramada; they are cut into cylinders, to be used as corks,<lb break="yes"/>and are far preferable to those made of the bark of the<lb break="yes"/>cork-tree.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Soon after, the travellers obtained precise information<lb break="yes" />respecting this substance:&#x2014;it was shown them at the depth<lb break="yes"/>of two or three feet, in a marshy soil, &#x201C;between the roots<lb break="yes"/>of two trees known by the name of the <hi rendition="#i" >jacio</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i">cur-<lb break="no"/>vana.</hi> The first is the hevea of Aublet, or siphonia of the<lb break="yes"/>modern botanists, known to furnish the caoutchouc of<lb break="yes"/>commerce in Cayenne and the Grand Para; the second<lb break="yes"/>has pinnate leaves, and its juice is milky, but very thin,<lb break="yes"/>and almost destitute of viscosity. The <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> appears to<lb break="yes"/>be the result of an extravasation of the sap from the roots.<lb break="yes"/>This extravasation takes place more especially when the<lb break="yes"/>trees have attained a great age, and the interior of the<lb break="yes"/>trunk begins to decay. The bark and alburnum crack;<lb break="yes"/>and thus is effected naturally, what the art of man per-<lb break="no"/>forms to collect in abundance the milky juices of the hevea,<lb break="yes"/>the castilloa, and the caoutchouc fig-tree.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The River Temi, near the banks of which this produc-<lb break="no"/>tion is found in sufficient quantities to supply all Europe,<lb break="yes"/>runs through forests which overshadow it in so wild and<lb break="yes"/>luxuriant a manner as almost to mingle together the crea-<lb break="no"/>tures of the several elements of air, earth, and water.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But these <hi rendition="#i">fishes among the woods,</hi> though the most<lb break="yes"/>singular, were not the most ungrateful of the animal crea-<lb break="no"/>tion to the startled Europeans. About this region they<lb break="yes"/>had to stop to be cured of an evil under which they suffered<lb break="yes"/>for two days. The author thus describes it: &#x201C;We felt<lb break="yes"/>an extraordinary irritation on the joints of the fingers, and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="667" facs="#f0022"/>on the backs of our hands. The missionary told us it was<lb break="yes"/>caused by the <hi rendition="#i">aradores</hi> (ploughman insects,) which get<lb break="yes"/>under the skin. We could distinguish with a lens nothing<lb break="yes"/>but streaks, or parallel and whitish furrows. It is the<lb break="yes"/>form of these furrows that has obtained this insect the<lb break="yes"/>name of <hi rendition="#i" >ploughman.</hi> A mulatto woman was sent for,<lb break="yes"/>who boasted of being thoroughly acquainted with all the<lb break="yes"/>little insects, that burrow in the human skin; the <hi rendition="#i">chego,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">nuche,</hi> the <hi rendition="#i" >coya,</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i">arador</hi>; she was the <hi rendition="#i">curandera,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>the physician of the place. She promised to extirpate the<lb break="yes"/>insects, that caused this smarting irritation, one by one. She<lb break="yes"/>heated at a lamp the point of a little bit of very hard wood,<lb break="yes"/>and dug with this point the furrows that marked the skin.<lb break="yes"/>After long researches, she announced with the pedantic<lb break="yes"/>gravity peculiar to the mulatto race, that an <hi rendition="#i">arador</hi> was<lb break="yes"/>found. I saw a little round bag, which I suspected to be<lb break="yes"/>the egg of an acarus. I was to find relief, when the mulatto<lb break="yes"/>woman had succeeded in taking out three or four of these<lb break="yes"/>
                    <choice><sic><hi rendition="#i">tradoves.</hi></sic><corr type="editorial"><hi rendition="#i">aradores.</hi></corr></choice> Having the skin of both hands filled with acari,<lb break="yes"/>I had not patience to wait the end of an operation, which<lb break="yes"/>had already lasted till late at night. The next day an In-<lb break="no"/>dian of Javita cured us radically, and with surprising<lb break="yes"/>promptitude.&#x201D;&#x2014;The medicament consisted of an infusion<lb break="yes"/>of a shrub called <hi rendition="#i">uzao.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The annexed noticed of the religious opinions of the<lb break="yes"/>natives has something very sublime in it.&#x2014;&#x201C;The nations<lb break="yes"/>of the Upper Oroonoko, the Atabapo, and the Inirida,<lb break="yes"/>like the ancient Germans and the Persians, have no other<lb break="yes"/>worship than that of the powers of nature. They call the<lb break="yes"/>good principle <hi rendition="#i" >Cachimana;</hi> it is the <hi rendition="#i">Manitou,</hi> the Great<lb break="yes"/>Spirit, that regulates the seasons, and favours the <choice><sic>harvests</sic><corr type="editorial">harvests.</corr></choice><lb break="yes"/>By the side of <hi rendition="#i">Cachimana</hi> there is an evil principle,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Iolokiamo,</hi> less powerful, but more artful, and in <choice><sic>par<lb break="yes"/>ticular</sic><corr type="editorial">par-<lb break="no"/>ticular</corr></choice> more active. The Indians of the forest, when<lb break="yes"/>they visit occasionally the missions, conceive with dif-<lb break="no"/>ficulty the idea of a temple or image. &#x2018;These good<lb break="yes"/>people,&#x2019; said the missionary, &#x2018;like only processions in the<lb break="yes"/>open air. When I last celebrated the patron festival of<lb break="yes"/>my village, that of San Antonio, the Indians of Inirida<lb break="yes"/>were present at mass. &#x2018;Your God,&#x2019; said they to me,<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;keeps himself shut up in a house, as if he were old and<lb break="yes"/>infirm; ours is in the forest, in the fields, and on the moun-<lb break="no"/>tains of Sipapu, whence the rains come.&#x2019; Some old Indians<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="668" facs="#f0023"/>pretend to be better instructed than others in what regard,<lb break="yes"/>the divinity; and to them is confined <hi rendition="#i">botuto,</hi> which is<lb break="yes"/>sounded under palm-trees, that they may bear abund-<lb break="no"/>ance of fruit. On the banks of the Oroonoko there<lb break="yes"/>exists no idol, as among all the nations who have remained<lb break="yes"/>faithful to the first worship of nature: but the <hi rendition="#i">botuto,</hi> the<lb break="yes"/>sacred trumpet, is become an object of veneration. To<lb break="yes"/>be initiated into the mysteries of the <hi rendition="#i">botuto,</hi> it is requisite<lb break="yes" />to have pure manners, and to have lived single. The<lb break="yes"/>initiated are subjected to flagellations, fastings, and other<lb break="yes"/>painful exercises. There are but a small number<lb break="yes"/>of those sacred trumpets. Sometimes the Great<lb break="yes"/>Spirit <hi rendition="#i" >(Cachimana)</hi> himself makes the <hi rendition="#i">botuto</hi> resound;<lb break="yes"/>sometimes he is content to manifest his will by him, to<lb break="yes"/>whom the keeping of the instrument is intrusted. These<lb break="yes"/>juggleries being very ancient (from fathers of our fathers,<lb break="yes"/>say the Indians), we must not be surprised, that some in-<lb break="no"/>credulous are already to be found; but these express<lb break="yes"/>their disbelief of the mysteries of the <hi rendition="#i" >botuto</hi> only in whis-<lb break="no"/>pers. Women are not permitted to see this marvellous<lb break="yes"/>instrument; and are excluded from all the ceremonies of<lb break="yes"/>this worship. If a woman have the misfortune to see the<lb break="yes"/>trumpet, she is put to death without mercy.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The nations of America, except those which border on<lb break="yes"/>the polar circle, from a single race, characterized by the<lb break="yes"/>formation of the scull, the colour of the skin, the extreme<lb break="yes"/>thinness of the beard, and straight and glossy hair. The<lb break="yes"/>American race bears a very striking resemblance to that<lb break="yes"/>of the Mongul nations, which include the descendants of<lb break="yes"/>the Hiong-Nu, known heretofore by the name of Huns,<lb break="yes"/>the Kilkas, the Kalmucks, and the Burats. It has been<lb break="yes"/>ascertained, by late observations, that not only the in-<lb break="no"/>habitants of Unalashka, but several tribes of South<lb break="yes"/>America, indicate, by the osteological characters of the<lb break="yes"/>head, a passage from the American to the Mongul race.<lb break="yes"/>When we shall have more completely studied the brown<lb break="yes"/>men of Africa, and that swarm of nations, who inhabit<lb break="yes"/>the interior and north-east of Asia, and who are vaguely<lb break="yes"/>described by systematic travellers under the name of<lb break="yes"/>Tartars and Tschoudes, the Caucasian, Mongul, Ame-<lb break="no"/>rican, Malay, and Negro races, will appear less insulated,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb facs="#f0024"/>
                    <pb facs="#f0025"/>
                    <pb n="669" facs="#f0026"/>and we shall acknowledge, in this great family of the<lb break="yes"/>human race, one single organic type, modified by cir-<lb break="no"/>cumstances which perhaps will never remain unknown.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#g">LANGUAGE.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The number of languages, which distinguish the dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent native tribes, appears still more considerable in the<lb break="yes"/>new continent than in Africa, where, according to the late<lb break="yes" />researches of Messrs. Seetzen and Vater, there are above<lb break="yes" />one hundred and forty. In this respect, the whole of<lb break="yes" />America resembles Caucasus, Italy before the conquest<lb break="yes"/>of the Romans, Asia Minor when that country contained,<lb break="yes"/>on a small extent of territory, the Cilicians of Semitic<lb break="yes"/>race, the Phrygians of Thracian origin, the Lydians, and<lb break="yes"/>the Celts. The configuration of the soil, the strength of<lb break="yes" />vegetation, the apprehensions of the mountaineers under<lb break="yes" />the tropics of exposing themselves to the burning heat of<lb break="yes" />the plains, are obstacles to communication, and contribute<lb break="yes" />to the amazing variety of American dialects.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>In eighty-three American languages, one hundred and<lb break="yes"/>seventy words have been found, the roots of which appear<lb break="yes"/>to be the same; and it is easy to perceive, that this analogy<lb break="yes"/>is not accidental, since it does not rest merely on imitative<lb break="yes" />harmony, or on that conformity in the organs, which pro-<lb break="no" />duces almost a prefect identity in the first sounds articu-<lb break="no" />lated by children. Of these one hundred and seventy<lb break="yes"/>words, which have this connexion with each other, three<lb break="yes"/>fifths resemble the Mantchou, the Tongouse, the Mongul,<lb break="yes"/>and the Samoyede; and two fifths the Celtic and Tschoud,<lb break="yes"/>the Biscayan, the Coptic, and the Congo languages.</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#g">MEXICAN TEMPLES.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Among those swarms of nations, which, from the seventh<lb break="yes"/>to the twelfth century of the Christian era, successively<lb break="yes"/>inhabited the country of Mexico, five are enumerated; the<lb break="yes"/>Toltecks, the Cicimecks, the Acoluhans, the Tlascaltecks,<lb break="yes"/>and the Aztecks, who, notwithstanding their political divi-<lb break="no"/>sions, spoke the same language, followed the same worship,<lb break="yes"/>and built pyramidal edifices, which they regarded as <hi rendition="#i">teo-<lb break="no"/>callis,</hi> that is to say, the houses of their gods. These<lb break="yes"/>edifices were all of the same form, though of very different<lb break="yes"/>dimensions; they were pyramids, with several terraces,<lb break="yes"/>and the sides of which stood exactly in the direction of the<lb break="yes"/>meridian, and the parallel of the place. The Teocalli at<lb break="yes"/>Cholula was raised in the midst of a square and walled<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="670" facs="#f0027"/>enclosure, which, somewhat like those of the Greeks, con-<lb break="no"/>tained gardens, fountains, the dwellings of the priests, and<lb break="yes"/>sometimes arsenals; since each house of a Mexican divini-<lb break="no"/>ty, like the ancient temple of Baal Berith, burnt by Abi-<lb break="no"/>melech, was a strong place. A great staircase led to the<lb break="yes"/>top of the truncated pyramid, and on the summit of the<lb break="yes"/>platform were one or two chapels, built like towers, which<lb break="yes"/>contained the colossal idols of the divinity, to whom the<lb break="yes"/>teocalli was dedicated. This part of the edifice must be<lb break="yes"/>considered as the most consecrated place; and it was there<lb break="yes"/>that the priests kept up the sacred fire. From the peculiar<lb break="yes"/>construction of the edifice we have just described, the<lb break="yes"/>priest who offered the sacrifice was seen by a great mass of<lb break="yes"/>the people at the same time: the procession of the <hi rendition="#i">teo-<lb break="no"/>pixqui,</hi> ascending or descending the staircase of the pyramid,<lb break="yes"/>was beheld at a considerable distance. The inside of the<lb break="yes"/>edifice was the burial place of the kings and principal per-<lb break="no"/>sonages of Mexico. It is impossible to read the descrip-<lb break="no"/>tions, which Herodotus and Diodorus Siculus have left us,<lb break="yes"/>of the temple of Jupiter Belus, without being struck with<lb break="yes"/>the resemblance of that Babylonian monument to the<lb break="yes"/>teocallis of Anahuac at Cholula.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The teocalli of Mexico was dedicated to Tezcatlipoca,<lb break="yes"/>the first of the Azteck divinities after Teotl, who is the<lb break="yes" />supreme and invisible being; and to Huitzilopochtli, the<lb break="yes" />god of war. It was built by the Aztecks, on the model of<lb break="yes" />the pyramids of Teotihuacan, six years only before the dis-<lb break="no" />covery of America by Christopher Columbus. This<lb break="yes"/>truncated pyramid, called by Cortez the principle temple,<lb break="yes"/>was a hundred and ten yards in breadth at its basis, and<lb break="yes"/>nearly sixty yards in height.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A remarkable tradition still exists among the Indians<lb break="yes"/>of Cholula, according to which the great pyramid was not<lb break="yes" />originally destined to serve for the worship of Quetzalcoatl.<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Before the great inundation which took place four thou-<lb break="no"/>sand eight hundred years after the creation of the World,<lb break="yes"/>the country of Anahuac was inhabited by giants (tzocuil-<lb break="no"/>lixeque). All those who did not perish were transformed<lb break="yes"/>into fishes, save seven, who fled into caverns. When the<lb break="yes"/>waters subsided, one of these giants, Xelhua, surnamed the<lb break="yes"/>architect, went to <choice><sic>Cholala</sic><corr type="editorial">Cholula</corr></choice>: where, as a memorial of the<lb break="yes"/>mountain Tlaloc, which had served for an asylum to him-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb facs="#f0028"/>
                        <pb facs="#f0029"/>
                        <pb n="671" facs="#f0030"/>self and his six brethren, he built an artificial hill in form of<lb break="yes"/>a pyramid. He ordered bricks to be made in the province<lb break="yes"/>of Tlamanalco, at the foot of the Sierra of Cocotl, and to<lb break="yes"/>convey them to Cholula he placed a file of men, who pas-<lb break="no"/>sed them from hand to hand. The gods beheld with wrath<lb break="yes"/>this edifice, the top of which was to reach the clouds.<lb break="yes"/>Irritated at the daring attempt of Xelhua, they hurled fire<lb break="yes"/>on the pyramid. Numbers of the workmen perished; the<lb break="yes"/>work was discontinued, and the monument was afterwards<lb break="yes"/>dedicated to Quetzalcoatl, the god of the air.&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The size of the platform of the pyramid of Cholula, on<lb break="yes"/>which I made a great number of astronomical observations,<lb break="yes"/>is four thousand eight hundred square yards. From it the<lb break="yes"/>eye ranges over a magnificent prospect: Popocatepetl,<lb break="yes"/>Iztaccihuatl, the peak of Orizaba, and the Sierra de Tlas-<lb break="no"/>calla, famous for the tempests, which gather around its<lb break="yes"/>summit. We view at the same time three mountains higher<lb break="yes"/>than Mount Blanc, two of which are still burning vol-<lb break="no"/>canoes. A small chapel, surrounded with cypress, and<lb break="yes"/>dedicated to the Virgin de los Remedios, has succeeded to<lb break="yes"/>the temple of the god of the air, or the Mexican Indra.<lb break="yes"/>An ecclesiastic of the Indian race celebrates mass every<lb break="yes"/>day on the top of this antique monument.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>When we compare the Mexican paintings with the<lb break="yes"/>hieroglyphics that decorated the temples, the obelisks, and<lb break="yes"/>perhaps even the pyramids of Egypt; and reflect on the<lb break="yes"/>progressive steps which the human mind appears to have<lb break="yes"/>followed in the invention of graphic means fitted to ex-<lb break="no"/>press ideas; we see that the nations of America were very<lb break="yes"/>distant from that perfection which the Egyptians had ob-<lb break="no"/>tained. Among the Mexican people the figures and sym-<lb break="no"/>bolic characters were not traced on separate leaves.<lb break="yes"/>Whatever was the substance employed for manuscripts,<lb break="yes"/>they were seldom destined to form rolls, but were almost<lb break="yes"/>always folded in zigzag, in a particular manner, like the<lb break="yes"/>mounts of our fans.</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#g">THE ANDES.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We distinguished three kinds of principal forms belonging<lb break="yes"/>to the high tops of the Andes. The volcanoes which are<lb break="yes"/>yet burning, those which have but a single crater of ex-<lb break="no" />traordinary size, are conic mountains, with summits trun-<lb break="no" />cated in a greater or less degree: such is the figure of<lb break="yes"/>Cotopaxi, of Popocatepec, and the Peak of Orizaba. Vol-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="672" facs="#f0031"/>canoes, the summits of which have sunk after a long series<lb break="yes"/>of eruptions, exhibit ridges bristled with points, needles<lb break="yes"/>leaning in different directions, and broken rocks falling into<lb break="yes"/>ruins. Such is the form of the Altar, or Capac-Urcu, a<lb break="yes"/>mountain once more lofty than Chimborazo, and the de-<lb break="no"/>struction of which is considered as a memorable period in the<lb break="yes"/>natural history of the New Continent; such is the form<lb break="yes"/>also of Carguairazo, a great part of which fell in on the<lb break="yes"/>night of the 19th of July, 1698. Torrents of water and<lb break="yes"/>mud then issued from the opened sides of the mountain, and<lb break="yes"/>laid waste the neighbouring country. This dreadful ca-<lb break="no"/>tastrophe was accompanied by an earthquake, which, in<lb break="yes"/>the adjacent towns of Hambato, and Llactacunga, swal-<lb break="no"/>lowed up thousands of inhabitants.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A third form of the high tops of the Andes, and the most<lb break="yes" />majestic of the whole, is that of Chimborazo, the summit<lb break="yes" />of which is circular; it reminds us of those paps without<lb break="yes" />craters, which the elastic force of the vapours swell up in<lb break="yes" />regions where the hollow crust of the globe is mined<lb break="yes"/>by subterraneous fires. The aspect of mountains of gra-<lb break="no"/>nite has little analogy with that of Chimborazo. The<lb break="yes"/>granitic summits are flattened hemispheres; the trappean<lb break="yes"/>porphyry forms slender cupolas. Thus on the shore of<lb break="yes"/>the South Sea, after the long rains of winter, when the<lb break="yes"/>transparency of the air has suddenly increased, we see<lb break="yes"/>Chimborazo appear like a cloud in the horizon; it detaches<lb break="yes"/>itself from the neighbouring summits, and towers over<lb break="yes"/>the whole chain of the Andes. The bulk of Chimborazo<lb break="yes"/>is so enormous, that the part which the eye embraces at<lb break="yes"/>once near the limit of the eternal snows is five miles in<lb break="yes"/>breadth. The extreme rarity of the strata of air, across<lb break="yes"/>which we see the tops of the Andes, contributes greatly to<lb break="yes"/>the splendour of the snow, and the magical effect of its<lb break="yes"/>reflection. Under the tropics, at the height of three miles<lb break="yes"/>the azure vault of the sky appears of an indigo tint. The<lb break="yes"/>outlines of the mountain detach themselves from the sky in<lb break="yes"/>this pure and transparent atmosphere, while the inferior<lb break="yes"/>strata of the air, reposing on a plain destitute of vegetation<lb break="yes"/>which reflects the radiant heat, are vaporous, and appear<lb break="yes"/>to veil the middle ground of the landscape.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>At a height superior to that of Mount Blanc, on the sum-<lb break="no"/>mit of the Andes, they found petrified sea shells; fossil<lb break="yes"/>bones of elephants are spread over the equinoctial re-<lb break="no"/>gions; and, what is very remarkable, they are not dis-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="673" facs="#f0032"/>covered at the feet of the paim-trees in the burning plains<lb break="yes"/>of the Oroonoco, but on the coldest and most elevated<lb break="yes"/>regions of the Cordilleras; and in the new world, as well as<lb break="yes"/>in the old, generations of species long extinct have pre-<lb break="no"/>ceded those which now people the earth, the waters, and<lb break="yes"/>the air.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Cotopaxi is the loftiest of those volcanoes of the<lb break="yes"/>Andes, which at recent epochs have undergone eruptions.<lb break="yes"/>Its absolute height is five thousand seven hundred and<lb break="yes" />fifty-four metres (two thousand nine hundred and fifty-two<lb break="yes" />toises); it is double that of Canigou; and consequently<lb break="yes" />eight hundred metres higher than Vesuvius would be, were<lb break="yes" />it placed on the top of the peak of Teneriffe. Cotopaxi is<lb break="yes" />also the most dreadful volcano of the kingdom of Quito,<lb break="yes" />and its explosions are the most frequent and disastrous. The<lb break="yes"/>mass of scori&#x00E6;, and the huge pieces of rock, thrown out of<lb break="yes"/>this volcano, which are spread over the neighbouring val-<lb break="no"/>leys, covering a surface of several square leagues, would<lb break="yes"/>form, were they heaped together, a colossal mountain.<lb break="yes"/>In 1738 the flames of Cotopaxi rose one thousand yards<lb break="yes"/>above the brink of the crater. In 1744 the roarings of the<lb break="yes"/>volcano were heard as far as Honda, a town on the borders<lb break="yes"/>of the Magdalena, and at the distance of four hundred<lb break="yes"/>miles. On the 4th of April, 1768, the quantity of ashes<lb break="yes"/>ejected by the mouth of Cotopaxi was so great, that in the<lb break="yes"/>towns of Hambato and Tacunga day broke only at three<lb break="yes"/>in the afternoon, and the inhabitants were obliged to use<lb break="yes"/>lanterns in walking the streets. The explosion which took<lb break="yes"/>place in the month of January, 1803, was preceded by a<lb break="yes"/>dreadful phenomenon, the sudden melting of the snows<lb break="yes"/>that covered the mountain. At the port of Guayaquil,<lb break="yes"/>one hundred and fifty miles distant in a straight line from<lb break="yes"/>the crater, we heard, day and night, the noises of the vol-<lb break="no"/>cano, like continued discharges of a battery; we distin-<lb break="no"/>guished these tremendous sounds even on the Pacific<lb break="yes"/>Ocean, to the south-west of the island of Puna.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The form of Cotopaxi is the most beautiful and regular<lb break="yes"/>of the colossal summits of the high Andes. It is a perfect<lb break="yes"/>cone, which, covered with an enormous layer of snow,<lb break="yes"/>shines with dazzling splendour at the setting of the sun,<lb break="yes"/>and detaches itself in the most picturesque manner from<lb break="yes"/>the azure vault of heaven.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 