<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="98" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">THE COW TREE.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mr. Humboldt, in his Personal Narrative, gives the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#et">following account of this wonder of the vegetable<lb break="yes"/>world.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Amid the great number of curious phenom-<lb break="no"/>ena which have presented themselves to me<lb break="yes"/>in the course of my travels, I confess there<lb break="yes"/>are few that have so powerfully affected<lb break="yes"/>my imagination, as the aspect of the <hi rendition="#i">cow<lb break="yes" />tree.</hi> Whatever regards corn, inspires an<lb break="yes"/>interest, which is not merely that of the<lb break="yes"/>physical knowledge of things, but is con-<lb break="no"/>nected with another order of ideas and senti-<lb break="no"/>ments. We can scarcely conceive how the hu-<lb break="no"/>man race could exist without farinaceous sub-<lb break="no"/>stances, and without that nourishing juice<lb break="yes"/>which the breast of the mother contains, and<lb break="yes"/>which is appropriated to the long feebleness of<lb break="yes"/>the infant. The amylaceous matter of corn, the<lb break="yes" />object of religious veneration among so many<lb break="yes"/>nations, ancient and modern, is diffused in the<lb break="yes"/>seeds and deposited in the roots of vegeta-<lb break="no"/>bles&#x2014;milk, which serves us as an aliment,<lb break="yes"/>appears to us exclusively the produce of ani-<lb break="no" />mal organization. Such are the impressions<lb break="yes"/>we have received in our earliest infancy;<lb break="yes"/>such is also the source of that astonish-<lb break="no"/>ment which seizes us at the aspect of the<lb break="yes"/>tree just described. It is not here the solemn<lb break="yes" />shades of forests, the majestic course of rivers,<lb break="yes"/>the mountains wrapped in eternal frosts, that<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>excite our emotion. A few drops of vegeta-<lb break="no"/>ble juice recall to our minds all the powerful-<lb break="no"/>ness and fecundity of nature. On the barren<lb break="yes"/>flank of a rock grows a tree with coriaceous<lb break="yes"/>and dry leaves. Its large woody roots can<lb break="yes" />scarcely penetrate into the stone. For seve-<lb break="no"/>ral months of the year not a single shower<lb break="yes"/>moistens its foliage. Its branches appear<lb break="yes"/>dead and dried; but when its trunk is pierced,<lb break="yes"/>there flows from it a sweet and nourishing<lb break="yes" />milk. It is at the rising of the sun that this<lb break="yes"/>vegetable fountain is most abundant. The<lb break="yes"/>blacks and natives are then seen hastening<lb break="yes"/>from all quarters; furnished with large bowls<lb break="yes"/>to receive the milk, which grows yellow, and<lb break="yes" />thickens at its surface. Some employ their<lb break="yes"/>bowls under the tree itself, others carry the<lb break="yes"/>juice home to their children. We seem to<lb break="yes"/>see the family of a shepherd, who distributes<lb break="yes"/>the milk to his flock.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have described the sensation which the<lb break="yes"/>cow tree awakes in the mind of the traveler,<lb break="yes"/>at the first view. In examining the physical<lb break="yes"/>properties of animal and vegetable products,<lb break="yes"/>science displays them as closely linked to-<lb break="no" />gether; but it strips them of what is marvel-<lb break="no"/>lous, and perhaps also a part of their charms,<lb break="yes"/>of what excited our astonishment. Nothing<lb break="yes"/>appears isolated; the chemical principles that<lb break="yes"/>were believed to be peculiar to animals are<lb break="yes" />found in plants; a common chain links together<lb break="yes"/>all organic nature.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 