<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">A man giving suck</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:52</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.47</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1818-Curious_Circumstance-03-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-03-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Curious_Circumstance-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>"From Humboldt’s Personal Travels." Alexander von Humboldt, Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 1, S. 376–378.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">A man giving suck</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1819</date>
          <pubPlace>Boston, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in:&lt;i&gt; New-England Galaxy &amp;amp; Masonic Magazine&lt;/i&gt; 2:73 (26. Februar 1819), S. 78.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div n="1">
                <head>A MAN GIVING SUCK.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#i">From Humboldt&#x2019;s Personal Travels.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the village of Arenas, on the road from<lb break="yes"/>San Fernando to Cumana, lives a labourer,<lb break="yes"/>Francisco Lozano, who presented a physiolog-<lb break="no"/>ical phenomenon, highly calculated to strike<lb break="yes"/>the imagination, though it is very conformable<lb break="yes" />to the known laws of organized nature. This<lb break="yes"/>man has suckled a child with his own milk.<lb break="yes"/>The mother having fallen sick, the father, to<lb break="yes"/>quiet the infant, took it into his bed, and press-<lb break="no"/>ed it to his bosom. Lozano, then thirty-two<lb break="yes" />years of age, had never remarked till that<lb break="yes"/>day that he had milk: but the irritation of the<lb break="yes"/>nipple, sucked by the child, caused the accu-<lb break="no"/>mulation of that liquid. The milk was thick<lb break="yes"/>and very sweet. The father, astonished at the<lb break="yes" />increased size of his breast, suckled his child<lb break="yes"/>two or three times a day during five months.<lb break="yes"/>He drew on himself the attention of his neigh-<lb break="no"/>bours, but he never thought, as he probably<lb break="yes"/>would in Europe, of deriving any advantage<lb break="yes"/>from the curiosity he excited. We saw the<lb break="yes"/>certificate which had been drawn up on the<lb break="yes"/>spot, to attest this remarkable fact, eye-wit-<lb break="no"/>nesses of which are still living. They assur-<lb break="no"/>ed us, that, during this suckling, the child had<lb break="yes" />no other nourishment than the milk of his fa-<lb break="no"/>ther. Lozano, who was not at Arenas during<lb break="yes"/>our journey in the Missions, came to us at Cu-<lb break="no"/>mana. He was accompanied by his son, who<lb break="yes" />was then thirteen or fourteen years of age.<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Bonpland examined with attention the fa-<lb break="no"/>ther&#x2019;s breast, and found it wrinkled like those<lb break="yes"/>of women who have given suck. He observed,<lb break="yes"/>that the left breast in particular was much<lb break="yes"/>enlarged; which Lozano explained to us from<lb break="yes"/>the circumstance, that the two breasts did not<lb break="yes"/>furnish milk in the same abundance. Don Vi-<lb break="no"/>cente Emparan, governor of the province, sent<lb break="yes"/>a circumstantial account of this phenomenon<lb break="yes"/>to Cadiz.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is not a very uncommon circumstance, to<lb break="yes"/>find, both among human-kind and animals,<lb break="yes"/>males whose breasts contain milk; and the<lb break="yes"/>climate does not appear to exert any marked<lb break="yes"/>influence on the more or less abundance of this<lb break="yes" />secretion. The ancients cite the milk of the<lb break="yes"/>he goats of Lemnos and Corsica. In our own<lb break="yes"/>time, we have seen in the country of Hanover,<lb break="yes"/>a he goat, which for a great number of years<lb break="yes"/>was milked every other day, and yielded more<lb break="yes" />milk than a female goat. Among the signs of<lb break="yes"/>the pretended weakness of the Americans, trav-<lb break="no"/>ellers have mentioned the milk contained in<lb break="yes"/>the breasts of men. It is however improbable,<lb break="yes"/>that it has ever been observed in a whole tribe,<lb break="yes" />in some part of America unknown to modern<lb break="yes"/>travellers; and I can affirm, that at present it<lb break="yes"/>is not more common in the new continent, than<lb break="yes"/>in the old. The labourer of Arenas, whose<lb break="yes"/>history we have just related, is not of the cop-<lb break="no" />per-coloured race of Chayma Indians: he is a<lb break="yes"/>white man, descended from Europeans. More-<lb break="no"/>over, the anatomists of Petersburg have observ-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb facs="#f0001"/>ed, that among the lower orders of the people<lb break="yes" />in Russia, milk in the breasts of men is much<lb break="yes"/>more frequent than among the more southern<lb break="yes"/>nations; and the Russians have never been<lb break="yes"/>deemed weak and effeminate.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There exists among the varieties of our kind<lb break="yes"/>a race of men, whose breasts at the age of pu-<lb break="no"/>berty acquire a considerable bulk. Lozano<lb break="yes"/>did not belong to this class; and he often<lb break="yes"/>repeated to us, that it was only the irritation of<lb break="yes"/>the nipple, in consequence of the suction, which<lb break="yes" />caused the flow of the milk. This confirms<lb break="yes"/>the observation of the ancients, &#x201C;that men,<lb break="yes"/>who have a small quantity of milk, yield it in<lb break="yes"/>abundance, when their breasts are sucked.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>These singular effects of a nervous stimulant<lb break="yes"/>were known to the shepherds of Greece; those<lb break="yes"/>of Mount Oeta rubbed the dugs of the young<lb break="yes" />goats, that had not yet conceived, with nettles,<lb break="yes"/>to make them produce milk.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When we reflect on the whole of the vital<lb break="yes"/>phenomena, we find, that no one of them is en-<lb break="no"/>tirely isolated. In every age examples are<lb break="yes"/>cited of young girls not marriageable, or wo-<lb break="no"/>men withered by age, who have suckled child-<lb break="no" />ren.&#x2014;Among men these examples are infinite-<lb break="no"/>ly more rare; and after numerous researches,<lb break="yes"/>I have not found above two or three. One is<lb break="yes"/>cited by the anatomist of Verona, Alexander<lb break="yes"/>Benedictus, who lived toward the end of the<lb break="yes" />fifteenth century. He relates the history of an<lb break="yes"/>inhabitant of Syria, who, to calm the uneasi-<lb break="no"/>ness of his child, after the death of the mother,<lb break="yes"/>pressed it to his bosom. The milk immediate-<lb break="no"/>ly came with such abundance, that the father<lb break="yes"/>could take on himself the nourishment of his<lb break="yes" />child, without assistance. Other examples are<lb break="yes"/>related by Santorellus, Paria, and Robert,<lb break="yes"/>bishop of Cork&#x2014;The greater part of these<lb break="yes"/>phenomena having been noticed in times very<lb break="yes"/>remote, it is not uninteresting to physiology,<lb break="yes"/>that we can confirm them in our own days.<lb break="yes" />Besides, they bear very strongly on the long<lb break="yes"/>disputed question respecting final causes. The<lb break="yes"/>existence of the nipple in men has long puz-<lb break="no"/>zled philosophers; and it has even been re-<lb break="no"/>cently affirmed, &#x201C;that nature has refused to<lb break="yes"/>one of the sexes the faculty of suckling, be-<lb break="no" />cause this faculty would not accord with the<lb break="yes"/>dignity of man.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 