<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>THE COW TREE.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mr. Humboldt, in the fourth volume of<lb break="yes"/>his personal Narrative, gives the following<lb break="yes"/>account of this wonder of the vegetable<lb break="yes"/>world in South-America:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Amid the great number of curious<lb break="yes"/>phenomena which have presented them-<lb break="no"/>selves to me in the course of my travels, I<lb break="yes"/>confess there are few that have so power-<lb break="no"/>fully affected my imagination as the as-<lb break="no"/>pect of the cow tree. Whatever relates<lb break="yes"/>to milk, whatever regards corn, inspires<lb break="yes"/>an interest, which is not merely that of<lb break="yes"/>the physical knowledge of things, but is<lb break="yes"/>connected with another order of ideas and<lb break="yes"/>sentiments. We can scarcely conceive<lb break="yes"/>how the human race could exist without<lb break="yes" />farinaceous <choice>
                        <sic>substrnces</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">substances</corr>
                    </choice> and without that<lb break="yes"/>nourishing juice which the breast of<lb break="yes"/>the mother contains, and which is appro-<lb break="no" />priated to the long feebleness of the in-<lb break="no"/>fant. The amylaceous matter of corn,<lb break="yes"/>the object of religious veneration among<lb break="yes"/>so many nations, ancient and modern, is<lb break="yes" />diffused in the seeds, and deposited in the<lb break="yes"/>roots of vegetables; milk, which serves<lb break="yes"/>us as an aliment, appears to us exclusive-<lb break="no"/>ly the produce of animal organization.<lb break="yes"/>Such are the impressions we have receiv-<lb break="no"/>ed in our earliest infancy; such is also<lb break="yes"/>the source of that astonishment which<lb break="yes"/>seizes us at the aspect of the tree just de-<lb break="no"/>scribed. It is not here the solemn shades of<lb break="yes"/>forests, the majestic course of rivers, the<lb break="yes"/>mountains wrapped in eternal frost, that<lb break="yes"/>excite our emotion. A few drops of ve-<lb break="no"/>getable juice recall to our minds all the<lb break="yes"/>powerfulness and fecundity of nature. On<lb break="yes" />the barren flank of a rock grows a tree<lb break="yes"/>with coriaceous and dry leaves. Its<lb break="yes"/>large woody roots can scarcely penetrate<lb break="yes"/>into the stone. For several months of<lb break="yes"/>the year not a single shower moistens its<lb break="yes"/>foilage.&#x2014;Its branches appear dead and<lb break="yes"/>dried; but when its trunk is pierced<lb break="yes"/>there flows from it a sweet and nourish-<lb break="no"/>ing milk. It is at the rising of the sun<lb break="yes"/>that this vegetable fountain is most abun-<lb break="no"/>dant. The blacks and natives are then<lb break="yes"/>seen hastening from all quarters, furnish-<lb break="no"/>ed with large bowls to receive the milk,<lb break="yes"/>which grows yellow, and thickens at its<lb break="yes"/>surface. Some employ their bowls un-<lb break="no"/>der the tree itself; others carry the juice<lb break="yes"/>home to their children. We seem to see<lb break="yes"/>the family of a shepherd, who distributes<lb break="yes"/>the milk to his flock.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;I have described the sensation which<lb break="yes"/>the cow tree awakens in the mind of the<lb break="yes"/>traveller at the first view. In examining<lb break="yes"/>the physical properties of animal and ve-<lb break="no" />getable products, science displays them as<lb break="yes"/>closely linked together; but it strips them<lb break="yes"/>of what is marvellous, and perhaps also of<lb break="yes"/>a part of their charms, of what excited<lb break="yes" />our astonishment.&#x2014;Nothing appears iso-<lb break="no"/>lated; the chemical principles that were<lb break="yes"/>believed to be peculiar to animals are<lb break="yes"/>found in plants; a common chain links<lb break="yes" />together all organic nature.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 