<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">The Great Cavern of Guacharo, in South America</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:52</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.46</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-06-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-02.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-03.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-06-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1818-Cavern_of_Guacharo-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 1, S. 413–422.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">The Great Cavern of Guacharo, in South America</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1826</date>
          <pubPlace>New York City, New York</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: John L. Blake, &lt;i&gt;A Geographical, Chronological, and Historical Atlas, on a New and Improved Plan; or, a View of the Present State of All the Empires, Kingdoms, States, and Colonies in the Known World&lt;/i&gt;, New York: Cooke and Co. 1826, S. 74.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Fußnoten mit Asterisken und Kreuzen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="74" facs="#f0001"/><cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">The Great Cavern of Guacharo, in South America.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">Abridged from the Personal Narrative of Humboldt, <hi rendition="#i">vol.</hi> iii.</note>&#x2014;</head>
                <p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>The Cueva del Guacharo is pierced in the vertical profile<lb break="yes"/>of a rock. The entrance is toward the south, and forms<lb break="yes"/>a vault eighty feet broad, and seventy-two feet high.<lb break="yes"/>The rock, that surmounts the grotto, is covered with<lb break="yes"/>trees of gigantic height. The mammee-tree, and the<lb break="yes"/>genipa with large and shining leaves, raise their branches<lb break="yes"/>vertically towards the sky; while those of the courbaril<lb break="yes"/>and the erythrina form, as they extend themselves, a<lb break="yes"/>thick vault of verdure. Plants of the family of pothos<lb break="yes"/>with succulent stems, oxalises, and orchide&#x00E6; of a singu-<lb break="no"/>lar structure, rise in the driest cliffs of the rocks; while<lb break="yes"/>creeping plants, waving in the winds, are interwoven in<lb break="yes"/>festoons before the opening of the cavern. We distin-<lb break="no"/>guished in these festoons a bignonia of a violet blue, the<lb break="yes"/>purple dolichos, and for the first time that magnificent<lb break="yes"/>olandra, the orange flower of which has a fleshy tube<lb break="yes"/>more than four inches long. The entrances of grottoes,<lb break="yes"/>like the view of cascades, derive their principal charm<lb break="yes"/>from the situation, more or less majestic, in which they<lb break="yes"/>are placed, and which in some sort determines the cha-<lb break="no"/>racter of the landscape. What a contrast between the<lb break="yes"/>Cueva of Caripe, and those caverns of the north crowned<lb break="yes"/>with oaks and gloomy larch-trees!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But this luxury of vegetation embellishes not only the<lb break="yes"/>outside of the vault, it appears even in the vestibule of the<lb break="yes"/>grotto. We saw with astonishment, plantain-leaved heli-<lb break="no"/>conias eighteen feet high, the praga palm-tree, and arbo-<lb break="no"/>rescent arums, follow the banks of the river even to those<lb break="yes"/>subterranean places. The vegetation continues in the<lb break="yes"/>cave of Caripe, as in those deep crevices of the Andes,<lb break="yes"/>half excluded from the light of day; and does not disap-<lb break="no"/>pear, till, advancing into the interior, we reach thirty or<lb break="yes"/>forty paces from the entrance. We measured the way by<lb break="yes"/>means of a cord: and we went on about four hundred<lb break="yes"/>and thirty feet, without being obliged to light our torches.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Daylight penetrates into this region, because the grotto<lb break="yes"/>forms but one single channel, which keeps the same di-<lb break="no"/>rection from south-east to north-west. Where the light<lb break="yes"/>begins to fail, we heard from afar the hoarse sounds of<lb break="yes"/>the nocturnal birds, sounds which the natives think be-<lb break="no"/>long exclusively to those subterraneous places. The gua-<lb break="no"/>charo is of the size of our fowls, has the mouth of the<lb break="yes"/>goatsuckers and procnias, and the port of those vultures,<lb break="yes"/>the crooked beak of which is surrounded with stiff silky<lb break="yes"/>hairs. It forms a new genus, very different from the<lb break="yes"/>goatsucker by the force of its voice, by the considerable<lb break="yes"/>strength of its beak, containing a double tooth, by its feet<lb break="yes"/>without the membranes that unite the anterior phalanxes<lb break="yes"/>of the claws. In its manners it has analogies both with<lb break="yes"/>the goatsuckers and the alpine crow. The plumage of<lb break="yes"/>the guacharo is of a dark bluish-gray, mixed with small<lb break="yes"/><cb/>streaks and specks of black. It is difficult to form an<lb break="yes"/>idea of the horrible noise occasioned by thousands of<lb break="yes"/>these birds in the dark part of the cavern, and which can<lb break="yes"/>only be compared to the croaking of our crows, which,<lb break="yes"/>in the pine forests of the north, live in society, and con-<lb break="no"/>struct their nests upon trees, the tops of which touch<lb break="yes"/>each other. The shrill and piercing cries of the guacha-<lb break="no"/>roes strike upon the vaults of the rocks, and are repeated<lb break="yes"/>by the echo in the depth of the cavern. The Indians<lb break="yes"/>showed us the nests of these birds, by fixing torches to the<lb break="yes"/>end of a long pole. These nests were fifty or sixty feet<lb break="yes"/>high above our heads, in holes in the shape of funnels,<lb break="yes"/>with which the roof of the grotto is pierced like a sieve.<lb break="yes"/>The noise increased as we advanced, and the birds were<lb break="yes"/>affrighted by the light of the torches of copal. When this<lb break="yes"/>noise ceased around us, we heard at a distance the plain-<lb break="no"/>tive cries of the birds roosting in other ramifications of<lb break="yes"/>the cavern. It seemed as if these bands answered each<lb break="yes"/>other alternately.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Indians enter into the Cueva del Guacharo once<lb break="yes"/>a-year, near midsummer, armed with poles, by means of<lb break="yes"/>which they destroy the greater part of the nests. At this<lb break="yes"/>season several thousands of birds are killed; and the old<lb break="yes"/>ones, to defend their brood, hover around the heads of the<lb break="yes"/>savage Indians, uttering terrible cries, which would appal<lb break="yes"/>any heart but that of man in an untutored state.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We followed, as we continued our progress through the<lb break="yes"/>cavern, the banks of the small river which issued from it,<lb break="yes"/>and is from twenty-eight to thirty feet wide. We walked<lb break="yes"/>on the banks, as far as the hills formed of calcareous in-<lb break="no"/>crustations permitted us. When the torrent winds among<lb break="yes"/>very high masses of stalactites, we were often obliged to<lb break="yes"/>descend into its bed, which is only two feet in depth.<lb break="yes"/>We learnt with surprise, that this subterraneous rivulet<lb break="yes"/>is the origin of the river Caripe, which, at a few leagues<lb break="yes"/>distance, after having joined the small river of Santa<lb break="yes"/>Maria, is navigable for canoes. It enters into the river<lb break="yes"/>Areo under the name of <hi rendition="#i">Canno de Terezen.</hi> We found<lb break="yes"/>on the banks of the subterraneous rivulet a great quantity<lb break="yes"/>of palm-tree wood, the remains of trunks, on which the<lb break="yes"/>Indians climb to reach the nests hanging to the roofs of<lb break="yes"/>the cavern. The rings, formed by the vestiges of the old<lb break="yes"/>footstalks of the leaves, furnish as it were the <choice>
                        <sic>foosteps</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">footsteps</corr>
                    </choice> of<lb break="yes"/>a ladder perpendicularly placed.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The grotto of Caripe preserves the same direction, the<lb break="yes"/>same breadth, and its primitive height of sixty or seventy<lb break="yes"/>feet, to the distance of 1,458 feet, accurately measured.<lb break="yes"/>I have never seen a cavern in either continent of so uni-<lb break="no"/>form and regular a construction. We had great difficulty<lb break="yes"/>in persuading the Indians to pass beyond the outer part<lb break="yes"/>of the grotto, the only part which they annually visit to<lb break="yes"/>collect the fat. The whole authority of <hi rendition="#i">los padres</hi> was<lb break="yes"/>necessary, to induce them to advance as far as the spot<lb break="yes"/>where the soil rises abruptly at an inclination of sixty de-<lb break="no"/>grees, and where the torrent forms a small subterraneous<lb break="yes"/>cascade.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">We find this phenomenon of a subterranean cascade, but on a<lb break="yes" />much larger scale, in England, at Yordas cave, near Kingsdale, in<lb break="yes"/>Yorkshire.</note> The natives connect mystic ideas with this<lb break="yes"/>cave, inhabited by nocturnal birds; they believe, that the<lb break="yes"/>souls of their ancestors sojourn in the deep recesses of the<lb break="yes"/>cavern. &#x201C;Man,&#x201D; say they, &#x201C;should avoid places which<lb break="yes"/>are enlightened neither by the Sun nor by the Moon.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>To go and join the guacharoes, is to rejoin their fathers,<lb break="yes"/>is to die. The magicians and the poisoners perform their<lb break="yes"/>nocturnal tricks at the entrance of the cavern, to conjure<lb break="yes"/>the chief of the evil spirits.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the point where the river forms the subterraneous<lb break="yes"/>cascade, a hill covered with vegetation, which is opposite<lb break="yes"/>the opening of the grotto, presents itself in a very pictu-<lb break="no"/>resque manner. It appears at the extremity of a straight<lb break="yes"/>passage, 240 toises in length. The stalactites, which de-<lb break="no"/>scend from the vault, and which resemble columns sus-<lb break="no"/>pended in the air, display themselves on a back-ground<lb break="yes"/>of verdure. The opening of the cavern appeared singu-<lb break="no"/>larly contracted, when we saw it about the middle of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="75" facs="#f0002"/><cb/>day, illuminated by the vivid light reflected at once from<lb break="yes"/>the sky, the plants, and the rocks. The distant light of<lb break="yes"/>day formed somewhat of magical contrast with the dark-<lb break="no"/>ness that surrounded us in those vast caverns. We climb-<lb break="no"/>ed, not without some difficulty, the small hill, whence the<lb break="yes"/>subterraneous rivulet descends. We saw that the grotto<lb break="yes"/>was perceptibly contracted, retaining only forty feet in<lb break="yes"/>its height; and that it continued stretching to the north-<lb break="no"/>east, without deviating from its primitive direction, which<lb break="yes"/>is parallel to that of the great valley of Caripe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The missionaries, with all their authority, could not<lb break="yes"/>prevail on the Indians to penetrate farther into the ca-<lb break="no"/>vern. As the vault grew lower, the cries of the guacha-<lb break="no"/>roes became more shrill. We were obliged to yield to the<lb break="yes"/>pusillanimity of our guides, and trace back our steps.<lb break="yes"/>We followed the course of the torrent to go out of the<lb break="yes"/>cavern. Before our eyes were dazzled with the light of<lb break="yes"/>day, we saw without the grotto, the water of the river<lb break="yes"/>sparkling amid the foliage of the trees that concealed it. It<lb break="yes"/>was like a picture placed in the distance, and to which the<lb break="yes"/>mouth of the cavern served as a frame. Having at length<lb break="yes"/>reached the entrance, and seated ourselves on the bank<lb break="yes"/>of the rivulet, we rested after our fatigues. We were<lb break="yes"/>glad to be beyond the hoarse cries of the birds, and to<lb break="yes"/>leave a place where darkness does not offer even the<lb break="yes"/>charms of silence and tranquillity.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 