<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="136" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">From Baron Humboldt&#x2019;s personal Narrative.&#x2014;Vol.</hi> 4.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>[We have selected from Baron Humboldt&#x2019;s personal narrative, which has<lb break="yes"/>not been republished in this country, the following account of his jour-<lb break="no"/>ney down the Rio Apure to its junction with the Oroonoko. We have<lb break="yes"/>marked some other passages, which we shall give in a future number.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Ed.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>P. F.]</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Having passed the Diatante, we entered a land inhabited only<lb break="yes"/>by tigers, crocodiles, and <hi rendition="#i">chiguires,</hi> a large species of the genus<lb break="yes"/>caria of Linn&#x00E6;us. We saw flocks of birds, crowded so close to-<lb break="no"/>gether, as to appear against the sky like a dark cloud, that every<lb break="yes"/>instant changed its form. The river widens by degrees. One of<lb break="yes"/>its banks is generally barren and sandy from the effect of inunda-<lb break="no"/>tions: the other is higher and covered with lofty trees. Some-<lb break="no"/>times the river is bordered by forest, on each side, and forms a<lb break="yes"/>straight canal, a hundred and fifty toises broad. The manner in<lb break="yes"/>which the trees are disposed, is very remarkable. We first find<lb break="yes"/>bushes of <hi rendition="#i">sauso</hi> forming a kind of hedge four feet high, and ap-<lb break="no" />pearing as if they had been clipped by the hand of man. A copse<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="137" facs="#f0002"/>of cedars, brazillettoes, and lignum vit&#x00E6;, rises behind this hedge.<lb break="yes"/>Palm trees are rare; we saw only a few scattered trunks of the<lb break="yes"/>thorny piritu and corozo. The large quadrupeds of those regions,<lb break="yes"/>the tigers, tapirs, and pecaris, have made openings in the hedge of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">sausos</hi> which we have just described. Through these the wild an-<lb break="no"/>imals pass, when they come to drink at the river. As they fear but lit-<lb break="no"/>tle the approach of a boat, we had the pleasure of viewing them,<lb break="yes"/>pace slowly along the shore, till they disappeared, in the forest,<lb break="yes"/>which they entered by one of the narrow passes left here<lb break="yes"/>and there between the bushes. I confess that these scenes,<lb break="yes"/>which were often repeated, had ever for me a peculiar at-<lb break="no"/>traction. The pleasure they excite is not owing solely to the in-<lb break="no"/>terest, which the naturalist takes in the objects of his study; it is<lb break="yes"/>connected with a feeling common to all men, who have been<lb break="yes"/>brought up in the habits of civilization. You find yourself in a<lb break="yes"/>new world, in the midst of untamed and savage nature. Now it is<lb break="yes"/>the jaguar, the beautiful panther of America, that appears upon<lb break="yes"/>the shore, and now the hocco<note place="foot" n="*">Crax alector, the peacock pheasant; c. pauxi, the cashew bird.</note> with its black plumage and its<lb break="yes"/>tufted head, that moves slowly along the <hi rendition="#i">sausos.</hi> Animals of the<lb break="yes"/>most different classes succed each other. &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Esse como en el Pa-<lb break="no"/>raiso,</hi>&#x201D;<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">&#x201C;It is just as it was in Paradise.&#x201D;</note> said our pilot, an old Indian of the missions. Every thing<lb break="yes"/>indeed here recalls to mind that state of the primitive world, the<lb break="yes"/>innocence and felicity of which, ancient and venerable traditions<lb break="yes"/>have transmitted to all nations: but, in carefully observing the<lb break="yes"/>manners of animals between themselves, we see that they mutual-<lb break="no"/>ly avoid and fear each other. The golden age has ceased; and in<lb break="yes"/>this Paradise of the American forests, as well as every where else,<lb break="yes"/>sad and long experience has taught all beings, that benignity is<lb break="yes"/>seldom found in alliance with strength.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When the shore is of considerable breadth, the hedge of sauso<lb break="yes" />remains at a distance from the river. In this intermediate ground<lb break="yes"/>we see crocodiles, sometimes to the number of eight or ten<lb break="yes"/>stretched on the sand motionless, the jaws opened at right angles,<lb break="yes"/>they repose by each other without displaying any of those marks<lb break="yes"/>of affection, observed in other animals that live in society. The<lb break="yes"/>troop separates as soon as they quit the shore. It is, however,<lb break="yes"/>probably composed of one male only, and many females; for, as<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Descourtils, who has so much studied the crocodiles of St.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="138" facs="#f0003"/>Domingo, observed before me, the males are rare, because they<lb break="yes"/>kill one another in fighting during the season of their loves.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>These monstrous reptiles are so numerous, that throughout the<lb break="yes"/>whole course of the river we had almost at every instant five or<lb break="yes"/>six in view. Yet at this period the swelling of the Rio Apure<lb break="yes"/>was scarely perceived; and consequently hundreds of crocodiles<lb break="yes"/>were still buried in the mud of the savannahs. About four in the<lb break="yes"/>afternoon we stopped to measure a dead crocodile, that the waters<lb break="yes"/>had thrown on the shore. It was only sixteen feet eight inches<lb break="yes"/>long; some days after Mr. Bonpland found another, a male, twenty<lb break="yes"/>two feet three inches long. In every zone, in America as in Egypt,<lb break="yes"/>this animal attains the same size. The species so abundant in the<lb break="yes"/>Apure, the Oroonoko, and the Rio de la Magdalena, is not a <hi rendition="#i">cayman,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>or alligator, but a real crocodile, with feet dentated at the exter-<lb break="no"/>nal edges, analagous to that of the Nile. When it is recollected,<lb break="yes"/>that the male enters the age of puberty only at ten years, and that<lb break="yes"/>its length is then eight feet, we may presume, that the crocodile,<lb break="yes"/>measured by Mr. Bonpland was at least twenty-eight years old. The<lb break="yes"/>Indians told us, that at San Fernando scarcely a year passes, without<lb break="yes"/>two or three grown up persons, particularly women who fetch water<lb break="yes"/>from the river, being drowned by these carniverous lizards. They<lb break="yes"/>related to us the history of a young girl of uritucu, who by singular<lb break="yes" />intrepidity and presence of mind, saved herself from the jaws of a<lb break="yes"/>crocodile. When she felt herself seized, she sought the eyes of<lb break="yes"/>the animal, and plunged her fingers into them with such violence,<lb break="yes"/>that the pain forced the crocodile to let her loose, after having bit-<lb break="no"/>ten off the lower part of her left arm. The girl, notwithstanding<lb break="yes"/>the enormous quantity of blood she lost, happily reached the shore,<lb break="yes"/>swimming with the hand she had still left. In those desert coun-<lb break="no"/>tries, where man is ever <choice><sic>wresting</sic><corr type="editorial">wrestling</corr></choice> with nature, discourse daily<lb break="yes"/>turns on the means, that may be employed to escape from a tiger,<lb break="yes"/>a boa or <hi rendition="#i">traga venado,</hi> or a crocodile; every one prepares himself<lb break="yes"/>in some sort for the dangers that await him. I knew, said the<lb break="yes"/>young girl of Uritucu coolly, &#x201C;that the <hi rendition="#i">cayman</hi> lets go his hold,<lb break="yes"/>if you push your fingers into his eyes.&#x201D; Long after my return to<lb break="yes" />Europe I learned, that in the interior of Africa the negroes know<lb break="yes"/>and practise the same means. Who does not recollect with a live-<lb break="no"/>ly interest <hi rendition="#i">Isaaco,</hi> the guide of the unfortunate Mungo Park, seiz-<lb break="no"/>ed twice, near Boulinkombou, by a crocodile, and twice escaping<lb break="yes"/>from the jaws of the monster, having succeeded in placing<lb break="yes"/>his fingers under water in both his eyes? The African Isaaco,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="139" facs="#f0004"/>and the young American, owed their safety to the same presence<lb break="yes"/>of mind, and the same combination of ideas.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The movements of the crocodile of the Apure are abrupt and<lb break="yes"/>rapid when it attacks any object; but it moves with the slowness<lb break="yes"/>of a salamander, when it is not excited by rage or hunger. The<lb break="yes"/>animal in running makes a rustling noise, that seems to proceed<lb break="yes"/>from the rubbing of the scales of its skin against one another. In<lb break="yes" />this movement it bends its back, and appears higher on its legs<lb break="yes" />than when at rest. We often heard this noise of the scales very<lb break="yes" />near us on the shore; but it is not true, as the Indians pretend,<lb break="yes"/>that, like the pangolins, the old crocodiles &#x201C;can erect their scales,<lb break="yes"/>and every part of their armour.&#x201D; The motion of these animals is<lb break="yes"/>no doubt generally in a straight line, or rather like that of an ar-<lb break="no"/>row which changes its direction at certain distances. However,<lb break="yes"/>notwithstanding the little apparatus of false ribs, that connects the<lb break="yes"/>vertebr&#x00E6; of the neck, and seems to impede the lateral movement,<lb break="yes"/>crocodiles can turn easily, when they please. I often saw young<lb break="yes"/>ones biting their tails; and other observers have seen the same<lb break="yes"/>action in crocodiles at their full growth. If their movements al-<lb break="no"/>most always appear to be straight forward, it is because, like our<lb break="yes" />small lizards, they execute them by starts. Crocodiles are excel-<lb break="no"/>lent swimmers; they go with facility against the most rapid cur-<lb break="no"/>rent. It appeared to me, however, that in descending the river<lb break="yes"/>they had some difficulty in turning quickly about. A large dog<lb break="yes"/>that had accompanied us in our journey from Caraccas to the Rio<lb break="yes"/>Negro, was one day pursued in swimming by an enormous croco-<lb break="no"/>dile, which had nearly reached him, when the dog escaped its en-<lb break="no"/>emy by turning round suddenly and swimming against the current.<lb break="yes"/>The crocodile performed the same movement, but much more<lb break="yes"/>slowly than the dog, which happily gained the shore.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The crocodiles of the Apure find abundant nourishment in the<lb break="yes" />chiguires, (the thick nosed tapir of the naturalists,) which live<lb break="yes"/>50 or 60 together in troops on the banks of the river. These un-<lb break="no"/>fortunate animals, as large as our pigs, have no weapons of de-<lb break="no"/>fence; they swim somewhat better than they run: yet they become<lb break="yes"/>the prey of the crocodiles in the water, as of the tigers on land.<lb break="yes"/>It is difficult to conceive, how, persecuted by two powerful ene-<lb break="no"/>mies, they can become so numerous; but they breed with the same<lb break="yes"/>rapidity as the cobayas, or little guinea-pigs, which come to us<lb break="yes"/>from Brazil.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="140" facs="#f0005"/>
                <p>We stopped below the mouth of the Cano de la Tigrera, in a<lb break="yes" />sinuosity called <hi rendition="#i">La Vuelta del Joval,</hi> to measure the velocity of<lb break="yes"/>the water at its surface. It was not more than 3.2 feet in a second;<lb break="yes"/>which gives 2.56 feet for the <hi rendition="#i">mean</hi> velocity. The barometrical<lb break="yes"/>heights, attending to the effects of the little horary variations, indi-<lb break="no" />cated scarcely a slope of seventeen inches in a mile of nine hun-<lb break="no"/>dred and fifty toises. The velocity is the simultaneous effect of<lb break="yes"/>the slope of the ground, and the accumulation of the waters by the<lb break="yes"/>swelling of the upper parts of the river. We were again surround-<lb break="no"/>ed by chiguires, which swim like dogs, raising the head and neck<lb break="yes"/>above the water. We saw with surprise a large crocodile on the<lb break="yes"/>opposite shore, motionless, and sleeping in the midst of these nib-<lb break="no"/>bling animals. It awoke at the approach of our canoe, and went<lb break="yes"/>into the water slowly, without affrighting the chiguires. Our In-<lb break="no"/>dians accounted for this indifference by the stupidity of the ani-<lb break="no"/>mal; but it is more probable, that the chiguires know by long<lb break="yes"/>experience, that the crocodile of the Apure and the Oroonoko<lb break="yes"/>does not attack upon land, unless he finds the object he would<lb break="yes"/>seize immediately in his way, at the instant when he throws him-<lb break="no"/>self into the water.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Near the <hi rendition="#i">Joval</hi> nature assumes an awful and savage aspect.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>We there saw the largest tiger we had ever met with. The na-<lb break="no"/>tives themselves were astonished at its prodigious length, which<lb break="yes"/>surpassed that of all the tigers of India I had seen in the collec-<lb break="no"/>tions of Europe. The animal lay stretched beneath the shade of<lb break="yes"/>a large zamang.<note place="foot" n="*">A species of mimosa.</note> It had just killed a chiguire, but had not yet<lb break="yes"/>touched its prey, on which it kept one of its paws. The zamuroes,<lb break="yes"/>a species of vulture which we have compared above to the perc-<lb break="no"/>nopterus of Lower Egypt, were assembled in flocks to devour the<lb break="yes"/>remains of the jaguar&#x2019;s repast. They afforded the most curious spec-<lb break="no"/>tacle, by a singular mixture of boldness and timidity. They advanc-<lb break="no"/>ed within the distance of two feet from the jaguar, but at the least<lb break="yes"/>movement the beast made, they drew back. In order to observe<lb break="yes"/>more nearly the manners of these animals, we went into the little<lb break="yes"/>boat, that accompanied our canoe. Tigers very rarely attack boats<lb break="yes"/>by swimming to them; and never but when their ferocity is<lb break="yes"/>heightened by a long privation of food. The noise of our oars led<lb break="yes"/>the animal to rise slowly and hide itself behind the <hi rendition="#i">sauso</hi> bushes<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="141" facs="#f0006"/>that bordered the shore. The vultures tried to profit by this mo-<lb break="no"/>ment of absence to devour the chiguire: but the tiger, notwith-<lb break="no"/>standing the proximity of our boat, leaped into the midst of them;<lb break="yes"/>and in a fit of rage, expressed by his gait and the movement of his<lb break="yes"/>tail, carried off his prey to the forest. The Indians regretted,<lb break="yes"/>that they were not provided with their lances, in order to go on<lb break="yes"/>shore, and attack the tiger. They are accustomed to this weap-<lb break="no"/>on, and were right in not trusting to our musquets, which, in an<lb break="yes"/>air so excessively humid, often miss fire.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Continuing to descend the river, we met with the great herd<lb break="yes"/>of chiguires, which the tiger had put to flight, and from which he<lb break="yes" />had selected his prey. These animals saw us land with great tran-<lb break="no"/>quility; some of them were seated, and gazed upon us, moving<lb break="yes"/>the upper lip like rabbits. They seemed not to be afraid of men,<lb break="yes"/>but the sight of our great dog put them to flight. Their hind<lb break="yes"/>legs being longer than their fore legs, their pace is a slight gal-<lb break="no"/>lop, but with so little swiftness, that we succeeded in catching two<lb break="yes"/>of them. The chiguire, which swims with the greatest agility,<lb break="yes"/>utters a short moan in running, as if its respiration were impeded.<lb break="yes"/>It is the largest of the family of gnawing animals. It defends it-<lb break="no"/>self only at the last extremity, when it is surrounded and wound-<lb break="no"/>ed. Having great strength in its grinding teeth, particularly the<lb break="yes"/>hinder ones, which are pretty long, it can tear the paw of a tiger,<lb break="yes"/>or the leg of a horse, with its bite. Its flesh has a smell of musk<lb break="yes"/>somewhat disagreeable; yet hams are made of it in this country,<lb break="yes"/>which almost justifies the name of <hi rendition="#i">water hog</hi> given to the chiguire<lb break="yes"/>by some of the older naturalists. The missionary monks do not<lb break="yes"/>hesitate to eat these hams during lent. According to their Zoo-<lb break="no"/>logical classifications, they place the armadillo, the thick nosed<lb break="yes"/>tapir, and the manatee near the tortoises; the first, because it is<lb break="yes"/>covered with a hard armour, like a sort of shell, and the others be-<lb break="no"/>cause they are amphibious. The chiguires are found in such<lb break="yes"/>numbers on the banks of the river Santo Domingo, Apure and<lb break="yes"/>Arauca, in the marshes and the inundated savannahs, of the Llanos,<lb break="yes"/>that the pasturages suffer from them. They browze the grass<lb break="yes"/>which fattens the horses best, and which bears the name of <hi rendition="#i">chi-<lb break="no"/>guirero,</hi> &#x201C;chiguire grass.&#x201D; They feed also upon fish; and we<lb break="yes" />saw with surprize, that, affrighted by the approach of a boat, the<lb break="yes"/>animal in diving remains eight or ten minutes under water.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We passed the night as usual, in the open air, though in a<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="142" facs="#f0007"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">plantation,</hi> the proprietor of which employed himself in hunting<lb break="yes"/>tigers. He was almost naked, and of a dark brown complexion<lb break="yes"/>like a Zambo. This did not prevent his thinking himself of the<lb break="yes"/>cast of Whites. He called his wife and his daughter, who were<lb break="yes"/>as naked as himself, Donna Isabella, and Donna Manuela. With-<lb break="no"/>out having ever quitted the banks of the Apure, he took a lively<lb break="yes"/>interest &#x201C;in the news of Madrid, in those wars which never end-<lb break="no"/>ed and in every thing down yonder; <hi rendition="#i">todas las cosas de alla.</hi>&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>He knew, that the king was soon to come and visit &#x201C;the grandees<lb break="yes"/>of the country of Caraccas,&#x201D; but, added he with some pleasantry,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;as the people of the court can eat only wheaten bread, they<lb break="yes"/>will never pass beyond the town of Victoria, and we shall not see<lb break="yes"/>them here.&#x201D; I had brought with me a chiguire, which I had<lb break="yes"/>intended to have roasted; but our host assured us, that such &#x201C;In-<lb break="no"/>dian game&#x201D; was not food fit for <hi rendition="#i">nos otros cavalleros blancos,</hi> &#x201C;white<lb break="yes"/>gentlemen like him and me.&#x201D; Accordingly he offered us some<lb break="yes"/>venison, which he had killed the day before with an arrow, for he<lb break="yes"/>had neither powder nor fire arms.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We supposed that a small wood of plantain trees concealed<lb break="yes"/>from us the hut of the farm: but this man, so proud of his nobility<lb break="yes"/>and the colour of his skin, had not taken the trouble of construct-<lb break="no" />ing an <hi rendition="#i">ajoupa</hi> of palm leaves. He invited us to have our ham-<lb break="no"/>mocks hung near his own, between two trees; and he assured us<lb break="yes"/>with an air of complacency, that, if we came up the river in the<lb break="yes"/>rainy season, we should find him beneath a roof, (<hi rendition="#i">baxo techo.</hi>)<lb break="yes"/>We soon had reason to complain of a philosophy, which, indul-<lb break="no"/>gent to indolence, renders a man indifferent to the conveniences<lb break="yes"/>of life. A furious wind arose after midnight, lightnings ploughed<lb break="yes"/>the horizon, the thunder rolled, and we were wet to the skin.<lb break="yes"/>During this storm a whimsical incident served to amuse us for a<lb break="yes"/>moment. Donna Isabella&#x2019;s cat had perched upon the tamarind-tree,<lb break="yes"/>at the foot of which we lay. It fell into the hammock of one of<lb break="yes"/>our companions, who, wounded by the claws of the cat, and awa-<lb break="no"/>kened from a profound sleep, thought he was attacked by some<lb break="yes"/>wild beast of the forest. We ran to him on hearing his cries,<lb break="yes"/>and had some trouble to convince him of his error. While it<lb break="yes"/>rained in torrents on our hammocks, and the instruments we had<lb break="yes"/>landed, don Ignacio congratulated us on our good fortune in not<lb break="yes"/>sleeping on the strand, but finding ourselves in his domain,<lb break="yes"/>among whites and persons of rank; <hi rendition="#i">entre gente blanca y de trato.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="143" facs="#f0008"/>Wet as we were, we could not easily persuade ourselves of the<lb break="yes"/>advantages of our situation, and listened with some impatience to<lb break="yes"/>the long narrative our host gave us of his pretended expedition<lb break="yes"/>to Rio Meta, of the valour he had displayed in a bloody combat<lb break="yes"/>with the Guahibo Indians, and &#x201C;the services that he had rendered<lb break="yes"/>God and his King, in carrying away children (<hi rendition="#i">los Indiecitos</hi>) from<lb break="yes"/>their parents, to distribute them in the missions.&#x201D; How singular a<lb break="yes"/>spectacle, to find in that vast solitude a man, who believes himself<lb break="yes"/>of European race, and knows no other shelter than the shade of a<lb break="yes"/>tree, with all the vain pretensions, all the hereditary prejudices,<lb break="yes"/>all the errors, of long civilization!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>April the 1st. At sun rise we quitted signior don Ignacio, and<lb break="yes" />Signora donna Isabella his wife. The weather was cooler, for<lb break="yes" />the thermometer, which generally kept up in the day to 30 or 35&#x00B0;<lb break="yes"/>had sunk to 24&#x00B0;. The temperature of the river was little changed, it<lb break="yes"/>continued constantly at 26&#x00B0; or 27&#x00B0;. The current carried with it<lb break="yes"/>an enormous quantity of trunks of trees. We might imagine, that<lb break="yes"/>on ground entirely smooth, and where the eye cannot distinguish<lb break="yes"/>the least hill, the river would have formed by the force of its<lb break="yes"/>current a channel in a straight line. A glance at the map, which<lb break="yes"/>I traced by the compass, will prove the contrary. The two banks,<lb break="yes"/>worn by the waters, do not furnish an equal resistance; and al-<lb break="no"/>most imperceptible inequalities of the level suffice to produce<lb break="yes"/>great sinuosities, yet below the Joval, where the bed of the river<lb break="yes"/>enlarges a little, it forms a channel that appears perfectly straight,<lb break="yes"/>and is shaded on each side by very tall trees. This part of the<lb break="yes"/>river is called <hi rendition="#i">Cano Ricco.</hi> I found it to be one hundred and thirty<lb break="yes"/>six toises broad. We passed a low island, inhabited by thousands<lb break="yes"/>of flamingoes rose-coloured spoonbills herons, and moorhens,<lb break="yes"/>which displayed a mixture of the most various colours. These<lb break="yes"/>birds were so close together, that they seemed to be unable to stir.<lb break="yes"/>The island they inhabit is called <hi rendition="#i">Isla de Aves.</hi> Lower down we<lb break="yes"/>passed the point, where the Rio Arichuna, an arm of the Apure,<lb break="yes"/>branches off to the Cabulare, carrying off a considerable body of<lb break="yes"/>its waters. We stopped on the right bank, at a little Indian mis-<lb break="no"/>sion, inhabited by the tribe of the Guamoes. There were yet only<lb break="yes" />sixteen or eighteen huts constructed with the leaves of the palm<lb break="yes"/>tree; yet, in the statistical tables presented annually by the mis-<lb break="no"/>sionaries to the court, this assemblage of huts is marked with the<lb break="yes"/>name of the <hi rendition="#i">village de Santa Barbara de Arichuna.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="144" facs="#f0009"/>
                <p>The Guamoes are a race of Indians very difficult to fix on a set-<lb break="no" />tled spot. They have great similarity of manners with the<lb break="yes" />Achaguas, the Guajiboes,<note place="foot" n="*">Their Indian name is <hi rendition="#i">Guaiva</hi> pronounced <hi rendition="#i">Guahiva.</hi>
                    </note> and the Otomacoes, partaking their<lb break="yes"/>disregard of cleanliness, their spirit of vengeance, and their taste<lb break="yes"/>for wandering; but their language differs essentially. The greater<lb break="yes" />part of these four tribes live by fishing and hunting, in plains of-<lb break="no"/>ten inundated, and situated between the Apure, the Meta, and the<lb break="yes"/>Guaviare. The nature of these regions seems to invite the na-<lb break="no"/>tions to a wandering life. On entering <hi rendition="#i" >the mountains of the Cataracts</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>of the Oroonoko we shall soon find among the <hi rendition="#i" >Piraoas,</hi> the <hi rendition="#i">Macoes,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and the <hi rendition="#i">Maquiritares,</hi> milder manners, the love of agriculture,<lb break="yes"/>and great cleanliness in the interior of their huts. On the backs<lb break="yes"/>of mountains, in the midst of impenetrable forests, man is com-<lb break="no"/>pelled to fix himself, and cultivate a small spot of land.&#x2014;This cul-<lb break="no"/>tivation requires little care; while in a country where there are no<lb break="yes" />other roads than rivers, the life of the hunter is laborious and dif-<lb break="no"/>ficult. The Guamoes of the mission of Santa Barbara could not<lb break="yes"/>furnish us with the provision we wanted. They cultivate only a<lb break="yes"/>little cassava. They appeared hospitable; and, when we entered<lb break="yes"/>their huts, offered us dried fish and water (in their tongue <hi rendition="#i">cub.</hi>)<lb break="yes"/>This water was cooled in porous vessels.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Beyond the <hi rendition="#i">Vuelta del Cochino roto,</hi> in a spot where the river<lb break="yes"/>has scooped itself a new bed, we passed the night on a bare and<lb break="yes"/>very extensive strand. The forest being impenetrable, we had<lb break="yes"/>the greatest difficulty to find dry wood to light fires, near which<lb break="yes"/>the Indians believe themselves in safety from the nocturnal attacks<lb break="yes"/>of the tiger. Our own experience seems to depose in favour of<lb break="yes"/>this opinion; but M. d&#x2019;Azzara asserts, that in his time a tiger in<lb break="yes"/>Paraguay carried off a man who was seated near a fire lighted in<lb break="yes"/>the savannah.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The night was calm and serene, and there was a beautiful<lb break="yes" />moonlight. The crocodiles were stretched along the shore.<lb break="yes"/>They placed themselves in such a manner as to be able to see the<lb break="yes" />fire. We thought we observed, that its splendour attracted them,<lb break="yes"/>as it attracts fishes, crayfish, and other inhabitants of the water.<lb break="yes"/>The Indians showed us the traces of three tigers in the sand, two<lb break="yes"/>of which were very young. A female had no doubt conducted her<lb break="yes"/>little ones to drink at the river. Finding no tree on the strand, we<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="145" facs="#f0010"/>stuck our oars in the ground, and to these we fastened our ham-<lb break="no"/>mocks. Every thing passed tranquilly till eleven at night; and<lb break="yes"/>then a noise so terrific arose in the neighbouring forest, that it<lb break="yes"/>was almost impossible to close our eyes. Amid the cries of so<lb break="yes"/>many wild beasts howling at once, the Indians discriminated such<lb break="yes"/>only as were heard separately. These were the little soft cries<lb break="yes"/>of the sapajous, the moans of the alouates, the howlings of the ti-<lb break="no"/>ger, the couguar, or American lion without mane, the pecari,<lb break="yes"/>and the sloth, and the voices of curassoa, the parraka, and some<lb break="yes"/>other gallinaceous birds. When the jaguars approached the skirt of<lb break="yes"/>the forest, our dog, which till then had never ceased barking, began<lb break="yes"/>to howl and seek for shelter beneath our hammocks. Sometimes, af-<lb break="no"/>ter a long silence, the cry of the tiger came from the tops of the<lb break="yes"/>trees; and in this case it was followed by the sharp and long whist-<lb break="no"/>ling of the monkeys, which appeared to flee from the danger<lb break="yes"/>that threatened them.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I notice every circumstance of these nocturnal scenes, because,<lb break="yes" />being recently embarked on the Rio Apure, we were not yet ac-<lb break="no" />customed to them. We heard the same noises repeated, during<lb break="yes" />the course of whole months, whenever the forest approached the<lb break="yes" />bed of the rivers. The security displayed by the Indians inspires<lb break="yes"/>travellers with confidence. You persuade yourself with them,<lb break="yes"/>that the tigers are afraid of fire, and do not attack a man lying in<lb break="yes"/>his hammock. These attacks are in fact extremely rare; and, dur-<lb break="no"/>ing a long abode in South America, I remember only one example<lb break="yes"/>of a Llanero, who was found torn in his hammock opposite the<lb break="yes"/>island of Achaguas.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When the natives are interrogated on the causes of this tre-<lb break="no" />mendous noise made by the beasts of the forest, at certain hours<lb break="yes"/>of the night, they reply gaily, &#x201C;they are keeping the feast of the<lb break="yes"/>full moon!&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I believe this agitation is most frequently the effect of some<lb break="yes" />contest, that has arisen in the depths of the forest. The jaguars,<lb break="yes"/>for instance, pursue the pecaris and the tapirs, which, having no<lb break="yes"/>defence but in their numbers, flee in close troops, and break down<lb break="yes"/>the bushes they find in their way. Affrighted at this struggle, the<lb break="yes"/>timid and mistrustful monkies answer from the tops of the trees,<lb break="yes"/>the cries of the large animals. They awaken the birds that live<lb break="yes"/>in society, and by degrees the whole assembly is in movement.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>We shall soon find, that it is not always in a fine moonlight, but<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="146" facs="#f0011"/>more particularly at the time of a storm and violent showers, that<lb break="yes"/>this tumult takes place among the wild beasts. &#x201C;May heaven<lb break="yes"/>grant them a quiet night and repose, and us also!&#x201D; said the monk<lb break="yes"/>who accompanied us to the Rio Negro, when, sinking with fatigue,<lb break="yes"/>he assisted in arranging our accomodations for the night. It was<lb break="yes"/>indeed a strange situation, to find no silence in the solitude of<lb break="yes"/>woods. In the inns of Spain we dread the sharp sounds of guitars<lb break="yes"/>from the next apartment; in those of the Oroonoko, which are an<lb break="yes"/>open beach, or the shelter of a solitary tree, we are afraid of being<lb break="yes"/>disturbed in our sleep by voices issuing from the forest.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>April 2d. We set sail before sunrise. The morning was beau-<lb break="no"/>tiful and cool, according to the feelings of those, who are accus-<lb break="no" />tomed to the heats of these climates. The thermometer rose to<lb break="yes" />28&#x00B0; only in the air; but the dry and white sand of the beach, not-<lb break="no"/>withstanding its radiation toward a sky without a cloud, retained<lb break="yes"/>a temperature of 36&#x00B0;. The porpoises <hi rendition="#i">(toninas)</hi> ploughed the ri-<lb break="no"/>ver in long files. The shore was covered with fishing birds.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Some of these embarked on the floating wood, that passed down<lb break="yes"/>the river, and surprized the fish that preferred the middle of the<lb break="yes"/>stream. Our canoe touched several times during the morning.<lb break="yes"/>These shocks, when violent, are capable of splitting a light bark.<lb break="yes"/>We struck on the points of several large trees, which remain for<lb break="yes" />years in an oblique position, sunk in the mud. These trees de-<lb break="no" />scend from Sarare, at the period of great inundations. These so<lb break="yes" />fill the bed of the river, that canoes in going up find it difficult<lb break="yes"/>sometimes to make their way over the shoals, or wherever there<lb break="yes"/>are eddies. We reached a spot near the island of Carizales, where<lb break="yes"/>we saw trunks of the locust tree of an enormous size above the<lb break="yes"/>surface of the water. They were covered with a species of plo-<lb break="no"/>tus nearly approaching the <hi rendition="#i" >anhinga,</hi> or white-bellied darter. These<lb break="yes"/>birds perch in files, like pheasants and parrakas. They remain<lb break="yes"/>for hours entirely motionless, with the beak raised toward the sky,<lb break="yes"/>which gives them a singular air of stupidity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Below the island of Carizales we observed a diminution of the<lb break="yes" />waters of the river, at which we were so much the more surprised,<lb break="yes"/>as, after the bifurcation at <hi rendition="#i">la Boca de Arichuna,</hi> there is no branch,<lb break="yes"/>no natural drain, that takes away water from the Apure. The<lb break="yes"/>loss is solely the effect of evaporation, and of filtration on a sandy<lb break="yes"/>and wet shore. We may form an idea of the magnitude of these<lb break="yes"/>effects, when we recollect, that we found the heat of the dry sands,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="147" facs="#f0012"/>at different hours of the day, from 36&#x00B0; to 52&#x00B0; and that of sands cov-<lb break="no"/>ered with three or four inches of water 32&#x00B0;. The beds of rivers<lb break="yes"/>are heated as far as the depth, to which the solar rays can pene-<lb break="no"/>trate without having undergone too great an extinction in their<lb break="yes"/>passage through the super incumbent strata of water. Besides,<lb break="yes"/>the effect of filtration extends far beyond the bed of the river; it<lb break="yes"/>may be said to be lateral. The shore, which appears dry to us, im-<lb break="no"/>bibes water as far as the level of the surface of the river. We saw<lb break="yes"/>water gush out at the distance of 50 toises from the shore, every time<lb break="yes"/>that the indians stuck their oars into the ground; now these sands,<lb break="yes"/>wet underneath, but dry above, and exposed to the solar rays, act<lb break="yes"/>like a sponge. They are losing the infiltrated water every in-<lb break="no"/>stant by evaporation. The vapour, that is emitted, traverses the<lb break="yes"/>upper stratum of sand strongly heated, and becomes sensible to<lb break="yes"/>the eye when the air cools toward the evening. As the beach dries,<lb break="yes"/>it draws from the rivers new portions of water; and it may be con-<lb break="no" />sidered, that this continual alternation of vaporization and lateral <hi rendition="#i">im-<lb break="no"/>bibition</hi> must cause an immense loss, difficult to submit to exact cal-<lb break="no"/>culation. The increase of these losses would be in proportion to<lb break="yes"/>the length of the course of the rivers, if from their source to their<lb break="yes"/>mouth they were equally surrounded by a flat shore; but these<lb break="yes"/>shores being formed by depositions from the water, and the water<lb break="yes"/>having less velocity in proportion as it is more remote from its<lb break="yes"/>source, deposing necessarily more in the lower than in the upper<lb break="yes"/>part of its course, many rivers of hot climates undergo a diminu-<lb break="no"/>tion in the quantity of their water, as they approach their mouth.<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Barrow has observed these curious effects of sands in the<lb break="yes" />southern part of Africa, on the banks of Orange river. They<lb break="yes" />are even become the subject of a very important discussion, in<lb break="yes" />the various hypotheses that have been formed on the course of<lb break="yes" />the Niger.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Near the Vuelta de Basilio, where we landed to collect plants,<lb break="yes"/>we saw on the top of a tree, two beautiful little monkies, black<lb break="yes"/>as jet, of the size of the sai, with <hi rendition="#i">prehensile</hi> tails. Their physi-<lb break="no"/>ognomy and their movements sufficiently showed, that they were<lb break="yes"/>neither the quato [simia beelzebub, L.], nor the chamek, nor any<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i">ateles.</hi> Our Indians themselves had never seen any that<lb break="yes"/>resembled them. These forests abound in sapajous unknown to<lb break="yes"/>the naturalists of Europe; and as monkeys, especially those that<lb break="yes"/>live in troops, and for this reason are more enterprising, make<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="148" facs="#f0013"/>long emigrations, at certain periods, it happens, that at the begin-<lb break="no"/>ning of the rainy season the natives discover round their huts dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent kinds, which they had never before observed. On this same<lb break="yes"/>bank, our guides showed us a nest of young iguanas, that were<lb break="yes"/>only four inches long. It was difficult to distinguish them from<lb break="yes"/>a common lizard. There was nothing yet formed but the dew-<lb break="no"/>lap below the throat. The dorsal spines, the large erect scales,<lb break="yes"/>all those appendages, that render the iguana so monstrous when<lb break="yes"/>it attains the length of three or four feet, were scarcely traced.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The flesh of this animal of the <hi rendition="#i">saurien</hi> family appeared to us to<lb break="yes"/>have an agreeable taste in every country, where the climate is<lb break="yes"/>very dry; we even found it so at periods when we where not in<lb break="yes"/>want of other food. It is extremely white, and next to the flesh<lb break="yes"/>of the armadillo, here called <hi rendition="#i" >cachicamo,</hi> one of the best eatables<lb break="yes"/>to be found in the huts of the natives.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It rained towards the evening. Before the rain fell, swallows,<lb break="yes" />exactly resembling our own, skimmed over the surface of the wa-<lb break="no" />ter. We saw also a flock of paroquets pursued by little goshawks<lb break="yes"/>without crests. The piercing cries of these paroquets contrasted<lb break="yes"/>singularly with the whistling of the birds of prey. We passed<lb break="yes"/>the night in the open air, upon the beach, near the island of Cari-<lb break="no"/>zales. There were several Indian huts in the neighbourhood,<lb break="yes"/>surrounded with plantations. Our pilots assured us before hand,<lb break="yes"/>that we should not hear the cries of the jaguar, which, when not<lb break="yes"/>extremely pressed by hunger, withdraws from places where he<lb break="yes"/>does not rule alone. &#x201C;Men put him out of humour,&#x201D; <hi rendition="#i">los hombres<lb break="yes"/>lo enfadan,</hi> say the people in the missions, a pleasant, and simple<lb break="yes"/>expression, that marks a well observed fact.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>April 3d. Since our departure from San Fernando we have not<lb break="yes"/>met a single boat on this fine river. Every thing denotes the<lb break="yes"/>most profound solitude. In the morning our Indians caught with<lb break="yes"/>a hook the fish known in the country by the name of <hi rendition="#i">caribe,</hi> or<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">caribito,</hi> because no other fish has such a thirst for blood. It at-<lb break="no"/>tacks bathers and swimmers, from whom it often carries away con-<lb break="no"/>siderable pieces of flesh. When a person is only slightly wound-<lb break="no"/>ed, it is difficult for him to get out of the water without receiving<lb break="yes"/>a severer wound. The Indians dread extremely these <hi rendition="#i">caribes;</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and several of them shewed us the scars of deep wounds, in the<lb break="yes"/>calf of the leg and in the thigh, made by these little animals, which<lb break="yes"/>the Maypures call <hi rendition="#i">umati.</hi> They live at the bottom of rivers; but<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="149" facs="#f0014"/>if a few drops of blood, be shed on the water, they arrive by thou-<lb break="no"/>sands at the surface. When we reflect on the number of<lb break="yes"/>these fish, the most voracious and cruel of which are only four or<lb break="yes"/>five inches long; on the triangular form of their sharp and cutting<lb break="yes"/>teeth, and on the amplitude of their <hi rendition="#i">retractile</hi> mouth, we need not<lb break="yes"/>be surprised at the fear which the caribe excites in the inhabit-<lb break="no" />ants of the banks of the Apure and the Oroonoko. In places where<lb break="yes"/>the river was very limpid, and where not a fish appeared, we<lb break="yes"/>threw into the water little morsels of flesh covered with blood.<lb break="yes"/>In a few minutes a cloud of caribes came to dispute the prey.<lb break="yes"/>The belly of this fish has a cutting edge, indented like a saw; a<lb break="yes"/>character that may be traced in several kinds, the <hi rendition="#i">serra-salmes,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">myletes,</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i" >pristigastres.</hi> The presence of a second<lb break="yes"/>adipous dorsal fin; and the form of the teeth, covered by lips dis-<lb break="no"/>tant from each other, and largest in the lower jaw; place the <hi rendition="#i">ca-<lb break="no"/>ribe</hi> among the <hi rendition="#i">serra-salmes.</hi> Its mouth is much wider than that<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i" >myletes</hi> of Mr. Cuvier. It&#x2019;s body toward the back is ash-<lb break="no"/>coloured, with a tint of green; but the belly, the gill covers, and<lb break="yes"/>the pectoral, anal, and ventral fins, are of a fine orange. Three<lb break="yes"/>species (or varieties) are known in the Oroonoko, and are distin-<lb break="no"/>guished by their size. The <hi rendition="#i" >mean,</hi> or intermediate, appears to be<lb break="yes"/>identical with the <hi rendition="#i">mean</hi> species of the piraya, or piranha of Marc-<lb break="no"/>grav. (<hi rendition="#i">Salmo rhombeus,</hi> Lin.) I described and drew it on the spot.<lb break="yes"/>The caribito has a very agreeable taste. As no one dares to<lb break="yes"/>bathe where it is found, it may be considered as one of the great-<lb break="no"/>est scourges of those climates, in which the sting of the moschet-<lb break="no"/>toes, and the irritation of the skin, render the use of baths so ne-<lb break="no"/>cessary.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We stopped at noon in a desert spot called <hi rendition="#i">Algodonal.</hi> I left<lb break="yes"/>my companions, while they drew the boat to land, and were occu-<lb break="no"/>pied in preparing our dinner. I went along the beach to observe<lb break="yes"/>nearer a group of crocodiles sleeping in the sun, and placed in<lb break="yes"/>such a manner, as to have their tails, furnished with broad plates,<lb break="yes"/>resting on one another. Some little herons, white as snow, walk-<lb break="no"/>ed along their backs, and even upon their heads, as if they were<lb break="yes"/>passing over trunks of trees. The crocodiles were of a greenish<lb break="yes"/>grey, half covered with dried mud; from their colour and immobi-<lb break="no"/>lity they might have been taken for statues of bronze. This ex-<lb break="no"/>cursion had nearly proved fatal to me. I had kept my eyes con-<lb break="no"/>stantly turned toward the river; but, on picking up some spangles<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="150" facs="#f0015"/>of mica agglomerated together in the sand, I discovered the re-<lb break="no"/>cent footsteps of a tiger, easily distinguishable from their form<lb break="yes"/>and size. The animal had gone toward the forest; and turning<lb break="yes"/>my eyes on that side, I found myself within eighty steps of a ja-<lb break="no"/>guar, lying under the thick foliage of a ceiba. No tiger had ever<lb break="yes"/>appeared to me so large.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There are accidents in life, against which we might seek in<lb break="yes"/>vain to fortify our reason. I was extremely frightened, and yet<lb break="yes" />sufficiently master of myself, and of my motions, to enable me to fol-<lb break="no"/>low the advice which the Indians had often given us, how to act in<lb break="yes"/>such cases. I continued to walk on, without running; avoided moving<lb break="yes"/>my arms; and thought I observed that the jaguar&#x2019;s attention was<lb break="yes"/>fixed on a herd of <hi rendition="#i">capybaras,</hi> which were crossing the river.&#x2014;I<lb break="yes"/>then began to return, making a large circuit toward the edge of<lb break="yes"/>the water. As the distance increased, I thought I might accelerate<lb break="yes"/>my pace. How often was I tempted to look back in order to assure<lb break="yes"/>myself that I was not pursued! Happily I yielded very tardily to<lb break="yes"/>this desire. The jaguar had remained motionless. These enor-<lb break="no"/>mous cats with spotted robes, are so well fed in countries abound-<lb break="no"/>ing in <hi rendition="#i">capybaras, pecaris,</hi> and deer, that they rarely attack men. I<lb break="yes" />arrived at the boat out of breath, and related my adventure to the<lb break="yes"/>Indians. They appeared very little moved by it; yet, after having<lb break="yes"/>loaded our firelocks, they accompained us to the ceiba, beneath<lb break="yes"/>which the jaguar had lain. He was there no longer, and it would<lb break="yes"/>have been imprudent to have pursued him into the forest where<lb break="yes"/>we must have dispersed, or marched in file, amid intertwining<lb break="yes"/>lianas.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the evening we passed the mouth of the <hi rendition="#i">Cano del Manati,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>thus named on account of the immense quantity of manatees<lb break="yes"/>caught there every year. This herbivorous animal of the ceta-<lb break="no"/>ceous family, called by the Indians <hi rendition="#i" >apcia</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">avia</hi> attains here ge-<lb break="no" />nerally ten or twelve feet in length. It weighs from five hundred<lb break="yes"/>to eight hundred pounds. We saw the water covered with it&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>excrements, which are very fetid, but perfectly resembling those<lb break="yes"/>of an ox. It abounds in the Oroonoko, below the cataracts, in the<lb break="yes"/>Rio Meta, and in the Apure, between the two islands of Carrizales<lb break="yes"/>and Conserva. We found no vestiges of nails on the external sur-<lb break="no"/>face or the edge of the fins, which are quite smooth; but little ru-<lb break="no"/>diments of nails appear at the third phalanx, when the skin of the<lb break="yes"/>fins is taken off. We dissected one of these animals, which was<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="151" facs="#f0016"/>nine feet long, at Carichana, a mission of the Oroonoko. The<lb break="yes"/>upper lip was four inches longer than the lower. It is covered<lb break="yes"/>with a very fine skin, and serves as a proboscis or probe to dis-<lb break="no"/>tinguish surrounding objects. The inside of the mouth, which<lb break="yes"/>has a sensible warmth in an animal newly killed, presents a very<lb break="yes"/>singular conformation. The tongue is almost motionless; but<lb break="yes"/>before the tongue there is a fleshy excrescence in each jaw, and<lb break="yes"/>a concavity, lined with a very hard skin, into which the excrescence<lb break="yes"/>fits. The manatee eats such quantities of grass, that we have<lb break="yes"/>found it&#x2019;s stomach, which is divided into several cavities, and it&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>intestines, which are a hundred and eight feet long, alike filled<lb break="yes"/>with it. On opening the animal at the back, we were struck with<lb break="yes"/>the magnitude, form, and situation of it&#x2019;s lungs. They have very<lb break="yes"/>large cells, and resemble immense swimming bladders. They<lb break="yes"/>are three feet long. Filled with air, they have a bulk of more than<lb break="yes"/>a thousand cubic inches. I was surprised to see, that, possessing<lb break="yes"/>such considerable receptacles for air, the manatee comes so often<lb break="yes"/>to the surface of the water to breathe. It&#x2019;s flesh, which, from<lb break="yes"/>what prejudice I know not, is considered unwholesome and <hi rendition="#i">calen-<lb break="no"/>turiosa,</hi> is very savoury. It appeared to me to resemble pork ra-<lb break="no"/>ther than beef. It is most esteemed by the Guanoes and the Ot-<lb break="no"/>tomacks; and these two nations addict themselves particularly<lb break="yes"/>to the catching of the manatee. It&#x2019;s flesh, salted and dried in the<lb break="yes"/>Sun, can be preserved a whole year; and, as the clergy regard<lb break="yes"/>this mammiferous animal as a fish, it is much sought for during<lb break="yes"/>Lent. The vital principal is singularly strong in the manatee; it<lb break="yes"/>is tied after being harpooned, but is not killed till it has been ta-<lb break="no" />ken into the canoe. This is effected, when the animal is very<lb break="yes" />large, in the middle of the river, by filling the canoe two-thirds<lb break="yes"/>with water, sliding it under the animal, and then bailing out the<lb break="yes"/>water by means of a calebash. This fishery is the easiest after<lb break="yes"/>great inundations, when the manatee has passed from the great<lb break="yes"/>rivers into the lakes and surrounding marshes, and the waters di-<lb break="no"/>minish rapidly. At the period when the Jesuits governed the<lb break="yes"/>missions of the lower Oroonoko, they assembled every year at<lb break="yes"/>Cabruta, below the mouth of the Apure, to have a grand fishing<lb break="yes"/>for manatees, with the Indians of their missions, at the foot of the<lb break="yes"/>mountain now called <hi rendition="#i">El Capuchino.</hi> The fat of the animal, known<lb break="yes"/>by the name of <hi rendition="#i">manteca de manati,</hi> is used for lamps in the churches;<lb break="yes"/>and is also employed in preparing food. It has not the fetid smell<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="152" facs="#f0017"/>of whale oil, or that of other cetaceous animals that spout water.<lb break="yes"/>The hide of the manatee, which is more than an inch and a half<lb break="yes"/>thick, is cut into slips, and serves, like thongs of ox leather, to<lb break="yes"/>supply the place of cordage in the Llanos. When immersed in<lb break="yes"/>water, it has the defect of undergoing an incipient degree of pu-<lb break="no"/>trefaction. Whips are made of it in the Spanish colonies. Hence<lb break="yes"/>the words <hi rendition="#i" >latigo</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">manati</hi> are synonimous. These whips of ma-<lb break="no"/>natee leather are a cruel instrument of punishment for the unhap-<lb break="no"/>py slaves, and even for the Indians of the missions, who, accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to the laws, ought to be treated like free men.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We passed the night opposite the island of Conserva. In skirt-<lb break="no"/>ing the forest, we were struck at the view of an enormous trunk<lb break="yes"/>of a tree seventy feet high, and thickly set with branching thorns.<lb break="yes" />It is called by the natives <hi rendition="#i">barba de tigre.</hi> It was perhaps a tree<lb break="yes"/>of the berberideous family. The Indians had kindled fires at the<lb break="yes"/>edge of the water. We again perceived, that their light attracted<lb break="yes"/>the crocodiles, and even the porpoises <hi rendition="#i">(toninas,)</hi> the noise of<lb break="yes"/>which interrupted our sleep, till the fire was extinguished. We<lb break="yes"/>had two persons on the watch this night; which I mention only<lb break="yes" />because it serves to paint the savage character of these places.<lb break="yes"/>A female jaguar approached our station in taking her young one<lb break="yes"/>to drink at the river. The Indians succeeded in chasing her away,<lb break="yes"/>but we heard for a long time the cries of the little jaguar, which<lb break="yes"/>mewed like a young cat. Soon after our great dog was bitten,<lb break="yes"/>or, as the Indians say, <hi rendition="#i" >pricked</hi> at the point of the nose by some<lb break="yes"/>enormous bats, that hovered around our hammocks. They were<lb break="yes"/>furnished with a long tail, like the <hi rendition="#i">molosses:</hi> I believe however,<lb break="yes"/>that they were <hi rendition="#i">phyllostomes,</hi> the tongue of which, furnished with<lb break="yes"/>papill&#x00E6;, is an organ of suction, and is capable of being considera-<lb break="no"/>bly elongated. The wound was very small and round. Though<lb break="yes"/>the dog uttered a plaintive cry, when he felt himself bitten, it was<lb break="yes"/>not from pain, but because he was affrighted at the sight of the<lb break="yes"/>bats, that came out from beneath our hammocks. These accidents<lb break="yes"/>are much more rare than is believed even in the country itself.<lb break="yes"/>In the course of several years, notwithstanding we slept so often<lb break="yes"/>in the open air, in climates where vampires<note place="foot" n="*">Verspertilio spectrum.</note> and other analogous<lb break="yes"/>species are so common, we were never wounded. Besides, the<lb break="yes"/>puncture is no way dangerous, and in general causes so little pain,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="153" facs="#f0018"/>that it often does not awaken the person, till after the bat has with-<lb break="no"/>drawn.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>April the 4th. This was the last day we passed on the Rio<lb break="yes"/>Apure. The vegetation of it&#x2019;s banks become more and more <choice>
                        <sic>uni-<lb break="no"/>form</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">uni-<lb break="no"/>form.</corr>
                    </choice> We had begun for some days past, particularly since we had<lb break="yes"/>left the mission of Arichuna, to suffer cruelly from the stings of<lb break="yes"/>insects, that covered our faces and hands. They were not mos-<lb break="no"/>chettoes, which have the appearance of little flies, or of the genus<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">simulium</hi> but <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes,</hi> which are real gnats, very different from<lb break="yes"/>our culex pipiens.<note place="foot" n="*">Mr. Latreille has discovered, that the moschettoes of South Carolina are<lb break="yes"/>of the genus simulium (attractocera meigen.)</note> These tipulari&#x00E6; appear only after sunset.<lb break="yes"/>Their proboscis is so long, that, when they fix on the lower sur-<lb break="no"/>face of a hammock, they pierce the hammock and the thickest gar-<lb break="no"/>ments with their sting.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We had intended to pass the night at the <hi rendition="#i">Vuelta del Palmito;</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>but the number of jaguars at this part of the Apure is so great,<lb break="yes"/>that our Indians found two hidden behind the trunk of a locust-<lb break="no"/>tree, at the moment when they were going to sling our hammocks.<lb break="yes"/>We were advised to re-embark, and take our station in the island<lb break="yes"/>of Apurito, near its junction with the Oroonoko. That portion<lb break="yes"/>of the island belongs to the province of Caraccas, while the right<lb break="yes"/>banks of the Apure and the Oroonoko make a part, one of the<lb break="yes"/>province of Varinas, the other of Spanish Guayana. We found<lb break="yes"/>no trees to which we could suspend our hammocks, and were<lb break="yes"/>obliged to sleep on ox hides spread on the ground. The boats<lb break="yes"/>are too narrow, and too full of <hi rendition="#i" >zancudoes,</hi> to pass the night in them.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the place where we had landed our instruments, the banks<lb break="yes"/>being steep, we saw new proofs of what I have elsewhere called<lb break="yes"/>the indolence of the gallinaceous birds of the tropics. The curas-<lb break="no" />soas and cashew birds<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">The latter (crax pauxi) is less common than the former.</note> have the habit of going down several times<lb break="yes"/>a day to the river to allay their thirst. They drink a great deal,<lb break="yes"/>and at short intervals. A great number of these birds had joined<lb break="yes"/>themselves near our station to a flock of parraka pheasants. They<lb break="yes"/>had great difficulty in climbing up the steep banks; they attempt-<lb break="no"/>ed it several times without using their wings. We drove them<lb break="yes"/>before us, as you would drive sheep. The zamuro vultures also<lb break="yes"/>raise themselves from the ground with great reluctance.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I had a good observation after midnight of the meridian height<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="154" facs="#f0019"/>of <hi rendition="#i">&#x03B1;</hi> in the Southern Cross. The latitude of the mouth of the<lb break="yes"/>Apure is 7&#x00B0; 36&#x2032; 23&#x2033;. Father Gumilla fixes it at 5&#x00B0; 5&#x2032;; D&#x2019;Anville<lb break="yes"/>at 7&#x00B0; 3&#x2032;; and Caulin at 7&#x00B0; 26&#x2032;. The longitude of the <hi rendition="#i">Boca</hi> of the<lb break="yes"/>Apure, calculated from the altitudes of the Sun, which I took on<lb break="yes"/>the 5th of April in the morning, is 69&#x00B0; 7&#x2032; 29&#x2033;, or 1&#x00B0; 12&#x2032; 41&#x2033; east of<lb break="yes"/>the meridian of San Fernando.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>April the 5th. We were singularly struck at the small quan-<lb break="no"/>tity of water, which the Rio Apure furnishes at this season to the<lb break="yes" />Oroonoko. The Apure, which, according to my measurements,<lb break="yes"/>was still one hundred and thirty-six toises broad at <hi rendition="#i">Cano Ricco,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>was only sixty or eighty at it&#x2019;s mouth.<note place="foot" n="*">Not quite so broad as the Seine at Pont Royal, opposite the palace of<lb break="yes"/>the Tuileries.</note> It&#x2019;s depth here was only<lb break="yes"/>three or four toises. It loses no doubt a part of it&#x2019;s waters by the<lb break="yes"/>Rio Arichuna, and the <hi rendition="#i">Cano</hi> del Manati, two branches of the Apure,<lb break="yes"/>that flow into the Payara and the Guarico; but it&#x2019;s greatest loss<lb break="yes"/>appears to be caused by filtrations on the breach, of which we<lb break="yes"/>have spoken above. The velocity of the Apure near it&#x2019;s mouth<lb break="yes"/>was only 3&#x00B7;2 feet a second; so that I could easily have calculated<lb break="yes"/>the whole quantity of the water, if I had taken by a series of proxi-<lb break="no"/>mate soundings the whole dimensions of the tranverse section.<lb break="yes"/>The barometer, which at San Fernando, twenty-eight feet above<lb break="yes"/>the mean height of the Apure, had kept, at half after nine in the<lb break="yes"/>morning, at 335&#x00B7;6 lines, was, at eleven in the morning, at the en-<lb break="no"/>trance of the Apure into the Oroonoko, 337&#x00B7;3 lines.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">The temperature of the air in these two places being 31&#x00B7;2&#x00B0; and 32&#x00B7;4&#x00B0;.</note> In estimat-<lb break="no"/>ing the total length, including the sinuosities,<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">I estimated them at a quarter of the distance.</note> at ninety-four miles,<lb break="yes"/>or eighty-nine thousand three hundred toises, and attending to<lb break="yes"/>the little correction arising from the horary movement of the ba-<lb break="no" />rometer, we find a mean fall of thirteen inches (exactly 1&#x00B7;15 foot)<lb break="yes"/>in a mile of nine hundred and fifty toises. La Condamine and the<lb break="yes"/>learned Major Rennel suppose, that the mean fall of the Amazon<lb break="yes"/>and the Ganges does not amount even to four or five inches in a<lb break="yes"/>mile.<note place="foot" n="§">Tuckey, Exped. to the Congo, 1818; Introduction, p. 17.</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We touched several times on shoals before we entered the<lb break="yes" />Oroonoko. The lands gained from the water are immense to-<lb break="no"/>ward the confluence of the two rivers. We were obliged to be<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="155" facs="#f0020"/>towed along by the bank. What a contrast between this state of<lb break="yes"/>the river, immediately before the entrance of the rainy season,<lb break="yes"/>when all the effects of the dryness of the air and of evaporation<lb break="yes"/>have attained their <hi rendition="#i" >maximum,</hi> and that autumnal state, when the<lb break="yes"/>Apure, like an arm of the sea, covers the savannahs as far as the<lb break="yes"/>eye can reach! We discerned toward the South the lonely hills<lb break="yes"/>of Coruato; while to the East the granitic rocks of Curiquima,<lb break="yes"/>the sugarloaf of Caycara, and the mountains of the Tyrant<note place="foot" n="*" >This name alludes no doubt to the expedition of Antonio Sedeno: thus<lb break="yes"/>the port of Caycara, opposite Cabruta, still bears the name of this <hi rendition="#i">Conquis-<lb break="no"/>tador.</hi>
                    </note> (<hi rendition="#i">Cer-<lb break="no"/>ros del Tirano</hi>) began to rise on the horizon. It is not without<lb break="yes"/>emotion, that we behold for the first time, after long expectation,<lb break="yes"/>the waters of the Oroonoko, at a point so distant from the coast.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 