<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.1" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.1" when="2018-10-10" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung für Verlag.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-30" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="65" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>BARON HUMBOLDT’S LAST VOLUME.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Personal Narrative of Travels to the<lb break="yes" />Equinoctial Regions of the New<lb break="yes"/>Continent.</hi> Vol. 4. London, 1819.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">For</hi>
                    </hi> ten years past, Baron Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt has been engaged in publishing,<lb break="yes"/>in detached parts, his learned and<lb break="yes"/>interesting observations and discove-<lb break="no"/>ries in the interior regions of South-<lb break="maybe"/>America, and New-Mexico.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In Europe his various works have<lb break="yes"/>been eagerly sought after, and the<lb break="yes"/>learned and curious inquirers of<lb break="yes"/>France, England, and Germany, have<lb break="yes"/>complimented this celebrated tra-<lb break="no"/>veller with the highest eulogiums.<lb break="yes"/>The calculating, and to us, the<lb break="yes"/>tedious manner in which the Baron<lb break="yes"/>continues to yield to the eager curi-<lb break="no"/>osity of the world his scientific re-<lb break="no"/>searches, and his adventures, may<lb break="yes"/>have the effect of continually re-<lb break="no"/>freshing our memory with the recol-<lb break="no"/>lection of his former works, and<lb break="yes"/>keeping alive the interest derived<lb break="yes"/>from his new and successive pub-<lb break="no"/>lications; but, the lapse of twenty<lb break="yes"/>years that has occurred since his<lb break="yes"/>travels in those regions, and the<lb break="yes"/>dreadful revolutions that have since<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="66" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/> convulsed, and are still continuing to<lb break="yes"/>ravage those devoted regions, are<lb break="yes"/>diverting our minds to the interest<lb break="yes"/>that would be excited by more re-<lb break="no"/>cent description. Of the former<lb break="yes"/>volumes of this narrative, two only<lb break="yes"/>have been printed in this country,<lb break="yes"/>and the remainder, we presume, will<lb break="yes"/>not be republished until the termi-<lb break="no"/>nation of the series can be disco-<lb break="no" />vered, as it can hardly be expected<lb break="yes"/>that any bookseller will venture<lb break="yes"/>again to begin a work of such indefi-<lb break="no" />nite extent<choice><sic></sic><corr type="editorial">.</corr></choice></p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Taking his departure from Ca-<lb break="no"/>raccas, he describes the mountainous<lb break="yes"/>regions of San Pedro, and of Los<lb break="yes" />Teques, La Victoria, the Valleys of<lb break="yes"/>Aragua, the Lake of Tacarigua, the<lb break="yes"/>Hot Springs of Mariara; then descends<lb break="yes"/>toward the coasts of Porto Cabello;<lb break="yes"/>describes the mountains that sepa-<lb break="no"/>rate the valleys of Aragua from the<lb break="yes"/>Llanos of Caraccas, Villa de Cura,<lb break="yes"/>Parapara, the great Llanos, or Plains,<lb break="yes"/>Calabozo, San Fernando De Apure;<lb break="yes"/>descends the river Apure to its con-<lb break="no"/>fluence with the great Oroonoko;<lb break="yes"/>and ascends the Oroonoko beyond<lb break="yes"/>the mountains of Encuramada, Uru-<lb break="no"/>ana, Baraguam, the mouth of the<lb break="yes"/>Meta, and above the Cataracts of<lb break="yes" />the Oroonoko, where the volume<lb break="yes"/>abruptly terminates. The closing<lb break="yes"/>part of this interesting voyage will<lb break="yes" />undoubtedly be in due time laid be-<lb break="no"/>fore the public, who can only await<lb break="yes"/>with exemplary patience the time<lb break="yes"/>that may suit the learned traveller<lb break="yes"/>to publish the remainder, or the<lb break="yes"/>conclusion of his observations. In<lb break="yes"/>the mean time, we propose to pre-<lb break="no"/>sent our readers with such portions<lb break="yes"/>of his recently published and most<lb break="yes" />interesting volume, as we may find<lb break="yes"/>suitable to our pages.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">We</hi> left Caraccas on the 7th of Fe-<lb break="no" />bruary, in the cool of the evening,<lb break="yes"/>and began our journey to the Oroo-<lb break="no"/>noko. The remembrance of that de-<lb break="no" />parture is more painful to us now<lb break="yes"/>than it was some years ago. Our<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> friends have perished in the sangui-<lb break="no"/>nary revolutions, which have succes-<lb break="no"/>sively given liberty to those distant<lb break="yes"/>regions, and deprived them of it.<lb break="yes"/>The house which we inhabited is<lb break="yes"/>now a heap of ruins. Tremendous<lb break="yes"/>earthquakes have changed the sur-<lb break="no"/>face of the soil. The city, which I<lb break="yes"/>have described, has disappeared;<lb break="yes"/>and on the same spot, on the ground<lb break="yes"/>fissured in various directions, another<lb break="yes"/>city is slowly rising. Already those<lb break="yes"/>heaps of ruins, the grave of a nu-<lb break="no" />merous population, are become anew<lb break="yes"/>the habitation of men.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In retracing changes of so general<lb break="yes"/>an interest, I shall be led to notice<lb break="yes"/>events that took place long after my<lb break="yes" />return to Europe. I shall pass over<lb break="yes"/>in silence the popular commotions,<lb break="yes"/>and the modifications which the<lb break="yes" />state of society has undergone. Mo-<lb break="no"/>dern nations, careful of their own<lb break="yes"/>remembrance, snatch from oblivion<lb break="yes"/>the history of human revolutions,<lb break="yes"/>which is that of ardent passions, and<lb break="yes"/>inveterate hatred. It is not the same<lb break="yes" />with respect to the revolutions of<lb break="yes"/>the physical world. These are de-<lb break="no"/>scribed with the least accuracy when<lb break="yes"/>they happen to coincide with the pe-<lb break="no"/>riod of civil dissentions. Earth-<lb break="no"/>quakes, and the eruptions of volca-<lb break="no" />noes, strike the imagination by the<lb break="yes"/>evils which are their necessary con-<lb break="no"/>sequence. Tradition seizes in pre-<lb break="no" />ference whatever is vague and mar-<lb break="no"/>vellous; and amid great public ca-<lb break="no"/>lamities, as in private misfortunes,<lb break="yes" />man seems to shun that light which<lb break="yes"/>leads us to discover the real causes<lb break="yes"/>of events, and recognise the circum-<lb break="no" />stances by which they are attended.<lb break="yes"/>I have thought proper to record in<lb break="yes"/>this work all I have been able to<lb break="yes" />collect, with certainty, respecting<lb break="yes"/>the earthquake of the 26th of March,<lb break="yes"/>1812, which destroyed the town of<lb break="yes" />Caraccas; and by which more than<lb break="yes"/>twenty thousand persons perished,<lb break="yes"/>almost at the same instant, in the<lb break="yes" />province of Venezuela. The inter-<lb break="no"/>course which I have kept up with<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="67" facs="#f0003"/>
                    <cb/> persons of all classes has enabled<lb break="yes"/>me to compare the description of<lb break="yes"/>many eye-witnesses, and to interro-<lb break="no" />gate them on objects that may throw<lb break="yes"/>light on physical science in general.<lb break="yes"/>The traveller, being the historian of<lb break="yes" />nature, should authenticate the dates<lb break="yes"/>of great catastrophes, examine their<lb break="yes"/>connection and mutual relations, and<lb break="yes"/>mark, in the rapid course of ages,<lb break="yes"/>in this continual progress of succes-<lb break="no"/>sive changes, those fixed points with<lb break="yes"/>which other catastrophes may one<lb break="yes"/>day be compared. All epochas ap-<lb break="no"/>proach each other in the immensity<lb break="yes"/>of time comprehended in the history<lb break="yes"/>of nature. Years passed away seem<lb break="yes"/>but a few instants; and if the physi-<lb break="no"/>cal descriptions of a country do not<lb break="yes"/>excite a very powerful and general<lb break="yes"/>interest, they have, at least, the ad-<lb break="no"/>vantage of never becoming old. Si-<lb break="no"/>milar considerations, no doubt, led<lb break="yes"/>Mr. De la Condamine to describe, in<lb break="yes"/>his <hi rendition="#i">Voyage à l’Equateur,</hi> the memo-<lb break="no"/>rable eruptions<note place="foot" n="*">Those of the 30th of November, 1744, and<lb break="yes"/>of the 3d of September, 1750. (<hi rendition="#i">Introd. Hist.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>p. 156 and 160.)</note> of the volcano of<lb break="yes" />Cotopaxi, which took place long af-<lb break="no"/>ter his departure from Quito. Fol-<lb break="no"/>lowing the example of this celebra-<lb break="no" />ted traveller, I think I shall the less<lb break="yes"/>deserve blame, as the events which I<lb break="yes"/>am going to relate will serve to elu-<lb break="no"/>cidate the theory of <hi rendition="#i">volcanic reac-<lb break="no"/>tions,</hi> or the influence of a <hi rendition="#i">system of<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes</hi> on a vast space of circum-<lb break="no"/>jacent country.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the time that Mr. Bonpland and<lb break="yes"/>myself inhabited the provinces of<lb break="yes"/>New Andalusia, Nueva Barcelona,<lb break="yes"/>and Caraccas, a general opinion pre-<lb break="no"/>vailed, that the easternmost parts of<lb break="yes"/>these coasts were the most exposed<lb break="yes"/>to the destructive effects of earth-<lb break="no"/>quakes. The inhabitants of Cumana<lb break="yes"/>dreaded the valley of Caraccas, on<lb break="yes" />account of its damp and variable cli-<lb break="no"/>mate, and its gloomy and foggy sky;<lb break="yes"/>while the inhabitants of that tem-<lb break="no" />perate valley considered Cumana as<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> a town where only a burning air was<lb break="yes"/>breathed, and where the soil is pe-<lb break="no"/>riodically agitated by violent com-<lb break="no" />motions. Forgetful of the overthrow<lb break="yes"/>of Riobamba, and other very eleva-<lb break="no"/>ted towns; ignorant that the penin-<lb break="no" />sula of Araya, composed of mica-<lb break="no"/>slate, has partaken of the commo-<lb break="no"/>tions of the calcareous coast of<lb break="yes" />Cumana; well-informed persons<lb break="yes"/>thought they perceived motives of<lb break="yes"/>security in the structure of the pri-<lb break="no" />mitive rocks of Caraccas, as well as<lb break="yes"/>in the elevated situation of this val-<lb break="no"/>ley. Religious ceremonies celebra-<lb break="no" />ted at La Guayra, and even in the<lb break="yes"/>capital, in the middle of the night,<note place="foot" n="*">For instance, the nocturnal procession of<lb break="yes"/>the 21st of October, instituted in commemora-<lb break="no" />tion of the great earthquake which took place<lb break="yes"/>on that day of the month, at one in the morn-<lb break="no"/>ing, in 1778. Other very violent shocks were<lb break="yes"/>those of 1641, 1703, and 1802.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>recalled, no doubt, to their memory,<lb break="yes"/>that the province of Venezuela had<lb break="yes"/>been subject, at intervals, to earth-<lb break="no"/>quakes; but dangers that seldom re-<lb break="no" />cur, are slightly feared. Cruel ex-<lb break="no"/>perience destroyed, in 1811, the<lb break="yes"/>charm of theory, and of popular<lb break="yes" />opinions. Caraccas, situate in the<lb break="yes"/>mountains, three degrees west of<lb break="yes"/>Cumana, and five degrees west of<lb break="yes"/>the volcanoes of the Caribbee islands,<lb break="yes"/>has felt greater shocks than were<lb break="yes"/>ever experienced on the coast of Pa-<lb break="no"/>ria or New Andalusia.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At my arrival in Terra Firma, I<lb break="yes"/>was struck with the connection of<lb break="yes"/>two physical events, the destruction<lb break="yes"/>of Cumana on the 14th of Decem-<lb break="no"/>ber, 1797, and the eruption of the<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes in the smaller West India<lb break="yes" />islands.<note place="foot" n="†">See vol, ii. p. 231.</note> This connection has been<lb break="yes"/>again manifested in the destruction<lb break="yes"/>of Caraccas on the 26th of March,<lb break="yes"/>1812. The volcano of Guadaloupe<lb break="yes"/>seemed to have reacted, in 1797, on<lb break="yes"/>the coasts of Cumana. Fifteen years<lb break="yes"/>after, it was a volcano situate nearer<lb break="yes"/>the continent, that of St. Vincent’s,<lb break="yes"/>which appeared to have extended it’s<lb break="yes"/>influence as far as Caraccas and the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="68" facs="#f0004"/>
                    <cb/> banks of the Apure. It is possible<lb break="yes"/>that, at these two epochas, the cen-<lb break="no"/>tre of the explosion was at an im-<lb break="no"/>mense depth, equally distant from<lb break="yes"/>the regions toward which the motion<lb break="yes"/>was propagated at the surface of the<lb break="yes"/>globe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From the beginning of 1811 till<lb break="yes"/>1813, a vast extent of the earth,<note place="foot" n="*">Between the latitudes of 5° and 36° North,<lb break="yes"/>and the meridians of 31° and 91° West from<lb break="yes" />Paris.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>limited by the meridian of the Azores,<lb break="yes"/>the valley of the Ohio, the Cordil-<lb break="no"/>leras of New Grenada, the coasts of<lb break="yes"/>Venezuela, and the volcanoes of the<lb break="yes" />smaller West India islands, has been<lb break="yes"/>shaken almost at the same time by<lb break="yes"/>commotions; which may be attribu-<lb break="no"/>ted to subterraneous fires. The fol-<lb break="no"/>lowing series of phenomena seems<lb break="yes"/>to indicate communications at enor-<lb break="no"/>mous distances. On the 30th of Ja-<lb break="no"/>nuary, 1811, a submarine volcano<lb break="yes"/>appeared near the island of St. Mi-<lb break="no"/>chael, one of the Azores. At a<lb break="yes"/>place where the sea was sixty fa-<lb break="no"/>thoms deep, a rock appeared above<lb break="yes"/>the surface of the waters. The<lb break="yes"/>heaving up of the softened crust of<lb break="yes"/>the globe appears to have preceded<lb break="yes"/>the eruption of flames by the crater,<note place="foot" n="†">See vol. i. p. 240.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>as had already been observed at the<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes of Jorullo in Mexico, and<lb break="yes"/>at the apparition of the little island<lb break="yes"/>of Kameni near Santorino. The<lb break="yes"/>new islet of the Azores was at first<lb break="yes"/>nothing more than a shoal; but on<lb break="yes"/>the 15th of January an eruption,<lb break="yes"/>which lasted six days, enlarged its<lb break="yes"/>extent, and carried it progressively<lb break="yes"/>to the height of fifty toises above the<lb break="yes"/>surface of the sea. This new land,<lb break="yes"/>of which Captain Tillard hastened<lb break="yes"/>to take possession in the name of the<lb break="yes"/>British government, calling it <hi rendition="#i" >Sabrina<lb break="yes"/>island,</hi> was nine hundred toises in<lb break="yes"/>diameter. It has again, it seems,<lb break="yes"/>been swallowed up by the ocean.<lb break="yes"/>This is the third time that submarine<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes have presented this ex-<lb break="no" />traordinary spectacle near the island<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> of St. Michael; and, as if the erup-<lb break="no"/>tions of these volcanoes were sub-<lb break="no"/>ject to a regular period, owing to a<lb break="yes"/>certain accumulation of elastic fluids,<lb break="yes"/>the island raised up has appeared at<lb break="yes"/>intervals of ninety-one or ninety-<lb break="maybe"/>two years.<note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Malte Brun, Geogra. Univ.</hi> vol. iii. p. 177&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>180 There remains, however, some doubt re-<lb break="no"/>specting the eruption of 1628, which some place<lb break="yes"/>in 1638. The rising always happened near the<lb break="yes" />island of St. Michael, though not identically on<lb break="yes"/>the same spot. It is remarkable that the small<lb break="yes"/>island of 1720 reached the same elevation as<lb break="yes"/>the island of Sabrina in 1811. See above, vol. i<lb break="yes"/>chap. i. p. 95.</note> It is to be regretted<lb break="yes"/>that, notwithstanding the proximity<lb break="yes" />of the spot, no European govern-<lb break="no"/>ment, or learned society, has sent<lb break="yes"/>natural philosophers and geologists<lb break="yes"/>to the Azores, to investigate a phe-<lb break="no"/>nomenon which would throw so much<lb break="yes"/>light on the history of volcanoes,<lb break="yes"/>and on that of the globe in general.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the time of the appearance of<lb break="yes"/>the new island of Sabrina, the small-<lb break="no"/>er West India islands, situate eight<lb break="yes" />hundred leagues to the south-west<lb break="yes"/>of the Azores, experienced frequent<lb break="yes"/>earthquakes. More than two hun-<lb break="no"/>dred shocks were felt from the month<lb break="yes"/>of May, 1811, to April, 1812, in the<lb break="yes"/>island of St. Vincent; one of the<lb break="yes"/>three where there are still active<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes. The commotion did not<lb break="yes"/>remain circumscribed to that insular<lb break="yes"/>portion of Eastern America. From<lb break="yes"/>the 16th of December, 1811, the<lb break="yes"/>earth was almost incessantly agitated<lb break="yes"/>in the valleys of the Mississippi, the<lb break="yes"/>Arkansas, and the Ohio. The oscil-<lb break="no"/>lations were more feeble on the east<lb break="yes" />of the Alleghanies than to the west<lb break="yes"/>of these mountains, in Tennessee<lb break="yes"/>and Kentucky. They were accom-<lb break="no" />panied by a great subterraneous<lb break="yes"/>noise, coming from the south-west.<lb break="yes"/>At the spots between New Madrid<lb break="yes" />and Little Prairie, as at the Saline,<lb break="yes"/>north of Cincinnati, in latitude 37°<lb break="yes"/>45′, the shocks were felt every day,<lb break="yes" />nay, almost every hour, during seve-<lb break="no"/>ral months. The whole of these<lb break="yes"/>phenomena lasted from the 16th of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="69" facs="#f0005"/>
                    <cb/> December, 1811, till the year 1813.<lb break="yes"/>The commotion, confined at first to<lb break="yes"/>the south, in the valley of the lower<lb break="yes"/>Mississippi, appeared to advance<lb break="yes"/>slowly toward the north.<note place="foot" n="*">See the interesting description of these<lb break="yes"/>earthquakes, given by Mr. Mitchill, in the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Trans. of the Liter. and Phil. Soc. of New<lb break="yes" />York,</hi> vol. i. p. 281&#x2014;308; and by Mr. Drake,<lb break="yes" />in the <hi rendition="#i">Nat. and Stat. View of Cincinnati,</hi> p.<lb break="yes"/>232&#x2014;238.</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the same period, when this long<lb break="yes"/>series of earthquakes began in the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Transalleghanian States,</hi> in the month<lb break="yes"/>of December, 1811, the town of<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas felt the first shock in calm<lb break="yes"/>and serene weather. This coinci-<lb break="no"/>dence of phenomena was probably<lb break="yes"/>not accidental; for we must not for-<lb break="no"/>get that, notwithstanding the distance<lb break="yes" />which separates these countries, the<lb break="yes"/>low grounds of Louisiana, and the<lb break="yes"/>coasts of Venezuela and Cumana,<lb break="yes"/>belong to the same basin, that of the<lb break="yes"/>Gulf of Mexico. This <hi rendition="#i">Mediterra-<lb break="no"/>nean sea, with several outlets,</hi> runs<lb break="yes"/>from the south-east to the north-<lb break="no"/>west; and an ancient prolongation<lb break="yes"/>of it seems to be found in those vast<lb break="yes"/>plains, rising gradually thirty, fifty,<lb break="yes"/>and eighty toises<note place="foot" n="†">Cincinnati, situated on the Ohio, in latitude<lb break="yes"/>39° 6 min has only eighty-five toises absolute<lb break="yes"/>elevation.</note> above the level of<lb break="yes"/>the ocean, covered with secondary<lb break="yes" />formations, and watered by the Ohio,<lb break="yes"/>the Missouri, the Arkansas, and the<lb break="yes"/>Mississippi. When we consider ge-<lb break="no"/>ologically <hi rendition="#i">the basin of the Caribbean<lb break="yes"/>sea, and of the Gulf of Mexico,</hi> we<lb break="yes" />find it bounded on the south by the<lb break="yes"/>chain of the coast of Venezuela and<lb break="yes"/>the Cordilleras of Merida and Pam-<lb break="no" />plona; on the east by the mountains<lb break="yes"/>of the West India islands, and the<lb break="yes"/>Alleghanies; on the west by the<lb break="yes"/>Andes of Mexico, and the Stony<lb break="yes"/>Mountains;<note place="foot" n="‡" xml:id="fn1-1" next="#fn1-2">It is with regret I use this vague and im-<lb break="no"/>proper denomination, which is given to the<lb break="yes" />northern prolongation of the mountains of New<lb break="yes"/>Mexico. I should prefer the name of Chippe-<lb break="no"/>wan Range, which Mr. Drake (Stat. View of</note> and on the north by<lb break="yes"/>very inconsiderable elevations which<lb break="yes"/>separate the Canadian lakes from the<lb break="yes"/>rivers that flow into the Mississippi.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> More than two-thirds of this basin<lb break="yes"/>are covered with water. It is bor-<lb break="no"/>dered by two ranges of active volca-<lb break="no" />noes; to the east, in the Caribbee<lb break="yes"/>islands, between the latitudes of 13°<lb break="yes"/>and 16°; and to the west in the Cor-<lb break="no"/>dilleras of Nicaragua, Guatimala, and<lb break="yes"/>Mexico, between 11° and 20°.<lb break="yes"/>When we reflect that the great earth-<lb break="no"/>quake at Lisbon, of the 1st of No-<lb break="no"/>vember, 1755, was felt almost at the<lb break="yes"/>same moment on the coasts of Swe-<lb break="no"/>den, at lake Ontario, and at the island<lb break="yes"/>of Martinico, it will not appear too<lb break="yes"/>daring to suppose, that all this basin<lb break="yes"/>of the West Indies, from Cumana<lb break="yes"/>and Caraccas as far as the plains of<lb break="yes"/>Louisiana, may be simultaneously<lb break="yes"/>agitated by commotions proceeding<lb break="yes"/>from the same centre of action.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>An opinion very generally pre-<lb break="no"/>vails on the coasts of Terra Firma,<lb break="yes"/>that earthquakes become more fre-<lb break="no" />quent when electric explosions have<lb break="yes"/>been very rare during some years.<lb break="yes"/>It is thought to have been observed,<lb break="yes" />at Cumana and Caraccas, that the<lb break="yes"/>rains were less frequently attended<lb break="yes"/>with thunder from the year 1792; and<lb break="yes" />the total destruction of Cumana in<lb break="yes"/>1797, and the commotions felt<note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Depons,</hi> vol. i. p. 125.</note> in<lb break="yes" />1800, 1801, and 1802, at Maracaibo,<lb break="yes"/>Porto Cabello, and Caraccas, have<lb break="yes"/>not failed to be attributed to “an<lb break="yes" />accumulation of electricity in the in-<lb break="no"/>terior of the earth.” It would be<lb break="yes"/>difficult for a person who has lived<lb break="yes"/>a long time in New Andalusia, or in<lb break="yes"/>the low regions of Peru, to deny<lb break="yes"/>that the season the most to be dread-<lb break="no" />ed, from the frequency of earth-<lb break="no"/>quakes, is that of the beginning of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="‡" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1">Cincinnati, p. 91.) and other geographers of<lb break="yes"/>the United States, begin to substitute for the<lb break="yes"/>received denomination of <hi rendition="#i">Stony Mountains;</hi> but<lb break="yes"/>nations almost of the same name, very distant<lb break="yes"/>from each other, and speaking different langua-<lb break="no"/>ges, the Chippeways of the sources of the Mis-<lb break="no"/>sissippi, and the Chepewyans of the Slave<lb break="yes" />Lake, described by Pike and Mackenzie, may<lb break="yes"/>occasion those mountains to the south and<lb break="yes"/>south-west of the great Canadian lakes, which<lb break="yes"/>lie east and west, to be confounded with<lb break="yes"/>the Stony Mountains, which run north and<lb break="yes" />south.</note>
                    <pb n="70" facs="#f0006"/>
                    <cb/> the rains, which is, however, the<lb break="yes"/>time of thunder storms. The at-<lb break="no"/>mosphere, and the slate of the sur-<lb break="no"/>face of the globe, seem to have an<lb break="yes"/>influence unknown to us on the<lb break="yes"/>changes produced at great depths;<lb break="yes"/>and I believe, that the connection<lb break="yes"/>which some persons pretend to re-<lb break="no"/>cognise between the absence of<lb break="yes"/>thunder storms and the frequency of<lb break="yes"/>earthquakes, is rather a physical hy-<lb break="no"/>pothesis, framed by the half-learned<lb break="yes"/>of the country, than the result of<lb break="yes"/>long experience. The coincidence<lb break="yes"/>of certain phenomena may be fa-<lb break="no" />voured by chance. The extraor-<lb break="no"/>dinary commotions felt almost con-<lb break="no"/>tinually during two years on the bor-<lb break="no" />ders of the Mississippi and the Ohio,<lb break="yes"/>and which coincided in 1812 with<lb break="yes"/>those of the valley of Caraccas, were<lb break="yes" />preceded at Louisiana by a year al-<lb break="no"/>most exempt from thunder storms.<note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Trans. of New York,</hi> vol. i. p. 285; <hi rendition="#i">Drake,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>p. 210.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Every mind was again struck with<lb break="yes"/>this phenomenon. We cannot deem<lb break="yes"/>it strange that in the country of<lb break="yes"/>Franklin a great predilection is re-<lb break="no"/>tained for explanations founded on<lb break="yes"/>the theory of electricity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The shock felt at Caraccas in the<lb break="yes"/>month of December, 1811, was the<lb break="yes"/>only one that preceded the horrible<lb break="yes" />catastrophe of the 26th of March,<lb break="yes"/>1812. The inhabitants of Terra<lb break="yes"/>Firma were ignorant of the agita-<lb break="no"/>tions of the volcano in the island of<lb break="yes"/>St. Vincent on one side, and on the<lb break="yes"/>other, of those that were felt in the<lb break="yes" />basin of the Mississippi, where, on<lb break="yes"/>the 7th and 8th of February, 1812,<lb break="yes"/>the earth was day and night in per-<lb break="no"/>petual oscillation. A great drought<lb break="yes"/>prevailed at this period in the pro-<lb break="no"/>vince of Venezuela. Not a single<lb break="yes"/>drop of rain had fallen at Caraccas,<lb break="yes"/>or in the country ninety leagues<lb break="yes"/>round, during the five months which<lb break="yes"/>preceded the destruction of the ca-<lb break="no"/>pital. The 26th of March was a re-<lb break="no"/>markably hot day. The air was<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> calm, and the sky unclouded. It was<lb break="yes"/>Holy Thursday, and a great part of<lb break="yes"/>the population was assembled in the<lb break="yes" />churches. Nothing seemed to pre-<lb break="no"/>sage the calamities of the day. At<lb break="yes"/>seven minutes after four in the after-<lb break="no" />noon the first shock was felt; it was<lb break="yes"/>sufficiently powerful to make the<lb break="yes"/>bells of the churches toll; it lasted<lb break="yes" />five or six seconds, during which time<lb break="yes"/>the ground was in a continual undu-<lb break="no"/>lating movement, and seemed to<lb break="yes" />heave up like a boiling liquid. The<lb break="yes"/>danger was thought to be past, when<lb break="yes"/>a tremendous subterraneous noise<lb break="yes"/>was heard, resembling the rolling of<lb break="yes"/>thunder, but louder, and of longer<lb break="yes"/>continuance, than that heard within<lb break="yes" />the tropics in time of storms. This<lb break="yes"/>noise preceded a perpendicular mo-<lb break="no"/>tion of three or four seconds, follow-<lb break="no"/>ed by an undulatory movement some-<lb break="no"/>what longer. The shocks were in<lb break="yes"/>opposite directions, from north to<lb break="yes"/>south, and from east to west. No-<lb break="no"/>thing could resist the movement<lb break="yes"/>from beneath upward, and undula-<lb break="no"/>tions crossing each other. The<lb break="yes"/>town of Caraccas was entirely over-<lb break="no"/>thrown. Thousands of the inhabi-<lb break="no" />tants (between nine and ten thou-<lb break="no"/>sand) were buried under the ruins<lb break="yes"/>of the houses and churches. The<lb break="yes" />procession had not yet set out; but<lb break="yes"/>the crowd was so great in the<lb break="yes"/>churches, that nearly three or four<lb break="yes" />thousand persons were crushed by<lb break="yes"/>the fall of their vaulted roofs. The<lb break="yes"/>explosion was stronger toward the<lb break="yes" />north, in that part of the town situ-<lb break="no"/>ate nearest the mountain of Avila,<lb break="yes"/>and the Silla. The churches of La<lb break="yes" />Trinidad and Alta Gracia, which<lb break="yes"/>were more than one hundred and<lb break="yes"/>fifty feet high, and the naves of which<lb break="yes" />were supported by pillars of twelve<lb break="yes"/>or fifteen feet diameter, left a mass<lb break="yes"/>of ruins scarcely exceeding five or<lb break="yes" />six feet in elevation. The sinking<lb break="yes"/>of the ruins has been so considera-<lb break="no"/>ble that there now scarcely remain<lb break="yes" />any vestiges of pillars or columns.<lb break="yes"/>The barracks, called <hi rendition="#i">El Quartel de</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="71" facs="#f0007"/>
                    <cb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">San Carlos,</hi> situate farther north of<lb break="yes"/>the church of the Trinity, on the<lb break="yes"/>road from the custom-house de la<lb break="yes"/>Pastora, almost entirely disappeared.<lb break="yes"/>A regiment of troops of the line,<lb break="yes"/>that was assembled under arms, ready<lb break="yes"/>to join the procession, was, with the<lb break="yes" />exception of a few men, buried un-<lb break="no"/>der the ruins of this great edifice.<lb break="yes"/>Nine tenths of the fine town of Ca-<lb break="no" />raccas were entirely destroyed. The<lb break="yes"/>walls of the houses that were not<lb break="yes"/>thrown down, as those of the street<lb break="yes"/>San Juan, near the Capuchin Hospi-<lb break="no"/>tal, were cracked in such a manner<lb break="yes"/>that it was impossible to run the risk<lb break="yes" />of inhabiting them. The effects of<lb break="yes"/>the earthquake were somewhat less<lb break="yes"/>violent in the western and southern<lb break="yes" />parts of the city, between the prin-<lb break="no"/>cipal square and the ravine of Cara-<lb break="no"/>quata. There, the cathedral, sup-<lb break="no" />ported by enormous buttresses, re-<lb break="no"/>mains standing.<note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Sur le Tremblement de Terre de Venezu-<lb break="no" />ela, en</hi> 1812, <hi rendition="#i">par M. Delpeche.</hi> MS.</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Estimating at nine or ten thousand<lb break="yes"/>the number of the dead in the city<lb break="yes"/>of Caraccas, we do not include those<lb break="yes" />unhappy persons who, dangerously<lb break="yes"/>wounded, perished several months<lb break="yes"/>after, for want of food and proper<lb break="yes" />care. The night of Holy Thursday<lb break="yes"/>presented the most distressing scene<lb break="yes"/>of desolation and sorrow. That<lb break="yes" />thick cloud of dust which, rising<lb break="yes"/>above the ruins, darkened the sky<lb break="yes"/>like a fog, had settled on the ground.<lb break="yes" />No shock was felt, and never was a<lb break="yes"/>night more calm or more serene.<lb break="yes"/>The Moon, nearly full, illumined the<lb break="yes" />rounded domes of the Silla, and the<lb break="yes"/>aspect of the sky formed a perfect<lb break="yes"/>contrast to that of the earth, covered<lb break="yes"/>with the dead, and heaped with ruins.<lb break="yes"/>Mothers were seen bearing in their<lb break="yes"/>arms their children, whom they<lb break="yes"/>hoped to <choice><sic>recal</sic><corr type="editorial">recall</corr></choice> to life. Desolate fa-<lb break="no"/>milies wandered through the city,<lb break="yes"/>seeking a brother, a husband, a friend,<lb break="yes"/>of whose fate they were ignorant,<lb break="yes" />and whom they believed to be lost<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> in the crowd. The people pressed<lb break="yes"/>along the streets, which could no<lb break="yes"/>more be recognized but by long lines<lb break="yes"/>of ruins.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>All the calamities experienced in<lb break="yes"/>the great catastrophes of Lisbon,<lb break="yes"/>Messina, Lima, and Riobamba, were<lb break="yes" />renewed on the fatal day of the 26th<lb break="yes"/>of March, 1812<choice><sic></sic><corr type="editorial">.</corr></choice> “The wounded,<lb break="yes"/>buried under the ruins, implored, by<lb break="yes" />their cries, the help of the passers<lb break="yes"/>by, and nearly two thousand were<lb break="yes"/>dug out. Never was pity displayed<lb break="yes" />in a more affecting manner; never<lb break="yes"/>had it been seen more ingeniously<lb break="yes"/>active than in the efforts employed to<lb break="yes"/>save the miserable victims whose<lb break="yes"/>groans reached the ear. Imple-<lb break="no"/>ments for digging, and clearing away<lb break="yes"/>the ruins, were entirely wanting;<lb break="yes"/>and the people were obliged to use<lb break="yes"/>their bare hands to disinter the liv-<lb break="no"/>ing. The wounded, as well as the<lb break="yes"/>sick who had escaped from the hos-<lb break="no"/>pitals, were laid on the banks of the<lb break="yes"/>small river Guayra. They found no<lb break="yes" />shelter but the foliage of trees.<lb break="yes"/>Beds, linen to dress the wounds, in-<lb break="no"/>struments of surgery, medicines, and<lb break="yes" />objects of the most urgent necessity,<lb break="yes"/>were buried under the ruins. Every<lb break="yes"/>thing, even food, was wanting during<lb break="yes" />the first days. Water became alike<lb break="yes"/>scarce in the interior of the city.<lb break="yes"/>The commotion had rent the pipes<lb break="yes"/>of the <choice><sic>fouutains</sic><corr type="editorial">fountains</corr></choice>; the falling in of the<lb break="yes"/>earth had choaked up the springs<lb break="yes"/>that supplied them; and it became<lb break="yes" />necessary, in order to have water, to<lb break="yes"/>go down to the river Guayra, which<lb break="yes"/>was considerably swelled; and then<lb break="yes" />vessels to convey the water were<lb break="yes"/>wanting.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>“</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial"/>
                    </choice>There remained a duty to be<lb break="yes"/>fulfilled toward the dead, enjoined<lb break="yes"/>at once by piety, and the dread of<lb break="yes" />infection. It being impossible to<lb break="yes"/>inter so many thousand corpses,<lb break="yes"/>half buried under the ruins, com-<lb break="no" />missaries were appointed to burn<lb break="yes"/>the bodies: and for this purpose<lb break="yes"/>funeral piles were erected between<lb break="yes" />the heaps of ruins. This ceremony<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="72" facs="#f0008"/>
                    <cb/> lasted several days. Amid so many<lb break="yes"/>public calamities, the people devo-<lb break="no"/>ted themselves to those religious<lb break="yes" />duties, which they thought were the<lb break="yes"/>most fitted to appease the wrath of<lb break="yes"/>Heaven. Some, assembling in pro-<lb break="no" />cessions, sung funeral hymns;<lb break="yes"/>others, in a state of distraction, con-<lb break="no"/>fessed themselves aloud in the<lb break="yes" />streets. In this town was now re-<lb break="no"/>peated what had been remarked in<lb break="yes"/>the province of Quito, after the<lb break="yes" />tremendous earthquake of 1797: a<lb break="yes"/>number of marriages were con-<lb break="no"/>tracted between persons, who had<lb break="yes" />neglected for many years to sanction<lb break="yes"/>their union by the sacerdotal bene-<lb break="no"/>diction. Children found parents, by<lb break="yes"/>whom they had never till then been<lb break="yes" />acknowledged; restitutions were<lb break="yes"/>promised by persons, who had ne-<lb break="no"/>ver been accused of fraud; and fa-<lb break="no"/>milies, who had long been enemies,<lb break="yes"/>were drawn together by the tie of<lb break="yes"/>common calamity. If this feeling<lb break="yes"/>seemed to calm the passions of some,<lb break="yes"/>and open the heart to pity, it had a<lb break="yes"/>contrary effect on others, rendering<lb break="yes"/>them more rigid and inhuman. In<lb break="yes"/>great calamities vulgar minds pre-<lb break="no"/>serve still less goodness than strength:<lb break="yes" />misfortune acts in the same manner,<lb break="yes"/>as the pursuits of literature and the<lb break="yes"/>study of nature; their happy influ-<lb break="no"/>ence is felt only by a few, giving<lb break="yes"/>more ardour to sentiment, more ele-<lb break="no"/>vation to the thoughts, and more be-<lb break="no"/>nevolence to the disposition.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>“</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial"/>
                    </choice>Shocks as violent as those,<lb break="yes"/>which in the space of one minute<note place="foot" n="*">The duration of the earthquake, that is to<lb break="yes"/>say, the whole of the movements of undulation<lb break="yes"/>and rising (<hi rendition="#i"><choice><sic>undulaceon</sic><corr type="editorial">undulacion</corr></choice> y trepidacion,</hi>) which<lb break="yes"/>occasioned the horrible catastrophe of the 26th<lb break="yes"/>of March, 1812, was estimated by some at 50″,<lb break="yes"/>by others at 1′ 12″</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>overthrew the city of Caraccas,<lb break="yes"/>could not be confined to a small por-<lb break="no"/>tion of the continent. Their fatal<lb break="yes"/>effects extended as far as the pro-<lb break="no"/>vinces of Venezuela, Varinas, and<lb break="yes"/>Maracaybo, along the coast; and<lb break="yes"/>still more to the inland mountains.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> La Guayra, Mayquetia, Antimano,<lb break="yes"/>Baruta, La Vega, San Felipe, and<lb break="yes"/>Merida, were almost entirely de-<lb break="no" />stroyed. The number of the dead<lb break="yes"/>exceeded four or five thousand at<lb break="yes"/>La Guayra, and at the town of San<lb break="yes"/>Felipe, near the copper mines of<lb break="yes"/>Aroa. It appears, that it was on a<lb break="yes"/>line running East-North-East, and<lb break="yes" />West-South-West, from La Guayra<lb break="yes"/>and Caraccas to the lofty mountains<lb break="yes"/>of Niquitao and Merida, that the<lb break="yes" />violence of the earthquake was<lb break="yes"/>principally directed. It was felt in<lb break="yes"/>the kingdom of New Grenada from<lb break="yes"/>the branches of the high Sierra de<lb break="yes"/>Santa Martha<note place="foot" n="*">As far as Villa de Los Remedios, and even<lb break="yes"/>to Carthagena.</note> as far as Santa Fe de<lb break="yes"/>Bogota and Honda, on the banks of<lb break="yes"/>the Magdalena, one hundred and<lb break="yes" />eighty leagues from Caraccas. It<lb break="yes"/>was every where more violent in<lb break="yes"/>the Cordilleras of gneiss and mica-<lb break="no"/>slate, or immediately at their foot,<lb break="yes"/>than in the plains, and this differ-<lb break="no"/>ence was particularly striking in<lb break="yes"/>the savannahs of Varinas and Cassa-<lb break="no"/>nara. (This is easily explained ac-<lb break="no"/>cording to the system of those geo-<lb break="no" />logists, who admit, that all the chains<lb break="yes"/>of mountains, volcanic and not volca-<lb break="no"/>nic, have been formed by being<lb break="yes" />raised up, as if through crevices.)<lb break="yes"/>In the valleys of Aragua, situate be-<lb break="no"/>tween Caraccas and the town of San<lb break="yes" />Felipe, the commotions were very<lb break="yes"/>weak: and La Victoria, Maracay,<lb break="yes"/>and Valencia, scarcely suffered at<lb break="yes" />all, notwithstanding their proximity<lb break="yes"/>to the capital. At Valecillo, a few<lb break="yes"/>leagues from Valencia, the earth,<lb break="yes"/>opening, threw out such an immense<lb break="yes"/>quantity of water, that it formed a<lb break="yes"/>new torrent. The same phenome-<lb break="no"/>non took place near Porto-Cabello.<note place="foot" n="†">It is asserted, that in the mountains of Aros,<lb break="yes"/>the ground, immediately after the great shocks,<lb break="yes"/>was found covered with a very fine and white<lb break="yes"/>earth, which appeared to have been projected<lb break="yes"/>through crevices.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>On the other hand, the lake of Ma-<lb break="no"/>racaybo diminished sensibly. At<lb break="yes"/>Coro no commotion was felt, though<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="73" facs="#f0009"/>
                    <cb/> the town is situate upon the coast,<lb break="yes"/>between other towns which suffered<lb break="yes"/>from the earthquake.”<note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Apuntamientos sobre las principales Cir-<lb break="no" />cunstancias del Terremoto de Caracas, por<lb break="yes"/>Don Manuel Palacio Fajardo.</hi> MS.</note> Fishermen,<lb break="yes"/>who had passed the day of the 26th<lb break="yes"/>of March in the island of Orchila,<lb break="yes"/>thirty leagues North-East of La<lb break="yes"/>Guayra, felt no shock. These dif-<lb break="no"/>ferences, in the direction and pro-<lb break="no"/>pagation of the shock, are probably<lb break="yes"/>owing to the peculiar arrangement<lb break="yes"/>of the stony strata.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Having thus traced the effects of<lb break="yes"/>the earthquake to the West of Ca-<lb break="no"/>raccas, as far as the snowy moun-<lb break="no"/>tains of Santa Marta, and the table<lb break="yes"/>land of Santa Fe de Bogota, we will<lb break="yes"/>proceed to consider their action on<lb break="yes"/>the country East of the capital.<lb break="yes"/>The commotions were very violent<lb break="yes"/>beyond Caurimare, in the valley of<lb break="yes"/>Capaya, where they extended as far<lb break="yes"/>as the meridian of Cape Codera:<lb break="yes"/>but it is extremely remarkable, that<lb break="yes"/>they were very feeble on the coasts<lb break="yes"/>of Nueva-Barcelona, Cumana, and<lb break="yes"/>Paria; though these coasts are the<lb break="yes"/>continuation of the shore of La<lb break="yes"/>Guayra, and formerly known to have<lb break="yes"/>been often agitated by subterraneous<lb break="yes" />commotions. Admitting that the<lb break="yes"/>destruction of the four towns of Ca-<lb break="no"/>raccas, La Guayra, San Felipe, and<lb break="yes"/>Merida, may be attributed to a vol-<lb break="no"/>canic focus placed under or near<lb break="yes"/>the island of St. Vincent, it may be<lb break="yes"/>conceived, that the motion might<lb break="yes"/>have been propagated from North-<lb break="maybe"/>East to North-West<note place="foot" n="†">Nearly in a line directed South, 64° west.</note> in a line pass-<lb break="no"/>ing through the islands of Los Her-<lb break="no"/>manos, near Blanquilla, without<lb break="yes"/>touching the coasts of Araya, Cu-<lb break="no"/>mana, and Nueva-Barcelona. This<lb break="yes"/>propagation of the shock might even<lb break="yes"/>have taken place, without the inter-<lb break="no"/>mediate points at the surface of the<lb break="yes"/>globe, the Hermanos Islands for in-<lb break="no"/>stance, having felt any commotion.<lb break="yes"/>This phenomenon is frequently re-<lb break="no"/>marked at Peru and Mexico, in<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> earthquakes which have followed<lb break="yes"/>during ages a determinate direction.<lb break="yes"/>The inhabitants of the Andes say<lb break="yes" />with simplicity, speaking of an inter-<lb break="no"/>mediary ground, which is not af-<lb break="no"/>fected by the general motion, “that<lb break="yes"/>it forms a bridge” (<hi rendition="#i">que hace puente:</hi>)<lb break="yes"/>as if they meant to indicate by this<lb break="yes"/>expression, that the undulations are<lb break="yes"/>propagated at an immense depth<lb break="yes"/>under an inert rock.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Fifteen or eighteen hours after<lb break="yes"/>the great catastrophe, the ground<lb break="yes"/>remained tranquil. The night, as<lb break="yes"/>we have already observed, was fine<lb break="yes"/>and calm; and the commotions did<lb break="yes"/>not recommence till after the 27th.<lb break="yes"/>They were then attended with a<lb break="yes"/>very loud and long continued subter-<lb break="no"/>ranean noise (<hi rendition="#i">bramido.</hi>) The in-<lb break="no"/>habitants of Caraccas wandered into<lb break="yes"/>the country; but the villages and<lb break="yes"/>farms having suffered as much as the<lb break="yes"/>town, they could find no shelter till<lb break="yes" />they were beyond the mountains of<lb break="yes"/>Los Teques, in the valleys of Ara-<lb break="no"/>gua, and in the Llanos or Savannahs.<lb break="yes"/>No less than fifteen oscillations were<lb break="yes"/>often felt in one day. On the 5th<lb break="yes"/>of April there was almost as violent<lb break="yes"/>an earthquake as that which over-<lb break="no"/>threw the capital. During several<lb break="yes"/>hours the ground was in a state of<lb break="yes" />perpetual undulation. Large masses<lb break="yes"/>of earth fell in the mountains; and<lb break="yes"/>enormous rocks were detached from<lb break="yes" />the Silla of Caraccas. It was even<lb break="yes"/>asserted, and this opinion prevails<lb break="yes"/>still in the country, that the two<lb break="yes" />domes of the Silla sunk fifty or sixty<lb break="yes"/>toises; but this assertion is founded<lb break="yes"/>on no measurement whatever. I<lb break="yes"/>am informed, that in the province of<lb break="yes"/>Quito also, the people, at every pe-<lb break="no"/>riod of great commotions, imagine<lb break="yes"/>that the volcano of Tunguragua is<lb break="yes" />diminished in height.&#x2014;It has been<lb break="yes"/>affirmed, in many descriptions pub-<lb break="no"/>lished of the destruction of Caraccas,<lb break="yes"/>“that the mountain of the Silla is<lb break="yes"/>an extinguished volcano; that a<lb break="yes"/>great quantity of volcanic substances<lb break="yes"/>are found on the road from La<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="74" facs="#f0010"/>
                    <cb/> Guayra to Caraccas;<note place="foot" n="*">See the account given by Mr. Drouet of<lb break="yes"/>Guadaloupe, translated in the <hi rendition="#i" >Trans. of New<lb break="yes"/>York,</hi> vol. i. p. 303 The author, in giving<lb break="yes"/>to the Silla nine hundred toises of <hi rendition="#i">absolute</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>height, has confounded the height of the moun-<lb break="no"/>tain, in my measurement, above the level of the<lb break="yes"/>sea, with its height above the valley of Cara-<lb break="no"/>cas, which makes a difference of four hundred<lb break="yes" />and sixty toises.</note> that the rocks<lb break="yes"/>do not present any regular stratifica-<lb break="no"/>tion; and that every thing bears the<lb break="yes"/>stamp of the action of fire.” It is<lb break="yes"/>even added, “that, twelve years be-<lb break="no"/>fore the great catastrophe, Mr. Bon-<lb break="no"/>pland and myself, from our physical<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> and mineralogical researches, had<lb break="yes"/>considered the Silla as a very dange-<lb break="no"/>rous neighbour to the city, because<lb break="yes" />that mountain contained a great<lb break="yes"/>quantity of sulphur, and that the<lb break="yes"/>commotions must come from the<lb break="yes" />North-East.” It is seldom that na-<lb break="no"/>tural philosophers have to justify<lb break="yes"/>themselves for an accomplished pre-<lb break="no" />diction; but I think it my duty to<lb break="yes"/>combat ideas that are too easily<lb break="yes"/>adopted on the <hi rendition="#i">local causes</hi> of earth-<lb break="no"/>quakes.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 