<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="251" facs="#f0001"/><cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">electrical eels.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> dread of the gymnoti, or electri-<lb break="no"/>cal eels of South America, is so great<lb break="yes"/>among the Indians, that the offer of re-<lb break="no"/>ward is unavailing to induce them to<lb break="yes" />endeavour to procure some of them;<lb break="yes"/>though they pretend, by only chewing a<lb break="yes"/>little tobacco, they may venture to touch<lb break="yes"/>them with impunity. &#x201C;This fable,&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>says M. de Humboldt, in his personal<lb break="yes"/>narrative of travels, &#x201C;of the influence of<lb break="yes"/>tobacco on animal electricity, is as gene-<lb break="no"/>ral on the continent of South America,<lb break="yes"/>as the belief among mariners of the<lb break="yes"/>effect of garlic and tallow on the mag-<lb break="no"/>netic needle,&#x201D; and as groundless too.<lb break="yes" />The gymnoti are difficult to be taken by<lb break="yes"/>nets, on account of their extreme agility,<lb break="yes"/>and their burying themselves in the mud<lb break="yes"/>like serpents; they are more easily<lb break="yes" />caught by the roots of the <hi rendition="#i">piscidea erith-<lb break="no" />ryna, jacquinia armillaris,</hi> and some spe-<lb break="no"/>cies of <hi rendition="#i">phyllanthus,</hi> which when thrown<lb break="yes"/>into the pool, intoxicate or benumb<lb break="yes"/>them. This, however, would have en-<lb break="no"/>feebled the gymnoti, and Humboldt<lb break="yes"/>wished to procure them in full vigour.<lb break="yes"/>The Indians therefore told him that they<lb break="yes"/>would set the fish to sleep, or intoxicate<lb break="yes"/>them with horses. He found it difficult<lb break="yes"/>to conceive what this meant; but he saw<lb break="yes"/>the guides, who had gone to the savan-<lb break="no"/>nah, return presently to the stream of<lb break="yes" />muddy water to which he had been con-<lb break="no"/>ducted, with about thirty horses and<lb break="yes"/>mules which they had collected. The<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>novel and singular scene which ensued is<lb break="yes"/>thus described by that traveller:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The extraordinary noise caused by<lb break="yes"/>the horses&#x2019; hoofs makes the fish issue<lb break="yes"/>from the mud, and excites them to com-<lb break="no" />bat. These yellowish and livid eels, re-<lb break="no"/>sembling large aquatic serpents, swim<lb break="yes"/>on the surface of the water, and crowd<lb break="yes"/>under the bellies of the horses and mules.<lb break="yes"/>A contest between animals of so different<lb break="yes"/>an organization, furnishes a striking<lb break="yes"/>spectacle. The Indians, provided with<lb break="yes"/>harpoons and long slender reeds, surround<lb break="yes"/>the pool closely; and some climb upon<lb break="yes"/>the trees, the branches of which extend<lb break="yes"/>horizontally over the surface of the water.<lb break="yes"/>By their wild cries and the length of<lb break="yes"/>their reeds, they prevent the horses from<lb break="yes"/>running away and reaching the bank of<lb break="yes"/>the pool. The eels, stunned by the noise,<lb break="yes"/>defend themselves by the repeated dis-<lb break="no"/>charge of their electric batteries. Dur-<lb break="no"/>ing a long time they seem to prove vic-<lb break="no"/>torious. Several horses sink beneath<lb break="yes"/>the violence of the invisible strokes,<lb break="yes"/>which they receive from all sides in<lb break="yes"/>organs the most essential to life; and<lb break="yes" />stunned by the force and frequency of<lb break="yes"/>the shocks, disappear under the water.<lb break="yes"/>Others, panting, with mane erect and<lb break="yes"/>haggard eyes, expressing anguish, raise<lb break="yes" />themselves, and endeavour to flee from<lb break="yes"/>the storm by which they are overtaken.<lb break="yes"/>They are driven back by the Indians<lb break="yes"/>into the middle of the water; but a<lb break="yes"/>small number succeed in eluding the<lb break="yes"/>active vigilance of the fishermen. These<lb break="yes"/>regain the shore, stumbling at every<lb break="yes" />step, and stretch themselves on the sand,<lb break="yes"/>exhausted with fatigue, and their limbs<lb break="yes"/>benumbed by the electric shocks of the<lb break="yes"/>gymnoti.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In less than five minutes, two horses<lb break="yes"/>were drowned. The eel, being five feet<lb break="yes"/>long, and pressing itself against the belly<lb break="yes"/>of the horses, <choice>
                        <sic>make</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">makes</corr>
                </choice> a discharge along<lb break="yes"/>the whole extent of its electric organ.<lb break="yes"/>It attacks at once the heart, the intes-<lb break="no"/>tines, and the <hi rendition="#i">plexus c&#x00E6;liacus</hi> of the<lb break="yes"/>abdominal nerves. It is natural that<lb break="yes"/>the effect felt by the horses should be<lb break="yes"/>more powerful than that produced upon<lb break="yes"/>man by the touch of the same fish at<lb break="yes" />only one of his extremities. The horses<lb break="yes"/>are probably not killed, but only stunned.<lb break="yes"/>They are drowned from the impossibility<lb break="yes"/>of rising amid the prolonged struggle<lb break="yes"/>between the other horses and the eels.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="252" facs="#f0002"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>&#x201C;We had little doubt that the fishing<lb break="yes"/>would terminate by killing successively<lb break="yes"/>all the animals engaged; but by degrees<lb break="yes"/>the impetuosity of this unequal combat<lb break="yes" />diminished, and the wearied gymnoti<lb break="yes"/>dispersed. They require a long rest,<lb break="yes"/>and abundant nourishment, to repair<lb break="yes" />what they have lost of galvanic force.<lb break="yes"/>The mules and horses appear less fright-<lb break="no"/>ened; their manes are no longer bristled,<lb break="yes"/>and their eyes express less dread. The<lb break="yes"/>gymnoti approach timidly the edge of<lb break="yes"/>the marsh, where they are taken by means<lb break="yes"/>of small harpoons fastened to long cords.<lb break="yes"/>When the cords are very dry, the In-<lb break="no"/>dians feel no shock in raising the fish<lb break="yes"/>into the air. In a few minutes we had<lb break="yes"/>five large eels, the greater part of which<lb break="yes"/>were but slightly wounded. Some were<lb break="yes"/>taken by the same means towards the<lb break="yes"/>evening.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. de Humboldt says it would be<lb break="yes"/>temerity to expose oneself to the first<lb break="yes"/>shocks of a large and strongly irritated<lb break="yes"/>gymnotus; that a stroke from such a<lb break="yes"/>face is productive of much pain and<lb break="yes"/>numbness; and that he received so<lb break="yes"/>dreadful a shock by imprudently placing<lb break="yes"/>his feet on one just taken out of the<lb break="yes"/>water, that he was affected the rest of the<lb break="yes"/>day with a violent pain in the knees, and<lb break="yes"/>in almost every joint. He adds that the<lb break="yes" />electric action of the fish depends en-<lb break="no"/>tirely on its will, and that it has the<lb break="yes"/>power of directing the action of its<lb break="yes"/>organs to any particular part of the ex-<lb break="no"/>ternal object that may affect it, or<lb break="yes"/>towards the point where it finds itself<lb break="yes"/>the most strongly irritated.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The presence of the gymnoti,&#x201D; says<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt, &#x201C;is considered as the prin-<lb break="no"/>cipal cause of the want of fish in the<lb break="yes" />ponds and pools of the Llanos. The<lb break="yes"/>gymnoti kill many more than they de-<lb break="no"/>vour; and the Indians told us, that<lb break="yes"/>when they take young alligators and<lb break="yes"/>gymnoti at the same time in very strong<lb break="yes"/>nets, the latter never display the slight-<lb break="no"/>est trace of a wound, because they<lb break="yes"/>disable the young alligators before they<lb break="yes"/>are attacked by them. All the inha-<lb break="no"/>bitants of the waters dread the society of<lb break="yes"/>the gymnoti. Lizards, tortoises, and<lb break="yes"/>frogs, seek the pools where they are<lb break="yes"/>secure from their action. It became ne-<lb break="no"/>cessary to change the direction of a road<lb break="yes"/>near Uritucu, because these electrical<lb break="yes"/>eels were so numerous in one river, that<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>they every year killed a great number of<lb break="yes"/>mules of burden as they forded the<lb break="yes"/>water.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 