<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="28" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>BARON HUMBOLDT&#x2019;S OBSERVATIONS ON THE GYMNOTUS, OR<lb break="yes"/>ELECTRICAL EEL.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> galvanic electricity of the gymnotus causes a sensation<lb break="yes"/>which can hardly be said to be specifically distinct from that<lb break="yes"/>which is occasioned by the conductor of an electrical machine,<lb break="yes"/>a Leyden jar, or even the voltaic pile. The same observation<lb break="yes"/>has been made respecting the torpedo, or electric ray. In<lb break="yes"/>the gymnotus, however, the difference that does exist is the<lb break="yes"/>more striking in proportion as the shocks are greater. No<lb break="yes"/>man exposes himself rashly to the first discharges of a strong<lb break="yes"/>and highly irritated gymnotus. If, by accident, a shock be<lb break="yes"/>received before the fish is wounded or tired out by the pur-<lb break="no"/>suit, this shock is so painful, that it is impossible even to<lb break="yes"/>find an expression to describe the nature of the sensation. I<lb break="yes"/>do not remember to have ever experienced, from the discharge<lb break="yes"/>of a large-sized Leyden jar, a shock so dreadful as one which<lb break="yes"/>I received on placing my feet on a gymnotus which had just<lb break="yes"/>been drawn out of the water. I felt during the rest of the<lb break="yes"/>day an acute pain in the knees, and in almost every joint of<lb break="yes"/>the body. A blow upon the stomach, a stone falling on the<lb break="yes"/>head, a violent electric explosion, produce instantly the same<lb break="yes"/>effect. We distinguish nothing when the whole nervous sy-<lb break="no"/>stem is affected at once. To experience the difference believed<lb break="yes"/>to exist between the sensations produced by the voltaic pile<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="29" facs="#f0002"/>and electrical fishes, the latter must be touched when they<lb break="yes"/>are reduced to a state of extreme weakness. In that case we<lb break="yes"/>observe, that the electrical eels and torpedos cause twitchings<lb break="yes"/>of the muscles (<hi rendition="#i">subsultus tendinum</hi>), which are propagated<lb break="yes"/>along the arm, from the part resting on the electric organ up<lb break="yes"/>to the elbow. This trembling, which is not visible externally,<lb break="yes"/>slightly resembles the very slight commotions produced by<lb break="yes"/>our artificial electrical apparatuses. M. Bayon, some time<lb break="yes"/>ago, was struck with this difference; and the common people,<lb break="yes"/>to characterize the nature of this extraordinary sensation,<lb break="yes"/>still confound, so to say, the cause with the effect, and call<lb break="yes"/>the gymnotus, <hi rendition="#i" >Tremblador</hi> in the Spanish colonies, and <hi rendition="#i">An-<lb break="no"/>guille tremblante</hi> in French Guiana. In fact, on touching<lb break="yes"/>these electrical fishes, we seem to feel at every shock a vibra-<lb break="no"/>tion, an internal trembling, which lasts for two or three se-<lb break="no"/>conds, and which is followed by a painful numbness.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If the sensation which is experienced on the contact of the<lb break="yes" />electric eel be different from that which is produced by the<lb break="yes" />voltaic pile or Leyden jar, it is, however, very analogous to<lb break="yes" />the pain caused by applying zinc and silver to wounds on the<lb break="yes" />back and on the hand. These wounds, which I have myself<lb break="yes" />made&#x2014;one by means of the blistering fly, and the other by<lb break="yes"/>a slight incision&#x2014;have furnished abundant and convincing<lb break="yes"/>proof of the relations which exist between the effect of elec-<lb break="no"/>trical fishes, and that of the galvanic current established by<lb break="yes"/>the application of different metals upon the human body.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After having handled gymnoti for four hours consecutively,<lb break="yes"/>we felt, even till the next morning, a pain in the joints of the<lb break="yes" />extremities, a debility in the muscles, and a general uneasi-<lb break="no" />ness, which was, without doubt, the consequence of a long<lb break="yes"/>and violent irritation of the whole nervous system. M. Van<lb break="yes"/>der Lott, surgeon at Essequibo, has published in Holland a<lb break="yes"/>Memoir on the Medical Properties of the Electrical Eel.<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Bancroft assures us, that at Demerara they are employ-<lb break="no"/>ed for the cure of paralytic subjects; but in the Spanish<lb break="yes"/>colonies they know nothing of this property in the gymnotus.<lb break="yes"/>The ancients, however, made use of the galvanic electricity<lb break="yes"/>of the torpedo, according to Scribonius Largus, in cases of<lb break="yes"/>head-ache, megrims, and gout. And such is all we know<lb break="yes"/>respecting medical electricity among the Greeks and the<lb break="yes"/>savages of America.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Persons most accustomed to electric shocks support, with<lb break="yes" />repugnance, those given by a torpedo one foot four inches<lb break="yes"/>in length; but the power of a gymnotus is ten times greater,<lb break="yes"/>as we have seen by its effect upon horses. It often happens,<lb break="yes"/>in taking young crocodiles of two or three feet in length, and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="30" facs="#f0003"/>little fishes in the same net with gymnoti, that the fishes are<lb break="yes"/>found dead, and the crocodile expiring. The Indians, in such<lb break="yes"/>cases, say that the young crocodile had not time to tear the<lb break="yes"/>net, because the gymnotus had paralysed and put him <hi rendition="#i">hors du<lb break="yes"/>combat.</hi> These terrible fishes, although carnivorous and of<lb break="yes"/>an aspect hideous as the serpent, are nevertheless in some<lb break="yes"/>measure docile, and naturally of a peaceable disposition.<lb break="yes"/>Much less active than our eels, they readily accustom them-<lb break="no"/>selves to their new prison; they eat everything that is offer-<lb break="no"/>ed them, but without manifesting a great voracity. They do<lb break="yes"/>not discharge their violent shocks unless irritated; and then<lb break="yes"/>especially if tickled along the under part of the body, at the<lb break="yes"/>transparent part of the electric organs, at the pectoral fin,<lb break="yes"/>the lips, the eyes, and especially if the skin be touched near<lb break="yes"/>the gill-cover. All these parts seem to be the most sensible,<lb break="yes"/>for here the skin is thinnest and least loaded with fat.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Fishes and reptiles which have never before felt the shocks<lb break="yes"/>of a gymnotus, do not seem to be warned of their danger by<lb break="yes"/>any particular instinct. Although its form and size are rather<lb break="yes" />imposing, a little tortoise which we put into the same tub<lb break="yes" />approached it with confidence; it wanted to hide itself under<lb break="yes" />the eel&#x2019;s belly; but scarcely had it touched it with the end of<lb break="yes" />one of its feet, when it received a shock, too feeble, indeed,<lb break="yes" />to kill it, but strong enough to make it retire as far away as<lb break="yes" />possible. From that moment the tortoise would no longer<lb break="yes"/>remain in the vicinity of the torpedo. And so, in all the<lb break="yes"/>pools or streamlets which it inhabits, one finds very few fishes<lb break="yes"/>of any other species. The gymnotus often kills without de-<lb break="no"/>vouring its victim. It instinctively regards as an enemy<lb break="yes"/>everything that approaches it. Like a cloud surcharged<lb break="yes"/>with the electric fluid, he comes upon the fish he means to<lb break="yes"/>destroy; when at a short distance from it, he rests for a few<lb break="yes"/>seconds, necessary perhaps to prepare the storm that is to<lb break="yes"/>burst, and then hurls his thunder against his devoted enemy.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i" >From the Voyage of Humbolt and Bonpland.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>[The remainder of these observations, with the mode of<lb break="yes"/>taking the gymnotus by the natives, will be given in a future<lb break="yes"/>Number].</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 