<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Humboldt’s Travels</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:54</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.62</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-03-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-03-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-21-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-22-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-23-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-24-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-25-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-26-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-27-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-28-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-29-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-30-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-31-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-32-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-33-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, Relation historique du Voyage aux régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 2, S. 7–9; 175–176; 189; 214.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Humboldt’s Travels</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1819</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The British Press&lt;/i&gt; 5230 (11. September 1819), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">HUMBOLDT&#x2019;S TRAVELS.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following interesting description of the last<lb break="yes"/>dreadful catastrophe which befel the city of Ca-<lb break="no"/>raccas, is taken from <hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels,</hi> just<lb break="yes" />published:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;A great drought prevailed at this period in the<lb break="yes"/>province of Venezuela. Not a single drop of<lb break="yes"/>rain had fallen at Caraccas, or in the country ninety<lb break="yes"/>leagues round, during the five months which pre-<lb break="no"/>ceded the destruction of the capital. The 26th of<lb break="yes"/>March was a remarkably hot day. The air was<lb break="yes" />calm and the sky unclouded. It was Holy Thurs-<lb break="no"/>day, and a great part of the population was assem-<lb break="no"/>bled in the churches. Nothing seemed to presage<lb break="yes"/>the calamities of the day. At seven minutes after<lb break="yes"/>four in the afternoon the first shock was felt; it<lb break="yes"/>was sufficiently powerful to make the bells of the<lb break="yes"/>churches toll; it lasted five or six seconds, during<lb break="yes"/>which time, the ground was in a continual undu-<lb break="no" />lating movement, and seemed to heave up like a<lb break="yes"/>boiling liquid. The danger was thought to be<lb break="yes"/>past, when a tremendous subterraneous noise was<lb break="yes"/>heard, resembling the rolling of thunder, but<lb break="yes"/>louder, and of longer continuance, than that heard<lb break="yes"/>within the tropics in time of storms. This noise<lb break="yes"/>preceded a perpendicular motion of three or four<lb break="yes" />seconds, followed by an undulatory movement<lb break="yes"/>somewhat longer. The shocks were in opposite<lb break="yes"/>directions, from north to south and from east to<lb break="yes"/>west. Nothing could resist the movement from<lb break="yes"/>beneath upward, and undulations crossing each<lb break="yes" />other. The town of Caraccas was entirely over-<lb break="no"/>thrown. Thousands of the inhabitants (between<lb break="yes"/>nine and ten thousand) were buried under the ruins<lb break="yes"/>of the houses and churches. The procession had<lb break="yes"/>not yet set out; but the crowd was so great in the<lb break="yes"/>churches, that nearly three or four thousand persons<lb break="yes"/>were crushed by the fall of their vaulted roofs.<lb break="yes" />The explosion was stronger toward the north, in<lb break="yes"/>that part of the town situate nearest the moun-<lb break="no"/>tain of Avila, and the Silla. The churches of La<lb break="yes"/>Trinidad and Alta Gracia, which were more than<lb break="yes"/>150 feet high, and the naves of which were sup-<lb break="no"/>ported by pillars of twelve or fifteen feet diameter,<lb break="yes"/>left a mass of ruins scarcely exceeding five or six<lb break="yes"/>feet in elevation. The sinking of the ruins has<lb break="yes" />been so considerable, that there now scarcely re-<lb break="no"/>main any vestiges of pillars or columns. The bar-<lb break="no"/>racks called El Quartel del San Carlos, situate<lb break="yes"/>farther north of the church of the Trinity, on the<lb break="yes"/>road from the Custom-house de la Pastora, almost<lb break="yes"/>entirely disappeared. A regiment of troops of the<lb break="yes"/>line, that was assembled under arms, ready to join<lb break="yes"/>the procession, was, with the exception of a few<lb break="yes" />men, buried under the ruins of this great edifice.<lb break="yes"/>Nine-tenths of the fine town of Caraccas were en-<lb break="no"/>tirely destroyed. The walls of the houses that<lb break="yes"/>were not thrown down, as those of the street San<lb break="yes"/>Juan, near the Capuchin Hospital, were cracked in<lb break="yes"/>such a manner, that it was impossible to run the<lb break="yes" />risk of inhabiting them. The effects of the earth-<lb break="no"/>quake were somewhat less violent in the western<lb break="yes"/>and southern parts of the city, between the princi-<lb break="no"/>pal square and the ravin of Caraguata. There the<lb break="yes"/>cathedral, supported by enormous buttresses, re-<lb break="no"/>mains standing.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Estimating at nine or ten thousand the num-<lb break="no"/>ber of the dead in the city of Caraccas, we do not<lb break="yes"/>include those unhappy persons, who, dangerously<lb break="yes"/>wounded, perished several months after, for want<lb break="yes"/>of food and proper care. The night of Holy<lb break="yes"/>Thursday presented the most distressing scene of<lb break="yes" />desolation and sorrow. That thick cloud of dust,<lb break="yes"/>which, rising above the ruins, darkened the sky<lb break="yes"/>like a fog, had settled on the ground. No shock<lb break="yes"/>was felt, and never was a night more calm, or more<lb break="yes"/>serene. The moon, nearly full, illumined the<lb break="yes"/>rounded domes of the Silla, and the aspect of the<lb break="yes"/>sky formed a perfect contrast to that of the earth,<lb break="yes"/>covered with the dead, and heaped with ruins.<lb break="yes" />Mothers were seen bearing in their arms their chil-<lb break="no"/>dren, whom they hoped to recal to life. Desolate<lb break="yes"/>families wandered through the city seeking a bro-<lb break="no"/>ther, a husband, a friend, of whose fate they were<lb break="yes"/>ignorant, and whom they believed to be lost in the<lb break="yes"/>crowd. The people pressed along the streets, which<lb break="yes"/>could no more be recognised but by long lines of<lb break="yes" />ruins.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;All the calamities experienced in the great ca-<lb break="no"/>tastrophes of Lisbon, Messina, Lima, and Rio-<lb break="no"/>bamba were renewed on the fatal day of the 26th<lb break="yes"/>of March, 1812; the wounded, buried under the<lb break="yes"/>ruins, implored by their cries the help of the<lb break="yes" />passers by, and nearly two thousand were dug out.<lb break="yes"/>Never was pity displayed in a more affecting man-<lb break="no"/>ner; never had it been seen more ingeniously ac-<lb break="no"/>tive, than in the efforts employed to save the mi-<lb break="no"/>serable victims, whose groans reached the ear. Im-<lb break="no"/>plements for digging, and clearing away the ruins<lb break="yes"/>were entirely wanting; and the people were obliged<lb break="yes"/>to use their bare hands, to disinter the living. The<lb break="yes"/>wounded, as well as the sick who had escaped from<lb break="yes"/>the hospitals, were laid on the banks of the small<lb break="yes"/>river Guayra. They found no shelter but the fo-<lb break="no" />liage of trees. Beds, linen to dress the wounds,<lb break="yes"/>instruments of surgery, medicines, and objects of<lb break="yes"/>the most urgent necessity, were buried under the<lb break="yes"/>ruins. Every thing, even food, was wanting dur-<lb break="no"/>ing the first days. Water became alike scarce in<lb break="yes"/>the interior of the city. The commotion had rent<lb break="yes" />the pipes of the fountains; the falling in of the<lb break="yes"/>earth had choked up the springs that supplied<lb break="yes"/>them; and it became necessary, in order to have<lb break="yes"/>water, to go down to the river Guayra, which was<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>considerably swelled; and then vessels to convey<lb break="yes"/>the water were wanting.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;There remained a duty to be fulfilled toward<lb break="yes"/>the dead, enjoined at once by piety, and the dread<lb break="yes"/>of infection. It being impossible to inter so many<lb break="yes"/>thousand corpses, half-buried under the ruins, com-<lb break="no"/>missaries were appointed to burn the bodies: and<lb break="yes"/>for this purpose funeral piles were erected between<lb break="yes"/>the heaps of ruins. This ceremony lasted several<lb break="yes" />days. Amid so many public calamities, the people<lb break="yes"/>devoted themselves to those religious duties, which<lb break="yes"/>they thought were the most fitted to appease the<lb break="yes"/>wrath of Heaven. Some, assembling in processions,<lb break="yes"/>sang funeral hymns; others, in a state of distraction,<lb break="yes"/>confessed themselves aloud in the streets. In this<lb break="yes"/>town was now repeated what had been remarked in<lb break="yes"/>the province of Quito, after the tremendous earth-<lb break="no"/>quake of 1797; a number of marriages were con-<lb break="no" />tracted between persons, who had neglected for many<lb break="yes"/>years to sanction their union by the sacerdotal bene-<lb break="no"/>diction; children found parents, by whom they had<lb break="yes"/>never till then been acknowledged; restitutions were<lb break="yes"/>promised by persons, who had never been accused<lb break="yes"/>of fraud; and families, who had long been ene-<lb break="no"/>mies, were drawn together by the tie of common<lb break="yes"/>calamity.&#x201D;&#x2014;pp. 12&#x2014;17.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Humboldt also gives the following curious ac-<lb break="no"/>count of the manner in which the Indians catch<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">Gymnoti,</hi> or electrical eels, by driving horses<lb break="yes"/>into the pools, and driving them out of the mud in<lb break="yes"/>which they lodge themselves:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The extraordinary noise caused by the horses&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>hoofs makes the fish issue from the mud, and ex-<lb break="no"/>cites them to combat. These yellowish and livid<lb break="yes"/>eels, resembling large aquatic serpents, swim on the<lb break="yes"/>surface of the water, and crowd under the bellies<lb break="yes"/>of the horses and mules. A contest between ani-<lb break="no" />mals of so different an organization furnishes a very<lb break="yes"/>striking spectacle. The Indians, provided with<lb break="yes"/>harpoons and long slender reeds, surround the<lb break="yes"/>pool closely; and some climb upon the trees, the<lb break="yes"/>branches of which extend horizontally over the sur-<lb break="no"/>face of the water. By their wild cries, and the<lb break="yes" />length of their reeds, they prevent the horses from<lb break="yes"/>running away and reaching the bank of the pool.<lb break="yes"/>The eels, stunned by the noise, defend them-<lb break="no"/>selves by the repeated discharge of their electric<lb break="yes"/>batteries. During a long time they seem to prove<lb break="yes"/>victorious. Several horses sink beneath the violence<lb break="yes"/>of the invisible strokes, which they receive from<lb break="yes"/>all sides in organs the most essential to life; and<lb break="yes"/>stunned by the force and frequency of the shocks<lb break="yes" />disappear under the water. Others, panting, with<lb break="yes"/>mane erect and haggard eyes, expressing anguish,<lb break="yes"/>raise themselves, and endeavour to flee from the<lb break="yes"/>storm by which they are overtaken. They are<lb break="yes"/>driven back by the Indians into the middle of the<lb break="yes"/>water; but a small number succeed in eluding the<lb break="yes" />active vigilance of the fishermen. These regain<lb break="yes"/>the shore, stumbling at every step, and stretch<lb break="yes"/>themselves on the sand, exhausted with fatigue,<lb break="yes"/>and their limbs benumbed by the electric shocks<lb break="yes"/>of the gymnoti.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In less than five minutes two horses were<lb break="yes"/>drowned. The eel, being five feet long, and press-<lb break="no"/>ing itself against the belly of the horses, makes<lb break="yes"/>a discharge along the whole extent of its electric<lb break="yes"/>organ. It attacks at once the heart, the intestines,<lb break="yes"/>and the <hi rendition="#i">plexus c&#x0153;liacus</hi> of the abdominal nerves.<lb break="yes"/>It is natural that the effect felt by the horses should<lb break="yes"/>be more powerful than that produced upon man by<lb break="yes"/>the touch of the same fish at only one of his ex-<lb break="no"/>tremities. The horses are probably not killed but<lb break="yes" />only stunned. They are drowned from the impos-<lb break="no"/>sibility of rising amid the prolonged struggle be-<lb break="no"/>tween the other horses and the eels.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;We had little doubt that the fishing would<lb break="yes"/>terminate by killing successively all the animals<lb break="yes"/>engaged; but by degrees the impetuosity of this<lb break="yes"/>unequal combat diminished, and the wearied<lb break="yes"/>gymnoti dispersed. They require a long rest, and<lb break="yes"/>abundant nourishment, to repair what they have<lb break="yes" />lost of galvanic force. The mules and horses ap-<lb break="no"/>pear less frightened; their manes are no longer<lb break="yes"/>bristled, and their eyes express less dread. The<lb break="yes"/>gymnoti approach timidly the edge of the marsh,<lb break="yes"/>where they are taken by means of small harpoons<lb break="yes"/>fastened to long cords. When the cords are very<lb break="yes" />dry the Indians feel no shock in raising the fish into<lb break="yes"/>the air. In a few minutes we had five large eels,<lb break="yes"/>the greater part of which were but slightly wounded.<lb break="yes"/>Some were taken by the same means toward the<lb break="yes"/>evening.&#x201D;&#x2014;pp. 348&#x2014;350.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. de Humboldt says it would be temerity to<lb break="yes"/>expose oneself to the first shocks of a large and<lb break="yes"/>strongly irritated gymnotus; that a stroke from<lb break="yes"/>such a fish is productive of more pain and numbness<lb break="yes"/>than from the discharge of a large Leyden jar; and<lb break="yes"/>that he received so dreadful a shock by imprudently<lb break="yes"/>placing his feet on one just taken out of the water,<lb break="yes"/>that he was affected the rest of the day with a vio-<lb break="no"/>lent pain in the knees, and in almost every joint.<lb break="yes"/>He adds, that the electric action of the fish depends<lb break="yes"/>entirely on its will, and that it has the power of<lb break="yes"/>directing the action of its organs to any particular<lb break="yes"/>part of the external object that may affect it, or<lb break="yes"/>towards the point where it finds itself the most<lb break="yes" />strongly irritated.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We have now a dissertation of about twenty<lb break="yes"/>pages on the nature and quality of the electrical<lb break="yes"/>action of fishes, of which we can only find room<lb break="yes"/>for the following curious paragraph:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The presence of the gymnoti is considered as<lb break="yes"/>the principal cause of the want of fish in the ponds<lb break="yes"/>and pools of the Llanos. The gymnoti kill many<lb break="yes"/>more than they devour; and the Indians told us,<lb break="yes"/>that when they take young alligators and gymnoti<lb break="yes"/>at the same time in very strong nets, the latter<lb break="yes" />never display the slightest trace of a wound, be-<lb break="no"/>cause they disable the young alligators before they<lb break="yes"/>are attacked by them. All the inhabitants of the<lb break="yes"/>waters dread the society of the gymnoti. Lizards,<lb break="yes"/>tortoises, and frogs seek the pools, where they are<lb break="yes"/>secure from their action. It became necessary to<lb break="yes"/>change the direction of a road near Uritucu, be-<lb break="no" />cause these electrical eels were so numerous in one<lb break="yes"/>river, that they every year killed a great number of<lb break="yes"/>mules of burden as they forded the water.&#x201D;&#x2014;p. 374.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the following anecdote he describes the man-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="2" facs="#f0002"/><cb/>ner in which the natives resist the attacks of the<lb break="yes"/>crocodile:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;They related to us the history of a young girl<lb break="yes"/>of Uritucu, who by singular intrepidity and pre-<lb break="no"/>sence of mind saved herself from the jaws of a cro-<lb break="no"/>codile. When she felt herself seized, she sought<lb break="yes"/>the eyes of the animal, and plunged her fingers<lb break="yes"/>into them with such violence, that the pain forced<lb break="yes"/>the crocodile to let her loose, after having bitten<lb break="yes"/>off the lower part of her left arm. The girl, not-<lb break="no"/>withstanding the enormous quantity of blood she<lb break="yes" />lost, happily reached the shore, swimming with the<lb break="yes"/>hand she had still left. In those desert countries,<lb break="yes"/>where man is ever wrestling with nature, discourse<lb break="yes"/>daily turns on the means that may be em-<lb break="no"/>ployed to escape from a tiger, a boa or <hi rendition="#i">traga<lb break="yes"/>venado,</hi> or a crocodile; every one prepares himself<lb break="yes"/>in some sort for the dangers that await him.<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;I knew,&#x201D; said the young girl of Uritucu coolly,<lb break="yes" />&#x201C;that the <hi rendition="#i">cayman</hi> lets go his hold, if you push<lb break="yes"/>your fingers into his eyes.&#x201D; Long after my return<lb break="yes"/>to Europe, I learned, that in the interior of Africa<lb break="yes"/>the negroes know and practice the same means.<lb break="yes" />Who does not recollect with a lively interest <hi rendition="#i">Isaaco,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>the guide of the unfortunate Mungo Park, seized<lb break="yes" />twice, near Boulinkombou, by a crocodile, and<lb break="yes"/>twice escaping from the jaws of the monster, hav-<lb break="no"/>ing succeeded in placing his fingers under water in<lb break="yes"/>both his eyes? The African Isaaco, and the<lb break="yes"/>young American, owed their safety to the same<lb break="yes"/>presence of mind, and the same combination of<lb break="yes" />ideas.&#x201D;&#x2014;pp. 423, 424.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI> 