<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Earthquake at Caraccas</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:54</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.62</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-17-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-17-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-21-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-22-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-23-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-24-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-25-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-26-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-27-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-28-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-29-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-30-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-31-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-32-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-33-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 2, S. 6–28. [Der Länge nach werden es wohl eher Ausschnitte aus dem genannten Seitenbereich sein. B. Z.]</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Earthquake at Caraccas</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1822</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: William Jillard Hort, &lt;i&gt;The English Reading Book, in Prose: Adapted to Domestic and to School Education&lt;/i&gt;, London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, and Brown 1822, S. 181–185.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="181" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">earthquake at caraccas.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> shock felt at Caraccas in the month of<lb break="yes"/>December, 1811, was the only one that preceded<lb break="yes" />the horrible catastrophe which desolated that<lb break="yes"/>unfortunate city in March, 1812. The inhabit-<lb break="no"/>ants of Terra Firma were ignorant of the agi-<lb break="no"/>tations of the volcano in the island of St. Vin-<lb break="no"/>cent, on one side, and of those felt in the basin<lb break="yes" />of the Mississippi on the other, on the seventh<lb break="yes"/>and eighth days of February, 1812, in which<lb break="yes"/>places the earth was during that time in perpe-<lb break="no"/>tual oscillation day and night. A great drought<lb break="yes"/>at this period prevailed throughout the province<lb break="yes"/>of Venezuela; no rain had fallen at Caraccas, or<lb break="yes" />in the country ninety leagues round, during the<lb break="yes"/>five months which preceded the destruction of<lb break="yes"/>that city. The twenty-sixth of March was re-<lb break="no"/>markable for excessive heat; the air was calm,<lb break="yes"/>the sky unclouded; it was Holy Thursday, and<lb break="yes"/>a great part of the population was assembled in<lb break="yes"/>the churches. No presage of the impending<lb break="yes"/>calamity was observable. Soon after four in the<lb break="yes"/>afternoon the first shock was felt; it was suffici-<lb break="no"/>ently strong to make the bells of the churches<lb break="yes"/>toll; and during five or six seconds the ground<lb break="yes" />was in continual undulating movement, and<lb break="yes"/>seemed to heave like a boiling liquid.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="182" facs="#f0002"/>
                <p>The danger was supposed to be passed, when<lb break="yes"/>a horrible subterraneous sound struck terror into<lb break="yes"/>every heart. It resembled the rolling of thunder,<lb break="yes"/>but louder, and of longer continuance, than that<lb break="yes"/>which usually accompanies tropical storms. This<lb break="yes"/>noise was followed by a perpendicular movement,<lb break="yes" />which was instantly succeeded by a somewhat<lb break="yes"/>longer waving motion. The shocks were repeated<lb break="yes"/>in opposite directions from north to south, and<lb break="yes"/>from east to west. These crossing impulses were<lb break="yes"/>irresistible; Caraccas was entirely overthrown;<lb break="yes"/>thousands of its unfortunate inhabitants were<lb break="yes" />buried under the ruins of their houses and<lb break="yes"/>churches. The solemn procession had not begun<lb break="yes"/>its march, but so great was the crowd in the<lb break="yes"/>churches, that multitudes were crushed by the<lb break="yes"/>fall of their vaulted roofs. The explosion to-<lb break="no" />wards the north was stronger in that part of the<lb break="yes"/>town nearest to the mountain of Avila, and the<lb break="yes"/>Silla. The churches of La Trinidad and Alta<lb break="yes"/>Gracia, which were more than 150 feet high,<lb break="yes"/>and whose naves were supported by columns of<lb break="yes" />twelve or fifteen feet diameter, yet left a mass of<lb break="yes"/>ruins scarcely exceeding five or six feet in ele-<lb break="no"/>vation. So wonderfully, indeed, have they sunk,<lb break="yes"/>that there now hardly remain any vestiges of<lb break="yes"/>pillars. The barracks, situated farther north,<lb break="yes"/>almost entirely disappeared; a regiment of troops,<lb break="yes"/>assembled under arms, ready to join the proces-<lb break="no" />sion, with the exception of a very few, were<lb break="yes"/>crushed beneath the ruins of that spacious build-<lb break="no"/>ing. The cathedral, supported by enormous<lb break="yes"/>buttresses, withstood the fury of the shock. The<lb break="yes"/>night of that fatal day presented the most dis-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="183" facs="#f0003"/>tressing scenes of desolation and sorrow; the<lb break="yes"/>thick, black cloud of dust, which rising from the<lb break="yes"/>crush of so many edifices thrown down, darkened<lb break="yes" />the face of heaven like an impenetrable fog, had<lb break="yes"/>settled on the ground; all nature seemed calm<lb break="yes"/>and tranquil; the moon nearly full, illuminated<lb break="yes"/>the rounded dome, like summits of the Silla; the<lb break="yes"/>aspect of the sky formed a perfect contrast to<lb break="yes"/>that of the earth, loaded with ruins, and heaped<lb break="yes" />with dead bodies; mothers were seen bearing in<lb break="yes"/>their arms their children, whom they hoped to<lb break="yes"/>recall to life; desolate families wandered through<lb break="yes"/>the city, seeking a brother, a husband, a father,<lb break="yes"/>of whose fate they were ignorant, and whom they<lb break="yes"/>believed to be lost in the crowd. The people<lb break="yes"/>hurried tumultuously along the streets, which<lb break="yes" />could be recognized only by long lines of ruins.<lb break="yes"/>Many lay wounded under heaps of rubbish, im-<lb break="no"/>ploring with cries the aid of those who were<lb break="yes"/>passing by; and nearly two thousand mutilated<lb break="yes"/>wretches were extricated from that dreadful situ-<lb break="no" />ation. Never was pity displayed in a more affect-<lb break="no"/>ing manner; never was it seen more ingeniously<lb break="yes"/>active than in the efforts made to save the miser-<lb break="no"/>able victims, whose groans reached the ear, and<lb break="yes"/>pierced to the heart. Implements for digging<lb break="yes"/>and clearing away the wreck of private and pub-<lb break="no" />lic buildings were unfortunately wanting. The<lb break="yes"/>compassionate used their bare hands to disinter<lb break="yes"/>their yet living fellow-citizens. The maimed as<lb break="yes"/>well as the sick, who had escaped from the shat-<lb break="no"/>tered hospital, were laid on the banks of the<lb break="yes"/>small river Guayra; the foliage of the trees was<lb break="yes" />their only shelter; beds, linen for their wounds,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="184" facs="#f0004"/>surgical instruments, medicines, all the most ne-<lb break="no"/>cessary articles for the mitigation of such misery,<lb break="yes"/>were involved in the common mass of devast-<lb break="no" />ation. During the immediately succeeding days,<lb break="yes"/>even food was wanting; in the interior of the<lb break="yes"/>desolated city water became alike scarce; the<lb break="yes"/>complete subversion had rent the pipes of the<lb break="yes"/>fountains; the falling in of the earth had choked<lb break="yes"/>up the springs that supplied them; it was neces-<lb break="no" />sary to seek water from the river Guayra, which<lb break="yes"/>was considerably swelled, and vessels could not<lb break="yes"/>be found for its conveyance.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There remained a duty towards the dead to be<lb break="yes"/>fulfilled, enjoined at once by piety and the dread<lb break="yes"/>of infection. It being impossible to inter so many<lb break="yes"/>thousand corpses, commissaries were appointed<lb break="yes"/>to burn the bodies, for which purpose funeral<lb break="yes"/>piles were erected between the heaps of ruins.<lb break="yes" />This mournful operation lasted several days.<lb break="yes"/>Amid so many public griefs, the people still<lb break="yes"/>attended to religious duties; some walking in<lb break="yes"/>procession, chaunted funeral hymns; some were<lb break="yes"/>offering up their humble supplications; while<lb break="yes" />others, in a state of distraction, were confessing<lb break="yes"/>themselves aloud.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Shocks of earthquake, so violent as to subvert<lb break="yes"/>in the space of one minute, such a city as Carac-<lb break="no"/>cas, could not be confined to a small portion of<lb break="yes"/>the continent; their destructive effects extended<lb break="yes"/>as far as the provinces of Venezuela, Varinas,<lb break="yes"/>and Maracaybo, along the coast; and still farther<lb break="yes"/>among the inland mountains. La Guayra, May-<lb break="no" />quetia, and other places so situated, were entirely<lb break="yes"/>ruined. Fifteen or eighteen hours after the great<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="185" facs="#f0005"/>catastrophe, the earth remained tranquil; the<lb break="yes"/>night was fine and calm, and the commotions did<lb break="yes" />not recommence till the day after. They were<lb break="yes"/>then attended with a very loud and long conti-<lb break="no"/>nued subterranean noise, called bramids. The<lb break="yes"/>inhabitants of Caraccas wandered into the coun-<lb break="no"/>try; but the villages and farms having suffered<lb break="yes" />as much as the city, they could find no shelter<lb break="yes"/>till they were beyond the mountains of Los<lb break="yes"/>Teques, in the vallies of Aragua, and in the<lb break="yes"/>Llanos, or Savannas. No less than fifteen oscil-<lb break="no"/>lations were often felt in one day. On the fifth<lb break="yes" />of April took place another earthquake, almost as<lb break="yes"/>formidable as that which overthrew the capital.<lb break="yes"/>For several hours the ground was in a state of<lb break="yes"/>perpetual undulation. Large masses of earth<lb break="yes"/>fell in the mountains, and enormous rocks were<lb break="yes"/>detached from the Silla of Caraccas. After the<lb break="yes" />recital of such calamities, it is soothing to fix the<lb break="yes"/>view upon consolatory remembrances.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When this dreadful desolation of Caraccas<lb break="yes"/>was known in the United States, the congress<lb break="yes"/>assembled at Washington, unanimously decreed<lb break="yes"/>that five ships laden with flour should be sent to<lb break="yes"/>the coast of Venezuela, to be distributed among<lb break="yes"/>the poorest inhabitants.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 