<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="77" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">account of the earthquake which<lb break="yes"/>destroyed the town of caraccas<lb break="yes"/>on the twenty-sixth march,</hi> 1812.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">By M. Humboldt.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>[<hi rendition="#k">from the edinburgh philosophical magazine.</hi>]</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There are few events in the physical<lb break="yes"/>world which are calculated to excite so deep<lb break="yes"/>and permanent an interest as the earthquake<lb break="yes"/>which destroyed the town of Caraccas,<lb break="yes"/>and by which more than 20,000 persons<lb break="yes"/>perished, almost at the same instant, in the<lb break="yes"/>province of Venezuela. The general results<lb break="yes"/>of this frightful catastrophe have been long<lb break="yes" />known in this country; but its particular<lb break="yes"/>details, so afflicting to human feelings, and<lb break="yes"/>the physical phenomena by which it was<lb break="yes"/>accompanied, so important in geological<lb break="yes"/>speculations, have been only recently de-<lb break="no" />scribed by M. Humboldt.<note place="foot" n="*">Personal Narrative, vol. iv. p. 12.</note> This distin-<lb break="no"/>guished traveller, who had visited the city<lb break="yes"/>of Caraccas previous to its destruction,<lb break="yes" />has been at great pains to collect and com-<lb break="no"/>pare the descriptions of individuals who<lb break="yes"/>had witnessed the effects of the earthquake,<lb break="yes"/>and has thus been enabled to draw a faithful<lb break="yes"/>picture of this terrible convulsion, marked<lb break="yes" />with that glowing eloquence which charac-<lb break="no"/>terises all his writings. We regret that our<lb break="yes"/>limits will not permit us to present our<lb break="yes"/>readers with all his reasonings respecting<lb break="yes"/>the influence of a system of volcanoes over<lb break="yes"/>a vast extent of circumjacent country; but<lb break="yes"/>we may afterwards have another opportunity<lb break="yes"/>of resuming this branch of the subject.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The 26th of March was a remarkably<lb break="yes"/>hot day. The air was calm, and the sky<lb break="yes"/>unclouded. It was Holy Thursday, and a<lb break="yes"/>great part of the population was assembled<lb break="yes"/>in the churches. Nothing seemed to pre-<lb break="no"/>sage the calamities of the day. At seven<lb break="yes"/>minutes after four in the afternoon the first<lb break="yes"/>shock was felt; it was sufficiently powerful<lb break="yes"/>to make the bells of the churches toll; it<lb break="yes"/>lasted five or six seconds, during which<lb break="yes"/>time the ground was in a continual undu-<lb break="no"/>lating movement, and seemed to heave up<lb break="yes" />like a boiling liquid. The danger was<lb break="yes"/>thought to be past, when a tremendous<lb break="yes"/>subterraneous noise was heard, resembling<lb break="yes"/>the rolling of thunder, but louder, and of<lb break="yes" />longer continuance, than that heard within<lb break="yes"/>the tropics. This noise preceded a perpen-<lb break="no"/>dicular motion of three or four seconds,<lb break="yes"/>followed by an undulatory movement some-<lb break="no"/>what longer. The shocks were in opposite<lb break="yes" />directions, from north to south, and from<lb break="yes"/>east to west. Nothing could resist the<lb break="yes"/>movement from beneath upward, and undu-<lb break="no"/>lations crossing each other. The town of<lb break="yes" />Caraccas was entirely overthrown. Be-<lb break="no"/>tween nine and ten thousand of the inha-<lb break="no"/>bitants were buried under the ruins of the<lb break="yes"/>houses and churches. The procession had<lb break="yes" />not yet set out; but the crowd was so great<lb break="yes"/>in the churches, that nearly three or four<lb break="yes"/>thousand persons were crushed by the fall<lb break="yes"/>of their vaulted roofs. The explosion was<lb break="yes"/>stronger towards the north, in that part of<lb break="yes"/>the town situated nearest the mountain of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>Avila, and the Silla. The churches of La<lb break="yes"/>Trinidad and Alta Gracia, which were more<lb break="yes"/>than 150 feet high, and the naves of which<lb break="yes"/>were supported by pillars of twelve or fifteen<lb break="yes"/>feet diameter, left a mass of ruins scarcely<lb break="yes" />exceeding five or six feet in elevation. The<lb break="yes"/>sinking of the ruins has been so considera-<lb break="no"/>ble, that there now scarcely remain any<lb break="yes"/>vestiges of pillars or columns. The bar-<lb break="no" />racks, called El Quartel de San Carlos,<lb break="yes"/>situate farther north of the Church of the<lb break="yes"/>Trinity, on the road from the Custom-house<lb break="yes"/>de la Pastora, almost entirely disappeared.<lb break="yes"/>A regiment of troops of the line, that was<lb break="yes" />assembled under arms, ready to join the<lb break="yes"/>procession, was, with the exception of a<lb break="yes"/>few men, buried under the ruins of this<lb break="yes"/>great edifice. Nine tenths of the fine town<lb break="yes"/>of Caraccas were entirely destroyed. The<lb break="yes"/>walls of the houses that were not thrown<lb break="yes"/>down, as those of the street San Juan, near<lb break="yes"/>the Capuchin Hospital, were cracked in<lb break="yes"/>such a manner, that it was impossible to run<lb break="yes"/>the risk of inhabiting them.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Estimating at nine or ten thousand the<lb break="yes"/>number of the dead in the city of Caraccas,<lb break="yes"/>we do not include those unhappy persons,<lb break="yes"/>who, dangerously wounded, perished several<lb break="yes" />months after, from want of food and proper<lb break="yes"/>attention. The night of Holy Thursday<lb break="yes"/>presented the most distressing scene of de-<lb break="no"/>solation and sorrow. That thick cloud of<lb break="yes" />dust, which, rising above the ruins, darkened<lb break="yes"/>the sky like a fog, had settled on the<lb break="yes"/>ground. No shock was felt, and never was<lb break="yes"/>a night more calm or more serene. The<lb break="yes" />moon, nearly full, illumined the rounded<lb break="yes"/>domes of the Silla, and the aspect of the<lb break="yes"/>sky formed a perfect contrast to that of the<lb break="yes"/>earth, covered with the dead, and heaped<lb break="yes" />with ruins. Mothers were seen bearing in<lb break="yes"/>their arms their children, whom they hoped<lb break="yes"/>to recal to life. Desolate families wandered<lb break="yes"/>through the city, seeking a brother, a hus-<lb break="no"/>band, a friend, of whose fate they were<lb break="yes"/>ignorant, and whom they believed to be lost<lb break="yes"/>in the crowd. The people pressed along<lb break="yes"/>the streets, which could no more be recog-<lb break="no"/>nised but by long lines of ruins.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;All the calamities experienced in the<lb break="yes"/>great catastrophes of Lisbon, Messina, Li-<lb break="no"/>ma, and Riobamba, were renewed on the<lb break="yes"/>fatal day of the 26th of March, 1812. The<lb break="yes" />wounded, buried under the ruins, implored<lb break="yes"/>by their cries the help of the passers by,<lb break="yes"/>and nearly 2000 were dug out. Implements<lb break="yes"/>for digging, and clearing away the ruins<lb break="yes"/>were entirely wanting; and the people were<lb break="yes" />obliged to use their bare hands to disinter<lb break="yes"/>the living. The wounded, as well as the<lb break="yes"/>sick who had escaped from the hospitals,<lb break="yes"/>were laid on the banks of the small river<lb break="yes"/>Guayra, They found no shelter but the<lb break="yes"/>foliage of <choice><sic>trees,.</sic><corr type="editorial">trees.</corr></choice> Beds, linen to dress the<lb break="yes"/>wounds, instruments of surgery, medicines,<lb break="yes"/>and objects of the most urgent necessity,<lb break="yes"/>were buried under the ruins. Every thing,<lb break="yes"/>even food, was wanting during the first<lb break="yes"/>days. Water became alike scarce in the<lb break="yes"/>interior of the city. The commotion had<lb break="yes"/>rent the pipes of the fountains; the falling<lb break="yes"/>in of the earth had choked up the springs<lb break="yes"/>that supplied them; and it became necessary<lb break="yes"/>in order to have water, to go down to the<lb break="yes"/>river Guayra, which was considerably<lb break="yes"/>swelled; and then vessels to convey the<lb break="yes"/>water were wanting.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>&#x201C;There remained a duty to be fulfilled<lb break="yes"/>towards the dead, enjoined at once by piety<lb break="yes"/>and the dread of infection. It being im-<lb break="no"/>possible to inter so many thousand corpses,<lb break="yes" />half-buried under the ruins, commissaries<lb break="yes"/>were appointed to burn the bodies: and for<lb break="yes"/>this purpose, funeral piles were erected<lb break="yes"/>between the heaps of ruins. This ceremony<lb break="yes"/>lasted several days. Amid so many public<lb break="yes" />calamities, the people devoted themselves<lb break="yes"/>to those religious duties, which they thought<lb break="yes"/>were the most fitted to appease the wrath<lb break="yes"/>of Heaven. Some, assembling in proces-<lb break="no" />sion, sung funeral hymns; others, in a state<lb break="yes"/>of distraction, confessed themselves aloud<lb break="yes"/>in the streets. In this town was now re-<lb break="no"/>peated what had been remarked in the pro-<lb break="no" />vince of Quito, after the tremendous earth-<lb break="no"/>quake of 1797; a number of marriages<lb break="yes"/>were contracted between persons, who had<lb break="yes"/>neglected for many years to sanction their<lb break="yes" />union by the sacerdotal benediction. Chil-<lb break="no"/>dren found parents, by whom they had never<lb break="yes"/>till then been acknowledged; restitutions<lb break="yes"/>were promised by persons, who had never<lb break="yes"/>been accused of fraud; and families, who<lb break="yes"/>had long been enemies, were drawn together<lb break="yes"/>by the tie of common calamity. If this<lb break="yes"/>feeling seemed to calm the passions of some,<lb break="yes"/>and open the heart to pity, it had a contrary<lb break="yes"/>effect on others, rendering them more rigid<lb break="yes"/>and inhuman.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Shocks as violent as those which, in<lb break="yes"/>the space of one minute,<note place="foot" n="†">The duration of the earthquake, that is to say the<lb break="yes"/>whole of the movements of undulation and rising<lb break="yes"/>which occasioned the horrible catastrophe of the 26th<lb break="yes"/>of March, 1812, was estimated by some at 50 seconds,<lb break="yes"/>by others at 1 minute 12 seconds.</note> overthrew the<lb break="yes"/>city of Caraccas, could not be confined to<lb break="yes"/>a small portion of the continent. Their<lb break="yes"/>fatal effects extended as far as the provinces<lb break="yes"/>of Venezuela, Varinas, and Maracaybo,<lb break="yes"/>along the coast; and still more to the in-<lb break="no"/>land mountains. La Guayra, Mayquetia,<lb break="yes"/>Antimano, Baruta, La Vega, San Felipe,<lb break="yes"/>near the copper mines of Aroa. It appears,<lb break="yes"/>that it was on a line running east north-east,<lb break="yes" />and west south-west, from La Guayra and<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas to the lofty mountains of Niquitao<lb break="yes"/>and Merida, that the violence of the earth-<lb break="no"/>quake was principally directed. It was felt<lb break="yes"/>in the kingdom of New Granada from the<lb break="yes"/>branches of the high Sierra de Santa Mar-<lb break="no"/>tha as far as Santa Fe de Bogota and Honda<lb break="yes"/>on the banks of the Magdalena, 180 leagues<lb break="yes"/>from Caraccas. It was everywhere more<lb break="yes"/>violent in the Cordilleras of gneiss and mica-<lb break="no"/>slate, or immediately at their foot, than<lb break="yes"/>in the plains: and this difference was par-<lb break="no"/>ticularly striking in the savannahs of Varinas<lb break="yes" />and Casanara. In the valleys of Aragua,<lb break="yes"/>situate between Caraccas and the town of<lb break="yes"/>San Felipe, the commotions were very<lb break="yes"/>weak: and La Victoria, Maracay, and<lb break="yes"/>Valencia, scarcely suffered at all, notwith-<lb break="no"/>standing their proximity to the capital. At<lb break="yes"/>Valecillo, a few leagues from Valencia, the<lb break="yes"/>earth, opening, threw out such an immense<lb break="yes" />quantity of water, that it formed a new<lb break="yes"/>torrent. The same phenomenon took place<lb break="yes"/>near Porto-Cabello. On the other hand,<lb break="yes"/>the lake of Maracaybo diminished sensibly.<lb break="yes"/>At Coro no commotion was felt, though<lb break="yes"/>the town is situated upon the coast, between<lb break="yes"/>other towns which suffered from the earth-<lb break="no"/>quake.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Fifteen or eighteen hours after the<lb break="yes"/>great catastrophe, the ground remained<lb break="yes"/>tranquil. The night, as we have already<lb break="yes"/>observed, was fine and calm; and the com-<lb break="no" />motions did not recommence till after the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>27th. They were then attended with a very<lb break="yes"/>loud and long continued subterranean noise.<lb break="yes"/>The inhabitants of Caraccas wandered into<lb break="yes"/>the country; but the villages and farms<lb break="yes"/>having suffered as much as the town, they<lb break="yes"/>could find no shelter till they were beyond<lb break="yes"/>the mountains of Los Teques, in the valleys<lb break="yes"/>of Aragua, and in the Llanos or savannahs.<lb break="yes"/>No less than fifteen oscillations were often<lb break="yes"/>felt in one day. On the 5th of April there<lb break="yes"/>was almost as violent an earthquake as that<lb break="yes"/>which overthrew the capital. During se-<lb break="no"/>veral hours the ground was in a state of<lb break="yes"/>perpetual undulation. Large masses of<lb break="yes"/>earth fell in the mountains; and enormous<lb break="yes"/>rocks were detached from the Silla of Ca-<lb break="no"/>raccas. It was even asserted and believed<lb break="yes"/>that the two domes of the Silla sunk fifty or<lb break="yes" />sixty toises; but this assertion is founded<lb break="yes"/>on no measurement whatever.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;While violent commotions were felt at<lb break="yes"/>the same time in the valley of the Missisippi,<lb break="yes"/>in the island of St. Vincent, and in the<lb break="yes"/>province of Venezuela, the inhabitants of<lb break="yes" />Caraccas, of Calabozo, situated in the<lb break="yes"/>midst of the steppes, and on the borders of<lb break="yes"/>the Rio Apura, in a space of 4000 square<lb break="yes"/>leagues, were terrified on the 30th of April<lb break="yes"/>1812, by a subterraneous noise, which re-<lb break="no" />sembled frequent discharges of the largest<lb break="yes"/>cannon. This noise began at two in the<lb break="yes"/>morning. It was accompanied by no shock;<lb break="yes"/>and, what is very remarkable, it was as<lb break="yes"/>loud on the coast as at eighty leagues dis-<lb break="no"/>tance inland. It was everywhere believed<lb break="yes"/>to be transmitted through the air; and was<lb break="yes"/>so far from being thought a subterraneous<lb break="yes" />noise, that at Caraccas, as well as at Cala-<lb break="no"/>bozo, preparations were made to put the<lb break="yes"/>place into a state of defence against an<lb break="yes"/>enemy, who seemed to be advancing with<lb break="yes"/>heavy artillery. Mr. Palacio, crossing the<lb break="yes"/>Rio Apura near the junction of the Rio<lb break="yes"/>Nula, was told by the inhabitants that the<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;<hi rendition="#i">firing of cannon</hi>&#x2019; had been heard as dis-<lb break="no"/>tinctly at the western extremity of the<lb break="yes" />province of Varinas, as at the port of La<lb break="yes"/>Guayra to the north of the chain of the<lb break="yes"/>coast.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The day on which the inhabitants of<lb break="yes"/>Terra Firma were alarmed by a subterra-<lb break="no"/>neous noise, was that on which happened<lb break="yes"/>the eruption of the volcano in the island of<lb break="yes" />St. Vincent. This mountain, near 500<lb break="yes"/>toises high, had not thrown out any lava<lb break="yes"/>since the year 1718. Scarcely was any<lb break="yes"/>smoke perceived to issue from its top, when,<lb break="yes"/>in the month of May 1811, frequent shocks<lb break="yes"/>announced, that the volcanic fire was either<lb break="yes"/>re-kindled, or directed anew toward that<lb break="yes"/>part of the West Indies. The first erup-<lb break="no" />tion did not take place till the 27th of April<lb break="yes"/>1812, at noon. It was only an ejection of<lb break="yes"/>ashes, but attended with a tremendous<lb break="yes"/>noise. On the 30th, the lava passed the<lb break="yes"/>brink of the crater, and, after a course of<lb break="yes" />four hours, reached the sea. The noise of<lb break="yes"/>the explosion &#x2018;resembled that of alternate<lb break="yes"/>discharges of very large cannon and of<lb break="yes"/>musketry; and, what is well worthy of<lb break="yes" />remark, it seemed much louder at sea, at a<lb break="yes"/>great distance from the island, than in sight<lb break="yes"/>of land, and near the burning volcano.&#x2019;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The distance in a straight line from the volcano<lb break="yes"/>of St. Vincent to the Rio Apura, near the mouth of<lb break="yes"/>the Nula, is 210 nautical leagues. The explosions<lb break="yes"/>were consequently heard at a distance equal to that<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="78" facs="#f0002"/><cb/>between Vesuvius and Paris. This phenomenon<lb break="yes"/>connected with a great number of facts observed in<lb break="yes"/>the Cordilleras of the Andes, shows how much more<lb break="yes"/>extensive the subterranean sphere of activity of a<lb break="yes"/>volcano is, than we are disposed to admit from the<lb break="yes"/>small changes effected at the surface of the globe.<lb break="yes"/>The detonations heard during whole days together<lb break="yes" />in the New World, 80, 100, or even 200 leagues<lb break="yes"/>distant from a crater, do not reach us by the propa-<lb break="no"/>gation of sound through the air; they are transmit-<lb break="no"/>ted to us by the ground. The little town of Honda,<lb break="yes"/>on the banks of the Magdalena, is not less than 145<lb break="yes"/>leagues from Cotopaxi; and yet in the great explo-<lb break="no"/>sions of this volcano, in 1774, a subterraneous<lb break="yes" />noise was heard at Honda, and supposed to be dis-<lb break="no"/>charges of heavy artillery. The monks of St.<lb break="yes"/>Francis spread the news, that the town of Carthagena<lb break="yes"/>was bombarded by the English; and the intelligence<lb break="yes"/>was believed. Now the volcano of Cotopaxi is a<lb break="yes"/>cone, more than 1800 toises above the basin of<lb break="yes"/>Honda, and rises from a table-land the elevation of<lb break="yes"/>which is more than 1500 toises above the valley of<lb break="yes"/>the Magdalena. In all the colossal mountains of<lb break="yes" />Quito, of the provinces of Los Pastos, and of<lb break="yes"/>Popayan, crevices and valleys without number are<lb break="yes"/>interposed. It cannot be admitted, under these<lb break="yes"/>circumstances, that the noise could be transmitted<lb break="yes"/>through the air, or by the superior surface of the<lb break="yes"/>globe, and that it came from that point, where the<lb break="yes"/>cone and crater of Cotopaxi are placed. It appears<lb break="yes"/>probable, that the higher part of the kingdom of<lb break="yes" />Quito and the neighbouring Cordilleras, far from<lb break="yes"/>being a group of distinct volcanoes, constitute a<lb break="yes"/>single swollen mass, an enormous volcanic wall,<lb break="yes"/>stretching from south to north, and the crest of<lb break="yes"/>which exhibits a surface of more than six hundred<lb break="yes"/>square leagues. Cotopaxi, Tunguragua, Antisana,<lb break="yes" />and Pichincha, are placed upon this same vault, on<lb break="yes"/>this raised ground. The fire issues sometimes from<lb break="yes"/>one, sometimes from another of these summits. The<lb break="yes"/>obstructed craters appear to be extinguished volca-<lb break="no"/>noes; but we may presume, that, while Cotopaxi<lb break="yes"/>or Tunguragua have only one or two eruptions in<lb break="yes"/>the course of a century, the fire is not less continu-<lb break="no"/>ally active under the town of Quito, under Pichin-<lb break="no" />cha and Imbahuru.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Advancing towards the north, we find, between<lb break="yes"/>the volcano of Cotopaxi and the town of Honda,<lb break="yes"/>two other <hi rendition="#i" >systems of volcanic mountains,</hi> those of<lb break="yes"/>Los Pastos and of Popayan. The connection of<lb break="yes"/>these systems was manifested in the Andes in an<lb break="yes"/>incontestible manner by a phenomenon, which I<lb break="yes"/>have already had occasion to notice. Since the<lb break="yes" />month of November 1796, a thick column of smoke<lb break="yes"/>had issued from the volcano of Pasto, west of the<lb break="yes"/>town of that name, and near the valley of Rio<lb break="yes"/>Guaytara. The months of the volcano are lateral,<lb break="yes"/>and placed on its western declivity, yet during<lb break="yes"/>three successive months the column rose so much<lb break="yes" />higher than the ridge of the mountain, that it was<lb break="yes"/>constantly visible to the inhabitants of the town of<lb break="yes"/>Pasto. They related to us their astonishment, when,<lb break="yes"/>on the 4th of February 1797, they observed the<lb break="yes"/>smoke disappear in an instant, without feeling any<lb break="yes"/>shock whatever. At that very moment, sixty-five<lb break="yes"/>leagues to the south, between Chimborazo, Tungu-<lb break="no" />ragua, and the Altar, (Capac Urcu) the town of<lb break="yes"/>Riobamba was overthrown by the most dreadful<lb break="yes"/>earthquake of which tradition has transmitted the<lb break="yes"/>history. Is it possible to doubt from this coincidence<lb break="yes"/>of phenomena, that the vapours issuing from the<lb break="yes"/>small apertures or <hi rendition="#i">ventanillas</hi> of the volcano of<lb break="yes"/>Pasto, had an influence on the pressure of those<lb break="yes"/>elastic fluids, which shook the ground of the king-<lb break="no"/>dom of Quito, and destroyed in a few minutes thirty<lb break="yes"/>or forty thousand inhabitants?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In order to explain these great effects of <hi rendition="#i">volcanic<lb break="yes"/>reactions,</hi> and to prove, that the group or system<lb break="yes"/>of the volcanoes of the West India Islands may<lb break="yes" />sometimes shake the continent, it was necessary to<lb break="yes"/>cite the Cordillera of the Andes. Geological rea-<lb break="no"/>soning can be supported only on the analogy of facts<lb break="yes"/>that are recent, and consequently well authenticated:<lb break="yes"/>and in what other region of the globe could we find<lb break="yes"/>greater, and at the same time more varied volcanic<lb break="yes"/>phenomena, than in that double chain of mountains<lb break="yes"/>heaved up by fire?&#x2014;in that land, where Nature has<lb break="yes"/>covered every summit and every valley with her<lb break="yes" />wonders? If we consider a burning crater only as<lb break="yes"/>an insulated phenomenon, if we satisfy ourselves<lb break="yes"/>with examining the mass of stony substances which<lb break="yes"/>it has thrown up, the volcanic action at the surface<lb break="yes"/>of the globe will appear neither very powerful nor<lb break="yes"/>very extensive. But the image of this action swells<lb break="yes"/>in the mind, when we study the relations that link<lb break="yes"/>together volcanoes of the same group; for instance,<lb break="yes"/>those of Naples and Sicily, of the Canary Islands,<lb break="yes"/>of the Azores, of the Caribbee Islands, of Mexico,<lb break="yes"/>of Guatimala, and of the table-land of Quito; when<lb break="yes"/>we examine either the reactions of these different<lb break="yes"/>systems of volcanoes on one another, or the distance<lb break="yes"/>to which, by subterranean communications, they<lb break="yes" />at the same moment shake the Earth.<note place="foot" n="‡">The following is the series of phenomena which<lb break="yes"/>M. Humboldt supposes to have had the same <choice>
                            <sic>origini:</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">origin:</corr>
                        </choice><lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;27th September 1796. Eruption in the West India<lb break="yes"/>Islands. Volcano of Guadaloupe.&#x2014;&#x2014;November 1796.<lb break="yes"/>The volcano of Pasto begins to smoke.&#x2014;&#x2014;14th of<lb break="yes"/>December 1796. Destruction of Cumana.&#x2014;&#x2014;4th of<lb break="yes"/>February 1797. Destruction of Riobamba.&#x2014;&#x2014;30th of<lb break="yes"/>January 1811. Appearance of Sabrina Island, in the<lb break="yes"/>Azores. It increases particularly on the 15th of June<lb break="yes" />1811.&#x2014;&#x2014;may 11. Beginning of the earthquakes in the<lb break="yes"/>Island of St. Vincent, which lasted till May 1812&#x2014;&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>16th of December 1811. Beginning of the commotions<lb break="yes"/>in the Valley of the Missisippi and the Ohio, which<lb break="yes"/>lasted till 1813.&#x2014;&#x2014;December 1811. Earthquake at<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas&#x2014;&#x2014;26th of March 1812. Destruction of<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas. Earthquakes which continued till 1813&#x2014;&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>30th April 1812. Eruption of the volcano at St. Vin-<lb break="no"/>cent&#x2019;s; and the same day subterranean noises at Carac-<lb break="no"/>cas, and on the banks of the Apura.</note>&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 