<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Earthquake at Caraccas in 1812</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:54</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.62</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-22-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-21-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-22-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-23-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-24-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-25-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-26-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-27-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-28-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-29-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-30-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-31-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-32-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-33-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Earthquake at Caraccas in 1812</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1835</date>
          <pubPlace>Hartford, Connecticut</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;Connecticut Courant&lt;/i&gt; 4:11 (15. Juni 1835), &lt;i&gt;Supplement&lt;/i&gt;, S. 87–88.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="87" facs="#f0001"/><cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">From Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>EARTHQUAKE AT CARACCAS,<lb break="yes"/>IN 1812.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">At</hi> this period the province of Venezuela<lb break="yes" />laboured under great drought; not a drop<lb break="yes"/>of rain had fallen at Caraccas, or to the<lb break="yes"/>distance of 311 miles around, during the<lb break="yes"/>five months which preceded the destruction<lb break="yes"/>of the capital. The 26th March was ex-<lb break="no"/>cessively hot: the air was calm and the<lb break="yes"/>sky cloudless. It was Holy Thursday, and<lb break="yes"/>a great part of the population was in the<lb break="yes" />churches. The calamities of the day were<lb break="yes"/>preceded by no indications of danger. At<lb break="yes"/>seven minutes after four in the evening the<lb break="yes"/><cb/>first commotion was felt. It was so strong<lb break="yes"/>as to make the bells of the churches ring.<lb break="yes"/>It lasted from five to six seconds, and was<lb break="yes"/>immediately followed by another shock of<lb break="yes"/>from ten to twelve seconds, during which<lb break="yes"/>the ground was in a continual state of un-<lb break="no" />dulation, and heaved like a fluid under<lb break="yes"/>ebullition. The danger was thought to be<lb break="yes"/>over, when a prodigious subterranean noise<lb break="yes"/>was heard, resembling the rolling of thun-<lb break="no"/>der, but louder and more prolonged than<lb break="yes"/>that heard within the tropics during thun-<lb break="no"/>der-storms. This noise preceded a perpen-<lb break="no"/>dicular motion of about three or four sec-<lb break="no"/>onds, followed by an undulatory motion of<lb break="yes"/>somewhat longer duration. The shocks<lb break="yes"/>were in opposite directions, from north to<lb break="yes"/>south and from east to west. It was im-<lb break="no"/>possible that any thing could resist the<lb break="yes"/>motion from beneath upwards, and the un-<lb break="no"/>dulations crossing each other. The city of<lb break="yes" />Caraccas was completely overthrown.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Thousands of the inhabitants (from nine to<lb break="yes"/>ten thousand) were buried under the ruins<lb break="yes"/>of the churches and houses. The proces-<lb break="no" />sion had not yet set out; but the crowd in<lb break="yes"/>the churches was so great that nearly three<lb break="yes"/>or four thousand individuals were crushed<lb break="yes"/>to death by the falling in of the vaulted<lb break="yes"/>roofs. The explosion was stronger on the<lb break="yes"/>north side of the town, in the part nearest<lb break="yes"/>the mountain of Avila and the Silla. The<lb break="yes"/>churches of the Trinity and Alta Gracia,<lb break="yes"/>which were more than a hundred and fifty<lb break="yes"/>feet in height, and of which the nave was<lb break="yes"/>supported by pillars from twelve to fifteen<lb break="yes"/>feet in diameter, left a mass of ruins no-<lb break="no"/>where higher than five or six feet. The<lb break="yes"/>sinking of the ruins has been so great that<lb break="yes"/>at present hardly any vestige remains of<lb break="yes"/>the pillars and columns. The barracks<lb break="yes"/>called <hi rendition="#i">El Quartel de San Carlos,</hi> situated<lb break="yes"/>farther to the north of the church of the<lb break="yes"/>Trinity, on the road to the custom-house<lb break="yes"/>de la Pastora, almost entirely disappeared.<lb break="yes"/>A regiment of troops of the line, which was<lb break="yes"/>assembled in it under arms to join in the<lb break="yes"/>procession, was, with the exception of a<lb break="yes"/>few individuals, buried under this large<lb break="yes"/>building. Nine-tenths of the fine town of<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas were entirely reduced to ruins.<lb break="yes"/>The houses which did not fall, as those of<lb break="yes"/>the street of San Juan, near the Capuchin<lb break="yes"/>Hospital, were so cracked that no one could<lb break="yes"/>venture to live in them. The effects of the<lb break="yes"/>earthquake were not quite so disastrous in<lb break="yes"/>the southern and western parts of the town,<lb break="yes"/>between the great square and the ravine of<lb break="yes"/>Caraguata;&#x2014;there the cathedral, supported<lb break="yes"/>by enormous buttresses, remains standing.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="88" facs="#f0002"/><cb/>
                <p>&#x201C;In estimating the number of persons<lb break="yes"/>killed in the city of Caraccas at nine or ten<lb break="yes"/>thousand, we do not include those unhappy<lb break="yes"/>individuals who were severely wounded,<lb break="yes"/>and perished several months after from want<lb break="yes"/>of food and proper attention. The night<lb break="yes"/>of Holy Thursday presented the most dis-<lb break="no"/>tressing scenes of desolation and sorrow.<lb break="yes"/>The thick cloud of dust, which rose above<lb break="yes"/>the ruins and darkened the air like a mist,<lb break="yes"/>had fallen again to the ground; the shocks<lb break="yes"/>had ceased; never was there a finer or<lb break="yes"/>quieter night,&#x2014;the moon, nearly at the full,<lb break="yes"/>illuminated the rounded summits of the<lb break="yes"/>Silla, and the serenity of the heavens con-<lb break="no"/>trasted strongly with the state of the earth,<lb break="yes"/>which was strewn with ruins and dead<lb break="yes"/>bodies. Mothers were seen carrying in<lb break="yes"/>their arms children whom they hoped to<lb break="yes"/>recall to life; desolate females ran through<lb break="yes"/>the city in quest of a brother, a husband,<lb break="yes"/>or a friend, of whose fate they were igno-<lb break="no"/>rant, and whom they supposed to have been<lb break="yes" />separated from them in the crowd. The<lb break="yes"/>people pressed along the streets, which now<lb break="yes"/>could only be distinguished by heaps of<lb break="yes"/>ruins arranged in lines.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;All the calamities experienced in the<lb break="yes"/>great earthquakes of Lisbon, Messina, Lima<lb break="yes"/>and Riobamba were repeated on the fatal<lb break="yes"/>day of the 26th March, 1812. The wound-<lb break="no"/>ed, buried under the ruins, implored the as-<lb break="no"/>sistance of the passers-by with loud cries,<lb break="yes"/>and more than two thousand of them were<lb break="yes"/>dug out. Never was pity displayed in a<lb break="yes" />more affecting manner; never, we may say,<lb break="yes"/>was it seen more ingeniously active than in<lb break="yes"/>the efforts made to succour the unhappy<lb break="yes"/>persons whose groans reached the ear.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>There was an entire want of instruments<lb break="yes"/>adapted for digging up the ground and<lb break="yes"/>clearing away the ruins, and the people<lb break="yes"/>were obliged to use their hands for the<lb break="yes"/>purpose of disinterring the living. Those<lb break="yes"/>who were wounded, as well as the patients<lb break="yes"/>who had escaped from the hospitals, were<lb break="yes"/>placed on the bank of the little river of<lb break="yes"/>Guayra, where they had no other shelter<lb break="yes"/>than the foliage of the trees. Beds, linen<lb break="yes"/>for dressing their wounds, surgical instru-<lb break="no"/>ments, medicines, in short, every thing ne-<lb break="no"/>cessary for their treatment, had been buried<lb break="yes"/>in the ruins. During the first days nothing<lb break="yes"/>could be procured,&#x2014;not even food. Within<lb break="yes"/>the city water became equally scarce. The<lb break="yes"/>commotion had broken the pipes of the<lb break="yes"/>fountains, and the falling in of the earth<lb break="yes"/>had obstructed the springs which supplied<lb break="yes"/>them. To obtain water it was necessary<lb break="yes"/>to descend as far as the Rio Guayra, which<lb break="yes"/><cb/>was considerably swelled, and there were<lb break="yes"/>no vessels for drawing it.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;There remained to be performed to-<lb break="no"/>wards the dead a duty imposed alike by<lb break="yes"/>piety and the dread of infection. As it was<lb break="yes"/>impossible to inter so many thousands of<lb break="yes"/>bodies half-buried in the ruins, commission-<lb break="no"/>ers were appointed to burn them. Funeral-<lb break="no"/>piles were erected among the heaps of rub-<lb break="no"/>bish. This ceremony lasted several days.<lb break="yes"/>Amid so many public calamities, the people<lb break="yes"/>ardently engaged in the religious exercises<lb break="yes"/>which they thought best adapted to appease<lb break="yes"/>the anger of Heaven. Some walked in<lb break="yes" />bodies chanting funeral-hymns, while oth-<lb break="no"/>ers, in a state of distraction, confessed<lb break="yes"/>themselves aloud in the streets. In this<lb break="yes"/>city was now repeated what had taken<lb break="yes" />place in the province of Quito after the<lb break="yes"/>dreadful earthquake of the 4th February,<lb break="yes"/>1797. Marriages were contracted between<lb break="yes"/>persons who for many years had neglected<lb break="yes"/>to sanction their union by the sacerdotal<lb break="yes"/>blessing. Children found parents in persons<lb break="yes"/>who had till then disavowed them; restitu-<lb break="no"/>tion was promised by individuals who had<lb break="yes"/>never been accused of theft; and families<lb break="yes"/>who had long been at enmity drew together,<lb break="yes"/>from the feeling of a common evil. But<lb break="yes"/>while in some this feeling seemed to soften<lb break="yes"/>the heart and open it to compassion, it had<lb break="yes"/>a contrary effect on others, rendering them<lb break="yes"/>more obdurate and inhuman. In great ca-<lb break="no"/>lamities vulgar minds retain still less good-<lb break="no"/>ness than strength; for misfortune acts<lb break="yes"/>like the pursuit of literature and the inves-<lb break="no"/>tigation of nature, which exercise their<lb break="yes"/>happy influence only upon a few, giving<lb break="yes"/>more warmth to the feelings, more eleva-<lb break="no"/>tion to the mind, and more benevolence to<lb break="yes"/>the character.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 