<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="299" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Observations respecting the Gymnotes, and other Electric Fish.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>[From Baron <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi>&#x2019;s <hi rendition="#i">Historical Relation of his Voyage in America.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">In his last voyage in America, Baron Humboldt made many original observa-<lb break="no"/>tions respecting the gymnotus and torpedo, which are highly interesting to the<lb break="yes"/>physiologist expressly, as well as to the naturalist in general; and, as the history of<lb break="yes"/>the Voyage of this philosopher is, from its great price, perhaps not in the pos-<lb break="no"/>session of many of our readers, we shall give some extracts from it, relating to<lb break="yes"/>the animals above designated.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Edit.</hi>
                    </note>]</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> Spaniards confound, under the name of <hi rendition="#i">tembladores (trem-<lb break="no"/>blers</hi>), all electric fish. They exist in the sea of the Antillas, on the<lb break="yes"/>coasts of Cumana. The Indians of Guayqueries, who are the most<lb break="yes"/>skilful fishers and most industrious people of those regions, brought us<lb break="yes" />a fish which, as they said, benumbed their hands. This fish rises up<lb break="yes"/>the little river of Manzanares. It was a new species of <hi rendition="#i">raja,</hi> the spots<lb break="yes"/>on the sides of which are but slightly visible, and which much resem-<lb break="no"/>bles the <hi rendition="#i">torpedo</hi> of <hi rendition="#k">Galvani.</hi> The torpedoes, provided with an<lb break="yes"/>electric organ, which is visible externally from the diaphanous state of<lb break="yes"/>the skin, form a genus or sub-genus different from the rajas, properly<lb break="yes"/>speaking.<note place="foot" n="†">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Cuvier.</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Regne Animal,</hi> t. ii. p. 156. There are in the Mediterranean, ac-<lb break="no"/>cording to Risso, four species of electric torpedoes, which were formerly con-<lb break="no"/>founded under the name of <hi rendition="#i">raja torpedo:</hi> namely, <hi rendition="#i">torpedo narke, torpedo unimaculata,<lb break="yes"/>torpedo galvani,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">torpedo marmorata.</hi> The torpedo of the Cape of Good Hope,<lb break="yes"/>on which Mr. Todd has recently made some experiments, is undoubtedly a non-<lb break="no"/>descript species.</note> The torpedo of Cumana was very lively, and extremely<lb break="yes"/>vigorous in his movements, and yet the electric shocks he gave us were<lb break="yes"/>but very weak. They became stronger on galvanising the animal by<lb break="yes"/>the contact of zinc and gold. Other <hi rendition="#i">tembladores,</hi> real gymnotes, or<lb break="yes"/>electric eels, inhabit the Rio Colorado, the Guarapiche, and many<lb break="yes"/>rivulets which traverse the Chaymas Indies. They enter also the<lb break="yes"/>great rivers of America,&#x2014;the Oroonoko, the Amazon, and the<lb break="yes"/>Meta; but the force of the current and depth of the water in those<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="300" facs="#f0002"/>parts prevent the Indians from catching them. They see these fish<lb break="yes"/>less frequently than they feel electric shocks from them, in swimming<lb break="yes"/>or bathing in the river. It is in the Llanos, especially in the environs<lb break="yes"/>of Calabozo, between Morichal and Aniba and Abaxo, that the ponds<lb break="yes"/>of stagnant water and the overflowings of the Oronooko (the Rio-<lb break="no"/>Guarico, the Canos of the Rastro, Berito, and Paloma), are filled with<lb break="yes"/>gymnotes. We wished at first to make our experiments in the house<lb break="yes"/>we inhabited at Calabozo; but the fear of the electric shocks of the<lb break="yes"/>gymnotus is so great, and their effects so much exaggerated by the<lb break="yes"/>people, that for three days we could not procure any of these animals,<lb break="yes" />although they may be caught with facility, and we had promised the<lb break="yes"/>Indians two piastres for each large and vigorous fish they would bring<lb break="yes"/>us. This fear of the Indians is the more extraordinary, because they<lb break="yes"/>do not resort to a means for preventing the shocks, in which, they state,<lb break="yes"/>they have much confidence. They tell white men, when they are<lb break="yes"/>interrogated respecting the effects of the <hi rendition="#i">tembladores,</hi> that they may<lb break="yes"/>be touched with impunity, if we chew tobacco. This fable of the in-<lb break="no"/>fluence of tobacco on the electric powers of these animals, is as general<lb break="yes"/>on the continent of South America, as the belief of sailors is in the<lb break="yes"/>effect of garlic and suet on the magnetic needle.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Impatient of this long delay, and obtaining only very indeterminate<lb break="yes"/>results from our observations on a living gymnotus very much<lb break="yes"/>weakened, which they had brought us, we went to Cano de Bera, to<lb break="yes"/>make our experiments in the open air on the side of the water. We<lb break="yes"/>sat out on the 19th of March early in the morning, for the little<lb break="yes"/>village called Rastro de Abaxo; whence the Indians led us to a small<lb break="yes"/>river, which, in seasons of great drought, forms a pool of muddy<lb break="yes"/>water, surrounded by beautiful trees,<note place="foot" n="*">Amyris <hi rendition="#i">lateriflora,</hi> A. <hi rendition="#i">coriacea,</hi> Laurus <hi rendition="#i">pichurin,</hi> Myroxilon <hi rendition="#i">secundum,</hi> Mal-<lb break="no"/>pighia <hi rendition="#i">reticulata.</hi>
                    </note> clusia, amyris, and mimoses<lb break="yes"/>with odoriferous flowers. The catching of the gymnotes with a net is<lb break="yes"/>very difficult, because of the extreme agility of these fish. We would<lb break="yes"/>not employ the <hi rendition="#i">barbasco,</hi> that is to say, the roots of the <hi rendition="#i">piscidia<lb break="yes"/>erithryna,</hi> the <hi rendition="#i">jacquinia armillaris,</hi> and some species of <hi rendition="#i">phyllanthus,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>which, thrown into a pond, intoxicate or stupify the fish: this mea-<lb break="no"/>sure would have weakened the gymnotes. The Indians told us, they<lb break="yes"/>would <hi rendition="#i">fish with horses.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="†">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Embarbascas con cavallos:</hi> properly, make the fish <hi rendition="#i">intoxicated or sleepy</hi> by means<lb break="yes" />of horses.</note> We could not imagine what this extraordi-<lb break="no" />nary way of fishing could be; but we soon saw our guides return from<lb break="yes"/>a savannah, where they had collected several wild horses and mules,<lb break="yes"/>which they drove before them into the pool. The noise made by the<lb break="yes"/>splashing of the horses made the fish rise from the bottom of the water,<lb break="yes"/>and prepare for the combat. These yellowish and livid eels, similar<lb break="yes"/>to large water-snakes, were then seen swimming on the surface of the<lb break="yes"/>water, and pressing themselves against the bellies of the horses and<lb break="yes"/>mules. A battle between animals so different presented a very pictu-<lb break="no"/>resque scene. The Indians, armed with harpoons and long sharp<lb break="yes"/>canes, closely surrounded the pool; some of them, too, climbed up<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="301" facs="#f0003"/>the trees whose branches hung over the water, and, by their cries and<lb break="yes"/>weapons, prevented the horses from escaping from the water. The<lb break="yes"/>eels defended themselves by repeated discharges of their electric bat-<lb break="no"/>teries. For a long time they seemed likely to become victorious.<lb break="yes"/>Many horses sunk under the violence of the shocks they received over<lb break="yes"/>all the organs most essential to life; benumbed by the force and fre-<lb break="no"/>quency of them, they disappeared under the water. Others, panting<lb break="yes"/>for breath, with erect mane, haggard eyes, and signs expressive of ex-<lb break="no"/>treme anguish, rose again, and endeavoured to escape from the storm<lb break="yes"/>around them; but the Indians drove them back again into the middle<lb break="yes"/>of the water. Some, however, escaped the vigilance of the fishermen,<lb break="yes"/>and gained the shore, stumbling at every pace, and stretching them-<lb break="no" />selves on the sands, apparently benumbed by the electric shocks of the<lb break="yes"/>gymnotes. In less than five minutes, two horses were drowned. The<lb break="yes"/>eel, being five feet in length, pressing itself along the belly of the<lb break="yes"/>horse, makes a discharge from the whole extent of his electric organ,<lb break="yes"/>and thus attacks at once the heart, the coeliac plexus, and the whole<lb break="yes"/>of the abdominal nerves. It is obvious that the effect in the horse<lb break="yes"/>must be greater than what it is in a man, when he only touches the<lb break="yes"/>animal by one of his extremities. The horses are, probably, not<lb break="yes"/>killed, but merely benumbed, and are drowned, from their inability to<lb break="yes"/>raise themselves during the combat between the rest with the gymnotes.<lb break="yes" />We at first had no doubt but that the battle would end with the death<lb break="yes"/>of all the horses engaged in it; but the impetuosity of it gradually<lb break="yes"/>diminished, and the gymnotes, fatigued, dispersed. They have occa-<lb break="no"/>sion for a long repose and an abundance of nutrition, to repair what<lb break="yes"/>they have lost of their galvanic power.<note place="foot" n="*">The Indians assured us, that, when a troop of horses were driven into that<lb break="yes"/>pool two days in succession, no horse is killed on the second day.</note> They timidly approached<lb break="yes"/>the margin of the pool, when they were taken by means of little har-<lb break="no"/>poons attached to long cords. When the cords were perfectly dry, the<lb break="yes"/>Indians drew them up without receiving any shocks. In a few mi-<lb break="no"/>nutes we had obtained five large gymnotes, most of which were but<lb break="yes"/>slightly wounded. Several others were taken towards the evening by<lb break="yes"/>the same means. The temperature of the water in which the gymnotes<lb break="yes"/>usually live, is about 26&#x00B0; or 27&#x00B0; Reaumur, (90&#x00B0; or 92&#x00B0; Fahrenheit.)<lb break="yes"/>They assured us that their electric power diminished in colder water;<lb break="yes"/>and it is very remarkable, as a celebrated naturalist has observed, that<lb break="yes" />animals, generally, endowed with organs productive of electric powers,<lb break="yes"/>the effects of which are sensible to man, are not found in the air, but<lb break="yes"/>in an electro-conductive fluid. The gymnotus is the largest of the<lb break="yes"/>electric fish. I have seen some of them which were from five feet to<lb break="yes"/>five feet three inches in length. The Indians declared that they had<lb break="yes"/>seen still longer. We found that a fish which was three feet ten<lb break="yes"/>inches long weighed twelve pounds. The transverse diameter of the<lb break="yes"/>body was, without including the anal fin, three inches and five lines,<lb break="yes"/>(very nearly four inches English measure.)</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The gymnotes of Cano de Bera are of a fine olive-green colour.<lb break="yes" />The part below the head is yellow, mingled with red. Two rows of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="302" facs="#f0004"/>small yellow spots are placed symmetrically along the back, from the<lb break="yes"/>head to the point of the tail: each spot surrounds an excretory open-<lb break="no"/>ing; and the skin of the animal is constantly covered with a mucous<lb break="yes"/>matter, which, as <hi rendition="#k">Volta</hi> proved, conducts electricity twenty or thirty<lb break="yes"/>times more powerfully than pure water. It is very remarkable, that<lb break="yes"/>no electric fish hitherto discovered is provided with scales.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The gymnotus, like the common eel, likes to respire the air on the<lb break="yes" />surface of the water. The latter is known to creep during the night<lb break="yes"/>on the grassy banks of rivers; but we must not conclude, with M.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Bajon,</hi> that the fish would die if it were not to come and respire air<lb break="yes"/>without the water. I have seen a very vigorous gymnotus die on<lb break="yes"/>the dry ground, after having darted out of the adjacent pool. M.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Provencal</hi> and myself have proved, by our researches on the respira-<lb break="no"/>tion of fishes, that their gills, when wet, are capable of performing the<lb break="yes"/>functions, both of decomposing atmospheric air, and of abstracting the<lb break="yes"/>oxygen dissolved in water. They do not suspend their respiration in<lb break="yes"/>the air, but absorb gaseous oxygen, like a reptile provided with lungs.<lb break="yes"/>It is well known that carps are fattened by feeding them out of water,<lb break="yes" />taking care to moisten from time to time their gills with some wet<lb break="yes"/>moss, to prevent them from becoming dry. Fish open their bronchial<lb break="yes"/>valves more in oxygen gas than in water; but their temperature is not<lb break="yes"/>raised, and they live as long in vital air as in a mixture of 90 parts of<lb break="yes"/>azote and 16 of oxygen. We have found that tenches, placed under<lb break="yes"/>bell-glasses filled with air, absorb in an hour half a cubic centimetre<lb break="yes"/>(about one-sixth of a cubic inch English measure) of oxygen. This<lb break="yes"/>action takes place in the gills alone; for, fish having cork-collars<lb break="yes"/>adapted to them, and placed thus with their head outwards and the<lb break="yes"/>rest of the body in a vessel filled with air, do not absorb the oxygen<lb break="yes" />by the rest of the body. It appears, that respiration of air is effected<lb break="yes"/>by the medium of an extremely thin layer of water over the surface of<lb break="yes"/>the gills.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The swimming-bladder of the gymnotus is two feet five inches long<lb break="yes" />in a fish three feet ten inches in length. It is separated from the skin<lb break="yes"/>by a mass of fat, and is situate on the electric organs, which fill more<lb break="yes"/>than two-thirds of the animal. The same vessels that are insinuated<lb break="yes"/>between the lamin&#x00E6; of these organs, give also numerous branches to the<lb break="yes"/>exterior surface of the bladder just mentioned. One hundred parts of<lb break="yes"/>the fluid contained in this bladder, I found to be constituted of 96<lb break="yes"/>parts azote and 4 oxygen.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The medullary substance of the brain presents but a slight analogy<lb break="yes" />with the albuminous and gelatinous matter of the electric organs, but<lb break="yes"/>these two substances have this in common,&#x2014;they receive a large quan-<lb break="no"/>tity of arterial blood, which is deprived of its oxygen in them.<note place="foot" n="*">We stop, at present, at the conclusion of these preliminary observations,<lb break="yes"/>because we wish to give an account of Baron Humboldt&#x2019;s experiments on the<lb break="yes"/>electric powers of the gymnotes in an uninterrupted manner, and the limits of the<lb break="yes"/>Journal will not permit us to do this in the present Number.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Edit.</hi>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 