<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. Validation.<note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe. Validierung.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="249" facs="#f0001"/><cb/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>EARTHQUAKE AT CARACCAS.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">There</hi> is something so awful in the<lb break="yes" />terrible catastrophe which befel the city<lb break="yes"/>of Caraccas, in South America, on the<lb break="yes"/>26th of March, 1812, that we cannot<lb break="yes"/>forbear transferring some account of it<lb break="yes"/>to our pages.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A great drought prevailed at this<lb break="yes"/>period in the province of Venezuala.<lb break="yes"/>Not a single drop of rain had fallen at<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas, or in the country ninety leagues<lb break="yes" />round, during the five months which<lb break="yes"/>preceded the destruction of the capital.<lb break="yes"/>The 26th of March was a remarkably<lb break="yes"/>hot day. The air was calm and the sky<lb break="yes" />unclouded. It was holy Thursday, and<lb break="yes"/>a great part of the population was as-<lb break="no"/>sembled in the churches. Nothing<lb break="yes"/>seemed to presage the calamities of the<lb break="yes"/>day. At seven minutes after four in the<lb break="yes"/>afternoon, the first shock was felt; it<lb break="yes"/><cb/>was sufficiently powerful to make the<lb break="yes" />bells of the churches toll; it lasted five<lb break="yes"/>or six seconds, during which time the<lb break="yes"/>ground was in a continual undulating<lb break="yes"/>movement, and seemed to heave up like<lb break="yes"/>a boiling liquid. The danger was<lb break="yes"/>thought to be past, when a tremendous<lb break="yes"/>subterraneous noise was heard, resem-<lb break="no"/>bling the rolling of thunder, but louder<lb break="yes"/>and of longer continuance than that<lb break="yes"/>heard within the tropics in time of storms.<lb break="yes"/>This noise preceded a perpendicular<lb break="yes"/>motion of three or four seconds, followed<lb break="yes"/>by an undulatory movement somewhat<lb break="yes"/>longer. The shocks were in opposite<lb break="yes" />directions, from north to south, and<lb break="yes"/>from east to west. Nothing could resist<lb break="yes"/>the movement from beneath upward,<lb break="yes"/>and undulations crossing each other.<lb break="yes"/>The town of Caraccas was entirely over-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="250" facs="#f0002"/><cb/>thrown. Thousands of the inhabitants<lb break="yes"/>(between nine and ten thousand) were<lb break="yes"/>buried under the ruins of the houses and<lb break="yes"/>churches. The procession had not yet<lb break="yes"/>set out; but the crowd was so great in<lb break="yes"/>the churches, that nearly three or four<lb break="yes"/>thousand persons were crushed by the<lb break="yes"/>fall of their vaulted roofs. The ex-<lb break="no"/>plosion was stronger toward the north,<lb break="yes"/>in that part of the town situate nearest<lb break="yes"/>the mountain of Avila, and the Silla.<lb break="yes"/> The churches of La Trinidad and Alta<lb break="yes" />Gracia, which were more than one hun-<lb break="no"/>dred and fifty feet high, and the naves<lb break="yes"/>of which were supported by pillars of<lb break="yes"/>twelve or fifteen feet diameter, left a<lb break="yes"/>mass of ruins scarcely exceeding five or<lb break="yes"/>six feet in elevation. The sinking of the<lb break="yes"/>ruins has been so considerable, that there<lb break="yes"/>now scarcely remain any vestiges of<lb break="yes"/>pillars or columns. The barracks, called<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">El Quartel de San Carlos</hi>, situated far-<lb break="no" />ther nort of the church of the Trinity,<lb break="yes"/>on the road from the Custom-house de<lb break="yes"/>la Pastora, almost entirely disappeared.<lb break="yes"/>A regiement of troops of the line, that<lb break="yes"/>was assembled under amrs, ready to<lb break="yes"/>join the procession, was, with the ex-<lb break="no"/>ception of a few men, buried under the<lb break="yes" />ruins of this great edifice. Nine-thenths<lb break="yes"/>of the fine town of Caraccas were en-<lb break="no"/>tirely destroyed. The walls of the<lb break="yes"/>houses that were not thrown down, as<lb break="yes"/>those of the street San Juan, near the<lb break="yes"/>Capuchin Hospital, were cracked in such<lb break="yes"/>a manner, that it was impossible to run<lb break="yes" />the risk of inhabiting them. The effects<lb break="yes"/>of the earthquake were somewhat less<lb break="yes"/>violent in the western and southern parts<lb break="yes"/>of the city, between the principal square<lb break="yes"/>and the ravin of Caraquata. There, the<lb break="yes"/>cathedral, supported by enormous but-<lb break="no"/>tresses, remains standing.<lb break="yes" />Estimating at nine or ten thousand<lb break="yes"/>the number of the dead in the city of<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas, we do not include those un-<lb break="no" />happy persons who, dangerously wound-<lb break="no"/>ed, perished several months after, for<lb break="yes"/>want of food and proper care. The<lb break="yes"/>night of Holy Thursday presented the<lb break="yes"/>most distressing scene of desolation and<lb break="yes"/>sorrow. The thick cloud of dust which,<lb break="yes"/>rising above the ruins, darkened the sky<lb break="yes"/>like a fog, had settled on the ground.<lb break="yes"/>No shock was felt, and never was a<lb break="yes"/>night more calm, or more serene. The<lb break="yes"/>moon, nearly full, illumined the rounded<lb break="yes" />domes of the Silla, and the aspect of the<lb break="yes"/><cb/>sky formed a perfect contrast to that of<lb break="yes"/>the earth, covered with the dead, and<lb break="yes"/>heaped with ruins. Mothers were seen<lb break="yes"/>bearing in their arms their children,<lb break="yes"/>whom they hoped to recal to life. De-<lb break="no"/>solate families wadered through the<lb break="yes"/>city seeking a brother, a husband, a<lb break="yes"/>friend, of whose fate they were ignorant,<lb break="yes"/>and whom they believed to be lost in the<lb break="yes"/>crowd. The people pressed along the<lb break="yes"/>streets, which could no more be recog-<lb break="no"/>nized but by long lines of ruins.<lb break="yes"/>All the calamities experienced in the<lb break="yes" />great catastrophes of Lisbon, Messina,<lb break="yes"/>Lima, and Riobamba were renewed on<lb break="yes"/>the fatal day of the 26th March, 1812.<lb break="yes" />The wounded, buried under the ruins, implored by their cries the help of the<lb break="yes"/>passers by, and nearly two thousand<lb break="yes"/>were dug out. Never was pity displayed<lb break="yes"/>in a more affecting manner; never had<lb break="yes"/>it been seen more ingenuously active,<lb break="yes" />than in the efforts employed to save the<lb break="yes"/>miserable victims, whose groans reached<lb break="yes"/>the ear. Implements for digging and<lb break="yes"/>clearing away the ruins were instantly<lb break="yes"/>wanting; and the people were obliged<lb break="yes"/>to use their bare hands, to disinter the<lb break="yes"/>living. The wounded, as well as the<lb break="yes"/>sick who had escaped from the hospitals,<lb break="yes"/>were laid on the banks of the small river<lb break="yes"/>Guayra. They found no shelter but the<lb break="yes"/>foliage of trees. Beds, linen to dress<lb break="yes"/>the wounds, instruments of surgery,<lb break="yes"/>medicines, and objects of the most urgent<lb break="yes"/>necessity, were buried under the ruins.<lb break="yes"/>Everything, even food, was wanting dur-<lb break="no"/>ing the first days. Water became alike<lb break="yes"/>scarce into the interior of the city. The<lb break="yes"/>commotions had rent the pipes of the<lb break="yes" />fountains; the falling in of the earth had<lb break="yes"/>choaked up the springs that supplied<lb break="yes"/>them; and it became necessary, in order<lb break="yes"/>to have water, to go down to the river<lb break="yes"/>Guayra, which was considerably swelled; and then vessels to convey the water<lb break="yes"/>were wanting.<lb break="yes"/>There remained a duty to be fulfilled<lb break="yes"/>towards the dead, enjoined at once by<lb break="yes"/>piety, and the dread of infection. It<lb break="yes"/>being impossible to inter so many thou-<lb break="no"/>sand corpses, half-buried under the ruins,<lb break="yes"/>commissaries were appointed to burn<lb break="yes" />the bodies; and for this purpose fu-<lb break="no"/>neral piles were erected between the<lb break="yes"/>heaps of ruins. This ceremony lasted<lb break="yes" />several days. Amid so many public<lb break="yes"/>calamities, the peole devoted themselves<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="251" facs="#f0003"/><cb/>to those religious duties, which they<lb break="yes" />thought were the most fitted to appease<lb break="yes"/>the wrath of Heaven. Some, assembling<lb break="yes"/>in processions, sang funeral hymns;<lb break="yes"/>others, in a state of distraction, confessed<lb break="yes" />themselves aloud in the streets. In this<lb break="yes"/>town was now repeated what had been<lb break="yes"/>remarked in the province of Quito, after<lb break="yes"/>the tremendous earthquake of 1767; a<lb break="yes"/>number of marriages were contracted<lb break="yes"/>between persons, who had neglected for<lb break="yes"/>many years to sanction their union by<lb break="yes" />the sacerdotal benedicition. Children<lb break="yes"/>found parents, by whom they had never<lb break="yes"/>till then been acknowledged; restitu-<lb break="no"/>tions were promised by persons, who<lb break="yes"/>had never been accused of fraud; and<lb break="yes"/>families, who had long been enemies, were<lb break="yes"/>drawn together by the tie of common<lb break="yes" />calamity.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 