<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="272" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Account of the Earthquake which destroyed the<lb break="yes"/>Town of Caraccas on the</hi> 26<hi rendition="#i">th March</hi> 1812. By M. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>HERE are few events in the physical world which are cal-<lb break="no"/>culated to excite so deep and permanent an interest as the earth-<lb break="no"/>quake which destroyed the town of Caraccas, and by which<lb break="yes"/>more than 20,000 persons perished, almost at the same instant,<lb break="yes"/>in the province of Venezuela. The general results of this<lb break="yes"/>frightful catastrophe have been long known in this country; but<lb break="yes"/>its particular details, so afflicting to human feelings, and the<lb break="yes"/>physical phenomena by which it was accompanied, so important<lb break="yes"/>in geological speculations, have been only recently described by<lb break="yes"/>M. Humboldt <note place="foot" n="†">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Personal Narrative,</hi> vol. iv. p. 12.</note>. This distinguished traveller, who had visited<lb break="yes"/>the city of Caraccas previous to its destruction, has been at<lb break="yes"/>great pains to collect and compare the descriptions of individuals<lb break="yes"/>who had witnessed the effects of the earthquake, and has thus<lb break="yes"/>been enabled to draw a faithful picture of this terrible convul-<lb break="no"/>sion, marked with that glowing eloquence which characterises<lb break="yes"/>all his writings. We regret that our limits will not permit us<lb break="yes"/>to present our readers with all his reasonings respecting the<lb break="yes"/>influence of a system of volcanoes over a vast extent of cir-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="273" facs="#f0002"/>cumjacent country; but we may afterwards have another op-<lb break="no"/>portunity of resuming this branch of the subject.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>“The 26th of March was a remarkably hot day. The air<lb break="yes"/>was calm, and the sky unclouded. It was Holy Thursday, and<lb break="yes"/>a great part of the population was assembled in the churches.<lb break="yes"/>Nothing seemed to presage the calamities of the day. At seven<lb break="yes"/>minutes after four in the afternoon the first shock was felt; it<lb break="yes"/>was sufficiently powerful, to make the bells of the churches toll;<lb break="yes"/>it lasted five or six seconds, during which time, the ground was<lb break="yes"/>in a continual undulating movement, and seemed to heave up<lb break="yes"/>like a boiling liquid. The danger was thought to be past, when<lb break="yes"/>a tremendous subterraneous noise was heard, resembling the<lb break="yes"/>rolling of thunder, but louder, and of longer continuance, than<lb break="yes"/>that heard within the tropics in time of storms. This noise pre-<lb break="no"/>ceded a perpendicular motion of three or four seconds, followed<lb break="yes"/>by an undulatory movement somewhat longer. The shocks<lb break="yes"/>were in opposite directions, from north to south, and from east<lb break="yes"/>to west. Nothing could resist the movement from beneath up-<lb break="no"/>ward, and undulations crossing each other. The town of Ca-<lb break="no"/>raccas was entirely overthrown. Between nine and ten thou-<lb break="no"/>sand of the inhabitants were buried under the ruins of the<lb break="yes"/>houses and churches. The procession had not yet set out;<lb break="yes"/>but the crowd was so great in the churches, that nearly three<lb break="yes"/>or four thousand persons were crushed by the fall of their<lb break="yes"/>vaulted roofs. The explosion was stronger towards the north,<lb break="yes"/>in that part of the town situated nearest the mountain of Avila,<lb break="yes"/>and the Silla. The churches of la Trinidad and Alta Gracia,<lb break="yes"/>which where more than 150 feet high, and the naves of which<lb break="yes"/>were supported by pillars of twelve or fifteen feet diameter, left<lb break="yes"/>a mass of ruins scarcely exceeding five or six feet in elevation.<lb break="yes"/>The sinking of the ruins has been so considerable, that there<lb break="yes"/>now scarcely remain any vestiges of pillars or columns. The<lb break="yes"/>barracks, called <hi rendition="#i">El Quartel de San Carlos,</hi> situate farther<lb break="yes"/>north of the Church of the Trinity, on the road from the Cus-<lb break="no"/>tom-house de la Pastora, almost entirely disappeared. A regi-<lb break="no"/>ment of troops of the line, that was assembled under arms,<lb break="yes"/>ready to join the procession, was, with the exception of a few<lb break="yes"/>men, buried under the ruins of this great edifice. Nine-tenths<lb break="yes"/>of the fine town of Caraccas were entirely destroyed. The<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="274" facs="#f0003"/> walls of the houses that were not thrown down, as those of the<lb break="yes"/>street San Juan, near the Capuchin Hospital, were cracked in such<lb break="yes"/>a manner, that it was impossible to run the risk of inhabiting them.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>“Estimating at nine or ten thousand the number of the dead<lb break="yes"/>in the city of Caraccas, we do not include those unhappy per-<lb break="no"/>sons, who, dangerously wounded, perished several months after,<lb break="yes"/>for want of food and proper attention. The night of Holy Thurs-<lb break="no"/>day presented the most distressing scene of desolation and sor-<lb break="no"/>row. That thick cloud of dust, which, rising above the ruins,<lb break="yes"/>darkened the sky like a fog, had settled on the ground. No<lb break="yes"/>shock was felt, and never was a night more calm or more serene.<lb break="yes"/>The moon, nearly full, illumined the rounded domes of the<lb break="yes"/>Silla, and the aspect of the sky formed a perfect contrast to that<lb break="yes"/>of the earth, covered with the dead, and heaped with ruins.<lb break="yes"/>Mothers were seen bearing in their arms their children, whom<lb break="yes"/>they hoped to recall to life. Desolate families wandered through<lb break="yes"/>the city, seeking a brother, a husband, a friend, of whose fate<lb break="yes"/>they were ignorant, and whom they believed to be lost in the<lb break="yes"/>crowd. The people pressed along the streets, which could no<lb break="yes"/>more be recognised but by long lines of ruins.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>“All the calamities experienced in the great catastrophes of<lb break="yes" />Lisbon, Messina, Lima, and Riobamba, were renewed on the<lb break="yes"/>fatal day of the 26th of March 1812. The wounded, buried<lb break="yes"/>under the ruins, implored by their cries the help of the passers<lb break="yes"/>by, and nearly 2000 were dug out. Implements for digging,<lb break="yes"/>and clearing away the ruins were entirely wanting; and the<lb break="yes"/>people were obliged to use their bare hands to disinter the<lb break="yes"/>living. The wounded, as well as the sick who had escaped<lb break="yes"/>from the hospitals, were laid on the banks of the small river<lb break="yes"/>Guayra. They found no shelter but the foliage of trees. Beds,<lb break="yes"/>linen to dress the wounds, instruments of surgery, medicines,<lb break="yes"/>and objects of the most urgent necessity, were buried under the<lb break="yes"/>ruins. Every thing, even food, was wanting during the first<lb break="yes"/>days. Water became alike scarce in the interior of the city.<lb break="yes"/>The commotion had rent the pipes of the fountains; the falling<lb break="yes"/>in of the earth had choked up the springs that supplied them;<lb break="yes"/>and it became necessary, in order to have water, to go down to<lb break="yes"/>the river Guayra, which was considerably swelled; and then<lb break="yes"/>vessels to convey the water were wanting.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="275" facs="#f0004"/>
                <p>“There remained a duty to be fulfilled towards the dead,<lb break="yes"/>enjoined at once by piety and the dread of infection. It being<lb break="yes"/>impossible to inter so many thousand corpses, half-buried under<lb break="yes"/>the ruins, commissaries were appointed to burn the bodies: and<lb break="yes"/>for this purpose, funeral piles were erected between the heaps<lb break="yes"/>of ruins. This ceremony lasted several days. Amid so many<lb break="yes"/>public calamities, the people devoted themselves to those reli-<lb break="no"/>gious duties, which they thought were the most fitted to appease<lb break="yes"/>the wrath of Heaven. Some, assembling in procession, sung<lb break="yes"/>funeral hymns; others, in a state of distraction, confessed them-<lb break="no"/>selves aloud in the streets. In this town was now repeated<lb break="yes"/>what had been remarked in the province of Quito, after the<lb break="yes"/>tremendous earthquake of 1797; a number of marriages were<lb break="yes"/>contracted between persons, who had neglected for many years<lb break="yes"/>to sanction their union by the sacerdotal benediction. Children<lb break="yes"/>found parents, by whom they had never till then been acknow-<lb break="no"/>ledged; restitutions were promised by persons, who had never<lb break="yes"/>been accused of fraud; and families, who had long been ene-<lb break="no"/>mies, were drawn together by the tie of common calamity. If<lb break="yes"/>this feeling seemed to calm the passions of some, and open the<lb break="yes"/>heart to pity, it had a contrary effect on others, rendering them<lb break="yes"/>more rigid and inhuman.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>“Shocks as violent as those which, in the space of one<lb break="yes"/>minute <note place="foot" n="*">The duration of the earthquake, that is to say the whole of the movements<lb break="yes"/>of undulation and rising which occasioned the horrible catastrophe of the 26th of<lb break="yes"/>March 1812, was estimated by some at 50″, by others at 1′ 12″.</note>, overthrew the city of Caraccas, could not be confined<lb break="yes"/>to a small portion of the continent. Their fatal effects extend-<lb break="no"/>ed as far as the provinces of Venezuela, Varinas, and Maracay-<lb break="no"/>bo, along the coast; and still more to the inland mountains.<lb break="yes"/>La Guayra, Mayquetia, Antimano, Baruta, La Vega, San Fe-<lb break="no"/>lipe, and Merida, were almost entirely destroyed. The number<lb break="yes"/>of the dead exceeded four or five thousand at La Guayra, and<lb break="yes"/>at the town of San Felipe, near the copper-mines of Aroa. It<lb break="yes"/>appears, that it was on a line running east north-east, and west<lb break="yes"/>south-west, from La Guayra and Caraccas to the lofty moun-<lb break="no"/>tains of Niquitao and Merida, that the violence of the earth-<lb break="no"/>quake was principally directed. It was felt in the kingdom of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="276" facs="#f0005"/>New Granada from the branches of the high Sierra de Santa<lb break="yes"/>Martha as far as Santa Fe de Bogota and Honda, on the<lb break="yes"/>banks of the Magdalena, 180 leagues from Caraccas. It was<lb break="yes"/>every where more violent in the Cordilleras of gneiss and mica-<lb break="no"/>slate, or immediately at their foot, than in the plains: and this<lb break="yes"/>difference was particularly striking in the savannahs of Varinas<lb break="yes"/>and Casanara. In the valleys of Aragua, situate between<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas and the town of San Felipe, the commotions were<lb break="yes"/>very weak: and La Victoria, Maracay, and Valentia, scarcely<lb break="yes"/>suffered at all, notwithstanding their proximity to the capital.<lb break="yes"/>At Valecillo, a few leagues from Valencia, the earth, opening,<lb break="yes"/>threw out such an immense quantity of water, that it formed a<lb break="yes"/>new torrent. The same phenomenon took place near Porto-<lb break="no"/>Cabello. On the other hand, the lake of Maracaybo diminish-<lb break="no"/>ed sensibly. At Coro no commotion was felt, though the town<lb break="yes"/>is situated upon the coast, between other towns which suffered<lb break="yes"/>from the earthquake.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>“Fifteen or eighteen hours after the great catastrophe, the<lb break="yes" />ground remained tranquil. The night, as we have already ob-<lb break="no" />served, was fine and calm; and the commotions did not recom-<lb break="no" />mence till after the 27th. They were then attended with a<lb break="yes"/>very loud and long continued subterranean noise. The in-<lb break="no"/>habitants of Caraccas wandered into the country; but the<lb break="yes"/>villages and farms having suffered as much as the town, they<lb break="yes"/>could find no shelter till they were beyond the mountains of Los<lb break="yes"/>Teques, in the valleys of Aragua, and in the Llanos or Sa-<lb break="no"/>vannahs. No less than fifteen oscillations were often felt in one<lb break="yes"/>day. On the 5th of April there was almost as violent an earth-<lb break="no"/>quake, as that which overthrew the capital. During several<lb break="yes"/>hours the ground was in a state of perpetual undulation. Large<lb break="yes"/>masses of earth fell in the mountains; and enormous rocks were<lb break="yes"/>detached from the Silla of Caraccas. It was even asserted and<lb break="yes"/>believed that the two domes of the Silla sunk fifty or sixty toises;<lb break="yes"/>but this assertion is founded on no measurement whatever.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>“While violent commotions were felt at the same time in the<lb break="yes" />valley of the Missisippi, in the island of St Vincent, and in the<lb break="yes"/>province of Venezuela, the inhabitants of Caraccas, of Calabozo,<lb break="yes"/>situated in the midst of the steppes, and on the borders of the<lb break="yes"/>Rio Apura, in a space of 4000 square leagues, were terrified<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="277" facs="#f0006"/>on the 30th of April 1812, by a subterraneous noise, which re-<lb break="no"/>sembled frequent discharges of the largest cannon. This noise<lb break="yes"/>began at two in the morning. It was accompanied by no<lb break="yes"/>shock; and, what is very remarkable, it was as loud on the<lb break="yes"/>coast as at eighty leagues distance inland. It was every where<lb break="yes"/>believed to be transmitted through the air; and was so far from<lb break="yes"/>being thought a subterraneous noise, that at Carraccas, as well<lb break="yes"/>as at Calabozo, preparations were made to put the place into a<lb break="yes"/>state of defence against an enemy, who seemed to be advancing<lb break="yes"/>with heavy artillery. Mr Palacio, crossing the Rio Apura<lb break="yes"/>near the junction of the Rio Nula, was told by the inhabitants<lb break="yes"/>that the ‘<hi rendition="#i">firing of cannon</hi>’ had been heard as distinctly at the<lb break="yes"/>western extremity of the province of Varinas, as at the port of<lb break="yes"/>La Guayra to the north of the chain of the coast.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>“The day on which the inhabitants of Terra Firma were<lb break="yes"/>alarmed by a subterraneous noise, was that on which happened<lb break="yes"/>the eruption of the volcano in the island of St Vincent. This<lb break="yes"/>mountain, near five hundred toises high, had not thrown out<lb break="yes"/>any lava since the year 1718. Scarcely was any smoke perceiv-<lb break="no"/>ed to issue from its top, when, in the month of May 1811, fre-<lb break="no"/>quent shocks announced, that the volcanic fire was either re-<lb break="no"/>kindled, or directed anew toward that part of the West Indies.<lb break="yes"/>The first eruption did not take place till the 27th of April<lb break="yes"/>1812, at noon. It was only an ejection of ashes, but attended<lb break="yes"/>with a tremendous noise. On the 30th, the lava passed the<lb break="yes"/>brink of the crater, and, after a course of four hours, reached<lb break="yes"/>the sea. The noise of the explosion ‘resembled that of alter-<lb break="no"/>nate discharges of very large cannon and of musketry; and,<lb break="yes"/>what is well worthy of remark, it seemed much louder at sea,<lb break="yes"/>at a great distance from the island, than in sight of land, and<lb break="yes"/>near the burning volcano.’</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>“The distance in a straight line from the volcano of St Vin-<lb break="no"/>cent to the Rio Apura, near the mouth of the Nula, is 210 nautical<lb break="yes" />leagues. The explosions were consequently heard at a distance<lb break="yes" />equal to that between Vesuvius and Paris. This phenomenon, con-<lb break="no" />nected with a great number of facts observed in the Cordilleras<lb break="yes" />of the Andes, shows how much more extensive the subterra-<lb break="no"/>nean sphere of activity of a volcano is, than we are disposed to<lb break="yes" />admit from the small changes effected at the surface of the globe.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="278" facs="#f0007"/>The detonations heard during whole days together in the<lb break="yes"/>New World, 80, 100, or even 200 leagues distant from a<lb break="yes"/>crater, do not reach us by the propagation of sound through<lb break="yes"/>the air; they are transmitted to us by the ground. The<lb break="yes"/>little town of Honda, on the banks of the Magdalena, is not<lb break="yes"/>less than 145 leagues from Cotopaxi; and yet in the great ex-<lb break="no"/>plosions of this volcano, in 1744, a subterraneous noise was<lb break="yes"/>heard at Honda, and supposed to be discharges of heavy artil-<lb break="no"/>lery. The monks of St Francis spread the news, that the town<lb break="yes"/>of Carthagena was bombarded by the English; and the intelli-<lb break="no"/>gence was believed. Now the volcano of Cotopaxi is a cone, more<lb break="yes"/>than 1800 toises above the basin of Honda, and rises from a table-<lb break="no"/>land, the elevation of which is more than 1500 toises above the<lb break="yes"/>valley of the Magdalena. In all the colossal mountains of<lb break="yes"/>Quito, of the provinces of Los Pastos, and of Popayan, crevices<lb break="yes"/>and valleys without number are interposed. It cannot be ad-<lb break="no"/>mitted, under these circumstances, that the noise could be<lb break="yes"/>transmitted through the air, or by the superior surface of the<lb break="yes"/>globe, and that it came from that point, where the cone<lb break="yes"/>and crater of Cotopaxi are placed. It appears probable, that<lb break="yes"/>the higher part of the kingdom of Quito and the neigh-<lb break="no"/>bouring Cordilleras, far from being a group of distinct vol-<lb break="no"/>canoes, constitute a single swollen mass, an enormous volcanic<lb break="yes"/>wall, stretching from south to north, and the crest of which<lb break="yes"/>exhibits a surface of more than six hundred square leagues.<lb break="yes"/>Cotopaxi, Tunguragua, Antisana, and Pichincha, are placed on<lb break="yes"/>this same vault, on this raised ground. The fire issues some-<lb break="no"/>times from one, sometimes from another of these summits.<lb break="yes"/>The obstructed craters appear to be extinguished volcanoes;<lb break="yes"/>but we may presume, that, while Cotopaxi or Tunguragua have<lb break="yes"/>only one or two eruptions in the course of a century, the fire<lb break="yes"/>is not less continually active under the town of Quito, under<lb break="yes"/>Pichincha and Imbaburu.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>“Advancing toward the north, we find, between the volcano<lb break="yes"/>of Cotopaxi and the town of Honda, two other <hi rendition="#i">systems of vol-<lb break="no"/>canic mountains,</hi> those of Los Pastos and of Popayan. The<lb break="yes"/>connection of these systems was manifested in the Andes in an<lb break="yes"/>incontestible manner by a phenomenon, which I have already had<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="279" facs="#f0008"/>occasion to notice. Since the month of November 1796, a thick<lb break="yes"/>column of smoke had issued from the volcano of Pasto, west of the<lb break="yes"/>town of that name, and near the valley of Rio Guaytara. The<lb break="yes"/>mouths of the volcano are lateral, and placed on its western de-<lb break="no"/>clivity, yet during three successive months the column rose so<lb break="yes"/>much higher than the ridge of the mountain, that it was con-<lb break="no"/>stantly visible to the inhabitants of the town of Pasto. They<lb break="yes"/>related to us their astonishment, when, on the 4th of February<lb break="yes"/>1797, they observed the smoke disappear in an instant, without<lb break="yes"/>feeling any shock whatever. At that very moment, sixty-five<lb break="yes"/>leagues to the south, between Chimborazo, Tunguragua, and<lb break="yes"/>the Altar (Capac Urcu,) the town of Riobamba was overthrown<lb break="yes"/>by the most dreadful earthquake of which tradition has trans-<lb break="no"/>mitted the history. Is it possible to doubt from this coincidence<lb break="yes"/>of phenomena, that the vapours issuing from the small apertures<lb break="yes"/>or <hi rendition="#i">ventanillas</hi> of the volcano of Pasto, had an influence on the<lb break="yes"/>pressure of those elastic fluids, which shook the ground of the<lb break="yes"/>kingdom of Quito, and destroyed in a few minutes thirty or<lb break="yes"/>forty thousand inhabitants?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>“In order to explain these great effects of <hi rendition="#i">volcanic reactions,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and to prove, that the group or system of the volcanoes of the<lb break="yes"/>West India Islands may sometimes shake the continent, it was<lb break="yes"/>necessary to cite the Cordillera of the Andes. Geological rea-<lb break="no"/>soning can be supported only on the analogy of facts that are<lb break="yes"/>recent, and consequently well authenticated: and in what other<lb break="yes"/>region of the globe could we find greater, and at the same<lb break="yes"/>time more varied volcanic phenomena, than in that double chain<lb break="yes"/>of mountains heaved up by fire? in that land, where Nature<lb break="yes"/>has covered every summit and every valley with her wonders?<lb break="yes"/>If we consider a burning crater only as an insulated phenome-<lb break="no"/>non, if we satisfy ourselves with examining the mass of stony<lb break="yes"/>substances which it has thrown up, the volcanic action at the<lb break="yes"/>surface of the globe will appear neither very powerful nor very<lb break="yes"/>extensive. But the image of this action swells in the mind,<lb break="yes"/>when we study the relations that link together volcanoes of the<lb break="yes"/>same group; for instance, those of Naples and Sicily, of the<lb break="yes"/>Canary Islands, of the Azores, of the Caribbee Islands, of Mexi-<lb break="no"/>co, of Guatimala, and of the table-land of Quito; when we<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="280" facs="#f0009"/>examine either the reactions of these different systems of volca-<lb break="no"/>noes on one another, or the distance to which, by subterranean<lb break="yes"/>communications, they at the same moment shake the Earth<note place="foot" n="*">The following is the series of phenomena which M. Humboldt supposes to<lb break="yes"/>have had the same origin:<lb break="yes"/>27th September 1796. Eruption in the West India Islands. Volcano of Gua-<lb break="no"/>daloupe.&#x2014;November 1796. The volcano of Pasto begins to emit smoke.&#x2014;14th of<lb break="yes"/>December 1796. Destruction of Cumana.&#x2014;4th of February 1797. Destruction<lb break="yes"/>of Riobamba.&#x2014;30th of January 1811. Appearance of Sabrina Island, in the<lb break="yes"/>Azores. It increases particularly on the 15th of June 1811.&#x2014;May 1811. Begin-<lb break="no"/>ning of the earthquakes in the Island St Vincent, which lasted till May 1812.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>16th of December 1811. Beginning of the commotions in the Valley of the Mis-<lb break="no"/>sisippi and the Ohio, which lasted till 1813.&#x2014;December 1811. Earthquake at<lb break="yes" />Caraccas.&#x2014;26th of March 1812. Destruction of Caraccas. Earthquakes which<lb break="yes"/>continued till 1813.&#x2014;30th April 1812. Eruption of the volcano at St Vincent’s;<lb break="yes"/>and the same day subterranean noises at Caraccas, and on the banks of the Apura.</note>.”</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 