<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="415" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>AN EARTHQUAKE IN THE CARACCAS.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">as described by humboldt.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The shock felt at Caraccas, in the month of December, 1811,<lb break="yes"/>was the only one that preceded the horrible catastrophe of the<lb break="yes"/>26th of March, 1812. The inhabitants of Terra Firma were<lb break="yes"/>ignorant of the agitations of the volcano in the island of St.<lb break="yes"/>Vincent on one side, and on the other, of those that were felt<lb break="yes"/>in the basin of the Missisippi, where, on the 7th and 8th of<lb break="yes"/>February, 1812, the earth was, day and night, in perpetual os-<lb break="no"/>cillation. A great drought prevailed at this period in the pro-<lb break="no"/>vince of Venezuela. Not a single drop of rain had fallen at<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas, or in the country ninety leagues round, during the<lb break="yes"/>five months which preceded the destruction of the capital. The<lb break="yes"/>26th of March was a remarkably hot day. The air was calm,<lb break="yes"/>and the sky unclouded. It was Holy Thursday, and a great<lb break="yes"/>part of the population was assembled in the churches. Nothing<lb break="yes"/>seemed to presage the calamities of the day. At seven minutes<lb break="yes"/>after four in the afternoon the first shock was felt; it was suf-<lb break="no"/>ficiently powerful to make the bells of the churches toll; it<lb break="yes"/>lasted five or six seconds, during which time the ground was in<lb break="yes"/>a continual undulating movement, and seemed to heave up like<lb break="yes"/>a boiling liquid. The danger was thought to be past, when a<lb break="yes"/>tremendous subterraneous noise was heard, resembling the<lb break="yes"/>rolling of thunder, but louder, and of longer continuance, than<lb break="yes"/>that heard within the tropics in time of storms. This noise<lb break="yes"/>preceded a perpendicular motion of three or four seconds, fol-<lb break="no"/>lowed by an undulatory movement somewhat longer. The<lb break="yes"/>shocks were in opposite directions, from north to south, and<lb break="yes"/>from east to west. Nothing could resist the movement from<lb break="yes"/>beneath upward, and undulations crossing each other. The<lb break="yes"/>town of Caraccas was entirely overthrown. Thousands of the<lb break="yes"/>inhabitants (between nine and ten thousand) were buried under<lb break="yes"/>the ruins of the houses and the churches. The procession had<lb break="yes"/>not yet set out; but the crowd was so great in the churches,<lb break="yes"/>that nearly three or four thousand persons were crushed by the<lb break="yes"/>fall of their vaulted roofs. The explosion was stronger toward<lb break="yes"/>the north, in that part of the town situate nearest the mountains<lb break="yes"/>of Avila, and the Silla. The churches of la Trinidad and Alta<lb break="yes"/>Gracia, which were more than 150 feet high, and the naves of<lb break="yes"/>which were supported by pillars of twelve or fifteen feet dia-<lb break="no"/>meter, left a mass of ruins scarcely exceeding five or six feet in<lb break="yes"/>elevation. The sinking of the ruins has been so considerable,<lb break="yes"/>that there now scarcely remain any vestiges of pillars or co-<lb break="no"/>lumns. The barracks, called <hi rendition="#i">El Quartel de San Carlos,</hi> situate<lb break="yes" />farther north of the church of the Trinity, on the road from the<lb break="yes"/>Custom-house de la Pastora, almost entirely disappeared. A<lb break="yes"/>regiment of troops of the line, that was assembled under arms,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="416" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>ready to join the procession, was, with the exception of a few<lb break="yes"/>men, buried under the ruins of this great edifice. Nine tenths<lb break="yes"/>of the fine town of Caraccas was entirely destroyed. The walls<lb break="yes"/>of the houses that were not thrown down, as those of the street<lb break="yes"/>San Juan, near the Capuchin hospital, were cracked in such a<lb break="yes"/>manner, that it was impossible to run the risk of inhabiting<lb break="yes"/>them. The effects of the earthquake were somewhat less vio-<lb break="no"/>lent in the western and southern parts of the city, between the<lb break="yes"/>principal square and the ravine of Caraguata. There the ca-<lb break="no"/>thedral, supported by enormous buttresses, remains standing.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Estimating at nine or ten thousand the number of the dead<lb break="yes"/>in the city of Caraccas, we do not include those unhappy per-<lb break="no"/>sons who, dangerously wounded, perished several months after,<lb break="yes"/>for want of food and proper care. The night of Holy Thursday<lb break="yes"/>presented the most distressing scene of desolation and sorrow.<lb break="yes"/>That thick cloud of dust, which, rising above the ruins, dark-<lb break="no"/>ened the sky like a fog, had settled on the ground. No shock<lb break="yes"/>was felt, and never was a night more calm or more serene.<lb break="yes"/>The moon, nearly full, illumined the rounded domes of the<lb break="yes"/>Silla, and the aspect of the sky formed a perfect contrast to<lb break="yes"/>that of the earth, covered with the dead, and heaped with ruins.<lb break="yes"/>Mothers were seen bearing in their arms their children, whom<lb break="yes"/>they hoped to recall to life. Desolate families wandered through<lb break="yes"/>the city, seeking a brother, a husband, a friend, of whose fate<lb break="yes"/>they were ignorant, and whom they believed to be lost in the<lb break="yes"/>crowd. The people pressed along the streets, which could no<lb break="yes"/>more be recognised but by long lines of ruins.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>All the calamities experienced in the great catastrophes of<lb break="yes" />Lisbon, Messina, Lima, and Riobamba were renewed on the<lb break="yes"/>fatal day of the 26th of March, 1812. &#x201C;The wounded, buried<lb break="yes"/>under the ruins, implored by their cries the help of the<lb break="yes"/>passers-by, and nearly two thousand were dug out. Never was<lb break="yes"/>pity displayed in a more affecting manner; never had it been<lb break="yes"/>seen more ingeniously active, than in the efforts employed to<lb break="yes"/>save the miserable victims, whose groans reached the ear. Im-<lb break="no"/>plements for digging, and clearing away the ruins were entirely<lb break="yes"/>wanting; and the people were obliged to use their bare hands<lb break="yes"/>to disinter the living. The wounded, as well as the sick who<lb break="yes"/>had escaped from the hospitals, were laid on the banks of the<lb break="yes"/>small river Guayra. They found no shelter but the foliage of<lb break="yes"/>trees. Beds, linen to dress the wounds, instruments of surgery,<lb break="yes"/>medicines, and objects of the most urgent necessity, were buried<lb break="yes"/>under the ruins. Everything, even food, was wanting during<lb break="yes"/>the first days. Water became alike scarce in the interior of<lb break="yes"/>the city. The commotion had rent the pipes of the fountains;<lb break="yes"/>the falling in of the earth had choked up the springs that sup-<lb break="no"/>plied them; and it became necessary, in order to have water,<lb break="yes"/>to go down to the river Guayra, which was considerably<lb break="yes"/>swelled; and then vessels to convey the water were wanting.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There remained a duty to be fulfilled toward the dead, en-<lb break="no"/>joined at once by piety, and the dread of infection. It being<lb break="yes" />impossible to inter so many thousand corpses, half-buried<lb break="yes" />under the ruins, commissaries were appointed to burn the<lb break="yes" />bodies; and, for this purpose, funeral piles were erected be-<lb break="no" />tween the heaps of ruins. This ceremony lasted several days.<lb break="yes" />Amid so many public calamities, the people devoted themselves<lb break="yes" />to those religious duties, which they thought were the <choice><sic>mos</sic><corr type="editorial">most</corr></choice> fit-<lb break="no" />ted to appease the wrath of Heaven. Some, assembling in pro-<lb break="no" />cessions, sung funeral hymns; others, in a state of distraction,<lb break="yes"/>confessed themselves aloud in the streets. In this town was<lb break="yes"/>now repeated what had been remarked in the province of Quito,<lb break="yes"/>after the tremendous earthquake of 1797; a number of mar-<lb break="no"/>riages were contracted between persons, who had neglected for<lb break="yes"/>many years to sanction their union by the sacerdotal benedic-<lb break="no"/>tion. Children found parents, by whom they had never till<lb break="yes"/>then been acknowledged; restitutions were promised by per-<lb break="no"/>sons, who had never been accused of fraud: and families, who<lb break="yes"/>had long been enemies, were drawn together by the tie of com-<lb break="no"/>mon calamity.&#x201D; If this feeling seemed to calm the passions of<lb break="yes"/>some, and open the heart to pity, it had a contrary effect on<lb break="yes"/>others, rendering them more rigid and inhuman. In great ca-<lb break="no"/>lamities, vulgar minds preserve still less goodness than strength;<lb break="yes"/>misfortune acts in the same manner, as the pursuits of litera-<lb break="no"/>ture and the study of nature; their happy influence is felt only<lb break="yes"/>by a few, giving more ardour to sentiment, more elevation to<lb break="yes"/>the thoughts, and more benevolence to the disposition.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 