<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="42" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">An Account of the Earthquake in South<lb break="yes" />America, on the</hi> 26<hi rendition="#i">th March,</hi> 1812.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">by the baron de humboldt.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A great drought prevailed at this period in<lb break="yes"/>the province of Venezuela. Not a single drop<lb break="yes"/>of rain had fallen at Caraccas, or in the country<lb break="yes"/>ninety leagues round, during the five months<lb break="yes"/>which preceded the destruction of the capital.<lb break="yes" />The 26th of March was a remarkably hot day.<lb break="yes"/>The air was calm and the sky unclouded. It<lb break="yes"/>was Holy Thursday, and a great part of the po-<lb break="no"/>pulation was assembled in the churches. Nothing<lb break="yes"/>seemed to presage the calamities of the day. At<lb break="yes" />seven minutes after four in the afternoon the<lb break="yes"/>first shock was felt; it was sufficiently power-<lb break="no"/>ful to make the bells of the churches toll; it<lb break="yes"/>lasted five or six seconds, during which time the<lb break="yes"/>ground was in a continual undulating movement,<lb break="yes"/>and seemed to heave up like a boiling liquid.<lb break="yes" />The danger was thought to be past, when a tre-<lb break="no"/>mendous subterraneous noise was heard, re-<lb break="no"/>sembling the rolling of thunder, but louder, and<lb break="yes"/><cb/>of longer continuance, than that heard within<lb break="yes"/>the tropics in time of storms. This noise pre-<lb break="no"/>ceded a perpendicular motion of three or four<lb break="yes" />seconds, followed by an undulatory movement<lb break="yes"/>somewhat longer. The shocks were in oppo-<lb break="no"/>site directions, from north to south, and from<lb break="yes"/>east to west. Nothing could resist the move-<lb break="no"/>ment from beneath upwards, and undulations<lb break="yes" />crossing each other. The town of Caraccas was<lb break="yes"/>entirely overthrown. Thousands of the inha-<lb break="no"/>bitants (between nine and ten thousand) were<lb break="yes"/>buried under the ruins of the houses and<lb break="yes"/>churches. The procession had not yet set out;<lb break="yes" />but the crowd was so great in the churches,<lb break="yes"/>that nearly three or four thousand persons were<lb break="yes"/>crushed by the fall of their vaulted roofs. The<lb break="yes"/>explosion was stronger toward the north, in<lb break="yes"/>that part of the town situate nearest the moun-<lb break="no"/>tain of Avila, and the Silla. The churches of<lb break="yes"/>la Trinidad and Alta Gracia, which were more<lb break="yes"/>than one hundred and fifty feet high, and the<lb break="yes"/>naves of which were supported by pillars of<lb break="yes"/>twelve or fifteen feet diameter, left a mass of<lb break="yes"/>ruins scarcely exceeding five or six feet in ele-<lb break="no" />vation. The sinking of the ruins has been so<lb break="yes"/>considerable, that there now scarcely remain<lb break="yes"/>any vestiges of pillars or columns. The bar-<lb break="no"/>racks, called <hi rendition="#i">El Quartel de San Carlos,</hi> situate<lb break="yes"/>farther north of the church of the Trinity, on<lb break="yes"/>the road from the Custom-house de la Pastora,<lb break="yes"/>almost entirely disappeared. A regiment of<lb break="yes" />troops of the line, that was assembled under<lb break="yes"/>arms, ready to join the procession, was, with<lb break="yes"/>the exception of a few men, buried under the<lb break="yes"/>ruins of this great edifice. Nine-tenths of the<lb break="yes"/>fine town of Caraccas was entirely destroyed.<lb break="yes"/>The walls of the houses that were not thrown<lb break="yes" />down, as those of the street San Juan, near the<lb break="yes"/>Capuchin Hospital, were cracked in such a<lb break="yes"/>manner, that it was impossible to run the risk<lb break="yes"/>of inhabiting them. The effects of the earth-<lb break="no"/>quake were somewhat less violent in the western<lb break="yes" />and southern parts of the city, between the<lb break="yes"/>principal square and the ravin of Caraguata.<lb break="yes"/>There, the cathedral, supported by enormous<lb break="yes"/>buttresses, remains standing.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Estimating at nine or ten thousand the num-<lb break="no"/>ber of the dead in the city of Caraccas, we do<lb break="yes"/>not include those unhappy persons, who, danger-<lb break="no"/>ously wounded, perished several months after,<lb break="yes"/>for want of food and proper care. The night<lb break="yes"/>of Holy Thursday presented the most distress-<lb break="no"/>ing scene of desolation and sorrow. That thick<lb break="yes"/>cloud of dust, which, rising above the ruins,<lb break="yes"/>darkened the sky like a fog, had settled on the<lb break="yes"/>ground. No shock was felt, and never was a<lb break="yes"/>night more calm, or more serene. The moon,<lb break="yes" />nearly full, illumined the rounded domes of the<lb break="yes"/>Silla, and the aspect of the sky formed a per-<lb break="no"/>fect contrast to that of the earth, covered with<lb break="yes"/>the dead, and heaped with ruins. Mothers<lb break="yes"/>were seen bearing in their arms their children,<lb break="yes" />whom they hoped to recal to life. Desolate<lb break="yes"/>families wandered through the city seeking a<lb break="yes"/>brother, a husband, a friend, of whose fate they<lb break="yes"/>were ignorant, and whom they believed to be<lb break="yes" />lost in the crowd. The people pressed along<lb break="yes"/>the streets, which could no more be recognised<lb break="yes"/>but by long lines of ruins.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>All the calamities experienced in the great<lb break="yes"/>catastrophes of Lisbon, Messina, Lima, and Rio-,<lb break="yes"/>bamba were renewed on the fatal day of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="43" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>26th March, 1812. The wounded, buried under<lb break="yes"/>the ruins, implored by their cries the help of<lb break="yes"/>the passers by, and nearly two thousand were<lb break="yes"/>dug out. Never was pity displayed in a more<lb break="yes"/>affecting manner; never had it been seen more<lb break="yes" />ingeniously active, than in the efforts employed<lb break="yes"/>to save the miserable victims, whose groans<lb break="yes"/>reached the ear. Implements for digging and<lb break="yes"/>clearing away the ruins, were entirely wanting;<lb break="yes"/>and the people were obliged to use their bare<lb break="yes" />hands, to disinter the living. The wounded, as<lb break="yes"/>well as the sick who had escaped from the hos-<lb break="no"/>pitals, were laid on the banks of the small river<lb break="yes"/>Guayra. They found no shelter but the foliage<lb break="yes"/>of trees. Beds, linen to dress the wounds, in-<lb break="no"/>struments of surgery, medicines, and objects of<lb break="yes" />the most urgent necessity, were buried under<lb break="yes"/>the ruins. Every thing, even food, was wanting<lb break="yes"/>during the first days. Water became alike<lb break="yes"/>scarce in the interior of the city. The commo-<lb break="no"/>tion had rent the pipes of the fountains; the<lb break="yes" />falling in of the earth had choked up the<lb break="yes"/>springs that supplied them; and it became ne-<lb break="no"/>cessary, in order to have water, to go down to<lb break="yes"/>the river Guayra, which was considerably swell-<lb break="no"/>ed; and then vessels to convey the water were<lb break="yes" />wanting.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There remained a duty to be fulfilled toward<lb break="yes"/>the dead, enjoined at once by piety, and the<lb break="yes"/>dread of infection. It being impossible to inter<lb break="yes"/>so many thousand corpses, half buried under<lb break="yes"/>the ruins, commissaries were appointed to burn<lb break="yes"/>the bodies: and for this purpose funeral piles<lb break="yes" />were erected between the heaps of ruins. This<lb break="yes"/>ceremony lasted several days. Amid so many<lb break="yes"/>public calamities, the people devoted them-<lb break="no"/>selves to those religious duties which they<lb break="yes"/>thought were most fitted to appease the wrath<lb break="yes" />of Heaven. Some, assembling in processions,<lb break="yes"/>sung funeral hymns; others, in a state of dis-<lb break="no"/>traction, confessed themselves aloud in the<lb break="yes"/>streets. In this town was now repeated what<lb break="yes"/>had been remarked in the province of Quito,<lb break="yes" />after the tremendous earthquake of 1797; a<lb break="yes"/>number of marriages were contracted between<lb break="yes"/>persons, who had neglected for many years to<lb break="yes"/>sanction their union by the sacerdotal benedic-<lb break="no"/>tion. Children found parents, by whom they<lb break="yes"/>had never till then been acknowledged; restitu-<lb break="no"/>tions were promised by persons who had never<lb break="yes"/>been accused of fraud; and families, who had<lb break="yes"/>long been enemies, were drawn together by the<lb break="yes"/>tie of common calamity.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 