<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="27" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">from humboldt&#x2019;s personal narrative.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">The Coffee Plant.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The coffee tree flowers only the<lb break="yes"/>second year, and the flowering lasts<lb break="yes"/>only twenty-four hours. At this time<lb break="yes" />the shrub has a charming aspect;<lb break="yes"/>seen from afar, it seems covered with<lb break="yes"/>snow. The produce of the third year<lb break="yes" />becomes very abundant. In planta-<lb break="no"/>tions well weeded and watered, and<lb break="yes"/>recently cultivated, we find trees<lb break="yes" />bearing sixteen, eighteen, and even<lb break="yes"/>twenty pounds of coffee. In general,<lb break="yes"/>however, a produce of more than a<lb break="yes" />pound and a half or two pounds can-<lb break="no"/>not be expected from each plant; and<lb break="yes"/>even this is superior to the mean pro-<lb break="no" />duce of the West India Islands.<lb break="yes"/>Rains at the time of the flowering,<lb break="yes"/>the want of water for artificial irri-<lb break="no"/>gations, and a <choice><sic>patastic</sic><corr type="editorial">parasitic</corr></choice> plant, a new<lb break="yes"/>species of coranthus, which clings to<lb break="yes"/>the branches, are extremely injurious<lb break="yes"/>to the coffee trees.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Sugar Cane.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Three species of sugar cane can<lb break="yes"/>be distinguished even at a distance,<lb break="yes"/>by the colour of their leaves; the<lb break="yes" />ancient Creole sugar cane, the Ota-<lb break="no"/>heite cane, and the Batavia cane.<lb break="yes"/>The first has a leaf of a deeper green,<lb break="yes" />the stem less thick, and the knots<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="28" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>nearer together.&#x2014;This sugar cane<lb break="yes"/>was the first introduced from India<lb break="yes"/>into Sicily, the Canary Islands and<lb break="yes"/>the West Indies. The second is of<lb break="yes"/>a lighter green; and its stem is high-<lb break="no"/>er, thicker, and more succulent. The<lb break="yes"/>whole plant displays a more luxuri-<lb break="no"/>ant vegetation. We owe this plant<lb break="yes"/>to the voyages of Bougainville, Cook,<lb break="yes"/>and Bligh. Bougainville carried it<lb break="yes"/>to the Isle of France, whence it pass-<lb break="no"/>ed to Cayenne, Martinique, and since<lb break="yes"/>1792, to the rest of the West India<lb break="yes" />Islands. The sugar cane of Otahe-<lb break="no"/>ite, the <hi rendition="#i" >To</hi> of those islanders, is one<lb break="yes"/>of the most important acquisitions,<lb break="yes"/>for which colonial agriculture is in-<lb break="no"/>debted to the travels of naturalists.<lb break="yes"/>It yields not only one third more of<lb break="yes"/>juice than the Creolian cane on the<lb break="yes"/>same space of land; but from the<lb break="yes" />thickness of its stem, and the tenaci-<lb break="no"/>ty of its ligneous fibres, it furnishes<lb break="yes"/>much more fuel. The last advantage<lb break="yes"/>is important to the West Indies,<lb break="yes"/>where the destruction of the forests<lb break="yes"/>has for a long time obliged the plant-<lb break="no"/>ers to use the canes deprived of their<lb break="yes" />juice, to keep up the fire under their<lb break="yes"/>boilers.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But from the knowledge of this<lb break="yes"/>new plant, the progress of <choice>
                        <sic>agri<lb break="no"/>culture</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">agri-<lb break="no"/>culture</corr>
                    </choice> on the continent of Spanish<lb break="yes"/>America, and the introduction of the<lb break="yes"/>East India and Java sugars, the revo-<lb break="no"/>lutions of St. Domingo, and the de-<lb break="no"/>struction of the great sugar planta-<lb break="no"/>tions of that island, would have had<lb break="yes"/>a more sensible effect on the prices<lb break="yes"/>of colonial produce in Europe. The<lb break="yes"/>Otaheite sugar cane was carried from<lb break="yes"/>the Isle of Trinidad to Caraccas.<lb break="yes"/>From Caraccas it passed to Cicuta<lb break="yes"/>and San Gil in the kingdom of New<lb break="yes"/>Grenada. In our days its cultivation<lb break="yes" />during twenty-five years almost <choice>
                        <sic>en<lb break="no"/>tirely</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">en-<lb break="no"/>tirely</corr>
                    </choice> removed the apprehension,<lb break="yes"/>which was at first entirely entertain-<lb break="no"/>ed, that, transplanted to America,<lb break="yes" />the plant would by degrees degene-<lb break="no"/>rate, and become as slender as the<lb break="yes"/>Creole cane. If it be a variety, it is<lb break="yes"/>a very constant one. The third spe-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/>cies, the violet sugar cane, called <hi rendition="#i">Ca-<lb break="no" />na de Batavia,</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">de Guinea,</hi> is entire-<lb break="no"/>ly indigenous in the island of Java,<lb break="yes"/>where it is cultivated in preference in<lb break="yes"/>the districts of Jupara and Pasuruan.<lb break="yes"/>Its foliage is purple, and very broad;<lb break="yes"/>and it is preferred in the province of<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas for rum. The <hi rendition="#i">tablones,</hi> or<lb break="yes"/>grounds planted with sugar canes, are<lb break="yes"/>divided by hedges of a collossal gra-<lb break="no"/>men; the latta, or gynesium with dis-<lb break="no" />tich leaves.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">American Fig Tree.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The trunks of these trees are co-<lb break="no"/>vered with very odoriferous plants of<lb break="yes"/>vanilla, which, in general, flower only<lb break="yes" />in the month of April.&#x2014;We were<lb break="yes"/>here again struck with those ligne-<lb break="no"/>ous excrescenses, which in the form<lb break="yes" />of ridges, or ribs augment, in so ex-<lb break="no"/>traordinary a manner, and as far as<lb break="yes"/>twenty feet above the ground, the<lb break="yes" />thickness of the trunk of the fig trees<lb break="yes"/>of America. I found trees twenty-<lb break="no"/>two feet and a half in diameter near<lb break="yes" />the roots.&#x2014;These ligneous ridges<lb break="yes"/>sometimes separate from the trunk<lb break="yes"/>at a height of eight feet, and are<lb break="yes" />transformed into cylindrical roots two<lb break="yes"/>feet thick. The tree looks as if it<lb break="yes"/>were supported by buttresses. This<lb break="yes" />scaffolding, however, does not pene-<lb break="no"/>trate very deep into the earth. The<lb break="yes"/>lateral roots wind at the surface of the<lb break="yes"/>ground, and when at twenty feet dis-<lb break="no"/>tance from the trunk, they are cut<lb break="yes"/>with the hatchet, we see the milky<lb break="yes"/>juice of the fig tree gush out, which,<lb break="yes"/>when deprived of the vital influence<lb break="yes"/>of the organs of the tree, is altered<lb break="yes"/>and coagulates. What a wonderful<lb break="yes" />combination of cells and vessels exist<lb break="yes"/>in these vegetable masses; in these<lb break="yes"/>gigantic trees of the torrid zone,<lb break="yes"/>which, without interruption, perhaps<lb break="yes"/>during a thousand years, prepare nu-<lb break="no"/>tritious fluids, raise them to the height<lb break="yes"/>of 180 feet, convey them down again<lb break="yes" />to the ground, and conceal beneath<lb break="yes"/>a rough and hard bark, under the<lb break="yes"/>inanimate layers of ligneous matter,<lb break="yes" />all the movements of organic life!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="29" facs="#f0003"/>
                <cb/>
            </div>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">The Cow Tree.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Amid the great number of curi-<lb break="no"/>ous phenomena which have present-<lb break="no"/>ed themselves to me in the course of<lb break="yes" />my travels, I confess there are few<lb break="yes"/>that have so powerfully affected my<lb break="yes"/>imagination, as the aspect of the cow<lb break="yes" />tree.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Whatever relates to milk, what-<lb break="no"/>ever regards corn, inspires an inter-<lb break="no"/>est, which is not merely that of the<lb break="yes"/>physical knowledge of things, but<lb break="yes"/>is connected with another order of<lb break="yes"/>ideas and sentiments. We can scarce-<lb break="no"/>ly conceive how the human race<lb break="yes"/>could exist without farinaceous sub-<lb break="no"/>stances, and without that nourishing<lb break="yes"/>juice which the breast of the mo-<lb break="no"/>ther contains, and which is appro-<lb break="no"/>priated to the long feebleness of the<lb break="yes"/>infant. The amylaceous matter of<lb break="yes"/>corn, the object of religious venera-<lb break="no"/>tion among so many nations, ancient<lb break="yes"/>and modern, is diffused in the seeds<lb break="yes" />and deposited in the roots of vegeta-<lb break="no"/>bles; milk, which serves us as an<lb break="yes"/>aliment, appears to us exclusively the<lb break="yes" />produce of animal organization.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Such are the impressions we have<lb break="yes"/>received in our earliest infancy; such<lb break="yes"/>is also the source of that astonish-<lb break="no"/>ment which seizes us at the aspect<lb break="yes"/>of the tree just described. It <choice><sic>has</sic><corr type="editorial">is</corr></choice> not<lb break="yes"/>here the solemn shades of forests,<lb break="yes"/>the majestic course of rivers, the<lb break="yes"/>mountains wrapped in eternal frosts,<lb break="yes"/>that excite our emotion.&#x2014;A few<lb break="yes" />drops of vegetable juice recal to our<lb break="yes"/>minds all the powerfulness and fecun-<lb break="no"/>dity of nature. On the barren flank<lb break="yes"/>of rock grows a tree with coriaceous<lb break="yes"/>and dry leaves. Its large woody roots<lb break="yes"/>can scarcely penetrate into the stone.<lb break="yes"/>For several months of the year not a<lb break="yes" />single shower moistens its foliage. Its<lb break="yes"/>branches appear dead and dried; but<lb break="yes"/>when its trunk is pierced, there flows<lb break="yes"/>from it a sweet and nourishing milk.<lb break="yes"/>It is at the rising of the sun that this<lb break="yes"/>vegetable fountain is most abundant.<lb break="yes"/>The blacks and natives are then seen<lb break="yes"/>hastening from all quarters, furnish-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/>ed with large bowls to receive the<lb break="yes"/>milk, which grows yellow, and thick-<lb break="no"/>ens at its surface. Some employ<lb break="yes" />their bowls under the tree itself,<lb break="yes"/>others carry the juice home to their<lb break="yes"/>children. We seem to see the fami-<lb break="no"/>ly of a shepherd, who distributes the<lb break="yes"/>milk to his flock.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;I have described the sensation<lb break="yes"/>which the cow tree awakens in the<lb break="yes"/>mind of the traveller, at the first<lb break="yes"/>view. In examining the physical pro-<lb break="no"/>perties of animal and vegetable pro-<lb break="no"/>ducts, science displays them as close-<lb break="no"/>ly linked together; but it strips them<lb break="yes"/>of what is marvellous, and perhaps<lb break="yes"/>also a part of their charms, of what<lb break="yes" />excited our astonishment.&#x2014;Nothing<lb break="yes"/>appears <choice><sic>insolated;</sic><corr type="editorial">isolated;</corr></choice> the chemical prin-<lb break="no"/>ciples that were believed to be pecu-<lb break="no"/>liar to animals are found in plants;<lb break="yes"/>a common chain links together all or-<lb break="no"/>ganic nature.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 