<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#k">From Humboldt&#x2019;s Personal Narrative,<lb break="yes"/>Volume IV.</hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">THE COFFEE PLANT.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The coffee tree flowers only the second<lb break="yes"/>year, and the flowering lasts only twenty-four<lb break="yes"/>hours. At this time the shrub has a charming<lb break="yes"/>aspect; seen from afar, it seems covered with<lb break="yes"/>snow. The produce of the third year becomes<lb break="yes" />very abundant. In plantations well weeded<lb break="yes"/>and watered, and recently cultivated, we find<lb break="yes"/>trees bearing sixteen, eighteen, and even<lb break="yes"/>twenty weight of coffee. In general, however,<lb break="yes"/>a produce of more than a pound and an half<lb break="yes"/>or two pounds cannot be expected from each<lb break="yes"/>plant; and even this is superiour to the mean<lb break="yes"/>produce of the West-India Islands. Rains at<lb break="yes"/>the time of the flowering, the want of water for<lb break="yes"/>artificial irrigations, and a parasitick plant, a<lb break="yes"/>new species of Coranthus, which clings to the<lb break="yes" />branches, are extremely injurious to the cof-<lb break="no"/>fee trees. When, in the plantations of eighty<lb break="yes"/>or a hundred thousand shrubs, we consider<lb break="yes"/>the immense quantity of organic matter con-<lb break="no"/>tained in the pulpy berry of the coffee tree,<lb break="yes"/>we may be astonished that no attempts have<lb break="yes"/>been made to extract a spiritous liquor from<lb break="yes"/>them.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#i">SUGAR-CANES.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Three species of sugar-cane can be distin-<lb break="no"/>guished even at a distance, by the colour of<lb break="yes"/>their leaves; the ancient Creole sugar-cane,<lb break="yes"/>the Otaheite cane, and the Batavin cane.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>The first has a leaf of a deeper green, the<lb break="yes"/>stem less thick, and the knots nearer together.<lb break="yes"/>This sugar-cane was the first introduced from<lb break="yes"/>India into Sicily, the Canary Islands, and the<lb break="yes"/>West-Indies. The second is of a lighter green<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;and its stem is higher, thicker, and more<lb break="yes"/>succulent. The whole plant displays a more<lb break="yes" />luxuriant vegetation. We owe this plant to<lb break="yes"/>the voyages of Bougainville, Cook and Bligh.<lb break="yes"/>Bougainville carried it to the Isle of France,<lb break="yes"/>whence it passed to Cayenne, Martinique, and<lb break="yes"/>1702, to the rest of the West-India Islands.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/><cb/>The sugar-cane of Otaheite, the <hi rendition="#i">To</hi> of those<lb break="yes"/>islanders, is one of the most important acqui-<lb break="no"/>sitions, for which colonial agriculture is in-<lb break="no"/>debted to the travels of naturalists. It yields<lb break="yes"/>not only a third more of juice than the Creol-<lb break="no"/>ian cane on the same space of land; but<lb break="yes"/>from the thickness of its stem, and the tenacity<lb break="yes"/>of its ligneous fibres, it furnishes much more<lb break="yes"/>fuel. The last advantage is important to the<lb break="yes"/>West-Indies, where the destruction of the for-<lb break="no"/>ests has for a long time obliged the planters<lb break="yes"/>to use the canes deprived of their juice, to<lb break="yes" />keep up the fire under their boilers. But<lb break="yes"/>for the knowledge of this new plant, the<lb break="yes"/>progress of agriculture on the continent of<lb break="yes"/>Spanish America, and the introduction of the<lb break="yes"/>East-India and Java sugars, the revolutions of<lb break="yes"/>St. Domingo, and the destruction of the great<lb break="yes"/>sugar plantations of that Island, would have<lb break="yes" />had a more sensible effect on the prices of co-<lb break="no"/>lonial produce in Europe. The Otaheite su-<lb break="no"/>gar-cane was carried from the Island of Trini-<lb break="no"/>dad to Caraccas. From Caraccas it passed to<lb break="yes"/>Cicuta and San Gil in the kingdom of New-<lb break="no"/>Grenada. In our days its cultivation during<lb break="yes" />twenty-five years has almost entirely removed<lb break="yes"/>the apprehension which was at first entertain-<lb break="no"/>ed, that, transplanted to America, the plant by<lb break="yes"/>degrees would degenerate, and become as<lb break="yes"/>slender as the Creole cane. If it be a va-<lb break="no"/>riety, it is a very constant one. The third<lb break="yes"/>species, the violet sugar-cane, called <hi rendition="#i" >Cana de<lb break="yes"/>Batavia,</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">de Guinea,</hi> is entirely indigenous<lb break="yes"/>in the island of Java, where it is cultivated in<lb break="yes"/>preference in the districts of Japara and Pasu-<lb break="no"/>ruan. Its foliage is purple, and very broad;<lb break="yes"/>and it is preferred in the province of Caraccas<lb break="yes"/>for rum. The <hi rendition="#i">tablones,</hi> or grounds planted<lb break="yes"/>with sugar-canes, are divided by hedges of a<lb break="yes"/>colossal gramen; the latta, or gynesium, with<lb break="yes"/>distich leaves.</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#i">AMERICAN FIG TREES.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The trunks of these trees are covered with<lb break="yes"/>very odoriferous plants of vanilla, which in<lb break="yes"/>general flower only in the month of April&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>We were here again struck with those ligne-<lb break="no"/>ous excrescences, which, in the form of ridges,<lb break="yes"/>or ribs, augment, in so extraordinary a man-<lb break="no" />ner, and as far as twenty feet above the ground,<lb break="yes"/>the thickness of the trunk, of the fig trees of<lb break="yes"/>America. I found trees twenty-two feet and<lb break="yes"/>a half in diameter near the roots. These lig-<lb break="no"/>neous ridges sometimes separate from the<lb break="yes"/>trunk at a height of eight feet, and are trans-<lb break="no"/>formed into cylindrical roots, two feet thick.<lb break="yes"/>The tree looks as if it were supported by but-<lb break="no"/>tresses. This scaffolding, however, does not<lb break="yes" />penetrate very deep into the earth. The lat-<lb break="no"/>eral roots wind at the surface of the ground,<lb break="yes"/>and when at twenty feet distance from the<lb break="yes"/>trunk they are cut with the hatchet, we see<lb break="yes"/>the milky juice of the fig tree gush out, which,<lb break="yes"/>when deprived of the vital influence of the<lb break="yes" />organs of the tree, is altered and coagulates.<lb break="yes"/>What a wonderful combination of cells and<lb break="yes"/>vessels exist in these vegetable masses, in<lb break="yes"/>these gigantick trees of the torrid zone, which,<lb break="yes"/>without interruption, perhaps during a thou-<lb break="no"/>sand years, prepare nutritious fluids, raise<lb break="yes" />them to the height of 180 feet, convey them<lb break="yes"/>down again to the ground, and conceal be-<lb break="no"/>neath a rough and hard bark, under the inan-<lb break="no"/>imate layers of ligneous matter, all the move-<lb break="no"/>ments of organick life!</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 