<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><body><pb n="2" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#b">The Gymnotus, or Electrical Eel.</hi></head><lb/><p>Several species of fish, particularly the ray, are<lb/>known to possess the power of giving, at will,<lb/>electrical shocks, of greater or less intensity.&#x2014;<lb/>The <hi rendition="#i">Gymnotus,</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">Electrical Eel,</hi> that has this<lb/>power in the highest degree, abounds in many of<lb/>the rivers of tropical South America, especially in<lb/>the Oroonoke, the Amazon and the rivers of<lb/>Dutch Guiana, whence most of the specimens<lb/>that have been seen in this country and Europe<lb/>have been procured. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt,</hi> in the personal<lb/><choice><sic>narative</sic><corr type="editorial">narrative</corr></choice> of his travels in the Equinoctial regions<lb/>of this continent during the years 1799 and 1804,<lb/>gives a very minute account of experiments he<lb/>made with electrical eels he obtained at Calabozo,<lb/>a small town in the <hi rendition="#i">Llanos,</hi> or Plains of Venezu-<lb/>la, that border the Oroonoko. The basins of stag-<lb/>nant water in that vicinity were full of the eels,<lb/>but the natives have so great a dread of their<lb/>shocks that they were very reluctant to catch<lb/>them, and as for catching them with nets, that<lb/>was almost impossible, on account of the extreme<lb/>agility of the fish, which bury themselves in the<lb/>mud like serpents. The travelers were unwilling<lb/>to employ any intoxicating drugs, that are some-<lb/>times used in taking fish, as the eels would there-<lb/>by be benumbed and lose much of their electri-<lb/>cal power. The Indians professed to believe that<lb/>the eels could be handled with impunity by a<lb/>person chewing tobacco, but their faith was not<lb/>strong enough to induce them to subject it to a<lb/>practical test. The enterprising travelers were,<lb/>however, determined to get some of the eels, and<lb/>finally the Indians told them that they would &#x201C;fish<lb/>with horses.&#x201D; &#x201C;We found it difficult,&#x201D; says<lb/><hi rendition="#k">Humboldt,</hi> &#x201C;to form an idea of this extraordinary<lb/>manner of fishing; but we soon saw our guides<lb/>return from the Savannah, which they had been<lb/>scouring for wild horses and mules.&#x201D; About thirty<lb/>of these animals were forced to enter the pool,<lb/>and the scene that ensued is thus described:</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;The extraordinary noise caused by the horses&#x2019;<lb/>hoofs makes the fish issue from the mud, and ex-<lb/>cites them to combat. These yellowish and livid<lb/>eels, resembling large aquatic serpents, swim on the<lb/>surface of the water, and crowd under the bellies of<lb/>the horses and mules. A contest between animals<lb/>of so different an organization furnishes a very strik-<lb/>ing spectacle. The Indians, provided with har-<lb/>poons and long slender reeds, surrounded the pool<lb/>closely, and soon climb upon the trees, the branches<lb/>of which extend horizontally over the surface of the<lb/>water. By their wild cries, and the length of their<lb/>reeds, they prevent the horses from running away,<lb/>and reaching the bank of the pool. The eels, stunn-<lb/>ed by the noise, defend themselves by the repeated<lb/>discharge of their batteries. During a long time<lb/>they seem to prove victorious. Several horses sink<lb/>beneath the violence of the invisible strokes, which<lb/>they receive from all sides in organs the most es-<lb/>sential to life, and stunned by the force and fre-<lb/>quency of the shocks, disappear under the water.&#x2014;<lb/>Others panting, with mane erect, and haggard eyes,<lb/>expressing anguish, raise themselves, and endeavor<lb/>to flee from the storm by which they are overtaken.<lb/>They are driven back by the Indians into the mid-<lb/>dle of the water but a small number succeed in<lb/>eluding the active vigilence of the fishermen. These<lb/>regain the shore, stumbling at every step, and<lb/>stretch themselves on the sand, exhausted with fa-<lb/>tigue, and their limbs benumbed by the electric<lb/>shocks of the Gymnoti.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;In less than five minutes two horses were<lb/>drowned. The eel, being five feet long, and press-<lb/>ing itself against the belly of the horses; makes a<lb/>discharge along the whole extent of its electric or-<lb/>gan. It attacks at once the heart, the intestines,<lb/>and the <hi rendition="#i">plexus c&#x0153;liacus</hi> of the abdominal <choice><sic>neves.</sic><corr type="editorial">nerves.</corr></choice> It<lb/>is natural, that the effect felt by the horses should<lb/>be more powerful, than that produced upon man<lb/>by the touch of the same fish at only one of his<lb/>extremities. The horses are probably not killed,<lb/>but stunned. They are drowned from the impossi-<lb/>bility of rising amid the prolonged struggle between<lb/>the other horses and the eels.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;We had little doubt that the fishing would ter-<lb/>minate by killing successively all the animals en-<lb/>gaged, but by degrees the impetuosity of this une-<lb/>qual combat diminished, and the wearied Gymnoti<lb/>dispersed. They require a long rest, and abundant<lb/>nourishment, to repair what they have lost of gal-<lb/>vanic force. The mules and horses appear less<lb/>frightened, their manes are no longer bristled, and<lb/>their eyes express less dread. The Gymnoti ap-<lb/>proach timidly the edge of the marsh, where they<lb/>are taken by means of small harpoons fastened to<lb/>long cords. In a few minutes we had five large eels,<lb/>the greater part of which were but slightly wounded.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>The temperature of the water in which these<lb/>eels live is about 80&#x00B0;. Their electric force di-<lb/>minishes, it is said, in colder waters, though they<lb/>will live in such. They are the longest of the<lb/>electrical fishes. Some of those obtained at<lb/>Calabozo measured five feet three inches in length,<lb/>and were three inches and a half through. Their<lb/>skin is constantly covered with a mucous matter,<lb/>which, as <hi rendition="#k">Volta</hi> has proved, conducts electricity<lb/>twenty or thirty times better than pure water.&#x2014;<lb/>No electrical fish yet discovered has scales. The<lb/>Gymnoti are fond of breathing air on the surface<lb/>of the water, but, unlike the common eels which<lb/>often wander a part of the night on the grass, soon<lb/>die if thrown upon the ground. Their brain,<lb/>electrical organs and muscles, are supplied with<lb/>an extraordinary amount of arterial blood. It is<lb/>dangerous to expose one&#x2019;s self to the first shocks of<lb/>a very large and strongly irritated gymnotus.<lb/><hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi> says he does not remember having<lb/>ever received from the discharge of a large Leyden<lb/>jar, a more dreadful shock, than he experienced<lb/>by imprudently placing both his feet on a gymnotus<lb/>just taken out of the water. He was affected the<lb/>rest of the day with a violent pain in the knees,<lb/>and in almost every joint. In Dutch Guiana<lb/>electrical eels were formerly employed to cure the<lb/>paralytic, as in old times, among the Greeks, the<lb/>torpedo, with a much less electrical power, was<lb/>used for the same purpose. Gymnoti are neither<lb/>charged conductors, nor batteries, nor electro-<lb/>motive apparatuses, the shock of which is re-<lb/>ceived every time they are touched. The electric<lb/>action of the fish depends entirely on its will,<lb/>sometimes suffering itself to be handled gently<lb/>without giving any indication of its peculiar<lb/>powers, and at others discharging its batteries on<lb/>the least touch. It has the power also of acting<lb/>toward the point of greatest irritation. For in-<lb/>stance two persons may have hold of the same<lb/>fish, and one by pressing too hard may receive a<lb/>severe shock, while the other experiences no<lb/>sensation. A still more remarkable power it<lb/>possesses is that of darting and directing its stroke<lb/>against an object at some distance from it. In<lb/>this way it often kills small fish. Although usual-<lb/>ly very prompt to resent any irritation by exerting<lb/>its electrical powers, it will sometimes struggle<lb/>violently with a person holding it by the tail with-<lb/>out communicating any shock. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi> made<lb/>a slight incision in one, near the pectoral fin, and<lb/>galvanized the wound by the contact of two pieces<lb/>of zinc and silver. The gymnotus bent itself con-<lb/>vulsively, and raised its head out of water, as if<lb/>affrighted by a sensation altogether new, but no<lb/>vibration was felt in the hands which held the<lb/>metals.</p><lb/><p>The gymnoti are called electrical eels, and pro-<lb/>bably with propriety, but the electrical power they<lb/>possess differs some what from common electricity.<lb/>Resinous substances, very dry wood, horn, bones,<lb/>&#x0026;c., generally believed to be good conductors,<lb/>prevent the action of the gymnoti from being<lb/>transmitted to man. When a chain is formed by<lb/>several persons holding each others&#x2019; hands, and<lb/>one of them touches the fish, the shock is some-<lb/>times felt by all simultaneously, while it some-<lb/>times happens that the shock, even when most<lb/>severe, is felt alone by the person in immediate<lb/>contact with the fish. The belief is popularly<lb/>entertained that the gymnoti are involuntarily at-<lb/>tracted by the loadstone, and some very respec-<lb/>table scientific authority can be cited in support of<lb/>this belief. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi> says he tried in a thousand<lb/>ways this pretended influence of the magnet on<lb/>the electrical organs, without having ever observ-<lb/>ed any sensible effect. Iron fillings thrown on the<lb/>back of the fish remained motionless. The flesh<lb/>of the fish is sometimes eaten, but it is not much<lb/>esteemed. Wherever the gymnoti abound, they<lb/>are considered great nuisances. They kill many<lb/>more fish than they devour, and all the inhabitants<lb/>of the water, such as lizards, tortoises, and frogs,<lb/>dread their society, and will, if possible, avoid<lb/>their companionship by seeking other pools.&#x2014;<lb/>They are even capable of disabling young alli-<lb/>gators. In one river near Uritucu it became<lb/>necessary to change the direction of a road, be-<lb/>cause the eels were so numerous that every year<lb/>they killed a great number of mules of burden as<lb/>they forded the water.</p></div><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>

</body></text>
</TEI>
