<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Baron Humboldt’s Last Volume. Extract from Baron Humboldt’s Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent. Vol. 4</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:54</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.60</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1819-Baron_Humboldts_Extract_Heft2-1-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>&lt;i&gt;Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of America&lt;/i&gt;, Bd. 2, übersetzt von Thomasina Ross, 1851, ab S. 174.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 2, S. 231–236.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Baron Humboldt’s Last Volume. Extract from Baron Humboldt’s Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent. Vol. 4</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1819</date>
          <pubPlace>New York City, New York</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Belles-Lettres Repository, and Monthly Magazine&lt;/i&gt; 1:2 (1. Juni 1819), S. 138–142.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="138" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>BARON HUMBOLDT’S LAST VOLUME.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Extract from Baron Humboldt’s Personal<lb break="yes" />Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial<lb break="yes"/>Regions of the New Continent. Vol.</hi> 4.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On leaving the Rio Apure, we<lb break="yes"/>found ourselves in a country of a to-<lb break="no"/>tally different aspect. An immense<lb break="yes"/>plain of water stretched before us<lb break="yes"/>like a lake, as far as we could see.<lb break="yes"/>White-topped waves rose to the<lb break="yes"/>height of several feet, from the con-<lb break="no"/>flict of the breeze and the current.<lb break="yes"/>The air resounded no longer with<lb break="yes" />the piercing cries of the herons, the<lb break="yes"/>flamingoes, and the spoonbills, cross-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/> ing in long files from one shore to<lb break="yes"/>the other. Our eyes sought in vain<lb break="yes"/>those water fowls, the inventive<lb break="yes" />snares of which vary in each tribe.<lb break="yes"/>All nature appears less animated.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Scarcely could we discover in the<lb break="yes"/>hollows of the waves a few large<lb break="yes"/>crocodiles, cutting obliquely, by the<lb break="yes"/>help of their long tails, the surface<lb break="yes"/>of the agitated waters. The hori-<lb break="no"/>zon was bounded by a zone of fo-<lb break="no"/>rests, but these forests no where<lb break="yes"/>reached so far as the bed of the ri-<lb break="no"/>ver. A vast beach, constantly parch-<lb break="no"/>ed by the heat of the sun, desert<lb break="yes"/>and bare as the shores of the sea,<lb break="yes"/>resembled, at a distance, from the<lb break="yes"/>effect of the <hi rendition="#i" >mirage,</hi> pools of stag-<lb break="no"/>nant water. These sandy shores,<lb break="yes"/>far from fixing the limits of the ri-<lb break="no" />ver, rendered them uncertain, by<lb break="yes"/>approaching or withdrawing them<lb break="yes"/>alternately, according to the varia-<lb break="no"/>ble action of the inflected rays.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In these scattered features of the<lb break="yes"/>landscape, in this character of so-<lb break="no"/>litude and of greatness, we recog-<lb break="no"/>nize the course of the Oroonoko,<lb break="yes"/>one of the most majestic rivers of<lb break="yes"/>the New World. The water, like<lb break="yes"/>the land, displays every where a<lb break="yes"/>characteristic and peculiar aspect.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>The bed of the Oroonoko resembles<lb break="yes"/>not the bed of the Meta, the Gua-<lb break="no"/>viare, the Rio Negro, or the Amazon.<lb break="yes"/>These differences do not depend al-<lb break="no"/>together on the breadth or the veloci-<lb break="no"/>ty of the current: they are connect-<lb break="no"/>ed with a multitude of impressions,<lb break="yes"/>which it is easier to perceive upon<lb break="yes"/>the spot, than to define with preci-<lb break="no"/>sion. Thus the mere form of the<lb break="yes"/>waves, the tint of the waters, the<lb break="yes"/>aspect of the sky and the clouds,<lb break="yes"/>would lead an experienced navigator<lb break="yes"/>to guess, whether he were in the At-<lb break="no"/>lantic, in the Mediterranean, or in the<lb break="yes"/>equinoctial part of the Great Ocean.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The wind blew fresh from east-<lb break="no"/>northeast. Its direction was fa-<lb break="no"/>vourable for our sailing up the Oroo-<lb break="no"/>noko, toward the mission of Enca-<lb break="no"/>ramada; but our canoes were so ill<lb break="yes"/>calculated to resist the shocks of the<lb break="yes"/>waves, that, from the violence of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="139" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/> the motion, those who suffered ha-<lb break="no"/>bitually at sea were incommoded on<lb break="yes"/>the river. The short broken waves<lb break="yes" />are caused by the conflict of the<lb break="yes"/>waters at the junction of the two<lb break="yes"/>rivers. This conflict is very violent,<lb break="yes" />but far from being so dangerous as<lb break="yes"/>Father Gumilla asserts.<note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Orinoco illustrado,</hi> vol. i, p. 47.</note> We passed<lb break="yes"/>the Punta Curiquima, which is an<lb break="yes" />isolated mass of quartzose granite,<lb break="yes"/>a small promontory composed of<lb break="yes"/>rounded blocks. There, on the<lb break="yes"/>right bank of the Oroonoko, Father<lb break="yes"/>Rotella founded, in the time of the<lb break="yes"/>Jesuits, a mission of Palenka and<lb break="yes" />Viriviri or Guire Indians. At the<lb break="yes"/>period of inundations, the rock Cu-<lb break="no"/>riquima and the village placed at its<lb break="yes" />foot, were surrounded every where<lb break="yes"/>by water. This serious inconve-<lb break="no"/>nience, and the sufferings of the mis-<lb break="no" />sionaries and Indians from the innu-<lb break="no"/>merable quantity of moschettoes and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">niguas,</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="†">The chego, <hi rendition="#i">pulex penetrans,</hi> which pe-<lb break="no"/>netrates under the nails of the toes in men<lb break="yes"/>and monkeys, and there deposits its eggs.</note> led them to forsake this<lb break="yes"/>humid spot. It is now entirely de-<lb break="no" />sert, while opposite to it, on the<lb break="yes"/>right bank of the river, the little<lb break="yes"/>mountains of Coruato are the retreat<lb break="yes" />of wandering Indians, expelled either<lb break="yes"/>from the missions, or from tribes<lb break="yes"/>that are not subjected to the govern-<lb break="no" />ment of the monks. Struck with the<lb break="yes"/>extreme breadth of the Oroonoko,<lb break="yes"/>between the mouth of the Apure and<lb break="yes" />the rock Curiquima, I ascertained it<lb break="yes"/>by means of a base measured twice<lb break="yes"/>on the western beach. The bed of<lb break="yes" />the Oroonoko, in its present state<lb break="yes"/>of low water, was 1906<note place="foot" n="‡">3714 metres, or 4441 varas, supposing 1<lb break="yes" />metre = 0.51307 of a toise = 1.19546 vara.</note> toises<lb break="yes" />broad; but this breadth attains 5517 <note place="foot" n="§">10753 metres, or 12855 varas.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>toises, when, in the rainy season,<lb break="yes"/>the rock Curiquimi, and the farm of<lb break="yes"/>Capuchino near the hill of Pocopo-<lb break="no"/>cori, become islands. The swelling<lb break="yes"/>of the Oroonoko is augmented by<lb break="yes"/>the impulse of the waters of the<lb break="yes"/>Apure, which far from forming, like<lb break="yes"/>other rivers, an acute angle with the<lb break="yes"/>upper part of that into which it<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> flows, meets it at right angles. The<lb break="yes"/>temperature of the waters of the<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko, measured in several parts<lb break="yes" />of its bed, was in the middle of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">thalweg,</hi> or deepest part of the chan-<lb break="no" />nel, where the current has the most<lb break="yes"/>swiftness, 28.3, and towards the<lb break="yes"/>banks 29.2.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We went up first towards the<lb break="yes"/>southwest, as far as the shore of<lb break="yes"/>the Guaricoto Indians, on the left<lb break="yes"/>bank of the Oroonoko, and then to-<lb break="no"/>wards the south. The river is so<lb break="yes"/>broad, that the mountains of Enca-<lb break="no"/>ramada appear to rise from the wa-<lb break="no"/>ter, as if they were seen above the<lb break="yes"/>horizon of the sea. They form a<lb break="yes"/>continued chain from east to west.<lb break="yes"/>As you approach them, the aspect of<lb break="yes"/>the country becomes more pictu-<lb break="no"/>resque. These mountains are com-<lb break="no"/>posed of enormous blocks of granite,<lb break="yes"/>cleft and piled one upon another.<lb break="yes"/>Their division into blocks is the ef-<lb break="no"/>fect of decomposition. What con-<lb break="no"/>tributes above all to embellish the<lb break="yes" />scene at Encaramada is the force of<lb break="yes"/>vegetation, that covers the sides of<lb break="yes"/>the rocks, leaving bare only their<lb break="yes" />rounded summits. They look like<lb break="yes"/>ancient ruins rising in the midst of<lb break="yes"/>a forest. The mountain immediate-<lb break="no"/>ly at the back of the mission, the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Tepupano</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Tepu-pano,</hi> “place of stones,” in which<lb break="yes"/>we recognize <hi rendition="#i">tepu,</hi> “stone rock,” as in <hi rendition="#i">tepu-<lb break="no"/>iri,</hi> mountain. We here again perceive that<lb break="yes"/>Lesgian Oigour-Tatar root <hi rendition="#i" >tep,</hi> (stone) found<lb break="yes"/>in America among the Mexicans, in <hi rendition="#i">tepetl;</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>among the Caribbees, in <hi rendition="#i">tebou;</hi> among the<lb break="yes"/>Tamanacks, in <hi rendition="#i">tepuiri;</hi> a striking analogy be-<lb break="no"/>tween the languages of Caucasus and Upper-<lb break="maybe"/>Asia and those of the banks of the Oroonoko.</note> of the Tamanack Indians,<lb break="yes"/>is covered by three enormous gra-<lb break="no"/>nitic cylinders; two of which are<lb break="yes"/>inclined, while the third, worn away<lb break="yes"/>at its basis, and more than eighty<lb break="yes"/>feet high, has preserved a vertical<lb break="yes"/>position. This rock, which calls to<lb break="yes" />mind the form of the <hi rendition="#i">Schnarcher</hi> in<lb break="yes"/>the Hartz, or that of the <hi rendition="#i">Organs</hi> of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Aetopan</hi> in Mexico<note place="foot" n="†">In Captain Tuckey’s Voyage on the Ri-<lb break="no"/>ver Congo, we find represented a granitic<lb break="yes"/>rock, the <hi rendition="#i">Taddi Enzazi,</hi> which bears a strik-<lb break="no"/>ing resemblance to the mountain of Encara-<lb break="no"/>mada.</note>, composed for-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="140" facs="#f0003"/>
                    <cb/> merly a part of the rounded summit<lb break="yes"/>of the mountain. In every zone it<lb break="yes"/>is the property of unstratified gra-<lb break="no" />nite, to separate by decomposition<lb break="yes"/>into blocks of prismatic, cylindric,<lb break="yes"/>or columnar figures.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Opposite the shore of the Guari-<lb break="no"/>cotoes, we drew near another heap<lb break="yes"/>of rocks, which is very low, and<lb break="yes"/>three or four toises long. It rises in<lb break="yes"/>the midst of the plain, and has less<lb break="yes"/>resemblance to a <hi rendition="#i">tumulus</hi> than to<lb break="yes"/>those masses of granitic stones,<lb break="yes"/>which in the north of Holland and<lb break="yes"/>of Germany bear the name of <hi rendition="#i">Hu-<lb break="no"/>enenbette, beds</hi> (or tombs) <hi rendition="#i">of heroes.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>The shore at this part of the Oroo-<lb break="no"/>noko, is no longer of pure and quart-<lb break="no"/>zose sand, but is composed of clay<lb break="yes"/>and spangles of mica, deposited in<lb break="yes"/>very thin strata, and most frequent-<lb break="no"/>ly with a dip of forty or fifty degrees.<lb break="yes"/>It looks like decomposed mica-slate.<lb break="yes" />This change in the geological con-<lb break="no"/>stitution of the shore extends far<lb break="yes"/>beyond the mouth of the Apure.<lb break="yes"/>We had begun to observe it in this<lb break="yes"/>latter river as far off as Algodonal<lb break="yes"/>and Canodel Manati. The spangles<lb break="yes" />of mica come no doubt from the<lb break="yes"/>granite mountains of Curiquima and<lb break="yes"/>Encaramada; since farther to the<lb break="yes"/>north and to the east we find only<lb break="yes"/>quartzose sand, sandstone, compact<lb break="yes"/>limestone, and gypsum. Alluvial earth<lb break="yes" />carried successively from the south<lb break="yes"/>to the north need not surprise us in<lb break="yes"/>the Oroonoko; but to what shall we<lb break="yes" />attribute the same phenomenon in<lb break="yes"/>the bed of the Apure, seven leagues<lb break="yes"/>west of its mouth? In the present<lb break="yes" />state of things, notwithstanding the<lb break="yes"/>swellings of the Oroonoko, the waters<lb break="yes"/>of the Apure never retrogade so far;<lb break="yes"/>and, to explain this phenomenon,<lb break="yes"/>we are forced to admit, that the mica-<lb break="no"/>ceous strata were deposited at a<lb break="yes"/>time when the whole of the very<lb break="yes"/>low country that lies between Cay-<lb break="no"/>cara, Algodonal, and the mountains<lb break="yes"/>of Encaramada, formed the basin of<lb break="yes"/>an inland lake.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We stopped some time at the port<lb break="yes"/>of Encaramada; it is a sort of <hi rendition="#i">embar-<lb break="no"/>cadere,</hi> a place where boats assem-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/>ble. A rock of forty or fifty feet<lb break="yes"/>high forms the shore. It is com-<lb break="no"/>posed of the same blocks of granite,<lb break="yes" />heaped one upon another, as at the<lb break="yes"/>Schneeberg in Franconia, and in al-<lb break="no"/>most all the <choice><sic>granatic</sic><corr type="editorial">granitic</corr></choice> mountains of<lb break="yes" />Europe. Some of these detached<lb break="yes"/>masses have a spheroidal form; they<lb break="yes"/>are not balls, however, with con-<lb break="no" />centric layers, as we have elsewhere<lb break="yes"/>described; but merely rounded<lb break="yes"/>blocks, nuclei separated from their<lb break="yes" />envelopes by the effect of decom-<lb break="no"/>position. This granite is of a gray-<lb break="no"/>ish lead-colour, often black, as if<lb break="yes" />covered with oxide of manganese;<lb break="yes"/>but this colour does not penetrate<lb break="yes"/>one fifth of a line into the rock, which<lb break="yes"/>is of a reddish white within, coarse-<lb break="maybe"/>grained, and destitute of hornblende.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Indian names of the mission<lb break="yes"/>of <hi rendition="#i">San Luis del Encaramada,</hi> are<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Guaja</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Caramana.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">All the missions of South America have<lb break="yes" />names composed of two words, the first of<lb break="yes"/>which is necessarily the name of a saint, the<lb break="yes"/>patron of the church, and the second an Indian<lb break="yes"/>name, that of the nation, or the spot where<lb break="yes"/>the establishment is placed. Thus we say,<lb break="yes"/>San Jose de Maypures, Santa Cruz de Cachi-<lb break="no" />po, San Juan Nepomuceno de los Atures, &amp;c.<lb break="yes"/>These compound names appear only in the<lb break="yes"/>official documents; the inhabitants adopt but<lb break="yes"/>one of the two names, and generally, provid-<lb break="no"/>ed it be sonorous, the Indian. As the names<lb break="yes"/>of saints are several times repeated in neigh-<lb break="no"/>bouring places, great confusion in geography<lb break="yes" />arises from these repetitions. The names of<lb break="yes"/>San Juan, San Diego, and San Pedro, are<lb break="yes"/>scattered in our maps as if by chance. It is<lb break="yes"/>pretended, that the mission of <hi rendition="#i">Guaji</hi> affords a<lb break="yes"/>very rare example of the composition of two<lb break="yes"/>Spanish words. The word <hi rendition="#i">Encaramada</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>means things raised one upon another, from<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">encaramar, attollere.</hi> It is derived from the<lb break="yes"/>figure of Tepupano and the neighboring rocks<lb break="yes" />perhaps it is only an Indian word, <hi rendition="#i">caramana,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>in which, as in <hi rendition="#i">manati,</hi> from a love for etymo-<lb break="no"/>logy, a Spanish signification was believed to be<lb break="yes"/>discovered.</note> This small<lb break="yes"/>village was founded in 1749, by Fa-<lb break="no"/>ther Gili, the Jesuit, author of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Storia dell Orinoco,</hi> published at<lb break="yes"/>Rome. This missionary, learned in<lb break="yes"/>the Indian tongues, lived in this<lb break="yes"/>solitude during eighteen years, till<lb break="yes"/>the expulsion of the Jesuits. To<lb break="yes"/>form a precise idea of the savage<lb break="yes"/>state of these countries, we must<lb break="yes" />recollect, that Father Gili speaks of<lb break="yes"/>Carichana, which is forty leagues<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="141" facs="#f0004"/>
                    <cb/> from Encaramada, as of a spot far<lb break="yes"/>distant; and that he never advanced<lb break="yes"/>so far as the first cataract of the<lb break="yes"/>river, of which he ventured to un-<lb break="no"/>dertake the description.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the port of Encaramada we<lb break="yes"/>met with some Caribbees of Panapa-<lb break="no"/>na. A Cacique was going up the<lb break="yes" />Oroonoko in his canoe, to join in<lb break="yes"/>the famous fishing of turtles’ eggs.<lb break="yes"/>His canoe was rounded towards the<lb break="yes" />bottom like a <hi rendition="#i">bongo,</hi> and followed<lb break="yes"/>by a smaller boat called <hi rendition="#i">curiara.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>He was seated beneath a sort of tent,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">toldo,</hi> constructed, as well as the sail,<lb break="yes" />of palm leaves. His cold and silent<lb break="yes"/>gravity, the respect with which he<lb break="yes"/>was treated by his attendants, eve-<lb break="no"/>ry thing denoted him to be a person<lb break="yes"/>of importance. He was equipped,<lb break="yes"/>however, in the same manner as<lb break="yes"/>his Indians. They were all equally<lb break="yes"/>naked, armed with bows and arrows,<lb break="yes"/>and covered with <hi rendition="#i">onoto,</hi> which is the<lb break="yes"/>colouring fecula of the bixa orella-<lb break="no" />na. The chief, the domestics, the<lb break="yes"/>furniture, the boat, and the sail,<lb break="yes"/>were all painted red. These Carib-<lb break="no"/>bees are men of an almost athletic<lb break="yes"/>stature; they appeared to us much<lb break="yes"/>taller than the Indians we had hith-<lb break="no" />erto seen. Their smooth and thick<lb break="yes"/>hair, cut upon their forehead like<lb break="yes"/>that of choristers, their eyebrows<lb break="yes" />painted black, their look at once<lb break="yes"/>gloomy and animated, give their<lb break="yes"/>physiognomy a singular hardness of<lb break="yes" />expression. Having till then seen<lb break="yes"/>only the skulls of some Caribbees<lb break="yes"/>of the West India Islands preserved<lb break="yes" />in the collections of Europe, we<lb break="yes"/>were surprised to find that these<lb break="yes"/>Indians, who were of pure race,<lb break="yes"/>had the forehead much more round-<lb break="no"/>ed than it has been described. The<lb break="yes"/>women, very tall, but disgusting from<lb break="yes" />their want of cleanliness, carried<lb break="yes"/>their infants on their backs, having<lb break="yes"/>their thighs and legs bound at certain<lb break="yes"/>distances by broad strips of cotton<lb break="yes"/>cloth. The flesh, strongly com-<lb break="no"/>pressed beneath the ligatures, was<lb break="yes"/>swelled in the interstices. It is gene-<lb break="no"/>rally to be observed, that the Carib-<lb break="no"/>bees are as attentive to their exte-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/>rior, and their ornaments, as it is<lb break="yes"/>possible for men to be, who are na-<lb break="no"/>ked and painted red. They attach<lb break="yes" />great importance to certain forms of<lb break="yes"/>the body; and a mother would be<lb break="yes"/>accused of culpable indifference to-<lb break="no" />wards her children, if she did not<lb break="yes"/>employ artificial means to shape the<lb break="yes"/>calf of the leg after the fashion of<lb break="yes" />the country. As none of our Indi-<lb break="no"/>ans of Apure understood the Carib-<lb break="no"/>bee language, we could obtain no<lb break="yes" />information from the Cacique of<lb break="yes"/>Panama respecting the encampments<lb break="yes"/>that are made at this season in seve-<lb break="no"/>ral islands of the Oroonoko for col-<lb break="no"/>lecting turtles’ eggs.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Near Encaramada, a very long<lb break="yes"/>island divides the river into two<lb break="yes"/>branches. We passed the night in a<lb break="yes"/>rocky creek, opposite the mouth of<lb break="yes"/>the Rio Cabullare, which is formed<lb break="yes"/>by the Payara and the Atamacia, and<lb break="yes"/>is sometimes considered as one of<lb break="yes"/>the branches of the Apure, because<lb break="yes"/>it communicates with this river by<lb break="yes" />the Rio Arichuna. The evening<lb break="yes"/>was beautiful. The moon illumin-<lb break="no"/>ed the tops of the granitic rocks.<lb break="yes" />The heat was so uniformly distri-<lb break="no"/>buted, that, notwithstanding the hu-<lb break="no"/>midity of the air, no twinkling of<lb break="yes"/>the stars was remarked, even at four<lb break="yes"/>or five degrees above the horizon.<lb break="yes"/>The light of the planets was singu-<lb break="no" />larly dimmed; and if, on account of<lb break="yes"/>the smallness of the apparent diame-<lb break="no"/>ter of Jupiter, I did not suspect<lb break="yes" />some error in the observation, I<lb break="yes"/>should say, that here, for the first<lb break="yes"/>time, we thought we distinguished<lb break="yes"/>the disk of Jupiter with the naked<lb break="yes"/>eye. Toward midnight, the north-<lb break="no"/>east wind became extremely violent.<lb break="yes"/>It brought no clouds, but the<lb break="yes"/>vault of the sky was covered more<lb break="yes"/>and more with vapours. Strong<lb break="yes"/>gusts were felt, and made us in fear<lb break="yes"/>for the safety of our canoe. During<lb break="yes"/>this whole day we had seen very<lb break="yes"/>few crocodiles, but all of an<lb break="yes"/>extraordinary size, from twenty to<lb break="yes" />twenty-four feet. The Indians as-<lb break="no"/>sured us, that the young crocodiles<lb break="yes"/>prefer the marshes, and the rivers<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="142" facs="#f0005"/>
                    <cb/> that are less broad, and less deep.<lb break="yes"/>They crowd together, particularly<lb break="yes"/>in the <choice>
                        <sic>
                            <hi rendition="#i">Canos,</hi>
                        </sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">
                            <hi rendition="#i">Canos,</hi>
                        </corr>
                    </choice> and we might be<lb break="yes"/>tempted to say of them, what Abd-<lb break="maybe"/>Allatif says of the crocodiles of the<lb break="yes"/>Nile, that “they swarm like worms<lb break="yes"/>in the shallow waters of the river,<lb break="yes"/>and in the shelter of uninhabited<lb break="yes"/>Islands.”</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 