<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">[Earthquake at Caraccas]</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:54</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.62</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-05-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-05-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-21-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-22-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-23-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-24-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-25-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-26-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-27-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-28-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-29-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-30-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-31-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-32-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Personal_Heft1-33-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 2, S. 7–9.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">[Earthquake at Caraccas]</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1819</date>
          <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Cambridge Chronicle and Journal, And Huntingdonshire Gazette&lt;/i&gt; 2971 (1. Oktober 1819), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <p>The following account of the <hi rendition="#i">Earthquake<lb break="yes"/>at Caraccas,</hi> on the 26th March 1812, is ex-<lb break="no"/>tracted from Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels:&#x2014;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;A great drought prevailed at this period in the<lb break="yes"/>province of Venezuela. Not a single drop of rain<lb break="yes"/>had fallen at Caraccas, or in the country ninety<lb break="yes"/>leagues round, during the five months which pre-<lb break="no"/>ceded the destruction of the capital. The 26th<lb break="yes"/>of March was a remarkably hot day. The air was<lb break="yes" />calm, and the sky unclouded. It was Holy Thurs-<lb break="no"/>day, and a great part of the population was as-<lb break="no"/>sembled in the churches. Nothing seemed to presage<lb break="yes"/>the calamities of the day. At seven minutes after<lb break="yes"/>four in the afternoon the first shock was felt; it was<lb break="yes"/>sufficiently powerful to make the bells of the churches<lb break="yes"/>toll; it lasted five or six seconds, during which time,<lb break="yes"/>the ground was in a continual undulating movement,<lb break="yes" />and seemed to heave up like a boiling liquid. The<lb break="yes"/>danger was thought to be past, when a tremendous<lb break="yes"/>subterraneous noise was heard, resembling the roll-<lb break="no"/>ing of thunder, but louder, and of longer conti-<lb break="no"/>nuance, than that heard within the tropics in time<lb break="yes"/>of storms. This noise preceded a perpendicular<lb break="yes" />motion of three or four seconds, followed by an<lb break="yes"/>undulatory movement somewhat longer. The shocks<lb break="yes"/>were in opposite directions, from north to south, and<lb break="yes"/>from east to west. Nothing could resist the move-<lb break="no"/>ment from beneath upward, and undulations cross-<lb break="no"/>ing each other. The town of Caraccas was entirely<lb break="yes" />overthrown. Thousands of the inhabitants (between<lb break="yes"/>nine and ten thousand) were buried under the ruins<lb break="yes"/>of the houses and churches. The procession had not<lb break="yes"/>yet set out; but the crowd was so great in the<lb break="yes"/>churches, that nearly three or four thousand persons<lb break="yes"/>were crushed by the fall of their vaulted roofs. The<lb break="yes" />explosion was stronger toward the north, in that part<lb break="yes"/>of the town situate nearest the mountain of Avila, and<lb break="yes"/>the Silla. The churches of la Trinidad and Alta<lb break="yes"/>Gracia, which were more than one hundred and<lb break="yes"/>fifty feet high, and the naves of which were sup-<lb break="no"/>ported by pillars of twelve or fifteen feet diameter,<lb break="yes" />left a mass of ruins scarcely exceeding five or six<lb break="yes"/>feet in elevation. The sinking of the ruins has been<lb break="yes"/>so considerable, that there now scarcely remain any<lb break="yes"/>vestiges of pillars or columns. The barracks, called<lb break="yes"/>
                <hi rendition="#i">El Quartel de San Carlos,</hi> situate farther north of the<lb break="yes"/>church of the Trinity, on the road from the Custom-<lb break="no" />house de la Pastora, almost entirely disappeared. A<lb break="yes"/>regiment of troops of the line, that was assembled<lb break="yes"/>under arms, ready to join the procession, was, with<lb break="yes"/>the exception of a few men, buried under the ruins<lb break="yes"/>of this great edifice. Nine tenths of the fine town<lb break="yes"/>of Caraccas were entirely destroyed. The walls of<lb break="yes" />the houses that were not thrown down, as those of<lb break="yes"/>the street San Juan, near the Capuchin Hospital,<lb break="yes"/>were cracked in such a manner, that it was impossi-<lb break="no"/>ble to run the risk of inhabiting them. The effects<lb break="yes"/>of the earthquake were somewhat less violent in the<lb break="yes"/>western and southern parts of the city, <choice><sic>betwen</sic><corr type="editorial">between</corr></choice> the<lb break="yes" />principal square and the ravin of Caraguata. There,<lb break="yes"/>the cathedral, supported by enormous buttresses, re-<lb break="no"/>mains standing.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;Estimating at nine or ten thousand the number<lb break="yes"/>of the dead in the city of Caraccas, we do not in-<lb break="no"/>clude those unhappy persons, who, dangerously<lb break="yes"/>wounded, perished several months after, for want<lb break="yes"/>of food and proper care. The night of Holy Thurs-<lb break="no" />day presented the most distressing scene of desolation<lb break="yes"/>and sorrow. That thick cloud of dust, which, rising<lb break="yes"/>above the ruins, darkened the sky like a fog, had<lb break="yes"/>settled on the ground. No shock was felt, and never<lb break="yes"/>was a night more calm, or more serene. The moon,<lb break="yes"/>nearly full, illumined the rounded domes of the<lb break="yes" />Silla, and the aspect of the sky formed a perfect<lb break="yes"/>contrast to that of the earth, covered with the dead,<lb break="yes"/>and heaped with ruins. Mothers were seen bearing<lb break="yes"/>in their arms their children, whom they hoped to<lb break="yes"/>recal to life. Desolate families wandered through<lb break="yes"/>the city seeking a brother, a husband, a friend, of<lb break="yes" />whose fate they were ignorant, and whom they be-<lb break="no"/>lieved to be lost in the crowd. The people pressed<lb break="yes"/>along the streets, which could no more be recognized<lb break="yes"/>but by long lines of ruins.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;All the calamities experienced in the great<lb break="yes"/><choice><sic>catastrosphes</sic><corr type="editorial">catastrophes</corr></choice> of Lisbon, Messina, Lima, and Rio-<lb break="no"/>bamba were renewed on the fatal day of the 26th<lb break="yes"/>of March, 1812. The wounded, buried under the<lb break="yes"/>ruins, implored by their cries the help of the passers<lb break="yes"/>by, and nearly two thousand were dug out. Never<lb break="yes"/>was pity displayed in a more affecting manner; never<lb break="yes"/>had it been seen more ingeniously active, than in the<lb break="yes"/>efforts employed to save the miserable victims, whose<lb break="yes"/>groans reached the ear. Implements for digging<lb break="yes"/>and clearing away the ruins were entirely wanting;<lb break="yes"/>and the people were obliged to use their bare hands,<lb break="yes" />to disinter the living. The wounded, as well as the sick<lb break="yes"/>who had escaped from the hospitals, were laid on the<lb break="yes"/>banks of the small river Guayra. They found no<lb break="yes"/>shelter but the foliage of trees. Beds, linen to dress<lb break="yes"/>the wounds, instruments of surgery, medicines, and<lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>objects of the most urgent necessity, were buried<lb break="yes"/>under the ruins. Every thing, even food, was want-<lb break="no"/>ing during the first days. Water became alike<lb break="yes"/>scarce in the interior of the city. The commotion<lb break="yes"/>had rent the pipes of the fountains; the falling in<lb break="yes"/>of the earth had choaked up the springs that supplied<lb break="yes"/>them; and it became necessary, in order to have<lb break="yes" />water, to go down to the river Guayra, which was<lb break="yes"/>considerably swelled; and then vessels to convey the<lb break="yes"/>water were wanting.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;There remained a duty to be fulfilled toward the<lb break="yes"/>dead, enjoined at once by piety, and the dread of<lb break="yes"/>infection. It being impossible to inter so many<lb break="yes"/>thousand corpses, half-buried under the ruins, com-<lb break="no"/>missaries were appointed to burn the bodies; and<lb break="yes"/>for this purpose funeral piles were erected between<lb break="yes" />the heaps of ruins. This ceremony lasted several<lb break="yes"/>days. Amid so many public calamities, the people<lb break="yes"/>devoted themselves to those religious duties, which<lb break="yes"/>they thought were the most fitted to appease the<lb break="yes"/>wrath of Heaven. Some, assembling in processions,<lb break="yes"/>sang funeral hymns; others, in a state of distraction,<lb break="yes"/>confessed themselves aloud in the streets. In this<lb break="yes" />town was now repeated what had been remarked<lb break="yes"/>in the province of Quito, after the tremendous earth-<lb break="no"/>quake of 1797; a number of marriages were con-<lb break="no"/>tracted between persons, who had neglected for<lb break="yes"/>many years to sanction their union by the sacredotal<lb break="yes" />benediction. Children found parents, by whom they<lb break="yes"/>had never till then been acknowledged; restitutions<lb break="yes"/>were promised by persons, who had never been ac-<lb break="no"/>cused of fraud; and families, who had long been<lb break="yes"/>enemies, were drawn together by the tie of common<lb break="yes" />calamity.&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI> 