<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.1" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.1" when="2018-10-10" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung für Verlag.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="266" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">baron humboldt’s last volume.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Personal Narrative of Travels to the<lb break="yes" />Equinoctial Regions of the New<lb break="yes"/>Continent.</hi> Vol. 4. London, 1819.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Consejo.</hi>&#x2014;We left the plantation<lb break="yes" />of Manterola on the 11th of Feb-<lb break="no"/>ruary, at sunrise. The road follows<lb break="yes"/>the smiling banks of the Tuy; the<lb break="yes" />morning was cool and humid, and<lb break="yes"/>the air seemed embalmed by the<lb break="yes"/>delicious odour of the Pranca-<lb break="no"/>tium undulatum, and other large<lb break="yes"/>liliaceous plants. In our way to La<lb break="yes"/><choice><sic>Victora</sic><corr type="editorial">Victoria</corr></choice>, we passed the pretty village<lb break="yes"/>of Mamon, or of Consejo, celebrat-<lb break="no"/>ed in the country for a miraculous<lb break="yes"/>image of the Virgin. A little before<lb break="yes"/>we reached Mamon, we stopped at a<lb break="yes"/>farm belonging to the family of Mon-<lb break="no"/>teras. A negress more than a hun-<lb break="no"/>dred years old was seated before a<lb break="yes"/>small hut, constructed with earth and<lb break="yes"/>reeds. Her age was known, be-<lb break="no"/>cause she was a creole slave. She<lb break="yes"/>seemed still to enjoy very good<lb break="yes"/>health. “I hold her to the Sun”<lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">la tengo al sol</hi>) said her grand-son;<lb break="yes"/>“the heat keeps her alive.” The<lb break="yes" />means appeared to us rather violent,<lb break="yes"/>for the Sun darted its rays almost<lb break="yes"/>perpendicularly. The nations with<lb break="yes"/>a brown skin, Blacks well seasoned,<lb break="yes"/>and Indians, attain a happy old age<lb break="yes"/>in the torrid zone. I have mention-<lb break="no"/>ed elsewhere the history of a native<lb break="yes"/>of Peru, who died at the age of one<lb break="yes"/>hundred and forty three years, after<lb break="yes" />having been ninety years married.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Don Francisco Montera, and his<lb break="yes"/>brother, a young and enlightened<lb break="yes"/>ecclesiastic, accompanied us, in or-<lb break="no"/>der to conduct us to their house at<lb break="yes"/>La Victoria. Almost all the fami-<lb break="no"/>lies, with whom we had lived in<lb break="yes"/>friendship at Caraccas, the Ustari-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/> zes, the Tovars, and the Toroes,<lb break="yes"/>were assembled in the fine valleys<lb break="yes"/>of Aragua. Proprietors of the<lb break="yes" />richest plantations, they contended<lb break="yes"/>with each other in whatever could<lb break="yes"/>render our stay agreeable. Before<lb break="yes" />we plunged into the forests of the<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko, we enjoyed once more all<lb break="yes"/>the advantages of an advanced civili-<lb break="no" />zation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The road from Mamon to La <choice><sic>Vic-<lb break="no"/>tora</sic><corr type="editorial">Vic-<lb break="no"/>toria</corr></choice> runs toward the south and the<lb break="yes"/>south-west. We soon lost sight of<lb break="yes"/>the river Tuy, which, turning to the<lb break="yes"/>east, forms an elbow at the foot of<lb break="yes"/>the high mountains of Guaraima.<lb break="yes"/>As we drew nearer to Victoria, the<lb break="yes"/>ground became smoother; it looked<lb break="yes"/>like the bottom of a lake, the waters<lb break="yes" />of which had been drained off. We<lb break="yes"/>might have fancied ourselves in the<lb break="yes"/>valley of Hasli, in the canton of<lb break="yes"/>Berne. The neighbouring hills,<lb break="yes"/>only one hundred and forty toises in<lb break="yes"/>height, are composed of calcareous<lb break="yes"/>tufa; but their abrupt declivities<lb break="yes"/>project like promontories on the<lb break="yes"/>plain. The form indicates the an-<lb break="no"/>cient shore of the lake. The eas-<lb break="no"/>tern extremity of this valley is<lb break="yes"/>parched and uncultivated. No ad-<lb break="no"/>vantage has been derived from the<lb break="yes"/>ravines, that water the neighbouring<lb break="yes"/>mountains; but a fine cultivation is<lb break="yes"/>commencing in the proximity of the<lb break="yes"/>town. I say of the town, though in<lb break="yes"/>my time Victoria was considered only<lb break="yes"/>as a village <choice>
                        <sic>(<hi rendition="#i">pueblo</hi>)</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">(<hi rendition="#i">pueblo</hi>).</corr>
                    </choice>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">La Victoria.</hi>&#x2014;The environs of<lb break="yes"/>La Victoria present a very remarka-<lb break="no"/>ble aspect, with regard to agricul-<lb break="no"/>ture. The height of the cultivated<lb break="yes" />ground is from two hundred and<lb break="yes"/>seventy to three hundred toises<lb break="yes"/>above the level of the ocean, and<lb break="yes"/>yet we there find fields of corn min-<lb break="no"/>gled with plantations of sugar canes,<lb break="yes"/>coffee, and plantains. Excepting the<lb break="yes" />interior of the island of Cuba, we<lb break="yes"/>scarcely find any where else in the<lb break="yes"/>equinoctial regions European corn<lb break="yes" />cultivated in large quantities in so<lb break="yes"/>low a region. The fine fields of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="267" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/> wheat in Mexico are between six<lb break="yes"/>hundred and twelve hundred toises<lb break="yes"/>of absolute elevation; and it is rare<lb break="yes" />to see them descend to four hundred<lb break="yes"/>toises. We shall soon perceive, that<lb break="yes"/>the produce of grain augments sen-<lb break="no" />sibly, from high latitudes toward the<lb break="yes"/>equator, with the mean temperature<lb break="yes"/>of the climate, in comparing spots of<lb break="yes"/>different elevations. The success<lb break="yes"/>of agriculture depends on the dry-<lb break="no"/>ness of the air; on the rains distri-<lb break="no"/>buted among different seasons, or ac-<lb break="no" />cumulated in one rainy season; on<lb break="yes"/>winds blowing constantly from the<lb break="yes"/>east, or bringing the cold air of the<lb break="yes" />north into very low latitudes, as in<lb break="yes"/>the gulf of Mexico; on mists, which<lb break="yes"/>for whole months diminish the in-<lb break="no" />tensity of the solar rays; in short,<lb break="yes"/>on a thousand local circumstances,<lb break="yes"/>which have less influence on the<lb break="yes"/>mean temperature of the whole<lb break="yes"/>year, than on the distribution of the<lb break="yes"/>same quantity of heat among the dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent parts of the year. It is a<lb break="yes"/>striking spectacle, to see the grain<lb break="yes"/>of Europe cultivated from the equa-<lb break="no"/>tor as far as Lapland, in the latitude<lb break="yes" />of 69°, in regions where the mean<lb break="yes"/>heat is from 22° to &#x2014;2°, in every<lb break="yes"/>place where the temperature of<lb break="yes"/>summer is above 9° or 10°. We<lb break="yes"/>know the minimum of heat requi-<lb break="no"/>site to ripen wheat, barley, and oats;<lb break="yes"/>we are less certain in respect to the<lb break="yes"/>maximum, which these species of<lb break="yes"/>grain, accommodating as they are,<lb break="yes"/>can support. We are even ignorant<lb break="yes"/>of all the circumstances, which fa-<lb break="no"/>vour the culture of corn between<lb break="yes"/>the tropics at very small heights.<lb break="yes"/>La Victoria and the neighbouring vil-<lb break="no"/>lage of San Matheo yield an annual<lb break="yes"/>produce of four thousand quintals of<lb break="yes"/>wheat. It is sown in the month of<lb break="yes"/>December, and the harvest is reap-<lb break="no"/>ed on the seventieth or seventy-fifth<lb break="yes"/>day. The grain is large, white, and<lb break="yes"/>abounding in gluten: its pellicle is<lb break="yes"/>thinner, and not so hard as that of the<lb break="yes" />wheat of the very cold table-lands<lb break="yes"/>of Mexico. An acre near Victoria<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> generally yields from three thousand<lb break="yes"/>to three thousand two hundred<lb break="yes"/>pounds weight of wheat. The ave-<lb break="no"/>rage produce is consequently here,<lb break="yes"/>as at Buenos Ayres, three or four<lb break="yes"/>times as much as that of northern<lb break="yes" />countries. Nearly sixteen times the<lb break="yes"/>quantity of the seed is reaped; while,<lb break="yes"/>according to Lavoisier, the surface<lb break="yes"/>of France yields on a <choice>
                        <sic>mien</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">mean</corr>
                    </choice> only five<lb break="yes"/>or six for one; or from one thou-<lb break="no"/>sand to twelve hundred pounds per<lb break="yes"/>acre. Notwithstanding this fecun-<lb break="no"/>dity of the soil, and this happy influ-<lb break="no"/>ence of the climate, the culture of<lb break="yes" />the sugar cane is more productive<lb break="yes"/>in the valleys of Aragua, than that<lb break="yes"/>of corn.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>La Victoria is traversed by the lit-<lb break="no"/>tle river Calanchas, running not into<lb break="yes"/>the Tuy, but into the Rio Aragua.<lb break="yes"/>It thence results, that this fine coun-<lb break="no"/>try, producing at once sugar and<lb break="yes"/>corn, belongs already to the basin of<lb break="yes" />the lake of Valencia, to a system of<lb break="yes"/>interior rivers which do not commu-<lb break="no"/>nicate with the sea. The quarter<lb break="yes"/>of the town West of the Rio Calan-<lb break="no"/>chas is called <hi rendition="#i" >la otra banda;</hi> it is the<lb break="yes"/>most commercial part; merchandize<lb break="yes"/>is every where exhibited, and ran-<lb break="no" />ges of shops form the streets. Two<lb break="yes"/>commercial roads pass through La<lb break="yes"/>Victoria; that of Valencia, or of<lb break="yes" />Porto Cabello, and the road of Villa<lb break="yes"/>de Cura, or of the plains, called<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">camino de los Llanos.</hi> We here find<lb break="yes"/>more white in proportion than at<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas. We visited at sunset the<lb break="yes"/>little hill of Calvary, where the<lb break="yes"/>view is extremely fine and exten-<lb break="no"/>sive. We discover on the west the<lb break="yes"/>smiling valleys of Aragua, a vast<lb break="yes"/>space covered with gardens, culti-<lb break="no"/>vated fields, clumps of wild trees,<lb break="yes"/>farms, and hamlets. Turning toward<lb break="yes"/>the south and south-east, we see,<lb break="yes"/>extending as far as the eye can<lb break="yes"/>reach, the lofty mountains of La<lb break="yes"/>Palma, Guayraima, Tiara, and Gui-<lb break="no"/>ripa, which conceal the immense<lb break="yes"/>plains or steppes of Calabozo. This<lb break="yes"/>interior chain stretches to the west<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="268" facs="#f0003"/>
                    <cb/>along the lake of Valencia, toward<lb break="yes"/>the Villa de Cura, the Cuesta de<lb break="yes"/>Yusma, and the denticulated moun-<lb break="no"/>tains of Guigue. It is very steep,<lb break="yes"/>and constantly covered with that<lb break="yes"/>light vapour, which in hot climates<lb break="yes"/>gives a vivid blue tint to distant ob-<lb break="no"/>jects, and far from concealing their<lb break="yes"/>outlines, renders them more strong-<lb break="no"/>ly marked. It is believed, that,<lb break="yes"/>among the mountains of the interior<lb break="yes"/>chain, that of Guayraima reaches an<lb break="yes" />elevation of twelve hundred toises.<lb break="yes"/>I found, in the night of the eleventh<lb break="yes"/>of February, the latitude of La Vic-<lb break="no" />toria 10° 13′ 35″, the magnetic dip<lb break="yes"/>40.8°, the intensity of the forces<lb break="yes"/>equal to 236 oscillations in 10′ of<lb break="yes" />time, and the variations of the nee-<lb break="no"/>dle 4.4° to the north-east.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We proceeded slowly on our way<lb break="yes"/>by the villages of San Matheo, Tur-<lb break="no"/>mero, and Maracay, to the Hacien-<lb break="no"/>da de Cura, a fine plantation belong-<lb break="no"/>ing to Count Tovar, where we did<lb break="yes"/>not arrive till the fourteenth of Feb-<lb break="no" />ruary, in the evening. The valley<lb break="yes"/>which gradually widens, is bordered<lb break="yes"/>with hills of calcareous tufa, called<lb break="yes"/>here <hi rendition="#i">tierra blanca.</hi> The scientific<lb break="yes"/>men of the country have made seve-<lb break="no"/>ral attempts to calcine this earth;<lb break="yes"/>mistaking it for the porcelain earth<lb break="yes"/>proceeding from the decomposition<lb break="yes"/>of strata of feldspar. We stayed<lb break="yes"/>some hours with a family equally<lb break="yes"/>enlightened and respectable, the<lb break="yes"/>Ustarizes, at Concession. The<lb break="yes"/>house, which contains a collection of<lb break="yes"/>choice books, is placed on an emi-<lb break="no"/>nence, and surrounded with planta-<lb break="no"/>tions of coffee and sugar canes. A<lb break="yes"/>grove of balsam trees (<hi rendition="#i">balsamo</hi>)<lb break="yes"/>gives coolness and shade to this spot.<lb break="yes"/>We observed with a lively interest<lb break="yes"/>the great number of scattered<lb break="yes"/>houses in the valley, inhabited<lb break="yes"/>by freedmen. In the Spanish colo-<lb break="no"/>nies, the laws, the institutions, and<lb break="yes"/>the manners, are more favourable to<lb break="yes"/>the liberty of the blacks, than in<lb break="yes"/>other European settlements.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>San Matheo, Turmero, and Mara-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/> cay, are charming villages, where<lb break="yes"/>every thing announces persons in<lb break="yes"/>the most easy circumstances. We<lb break="yes" />seemed to be transported to the<lb break="yes"/>most industrious parts of Catalonia.<lb break="yes"/>Near San Matheo we find the last<lb break="yes" />fields of wheat, and the last mills<lb break="yes"/>with horizontal hydraulic wheels.<lb break="yes"/>A harvest of twenty for one was<lb break="yes" />expected: and, as if the produce<lb break="yes"/>were but moderate, I was asked,<lb break="yes"/>whether corn produced more in<lb break="yes"/>Prussia and in Poland. It is an er-<lb break="no"/>ror that generally prevails under the<lb break="yes"/>tropics, to consider grain as plants<lb break="yes" />which degenerate in advancing to-<lb break="no"/>ward the equator; and to believe,<lb break="yes"/>that the harvests are more abundant<lb break="yes" />in the northern climates. Since<lb break="yes"/>calculations have been made on the<lb break="yes"/>progress of agriculture in the differ-<lb break="no" />ent zones, and the temperatures un-<lb break="no"/>der the influence of which corn will<lb break="yes"/>flourish, it has been found, that, be-<lb break="no" />yond the latitude of 45°, the pro-<lb break="no"/>duce of wheat is no where so consi-<lb break="no"/>derable, as on the northern coast of<lb break="yes" />Africa, and on the table-lands of<lb break="yes"/>New Grenada, Peru, and Mexico.<lb break="yes"/>Without comparing the mean tem-<lb break="no" />perature of the whole year, but on-<lb break="no"/>ly the mean temperature of the sea-<lb break="no"/>son which embraces the <hi rendition="#i">cycle of ve-<lb break="no"/>getation</hi> of corn, we find for three<lb break="yes"/>months of summer, in the north of<lb break="yes"/>Europe, from 15° to 19°; in Bar-<lb break="no"/>bary, and in Egypt, from 27° to 29°;<lb break="yes"/>within the tropics, between fourteen<lb break="yes"/>and six hundred toises of height,<lb break="yes"/>from 14° to 25.5° of the centigrade<lb break="yes"/>thermometer.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The fine harvests of Egypt and<lb break="yes"/>of the kingdom of Algiers, those of<lb break="yes"/>the valleys of Aragua and the interi-<lb break="no"/>or of the island of Cuba, sufficient-<lb break="no"/>ly prove, that the augmentation of<lb break="yes"/>heat is not prejudicial to the harvest<lb break="yes"/>of wheat and other alimentary grain,<lb break="yes"/>unless it is attended with an excess<lb break="yes"/>of drought or moisture. To this<lb break="yes"/>circumstance, no doubt, we must<lb break="yes"/>attribute the apparent anomalies,<lb break="yes"/>that are sometimes observed between<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="269" facs="#f0004"/>
                    <cb/>the tropics, in the <hi rendition="#i">inferior limit of<lb break="yes" />corn.</hi> We are astonished to see the<lb break="yes"/>east of the Havannah, in the famous<lb break="yes"/>district of Quatro Villas, this limit<lb break="yes"/>descend almost to the level of the<lb break="yes"/>ocean; while to the west of the<lb break="yes"/>Havannah, on the slope of the moun-<lb break="no"/>tains of Mexico and Xalappa, at six<lb break="yes"/>hundred and seventy-seven toises of<lb break="yes"/>height, the luxury of vegetation is<lb break="yes"/>such, that wheat does not form ears.<lb break="yes"/>At the beginning of the conquest,<lb break="yes"/>the corn of Europe was cultivated<lb break="yes"/>with success in several regions,<lb break="yes"/>which are now thought too hot, or<lb break="yes"/>too damp, for this branch of agricul-<lb break="no"/>ture. The Spaniards recently re-<lb break="no"/>moved to America were less accus-<lb break="no"/>tomed to live on maize; they still<lb break="yes"/>adhered to their European customs;<lb break="yes"/>they did not calculate whether corn<lb break="yes"/>would be less profitable than coffee<lb break="yes"/>or cotton; they tried seeds of every<lb break="yes"/>kind; they interrogated nature with<lb break="yes"/>more boldness, because their rea-<lb break="no"/>sonings were less founded on false<lb break="yes"/>theories. The province of Cartha-<lb break="no"/>gena, crossed by the chain of the<lb break="yes"/>mountains Maria and Guamoco, pro-<lb break="no"/>duced wheat till the sixteenth centu-<lb break="no"/>ry. In the province of Caraccas,<lb break="yes"/>this culture is very ancient among<lb break="yes"/>the mountainous lands of Tocuyo,<lb break="yes"/>Quibor, and Barquisimeto, which<lb break="yes"/>connect the littoral chain with the<lb break="yes"/>Sierra Nevada of Merida. It is still<lb break="yes"/>happily practised there, and the<lb break="yes"/>environs of the town of Tocuyo<lb break="yes"/>alone export annually more than<lb break="yes"/>eight thousand quintals of excel-<lb break="no"/>lent flour. But, though the pro-<lb break="no"/>vince of Caraccas, in its vast ex-<lb break="no"/>tent, presents several spots very fa-<lb break="no"/>vourable to the cultivation of Euro-<lb break="no"/>pean corn, I believe, that in general<lb break="yes"/>this branch of agriculture will never<lb break="yes"/>become of great importance there.<lb break="yes"/>The most temperate valleys are not<lb break="yes"/>sufficiently wide; they are not real<lb break="yes"/>table-lands; and their mean eleva-<lb break="no" />tation above the level of the sea is<lb break="yes"/>not considerable enough, for the in-<lb break="no"/>habitants to avoid perceiving, that it is<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>more their interest to establish plan-<lb break="no"/>tations of coffee, than to cultivate<lb break="yes"/>corn. Flour now comes to Carac-<lb break="no" />cas either from Spain, or from the<lb break="yes"/>United States. When, in circum-<lb break="no"/>stances more favourable to industry<lb break="yes" />and public tranquillity, the road from<lb break="yes"/>Santa Fe de Bogota to the port of<lb break="yes"/>Pachaquiaro is laid open, the inha-<lb break="no" />bitants of Venezuela will receive<lb break="yes"/>the flour of New Grenada by way<lb break="yes"/>of the Rio Meta and the Oroonoko.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Turmero.</hi>&#x2014;The village of Turme-<lb break="no"/>ro is four leagues distant from San<lb break="yes"/>Matheo. The road leads through<lb break="yes"/>plantations of sugar, indigo, cotton,<lb break="yes" />and coffee. The regularity, which<lb break="yes"/>we observed in the construction of<lb break="yes"/>the villages, reminded us, that they<lb break="yes"/>all owe their origin to monks and<lb break="yes"/>missions. The streets are straight<lb break="yes"/>and parallel; they cross each other<lb break="yes"/>at right angles; and the church is<lb break="yes"/>erected in the great square, situate<lb break="yes"/>in the centre. The church of Tur-<lb break="no"/>mero is a sumptuous edifice, but<lb break="yes"/>overloaded with architectural orna-<lb break="no"/>ments. Since the missionaries have<lb break="yes"/>been replaced by vicars, the whites<lb break="yes"/>have mixed their habitations with<lb break="yes"/>the Indians. The latter gradually<lb break="yes"/>disappear as a separate race; that<lb break="yes"/>is to say, they are represented in the<lb break="yes"/>general statement of the population<lb break="yes"/>by the Mestizoes and the Zamboes,<lb break="yes" />whose numbers daily increase. I<lb break="yes"/>still found, however, four thousand<lb break="yes"/>tributary Indians in the valleys of<lb break="yes" />Aragua. Those of Turmero and<lb break="yes"/>Guacara are the most numerous.<lb break="yes"/>They are little, but less squat than<lb break="yes"/>the Chaymas; their eyes announce<lb break="yes"/>more vivacity and intelligence, owing<lb break="yes"/>perhaps less to a diversity in the<lb break="yes" />race, than to a superior state of ci-<lb break="no"/>vilization. They work like freemen<lb break="yes"/>by the day; they are active and la-<lb break="no" />borious during the short time they allot<lb break="yes"/>to labour; but what they earn in two<lb break="yes"/>months is spent in one week, in buy-<lb break="no"/>ing strong liquors, at the small inns,<lb break="yes"/>of which, unhappily, the numbers<lb break="yes"/>daily increase.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="270" facs="#f0005"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>We saw at Turmero the remains<lb break="yes"/>of the assembled militia of the coun-<lb break="no"/>try, and their appearance alone suf-<lb break="no" />ficiently indicated, that these valleys<lb break="yes"/>had enjoyed for ages undisturbed<lb break="yes"/>peace. The captain-general, in or-<lb break="no" />der to give a new impulse to the<lb break="yes"/>military service, had ordered a grand<lb break="yes"/>review; and the battalion of Turmero,<lb break="yes"/>in a mock fight, had fired on that of<lb break="yes"/>La Victoria. Our host, a lieuten-<lb break="no"/>ant of the militia, was never weary<lb break="yes" />of describing to us the danger of<lb break="yes"/>these manœuvres. “He had been<lb break="yes"/>surrounded with muskets, which<lb break="yes"/>might have burst at every instant;<lb break="yes"/>he had been kept four hours in the<lb break="yes"/>Sun, and his slaves were not per-<lb break="no"/>mitted to hold an umbrella over his<lb break="yes"/>head”. With what rapidity do na-<lb break="no"/>tions, who appear the most pacific,<lb break="yes"/>acquire military habits! I then<lb break="yes"/>smiled at a timidity avowed with<lb break="yes"/>such simple frankness; and twelve<lb break="yes"/>years afterward those valleys of<lb break="yes"/>Aragua, those peaceful plains of La<lb break="yes"/>Victoria and Turmero, the defile of<lb break="yes" />Cabrera, and the fertile banks of the<lb break="yes"/>lake of Valencia, have become the<lb break="yes"/>theatre of the most obstinate and<lb break="yes" />bloody conflicts between the natives<lb break="yes"/>and the soldiers of the mother coun-<lb break="no"/>try.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Upon quitting the village of Turme-<lb break="no"/>ro, we discover, at a league distant,<lb break="yes"/>an object, which appear at the hori-<lb break="no" />zon like a round hillock, or <hi rendition="#i">tumulus,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>covered with vegetation. It is nei-<lb break="no"/>ther a hill, nor a group of trees close<lb break="yes"/>to each other, but one single tree<lb break="yes"/>the famous <hi rendition="#i">zamang del Guayre,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>known throughout the province for<lb break="yes"/>the enormous extent of its branches,<lb break="yes"/>which form a hemispheric head five<lb break="yes"/>hundred and seventy-six feet in cir-<lb break="no"/>cumference. The zamang is a fine<lb break="yes"/>species of mimosa, the tortuous<lb break="yes"/>branches of which are divided by<lb break="yes"/>bifurcation. Its delicate and tender<lb break="yes"/>foliage displayed itself agreeably on<lb break="yes"/>the azure of the sky. We stopped<lb break="yes"/>a long time under this vegetable roof.<lb break="yes"/>The trunk of the zamang del Guayre,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> which is found on the road from<lb break="yes"/>Turmero to Maracay, is only sixty<lb break="yes"/>feet high, and nine thick; but its<lb break="yes" />real beauty consists in the form of<lb break="yes"/>its head. The branches extended<lb break="yes"/>like an immense umbrella, and bend<lb break="yes" />toward the ground, from which they<lb break="yes"/>remain at a uniform distance of<lb break="yes"/>twelve or fifteen feet. The circum-<lb break="no" />ference of this head is so regular,<lb break="yes"/>that, having traced different diame-<lb break="no"/>ters, I found them one hundred and<lb break="yes"/>ninety-two and one hundred and<lb break="yes"/>eighty-six feet. One side of the<lb break="yes"/>tree was entirely stripped of its foli-<lb break="no"/>age, owing to the drought; and on<lb break="yes"/>the other side there remained at<lb break="yes"/>once leaves and flowers. Tilland-<lb break="no"/>sias, lorantheæ, cactus pitahayas,<lb break="yes"/>and other parasite plants, cover its<lb break="yes"/>branches, and crack the bark. The<lb break="yes"/>inhabitants of these villages, but<lb break="yes"/>particularly the indians, hold in ve-<lb break="no"/>neration the zamang del Guayre,<lb break="yes"/>which the first conquerors found al-<lb break="no"/>most in the same state in which it<lb break="yes"/>now remains. Since it has been<lb break="yes"/>observed with attention, no change<lb break="yes"/>has appeared in its thickness or<lb break="yes"/>height. This zamang must be at least<lb break="yes"/>as old as the Orotava dragon-tree.<lb break="yes"/>There is something solemn and ma-<lb break="no"/>jestic in the aspect of aged trees,<lb break="yes"/>and the violation of these monuments<lb break="yes"/>of nature is severely punished in<lb break="yes"/>countries, that are destitute of <choice><sic>mon-<lb break="no"/>numents</sic><corr type="editorial">mo-<lb break="no"/>numents</corr></choice> of art. We heard with<lb break="yes"/>satisfaction, that the present propri-<lb break="no"/>etor of the zamang had brought an<lb break="yes"/>action against a farmer, who had had<lb break="yes"/>the temerity to cut off a branch.<lb break="yes"/>The cause was tried<choice>
                        <sic>,,</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">,</corr>
                    </choice> and the tribu-<lb break="no"/>nal condemned the farmer. We<lb break="yes"/>find near Turmero and the hacienda<lb break="yes"/>de Cura other zamangs, the trunks<lb break="yes"/>of which are larger than that of<lb break="yes"/>Guayre, but their hemispherical<lb break="yes"/>head is not of equal extent.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The culture and population of the<lb break="yes"/>plains augment as we advance to-<lb break="no"/>ward Cura and Guacara, on the<lb break="yes"/>northern side of the lake. The<lb break="yes"/>valleys of Aragua contain more than<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="271" facs="#f0006"/>
                    <cb/>52,000 inhabitants, on a space of<lb break="yes"/>ground thirteen leagues long, and<lb break="yes"/>two wide. This is a relative popu-<lb break="no" />lation of two thousand souls on a<lb break="yes"/>square league, which equals almost<lb break="yes"/>that of the most populous parts of<lb break="yes" />France. The village, or rather the<lb break="yes"/>small town of Maracay, was hereto-<lb break="no"/>fore the centre of the indigo planta-<lb break="no" />tions, when this branch of colonial<lb break="yes"/>industry was in its greatest prosperi-<lb break="no"/>ty. In 1795, seventy tradesmen<lb break="yes" />had established shops in a popula-<lb break="no"/>tion of six thousand inhabitants<lb break="yes"/>The houses are all of masonry, and<lb break="yes"/>every court contains cocoa-trees,<lb break="yes"/>which rise above the habitations.<lb break="yes"/>The aspect of general wealth is still<lb break="yes"/>more striking at Maracay, than at<lb break="yes"/>Turmero. The anil, or indigo, of<lb break="yes"/>these provinces, has always been<lb break="yes"/>considered in commerce as equal,<lb break="yes"/>and sometimes superior to that of<lb break="yes"/>Guatimala. This branch of culture<lb break="yes"/>has, since 1772, followed that of<lb break="yes"/>cacao, and preceded the cultivation<lb break="yes"/>of cotton and coffee. The predilec-<lb break="no"/>tion of the colonists has been alter-<lb break="no"/>nately fixed on each of these four<lb break="yes"/>productions; but the cacao and cof-<lb break="no"/>fee are now the only important bran-<lb break="no"/>ches of commerce with Europe. In<lb break="yes"/>the most prosperous times the fabri-<lb break="no"/>cation of indigo has almost equalled<lb break="yes" />that of Mexico; it rose in the pro-<lb break="no"/>vince of Venezuela to 40,000 arro-<lb break="no"/>bas, or a million of pounds, the<lb break="yes" />value of which exceeded 1,250,000<lb break="yes"/>piastres.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 