<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="242" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Account of the Electrical Eels, and of the Me-<lb break="no" />thod of catching them in South America by means of Wild<lb break="yes"/>Horses.</hi> Abridged from <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt&#x2019;s</hi> Personal Narrative.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#in">R</hi>eal</hi> Gymnoti or Electrical Eels, inhabit the Rio Colorado,<lb break="yes"/>the Guarapiche, and several little streams, that cross the missions<lb break="yes"/>of the Chayma Indians. They abound also in the large rivers<lb break="yes"/>of America, the Oroonoko, the Amazon, and the Meta; but the<lb break="yes"/>strength of the current, and the depth of the water, prevent<lb break="yes"/>their being caught by the Indians. They see these fish less<lb break="yes"/>frequently than they feel electrical shocks from them when swim-<lb break="no"/>ming or bathing in the river. In the <hi rendition="#i">Llanos,</hi> particularly in<lb break="yes"/>the environs of Calabozo, between the farms of Morichal, and<lb break="yes"/>the missions <hi rendition="#i">de arriba</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">de abaxo,</hi> the basins of stagnant wa-<lb break="no"/>ter, and the confluents of the Oroonoko, (the Rio Guarico and<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">Canos</hi> of Rastro, Berito and Paloma), are filled with elec-<lb break="no"/>trical eels. We at first wished to make our experiments in the<lb break="yes"/>house we inhabited at Calabozo; but the dread of the electri-<lb break="no"/>cal shocks of the gymnoti is so exaggerated among the vulgar,<lb break="yes"/>that during three days we could not obtain one, though they<lb break="yes"/>are easily caught, and though we had promised the Indians two<lb break="yes"/>piastres for every strong and vigorous fish.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Impatient of waiting, and having obtained very uncertain re-<lb break="no"/>sults from an electrical eel that had been brought to us alive, but<lb break="yes" />much enfeebled, we repaired to the Cano de Bera, to make our<lb break="yes" />experiments in the open air, on the borders of the water itself. We<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="243" facs="#f0002"/>set off on the 19th of March for the village <hi rendition="#i">Rastro de abaxo;</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>thence we were conducted to a stream, which, in the time of<lb break="yes"/>drought, forms a basin of muddy water, surrounded by fine trees.<lb break="yes"/>To catch the gymnoti with nets is very difficult, on account of the<lb break="yes"/>extreme agility of the fish, which bury themselves in the mud<lb break="yes"/>like serpents. We would not employ the <hi rendition="#i">barbasco,</hi> that is to<lb break="yes"/>say, the roots of the Piscidea erithryna and Jacquinia armillaris,<lb break="yes"/>which, when thrown into the pool, intoxicate or benumb these<lb break="yes"/>animals. These means would have enfeebled the gymnoti; the<lb break="yes"/>Indians therefore told us, that they would &#x201C;fish with horses.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>We found it difficult to form an idea of this extraordinary man-<lb break="no"/>ner of fishing; but we soon saw our guides return from the sa-<lb break="no" />vannah, which they had been scouring for wild horses and<lb break="yes" />mules. They brought about thirty with them, which they<lb break="yes"/>forced to enter the pool.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The extraordinary noise caused by the horses&#x2019; hoofs makes<lb break="yes" />the fish issue from the mud, and excites them to combat. These<lb break="yes" />yellowish and livid eels, resembling large aquatic serpents, swim<lb break="yes"/>on the surface of the water, and crowd under the bellies of the<lb break="yes"/>horses and mules. A contest between animals of so different<lb break="yes"/>an organization furnishes a very striking spectacle. The In-<lb break="no"/>dians, provided with harpoons and long slender reeds, surround<lb break="yes"/>the pool closely; and some climb upon the trees, the branches<lb break="yes"/>of which extend horizontally over the surface of the water. By<lb break="yes"/>their wild cries, and the length of their reeds, they prevent the<lb break="yes"/>horses from running away, and reaching the bank of the pool.<lb break="yes"/>The eels, stunned by the noise, defend themselves by the re-<lb break="no"/>peated discharge of their electric batteries. During a long time<lb break="yes"/>they seem to prove victorious. Several horses sink beneath the<lb break="yes"/>violence of the invisible strokes, which they receive from all<lb break="yes"/>sides in organs the most essential to life; and stunned by the<lb break="yes"/>force and frequency of the shocks, disappear under the water.<lb break="yes"/>Others, panting, with mane erect, and haggard eyes, express-<lb break="no"/>ing anguish, raise themselves, and endeavour to flee from the<lb break="yes"/>storm by which they are overtaken. They are driven back by<lb break="yes"/>the Indians into the middle of the water; but a small number<lb break="yes"/>succeed in eluding the active vigilance of the fishermen. These<lb break="yes"/>regain the shore, stumbling at every step, and stretch them-<lb break="no"/>selves on the sand, exhausted with fatigue, and their limbs be-<lb break="no"/>numbed by the electric shocks of the gymnoti.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="244" facs="#f0003"/>
                <p>In less than five minutes two horses were drowned. The<lb break="yes"/>eel, being five feet long, and pressing itself against the belly of<lb break="yes"/>the horses, makes a discharge along the whole extent of its elec-<lb break="no" />tric organ. It attacks at once the heart, the intestines, and the<lb break="yes"/><hi rendition="#i">plexus c&#x0153;liacus</hi> of the abdominal nerves. It is natural, that the<lb break="yes"/>effect felt by the horses should be more powerful than that pro-<lb break="no"/>duced upon man by the touch of the same fish at only one of<lb break="yes"/>his extremities. The horses are probably not killed, but only<lb break="yes"/>stunned. They are drowned from the impossibility of rising<lb break="yes"/>amid the prolonged struggle between the other horses and the<lb break="yes"/>eels.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We had little doubt, that the fishing would terminate by<lb break="yes"/>killing successively all the animals engaged; but by degrees<lb break="yes"/>the impetuosity of this unequal combat diminished, and the<lb break="yes"/>wearied gymnoti dispersed. They require a long rest <note place="foot" n="*">The Indians assured us, that when the horses are made to run two days<lb break="yes" />successively into the same pool, none are killed the second day.</note>, and<lb break="yes"/>abundant nourishment, to repair what they have lost of galva-<lb break="no"/>nic force. The mules and horses appear less frightened; their<lb break="yes"/>manes are no longer bristled, and their eyes express less dread.<lb break="yes"/>The gymnoti approach timidly the edge of the marsh, where<lb break="yes"/>they are taken by means of small harpoons fastened to long<lb break="yes"/>cords. When the cords are very dry, the Indians feel no shock<lb break="yes"/>in raising the fish into the air. In a few minutes we obtained<lb break="yes"/>five large eels, the greater part of which were but slightly wound-<lb break="no"/>ed. Some were taken by the same means toward the evening.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The temperature of the waters in which the gymnoti habitu-<lb break="no"/>ally live, is about 86&#x00B0; of Fahrenheit. Their electric force,<lb break="yes"/>it is said, diminishes in colder waters. The gymnotus is the<lb break="yes"/>largest of electrical fishes. I measured some that were from five<lb break="yes"/>feet to five feet three inches long; and the Indians assert, that<lb break="yes" />they have seen them still longer. We found, that a fish of three<lb break="yes"/>feet ten inches long weighed twelve pounds. The transverse dia-<lb break="no"/>meter of the body was three inches five lines. The gymnoti of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Cano de Bera</hi> are of a fine olive-green colour. The under part<lb break="yes"/>of the head is yellow, mingled with red. Two rows of small<lb break="yes"/>yellow spots are placed symmetrically along the back, from the<lb break="yes"/>head to the end of the tail. Every spot contains an excretory<lb break="yes"/>aperture. In consequence, the skin of the animal is constantly<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="245" facs="#f0004"/>covered with a mucous matter, which, as Volta has proved, con-<lb break="no"/>ducts electricity twenty or thirty times better than pure water.<lb break="yes"/>It is in general somewhat remarkable, that no electrical fish, yet<lb break="yes"/>discovered <note place="foot" n="*">We yet know with certainty only seven electrical fishes: Torpedo narke, Ris-<lb break="no"/>so, t. unimaculata, t. marmorata, t. galvanii, Silurus electricus, Tetraodon electricus,<lb break="yes"/>Gymnotus electricus.</note> in the different parts of the world, is covered with<lb break="yes"/>scales.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It would be temerity to expose ourselves to the first shocks<lb break="yes"/>of a very large and strongly irritated gymnotus. If by chance<lb break="yes"/>you receive a stroke before the fish is wounded, or wearied by a<lb break="yes" />long pursuit, the pain and numbness are so violent, that it is im-<lb break="no"/>possible to describe the nature of the feeling they excite. I do not<lb break="yes"/>remember having ever received from the discharge of a large Ley-<lb break="no"/>den jar, a more dreadful shock than that which I experienced by<lb break="yes"/>imprudently placing both my feet on a gymnotus just taken out<lb break="yes"/>of the water. I was affected the rest of the day with a violent<lb break="yes"/>pain in the knees, and in almost every joint. To be aware of<lb break="yes"/>the difference, which is sufficiently striking, that exists between<lb break="yes"/>the sensation produced by the pile of Volta and an electrical fish,<lb break="yes"/>the latter should be touched when they are in a state of extreme<lb break="yes"/>weakness. The gymnoti and the torpedoes then cause a twit-<lb break="no"/>ching, which is propagated from the part that rests on the<lb break="yes"/>electric organs as far as the elbow. We seem to feel at every<lb break="yes"/>stroke an internal vibration, that lasts two or three seconds, and<lb break="yes"/>is followed by a painful numbness.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Gymnoti are neither charged conductors, nor batteries, nor<lb break="yes" />electromotive apparatuses, the shock of which is received every<lb break="yes" />time they are touched with one hand, or when both hands are<lb break="yes" />applied to form a conducting circle between two heterogeneous<lb break="yes" />poles. The electric action of the fish depends entirely on its<lb break="yes" />will; whether because it does not keep its electric organs al-<lb break="no" />ways charged, or by the secretion of some fluid, or by any<lb break="yes" />other means alike mysterious to us, it be capable of directing the<lb break="yes"/>action of its organs to an external object. We often both tried,<lb break="yes"/>both insulated and uninsulated, to touch the fish, without feel-<lb break="no"/>ing the least shock. When Mr Bonpland held it by the head,<lb break="yes"/>or by the middle of the body, while I held it by the tail, and,<lb break="yes"/>standing on the moist ground, did not take each other&#x2019;s hand,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="246" facs="#f0005"/>one of us received shocks, which the other did not feel. It de-<lb break="no"/>pends upon the gymnotus to act toward the point where it finds<lb break="yes"/>itself the most strongly irritated. The discharge is then made<lb break="yes"/>at one point only, and not at the neighbouring points. If two<lb break="yes"/>persons touch the belly of the fish with their fingers, at an inch<lb break="yes"/>distance, and press it simultaneously, sometimes one, sometimes<lb break="yes"/>the other, will receive the shock. In the same manner, when<lb break="yes"/>one insulated person holds the tail, and another pinches the<lb break="yes"/>gills, or pectoral fin, it is often the first only by whom the shock<lb break="yes"/>is received. It did not appear to us, that these differences<lb break="yes"/>could be attributed to the dryness or dampness of our hands,<lb break="yes"/>or to their unequal conducting power. The gymnotus seemed<lb break="yes"/>to direct its strokes sometimes from the whole surface of its<lb break="yes"/>body, sometimes from one point only.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Nothing proves more strongly the faculty which the gymno-<lb break="no"/>tus possesses, of darting and directing its stroke according to<lb break="yes"/>its will, than the observations made at Philadelphia, and re-<lb break="no"/>cently at Stockholm, on gymnoti rendered extremely tame.<lb break="yes"/>When they had been made to fast a long time, they killed from<lb break="yes"/>afar small fishes put into the tub. They acted at a distance;<lb break="yes"/>that is to say, their electrical stroke passed through a very thick<lb break="yes"/>stratum of water. We need not be surprised, that what was ob-<lb break="no"/>served in Sweden, on a single gymnotus only, we could not see<lb break="yes"/>on a great number of individuals in their native country. The<lb break="yes"/>electric action of animals being <hi rendition="#i">a vital action,</hi> and subject to<lb break="yes"/>their will, it does not depend solely on their state of health and<lb break="yes"/>vigour. A gymnotus, that has made the voyage from Surinam<lb break="yes"/>to Philadelphia and Stockholm, accustoms itself to the impri-<lb break="no"/>sonment to which it is reduced; it resumes by degrees the same<lb break="yes"/>habits in the tub which it had in the rivers and pools. An elec-<lb break="no"/>trical eel was brought to me at Calabozo, taken in a net, and<lb break="yes"/>consequently having no wound. It ate meat, and terribly<lb break="yes"/>frightened the little tortoises and frogs, which, not knowing the<lb break="yes"/>danger, placed themselves with confidence on its back. The<lb break="yes"/>frogs did not receive the stroke till the moment when they<lb break="yes"/>touched the body of the gymnotus. When they recovered,<lb break="yes"/>they leaped out of the tub; and when replaced near the fish,<lb break="yes"/>they were frightened at its sight only. We then observed no-<lb break="no"/>thing that indicated <hi rendition="#i">an action at a distance;</hi> but our gymno-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="247" facs="#f0006"/>tus, recently taken, was not yet sufficiently tamed to attack and<lb break="yes"/>devour frogs. On approaching the finger, or metallic points,<lb break="yes"/>within the distance of half a line from the electric organs, no<lb break="yes"/>shock was felt. Perhaps the animal did not perceive the neigh-<lb break="no"/>bourhood of this foreign body; or, if it did, we must suppose<lb break="yes"/>that the timidity it felt in the commencement of its captivity,<lb break="yes"/>prevented it from darting forth its energetic strokes, except<lb break="yes"/>when strongly irritated by an immediate contact. The gymno-<lb break="no"/>tus being immersed in water, I approached my hand, both<lb break="yes"/>armed and unarmed with a metal, within the distance of a few<lb break="yes"/>lines from the electric organs; yet the strata of water transmit-<lb break="no"/>ted no shock, while Mr Bonpland irritated the animal strongly<lb break="yes"/>by an immediate contact, and received some very violent shocks.<lb break="yes"/>If I had plunged the most delicate electroscopes we know, pre-<lb break="no"/>pared frogs, into contiguous strata of water, they would no<lb break="yes"/>doubt have felt contractions at the moment when the gymnotus<lb break="yes"/>seemed to direct its stroke elsewhere.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The electrical organ of the gymnoti acts only under the im-<lb break="no" />mediate influence of the brain and the heart. On cutting a very<lb break="yes" />vigorous fish through the middle of the body, the fore part a-<lb break="no" />lone gave me shocks. The shocks are equally strong, in what-<lb break="no" />ever part of the body the fish is touched; it is most disposed,<lb break="yes" />however, to dart them forth when the pectoral fin, the electri-<lb break="no" />cal organ, the lips, the eyes, or the gills are pinched. Some-<lb break="no" />times the animal struggles violently with a person holding it by<lb break="yes"/>the tail, without communicating the least shock. Nor did I feel<lb break="yes"/>any when I made a slight incision near the pectoral fin of the<lb break="yes"/>fish, and <hi rendition="#i">galvanized</hi> the wound by the simple contact of two<lb break="yes"/>pieces of zinc and silver. The gymnotus bent itself convulsive-<lb break="no"/>ly, and raised its head out of the water, as if terrified by a<lb break="yes"/>sensation altogether new; but I felt no vibration in the hands<lb break="yes"/>which held the two metals. The most violent muscular move-<lb break="no"/>ments are not always accompanied by electric discharges.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The action of the fish on the organs of man is transmitted<lb break="yes"/>and intercepted by the same bodies that transmit and intercept<lb break="yes"/>the electrical current of a conductor charged by a Leyden vial,<lb break="yes"/>or Volta&#x2019;s pile.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In wounded gymnoti, which give feeble but very equal<lb break="yes"/>shocks, these shocks appeared to us constantly stronger on<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="248" facs="#f0007"/>touching the body of the fish with a hand armed with metal,<lb break="yes"/>than with the naked hand. They are stronger also, when, in-<lb break="no"/>stead of touching the fish with one hand, naked, or armed with<lb break="yes"/>metal, we press it at once with both hands, either naked or<lb break="yes"/>armed. These differences, I repeat, become sensible only when<lb break="yes"/>you have gymnoti enough at your disposal, to be able to choose<lb break="yes"/>the weakest; and the extreme equality of the electric dischar-<lb break="no"/>ges admits of distinguishing between the sensations felt alter-<lb break="no"/>nately by the hand naked or armed with a metal, by one or<lb break="yes"/>both hands naked, and by one or both hands armed with metal.<lb break="yes"/>It is also in the case only of small shocks, weak and uniform,<lb break="yes"/>that the shocks are more sensible on touching the gymnotus<lb break="yes"/>with one hand (without forming a chain) with zinc, than with<lb break="yes"/>copper or iron.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Resinous substances, glass, very dry wood, horn, and even<lb break="yes"/>bones, which are generally believed to be good conductors, pre-<lb break="no"/>vent the action of the gymnoti from being transmitted to man.<lb break="yes"/>I was surprised at not feeling the least shock on pressing wet sticks<lb break="yes" />of sealing-wax against the organs of the fish; while the same ani-<lb break="no"/>mal gave me the most violent strokes, when excited by means<lb break="yes"/>of a metallic rod. Mr Bonpland received shocks when carry-<lb break="no"/>ing a gymnotus on two cords of the fibres of the palm-tree,<lb break="yes"/>which appeared to us extremely dry. A strong discharge makes<lb break="yes"/>its way through very imperfect conductors. Perhaps also the<lb break="yes"/>obstacle which the conducting arc presents, renders the dis-<lb break="no"/>charge more painful. I touched the gymnotus with a wet pot<lb break="yes"/>of brown clay without effect; yet I received violent shocks when<lb break="yes"/>I carried the gymnotus in the same pot, because the contact<lb break="yes"/>was greater.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When two persons, insulated or not insulated, hold each<lb break="yes" />other&#x2019;s hands, and one of these persons only touches the fish<lb break="yes"/>with the hand, either naked or armed with metal, the shock is<lb break="yes"/>most commonly felt by both at once. It happens, however, al-<lb break="no"/>so, that, in the most painful shocks, the person who comes into<lb break="yes"/>immediate contact with the fish alone feels the shock. When<lb break="yes"/>the gymnotus is exhausted, or in a very weak state of excitabi-<lb break="no"/>lity, and will no longer emit strokes on being irritated with one<lb break="yes"/>hand; the shocks are felt, in a very vivid manner, on forming<lb break="yes"/>the chain, and employing both hands. Even then, however,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="249" facs="#f0008"/>the electric shock takes place only at the will of the animal.<lb break="yes"/>Two persons, one of whom holds the tail, and the other the<lb break="yes"/>head, cannot, by joining hands and forming a chain, force the<lb break="yes"/>gymnotus to dart his stroke.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In employing very delicate electrometers in a thousand ways,<lb break="yes" />insulating them on a plate of glass, and receiving very strong<lb break="yes" />shocks, which passed through the electrometer, I could never<lb break="yes" />discover any phenomenon of attraction or repulsion. The same<lb break="yes" />observation was made by Mr Fahlberg at Stockholm. This<lb break="yes" />philosopher, however, has seen an electric spark, as Walsh and<lb break="yes" />Ingenhousz had done before him at London, by placing the<lb break="yes" />gymnotus in the air, and interrupting the conducting chain by<lb break="yes" />two gold leaves pasted upon glass, and a line distant from each<lb break="yes" />other. No person, on the contrary, has ever perceived a spark<lb break="yes" />issue from the body of the fish itself. We have irritated it for<lb break="yes"/>a long time during the night, at Calabozo, in perfect darkness,<lb break="yes"/>without observing any luminous appearance.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 