<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <pb n="144" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>THE GYMNOTUS, <hi rendition="#k">or</hi> ELECTRIC EEL.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">The</hi>
                    </hi> Gymnoti, or Electrical Eels, which resemble<lb break="yes"/>large water serpents, inhabit several streams of South<lb break="yes"/>America, and abound also in the Oroonoko, the<lb break="yes"/>Amazon, and the Meta, but the strength of the<lb break="yes"/>current, and the depth of the water in these large<lb break="yes"/>rivers, prevent their being caught by the Indians.<lb break="yes"/>They see these fish less frequently than they feel<lb break="yes"/>electric shocks from them, when swimming or bathing<lb break="yes"/>in the river. To catch the Gymnoti with nets is<lb break="yes" />very difficult, on account of the extreme agility of<lb break="yes"/>the fish, which bury themselves in the mud like<lb break="yes"/>serpents. Roots are sometimes thrown into the<lb break="yes"/>water to intoxicate or benumb these animals, but we<lb break="yes"/>would not employ these means, as they would have<lb break="yes"/>enfeebled the gymnoti: the Indians, therefore, told<lb break="yes"/>us, that they would &#x201C;fish with horses.&#x201D; We found it<lb break="yes"/>difficult to form an idea of this extraordinary manner<lb break="yes"/>of fishing; but we soon saw our guides return from<lb break="yes"/>the savannah, which they had been scouring for wild<lb break="yes"/>horses and mules. They brought about thirty with<lb break="yes" />them, which they forced to enter the pool.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The extraordinary noise caused by the horses&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>hoofs, makes the fish issue from the mud, and<lb break="yes"/>excites them to combat; they swim on the surface<lb break="yes"/>of the water, and crowd under the bellies of the<lb break="yes"/>horses and mules. A contest between animals of so<lb break="yes"/>different an organization, furnishes a very striking<lb break="yes"/>spectacle. The Indians, provided with harpoons and<lb break="yes"/>long slender reeds, surround the pool closely; and<lb break="yes"/>some climb upon the trees, the branches of which<lb break="yes" />extend horizontally over the surface of the water.<lb break="yes"/>By their wild cries, and the length of their reeds,<lb break="yes"/>they prevent the horses from running away, and<lb break="yes"/>reaching the bank of the pool. The eels, stunned by<lb break="yes"/>the noise, defend themselves by the repeated discharge<lb break="yes"/>of their electric power, and during a long time<lb break="yes"/>they seem to prove victorious. Several horses sink<lb break="yes"/>beneath the violence of the invisible strokes, which<lb break="yes"/>they receive from all sides, and stunned by the force<lb break="yes"/>and frequency of the shocks, disappear under the<lb break="yes" />water. Others, panting, with mane erect, and haggard<lb break="yes"/>eyes, expressing anguish, raise themselves, and en-<lb break="no"/>deavour to flee from the storm by which they are<lb break="yes"/>overtaken. They are driven back by the Indians<lb break="yes"/>into the middle of the water; but a small number<lb break="yes"/>succeed in eluding the active vigilance of the fishermen.<lb break="yes"/>These regain the shore, stumbling at every step, and<lb break="yes"/>stretch themselves on the sand, exhausted with<lb break="yes"/>fatigue, and their limbs benumbed by the electric<lb break="yes"/>shocks of the gymnoti. In less than five minutes<lb break="yes" />two horses were drowned. The eel being five feet<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>long, and pressing itself against the belly of the<lb break="yes"/>horses, makes a discharge along the whole extent of<lb break="yes"/>its electric organ. The horses are probably only<lb break="yes"/>stunned, not killed, but they are drowned from<lb break="yes"/>the impossibility of rising, amid the prolonged<lb break="yes"/>struggles between the other horses and the eels.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We had little doubt, that the fishing would termi-<lb break="no"/>nate by killing, successively, all the animals engaged;<lb break="yes"/>but, by degrees, the impetuosity of this unequal<lb break="yes"/>contest diminished, and the wearied gymnoti dispersed.<lb break="yes"/>The mules and horses appeared less frightened; their<lb break="yes"/>manes no longer bristled, and their eyes expressed<lb break="yes"/>less dread. The Gymnoti, which require a long rest<lb break="yes"/>and abundant nourishment to repair what they have<lb break="yes"/>lost of galvanic force, approach timidly the edge of<lb break="yes"/>the marsh, where they are taken by means of small<lb break="yes"/>harpoons, fastened to long cords.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Gymnotus is the largest of electrical fishes; I<lb break="yes"/>measured some that were from five to five feet three<lb break="yes"/>inches long, and the Indians assert that they have<lb break="yes"/>seen still longer. We found that a fish of three feet<lb break="yes"/>ten inches long weighed twelve pounds; the trans-<lb break="no"/>verse diameter of the body was three inches five<lb break="yes"/>lines. The Gymnoti of Cano de Bera are of a fine<lb break="yes" />olive-green; the under part of the head is yellow,<lb break="yes"/>mingled with red. Along the back are two rows of<lb break="yes"/>small yellow spots, from which exudes a slimy<lb break="yes"/>matter that spreads over the skin of the animal, and<lb break="yes"/>which, as Volta has proved, conducts electricity<lb break="yes"/>twenty or thirty times better than pure water. It is,<lb break="yes"/>in general, somewhat remarkable, that no electrical<lb break="yes"/>fish yet discovered in the different parts of the world,<lb break="yes"/>is covered with scales.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Gymnoti, which are objects of the most lively<lb break="yes"/>interest to the philosopher of Europe, are dreaded<lb break="yes"/>and detested by the natives. Their flesh furnishes<lb break="yes"/>pretty good food, but the electric organ fills the<lb break="yes"/>greater part of the body, and this being slimy and<lb break="yes"/>disagreeable to the taste, is carefully separated from<lb break="yes"/>the rest. The presence of the Gymnoti is also con-<lb break="no"/>sidered as the principal cause of the want of fish<lb break="yes"/>in the ponds and pools of the Llanos, where they<lb break="yes" />kill many more fish than they devour. The Indians<lb break="yes"/>told us, that when they take young alligators and<lb break="yes"/>gymnoti at the same time in very strong nets, the<lb break="yes"/>latter never display the slightest trace of a wound,<lb break="yes"/>because they disable the young alligators before<lb break="yes"/>they are attacked by them. All the inhabitants of<lb break="yes"/>the waters dread the Gymnoti; lizards, tortoises,<lb break="yes"/>and frogs, seek the pools, where they are secure<lb break="yes" />from their action. It became necessary to change<lb break="yes"/>the direction of a road near Uritucu, because these<lb break="yes"/>electrical eels were so numerous in one river, that<lb break="yes"/>they every year killed a great number of mules of<lb break="yes"/>burden as they forded the river.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It would be temerity to expose ourselves to the<lb break="yes"/>first shocks of a very large and strongly irritated<lb break="yes"/>Gymnotus. If by chance you receive a stroke before<lb break="yes"/>the fish is wounded, or wearied by a long pursuit,<lb break="yes"/>the pain and numbness are so violent, that it is<lb break="yes"/>impossible to describe the nature of the feeling they<lb break="yes"/>excite. I do not remember having ever received<lb break="yes" />from the discharge of an electrical machine, a more<lb break="yes"/>dreadful shock, than that which I experienced by<lb break="yes"/>imprudently placing both my feet on a Gymnotus<lb break="yes"/>just taken out of the water. I was affected the rest<lb break="yes"/>of the day with a violent pain in the knees, and<lb break="yes"/>in almost every joint.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">[<hi rendition="#k">Humboldt&#x2019;s</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Personal Narrative.</hi>]</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 