<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <p><hi rendition="#c">THE COFFEE PLANT.<lb/><hi rendition="#i">From Humboldt&#x2019;s Personal Narrative</hi><lb/></hi></p>
                <p>The coffee-tree flowers only the second<lb/>year, and the flowering lasts only twenty-<lb/>four hours. At this time the shrub has a<lb/>charming aspect; seen from afar, it seems co-<lb/>vered with snow. The produce of the third<lb/>year becomes very abundant. In plantations<lb/>well weeded and watered, and recently cul-<lb/>tivated, we find trees bearing sixteen,<lb/>eighteen, and even twenty pounds of coffee.<lb/>In general, however, a produce of more than<lb/>a pound and an half or two pounds cannot be<lb/>expected from each plant; and even this is<lb/>superior to the mean produce of the West<lb/>India islands. Rains at the time of the flow-<lb/>ering, the want of water for artificial irriga-<lb/>tions, and a parasitic plant, a new species of<lb/>Coranthus, which clings to the branches, are<lb/>extremely injurious to the coffee trees. When<lb/>in the plantations of eighty or a hundred<lb/>thousand shrubs, we consider the immense<lb/>quantity of organic matter contained in the<lb/>pulpy berry of the coffee tree, we may be a-<lb/>stonished that no attempts have been made<lb/>to extract a spiritous liquor from them.</p><lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#c">SUGAR CANES.</hi></p><lb/>
                <p>Three species of sugar cane can be distin-<lb/>guished even at a distance, by the color of<lb/>their leaves; the ancient Creole sugar cane,<lb/>the Otaheite cane, and the Batavin cane. The<lb/>first has a leaf of a deeper green, the stem<lb/>less thick, and the knots nearer together.<lb/>This sugar cane was the first introduced from<lb/>India into Sicily, the Canary Islands and the<lb/>West Indies. The second is of a lighter<lb/>green; and its stem is higher, thicker, and<lb/>more succulent. The whole plant displays<lb/>a more luxuriant vegetation. We owe this<lb/>plant to the voyages of Bougainville, Cook,<lb/>and Bligh. Bougainville carried it to the<lb/>Isle of France, whence it passed to Cayenne,<lb/>Martinique, and since 1792, to the rest of<lb/>the West India Islands. The sugar cane of<lb/>Otaheite, the <hi rendition="#i">To</hi> of those islanders, is one of<lb/>the most important acquisitions, for which<lb/>colonial agriculture is indebted to the travels<lb/>of naturalists. It yields not only one third<lb/>more of juice than the Creolian cane on the<lb/>same space of land; but from the thickness<lb/>of its stem, and the tenacity of its ligneous<lb/>fibres, it furnishes much more fuel. The last<lb/>advantage is important to the West Indies,<lb/>where the destruction of the forests has for a<lb/>long time obliged the planters to use the<lb/>canes deprived of their juice, to keep up the<lb/>fire under their boilers. But for the know-<lb/>ledge of this new plant, the progress of agri-<lb/>culture on the continent of Spanish America,<lb/>and the introduction of the East India and<lb/>Java Sugars, the revolutions of St. Domingo,<lb/>and the destruction of the great sugar plan-<lb/>tations of that island, would have had a more<lb/>sensible effect on the prices of colonial pro-<lb/>duce in Europe. The Otaheite sugar cane<lb/>was carried from the isle of Trinidad to Car-<lb/>accas. From Caraccas it passed to Cicuta<lb/>and San Gil in the kingdom of New Grena-<lb/>da. In our days its cultivation during twen-<lb/>ty-five years almost entirely removed the ap-<lb/>prehension, which was at first entertained,<lb/>that, transplanted to America, the plant<lb/>would by degrees degenerate, and become as<lb/>slender as the Creole cane. If it be a variety,<lb/>it is a very constant one. The third species,<lb/>the violet sugar-cane, called <hi rendition="#i">Cana de Batavia,</hi><lb/>or <hi rendition="#i">de Guinea,</hi> is entirely indigenous in the<lb/>island of Java, where it is cultivated in pre-<lb/>ference in the districts of Japara and pasu-<lb/>ruan. Its foliage is purple, and very broad;<lb/>and it is preferred in the province of Caracas<lb/>for rum. The <hi rendition="#i">tablones</hi> or grounds planted<lb/>with sugar canes, are divided by hedges of a<lb/>collosal gramen; the latta, or gynesium with<lb/>distich leaves.</p><lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#c">AMERICAN FIG TREES.</hi></p><lb/>
                <p>The trunks of these trees are covered with<lb/>very odoriferous plants of vanilla which in<lb/>general flower only in the month of April.<lb/>We were here again struck with those ligne-<lb/>ous excrescences, which in the form of ridges,<lb/>or ribs, augment, in so extraordinary a man-<lb/>ner, and as far as twenty feet above the<lb/>ground, the thickness of the trunk of the fig<lb/>trees of America. I found trees twenty-two<lb/>feet and a half in diameter near the roots.<lb/>These ligneous ridges sometimes separate<lb/>from the trunk at a height of eight feet, and<lb/>are transformed into cylindrical roots two feet<lb/>thick. The tree looks as if it were supported<lb/>by buttresses. This scaffolding, however,<lb/>does not penetrate very deep into the earth.<lb/>The lateral roots wind at the surface of the<lb/>ground, and, when at twenty feet distance<lb/>from the trunk, they are cut with the hatchet,<lb/>we see the milky juice of the fig-tree gush out,<lb/>which, when deprived of the vital influence of<lb/>the organs of the tree, is altered and coagu-<lb/>lates. What a wonderful combination of<lb/>cells and vessels exist in these vegetable mas-<lb/>ses; in these gigantic trees of the torrid zone,<lb/>which, without interruption, perhaps during<lb/>thousand years, prepare nutritious fluids, raise<lb/>them to the beight of 180 feet, convey them<lb/>down again to the ground, and conceal be-<lb/>neath a rough and hard bark, under the inani-<lb/>mate layers of lignous matter, all the move-<lb/>ments of organic life!</p><lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#c">THE COW TREE.</hi></p><lb/>
                <p>Amid the great number of curious pheno-<lb/>mena which have presented themselves to<lb/>me in the course of my travels, I confess<lb/>there are few that have so powerfully affect-<lb/>ed my imagination as the aspect of the cow<lb/>tree. Whatever relates to milk, whatever<lb/>regards corn, inspires an interest, which is<lb/>not merely that of the physical knowledge of<lb/>things, but is connected with another order<lb/>of ideas and sentiments. We can scarcely<lb/>conceive how the human race could exist<lb/>without <choice><sic>farnaceous</sic><corr type="editorial">farinaceous</corr></choice> substances and without<lb/>that <choice><sic>nouishing</sic><corr type="editorial">nourishing</corr></choice> juice which the breast of the<lb/>mother contains, and which is appropriated<lb/>to the long feebleness of the infant. The<lb/>amylaceous matter of corn, the object of re-<lb/>ligious veneration among so many nations,<lb/>ancient and modern, is diffused in the seeds,<lb/>and deposited in the roots of vegetables; milk,</p>
                <pb facs="#f0002"/>
                <p>which serves us as an aliment, appears to us<lb/>exclusively the produce of animal organiza-<lb/>tion. Such are the impressions we have re-<lb/>ceived in our earliest infancy; such is also<lb/>the source of that astonishment which seizes<lb/>us at the aspect of the tree just described.&#x2014;<lb/>It is not here the solemn shades of forests,<lb/>the majestic course of rivers, the mountains<lb/>wrapped in eternal frost, that excite our emo-<lb/>tion. A few drops of vegetable juice recal<lb/>to our minds all the powerfulness and fecun-<lb/>dity of nature. On the barren flank of a rock<lb/>grows a tree with coriaceous and dry leaves.<lb/>Its large woody roots can scarcely penetrate<lb/>into the stone. For several months of the<lb/>year not a single shower moistens its foliage.<lb/>Its branches appear dead and dried; but when<lb/>its trunk is pierced there flows from it a<lb/>sweet and nourishing milk. It is at the ri-<lb/>sing of the sun that this vegetable fountain is<lb/>most abundant. The blacks and natives are<lb/>then seen hastening from all quarters, fur-<lb/>nished with large bowls to receive the milk,<lb/>which grows yellow, and thickens at its sur-<lb/>face. Some employ their bowls under the<lb/>tree itself; others carry the juice home to<lb/>their children. We seem to see the family<lb/>of a shepherd, who distributes the milk to his<lb/>flock.</p>
                <p>I have described the sensation which the<lb/>cow tree awakens in the mind of the travel-<lb/>ler at the first view. In examining the phy-<lb/>sical properties of animal and vegetable pro-<lb/>ducts, science displays them as closely link-<lb/>ed together; but it strips them of what is<lb/>marvellous, and perhaps also of a part of<lb/>their charms, of what excited our aston-<lb/>ishment. Nothing appears isolated; the<lb/>chemical principles that were believed to be<lb/>peculiar to animals are found in plants; a<lb/>common chain links together all organic na-<lb/>ture.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 