<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Baron Humboldt’s Last Volume. Extract from Baron Humboldt’s Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent. Vol. 4</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:54</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">III.61</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1819-Baron_Humboldts_Extract_Heft3-1-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Extract_Heft3-1-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Extract_Heft3-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Extract_Heft3-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Extract_Heft3-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1819-Baron_Humboldts_Extract_Heft3-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>&lt;i&gt;Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent&lt;/i&gt;, Bd. 4.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 2, S. 29–33, 34–35, 47–48.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Baron Humboldt’s Last Volume. Extract from Baron Humboldt’s Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent. Vol. 4</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1819</date>
          <pubPlace>New York City, New York</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Belles-Lettres Repository, and Monthly Magazine&lt;/i&gt; 1:3 (1. Juli 1819), S. 209–212.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="209" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>BARON HUMBOLDT’S LAST VOLUME.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Extract from Baron Humboldt’s Per-<lb break="no"/>sonal Narrative of Travels to the<lb break="yes"/>Equinoctial Regions of the New<lb break="yes"/>Continent.</hi> Vol. 4.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>DEPARTURE FROM CARACCAS.</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>To take the shortest road from<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas to the banks of the Oroono-<lb break="no"/>ko, we should have crossed the<lb break="yes" />southern chain of mountains between<lb break="yes"/>Baruta, Salamanca, and the savan-<lb break="no"/>nahs of Ocumare; traversed the<lb break="yes" />steppes or <hi rendition="#i">Llanos</hi> of Orituca; and<lb break="yes" />embarked at Cabruta, near the<lb break="yes"/>mouth of the Rio Guarico. But<lb break="yes"/>this direct road would have deprived<lb break="yes" />us of the opportunity of surveying<lb break="yes"/>the finest and most cultivated part<lb break="yes"/>of the province, the valleys of Ara-<lb break="no"/>gua; of taking the level of an im-<lb break="no"/>portant part of the chain of the coast<lb break="yes"/>by means of the barometer; and of<lb break="yes"/>descending the Rio Apure as far as<lb break="yes" />its junction with the Oroonoko. A<lb break="yes"/>traveller, who has the intention of<lb break="yes"/>studying the configuration and natu-<lb break="no"/>ral riches of a country, is not guided<lb break="yes"/>by distances, but by the interest<lb break="yes"/>which the regions he may traverse<lb break="yes"/>excites in his mind. This power-<lb break="no" />ful motive led us to the mountains<lb break="yes"/>of Los Teques, to the thermal<lb break="yes"/>springs of Mariara, to the fertile<lb break="yes"/>banks of the lake of Valencia, and<lb break="yes"/>through the immense savannahs of<lb break="yes"/>Calabozo to San Fernando de Apure,<lb break="yes"/>in the eastern part of the province<lb break="yes"/>of Varinas. Following this road,<lb break="yes"/>our first direction was to the west,<lb break="yes"/>then to the south, and finally to the<lb break="yes"/>east-southeast, to enter the Oroo-<lb break="no" />noko by the Apure in the latitude of<lb break="yes"/>7° 36′ 23′.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The day that we quitted the capi-<lb break="no"/>tal of Venezuela, subsequently swal-<lb break="no"/>lowed up by terrible earthquakes,<lb break="yes"/>we reached the foot of the woody<lb break="yes"/>mountains, that close the valley to-<lb break="no"/>ward the southwest, where we<lb break="yes"/>slept. We followed the right bank<lb break="yes"/>of the Rio Guayra as far as the vil-<lb break="no"/>lage of Antimano, by a very fine road,<lb break="yes"/>partly scooped out of the rock: and<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> passed by La Vega, and Carapa.<lb break="yes"/>The church of La Vega displays it-<lb break="no"/>self in a very picturesque manner<lb break="yes" />on a range of hills covered with<lb break="yes"/>thick vegetation. Scattered houses<lb break="yes"/>are surrounded with date-trees, and<lb break="yes"/>seem to proclaim the easy circum-<lb break="no"/>stances of their inhabitants. A chain<lb break="yes"/>of low mountains separates the little<lb break="yes"/>river Guayra from the valley of <hi rendition="#i">La<lb break="yes"/>Pascua,</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="*">Valley of Cortes, or Easter Valley, so<lb break="yes"/>called because Diego de Losada, after having<lb break="yes"/>defeated the Teques Indians, and their cacique<lb break="yes"/>Guaycapuro, in the mountains of San Pedro,<lb break="yes"/>spent his Easter there in 1567, before enter-<lb break="no"/>ing the valley of San Francisco, where he<lb break="yes" />founded the city of Caraccas, (Oviedo, p.<lb break="yes"/>252.)</note> so much celebrated in the<lb break="yes"/>history of the country, and from the<lb break="yes"/>ancient gold-mines of Baruta and<lb break="yes" />Oripoto. Ascending toward Carapa,<lb break="yes"/>we enjoy once more the sight of the<lb break="yes"/>Silla, which appears like an immense<lb break="yes"/>dome with a cliff toward the sea.<lb break="yes"/>This rounded summit, and the ridge<lb break="yes"/>of Galipano crenated like a wall, are<lb break="yes"/>the only objects that, in this basin<lb break="yes"/>of gneiss and mica-slate, impress a<lb break="yes" />character on the landscape. The<lb break="yes"/>other mountains are of a uniform and<lb break="yes"/>dull monotonous aspect.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Near Antimano all the orchards<lb break="yes"/>were full of peach-trees loaded with<lb break="yes"/>flowers. This village, the <hi rendition="#i" >Valle,</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the Macarao, furnish<lb break="yes"/>great abundance of peaches, quinces,<lb break="yes"/>and other European fruits, for the<lb break="yes"/>market of Caraccas. Between An-<lb break="no"/>timano and Ajuntas we crossed the<lb break="yes"/>Rio Guayra seventeen times. The<lb break="yes"/>road is very fatiguing; yet, instead of<lb break="yes"/>constituting a new one, it would per-<lb break="no"/>haps be better to change the bed of<lb break="yes"/>the river, which loses a great quan-<lb break="no"/>tity of water by the combined effects<lb break="yes"/>of filtration and evaporation. Each<lb break="yes"/>sinuosity forms a marsh more or less<lb break="yes" />extensive. This loss of water is to<lb break="yes"/>be regretted in a province, the whole<lb break="yes"/>cultivated region of which, with the<lb break="yes"/>exception of the land between the<lb break="yes"/>sea and the littoral chain of Mariara<lb break="yes"/>and Niguatar, is extremely dry. The<lb break="yes"/>rains are much less frequent and less<lb break="yes"/>violent in this place than in the inte-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="210" facs="#f0002"/>
                        <cb/> rior of New Andalusia, at Cumanacoa,<lb break="yes"/>and on the banks of the Guarapiche.<lb break="yes"/>Many of the mountains of Caraccas<lb break="yes"/>enter the region of the clouds; but<lb break="yes"/>the strata of primitive rocks dip at<lb break="yes"/>an angle of 70° or 80°, and general-<lb break="no"/>ly toward the northwest, so that the<lb break="yes"/>waters are either lost in the interior<lb break="yes"/>of the earth, or gush out in copious<lb break="yes"/>springs, not toward the south, but to<lb break="yes"/>the north of the mountains of the<lb break="yes"/>coast of Niguatar, Avila, and Mariara.<lb break="yes"/>The rising of the gneiss and mica-<lb break="no"/>slate strata toward the south appears<lb break="yes"/>to me to explain, in great part, the<lb break="yes"/>extreme humidity of the coast. In<lb break="yes"/>the interior of the province we meet<lb break="yes"/>with spaces of land, two or three<lb break="yes"/>leagues square, quite destitute of<lb break="yes" />springs. The sugar-cane, indigo,<lb break="yes"/>and coffee, can grow only in places<lb break="yes"/>where running waters can be made<lb break="yes" />to supply the artificial irrigations ne-<lb break="no"/>cessary during very dry weather.<lb break="yes"/>The first colonists very imprudently<lb break="yes"/>destroyed the forests. Evaporation<lb break="yes"/>is enormous on a stony soil surround-<lb break="no"/>ed with rocks, that radiate heat on<lb break="yes"/>every side. The mountains of the<lb break="yes"/>coast appear like a wall, extending<lb break="yes"/>east and west from Cape Codera to-<lb break="no"/>ward Point Tucacas. They prevent<lb break="yes"/>the humid air of the shore, those in-<lb break="no"/>ferior strata of the atmosphere rest-<lb break="no"/>ing immediately on the sea, and dis-<lb break="no"/>solving the largest proportion of wa-<lb break="no"/>ter, from penetrating to the inlands.<lb break="yes"/>There are few apertures, few ra-<lb break="no"/>vines, which, like those of Catia, or<lb break="yes"/>of Tipe, lead from the coast to the<lb break="yes"/>high longitudinal valleys. No bed<lb break="yes"/>of a great river, no gulf allowing the<lb break="yes"/>sea to flow into the lands, spreads<lb break="yes"/>moisture by an abundant evaporation.<lb break="yes"/>In the eighth and tenth degrees of lati-<lb break="no" />tude, in regions where the clouds do<lb break="yes"/>not glide along the soil, many trees<lb break="yes"/>are stripped of their leaves in the<lb break="yes"/>months of January and February;<lb break="yes"/>not on account of the sinking of the<lb break="yes"/>temperature, as in Europe, but be-<lb break="no"/>cause the air, at this season, the far-<lb break="no" />thest from that of rains, has nearly<lb break="yes"/>attained its maximum of dryness.<lb break="yes"/>The plants with very tough and<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> glossy leaves alone resist this ab-<lb break="no"/>sence of humidity. Beneath the fine<lb break="yes"/>sky of the tropics, the traveller is<lb break="yes"/>struck with the aspect almost hiber-<lb break="no"/>nal of the country; but the freshest<lb break="yes"/>verdure again appears, when he has<lb break="yes"/>reached the banks of the Oroonoko,<lb break="yes" />where another climate prevails; and<lb break="yes"/>the great forests preserve by their<lb break="yes"/>shade a certain quantity of moisture<lb break="yes"/>in the soil, which they shelter from<lb break="yes"/>the devouring ardour of the sun.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Beyond the small village of Anti-<lb break="no"/>mano the valley becomes much nar-<lb break="no"/>rower. The river is bordered with<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">lata,</hi> that fine gramineous plant with<lb break="yes" />distich leaves, which sometimes<lb break="yes"/>reaches the height of thirty feet, and<lb break="yes"/>which we have described under the<lb break="yes"/>name of <hi rendition="#i">gynerium.</hi> Every hut is sur-<lb break="no"/>rounded with enormous trees of per-<lb break="no" />sea, at the foot of which the aris-<lb break="no"/>tolochiæ, paullinia, and other creep-<lb break="no"/>ers, vegetate. The neighbouring<lb break="yes"/>mountains, covered with forests,<lb break="yes"/>seem to spread humidity over the<lb break="yes"/>western extremity of the valley of<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas. We passed the night in<lb break="yes"/>a plantation of sugar-canes, before<lb break="yes"/>our arrival at Las Ajuntas. A square<lb break="yes"/>house contained nearly eighty ne-<lb break="no"/>groes; they were lying on skins<lb break="yes"/>of oxen spread upon the ground. In<lb break="yes"/>each apartment of the house were<lb break="yes"/>four slaves; it looked like a barrack.<lb break="yes"/>A dozen fires were burning in the<lb break="yes" />farm-yard, where people were em-<lb break="no"/>ployed in dressing victuals. We<lb break="yes"/>were again struck with the noisy<lb break="yes" />mirth of the blacks, which almost<lb break="yes"/>prevented us from sleeping. The<lb break="yes"/>clouds hindered me from observing<lb break="yes"/>the stars; the moon appeared only<lb break="yes"/>at intervals. The aspect of the land-<lb break="no"/>scape was dull and uniform, and all<lb break="yes"/>the surrounding hills were covered<lb break="yes"/>with aloes. Workmen were em-<lb break="no"/>ployed at a small canal, which was<lb break="yes"/>intended to convey the waters of the<lb break="yes"/>Rio San Pedro to the farm, at a height<lb break="yes"/>of more than seventy feet. Accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to a barometic calculation, the<lb break="yes"/>site of the <hi rendition="#i" >hacienda</hi> is only fifty toises<lb break="yes"/>above the bed of the Rio Guayra at<lb break="yes"/>La Noria, near Caraccas.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="211" facs="#f0003"/>
                    <cb/>
                </div>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>COFFEE-TREE.</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The soil of these countries has<lb break="yes"/>been found but little favorable to the<lb break="yes"/>cultivation of the coffee-tree, which<lb break="yes"/>in general is less productive in the<lb break="yes"/>valley of Caraccas, than was imagined<lb break="yes"/>when the first plantations were made<lb break="yes"/>near Chacao. In order to form a<lb break="yes" />general idea of the importance of this<lb break="yes"/>branch of commerce, we must re-<lb break="no"/>member, that the produce of the<lb break="yes" />whole province of Caraccas in its<lb break="yes"/>greatest prosperity, before the revo-<lb break="no"/>lutionary wars of 1812, amounted to<lb break="yes"/>fifty or sixty thousand quintals of<lb break="yes"/>coffee. This quantity, almost equal<lb break="yes"/>to the produce of Guadaloupe and<lb break="yes"/>Martinico both together, must appear<lb break="yes" />so much the more considerable, as<lb break="yes"/>it is only since 1781 that a respect-<lb break="no"/>able citizen, Don Bartholomew Blan-<lb break="no"/>din, endeavoured to introduce this<lb break="yes"/>branch of culture on the coasts of<lb break="yes"/>Terra Firma. Mr. Depons, in his<lb break="yes"/>statistical account of the Capitania-<lb break="maybe" />general of Venezuela, having been<lb break="yes"/>able to give information respecting<lb break="yes"/>the state of commerce and agricul-<lb break="no"/>ture only as far as the year 1804, it<lb break="yes"/>will not be uninteresting to add some<lb break="yes"/>of a more recent date, and not less<lb break="yes"/>exact. The finest coffee-plantations<lb break="yes" />are now found in the savannah of<lb break="yes"/>Ocumare, near Salamanca, and at<lb break="yes"/>Rincon, in the mountainous countries<lb break="yes" />of Los Mariches, San Antonio Hatillo,<lb break="yes"/>and Los Budares. The coffee of<lb break="yes"/>the last three places, to the east of<lb break="yes"/>Caraccas, is of a superior quality,<lb break="yes"/>but the trees bear a smaller quantity,<lb break="yes"/>which is attributed to the height of<lb break="yes"/>the spot, and the coolness of the<lb break="yes" />climate. The greater plantations of<lb break="yes"/>the province of Venezuela, as Agua-<lb break="no"/>cates, near Valencia, and Rincon,<lb break="yes"/>yield in good years a produce of three<lb break="yes" />thousand quintals. In 1796 the to-<lb break="no"/>tal exportation of the province was<lb break="yes"/>only four thousand eight hundred<lb break="yes" />quintals, and in 1804, ten thousand;<lb break="yes"/>yet it began in 1789. The prices<lb break="yes"/>varied from six to eighteen piastres<lb break="yes"/>per quintal. At the Havana it has<lb break="yes"/>sunk as low as three piastres; but<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> at this period, so disastrous for the<lb break="yes"/>planters, in 1810 and 1812, more than<lb break="yes"/>two millions of quintals of coffee,<lb break="yes"/>amounting in value to ten millions<lb break="yes"/>sterling, were accumulated in the<lb break="yes" />warehouses of England.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The extreme predilection enter-<lb break="no"/>tained in this province for the culture<lb break="yes"/>of the coffee-tree is partly founded<lb break="yes"/>on the circumstance, that the berry<lb break="yes"/>can be preserved during a great num-<lb break="no"/>ber of years; whereas, notwithstand-<lb break="no"/>ing every possible care, cocoa spoils<lb break="yes"/>in the warehouses after ten or twelve<lb break="yes" />months. During the long dissensions<lb break="yes"/>of the European powers, at a time<lb break="yes"/>when the metropolis was too weak<lb break="yes"/>to protect the commerce of the colo-<lb break="no"/>nies, industry was directed in prefer-<lb break="no"/>ence towards productions, of which<lb break="yes"/>the sale was less urgent, and could<lb break="yes" />wait the chances of political and<lb break="yes"/>commercial events. I remarked,<lb break="yes"/>that, in the coffee-plantations, the<lb break="yes"/>nurseries are formed not so much<lb break="yes"/>by collecting together those young<lb break="yes"/>plants which accidentally rise under<lb break="yes"/>trees that have yielded a crop, as<lb break="yes" />by exposing the seeds of coffee to<lb break="yes"/>germination during five days, in heaps<lb break="yes"/>between plantain leaves. These<lb break="yes" />seeds are taken out of the pulp, but<lb break="yes"/>yet retaining a part of it adherent to<lb break="yes"/>them. When this seed has germi-<lb break="no"/>nated, it is sown, and produces plants<lb break="yes"/>that can bear the ardour of the sun<lb break="yes"/>better than those that spring up in the<lb break="yes"/>shade in the coffee-plantations. In<lb break="yes" />this country five thousand three hun-<lb break="no"/>dred coffee-trees are generally plant-<lb break="no"/>ed in a <hi rendition="#i">vanega</hi> of ground, amounting<lb break="yes"/>to five thousand four hundred and<lb break="yes"/>seventy-six square toises. This<lb break="yes"/>land, if it be capable of artificial irri-<lb break="no"/>gation, costs five hundred piastres in<lb break="yes"/>the northern part of the province.<lb break="yes"/>The coffee-tree bears flowers only<lb break="yes"/>the second year, and its flowering<lb break="yes"/>lasts only twenty-four hours. At this<lb break="yes"/>time the shrub has a charming as-<lb break="no" />pect; seen from afar, it appears co-<lb break="no"/>vered with snow. The produce of<lb break="yes"/>the third year becomes very abun-<lb break="no" />dant. In plantations well weeded<lb break="yes"/>and watered, and recently cultivated,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="212" facs="#f0004"/>
                        <cb/> we find trees bearing sixteen, eigh-<lb break="no"/>teen, and even twenty pounds of cof-<lb break="no"/>fee. In general, however, a produce<lb break="yes"/>of more than a pound and an half or<lb break="yes"/>two pounds cannot be expected from<lb break="yes"/>each plant; and even this is superior<lb break="yes"/>to the mean produce of the West-In-<lb break="no"/>dia Islands. Rains at the time of<lb break="yes"/>flowering, the want of water for arti-<lb break="no"/>ficial irrigations, and a parasitic<lb break="yes"/>plant, a new species of loranthus,<lb break="yes"/>which clings to the branches, are ex-<lb break="no" />tremely injurious to the coffee-trees.<lb break="yes"/>When, in plantations of eighty or a<lb break="yes"/>hundred thousand shrubs, we consi-<lb break="no"/>der the immense quantity of organic<lb break="yes" />matter contained in the pulpy berry<lb break="yes"/>of the coffee-tree, we may be aston-<lb break="no"/>ished that no attempts have been<lb break="yes" />made to extract a spirituous liquor<lb break="yes"/>from them.</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>FIG-TREE.</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We were here struck with those<lb break="yes"/>ligneous excrescences, which in the<lb break="yes"/>form of ridges, or ribs, augment in<lb break="yes" />so extraordinary a manner, and as<lb break="yes"/>far as twenty feet above the ground,<lb break="yes"/>the thickness of the trunk of the fig-<lb break="no"/>trees of America. I found trees<lb break="yes"/>twenty-two feet and a half in diame-<lb break="no"/>ter near the roots<hi rendition="#i">:</hi> These ligneous<lb break="yes"/>ridges sometimes separate from the<lb break="yes"/>trunk at a height of eight feet, and<lb break="yes"/>are transformed into cylindrical roots<lb break="yes"/>two feet thick. The tree looks as<lb break="yes"/>if it were supported by buttresses.<lb break="yes"/>This scaffolding however does not<lb break="yes"/>penetrate very deep into the earth.<lb break="yes"/>The lateral roots wind at the surface<lb break="yes"/>of the ground, and when at twenty<lb break="yes"/>feet distance from the trunk, they<lb break="yes" />are cut with a hatchet: we see the<lb break="yes"/>milky juice of the fig-tree gush out,<lb break="yes"/>which, when deprived of the vital<lb break="yes"/>influence of the organs of the tree,<lb break="yes"/>is altered and coagulates. What a<lb break="yes"/>wonderful combination of cells and<lb break="yes"/>vessels exists in these vegetable<lb break="yes" />masses, in these gigantic trees of the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone, which without interrup-<lb break="no"/>tion, perhaps during a thousand<lb break="yes"/>years, prepare nutritious fluids, raise<lb break="yes" />them to the height of one hundred<lb break="yes"/>and eighty feet, convey them down<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> again to the ground, and conceal be-<lb break="no"/>neath a rough and hard bark, under<lb break="yes"/>the inaminate layers of ligneous mat-<lb break="no"/>ter, all the movements of organic<lb break="yes"/>life!</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 