<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/132876787">
                        <surname>Welge</surname>
                        <forename>Jobst</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.1" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="321" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>THE GYMNOTUS, OR ELECTRICAL EEL.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Extract from Baron Humboldt&#x2019;s Per-<lb break="no"/>sonal Narrative of Travels to the<lb break="yes"/>Equinoctial Regions of the New<lb break="yes"/>Continent. Vol.</hi> 4.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I was impatient, from the time of<lb break="yes"/>my arrival at Cumana, to procure<lb break="yes"/>electrical eels. We had been pro-<lb break="no" />mised them often, but our hopes had<lb break="yes"/>always been disappointed. Money<lb break="yes"/>loses its value as you withdraw from<lb break="yes" />the coast; and how is the impertur-<lb break="no"/>bable phlegm of the vulgar to be van-<lb break="no"/>quished, when they are not excited<lb break="yes"/>by the desire of gain?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Spaniards confound all elec-<lb break="no"/>trical fishes under the name of <hi rendition="#i">tem-<lb break="no"/>bladores,</hi> (<hi rendition="#i" >producers of trembling,</hi> lite-<lb break="no"/>rally <hi rendition="#i" >tremblers.</hi>) There are some<lb break="yes"/>in the Caribbean sea, on the coast of<lb break="yes"/>Cumana. The Guayqueria Indians,<lb break="yes"/>who are the most skilful and indus-<lb break="no"/>trious fishermen in those parts,<lb break="yes"/>brought us a fish, which, they said,<lb break="yes" />had benumbed their hands. This<lb break="yes"/>fish ascends the little river Manza-<lb break="no"/>nares. It is a new species of the<lb break="yes"/>ray, the lateral spots of which are<lb break="yes"/>scarcely visible, and which much re-<lb break="no"/>sembles the torpedo of Galvani.<lb break="yes"/>The torpedoes, furnished with an<lb break="yes"/>electric organ that is externally visi-<lb break="no"/>ble, on account of the transparency<lb break="yes"/>of the skin, form a genus or subge-<lb break="no"/>nus, different from the rays properly<lb break="yes"/>so called. The torpedo of Cumana<lb break="yes" />was very lively, very energetic in its<lb break="yes"/>muscular movements, and yet the<lb break="yes"/>electrical shocks it gave us were<lb break="yes" />extremely feeble. They became<lb break="yes"/>stronger on <hi rendition="#i" >galvanizing</hi> the animal<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>by the contact of zinc and gold.<lb break="yes"/>Other <hi rendition="#i" >tembladores,</hi> real gymnoti or<lb break="yes"/>electrical eels, inhabit the Rio Co-<lb break="no"/>lorado, the Guarapiche, and several<lb break="yes" />little streams that cross the missions<lb break="yes"/>of the Chayma Indians. They<lb break="yes"/>abound also in the large rivers of<lb break="yes" />America, the Oroonoko, the Ama-<lb break="no"/>zon, and the Meta: but the strength<lb break="yes"/>of the current, and the depth of the<lb break="yes" />water, prevent their being caught by<lb break="yes"/>the Indians. They see these fish<lb break="yes"/>less frequently than they feel elec-<lb break="no" />trical shocks from them when swim-<lb break="no"/>ming or bathing in the river. In<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">Llanos,</hi> particularly in the envi-<lb break="no"/>rons of Calabozo, between the farms<lb break="yes"/>of Morichal and the missions <hi rendition="#i">de arri-<lb break="no"/>ba</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">de abaxo,</hi> the basins of stag-<lb break="no"/>nant water, and the confluents of the<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko (the Rio Guarico and the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Canos</hi> of Rastro, Berito, and Paloma)<lb break="yes"/>are filled with electrical eels. We<lb break="yes"/>at first wished to make our experi-<lb break="no"/>ments in the house we inhabited at<lb break="yes" />Calabozo; but the dread of the elec-<lb break="no"/>trical shocks of the gymnoti is so<lb break="yes"/>great, and so exaggerated among the<lb break="yes" />vulgar, that during three days we<lb break="yes"/>could not obtain one, though they<lb break="yes"/>are easily caught, and we had pro-<lb break="no"/>mised the Indians two piastres for<lb break="yes"/>every strong and vigorous fish. This<lb break="yes"/>fear of the Indians is the more extra-<lb break="no" />ordinary, as they do not attempt to<lb break="yes"/>employ means in which they profess<lb break="yes"/>to have great confidence. When in-<lb break="no" />terrogated on the effect of the <hi rendition="#i">tem-<lb break="no" />bladores,</hi> they never fail to tell the<lb break="yes"/>whites that they may be touched<lb break="yes"/>with impunity, while you are chew-<lb break="no"/>ing tobacco. This fable of the influ-<lb break="no"/>ence of tobacco on animal electricity<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="322" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>is as general on the continent of<lb break="yes"/>South America, as the belief among<lb break="yes"/>mariners of the effect of garlic and<lb break="yes" />tallow on the magnetic needle.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Impatient of waiting, and having<lb break="yes"/>obtained very uncertain results from<lb break="yes"/>an electrical eel that had been<lb break="yes"/>brought to us alive, but much enfee-<lb break="no"/>bled, we repaired to the Cano de<lb break="yes"/>Bera, to make our experiments in<lb break="yes"/>the open air, on the borders of the<lb break="yes"/>water itself. We set off on the 19th<lb break="yes"/>of March, at a very early hour, for<lb break="yes"/>the village of <hi rendition="#i">Rastro de abaxo;</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>thence we were conducted by the<lb break="yes"/>Indians to a stream, which, in the<lb break="yes"/>time of drought, forms a basin of<lb break="yes"/>muddy water, surrounded by fine<lb break="yes"/>trees, the clusia, the amyris, and the<lb break="yes"/>mimosa with fragrant flowers. To<lb break="yes"/>catch the gymnoti with nets is very<lb break="yes"/>difficult, on account of the extreme<lb break="yes"/>agility of the fish, which bury them-<lb break="no"/>selves in the mud like serpents. We<lb break="yes" />would not employ the <hi rendition="#i">barbasco,</hi> that<lb break="yes"/>is to say, the roots of the piscidea<lb break="yes"/>erithryna, jacquinia armillaris, and<lb break="yes"/>some species of phyllanthus, which,<lb break="yes"/>thrown into the pool, intoxicate or<lb break="yes"/>benumb these animals. These<lb break="yes"/>means would have enfeebled the<lb break="yes"/>gymnoti; the Indians, therefore,<lb break="yes"/>told us, that they would &#x201C;fish with<lb break="yes"/>horses,&#x201D; <hi rendition="#i">embarbascar con cavallos.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>We found it difficult to form an idea<lb break="yes"/>of this extraordinary manner of fish-<lb break="no"/>ing; but we soon saw our guides re-<lb break="no"/>turn from the savannah, which they<lb break="yes"/>had been scouring for wild horses<lb break="yes"/>and mules. They brought about<lb break="yes"/>thirty with them, which they forced<lb break="yes"/>to enter the pool.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The extraordinary noise caused<lb break="yes"/>by the horses&#x2019; hoofs makes the fish<lb break="yes"/>issue from the mud, and excites them<lb break="yes"/>to combat. These yellowish and<lb break="yes"/>livid eels, resembling large aquatic<lb break="yes"/>serpents, swim on the surface of the<lb break="yes" />water, and crowd under the bellies<lb break="yes"/>of the horses and mules. A contest<lb break="yes"/>between animals of so different an<lb break="yes" />organization furnishes a very striking<lb break="yes"/>spectacle. The Indians, provided<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>with harpoons and long slender reeds,<lb break="yes"/>surround the pool closely; and some<lb break="yes"/>climb upon the trees, the branches<lb break="yes"/>of which extend horizontally over<lb break="yes"/>the surface of the water. By their<lb break="yes"/>wild cries, and the length of their<lb break="yes"/>reeds, they prevent the horses from<lb break="yes"/>running away, and reaching the bank<lb break="yes"/>of the pool. The eels, stunned by<lb break="yes"/>the noise, defend themselves by the<lb break="yes"/>repeated discharge of their electric<lb break="yes"/>batteries. During a long time they<lb break="yes"/>seem to prove victorious. Several<lb break="yes" />horses sink beneath the violence of<lb break="yes"/>the invisible strokes, which they re-<lb break="no"/>ceive from all sides in organs the<lb break="yes" />most essential to life; and stunned<lb break="yes"/>by the force and frequency of the<lb break="yes"/>shocks, disappear under the water.<lb break="yes" />Others, panting, with mane erect,<lb break="yes"/>and haggard eyes, expressing anguish,<lb break="yes"/>raise themselves, and endeavour to<lb break="yes" />flee from the storm by which they<lb break="yes"/>are overtaken. They are driven<lb break="yes"/>back by the Indians into the middle<lb break="yes" />of the water; but a small number<lb break="yes"/>succeed in eluding the active vigi-<lb break="no"/>lance of the fisherman. These re-<lb break="no"/>gain the shore, stumbling at every<lb break="yes"/>step, and stretch themselves on the<lb break="yes"/>sand, exhausted with fatigue, and<lb break="yes"/>their limbs benumbed by the elec-<lb break="no"/>tric shocks of the gymnoti.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In less than five minutes two<lb break="yes"/>horses were drowned. The eel,<lb break="yes"/>being five feet long, and pressing<lb break="yes"/>itself against the belly of the horses,<lb break="yes"/>makes a discharge along the whole<lb break="yes"/>extent of its electric organ. It at-<lb break="no" />tacks at once the heart, the intes-<lb break="no"/>tines, and the <hi rendition="#i">plexus c&#x0153;liacus</hi> of the<lb break="yes"/>abdominal nerves. It is natural, that<lb break="yes"/>the effect felt by the horses should<lb break="yes"/>be more powerful than that produ-<lb break="no"/>ced upon man by the touch of the<lb break="yes"/>same fish at only one of his extremi-<lb break="no"/>ties. The horses are probably not<lb break="yes"/>killed, but only stunned. They are<lb break="yes"/>drowned from the impossibility of<lb break="yes"/>rising amid the prolonged struggle<lb break="yes"/>between the other horses and the<lb break="yes"/>eels.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We had little doubt, that the fish-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="323" facs="#f0003"/>
                    <cb/>ing would terminate by killing suc-<lb break="no"/>cessively all the animals engaged;<lb break="yes"/>but by degrees the impetuosity of this<lb break="yes"/>unequal combat diminished, and the<lb break="yes"/>wearied gymnoti dispersed. They<lb break="yes"/>require a long rest, and abundant<lb break="yes"/>nourishment, to repair what they<lb break="yes"/>have lost of galvanic force. The<lb break="yes"/>mules and horses appear less fright-<lb break="no"/>ened; their manes are no longer<lb break="yes"/>bristled, and their eyes express<lb break="yes"/>less dread. The gymnoti approach<lb break="yes"/>timidly the edge of the marsh, where<lb break="yes"/>they are taken by means of small<lb break="yes"/>harpoons fastened to long cords.<lb break="yes"/>When the cords are very dry the<lb break="yes"/>Indians feel no shock in raising the<lb break="yes"/>fish into the air. In a few minutes<lb break="yes"/>we had five large eels, the greater<lb break="yes"/>part of which were but slightly<lb break="yes"/>wounded. Some were taken by the<lb break="yes"/>same means toward the evening.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The temperature of the waters in<lb break="yes"/>which the gymnoti habitually live,<lb break="yes"/>is from 26&#x00B0; to 27&#x00B0;. Their electric<lb break="yes" />force diminishes, it is said, in colder<lb break="yes"/>waters; and it is remarkable, that in<lb break="yes"/>general, as a celebrated naturalist<lb break="yes"/>has already observed, animals endow-<lb break="no"/>ed with electromotive organs, the<lb break="yes"/>effects of which are sensible to man,<lb break="yes"/>are not found in the air, but in a fluid<lb break="yes" />that is a conductor of electricity.<lb break="yes"/>The gymnotus is the largest of elec-<lb break="no"/>trical fishes. I measured some that<lb break="yes"/>were from five feet to five feet three<lb break="yes"/>inches long; and the Indians assert<lb break="yes"/>that they have seen still longer. We<lb break="yes"/>found that a fish of three feet ten<lb break="yes" />inches long weighed twelve pounds.<lb break="yes"/>The transverse diameter of the body,<lb break="yes"/>without reckoning the anal fin, which<lb break="yes" />is elongated in the form of a keel,<lb break="yes"/>was three inches five lines. The<lb break="yes"/>gymnoti of <hi rendition="#i">Cano de Bera</hi> are of a<lb break="yes"/>fine olive green. The under part<lb break="yes"/>of the head is yellow, mingled with<lb break="yes"/>red. Two rows of small yellow<lb break="yes"/>spots are placed symmetrically along<lb break="yes"/>the back, from the head to the end<lb break="yes"/>of the tail. Every spot contains an<lb break="yes"/>excretory aperture. In conse-<lb break="no"/>quence, the skin of the animal is<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>constantly covered with a mucous<lb break="yes"/>matter, which, as Volta has proved,<lb break="yes"/>conducts electricity twenty or thirty<lb break="yes" />times better than pure water. It is,<lb break="yes"/>in general, somewhat remarkable,<lb break="yes"/>that no electrical fish, yet discover-<lb break="no"/>ed in the different parts of the world,<lb break="yes"/>is covered with scales.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The gymnoti, like our eels, are<lb break="yes"/>fond of swallowing and breathing air<lb break="yes"/>on the surface of the water; but we<lb break="yes"/>must not thence conclude with Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Bajon, that the fish would perish if<lb break="yes"/>it could not come up to breathe the<lb break="yes"/>air. Our eels wander a part of the<lb break="yes"/>night upon the grass, while I have<lb break="yes"/>seen a very vigorous gymnotus, that<lb break="yes"/>had sprung out of the tub, die on<lb break="yes"/>the ground. Mr. Proven&#x00E7;al and<lb break="yes"/>myself have proved, by our re-<lb break="no"/>searches on the respiration of fishes,<lb break="yes"/>that their humid bronchi&#x00E6; can exe-<lb break="no"/>cute the double function of decom-<lb break="no"/>posing the atmospheric air, and of<lb break="yes"/>appropriating the oxygen dissolved<lb break="yes"/>in water. They do not suspend<lb break="yes"/>their respiration in the air; but they<lb break="yes"/>absorb the gazeous oxygen, like a<lb break="yes"/>reptile furnished with lungs. It is<lb break="yes"/>known that carp may be fatten-<lb break="no"/>ed by being fed out of the water,<lb break="yes"/>and wetting their gills from time to<lb break="yes"/>time with humid moss, to prevent<lb break="yes"/>their drying. Fish separate their<lb break="yes"/>gill covers wider in oxygen gas, than<lb break="yes"/>in water. Their temperature, how-<lb break="no"/>ever, does not rise; and they live the<lb break="yes"/>same length of time in pure vital air,<lb break="yes"/>and in a mixture of ninety parts azot,<lb break="yes"/>and ten oxygen. We found, that<lb break="yes"/>tench (cyprinus tinca) placed under<lb break="yes"/>inverted jars filled with air, absorb<lb break="yes"/>half a cubic centimetre of oxygen in<lb break="yes"/>an hour. This action takes place in<lb break="yes"/>the gills only; for fishes, on which a<lb break="yes"/>collar of cork has been fastened,<lb break="yes"/>and leaving their head out of the<lb break="yes" />jar filled with air, do not act upon<lb break="yes"/>the oxygen by the rest of their<lb break="yes"/>body.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It would be temerity to expose<lb break="yes"/>ourselves to the first shocks of a very<lb break="yes"/>large and strongly irritated gymno-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="324" facs="#f0004"/>
                    <cb/>tus. If by chance you receive a<lb break="yes"/>stroke before the fish is wounded or<lb break="yes"/>wearied by a long pursuit, the pain<lb break="yes" />and numbness are so violent that it<lb break="yes"/>is impossible to describe the nature<lb break="yes"/>of the feeling they excite. I do not<lb break="yes" />remember having ever received from<lb break="yes"/>the discharge of a large Leyden jar,<lb break="yes"/>a more dreadful shock than that<lb break="yes" />which I experienced by imprudently<lb break="yes"/>placing both my feet on a gymnotus<lb break="yes"/>just taken out of the water. I was<lb break="yes" />affected the rest of the day with a vio-<lb break="no"/>lent pain in the knees, and in almost<lb break="yes"/>every joint. To be aware of the dif-<lb break="no"/>ference, which is sufficiently strik-<lb break="no"/>ing, that exists between the sensa-<lb break="no"/>tion produced by the pile of Volta<lb break="yes"/>and an electrical fish, the latter<lb break="yes"/>should be touched when they are in<lb break="yes"/>a state of extreme weakness. The<lb break="yes"/>gymnoti and the torpedoes then cause<lb break="yes"/>a twitching, which is propagated<lb break="yes"/>from the part that rests on the elec-<lb break="no"/>tric organs as far as the elbow. We<lb break="yes" />seem to feel at every stroke an in-<lb break="no"/>ternal vibration that lasts two or three<lb break="yes"/>seconds, and is followed by a pain-<lb break="no" />ful numbness. Accordingly, the<lb break="yes"/>Tamanac Indians call the <hi rendition="#i">temblador,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>in their expressive language, <hi rendition="#i">arimna,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>which means <hi rendition="#i">something that deprives<lb break="yes"/>of motion.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The sensation caused by the fee-<lb break="no"/>ble shocks of an electrical eel ap-<lb break="no"/>peared to me analogous to that pain-<lb break="no"/>ful twitching, with which I have<lb break="yes"/>been seized at each contact of two<lb break="yes"/>heterogeneous metals applied to<lb break="yes"/>wounds, which I had made on my<lb break="yes"/>back by means of cantharides. This<lb break="yes"/>difference of sensation between the<lb break="yes"/>effects of electrical fishes and those<lb break="yes"/>of the pile, or a Leyden vial weakly<lb break="yes"/>charged, has struck every observer;<lb break="yes" />there is, however, nothing in this<lb break="yes"/>contrary to the supposition of the<lb break="yes"/>identity of electricity and the galva-<lb break="no"/>nic action of fishes. The electricity<lb break="yes"/>may be the same; but its effects<lb break="yes"/>will be variously modified by the<lb break="yes" />disposition of the electrical apparatus,<lb break="yes"/>by the intensity of the fluid, by the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>rapidity of the current, and by a<lb break="yes"/>particular mode of action.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In Dutch Guyana, at Demerary,<lb break="yes"/>for instance, electrical eels were for-<lb break="no"/>merly employed to cure the paraly-<lb break="no"/>tic. At a time when the physicians<lb break="yes"/>of Europe had a great confidence in<lb break="yes"/>the effects of electricity, a surgeon<lb break="yes"/>of Essequibo, Mr. Vander Lott, pub-<lb break="no"/>lished in Holland a treatise on the<lb break="yes"/>medical properties of the gymnoti.<lb break="yes"/>These <hi rendition="#i">electrical cures</hi> are found<lb break="yes"/>among the savages of America, as<lb break="yes"/>well as among the Greeks. We are<lb break="yes"/>told by Scribonius Largus, Galen,<lb break="yes"/>and Dioscorides, that torpedoes cure<lb break="yes"/>the <choice>
                        <sic>headach</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">headache</corr>
                    </choice> and the gout. I did not<lb break="yes"/>hear of this species of remedy in<lb break="yes"/>the Spanish colonies which I visited;<lb break="yes"/>but I can assert, that, after having<lb break="yes"/>made experiments during four hours<lb break="yes"/>successively with gymnoti, Mr. Bon-<lb break="no" />pland and myself felt till the next<lb break="yes"/>day a debility in the muscles, a pain<lb break="yes"/>in the joints, and a general uneasi-<lb break="no"/>ness, which was the effect of a strong<lb break="yes" />irritation of the nervous system.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Gymnoti are neither charged con-<lb break="no"/>ductors, nor batteries, nor electro-<lb break="no"/>motive apparatuses, the shock of<lb break="yes" />which is received every time they<lb break="yes"/>are touched with one hand, or when<lb break="yes"/>both hands are applied to form a<lb break="yes" />conducting circle between two hete-<lb break="no"/>rogeneous poles. The electric ac-<lb break="no"/>tion of the fish depends entirely on<lb break="yes" />its will; whether because it do not<lb break="yes"/>keep its electric organs always<lb break="yes"/>charged, or by the secretion of some<lb break="yes" />fluid, or by any other means alike<lb break="yes"/>mysterious to us, it be capable of di-<lb break="no"/>recting the action of its organs to an<lb break="yes"/>external object. We often tried,<lb break="yes"/>both insulated and uninsulated, to<lb break="yes"/>touch the fish, without feeling the<lb break="yes"/>least shock. When Mr. Bonpland<lb break="yes"/>held it by the head, or by the middle<lb break="yes"/>of the body, while I held it by the<lb break="yes"/>tail, and, standing on the moist<lb break="yes"/>ground, did not take each others<lb break="yes"/>hand, one of us received shocks<lb break="yes"/>which the other did not feel. It de-<lb break="no"/>pends upon the gymnotus to act to-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="325" facs="#f0005"/>
                    <cb/>ward the point, where it finds itself<lb break="yes"/>the most strongly irritated. The<lb break="yes"/>discharge is then made at one point<lb break="yes"/>only, and not at the neighbouring<lb break="yes"/>points. If two persons touch the<lb break="yes"/>belly of the fish with their fingers,<lb break="yes"/>at an inch distance, and press it<lb break="yes" />simultaneously, sometimes one,<lb break="yes"/>sometimes the other, will receive<lb break="yes"/>the shock. In the same manner,<lb break="yes"/>when one insulated person holds the<lb break="yes"/>tail of a vigorous gymnotus, and<lb break="yes"/>another pinches the gills, or pec-<lb break="no"/>toral fin, it is often the first only<lb break="yes"/>by whom the shock is received. It<lb break="yes"/>did not appear to us that these dif-<lb break="no" />ferences could be attributed to the<lb break="yes"/>dryness or dampness of our hands,<lb break="yes"/>or to their unequal conducting power.<lb break="yes" />The gymnotus seemed to direct its<lb break="yes"/>strokes sometimes from the whole<lb break="yes"/>surface of its body, sometimes from<lb break="yes" />one point only. This effect indi-<lb break="no"/>cates less a partial discharge of the<lb break="yes"/>organ composed of an innumerable<lb break="yes" />quantity of leaves, than the faculty<lb break="yes"/>which the animal possesses, perhaps<lb break="yes"/>by the instantaneous secretion of a<lb break="yes"/>fluid spread through the cellular<lb break="yes"/>membrane, of establishing the com-<lb break="no"/>munication between its organs and<lb break="yes"/>the skin only, in a very limited space.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Nothing proves more strongly the<lb break="yes"/>faculty which the gymnotus pos-<lb break="no"/>sesses, of darting and directing its<lb break="yes" />stroke according to its will, than the<lb break="yes"/>observations made at Philadelphia,<lb break="yes"/>and recently at Stockholm, on gym-<lb break="no"/>noti rendered extremely tame. When<lb break="yes"/>they had been made to fast a long<lb break="yes"/>time, they killed from afar small<lb break="yes"/>fishes put into the tub. They acted<lb break="yes"/>at a distance; that is to say, their<lb break="yes"/>electrical stroke passed through a<lb break="yes"/>very thick stratum of water. We<lb break="yes"/>need not be surprised, that what was<lb break="yes"/>observed in Sweden on a single gym-<lb break="no"/>notus only, we could not see on a<lb break="yes"/>great number of individuals in their<lb break="yes"/>native country. The electric action<lb break="yes"/>of animals being <hi rendition="#i">a vital action,</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>subject to their will, it does not de-<lb break="no"/>pend solely on their state of health<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>and vigour. A gymnotus that has<lb break="yes"/>made the voyage from Surinam to<lb break="yes"/>Philadelphia and Stockholm, accus-<lb break="no" />toms itself to the imprisonment, to<lb break="yes"/>which it is reduced; it resumes, by<lb break="yes"/>degrees, the same habits in the tub,<lb break="yes" />which it had in the rivers and pools.<lb break="yes"/>An electrical eel was brought to me<lb break="yes"/>at Calabozo, taken in a net, and, con-<lb break="no"/>sequently, having no wound. It ate<lb break="yes"/>meat, and terribly frightened the lit-<lb break="no"/>tle tortoises and frogs, which, not<lb break="yes"/>knowing the danger, placed them-<lb break="no"/>selves with confidence on its back.<lb break="yes"/>The frogs did not receive the stroke<lb break="yes"/>till the moment when they touched<lb break="yes"/>the body of the gymnotus. When<lb break="yes"/>they recovered, they leaped out of<lb break="yes"/>the tub; and when replaced near the<lb break="yes"/>fish, they were frightened at its sight<lb break="yes"/>only. We then observed nothing<lb break="yes"/>that indicated <hi rendition="#i">an action at a distance;</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>but our gymnotus, recently taken,<lb break="yes"/>was not yet sufficiently tamed to at-<lb break="no"/>tack and devour frogs. On ap-<lb break="no"/>proaching the finger, or metallic<lb break="yes"/>points, within the distance of half a<lb break="yes"/>line from the electric organs, no<lb break="yes"/>shock was felt. Perhaps the animal<lb break="yes"/>did not perceive the neighbourhood<lb break="yes"/>of this foreign body; or, if it did,<lb break="yes"/>we must suppose, that the timidity it<lb break="yes" />felt in the commencement of its cap-<lb break="no"/>tivity, prevented it from darting<lb break="yes"/>forth its energetic strokes, except<lb break="yes" />when strongly irritated by an imme-<lb break="no"/>diate contact. The gymnotus being<lb break="yes"/>immersed in water, I approached my<lb break="yes" />hand, both armed and unarmed with<lb break="yes"/>a metal, within the distance of a few<lb break="yes"/>lines from the electric organs; yet<lb break="yes"/>the strata of water transmitted no<lb break="yes"/>shock, while Mr. Bonpland irritated<lb break="yes"/>the animal strongly by an immediate<lb break="yes" />contact, and received some very vio-<lb break="no"/>lent shocks. If I had plunged the most<lb break="yes"/>delicate electroscopes we know, pre-<lb break="no"/>pared frogs, into contiguous strata<lb break="yes"/>of water, they would no doubt have<lb break="yes"/>felt contractions at the moment when<lb break="yes"/>the gymnotus seemed to direct its<lb break="yes"/>stroke elsewhere. Prepared frogs,<lb break="yes"/>placed immediately on the body of a<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="326" facs="#f0006"/>
                    <cb/>torpedo, experience, according to<lb break="yes"/>Galvani, a strong contraction at every<lb break="yes"/>discharge of the fish.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The electrical organ of the gymnoti<lb break="yes"/>acts only under the immediate <choice><sic>influ-<lb break="yes"/>of</sic><corr type="editorial">influ-<lb break="no"/>ence of</corr></choice> the brain and the heart. On cut-<lb break="no"/>ting a very vigorous fish through the<lb break="yes"/>middle of the body, the fore part<lb break="yes"/>alone gave me shocks. The shocks<lb break="yes"/>are equally strong, in whatever part<lb break="yes"/>of the body the fish is touched; it is<lb break="yes"/>most disposed, however, to dart them<lb break="yes" />forth when the pectoral fin, the elec-<lb break="no"/>trical organ, the lips, the eyes, or<lb break="yes"/>the gills, are pinched. Sometimes<lb break="yes" />the animal struggles violently with a<lb break="yes"/>person holding it by the tail, without<lb break="yes"/>communicating the least shock. Nor<lb break="yes" />did I feel any when I made a slight<lb break="yes"/>incision near the pectoral fin of the<lb break="yes"/>fish, and <hi rendition="#i">galvanized</hi> the wound by<lb break="yes"/>the simple contact of two pieces of<lb break="yes" />zinc and silver. The gymnotus bent<lb break="yes"/>itself convulsively, and raised its<lb break="yes"/>head out of the water, as if affright-<lb break="no" />ed by a sensation altogether new;<lb break="yes"/>but I felt no vibration in the hands<lb break="yes"/>which held the two metals. The<lb break="yes"/>most violent muscular movements<lb break="yes"/>are not always accompanied by elec-<lb break="no"/>tric discharges.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The action of the fish on the or-<lb break="no"/>gans of man is transmitted and inter-<lb break="no"/>cepted by the same bodies that trans-<lb break="no" />mit and intercept the electrical cur-<lb break="no"/>rent of a conductor charged by a<lb break="yes"/>Leyden vial, or Volta&#x2019;s pile. Some<lb break="yes" />anomalies, which we thought we ob-<lb break="no"/>served, are easily explained, when<lb break="yes"/>we recollect, that even metals (as is<lb break="yes"/>proved from their ignition when ex-<lb break="no"/>posed to the action of the pile) pre-<lb break="no"/>sent a slight obstacle to the passage<lb break="yes"/>of electricity; and that a bad con-<lb break="no"/>ductor annihilates the effect of a fee-<lb break="no"/>ble electricity on our organs, while<lb break="yes"/>it transmits to us the effect of a very<lb break="yes" />strong electricity. The repulsive<lb break="yes"/>force that zinc and silver exercise<lb break="yes"/>between each other, being far supe-<lb break="no" />rior to that between gold and silver,<lb break="yes"/>I have found, that when a frog, pre-<lb break="no"/>pared and armed with silver, is <hi rendition="#i" >gal-</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/><hi rendition="#i">vanized</hi> under water, the conducting<lb break="yes"/>arc of zinc produces contractions as<lb break="yes"/>soon as one of its extremities ap-<lb break="no"/>proaches the muscles within three<lb break="yes"/>lines distance; while an arc of gold<lb break="yes"/>does not excite the organs, when the<lb break="yes"/>stratum of water between the gold<lb break="yes"/>and the muscles is more than half a<lb break="yes"/>line thick. In the same manner, by<lb break="yes"/>employing a conducting arc composed<lb break="yes"/>of two pieces of zinc and silver sol-<lb break="no"/>dered together endwise, and resting<lb break="yes"/>as before, one of the extremities of<lb break="yes" />the metallic arc on the ischiatic<lb break="yes"/>nerve, it is necessary, in order to<lb break="yes"/>produce contractions, to bring the<lb break="yes" />other extremity of the conducting<lb break="yes"/>arc nearer and nearer to the mus-<lb break="no"/>cles, in proportion as the irritability<lb break="yes" />of the organs diminishes. Toward<lb break="yes"/>the end of the experiment, the<lb break="yes"/>slightest stratum of water prevents<lb break="yes"/>the passage of the electrical current,<lb break="yes"/>and it is only by the immediate con-<lb break="no"/>tact of the arc with the muscles, that<lb break="yes"/>the contractions take place. I dwell<lb break="yes"/>on these effects, dependent on three<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">variable</hi> circumstances: the energy<lb break="yes"/>of the electromotive apparatus, the<lb break="yes"/>conductibility of the medium, and the<lb break="yes"/>irritability of the organs that receive<lb break="yes" />the impressions; as it is because ex-<lb break="no"/>periments have not been sufficiently<lb break="yes"/>multiplied with a view to these three<lb break="yes"/>variable elements, that, in the action<lb break="yes"/>of electrical eels and torpedoes, the<lb break="yes"/>accidental circumstances have been<lb break="yes"/>taken for absolute conditions, with-<lb break="no"/>out which the electric shocks are<lb break="yes"/>not felt.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In wounded gymnoti, which give<lb break="yes"/>feeble, but very equal shocks, these<lb break="yes"/>shocks appeared to us constantly<lb break="yes" />stronger on touching the body of the<lb break="yes"/>fish with a hand armed with metal,<lb break="yes"/>than with the naked hand. They<lb break="yes"/>are stronger also, when, instead of<lb break="yes"/>touching the fish with one hand,<lb break="yes"/>naked, or armed with metal, we press<lb break="yes" />it at once with both hands, either<lb break="yes"/>naked or armed. These differences,<lb break="yes"/>I repeat, become sensible only when<lb break="yes"/>you have gymnoti enough at your<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="327" facs="#f0007"/>
                    <cb/>disposal to be able to choose the<lb break="yes"/>weakest; and the extreme equality<lb break="yes"/>of the electric discharges admits of<lb break="yes" />distinguishing between the sensa-<lb break="no"/>tions felt alternately by the hand<lb break="yes"/>naked or armed with a metal, by one<lb break="yes"/>or both hands naked, and by one or<lb break="yes"/>both hands armed with metal. It is<lb break="yes"/>also in the case only of small shocks,<lb break="yes" />weak and uniform, that the shocks<lb break="yes"/>are more sensible on touching the<lb break="yes"/>gymnotus with one hand (without<lb break="yes" />forming a chain) with zinc, than with<lb break="yes"/>copper or iron.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Resinous substances, glass, very<lb break="yes"/>dry wood, horn, and even bones,<lb break="yes"/>which are generally believed to be<lb break="yes" />good conductors, prevent the action<lb break="yes"/>of the gymnoti from being transmit-<lb break="no"/>ted to man. I was surprised at not<lb break="yes" />feeling the least shock on pressing<lb break="yes"/>wet sticks of sealing wax against the<lb break="yes"/>organs of the fish, while the same<lb break="yes" />animal gave me the most violent<lb break="yes"/>strokes, when excited by means of a<lb break="yes"/>metallic rod. Mr. Bonpland receiv-<lb break="no"/>ed shocks when carrying a gymnotus<lb break="yes"/>on two cords of the fibres of the palm-<lb break="no"/>tree, which appeared to us extreme-<lb break="no"/>ly dry. A strong discharge makes<lb break="yes"/>its way through very imperfect con-<lb break="no"/>ductors. Perhaps, also, the obsta-<lb break="no"/>cle which the conducting arc pre-<lb break="no"/>sents, renders the discharge more<lb break="yes"/>painful. I touched the gymnotus<lb break="yes"/>with a wet pot of brown clay, with-<lb break="no"/>out effect; yet I received violent<lb break="yes"/>shocks when I carried the gymnotus<lb break="yes" />in the same pot, because the contact<lb break="yes"/>was greater.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When two persons, insulated or<lb break="yes"/>not insulated, hold each other&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>hands, and one of these persons only<lb break="yes" />touches the fish with the hand, either<lb break="yes"/>naked or armed with metal, the<lb break="yes"/>shock is most commonly felt by both<lb break="yes" />at once. It happens, however, also,<lb break="yes"/>that in the most painful shocks, the<lb break="yes"/>person who comes into immediate<lb break="yes" />contact with the fish alone feels the<lb break="yes"/>shock. When the gymnotus is ex-<lb break="no"/>hausted, or in a very weak state of<lb break="yes" />excitability, and will no longer emit<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>strokes on being irritated with one<lb break="yes"/>hand, the shocks are felt in a very<lb break="yes"/>vivid manner, on forming the chain,<lb break="yes"/>and employing both hands. Even<lb break="yes"/>then, however, the electric shock<lb break="yes"/>takes place only at the will of the<lb break="yes"/>animal. Two persons, one of whom<lb break="yes"/>holds the tail, and the other the head,<lb break="yes"/>cannot, by joining hands and forming<lb break="yes"/>a chain, force the gymnotus to dart<lb break="yes" />his stroke.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In employing very delicate elec-<lb break="no"/>trometers in a thousand ways, insu-<lb break="no"/>lating them on a plate of glass, and<lb break="yes" />receiving very strong shocks, which<lb break="yes"/>passed through the electrometer, I<lb break="yes"/>could never discover any phenome-<lb break="no" />non of attraction or repulsion. The<lb break="yes"/>same observation was made by Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Fahlberg at Stockholm. This philo-<lb break="no"/>sopher, however, has seen an elec-<lb break="no"/>tric spark, as Walsh and Ingenhousz<lb break="yes"/>had done before him at London, by<lb break="yes"/>placing the gymnotus in the air, and<lb break="yes"/>interrupting the conducting chain by<lb break="yes"/>two gold leaves pasted upon glass,<lb break="yes"/>and a line distant from each other.<lb break="yes"/>No person, on the contrary, has ever<lb break="yes"/>perceived a spark issue from the<lb break="yes"/>body of the fish itself. We have ir-<lb break="no"/>ritated it for a long time during the<lb break="yes"/>night, at Calabozo, in perfect dark-<lb break="no"/>ness, without observing any lumi-<lb break="no"/>nous appearance. Having placed four<lb break="yes"/>gymnoti of unequal strength in such<lb break="yes"/>a manner as to receive the shocks of<lb break="yes"/>the most vigorous fish by <hi rendition="#i">communi-<lb break="no"/>cation,</hi> that is to say, by touching only<lb break="yes"/>one of the other fishes, I did not ob-<lb break="no"/>serve that these last were agitated at<lb break="yes"/>the moment when the current passed<lb break="yes"/>by their bodies. Perhaps the current<lb break="yes"/>established itself on the humid sur-<lb break="no" />face of the skin. We will not, how-<lb break="no"/>ever, conclude from this, that the<lb break="yes"/>gymnoti are insensible to electricity;<lb break="yes" />and that they cannot fight with each<lb break="yes"/>other at the bottom of the pools.<lb break="yes"/>Their nervous system must be sub-<lb break="no"/>ject to the same agents as the nerves<lb break="yes"/>of other animals. I have, indeed,<lb break="yes"/>seen, that, on baring their nerves,<lb break="yes" />they undergo muscular contractions<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="328" facs="#f0008"/>
                    <cb/>at the simple contact of two hetero-<lb break="no"/>geneous metals; and Mr. Fahlberg,<lb break="yes"/>of Stockholm, found, that his gymno-<lb break="no" />tus was convulsively agitated when<lb break="yes"/>placed in a copper vessel, and feeble<lb break="yes"/>discharges from a Leyden vial passed<lb break="yes" />through its skin.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After the experiments I had made<lb break="yes"/>on gymnoti, it became highly inte-<lb break="no"/>resting to me, at my return to Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope, to know with precision the va-<lb break="no"/>rious circumstances in which another<lb break="yes"/>electrical fish, the torpedo of our<lb break="yes" />seas, gives, or does not give, shocks.<lb break="yes"/>Though this fish had been examined<lb break="yes"/>by a great number of natural philo-<lb break="no" />sophers, I found all that had been<lb break="yes"/>published on its electrical effects ex-<lb break="no"/>tremely vague. It has been very<lb break="yes" />arbitrarily supposed that this fish<lb break="yes"/>acts like a Leyden vial, which may<lb break="yes"/>be discharged at will, by touching it<lb break="yes" />with both hands; and this supposi-<lb break="no"/>tion appears to have led observers<lb break="yes"/>into error, who have devoted them-<lb break="no" />selves to researches of this kind.<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Gay-Lussac and myself, during<lb break="yes"/>our journey to Italy, made a great<lb break="yes" />number of experiments on torpedoes<lb break="yes"/>taken in the Gulf of Naples. These<lb break="yes"/>experiments furnish many results<lb break="yes" />somewhat different from those I col-<lb break="no"/>lected on the gymnoti. It is proba-<lb break="no"/>ble, that the cause of these anoma-<lb break="no"/>lies proceeds rather from the ine-<lb break="no"/>quality of electric power in the two<lb break="yes"/>fishes, than the different disposition<lb break="yes" />of their organs.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Though the power of the torpedo<lb break="yes"/>cannot be compared with that of the<lb break="yes"/>gymnoti, it is sufficient to cause very<lb break="yes" />painful sensations. A person ac-<lb break="no"/>customed to electric shocks can with<lb break="yes"/>difficulty hold in his hands a torpedo<lb break="yes" />of twelve or fourteen inches, and in<lb break="yes"/>possession of all its vigour. When<lb break="yes"/>the animal no longer gives any but<lb break="yes" />very feeble strokes under water, the<lb break="yes"/>shocks become more sensible if it be<lb break="yes"/>raised above the surface. I have<lb break="yes"/>often observed the same phenome-<lb break="no"/>non in <hi rendition="#i">galvanizing</hi> frogs.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The torpedo moves the pectoral<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>fins convulsively, every time it emits<lb break="yes"/>a stroke; and this stroke is more or<lb break="yes"/>less painful, according as the im-<lb break="no"/>mediate contact takes place by a<lb break="yes"/>greater or less surface. We have<lb break="yes"/>above observed, that the gymnotus<lb break="yes"/>gives the strongest shocks without<lb break="yes"/>making any movement with the eyes,<lb break="yes"/>head, or fins. Is this difference<lb break="yes"/>caused by the position of the elec-<lb break="no"/>tric organ, which is not double in<lb break="yes"/>the gymnoti? or, does the movement<lb break="yes"/>of the pectoral fins of the torpedo<lb break="yes"/>directly prove, that the fish restores<lb break="yes"/>the electrical equilibrium by its<lb break="yes"/>own skin, discharges itself by its<lb break="yes"/>own body, and that we generally<lb break="yes"/>feel only the effect of a lateral<lb break="yes"/>shock?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We cannot discharge at will either<lb break="yes"/>a torpedo or a gymnotus, as we dis-<lb break="no"/>charge at will a Leyden vial or a<lb break="yes" />Voltaic pile. A shock is not always<lb break="yes"/>felt, even in touching the electric<lb break="yes"/>fish with both hands. We must irri-<lb break="no" />tate it to make it give the shock.<lb break="yes"/>This action in the torpedoes, as well<lb break="yes"/>as in the gymnoti, is a <hi rendition="#i" >vital action;</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>it depends on the will only of the<lb break="yes"/>animal, which, perhaps, does not al-<lb break="no"/>ways keep its electrical organs<lb break="yes"/>charged, or does not always employ<lb break="yes"/>the action of its nerves to establish<lb break="yes"/>the chain between the positive and<lb break="yes"/>negative poles. This is certain,<lb break="yes"/>that the torpedo gives a long series<lb break="yes"/>of shocks with astonishing celerity:<lb break="yes"/>whether it be, that the plates or la-<lb break="no"/>min&#x00E6; of his organs are not wholly<lb break="yes"/>exhausted, or that the fish recharges<lb break="yes"/>them instantaneously.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The electric stroke is felt when<lb break="yes"/>the animal is disposed to give it,<lb break="yes"/>whether we touch with a single fin-<lb break="no"/>ger only one of the surfaces of the<lb break="yes"/>organs, or apply both hands to the<lb break="yes"/>two surfaces, the superior and in-<lb break="no"/>ferior at once. In either case, it is<lb break="yes"/>altogether indifferent, whether the<lb break="yes"/>person who touches the fish with<lb break="yes"/>one finger, or both hands, be insulat-<lb break="no"/>ed or not. All that has been said<lb break="yes"/>on the necessity of a communication<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="329" facs="#f0009"/>
                    <cb/>with the damp ground, to establish a<lb break="yes"/>circuit, is founded on inaccurate ob-<lb break="no"/>servations.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mr. Gay-Lussac made the import-<lb break="no"/>ant observation, that, when an insu-<lb break="no"/>lated person touches the torpedo with<lb break="yes" />one finger, it is indispensable that<lb break="yes"/>the contact be immediate. The fish<lb break="yes"/>may with impunity be touched with<lb break="yes"/>a key or any other metallic instru-<lb break="no"/>ment; no shock is felt when a con-<lb break="no"/>ducting or nonconducting body is in-<lb break="no" />terposed between the finger and the<lb break="yes"/>electrical organ of the torpedo. This<lb break="yes"/>circumstance furnishes a great dif-<lb break="no" />ference between the torpedo and the<lb break="yes"/>gymnotus, the latter giving his<lb break="yes"/>strokes through an iron rod several<lb break="yes" />feet long.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When the torpedo is placed on a<lb break="yes"/>metallic plate of very little thickness,<lb break="yes"/>so that the plate touches the inferior<lb break="yes"/>surface of the organs, the hand that<lb break="yes"/>supports the plate never feels any<lb break="yes"/>shock, though another insulated per-<lb break="no"/>son excites the animal, and the con-<lb break="no" />vulsive movement of the pectoral<lb break="yes"/>fins denotes the strongest and most<lb break="yes"/>reiterated discharges.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If, on the contrary, a person sup-<lb break="no"/>port the torpedo, placed upon a me-<lb break="no"/>tallic plate, with the left hand, as in<lb break="yes" />the foregoing experiment, and the<lb break="yes"/>same person touch the superior sur-<lb break="no"/>face of the electrical organ with the<lb break="yes"/>right hand; a strong shock is then<lb break="yes"/>felt in both arms. The sensation is<lb break="yes"/>the same when the fish is placed be-<lb break="no"/>tween two metallic plates, the edges<lb break="yes"/>of which do not touch, and the per-<lb break="no"/>son applies both hands at once to these<lb break="yes"/>plates. The interposition of one<lb break="yes" />metallic plate prevents the communi-<lb break="no"/>cation, if that plate be touched with<lb break="yes"/>one hand only, while the interposi-<lb break="no" />tion of two metallic plates does not<lb break="yes"/>prevent the shock when both hands<lb break="yes"/>are applied. In the latter case, it<lb break="yes" />cannot be doubted, that the circula-<lb break="no"/>tion of the fluid is established by the<lb break="yes"/>two arms.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If, in this situation of the fish be-<lb break="no"/>tween two plates, there exist any<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>immediate communication between<lb break="yes"/>the edges of these two plates, no<lb break="yes"/>shock takes place. The chain be-<lb break="no"/>tween the two surfaces of the elec-<lb break="no"/>tric organ is then formed by the<lb break="yes"/>plates; and the new communication<lb break="yes"/>established by the contact of the two<lb break="yes"/>hands with the two plates, remains<lb break="yes"/>without effect. We carried the tor-<lb break="no"/>pedo with impunity between two<lb break="yes"/>dishes of metal, and felt the strokes<lb break="yes"/>it gave only at the instant when the<lb break="yes"/>dishes no longer touched each other<lb break="yes"/>at the edges.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Nothing in the torpedo, or in the<lb break="yes"/>gymnotus, indicates that the animal<lb break="yes"/>modifies the electrical state of the<lb break="yes" />bodies by which it is surrounded.<lb break="yes"/>The most delicate electrometer is no<lb break="yes"/>way affected, in whatever manner it<lb break="yes"/>is employed, whether bringing it<lb break="yes"/>near the organs, or insulating the<lb break="yes"/>fish, covering it with a metallic plate,<lb break="yes"/>and causing the plate to communi-<lb break="no"/>cate by a conducting wire with the<lb break="yes"/>condenser of Volta. We were at<lb break="yes"/>great pains to vary the experiments<lb break="yes"/>by which we sought to render the<lb break="yes"/>electrical tension in the organs of<lb break="yes"/>the torpedo sensible; but they were<lb break="yes"/>constantly without effect, and per-<lb break="no"/>fectly confirmed what Mr. Bonpland<lb break="yes"/>and myself had observed respecting<lb break="yes"/>the gymnoti during our abode in<lb break="yes"/>South America.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Electrical fishes, when very vigo-<lb break="no"/>rous, act with the same energy under<lb break="yes"/>water and in the air. This observa-<lb break="no" />tion led us to examine the conduct-<lb break="no"/>ing property of water; and we found<lb break="yes"/>that when several persons form the<lb break="yes" />chain between the superior and in-<lb break="no"/>ferior surface of the organs of the<lb break="yes"/>torpedo, the shock is felt only when<lb break="yes" />these persons have united their<lb break="yes"/>hands. The action is not intercept-<lb break="no"/>ed if two persons who support the<lb break="yes" />torpedo with their right hands, in-<lb break="no"/>stead of taking one another by the<lb break="yes"/>left hand, plunge each a metallic<lb break="yes"/>point into a drop of water placed on<lb break="yes"/>an insulating substance. On substi-<lb break="no"/>tuting flame for the drop of water,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="330" facs="#f0010"/>
                    <cb/>the communication is interrupted,<lb break="yes"/>and is only re-established, as in the<lb break="yes"/>gymnoti, when the two points imme-<lb break="no"/>diately touch each other in the inte-<lb break="no"/>rior of the flame.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 