<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="542" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
            <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">from the new monthly magazine.</hi>
                </head>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="2">
                <head>
                        <hi rendition="#k">NOCTURNAL INCREASE OF SOUNDS.</hi>
                    </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Humboldt endeavours to account for the increase of sounds during the<lb
                            break="yes"/>night, from observing that the presence of the sun affects
                        the propagation<lb break="yes"/>and intensity of sound by the obstacles
                        opposed to its transmission by cur-<lb break="no"/>rents of air of different
                        densities and partial undulation&#x2014;the result of the<lb break="yes"
                        />unequal heating of various parts of the earth&#x2019;s surface. In air at
                        rest, whe-<lb break="no"/>ther it be dry, or mixed with elastic vapours
                        equally distributed through it,<lb break="yes"/>the sonorous undulation is
                        propagated without difficulty. But when this<lb break="yes"/>air is crossed
                        in every direction by small currents of a warmer tempera-<lb break="no"
                        />ture, the sonorous undulation divides into two waves, at the spot where<lb
                            break="yes"/>there is the most sudden change in the density of the
                        medium; thus pro-<lb break="no"/>ducing partial echoes, which weaken the
                        body of sound, because one of the<lb break="yes"/>sonorous waves is
                        reflected back upon itself. The theory of these partitions<lb break="yes"
                        />of sonorous waves has been explained by M. Poisson.<note place="foot"
                            n="*">Ann. de Chimie, t. 7.</note> It is not, therefore,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="543" facs="#f0002"/> the motion of the passage of the particles of
                        air from below upwards, nor<lb break="yes"/>the small oblique currents of
                        this fluid that we consider as opposing, by im-<lb break="no"/>pulse, the
                        propagation of the sonorous waves. A <hi rendition="#i">stroke</hi> or
                        impulse im-<lb break="no"/>pressed on the surface of the liquid will form
                        circles around the impinging<lb break="yes"/>centre, even when the liquid is
                        in agitation. Several kinds of waves may<lb break="yes"/>cross in air, as
                        well as in water, without interfering with each other; but<lb break="yes"
                        />the true cause of the less intensity of sound in the day-time appears to
                            be<lb break="yes"/>the want of homogeneity in the elastic medium. There
                        is at this time a<lb break="yes"/>sudden change of density throughout,
                        produced by small currents of air, of<lb break="yes"/>a high temperature,
                        rising from portions of the earth&#x2019;s surface that are un-<lb
                            break="no"/>equally heated. The sonorous waves are then divided in the
                        same manner<lb break="yes"/>as luminous rays are refracted, and form a <hi
                            rendition="#i">mirage</hi> of sound wherever<lb break="yes"/>strata of
                        air of unequal density are contiguous. A distinction must be kept<lb
                            break="yes"/>between the <hi rendition="#i">intensity</hi> of sound or
                        of light, and the <hi rendition="#i">direction</hi> of the sonorous<lb
                            break="yes"/>or luminous wave. When these waves are propelled across
                        strata of differ-<lb break="no"/>ent densities two simultaneous effects will
                        be produced&#x2014;there will be a<lb break="yes"/>change in the direction
                        of the wave, and extinction of light or sound. The<lb break="yes"
                        />reflection that accompanies each refraction weakens the intensity of
                            light;<lb break="yes"/>the separation of the sonorous wave causes
                        partial echoes, and that portion<lb break="yes"/>which returns on itself
                        becomes insensible to our ear, in weak noises, at the<lb break="yes"/>spot
                        where the density of the medium suddenly changes. In the <hi rendition="#i"
                            >mirage</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>with double images, that which has undergone refraction
                        contiguous to the<lb break="yes"/>earth is always weaker than the direct
                        image. Strata of fluids, of very dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent density, may so
                        alternate, that the primitive direction of the lumi-<lb break="no"/>nous or
                        the sonorous ray will remain the same, but the intensity of the ray<lb
                            break="yes"/>will be not the less weakened on that account. During the
                        night the sur-<lb break="no"/>face of the earth cools; the parts covered
                        with grass, or with sand take the<lb break="yes"/>same temperature: the
                        atmosphere is no longer crossed by currents of hot<lb break="yes"/>air,
                        rising obliquely or vertically in every direction. The medium being<lb
                            break="yes"/>now become more homogeneous, the sonorous wave passes with
                        less difficul-<lb break="no"/>ty, and the intensity of sound increases, as
                        the separations of the sonorous<lb break="yes"/>waves and echoes become less
                        frequent.</p>
            </div>
        </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 