<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<pb facs="#f0002" />
<div n="1"><head>NOCTURNAL INCREASE OF SOUNDS.</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi> endeavours to account for the increase<lb/>of sounds during the
                    night, from observing that the<lb/>presence of the sun affects the propagation
                    and inten-<lb/>sity of sound by the obstacles opposed to its trans-<lb/>mission
                    by currents of air of different densities and<lb/>partial undulation, the result
                    of the unequal heating<lb/>of various parts of the earth&#x2019;s surface. In
                    air at rest,<lb/>whether it be dry or mixed with elastic vapours<lb/>equally
                    distributed through it, the sonorous undula-<lb/>tion is propagated without
                    difficulty; but when this<lb/>air is crossed in every direction by small
                    currents of a<lb/>warmer temperature, the sonorous undulation divides<lb/>into
                    two waves at the spot where there is the most<lb/>sudden change in the density
                    of the medium; thus<lb/>producing partial echoes, which weaken the body
                    of<lb/>sound, because one of the sonorous waves is reflected<lb/>back upon
                    itself. The theory of these partitions of<lb/>sonorous waves has been explained
                    by M. <hi rendition="#k">Poisson.</hi><note place="foot" n="*">Ann. de Chimie,
                        t. 7.</note><lb/>It is not, therefore, the motion of the passage of
                    the<lb/>particles of air from below upwards, nor the small<lb/>oblique currents
                    of this fluid that we consider as<lb/>opposing, by impulse, the propagation of
                    the so-<lb/>norous waves. A <hi rendition="#i">stroke</hi> or impulse impressed
                    on<lb/>the surface of the liquid will form circles around the<lb/>impinging
                    centre, even when the liquid is in agitation.<lb/>Several kinds of waves may
                    cross in air, as well as in<lb/>water, without interfering with each other; but
                    the<lb/>true cause of the less intensity of sound in the day-<lb/>time, appears
                    to be the want of homogenity in the<lb/>elastic medium. There is at this time a
                    sudden<lb/>change of density throughout, produced by small<lb/>currents of air,
                    of a high tempetature, rising from<lb/>portions of the earth&#x2019;s surface
                    that are unequally<lb/>heated. The sonorous waves are then divided in
                    the<lb/>same manner as luminous rays are refracted, and<lb/>from a <hi
                        rendition="#i">mirage</hi> of sound wherever strata of air of un-<lb/>equal
                    density are contiguous. A distinction must be<lb/>kept between the <hi
                        rendition="#i">intensity</hi> of sound or of light and<lb/>the <hi
                        rendition="#i">direction</hi> of the sonorous or luminous wave.<lb/>When
                    these waves are propelled across strata of<lb/>different densities, two
                    simultaneous effects will<lb/>be produced&#x2014;there will be a change in
                    the<lb/>direction of the wave, and extinction of light<lb/>or sound. The
                    reflection that accompanies each<lb/>refraction weakens the intensity of light;
                    the<lb/>separation of the sonorous ware causes partial<lb/>echoes, and that
                    portion which returns on itself be-<lb/>comes insensible to our ear, in weak
                    noises, at the<lb/>spot where the density or the medium suddenly<lb/>changes. In
                    the <hi rendition="#i">mirage</hi> with double images, that<lb/>which has
                    undergone refraction contiguous to the<lb/>earth is always weaker than the
                    direct image. Strata<lb/>of fluids, of very different density, may so
                    alternate,<lb/>that the primitive direction of the luminous or the
                    so-<lb/>norous ray will remain the same, but the intensity of<lb/>the ray will
                    be not the less weakened on that account.<lb/>During the night the surface of
                    the earth cools, the<lb/>parts covered with grass, or with sand, take the
                    same<lb/>temperature: the atmosphere is no longer crossed<lb/>by currents of hot
                    air, rising obliquely or vertically<lb/>in every direction. The medium being now
                    become<lb/>more homogeneous, the sonorous wave passes with<lb/>less difficulty,
                    and the intensity of sound increases,<lb/>as the separations of the sonorous
                    waves and echoes<lb/>becomes less frequent.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
