<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Comparative intensity of sounds</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:55</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.2</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1820-Sur_l_accroissement-06-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1820-Sur_l_accroissement-01.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1820-Sur_l_accroissement-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1820-Sur_l_accroissement-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1820-Sur_l_accroissement-04.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1820-Sur_l_accroissement-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1820-Sur_l_accroissement-06-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1820-Sur_l_accroissement-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1820-Sur_l_accroissement-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1820-Sur_l_accroissement-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1820-Sur_l_accroissement-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1820-Sur_l_accroissement-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1820-Sur_l_accroissement-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1820-Sur_l_accroissement-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Comparative intensity of sounds</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1821</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Leeds Correspondent, a Literary, Mathematical and Philosophical Miscellany&lt;/i&gt; 3:4 (Juli 1821), S. 228–230.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="228" facs="#f0001" /><lb/>
<div n="1"><head>COMPARATIVE INTENSITY OF SOUNDS.</head><lb/><p>The inhabitants of Atures and Maypures, what-<lb/>ever the missionaries may have asserted in their works,<lb/>are not more struck with deafness by the noise of the<lb/>great cataracts, than the Catadupes of the Nile. When<lb/>this noise is heard in the plain that surrounds the<lb/>mission, at the distance of more than a league, you<lb/>seem to be near a coast skirted by reefs and breakers.<lb/>The noise is three times as loud by night as by day,<lb/>and gives an inexpressible charm to these solitary<lb/>scenes. What can be the cause of this increased in-<lb/>tensity of sound in a desert, where nothing seems to<lb/>interrupt the silence of nature? The velocity of the<lb/>propagation of sound, far from augmenting, decreases<lb/>with the lowering of the temperature. The intensity<lb/>diminishes in air, agitated by a wind, which is con-<lb/>trary to the direction of the sound; it diminishes also<lb/>by dilatation of the air, and is weaker in the higher than<lb/>in the lower regions of the atmosphere, where the<lb/>number of particles of air in motion is greater in the<lb/>same radius. The intensity is the same in dry air,<lb/>and in air mingled with vapours; but it is feebler in<lb/><pb n="229" facs="#f0002" />
carbonic acid gas, than in mixtures of azot and oxygen.<lb/>From these facts, which are all we know with any cer-<lb/>tainty, it is difficult to explain a phenomenon observed<lb/>near every cascade in Europe, and which, long before<lb/>our arrival in the village of Atures, had struck the<lb/>missionary and the Indians. The nocturnal tempera-<lb/>ture of the atmosphere is 3° less than the temperature<lb/>of the day; at the same time the apparent humidity<lb/>augments at night, and the mist that covers the cata-<lb/>racts becomes thicker. We have just seen, that the<lb/>hygroscopic state of the air has no influence on the<lb/>propagation of the sound, and that the cooling of the<lb/>air diminishes its swiftness.</p><lb/><p>It may be thought, that, even in places not inhabited<lb/>by man, the hum of insects, the song of birds, the<lb/>rustling of leaves agitated by the feeblest winds, occa-<lb/>sion, during the day, a confused noise, which we per-<lb/>ceive the less because it is uniform, and constantly<lb/>strikes the ear. Now this noise, however slightly<lb/>perceptible it may be, may diminish the intensity of a<lb/>louder noise; and this diminution may cease, if during<lb/>the calm of the night the song of birds, the hum of<lb/>insects, and the action of the wind upon the leaves, be<lb/>interrupted. But this reasoning, even admitting its<lb/>justness, can scarcely be applied to the forests of the<lb/>Oroonoko, where the air is constantly filled by an in-<lb/>numerable quantity of moschettoes, where the hum of<lb/>insects is much louder by night than by day, and<lb/>where the breeze, if ever it be felt, blows only after<lb/>sunset.</p><lb/><p>I rather think, that the presence of the sun acts<lb/>upon the propagation and intensity of the
                    sound by<lb/>the obstacles which they find in the currents of air
                    of<lb/>different density, and the partial undulations of the<lb/>atmosphere
                    caused by the unequal heating of different<lb/>parts of the soil. In calm air,
                    whether it be dry, or<lb/>mingled with vesicular vapours equally
                        distributed,<lb/><pb n="230" facs="#f0003"/> the <hi rendition="#i">sonorous
                        undulation</hi> is propagated without difficulty.<lb/>But when the air is
                    crossed in every direction by<lb/>small currents of hotter air, the sonorous
                    undulation<lb/>is divided into two undulations; where the density of<lb/>the
                    medium changes abruptly, partial echoes are<lb/>formed, that weaken the sound,
                    because one of the<lb/>streams comes back upon itself; and those
                    divisions<lb/>of undulations take place, of which Mr. Poisson has<lb/>recently
                    developed the theory with great sagacity.<lb/>It is not therefore the movement
                    of the particles of<lb/>air from below to above in the ascending current,
                    or<lb/>the small oblique currents, that we consider as oppos-<lb/>ing by a shock
                    the propagation of the sonorous undu-<lb/>lations. A shock, given to the surface
                    of a liquid,<lb/>will form circles around the center of percussion,<lb/>even
                    when the liquid is agitated. Several kinds of<lb/>undulations may cross each
                    other in water, as in air,<lb/>without being disturbed in their propagation;
                    little<lb/>movements may <hi rendition="#i">ride over each other,</hi> and the
                    real cause<lb/>of the less intensity of sound during the day appears to
                    be<lb/>the interruption of homogeneity in the elastic medium.<lb/>During the
                    day, there is a sudden interruption of den-<lb/>sity wherever small streamlets
                    of air of a high tempe-<lb/>rature rise over parts of the soil unequally heated.
                    The<lb/>sonorous undulations are divided, as the rays of light<lb/>are
                    refracted, and form the <hi rendition="#i">mirage</hi> (looming,)
                    wherever<lb/>strata of air of unequal density are contiguous.
                    The<lb/>propagation of sound is altered, when a stratum of hy-<lb/>drogen gas is
                    made to rise in a tube closed at one end<lb/>above a stratum of atmospheric air;
                    and Mr. Biot has<lb/>well explained, by the interposition of bubbles of
                    car-<lb/>bonic acid gas, why a glass filled with Champagne<lb/>wine is little
                    sonorous so long as the gas is evolved,<lb/>and continues to pass through the
                    strata of the liquid.</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Personal Narrative.</hi></hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
