<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="375" facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Nocturnal Increase in the Intensity of Sound.<lb/>By M.</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">de Humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb/>From the <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Annales de Chimie et de Physique.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>HE increase in the intensity of sound during the<lb/>night, is a problem which is not resolved in any of the<lb/>works on natural philosophy. I shall endeavour to give<lb/>a solution derived from the latest researches on the theory<lb/>of sonorous undulations; but before treating of the cause<lb/>of this phenomenon, I shall mention the circumstances<lb/>under which it takes place.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>It has been remarked from the earliest antiquity that<lb/>the intensity of sound increases during the night. Aris-<lb/>totle has spoken of it in his Problems, and Plutarch in<lb/>his Dialogues. It is only the increase of sound when the<lb/>air is calm that we are now treating of, not that which<lb/>accompanies a change of wind in the night, and which is<lb/>modified by the relation that exists between the direction<lb/>of the wind, and that of the sonorous ray. Under the<lb/>same latitude (between the tropics for example), the<lb/>nightly increase of sound has appeared to me greater on<lb/>the plains than on the heights of the Andes, 3000 metres<lb/>above the level of the sea; and also, when on a low level,<lb/>more considerable in the middle of continents than in the<lb/>open sea. This estimation is founded on the compara-<lb/>tive noise of two volcanos, that of Guacamayo, and of<lb/>Cotopaxi, which I have frequently heard both by day<lb/>and by night, one in a level plain between the city of<lb/>Quito and the savannahs of Chillo, and the other on the<lb/>Pacific Ocean, ten leagues west of the coast of Peru.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The roarings of the volcanos of the Cordilleras usually<lb/>succeed each other with great uniformity every five mi-<lb/>nutes: they are not attended with any visible explosion<lb/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">above</fw>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="376" facs="#f0002" /> above the edges of the craters; and resemble, sometimes<lb/>distant thunder, at other times, repeated discharges of<lb/>heavy cannon. In places in which the ground is covered<lb/>in winter with snow in the vicinity of cascades, it would<lb/>be interesting to examine whether the nocturnal increase<lb/>of sound is not less in winter than in summer, when the<lb/>soil is strongly heated by the rays of the sun. It is to be<lb/>observed, that in what I have mentioned of the differ-<lb/>ence between the daily and nightly sound from sonorous<lb/>objects in the high and low levels of South America, I<lb/>only consider the comparative intensities under the same<lb/>barometric pressure. I do not compare the absolute in-<lb/>tensity at different altitudes, but the difference between<lb/>the diurnal and nocturnal intensity on high levels and on<lb/>plains. The variation of absolute intensity observed at<lb/>different heights of the atmosphere, is a problem which<lb/>the mathematical theory of sound has long resolved. M.<lb/>Poisson has even arrived at this remarkable result, that<lb/>the intensity of sound from below upwards or from above<lb/>downwards, whether the sonorous rays are propagated<lb/>vertically or obliquely, depends only on the density of the<lb/>stratum of air whence the sound has proceeded. One<lb/>must not therefore confound totally distinct problems.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>When the noise of the great cataracts of the Orinoco<lb/>is heard, at more than a league distance, in the plain<lb/>that surrounds the mission of Alures, the observer thinks<lb/>he is close to a coast surrounded with reefs and breakers.<lb/>The noise is three times as great by night as by day, and<lb/>gives an inexpressible charm to those solitary regions.<lb/>What can be the cause of this nocturnal increase of<lb/>sound in a desert, in which nothing seems to break in<lb/>upon the silence of nature? The diminution of tempera-<lb/>ture, so far from increasing, would retard the velocity<lb/>of sound. The intensity of sound diminishes in a wind<lb/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">blowing</fw>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="377" facs="#f0003" /> blowing in an opposite direction: it also diminishes by the<lb/>expansion of the air; it is weaker in the higher than in<lb/>the lower regions of the atmosphere, where the particles<lb/>of the agitated air have more density and more elasticity<lb/>in the same ray. The intensity is the same in a dry air<lb/>as in one full of vapour, but it is weaker in carbonic acid<lb/>than in the mixtures of azote and oxygen. On consider-<lb/>ing these facts (the only ones that we know with cer-<lb/>tainty), it is difficult to explain a phenomenon which is<lb/>observed near every cascade, and has been the subject of<lb/>common remark both in Europe and in America. Near<lb/>the Orinoco the temperature of the air is lower by about<lb/>five degrees (Fahrenheit) by night than by day; whilst the<lb/>visible moisture increases at night, and the haze round<lb/>the cataracts becomes denser. We have just seen that<lb/>the hygroscopic state of the air has no influence on the<lb/>propagation of sound, whilst the velocity of the latter is<lb/>diminished by the cooling of the atmosphere.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>It might be supposed that, even in places remote from<lb/>the habitation of man, the buzzing of insects, the sing-<lb/>ing of birds, and the rustling of leaves in the gentlest<lb/>winds, produce, by day, a confused noise; which, being<lb/>uniform, may fill the ears without materially distracting<lb/>the attention, and thus imperceptibly lessen the effect of<lb/>any louder sound. But this reasoning, whatever be its<lb/>force, can hardly apply to the forests of the Orinoco,<lb/>when the air is constantly filled with an innumerable<lb/>multitude of moskitoes, so that the buzzing of insects is<lb/>much stronger by night than by day; and where also<lb/>the breeze, when it occurs at all, springs up after sun-<lb/>set.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>I am inclined to think, that the presence of the sun af-<lb/>fects the propagation and intensity of sound by the ob-<lb/>stacles opposed to its transmission by currents of air of<lb/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">dif-</fw>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="378" facs="#f0004" /> different densities and partial undulations, the result of<lb/>the unequal heating of various parts of the earth&#x2019;s sur-<lb/>face. In air at rest, whether it be dry, or mixed with<lb/>elastic vapours equally distributed through it, the sonor-<lb/>ous undulation is propagated without difficulty. But<lb/>when this air is crossed in every direction by small cur-<lb/>rents of a warmer temperature, the sonorous undulation<lb/>divides into two waves, at the spot where there is the<lb/>most sudden change in the density of the medium; thus<lb/>producing partial echoes, which weaken the body of<lb/>sound, because one of the sonorous waves is reflected<lb/>back upon itself. The theory of these partitions of sonor-<lb/>ous waves has been lately explained by M. Poisson, with<lb/>the intelligence which distinguishes all his labours. <note place="foot" n="*">Annales de Chimie, T. 7.</note>. It<lb/>is not, therefore, the motion of the passage of the parti-<lb/>cles of air from below upwards, nor the small oblique<lb/>currents of this fluid that we consider as opposing, by<lb/>impulse, the propagation of the sonorous waves. A <hi rendition="#i">stroke</hi>
                    <lb/>or impulse impressed on the surface of the liquid will<lb/>form circles around the impinging centre, even when the<lb/>liquid is in agitation. Several kinds of waves may cross<lb/>in air, as well as in water, without interfering with each<lb/>other; but the true cause of the less intensity of sound<lb/>in the day time appears to be the want of homogeniety<lb/>in the elastic medium. There is at this time a sudden<lb/>change of density throughout, produced by small cur-<lb/>rents of air, of a high temperature, rising from portions<lb/>of the earth&#x2019;s surface that are unequally heated. The<lb/>sonorous waves are then divided in the same manner as<lb/>luminous rays are refracted, and form a <hi rendition="#i">mirage</hi> of sound<lb/>wherever strata of air of unequal density are contiguous.<lb/>A distinction must be kept between the <hi rendition="#i">intensity</hi> of sound<lb/>or of light, and the <hi rendition="#i">direction</hi> of the sonorous or luminous<lb/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">wave.</fw>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="379" facs="#f0005" /> wave. When these waves are propelled across strata of<lb/>different densities two simultaneous effects will be pro-<lb/>duced, there will be a change in the direction of the<lb/>wave, and extinction of light or sound. The reflexion<lb/>that accompanies each refraction weakens the intensity<lb/>of light; the separation of the sonorous wave causes par-<lb/>tial echoes, and that portion which returns on itself be-<lb/>comes insensible to our ear, in weak noises, at the spot<lb/>where the density of the medium suddenly changes.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In the <hi rendition="#i">mirage</hi> with double images, that which has un-<lb/>dergone refraction contiguous to the earth is always<lb/>weaker than the direct image. Strata of fluids, of very<lb/>different density, may so alternate, that the primitive di-<lb/>rection of the luminous or the sonorous ray will remain<lb/>the same, but the intensity of the ray will be not the less<lb/>weakened on that account. During the night the surface<lb/>of the earth cools; the parts covered with grass, or with<lb/>sand take the same temperature; the atmosphere is no<lb/>longer crossed by currents of hot air, rising obliquely or<lb/>vertically in every direction. The medium being now<lb/>become more homogeneous, the sonorous wave passes<lb/>with less difficulty, and the intensity of sound increases,<lb/>as the separations of the sonorous waves and echoes be-<lb/>come less frequent.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>To give a precise idea of the cause of these currents of<lb/>hot air, which rise in the day-time from a soil unequally<lb/>heated; I will mention some observations which I have<lb/>made under the Tropic. In the <hi rendition="#i">Llanos,</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">steppes</hi> of Ven-<lb/>zuela, I have found the sand at two o&#x2019;clock heated to<lb/>126° Fahrenheit, and sometimes as high as 140°. The<lb/>air under the shade of a Bombax was 97°; in the sun,<lb/>eighteen inches from the ground, 109°. At night the<lb/>sand was only 82°, having lost at least 46°. Near the<lb/>falls of the Orinoco, the ground being covered with<lb/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">grasses,</fw>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="380" facs="#f0006" /> grasses, its temperature rose in the day only to 86°, that<lb/>of the air being 79°, but at the same time the tempera-<lb/>ture of beds of granite lying on the surface was 118°. I<lb/>have published a great number of similar observations in<lb/>my account of experiments on the <hi rendition="#i">mirage</hi> at Cumana, at<lb/>the same period that Dr. Wollaston was employed on the<lb/>same subject in Europe.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>If I have given the true cause of the nightly increase<lb/>of sound, it will not be surprising that, under the torrid<lb/>zone, this increase is greater within land than on the<lb/>open sea; greater in the level plains than on the sides of<lb/>the Cordilleras. The surface of the equatorial seas heats<lb/>uniformly, and not beyond 85° Fahrenheit, whilst that of<lb/>the continents, being variously coloured, and composed<lb/>of materials of very different powers of radiation, acquires<lb/>a heat of from 86 to 126°. Under the tropics the earth<lb/>usually remains warmer during the night than the air: in<lb/>the temperate zones, on the other hand, in calm nights,<lb/>the surface of the ground cools down to seven or eight<lb/>degrees below that of the air. In Europe, the tempera-<lb/>ture, instead of diminishing as the distance from the<lb/>ground recedes, presents a regular progressive increase<lb/>to the height of fifty or sixty feet. It is not surprising,<lb/>therefore, that the terrestrial refractions are sometimes in<lb/>the temperate zone almost as great by night as by day.<lb/>There will always be strata of air, of different densities,<lb/>resting horizontally one upon the other; but the streams<lb/>of warm air that cross the atmosphere obliquely, will be<lb/>more rare at night than in the day. At 3000 metres in<lb/>height, in that part of the Andes which is situated be-<lb/>neath the equator, the mean temperature of the air is only<lb/>57°, and the force of radiation towards a cloudless sky,<lb/>through a dry and very pure air, hinders the soil from<lb/>heating considerably in the day time.</p>
                <lb/>
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">I shall</fw>
                <lb/>
                <pb n="381" facs="#f0007" />
                <p>I shall not dwell farther on these local circumstances,<lb/>it is sufficient to have made the general deduction of the<lb/>nocturnal increase of sound from the theory of sonorous<lb/>undulations and their divisions. The whole depends on<lb/>the want of homogeniety in the vertical columns of the<lb/>atmosphere, which (according to the ingenious applica-<lb/>tion that M. Arrago has made of the interference and<lb/>neutralisation of the rays) is also the true cause of the<lb/>scintillation of the stars. Besides, it is well known that<lb/>the propagation of sound is sensibly altered when a stra-<lb/>tum of hydrogen gas is made to rest above one of com-<lb/>mon air, in a tube closed at one extremity.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The mountaineers of the Alps, as well as those of the<lb/>Andes, regard an unusual increase of sound in calm<lb/>nights as a sure prognostic of a change in the weather.<lb/>&#x201C;It is about to rain,&#x201D; say they, &#x201C;for the noise of the<lb/>torrent comes nearer.&#x201D; M. Deluc has endeavoured to<lb/>explain this phenomenon by a change in barometric<lb/>pressure, and by an increased number of bubbles of air<lb/>breaking on the surface of the water. This explanation<lb/>is forced, and but little satisfactory. I will not attempt<lb/>another hypothesis, but I will suggest the analogy that<lb/>exists between the prognostic derived from an increase<lb/>of sound, and from that of light. The inhabitants of the<lb/>mountains also expect a change of weather, when, in calm<lb/>weather, the mountains covered with snow appear sud-<lb/>denly to approach nearer to the observer, and when their<lb/>outlines are unusually well defined upon the blue sky that<lb/>surrounds them. Whatever be the constitution of the<lb/>atmosphere that causes these appearances, it is not a lit-<lb/>tle curious to observe in it a new analogy between the<lb/>motions of the sonorous and the luminous undulations.</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>