<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="231" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>MUSQUITOS.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Persons who have not navigated the great rivers of<lb break="yes"/>equinoctial America, for instance, the Oroonoko and<lb break="yes"/>the Rio Magdalena, can scarcely conceive, how with-<lb break="no"/>out interruption, at every instant of life, you may be<lb break="yes"/>tormented by insects flying in the air, and how the<lb break="yes"/>multitude of these little animals may render vast re-<lb break="no"/>gions wholly uninhabitable. However accustomed<lb break="yes" />you may be to endure pain without complaint, how-<lb break="no"/>ever lively an interest you may take in the objects of<lb break="yes"/>your researches, it is impossible not to be constantly<lb break="yes"/>disturbed by the moschettoes, <hi rendition="#i">zaucudoes, jejens,</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">tempraneroes,</hi> that cover the face and hands, pierce the<lb break="yes"/>clothes with their long sucker in the form of a needle,<lb break="yes"/>and, getting into the mouth and nostrils, set you<lb break="yes"/>coughing and sneezing whenever you attempt to speak<lb break="yes"/>in the open air. In the missions of the Oroonoko, in<lb break="yes"/>the villages placed on the banks of the river, sur-<lb break="no"/>rounded by immense forests, the <hi rendition="#i">plaga de les moscas,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;the plague of the flies,&#x201D; affords an inexhaustible subject<lb break="yes"/>of conversation. When two persons meet in the morn-<lb break="no"/>ing, the first questions they address to each other are,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;How did you find the zancudoes during the night?<lb break="yes"/>How are we to-day for the moschettoes?&#x201D; These<lb break="yes"/>questions remind us of a Chinese form of politeness,<lb break="yes"/>which indicates the ancient state of the country where<lb break="yes"/>it took birth. Salutations were made heretofore in the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">celestial empire,</hi> in the following words, <hi rendition="#i">vou-tou-hou,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Have you been incommoded in the night by the ser-<lb break="no"/>pents?&#x201D; We shall soon see, that on the banks of the<lb break="yes"/>Tuamini, in the river Magdalena, and still more at<lb break="yes"/>Choco, the country of gold and platina, the Chinese<lb break="yes"/>compliment on the serpents might be added to that of<lb break="yes"/>the moschettoes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At Mandavaca we found an old missionary, who<lb break="yes"/>told us with an air of sadness, that he had spent <hi rendition="#i">his</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="232" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">twenty years of moschettoes</hi> in America. He desired us<lb break="yes"/>to look well at his legs, that we might be able to tell<lb break="yes"/>one day, &#x201C;poor alla (beyond the sea,) what the poor<lb break="yes"/>monks suffer in the forests of Cassiquiare.&#x201D; Every<lb break="yes"/>sting leaving a small darkish brown point, his legs<lb break="yes"/>were so speckled, that it was difficult to recognize the<lb break="yes"/>whiteness of his skin through the spots of coagulated<lb break="yes"/>blood. If the insects of the simulium genus abound<lb break="yes"/>in the Cassiquiare, which has <hi rendition="#i">white waters,</hi> the culices,<lb break="yes"/>or <hi rendition="#i" >zancudoes,</hi> are so much the more rare; you scarcely<lb break="yes" />find any there, while on the rivers of <hi rendition="#i">black waters</hi> in<lb break="yes"/>the Atabapo and the Rio Negro, there are generally<lb break="yes"/>some <hi rendition="#i">zan cudoes</hi> and no <hi rendition="#i">moschettoes.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have just shown, from my own observations, how<lb break="yes"/>much the geographical distribution of venomous in-<lb break="no"/>sects varies in this labyrinth of rivers, with white and<lb break="yes"/>black waters. It were to be wished, that a learned<lb break="yes"/>entomologist could study on the spot the specific dif-<lb break="no"/>ferences of these noxious insects, which in the torrid<lb break="yes"/>zone, in spite of their littleness, act an important part<lb break="yes"/>in the economy of nature. What appeared to us very<lb break="yes"/>remarkable, and is a fact, known to all the missionaries,<lb break="yes"/>is, that the different species do not associate together,<lb break="yes"/>and that at different hours of the day you are stung<lb break="yes"/>by a distinct species. Every time that the scene<lb break="yes" />changes, and to use the simple expression of the mis-<lb break="no" />sionaries, other insects &#x201C;mount guard,&#x201D; you have a<lb break="yes"/>few minutes, often a quarter of an hour, of repose.<lb break="yes"/>The insects that disappear have not their places in-<lb break="no"/>stantly supplied in equal numbers by their successors.<lb break="yes"/>From half after six in the morning till five in the after-<lb break="no"/>noon, the air is filled with moschettoes; which have<lb break="yes"/>not, as we find related in some travels, the form of our<lb break="yes"/>gnats, but that of a small fly. They are simuliums of<lb break="yes"/>the family nemocer&#x00E6; of the system of Latreille. Their<lb break="yes"/>sting is as painful as that of <hi rendition="#i" >stomoxes.</hi> It leaves a little<lb break="yes"/>reddish brown spot, which is extravasated and coagu-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="233" facs="#f0003"/> lated blood, where their proboscis has pierced the skin.<lb break="yes"/>An hour before sun-set a species of small gnats, called<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">tempraneros,</hi> because they appear also at sun-rise, take<lb break="yes"/>the place of the moschettoes. Their presence scarcely<lb break="yes"/>lasts an hour and a half; they disappear between six<lb break="yes"/>and seven in the evening, or, as they say here, after<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">Angelus (a la oracion).</hi> After a few minutes&#x2019; re-<lb break="no"/>pose, you feel yourself stung by <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi> another<lb break="yes"/>species of gnat (culex) with very long legs. The zan-<lb break="no"/>cudo, the proboscis of which contains a sharp pointed<lb break="yes"/>sucker, causes the most acute pain, and a swelling that<lb break="yes"/>remains several weeks. Its hum resembles that of our<lb break="yes"/>gnats in Europe, but is louder and more prolonged.<lb break="yes"/>The Indians pretend to distinguish &#x201C;by their song&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i">tempraneroes;</hi> the latter of which<lb break="yes" />are real <hi rendition="#i">twilight insects,</hi> while the <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi> are most<lb break="yes"/>frequently <hi rendition="#i">nocturnal insects,</hi> and disappear towards<lb break="yes" />sun-rise.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The <hi rendition="#i">culices</hi> of South America, have generally the<lb break="yes"/>wings, corselet, and legs of an azure colour, annulated,<lb break="yes"/>and variable from a mixture of spots of a metallic<lb break="yes"/>lustre. Here, as in Europe, the males, which are dis-<lb break="no"/>tinguished by their feath@ed antenn&#x00E6;, are extremely<lb break="yes"/>rare; you are seldom stung except by females. The<lb break="yes"/>preponderance of this sex explains the immense in-<lb break="no"/>crease of the species, each female laying several hun-<lb break="no"/>dred eggs. In going up one of the great rivers of<lb break="yes" />America, it is observed, that the appearance of a new<lb break="yes"/>species of <hi rendition="#i">culex</hi> denotes the approximity of a new stream<lb break="yes"/>flowing in.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The whites born in the torrid zone walk barefoot with<lb break="yes"/>impunity in the same apartment, where a European,<lb break="yes"/>recently landed, is exposed to the attack of the <hi rendition="#i">niguas</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>or <hi rendition="#i">chegoes (pulex penetrans).</hi> These animals almost<lb break="yes"/>invisible to the eye, get under the nails of the feet,<lb break="yes"/>and there acquire the size of a small pea by the quick<lb break="yes"/>increase of its eggs, which are placed in a bag under<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="234" facs="#f0004"/> the belly of the insect. The <hi rendition="#i" >nigua,</hi> therefore, distin-<lb break="no"/>guishes, what the most delicate chemical analysis<lb break="yes"/>could not distinguish, the cellular membrane and<lb break="yes"/>blood of a European from those of a Creole white. It<lb break="yes"/>is not so with the moschettoes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the day, even when labouring at the oar, the<lb break="yes"/>natives, in order to chase the insects, are continually<lb break="yes"/>giving one another smart slaps with the palm of the<lb break="yes"/>hand. Rude in all their movements, they strike<lb break="yes"/>themselves and their comrades mechanically during<lb break="yes"/>their sleep. The violence of their blows reminds us of<lb break="yes"/>the Persian tale of the bear, that tried to kill with his<lb break="yes"/>paw the insects on the forehead of his sleeping master.<lb break="yes"/>Near Maypures we saw some young Indians seated in<lb break="yes"/>a circle and rubbing cruelly each others&#x2019; backs with<lb break="yes"/>the bark of trees dried at the fire. Indian women<lb break="yes"/>were occupied with a degree of patience, of which the<lb break="yes"/>copper-coloured race alone are capable, in extirpating<lb break="yes"/>by means of a sharp bone the little mass of coagulated<lb break="yes"/>blood, that forms the centre of every sting, and gives<lb break="yes"/>the skin a speckled appearance. One of the most bar-<lb break="no"/>barous nations of the Oroonoko, that of the Ottomacs,<lb break="yes"/>is acquainted with the use of moschetto curtains <hi rendition="#i">(mos-<lb break="no"/>quiteros)</hi> formed of a tissue of fibres of the palm tree,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">murichi.</hi> We had lately seen, that at Higuerote, on the<lb break="yes"/>coast of Caraccas, the people of a copper-colour sleep<lb break="yes"/>buried in the sand. In the villages of the Rio Magda-<lb break="no"/>lena the Indians often invited us to stretch ourselves<lb break="yes"/>with them on ox-skins, near the church, in the middle of<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">plaza grande,</hi> where they had assembled all the<lb break="yes"/>cows in the neighbourhood. The proximity of cattle<lb break="yes"/>gives some repose to man. The Indians of the Upper<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko and the Cassiquiare, seeing that Mr. Bonp-<lb break="no"/>land could not prepare his herbal, on account of the<lb break="yes"/>continual torment of the moschettoes, invited him to<lb break="yes"/>enter their ovens, <hi rendition="#i">(hornitos).</hi> Thus they call little<lb break="yes"/>chambers, without doors or windows, into which they<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="235" facs="#f0005"/> creep horizontally through a very small opening.<lb break="yes"/>When they have driven away the insects by means of<lb break="yes"/>a fire of wet brush-wood, which emits a great deal of<lb break="yes"/>smoke, they close the opening of the oven. The ab-<lb break="no"/>sence of moschettoes is purchased dearly enough by<lb break="yes"/>the excessive heat of stagnant air, and the smoke of a<lb break="yes"/>torch of <hi rendition="#i">copal,</hi> which lights the oven during your stay<lb break="yes"/>in it. Mr. Bonpland, with courage, and patience well<lb break="yes"/>worthy of praise, dried hundreds of plants, shut up in<lb break="yes"/>these <hi rendition="#i">hornitos</hi> of the Indians.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is difficult not to smile at hearing the missionaries<lb break="yes"/>dispute on the size and voracity of the moschettoes at<lb break="yes"/>different parts of the same river. In the centre of a<lb break="yes"/>country ignorant of what is passing in the rest of the<lb break="yes"/>world, this is the favourite subject of conversation.<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;How I pity your situation!&#x201D; said the missionary of<lb break="yes"/>the Raudales to the missionary of Cassiquiare, at our<lb break="yes"/>departure; &#x201C;you are alone, like me, in this country of<lb break="yes"/>tigers and monkeys; with you fish is still more rare,<lb break="yes"/>and the heat more violent; but as for my flies, <hi rendition="#i">(mia<lb break="yes"/>moscas)</hi> I can boast, that with one of mine I would<lb break="yes"/>beat three of yours.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This voracity of insects in certain spots, the rage<lb break="yes"/>with which they attack man, the activity of the venom<lb break="yes"/>varying in the same species, are very remarkable<lb break="yes"/>facts; which find their analogy, however, in the classes<lb break="yes"/>of large animals. The crocodile of Angostura pursues<lb break="yes"/>men, while at Nueva, Barcelona, in the Rio Neveri,<lb break="yes"/>you may bathe tranquilly in the midst of these carni-<lb break="no"/>vorous reptiles. The jaguars of Maturin, Cumanacoa,<lb break="yes"/>and the isthmus of Panama, are cowardly in compari-<lb break="no"/>son to those of the Upper Oroonoko. The Indians<lb break="yes" />well know, that the monkeys of some valleys can<lb break="yes"/>easily be tamed, while others of the same species,<lb break="yes"/>caught elsewhere, will rather die of hunger, than sub-<lb break="no"/>mit to slavery. I might have added the example of<lb break="yes"/>the scorpion of Camana, which it is very difficult to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="236" facs="#f0006"/> distinguish from that of the island of Trinidad, Ja-<lb break="no"/>maica, Carthagena, and Guayaquil; yet the former is<lb break="yes"/>not more to be feared than the <hi rendition="#i">scorpio europ&#x0153;us</hi> (of the<lb break="yes"/>south of France,) while the latter produces conse-<lb break="no"/>quenees far more alarming than the <hi rendition="#i">scorpio occitanus,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(of Spain and Barbary.) At Carthagena and Guaya-<lb break="no" />quil, the sting of the scorpion <hi rendition="#i">(alaoran)</hi> instantly<lb break="yes"/>causes the loss of speech. Sometimes a singular torpor<lb break="yes"/>of the tongue is observed for fifteen or sixteen hours.<lb break="yes"/>The patient, when stung in the legs, stammers as if<lb break="yes"/>he had been struck with apoplexy.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i" >Ibid.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 