<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Humboldt’s Personal Narrative. Dirt Eaters</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:55</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.9</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1821-Humboldts_Personal_Narrative-1-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Humboldts_Personal_Narrative-1-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Humboldts_Personal_Narrative-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Humboldts_Personal_Narrative-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Humboldts_Personal_Narrative-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Humboldts_Personal_Narrative-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent&lt;/i&gt;, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 2, S. 609–616.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Humboldt’s Personal Narrative. Dirt Eaters</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1821</date>
          <pubPlace>Kendal</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Westmorland Gazette, and Kendal Advertiser&lt;/i&gt; 4:177 (6. Oktober 1821), [o. S.]. [Zuvor bereits in: „Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent, during the years 1799–1804. By Alexander de Humboldt, and Aimé Bonpland, &amp;amp;c. &amp;amp;c. London, 1821, 8vo. 2 Vols. pp. 864“, in: &lt;i&gt;The Literary Gazette; and Journal of Belles Lettres, Arts, Sciences, &amp;amp;c.&lt;/i&gt; 229 (9. Juni 1821), S. 353–355; 230 (16. Juni 1821), S. 374–376; 231 (23. Juni 1821), S. 389–391; 232 (30. Juni 1821), S. 405–406; 234 (14. Juli 1821), S. 441–442; 242 (8. September 1821), S. 563–565; 243 (15. September 1821), S. 580–582; 245 (29. September 1821), S. 615–616; 248 (20. Oktober 1821), S. 662–663, hier 245 (29. September 1821), S. 615–616.]</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">HUMBOLDT'S <choice>
                            <sic>PERSONALN ARRATIVE</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">PERSONAL NARRATIVE</corr>
                        </choice>.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">dirt eaters.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The inhabitants of Uruana belong to those <hi rendition="#i">na-<lb break="no"/>tions of the savannahs (Indios Andantes),</hi> who, more<lb break="yes"/>difficult to civilize than the <hi rendition="#i">nations of the forest, (In-<lb break="no"/>dios del monte),</hi> have a decided aversion to cultivate<lb break="yes"/>the land, and live almost exclusively on hunting and<lb break="yes"/>fishing. They are men of a very robust constitution;<lb break="yes"/>but ugly, savage, vindictive, and passionately fond<lb break="yes"/>of fermented liquors. They are omnivorous <hi rendition="#i">animals</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>in the highest degree; and therefore the other In-<lb break="no"/>dians, who consider them as barbarians, have a com-<lb break="no"/>mon saying, &#x2018;nothing is so disgusting that an Oto-<lb break="no"/>mac will not eat it.&#x2019; While the waters of the Oroo-<lb break="no"/>noko and its tributary streams are low, the Otomacs<lb break="yes"/>subsist on fish and turtles. The former they kill<lb break="yes"/>with surprising dexterity, by shooting them with<lb break="yes" />an arrow, when they appear at the surface of the<lb break="yes"/>water. When the rivers swell, which in South<lb break="yes"/>America, as well as in Egypt and in Nubia, is er-<lb break="no"/>roneously attributed to the melting of the snows, and<lb break="yes"/>which occurs periodically in every part of the torrid<lb break="yes"/>zone, fishing almost entirely ceases. It is then as<lb break="yes"/>difficult to procure fish in the rivers which are become<lb break="yes"/>deeper, as when you are sailing on the open sea. It<lb break="yes"/>often fails the poor missionaries, on fast-days as well<lb break="yes"/>as flesh-days, though all the young Indians are under<lb break="yes"/>the obligation of &#x2018;fishing for the convent.&#x2019; At the<lb break="yes"/>period of these inundations, which last two or three<lb break="yes"/>months, the Otomacs swallow a prodigious quantity<lb break="yes"/>of earth. We found heaps of balls in their huts,<lb break="yes"/>piled up in pyramids three or four feet high. These<lb break="yes"/>balls were five or six inches in diameter. The earth<lb break="yes"/>which the Otomacs eat is a very fine and unctuous<lb break="yes"/>clay, of a yellowish grey colour; and, being slightly<lb break="yes"/>baked in the fire, the hardened crust has a tint inclin-<lb break="no"/>ing to red, owing to the oxid of iron which is mingled<lb break="yes"/>with it. We brought away some of this earth, which<lb break="yes"/>we took from the winter provision of the Indians;<lb break="yes"/>and it is absolutely false, that it is steatitic, and con-<lb break="no"/>tains magnesia. Mr. Vauquelin did not discover<lb break="yes" />any traces of this earth in it; but he found that it<lb break="yes"/>contained more silex than alumin, and three or four<lb break="yes"/>per cent. of lime.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The Otomacs do not eat every kind of clay in-<lb break="no"/>differently; they choose the alluvial beds or strata<lb break="yes"/>that contain the most unctuous earth, and the smooth-<lb break="no"/>est to the feel. I inquired of the missionary, whether<lb break="yes"/>the moistened clay were made to undergo, as Father<lb break="yes"/>Gumilla asserts, that peculiar decomposition, which<lb break="yes"/>is indicated by a disengagement of carbonic acid and<lb break="yes"/>sulphuretted hydrogen, and which is designated in<lb break="yes"/>every language by the term of <hi rendition="#i" >putrefaction;</hi> but he<lb break="yes"/>assured us, that the natives neither cause the <hi rendition="#i">clay</hi> to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">rot,</hi> nor do they <choice><sic>mingl,</sic><corr type="editorial">mingle</corr></choice> it with flour of maize, oil of<lb break="yes"/>turtles&#x2019; eggs, or fat of the crocodile. We ourselves<lb break="yes"/>examined, both at the Oroonoko and after our return<lb break="yes"/>to Paris, the balls of earth which we brought away<lb break="yes"/>with us, and found no trace of the mixture of an or-<lb break="no"/>ganic substance, whether oily or farinaceous. The<lb break="yes" />savage regards every thing as nourishing that appeases<lb break="yes"/>hunger; when, therefore, you inquire of an Otomac<lb break="yes"/>on what he subsists during the two months when the<lb break="yes"/>river is the highest, he shows you his balls of clayey<lb break="yes"/>earth. This he calls his principal food; for at this<lb break="yes"/>period he can seldom procure a lizard, a root of fern,<lb break="yes"/>or a dead fish swimming on the surface of the water.<lb break="yes"/>If the Indian eat earth from want during the two<lb break="yes"/>months, (and from three quarters to five quarters of a<lb break="yes"/>pound in twenty-four hours), he does not the less re-<lb break="no"/>gale himself with it during the rest of the year. Every<lb break="yes"/>day in the season of drought, when fishing is most<lb break="yes"/>abundant, he scrapes his balls of <hi rendition="#i">poya,</hi> and mingles<lb break="yes"/>a little clay with his other aliment. What is most<lb break="yes"/>surprising is, that the Otomacs do not become lean<lb break="yes"/>by swallowing such quantities of earth; they are, on<lb break="yes"/>the contrary, extremely robust, and far from having<lb break="yes"/>the belly tense and puffed up. The missionary Fray<lb break="yes"/>Ramon Bueno asserts, that he never remarked any<lb break="yes" />alteration in the health of the natives at the period of<lb break="yes"/>the great risings of the Oroonoko.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The following are the facts in all their simplicity<lb break="yes"/>which we were able to verify. The Otomacs, during<lb break="yes"/>some months, eat daily three quarters of clay slightly<lb break="yes"/>hardened by fire, without their health being sensibly<lb break="yes"/>affected by it. They moisten the earth afresh when<lb break="yes"/>they are going to swallow it. It has not been possi-<lb break="no"/>ble to verify hitherto with precision how much nutri-<lb break="no"/>tious vegetable or animal matter the Indians take in<lb break="yes"/>a week at the same time; but it is certain that they<lb break="yes"/>attribute the sensation of satiety which they feel, to<lb break="yes"/>the clay, and not to the wretched aliments which<lb break="yes" />they take with it occasionally. No physiological<lb break="yes"/>phenomenon being entirely insulated, it may be in-<lb break="no"/>teresting to examine several analogous phenomena,<lb break="yes"/>which I have been able to collect.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;I observed every where within the torrid zone,<lb break="yes"/>in a great number of individuals, children, women,<lb break="yes"/>and sometimes even full-grown men, an inordinate<lb break="yes"/>and irresistible desire of swallowing earth; not an<lb break="yes"/>alkaline or calcareous earth, to neutralize (as it is<lb break="yes"/>vulgarly said) acid juices, but a fat clay, unctuous,<lb break="yes"/>and exhaling a strong smell. It is often found ne-<lb break="no"/>cessary to tie the childrens&#x2019; hands, or to confine them,<lb break="yes"/>to prevent their eating the earth, when the rain ceases<lb break="yes"/>to fall. At the village of Banco, on the bank of<lb break="yes"/>the river Magdalena, I saw the Indian women who<lb break="yes" />make pottery, continually swallowing great pieces of<lb break="yes" />clay.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The author goes at some length into analogies and<lb break="yes"/>reasoning on them, but we confine our quotation<lb break="yes"/>principally to the facts.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The negroes on the coast of Guinea delight in<lb break="yes"/>eating a yellowish earth, which they call <hi rendition="#i">caouac.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>The slaves who are taken to America try to procure<lb break="yes"/>for themselves the same enjoyment: but it is con-<lb break="no" />stantly detrimental to their health. They say, that<lb break="yes"/>the earth of the West Indies is not so easy of diges-<lb break="no"/>tion as that of their country.&#x2019;&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In the Indian Archipelago, at the island of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>Java, Mr. Labillardière saw, between Surabaya and<lb break="yes"/>Samarang, little square and reddish cakes exposed to<lb break="yes"/>sale. These cakes, called <hi rendition="#i">tanaampo,</hi> were cakes of<lb break="yes"/>clay, slightly baked, which the natives eat with ap-<lb break="no"/>petite. The attention of physiologists, having been<lb break="yes"/>powerfully fixed on these phenomena of <hi rendition="#i">geophagy,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Mr. Leschenault (one of the naturalists of the ex-<lb break="no"/>pedition to the Southern Lands under the command<lb break="yes" />of Captain Baudin) has published some curious de-<lb break="no"/>tails on the <hi rendition="#i">tanaampo,</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">ampo,</hi> of the Javanese.<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;The reddish and somewhat ferruginous clay,&#x2019; he<lb break="yes"/>says, &#x2018;which the inhabitants of Java are fond of<lb break="yes"/>eating occasionally, is spread on a plate of iron, and<lb break="yes"/>baked, after having been rolled into little cylinders<lb break="yes"/>in the form of the bark of cinnamon. In this state<lb break="yes"/>it takes the name of <hi rendition="#i">ampo,</hi> and is sold in the public<lb break="yes"/>markets. This clay has a peculiar taste, which is<lb break="yes"/>owing to the torrefaction; it is very absorbent, and<lb break="yes"/>adheres to the tongue, which it dries. In general it<lb break="yes"/>is only the Javanese women who eat the <hi rendition="#i" >ampo,</hi> either<lb break="yes"/>in the time of their pregnancy, or in order to grow<lb break="yes"/>thin; the want of plumpness being a kind of beauty<lb break="yes"/>in this country. The use of this earth is fatal to<lb break="yes"/>health; the women lose their appetite imperceptibly,<lb break="yes"/>and no longer take without disgust a very small<lb break="yes" />quantity of food: but the desire of becoming lean,<lb break="yes"/>and of preserving a slender shape, can brave these<lb break="yes"/>dangers, and maintains the credit of the <hi rendition="#i">ampo.</hi>&#x2019; The<lb break="yes"/>savage inhabitants of New Caledonia also, to appease<lb break="yes"/>their hunger in times of scarcity, eat great pieces of<lb break="yes"/>a friable <hi rendition="#i">lapis ollaris.</hi> Mr. Vauquelin analysed<lb break="yes"/>this stone, and found in it, besides magnesia and<lb break="yes"/>silex in equal portions, a small quantity of oxid of<lb break="yes"/>copper. Mr. Goldberry had seen the negroes in<lb break="yes" />Africa, in the islands of Bunck and Los Idolos, eat<lb break="yes"/>an earth of which he had himself eaten, without<lb break="yes"/>being incommoded by it, and which also was a white<lb break="yes"/>and friable steatite.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;When we reflect on the whole of these facts, we<lb break="yes"/>perceive that this disorderly appetite for clayey mag-<lb break="no"/>nesian, and calcareous earth, is most common among<lb break="yes"/>the people of the torrid zone; that it is not always a<lb break="yes"/>cause of disease; and that some tribes eat earth from<lb break="yes"/>choice, while others (the Otomacs in America, and<lb break="yes"/>the inhabitants of New Caledonia, in the Pacific<lb break="yes"/>Ocean), eat it from want, and to appease hunger.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The observations, which I made on the banks<lb break="yes"/>of the Oroonoko, have been recently confirmed by<lb break="yes"/>the direct experiments of two distinguished young<lb break="yes"/>physiologists, Messrs. Hippolyte Cloquet and Bres-<lb break="no"/>chet. After long fasting, they ate as much as five<lb break="yes"/>ounces of a silvery green and very flexible laminar<lb break="yes"/>talc. Their hunger was completely satisfied, and<lb break="yes" />they felt no inconvenience from a kind of food, to<lb break="yes"/>which their organs were unaccustomed. It is known,<lb break="yes"/>that great use is still made in the East of the bolar<lb break="yes"/>and sigillated carths of Lemnos, which are clay<lb break="yes"/>mingled with oxid of iron. In Germany, the work-<lb break="no"/>men employed in the quarries of sandstone worked<lb break="yes"/>at the mountain of Kiffh&#x00E6;user spread a very fine<lb break="yes"/>clay upon their bread, instead of butter, which they<lb break="yes"/>call <hi rendition="#i">steinbutter,</hi> stone butter; and they find it singu-<lb break="no"/>larly filling, and easy of digestion.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 