<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">[Maternal attachment]</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:58</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.23</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-21-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-21-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-22-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-23-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-24-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">[Maternal attachment]</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1835</date>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;Waldie’s Select Circulating Library&lt;/i&gt; 2:22 (21. November 1835), S. 341.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="341" facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>Humboldt, in his Travels to the Equinoctial Regions<lb break="yes"/>of the New
                Continent, relates a touching example of<lb break="yes"/>maternal affection.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>Near the confluence of the Atabapo and the Rio <choice><sic>Jerni</sic><corr
                        type="editorial">Temi</corr></choice>,<lb break="yes"/>there is a granite
                hummock that rises on the western<lb break="yes"/>bank, near the mouth of the
                        <choice><sic>Guaosiau</sic><corr type="editorial">Guasacavi</corr></choice>;
                it is called the<lb break="yes"/>Rock of the Guahiba Woman, or the Rock of the
                    Mo-<lb break="no"/>ther, (<hi rendition="#i">Piedra de la Madre,</hi>) from the
                trait of maternal<lb break="yes"/>affection attached to it.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;If,&#x201D; says the enterprising Humboldt, &#x201C;in these soli-<lb
                    break="no"/>tary scenes, man scarcely leaves behind him any traces<lb
                    break="yes"/>of his existence, it is doubly humiliating for a European<lb
                    break="yes"/>to see perpetuated by the name of a rock, by one of those<lb
                    break="yes"/>imperishable monuments of nature, the remembrance of<lb break="yes"
                />the moral degradation of our species, and the contrast<lb break="yes"/>between the
                virtue of a savage, and the barbarism of<lb break="yes"/>civilised man.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;In 1797, the missionary of San Fernando had led<lb break="yes"/>his Indians
                to the mouth of the Rio Guaviare, on one of<lb break="yes"/>these hostile incursions
                which are prohibited alike by<lb break="yes"/>religion and the Spanish laws. They
                found, in an Indian<lb break="yes"/>hut, a Guahiba mother with three children, two
                of whom<lb break="yes"/>were still infants. They were occupied in preparing the<lb
                    break="yes"/>flour of cassava. Resistance was impossible; the father<lb
                    break="yes"/>was gone to fish, and the mother tried in vain to flee<lb
                    break="yes"/>with her ehildren. Scarcely had she reached the savan-<lb
                    break="no"/>nah, when she was seized by the Indians of the mission.<lb
                    break="yes"/>who go to <hi rendition="#i">hunt men</hi>, like the whites and the
                negroes in<lb break="yes"/>Africa. The mother and her children were found, and<lb
                    break="yes"/>dragged to the bank of the river. The monk, seated in<lb
                    break="yes"/>his boat, waited the issue of an expedition of which he<lb
                    break="yes"/>partook not the danger. Had the mother made too vio-<lb break="no"
                />lent a resistance, the Indians would have killed her, for<lb break="yes"/>every
                thing is permitted when they go to the conquest<lb break="yes"/>of souls, (<hi
                    rendition="#i">à la conquista espiritual,</hi>) and it is children<lb
                    break="yes"/>in particular they seek to capture, in order to treat them,<lb
                    break="yes"/>in the mission, as <hi rendition="#i">poitos</hi>, or slaves of the
                    Christians.<lb break="yes"/>The prisoners were carried to San Fernando, in the
                    hope<lb break="yes"/>that the mother would be unable to find her way back<lb
                    break="yes"/>to her home by land. Far from those children who had<lb break="yes"
                />accompanied their father on the day on which she had<lb break="yes"/>been carried
                off, this unhappy woman showed signs of<lb break="yes"/>the deepest despair. She
                attempted to take back to her<lb break="yes"/>family the children who had been
                snatched away by the<lb break="yes"/>missionary, und fled with them repeatedly from
                the vil-<lb break="no"/>lage of San Fernando; but the Indians never failed to<lb
                    break="yes"/>seize her anew; and the missionary, after having caused<lb
                    break="yes"/>her to be mercilessly beaten, took the cruel resolution of<lb
                    break="yes"/>separating the mother from the two children who had<lb break="yes"
                />been carried off with her. She was conveyed alone to-<lb break="no"/>ward the
                missions of the Rio Negro, going up to the<lb break="yes"/>Atabapo. Slightly bound,
                she was seated at the bow of<lb break="yes"/>the boat, ignorant of the fate that
                awaited her; but she<lb break="yes"/>judged by the direction of the sun, that she
                was removed<lb break="yes"/>farther and farther from her hut and her native
                    country.<lb break="yes"/>She succeeded in breaking her bonds, threw herself
                    into<lb break="yes"/>the water, and swam to the left bank of the Atabapo.<lb
                    break="yes"/>The current carried her to a shelf of rock, which bears<lb
                    break="yes"/>her name to this day. She landed, and took shelter in<lb
                    break="yes"/>the woods; but the president of the missions ordered<lb break="yes"
                />the Indians to row to the shore, and follow the traces of<lb break="yes"/>the
                Guahiba. In the evening, she was brought back.<lb break="yes"/>Stretched upon the
                rock, <hi rendition="#i">la Piedra de la Madre,</hi> a cruel<lb break="yes"
                />punishment was inflicted on her with those straps of<lb break="yes"/>manatee
                leather which serve for whips in that country,<lb break="yes"/>and with which the
                alcades are always furnished. This<lb break="yes"/>unhappy woman, her hands tied
                behind her back with<lb break="yes"/>strong stalks of <hi rendition="#i"
                    >mavacure</hi>, was then dragged to the mis-<lb break="no"/>sion of Javita.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;She was there thrown into one of the caravanseras,<lb break="yes"/>that are
                called Casa del Rey. It was the rainy season,<lb break="yes"/>and the night was
                profoundly dark. Forests, till then<lb break="yes"/>believed to be impenetrable,
                separated the mission of<lb break="yes"/>Javita from that of San Fernando, which was
                    twenty-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>five leagues distant in a straight line. No other
                path is<lb break="yes"/>known than that of the rivers; no man ever attempted<lb
                    break="yes"/>to go by land from one village to another, were they only<lb
                    break="yes"/>a few leagues apart. But such difficulties do not stop a<lb
                    break="yes"/>mother, who is separated from her children. Her chil-<lb break="no"
                />dren are at San Fernando de Atabapo; she must find<lb break="yes"/>them again; she
                must exceute her project of delivering<lb break="yes"/>them from the hands of the
                Christians, of bringing them<lb break="yes"/>back to their father on the banks of
                the Guaviare. The<lb break="yes"/>Guahiba was carelessly guarded in the caravansera.
                    Her<lb break="yes"/>arms being wounded, the Indians of Javita had loosened<lb
                    break="yes"/>her bonds, unknown to the missionary and the alcades.<lb
                    break="yes"/>She succeeded, by the help of her teeth, in breaking<lb break="yes"
                />them entirely; disappeared during the night; and at the<lb break="yes"/>fourth
                rising sun, was seen at the mission of San Fer-<lb break="no"/>nando, hovering
                around the hut where her children were<lb break="yes"/>confined. &#x2018;What the
                woman performed,&#x2019; added the<lb break="yes"/>missionary, who gave us this sad
                narrative, &#x2018;the most<lb break="yes"/>robust Indian would not have ventured to
                    undertake.<lb break="yes"/>She traversed the woods at a season when the sky
                    is<lb break="yes"/>constantly covered with clouds, and the sun, during<lb
                    break="yes"/>whole days, appears but for a few minutes. Did the<lb break="yes"
                />course of the waters direct her way? The inundations<lb break="yes"/>of the rivers
                forced her to go far from the banks of the<lb break="yes"/>main stream, through the
                midst of woods, where the<lb break="yes"/>movement of the waters is almost
                imperceptible. How<lb break="yes"/>often must she have been stopped by the thorny
                    lianas,<lb break="yes"/>that form a net work around the trunks they entwine!<lb
                    break="yes"/>How often must she have swam across the rivulets that<lb
                    break="yes"/>run into the Atabapo!&#x2019; This unfortunate woman was<lb
                    break="yes"/>asked how she had sustained herself during the four<lb break="yes"
                />days? She said, &#x2018;that, exhausted with fatigue, she could<lb break="yes"
                />find no other nourishment than those great black ants,<lb break="yes"/>called <hi
                    rendition="#i">vachacos</hi>, which climb the trees in long bands, to<lb
                    break="yes"/>suspend on them their resinous nests.&#x2019; We pressed the<lb
                    break="yes"/>missionary to tell us whether the Guahiba had peace-<lb break="no"
                />fully enjoyed the happiness of remaining with her chil-<lb break="no"/>dren; and
                if any repentance had followed this excess of<lb break="yes"/>cruelty. He would not
                satisfy our curiosity; but at our<lb break="yes"/>return from the Rio Negro, we
                learnt that the Indian<lb break="yes"/>mother was not allowed time to cure her
                wounds; but<lb break="yes"/>was again separated from her children, and sent to
                    one<lb break="yes"/>of the missions of the Upper Oroonoko. There she<lb
                    break="yes"/>died, refusing all kind of nourishment, as the savages do<lb
                    break="yes"/>in great calamities.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;Such is the remembrance annexed to this fatal rock,<lb break="yes"/>to <hi
                    rendition="#i">Piedra de la Madre.</hi>&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 