<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157">
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-18" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body><pb n="353" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head><hi rendition="#i">Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equi-<lb break="no"
                        />noctial Regions of the New Continent,<lb break="yes"/>during the
                        years</hi> 1799&#x2014;1804. By Alex-<lb break="no"/>ander de Humboldt, and
                    Aimé Bonpland,<lb break="yes"/>&amp;c. &amp;c. London, 1821, 8vo. 2 Vols.<lb
                        break="yes"/>pp. 864.<lb break="yes"/>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>These volumes, translated by H. Maria<lb break="yes"/>Williams,
                    terminate the second volume<lb break="yes"/>(in quarto) of M. Humboldt&#x2019;s
                        personal<lb break="yes"/>narrative; and belong to a work so univer-<lb
                        break="no"/>sally celebrated, that we need only say,<lb break="yes"/>they
                    are, if possible, more thickly studded<lb break="yes"/>with pieces of valuable
                    information and<lb break="yes"/>curious matter, than the parts which have<lb
                        break="yes"/>preceded them.</p>
                <p>We never take up Humboldt but he re-<lb break="no"/>minds us of Othello, who<lb
                        break="yes"/>&#x2014;Spake of most disastrous chances,<lb break="yes"/>Of
                    moving accidents, by flood, and field;<lb break="yes"/>Of hair-breadth
                        &#x2019;scapes&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>And portance in his travel&#x2019;s
                        history;<lb break="yes"/>Wherein of antres vast, and
                            <choice><sic>desarts</sic><corr type="editorial">deserts</corr></choice>
                        idle,<lb break="yes"/>Rough quarries, rocks, and hills whose heads<lb
                        break="yes"/>touch heaven,&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>And of the cannibals that
                    each other eat;<lb break="yes"/>The Anthropophagi, and men whose heads<lb
                        break="yes"/>Do grow beneath their shoulders,<lb break="yes"/>he told the
                    marvellous stories. Our au-<lb break="no"/>thor is hardly a trace behind him;
                        and,<lb break="yes"/>like the fair Desdemona, we, with greedy<lb break="yes"
                    />ear, devour up his discourse; whence,<lb break="yes"/>without further preface,
                    we shall now pro-<lb break="no"/>ceed to draw for the benefit of our
                    readers.</p>
                <p>The natives near the cataracts or rau-<lb break="no"/>dales of the Oroonoko, up
                    which river M.<lb break="yes"/>de Humboldt made his way to a height<lb
                        break="yes"/>little known to Europeans, are distin-<lb break="no"/>guished
                    by several remarkable prejudices,<lb break="yes"/>among which, none are more
                    fatal than<lb break="yes"/>those narrated in the following:&#x2014;<lb
                        break="yes"/>&#x201C;Among the causes of the depopulation<lb break="yes"/>of
                    the Raudales, I have not reckoned the<lb break="yes"/>small pox; that malady
                    which, in other<lb break="yes"/>parts of America, makes such cruel ravages,<lb
                        break="yes"/>that the natives, seized with dismay, burn<lb break="yes"
                    />their huts, kill their children, and renounce<lb break="yes"/>every kind of
                    society.<note place="foot" n="*">As the Mahas in the <choice><sic>planes</sic><corr type="editorial">plaines</corr></choice> of the Mis-<lb
                            break="no"/>soury, according to the accounts of the Ame-<lb break="no"
                        />rican travellers, Clark and Lewis.</note> This scourge is<lb break="yes"
                    />almost unknown on the banks of the<lb break="yes"/>Oronoko. What depopulates
                    the Chris-<lb break="no"/>tian settlements is, the repugnance of the<lb
                        break="yes"/>Indians for the regulations of the missions,<lb break="yes"
                    />the insalubrity of a climate at once hot and<lb break="yes"/>damp, bad
                    nourishment, want of care in<lb break="yes"/>the diseases of children, and the
                        guilty<lb break="yes"/>practice of mothers of preventing pregnancy<lb
                        break="yes"/>by the use of deleterious herbs. Among<lb break="yes"/>the
                    barbarous people of Guyana, as well as<lb break="yes"/>those of the
                    half-civilized islands of the<lb break="yes"/><cb/>South Sea, young wives will
                    not become<lb break="yes"/>mothers. If they have children, their off-<lb
                        break="no"/>spring are exposed, not only to the dangers<lb break="yes"/>of
                    savage life, but also to the dangers aris-<lb break="no"/>ing from the strangest
                    popular prejudices.<lb break="yes"/>When twins are born, false notions of
                        pro-<lb break="no"/>priety and family honour require, that one<lb
                        break="yes"/>of them should be destroyed. &#x2018;To bring<lb break="yes"
                    />twins into the world, is to be exposed to<lb break="yes"/>public scorn; it is
                    to resemble rats, opos-<lb break="no"/>sums, and the vilest animals, which
                        bring<lb break="yes"/>forth a great number of young at a time.&#x2019;<lb
                        break="yes"/>Nay more: &#x2018;two children born at the<lb break="yes"/>same
                    time cannot belong to the same fa-<lb break="no"/>ther.&#x2019; This is an axiom
                    of physiology of<lb break="yes"/>the Salivas; and in every zone, and in dif-<lb
                        break="no"/>ferent states of society, when the vulgar<lb break="yes"/>seize
                    upon an axiom, they adhere to it<lb break="yes"/>with more stedfastness than the
                        better<lb break="yes"/>informed men, by whom it was first ha-<lb break="no"
                    />zarded. To avoid a disturbance of con-<lb break="no"/>jugal tranquillity, the
                    old female relations<lb break="yes"/>of the mother, or the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >mure japoic-nei</hi> (mid-<lb break="no"/>wives,) take care, that one of
                    the twins<lb break="yes"/>shall disappear. If the new-born infant,<lb
                        break="yes"/>though not a twin, have any physical de-<lb break="no"
                    />formity, the father instantly puts it to<lb break="yes"/>death. They will have
                    only robust and<lb break="yes"/>well-made children, for deformities indicate<lb
                        break="yes"/>some influence of the evil spirit Ioloquiamo,<lb break="yes"
                    />or the bird <hi rendition="#i">Tikitiki</hi>, the enemy of the hu-<lb
                        break="no"/>man race. Sometimes children of a feeble<lb break="yes"
                    />constitution undergo the same fate. When<lb break="yes"/>the father is asked,
                    what is become of one<lb break="yes"/>of his sons, he will pretend, that he
                        has<lb break="yes"/>lost him by a natural death. He will dis-<lb break="no"
                    />avow an action, that appears to him blame-<lb break="no"/>able, but not
                    criminal. &#x2019;The poor <hi rendition="#i">mure</hi>,<note place="foot" n="*"
                        >In Tamanack <hi rendition="#i">mure</hi> signifies a child; <hi
                            rendition="#i">emuru</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>a son.</note>&#x201D;<lb
                        break="yes"/>he will tell you, &#x2019;could not follow us; we<lb
                        break="yes"/>must have waited for him every moment;<lb break="yes"/>he has
                    not been seen again, he did not<lb break="yes"/>come to sleep where we passed
                    the night.&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>Such is the candour and simplicity of man-<lb
                        break="no"/>ners, such the boasted happiness of man<lb break="yes"/>in the
                        <hi rendition="#i">state of nature</hi>! He kills his son,<lb break="yes"
                    />to escape the ridicule of having twins, or<lb break="yes"/>to avoid journeying
                    more slowly; in fact,<lb break="yes"/>to avoid a little
                    inconvenience.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>Amid the prodigality and magnificence<lb break="yes"/>of nature, such are the
                    moral evils which<lb break="yes"/>deform the scene; and we are often com-<lb
                        break="no"/>pelled to leave the author&#x2019;s glowing des-<lb break="no"
                    />criptions of superb landscape in the torrid<lb break="yes"/>zone, to vex our
                    spirits with similar details.<lb break="yes"/>But, the able manner in which
                    distant ob-<lb break="no"/>jects and remote similitudes are brought to<lb
                        break="yes"/>bear on almost every subject discussed, is<lb break="yes"/>the
                    great charm of this work; and we have<lb break="yes"/>so vast a quantity of
                    intelligence combined<lb break="yes"/>with so rich a fund of amusing
                        anecdote,<lb break="yes"/>that the mind never tires. It has been<lb
                        break="yes"/><cb/>alleged, that Mr. H. is too prone to this<lb break="yes"
                    />sort of classification, and to theories built<lb break="yes"/>upon it; but
                    however that may be in a<lb break="yes"/>philosophical point of view, as a
                        popular<lb break="yes"/>performance, it wonderfully enhances the<lb
                        break="yes"/>attractions of his narrative. He is, in<lb break="yes"/>truth,
                    the very Jacques of travellers; and<lb break="yes"/>his way is delectable,
                    &#x201C; compounded of<lb break="yes"/>many simples, extracted from many ob-<lb
                        break="no"/>jects; and, indeed, the sundry contempla-<lb break="no"/>tion of
                    his travels, in which his often ru-<lb break="no"/>mination wraps him in a most humourous<lb break="yes"/>sadness.&#x201D; He morals on every thing; for
                    example:&#x2014;</p>
                <p>&#x201C;The inhabitants of Atures and May-<lb break="no"/>pures, whatever the
                    missionaries may have<lb break="yes"/>asserted in their works, are not more
                        struck<lb break="yes"/>with deafness by the noise of the great<lb
                        break="yes"/>cataracts, than the catadupes of the Nile.<lb break="yes"/>When
                    this noise is heard in the plain that<lb break="yes"/>surrounds the mission, at
                    the distance of<lb break="yes"/>more than a league, you seem to be near<lb
                        break="yes"/>a coast skirted by reefs and breakers. The<lb break="yes"
                    />noise is three times as loud by night as by<lb break="yes"/>day, and gives an
                    inexpressible charm to<lb break="yes"/>these solitary scenes. What can be the<lb
                        break="yes"/>cause of this increased intensity of sound<lb break="yes"/>in a
                    desert, where nothing seems to inter-<lb break="no"/>rupt the silence of nature?
                    The velocity<lb break="yes"/>of the propagation of sound, far from aug-<lb
                        break="no"/>menting, decreases with the lowering of the<lb break="yes"
                    />temperature. The intensity diminishes in<lb break="yes"/>air, agitated by a
                    wind, which is contrary<lb break="yes"/>to the direction of the sound; it
                        diminishes<lb break="yes"/>also by dilatation of the air, and is weaker<lb
                        break="yes"/>in the higher than in the lower regions of<lb break="yes"/>the
                    atmosphere, where the number of par-<lb break="no"/>ticles of air in motion is
                    greater in the<lb break="yes"/>same radius. The intensity is the same in<lb
                        break="yes"/>dry air, and in air mingled with vapours;<lb break="yes"/>but
                    it is feebler in carbonic acid gas, than<lb break="yes"/>in mixtures of azot and
                    oxygen. From<lb break="yes"/>these facts, which are all we know with<lb
                        break="yes"/>any certainty, it is difficult to explain a<lb break="yes"
                    />phenomenon observed near every cascade<lb break="yes"/>in Europe, and which,
                    long before our ar-<lb break="no"/>rival in the village of Atures, had struck<lb
                        break="yes"/>the missionary and the Indians. The noc-<lb break="no"/>turnal
                    temperature of the atmosphere is<lb break="yes"/>3° less than the temperature of
                    the day;<lb break="yes"/>at the same time the apparent humidity<lb break="yes"
                    />augments at night, and the mist that covers<lb break="yes"/>the cataracts
                    becomes thicker. We have<lb break="yes"/>just seen, that the hygroscopic state
                    of the<lb break="yes"/>air has no influence on the propagation of<lb break="yes"
                    />the sound, and that the cooling of the air<lb break="yes"/>diminishes its
                    swiftness.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;It may be thought, that, even in places<lb break="yes"/>not inhabited by
                    man, the hum of insects,<lb break="yes"/>the song of birds, the rustling of
                        leaves<lb break="yes"/>agitated by the feeblest winds, occasion,<lb
                        break="yes"/>during the day, a confused noise, which we<lb break="yes"
                    />perceive the less because it is uniform, and<lb break="yes"/>constantly
                    strikes the ear. Now this noise,<lb break="yes"/>
                </p>
                <pb n="354" facs="#f0002"/>
                <p>however slightly perceptible it may be,<lb break="yes"/>may diminish the
                    intensity of a louder,<lb break="yes"/>noise; and this diminution may cease,
                        if<lb break="yes"/>during the calm of the night the song of<lb break="yes"
                    />birds, the hum of insects, and the action of<lb break="yes"/>the wind upon the
                    leaves, be interrupted.<lb break="yes"/>But this reasoning, even admitting its
                        just-<lb break="no"/>ness, can scarcely be applied to the forests<lb
                        break="yes"/>of the Oroonoko, where the air is con-<lb break="no"/>stantly
                    filled by an innumerable quantity<lb break="yes"/>of moschettoes, where the hum
                    of insects<lb break="yes"/>is much louder by night than by day, and<lb
                        break="yes"/>where the breeze, if ever it be felt, blows<lb break="yes"
                    />only after sunset.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;I rather think, that the presence of<lb break="yes"/>the sun acts upon
                    the propagation and in-<lb break="no"/>tensity of the sound by the obstacles
                        which<lb break="yes"/>they find in the currents of air different<lb
                        break="yes"/>density, and the partial undulations of the<lb break="yes"
                    />atmosphere caused by the unequal heating<lb break="yes"/>of different parts of
                    the soil. In calm air,<lb break="yes"/>whether it be dry, or mingled with
                        vesi-<lb break="no"/>cular vapours equally distributed, the <hi
                        rendition="#i">so-<lb break="no"/>norous undulation</hi> is propagated
                        without<lb break="yes"/>difficulty. But when the air is crossed in<lb
                        break="yes"/>every direction by small currents of hotter<lb break="yes"
                    />air, the sonorous undulation is divided into<lb break="yes"/>two undulations;
                    where the density of the<lb break="yes"/>medium changes abruptly, partial
                        echoes<lb break="yes"/>are formed, that weaken the sound, because<lb
                        break="yes"/>one of the streams comes back upon itself;<lb break="yes"/>and
                    those divisions of undulations take<lb break="yes"/>place, of which Mr. Poisson
                    has recently<lb break="yes"/>developed the theory with great sagacity.<lb
                        break="yes"/>It is not therefore the movement of the<lb break="yes"
                    />particles of air from below to above in the<lb break="yes"/>ascending current,
                    or the small oblique<lb break="yes"/>currents, that we consider as opposing
                        by<lb break="yes"/>a shock the propagation of the sonorous<lb break="yes"
                    />undulations. A shock, given to the sur-<lb break="no"/>face of a liquid, will
                    form circles around<lb break="yes"/>the center of percussion, even then the<lb
                        break="yes"/>liquid is agitated. Several kinds of undu-<lb break="no"
                    />lations may cross each other in water, as in<lb break="yes"/>air, without
                    being disturbed in their pro-<lb break="no"/>pagation; little movements may <hi
                        rendition="#i">ride over<lb break="yes"/>each other</hi>, and the real cause
                    of the less<lb break="yes"/>intensity of sound during the day appears<lb
                        break="yes"/>to be the interruption of homogeneity in<lb break="yes"/>the
                    elastic medium. During the day,<lb break="yes"/>there is a sudden interruption
                    of density,<lb break="yes"/>where ever small streamlets of air of a high<lb
                        break="yes"/>temperature rise over parts of the soil un-<lb break="no"
                    />equally heated. The sonorous undulations<lb break="yes"/>are divided, as the
                    rays of light are re-<lb break="no"/>fracted, and form the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >mirage</hi> (looming),<lb break="yes"/>wherever strata of air of unequal
                        density<lb break="yes"/>are contiguous. The propagation of sound<lb
                        break="yes"/>is altered, when a stratum hydrogen gas<lb break="yes"/>is made
                    to rise in a tube closed at one<lb break="yes"/>end above a stratum of
                    atmospheric air;<lb break="yes"/>and Mr. Biot has well explained, by the in-<lb
                        break="no"/>terposition of bubbles of carbonic acid gas,<lb break="yes"/>why
                    a glass filled with Champagne wine<lb break="yes"/>is little sonorous so long as
                    the gas is<lb break="yes"/>evolved, and continues to pass through<lb break="yes"
                    />the strata of the liquid.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>This hypothesis is well worth further<lb break="yes"/>investigations; but we must
                    surrender it to<lb break="yes"/>the scientific journals, and continue our<lb
                        break="yes"/>more mixed career.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;The Indians of Atures,&#x201D; says Mr. H.,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;are
                    mild, moderate, and accustomed, from<lb break="yes"/>the effects of their
                    idleness, to the greatest<lb break="yes"/><cb/>privations. Formerly, excited to
                        labour<lb break="yes"/>by the Jesuits, they did not want for food.<lb
                        break="yes"/>The fathers cultivated maize, French beans,<lb break="yes"
                        />(<hi rendition="#i">frisoles</hi>), and other European vegetables;<lb
                        break="yes"/>they even planted sweet oranges and ta-<lb break="no"/>marinds
                    round the villages ; and they pos-<lb break="no"/>sessed twenty or thirty
                    thousand head of<lb break="yes"/>cows and horses, in the savannahs of<lb
                        break="yes"/>Atures and Carichana. They had at their<lb break="yes"/>service
                    a great number of slaves and ser-<lb break="no"/>vants (<hi rendition="#i"
                        >peones</hi>), to take care of their herds.<lb break="yes"/>Nothing is now
                    cultivated but a little cas-<lb break="no"/>sava, and a few plantains. The
                        fertility<lb break="yes"/>of the soil however is such, that at Atures<lb
                        break="yes"/>I counted on a single branch of musa 108<lb break="yes"
                    />fruits, 4 or 5 of which would almost suffice<lb break="yes"/>for the daily
                    nourishment of a man. The<lb break="yes"/>culture of maize is entirely
                    neglected, and<lb break="yes"/>the horses and cows have disappeared.<lb
                        break="yes"/>Near the <hi rendition="#i">raudal</hi>, a part of the village
                        still<lb break="yes"/>bears the name of <hi rendition="#i">Passo del
                        ganado</hi> (ford<lb break="yes"/>of the cattle), while the descendants
                        of<lb break="yes"/>those very Indians, whom the Jesuits had<lb break="yes"
                    />assembled in a mission, speak of horned<lb break="yes"/>cattle as of animals
                    of a race that is lost.<lb break="yes"/>In going up the Oroonoko, toward San<lb
                        break="yes"/>Carlos del Rio Negro, we saw the last cow<lb break="yes"/>at
                    Carichana. The fathers of the Observ-<lb break="no"/>ance, who now govern these
                    vast countries,<lb break="yes"/>did not immediately succeed the Jesuits.<lb
                        break="yes"/>During an interregnum of eighteen years,<lb break="yes"/>the
                    missions were visited only from time<lb break="yes"/>to time, and by Capuchin
                    monks. The<lb break="yes"/>agents of the secular government, under<lb
                        break="yes"/>the title of <hi rendition="#i">Commissioners of the King</hi>,
                        ma-<lb break="no"/>naged the <hi rendition="#i">hatos</hi> or farms of the
                        Jesuits<lb break="yes"/>with culpable negligence. They killed the<lb
                        break="yes"/>cattle in order to sell the hides. Many<lb break="yes"/>heifers
                    were devoured by tigers, and a<lb break="yes"/>greater number perished in
                        consequence<lb break="yes"/>of wounds made by the bats of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">raudales</hi>, which are much less, but far<lb break="yes"
                    />bolder than the bats of the Llanos. At<lb break="yes"/>the time of the
                    expedition of the bounda-<lb break="no"/>ries, the horses of Encaramada,
                        Carichana,<lb break="yes"/>and Atures, were conveyed as far as San<lb
                        break="yes"/>Jose of Maravitanos, where, on the banks<lb break="yes"/>of the
                    Rio Negro, the Portugueze could<lb break="yes"/>only procure them after a long
                        passage,<lb break="yes"/>and of a very inferior quality, by the river<lb
                        break="yes"/>Amazon and Grand Para. Since the year<lb break="yes"/>1795, the
                    cattle of the Jesuits have entirely<lb break="yes"/>disappeared. There now
                    remains in tes-<lb break="no"/>timony of the ancient cultivation of these<lb
                        break="yes"/>countries, and the industrious activity of<lb break="yes"/>the
                    first missionaries, only a few trunks of<lb break="yes"/>the orange and tamarind
                    in the savannahs, <lb break="yes"/>surrounded by wild trees.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;The tigers, or jaguars, which are less<lb break="yes"/>dangerous for the
                    cattle than the bats,<lb break="yes"/>come into the village at Atures, and
                        devour<lb break="yes"/>the pigs of the poor Indians. The mis-<lb break="no"
                    />sionary related to us a striking instance of<lb break="yes"/>the familiarity
                    of these animals, upon the<lb break="yes"/>whole so ferocious. Some months
                        before<lb break="yes"/>our arrival, a jaguar, which was thought to<lb
                        break="yes"/>be young, though of a large size, had<lb break="yes"/>wounded a
                    child in playing with him; I use<lb break="yes"/> confidently this expression,
                    which may<lb break="yes"/>seem strange, having on the spot verified<lb
                        break="yes"/>facts which are not without interest in the<lb break="yes"
                    />history of the manners of animals. Two<lb break="yes"/>Indian children, a boy
                    and a girl, about<lb break="yes"/>eight and nine years of age, were seated<lb
                        break="yes"/><cb/>on the grass near the village of Atures, in<lb break="yes"
                    />the middle of a savannah, which we have<lb break="yes"/>often traversed. At
                    two o&#x2019;clock in the af-<lb break="no"/>ternoon, a jaguar issued from the
                        forest,<lb break="yes"/>and approached the children, bounding<lb break="yes"
                    />around them; sometimes he hid himself<lb break="yes"/>in the high grass,
                    sometimes he sprang<lb break="yes"/>forward, his back bent, his head hung<lb
                        break="yes"/>down, in the manner of our cats. The<lb break="yes"/>little
                    boy, ignorant of his danger, seemed<lb break="yes"/>to be sensible of it only
                    when the jaguar<lb break="yes"/>with one of bis paws gave him some blows<lb
                        break="yes"/>on the head. These blows, at first slight,<lb break="yes"
                    />became ruder and ruder; the claws of the<lb break="yes"/>jaguar wounded the
                    child, and the blood<lb break="yes"/>flowed with violence. The little girl
                        then<lb break="yes"/>took a branch of a tree, struck the animal,<lb
                        break="yes"/>and it fled from her. The Indians ran up<lb break="yes"/>at the
                    cries of the children, and saw the<lb break="yes"/>jaguar, which retired
                    bounding, without the<lb break="yes"/>least show of resistance.</p>
                <p> &#x201C;The little boy was brought to us, who<lb break="yes"/>appeared lively
                    and intelligent. The claw<lb break="yes"/>of the jaguar had taken away the skin
                        from<lb break="yes"/>the lower part of the forehead, and there<lb
                        break="yes"/>was a second scar at the top of the head.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>&#x201C;Among the monkeys,&#x201D; the author<lb break="yes"/>continues,
                    &#x201C;which we saw at the mission<lb break="yes"/>of the Atures, we found one
                    new species<lb break="yes"/>of the tribe of <hi rendition="#i">sais</hi> and <hi
                        rendition="#i">sajous</hi>, which the<lb break="yes"/>Creoles vulgarly call
                        <hi rendition="#i">machis</hi>. It is the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">ouavapavi</hi> with grey hair and a bluish face.<lb
                        break="yes"/>It has the orbits of the eyes and forehead<lb break="yes"/>as
                    white as snow, which at first sight dis-<lb break="no"/>tinguish it from the <hi
                        rendition="#i">simia capucina</hi>, the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">simia apella</hi>, the <hi rendition="#i">simia trepida</hi>,
                    and the<lb break="yes"/>other weeping monkeys hitherto so con-<lb break="no"
                    />fusedly described. This little animal is as<lb break="yes"/>gentle as it is
                    ugly. Every day in the<lb break="yes"/>court-yard of the missionary it seized a
                        pig,<lb break="yes"/>upon which it remained from morning till<lb break="yes"
                    />night, traversing the savannahs. We have<lb break="yes"/>also seen it upon the
                    back of a large cat,<lb break="yes"/>which bad been brought up with it in fa-<lb
                        break="no"/>ther Zea's house.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;It was among the cataracts that we began<lb break="yes"/>to hear of the
                    hairy man of the woods, called<lb break="yes"/>salvaje, that carries off women,
                        constructs<lb break="yes"/>huts, and sometimes eats human flesh. The<lb
                        break="yes"/>Tamanacks call it <hi rendition="#i">achi</hi>, and the
                        Maypures<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">vasitri</hi>, or <hi rendition="#i">great devil</hi>. The
                    natives and the<lb break="yes"/>missionaries have no doubt of the exist-<lb
                        break="no"/>ence of this anthropomorphous monkey,<lb break="yes"/>which they
                    singularly dread. Father Gili<lb break="yes"/>gravely relates the history of a
                    lady in the<lb break="yes"/>town of San Carlos, who much praised the<lb
                        break="yes"/>gentle character and attentions of the man<lb break="yes"/>of
                    the woods. She lived several years with<lb break="yes"/>one in great domestic
                    harmony, and only<lb break="yes"/>requested some hunters to take her back,<lb
                        break="yes"/>&#x2018;because she was tired, she and her chil-<lb break="no"
                    />dren (a little hairy also), of living far from<lb break="yes"/>the church and
                    the sacraments.&#x201D; The<lb break="yes"/>same author, notwithstanding his
                        credulity,<lb break="yes"/>confesses, that he had not been able to<lb
                        break="yes"/>find an Indian, who asserted positively that<lb break="yes"/>he
                    had seen the <hi rendition="#i">salvaje</hi> with his own eyes.<lb break="yes"
                    />This fable, which the missionaries, the Eu-<lb break="no"/>ropean planters,
                    and the negroes of Africa,<lb break="yes"/>have no doubt embellished with many
                        fea-<lb break="no"/>tures taken from the description of the<lb break="yes"
                    />manners of the ourang outang, the gibbon,<lb break="yes"/>the jocko or
                    chimpanzee, and the pongo,<lb break="yes"/>pursued us during five years from the
                        north-<lb break="no"/>
                </p>
                <pb n="355" facs="#f0003"/>
                <p>ern to the southern hemisphere; and we<lb break="yes"/>were every where blamed,
                    in the most cul-<lb break="no"/>tivated class of society, for being the only<lb
                        break="yes"/>persons to doubt the existence of the great<lb break="yes"
                    />anthropomorphous monkey of America.<lb break="yes"/>We shall first observe,
                    that there are cer-<lb break="no"/>tain regions, where this belief is
                        particu-<lb break="no"/>larly prevalent among the people; such<lb
                        break="yes"/>are the banks of the Upper Oroonoko, the<lb break="yes"/>valley
                    of Upar near the Lake of Maracaybo,<lb break="yes"/>the mountains of Santa
                    Martha and of Me-<lb break="no"/>rida, the provinces of Quixos, and the<lb
                        break="yes"/>banks of the Amazon near Tomependa.<lb break="yes"/>In all
                    these places, so distant one from the<lb break="yes"/>other, it is repeated,
                    that the <hi rendition="#i">salvaje</hi> is<lb break="yes"/>easily recognized by
                    the traces of its feet,<lb break="yes"/>the toes of which are turned
                        backward.<lb break="yes"/> But if there exist a monkey of a large size<lb
                        break="yes"/>in the New Continent, how has it hap-<lb break="no"/>pened,
                    that during three centuries no man<lb break="yes"/> worthy of belief has been
                    able to procure<lb break="yes"/>the skin of one? Several hypotheses pre-<lb
                        break="no"/>sent themselves to the mind, in order to<lb break="yes"/>explain
                    the source of so ancient an error<lb break="yes"/>or belief. Has the famous <hi
                        rendition="#i">capuchin</hi> mon-<lb break="no"/>key of Esmeralda, the
                    canine teeth of<lb break="yes"/>which are more than six lines and a half
                        long,<lb break="yes"/>the physiognomy much more like man&#x2019;s<lb
                        break="yes"/>than that of the ourang outang, and which,<lb break="yes"/>
                    when irritated, rubs its beard with its hand,<lb break="yes"/> give rise to the
                    fable of the <hi rendition="#i">salvaje</hi>? It<lb break="yes"/>is not so large
                    indeed as the coaita<lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">simia paniscus</hi>);
                    but when seen at<lb break="yes"/>the top of a tree, and the head only<lb
                        break="yes"/>visible, it might easily be taken for<lb break="yes"/>a human
                    being. It may be also (and<lb break="yes"/>this opinion appears to me the most
                        pro-<lb break="no"/>bable), that the man of the woods was one<lb break="yes"
                    />of those large bears, the footsteps of which<lb break="yes"/>resemble those of
                    a man, and which is be-<lb break="no"/>lieved in every country to attack
                        women.<lb break="yes"/> The animal killed in my time at the foot of<lb
                        break="yes"/> the mountains of Merida, and sent, by the<lb break="yes"/>name
                    of <hi rendition="#i">salvaje</hi>, to Colonel Ungaro, the go-<lb break="no"
                    />vernor of the province Varinas, was in fact<lb break="yes"/>a bear with black
                    and smooth fur.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>These extraordinary accounts are suc-<lb break="no"/>ceeded by a detailed history
                    of the Moschet-<lb break="no"/>toes of this region; perhaps the most re-<lb
                        break="no"/>markable of all its animal phenomena.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;Persons who have not navigated the<lb break="yes"/>great rivers of
                    equinoctial America, for in-<lb break="no"/>stance, the Oroonoko and the Rio
                        Magda-<lb break="no"/>lena, can scarcely conceive, how without in-<lb
                        break="no"/>terruption, at every instant of life, you may<lb break="yes"/>be
                    tormented by insects flying in the air,<lb break="yes"/>and how the multitude of
                    these little ani-<lb break="no"/>mals may render vast regions wholly unin-<lb
                        break="no"/>habitable. However accustomed you may be<lb break="yes"/> to
                    endure pain without complaint, however<lb break="yes"/> lively an interest you
                    may take in the ob-<lb break="no"/>jects of your researches, it is impossible
                        not<lb break="yes"/>to be constantly disturbed by the moschet-<lb break="no"
                    />toes, <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes, jejens</hi> and <hi rendition="#i"
                        >tempraneroes</hi>, that<lb break="yes"/>cover the face and hands, pierce
                    the clothes<lb break="yes"/>with their long sucker in the form of a nee-<lb
                        break="no"/>dle, and, getting into the mouth and nos-<lb break="no"/>trils,
                    set you coughing and sneezing when-<lb break="no"/>ever you attempt to speak in
                    the open air.<lb break="yes"/>In the missions of the Oroonoko, in the vil-<lb
                        break="no"/>lages placed on the banks of the river, sur-<lb break="no"
                    />rounded by immense forests, the <hi rendition="#i">plaga de<lb break="yes"
                        />las moscas</hi>, the plague of the flies, affords an<lb break="yes"
                    />inexhaustible subject of conversation. When<lb break="yes"/><cb/>two persons
                    meet in the morning, the first<lb break="yes"/>questions they address to each
                    other are,<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;How did you find the zancudoes during<lb
                        break="yes"/>the night? How are we to day for the<lb break="yes"
                    />moschettoes.&#x2019; These questions remind<lb break="yes"/>us of a Chinese
                    form of politeness,<lb break="yes"/> which indicates the ancient state of the<lb
                        break="yes"/>country where it took birth. Salutations<lb break="yes"/>were
                    made heretofore in the <hi rendition="#i">celestial<lb break="yes"/>empire</hi>,
                    in the following <choice><sic>works</sic><corr type="editorial"
                        >words</corr></choice>, <hi rendition="#i">vou-tou-<lb break="maybe"
                        />hou</hi>, &#x2018;Have you been incommoded in the<lb break="yes"/>night by
                    the serpents?<choice><sic/><corr type="editorial">&#x2019;</corr></choice> We
                    shall soon see,<lb break="yes"/>that on the banks of the Tuamini, in<lb
                        break="yes"/> the river Magdalena, and still more at<lb break="yes"/>Choco,
                    the country of gold and platina, the<lb break="yes"/>Chinese compliment on the
                    serpents might<lb break="yes"/>be added to that of the moschettoes.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>Other curious facts are recorded, and il-<lb break="no"/>lustrate this subject.
                    Mr. H. says&#x2014;</p>
                <p>&#x201C;At Mandavaca we found an old mis-<lb break="no"/>sionary, who told us
                    with an air of sadness,<lb break="yes"/>that he bad spent <hi rendition="#i">his
                        twenty years of mos-<lb break="no"/>chettoes</hi> in America. He desired us
                    to look<lb break="yes"/>well at his legs, that we might be able to<lb
                        break="yes"/> tell one day, &#x2018;poor alla (beyond sea), what<lb
                        break="yes"/>the poor monks suffer in the forests of<lb break="yes"
                    />Cassiquiare.&#x2019; Every sting leaving a small<lb break="yes"/>darkish brown
                    point, his legs were so<lb break="yes"/>speckled, that it was difficult to
                        recognize<lb break="yes"/>the whiteness of his skin through the spots<lb
                        break="yes"/>of coagulated blood. If the insects of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    simulium genus abound in the Cassiquiare,<lb break="yes"/>which has <hi
                        rendition="#i">white waters</hi>, the culices, or<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi>, are so much the more rare;<lb break="yes"
                    />you scarcely find any there, while on the<lb break="yes"/>rivers of <hi
                        rendition="#i">black waters</hi>, in the Atabapo and<lb break="yes"/>the Rio
                    Negro, there are generally some<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi> and no <hi rendition="#i"
                    >moschettoes</hi>.&#x201D; <lb break="yes"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">To be continued</hi>). </p>
            </div><pb n="374" facs="#f0004"/><div n="1">
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">HUMBOLDT&#x2019;S TRAVELS,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#c">(Continued.)</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Our last number left us in the midst of a<lb break="yes"/>swarm
                    of moschettoes, and, however pain-<lb break="no"/>ful it has been to remain a
                    week among<lb break="yes"/>these pestiferous insects, there we are<lb
                        break="yes"/>still. Proceeding with his anecdotes to il-<lb break="no"
                    />lustrate their natural history, our author<lb break="yes"/>says:<lb
                        break="yes"/>&#x201C;I have just shown, from my own obser-<lb break="no"
                    />vations, how much the geographical distri-<lb break="no"/>bution of venomous
                    insects varies in this la-<lb break="no"/>byrinth of rivers with white and black
                        waters.<lb break="yes"/>It were to be wished, that a learned entomo-<lb
                        break="no"/>logist could study on the spot the specific<lb break="yes"
                    />differences of these noxious insects, which<lb break="yes"/>in the torrid
                    zone, in spite of their little-<lb break="no"/>ness, act an important part in
                    the economy<lb break="yes"/>of nature. What appeared to us very re-<lb
                        break="no"/>markable, and is a fact, known to all the<lb break="yes"
                    />missionaries, is, that the different species<lb break="yes"/>do not associate
                    together, and that at dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent hours of the day you are stung
                    by a<lb break="yes"/>distinct species. Every time that the scene<lb break="yes"
                    />changes, and to use the simple expression<lb break="yes"/>of the missionaries,
                    other insects &#x2018;mount<lb break="yes"/>guard<choice><sic>.</sic><corr
                            type="editorial">,</corr></choice>&#x2019; you have a few minutes, often
                        a<lb break="yes"/>quarter of an hour, of repose. The insects<lb break="yes"
                    />that disappear have not their places in-<lb break="no"/>stantly supplied in
                    equal numbers by their<lb break="yes"/>successors. From half after six in the<lb
                        break="yes"/>morning till five in the afternoon, the air is</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="375" facs="#f0005"/>
                <p>filled with moschettoes; which have not, as<lb break="yes"/>we find related in
                    some travels, the form of<lb break="yes"/>our gnats, but that of a small fly.
                    They are<lb break="yes"/>simuliums of the family nemocer&#x00E6; of the<lb
                        break="yes"/>system of Latreille. Their sting is as pain-<lb break="no"/>ful
                    as that of <hi rendition="#i">stomoxes</hi>. It leaves a little red-<lb
                        break="no"/>dish-brown spot, which is extravasated and<lb break="yes"
                    />coagulated blood, where their proboscis has<lb break="yes"/>pierced the skin.
                    An hour before sun-set a<lb break="yes"/>species of small gnats, called <hi
                        rendition="#i">tempraneros</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>because they appear also at
                    sun-rise, take<lb break="yes"/>the place of the moschettoes. Their pre-<lb
                        break="no"/>sence scarcely lasts an hour and a half;<lb break="yes"/>they
                    disappear between six and seven in the<lb break="yes"/>evening, or, as they say
                    here, after the <hi rendition="#i">An-<lb break="no"/>gelus</hi>(<hi
                        rendition="#i">a la oracion</hi>). After a few minutes<lb break="yes"
                    />repose, you feel yourself stund by <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi>,<lb
                        break="yes"/>another species of gnat (culex) with very<lb break="yes"/>long
                    legs. The zancudo, the proboscis of<lb break="yes"/>which contains a sharp
                    pointed sucker,<lb break="yes"/>causes the most acute pain, and a swelling<lb
                        break="yes"/>that remains several weeks. Its hum re-<lb break="no"/>sembles
                    that of our gnats in Europe, but is<lb break="yes"/>louder and more prolonged.
                    The Indians<lb break="yes"/>pretend to distinguish &#x2018;by their song&#x2019;
                        the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i">tempraneroes</hi>;
                    the latter<lb break="yes"/>of which are real <hi rendition="#i">twilight
                        insects</hi>, while the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi> are most frequently <hi rendition="#i"
                        >nocturnal in-<lb break="no"/>sects</hi>, and disappear towards
                    sun-rise.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;The <hi rendition="#i">culices</hi> of South America, have ge-<lb
                        break="no"/>nerally the wings, corselet, and legs of an<lb break="yes"
                    />azure colour, annulated, and variable from<lb break="yes"/>a mixture of spots
                    of a metallic lustre.<lb break="yes"/>Here, as in Europe, the males, which
                        are<lb break="yes"/>distinguished by their feathered antenn&#x00E6;,<lb
                        break="yes"/>are extremely rare; you are seldom stung<lb break="yes"/>except
                    by females. The preponderance of<lb break="yes"/>this sex explains the immense
                    increase of<lb break="yes"/>the species, each female laying several hun-<lb
                        break="no"/>dred eggs. In going up one of the great<lb break="yes"/>rivers
                    of Ameriva, it is observed, that the<lb break="yes"/>appearance of a new species
                    of <hi rendition="#i">culex</hi> denotes<lb break="yes"/>the approximity of a
                    new stream flowing<lb break="yes"/>in.<choice><sic>j</sic><corr type="editorial"
                        /></choice>&#x2019;</p>
                <p>&#x201C;The whites born in the torrid zone walk<lb break="yes"/>barefoot with
                    impunity in the same apart-<lb break="no"/>ment where a European recently landed
                        is<lb break="yes"/>exposed to the attack of the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >niguas</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">chegoes</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">pulex penetrans</hi>). These animals,
                        almost<lb break="yes"/>invisible to the eye, get under the nails of<lb
                        break="yes"/>the feet, and there acquire the size of a<lb break="yes"/>small
                    pea by the quick increase of its eggs,<lb break="yes"/>which are placed in a bag
                    under the belly<lb break="yes"/>of the insect. The <hi rendition="#i"
                    >nigua</hi>, therefore, distin-<lb break="no"/>guishes, what the most delicate
                        chemical<lb break="yes"/>analysis could not distinguish, the cellular<lb
                        break="yes"/>membrane and blood of a European from<lb break="yes"/>those of
                    a Creole white. It is not so with<lb break="yes"/>the moschettoes.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;In the day, even when labouring at<lb break="yes"/>the oar, the natives,
                    in order to chase the<lb break="yes"/>insects, are continually giving one
                        another<lb break="yes"/>smart slaps with the palm of the hand.<lb
                        break="yes"/>Rude in all their movements, they strike<lb break="yes"
                    />themselves and their comrades mechanically<lb break="yes"/>during their sleep.
                    The violence of their<lb break="yes"/>blows reminds us of the Persian tale of
                        the<lb break="yes"/>bear, that tried to kill with his paw the in-<lb
                        break="no"/>sects on the forehead of his sleeping mas-<lb break="no"/>ter.
                    Near Maypures we saw some young In-<lb break="no"/>dians seated in a circle and
                    rubbing cruelly<lb break="yes"/>each others backs with the bark of trees<lb
                        break="yes"/>dried at the fire. Indian women were oc-<lb break="no"/>cupied
                    with a degree of patience, of which<lb break="yes"/><cb/>the copper-coloured
                    race alone are capable,<lb break="yes"/>in extirpating by means of a sharp
                        bone<lb break="yes"/>the little mass of coagulated blood, that<lb
                        break="yes"/>forms the centre of every sting, and<lb break="yes"/>gives the
                    skin a speckled appearance.<lb break="yes"/>One of the most barbarous nations of
                        the<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko, that of the Otomacs, is ac-<lb break="no"
                    />quainted with the use of moschetto curtains<lb break="yes"/>(<hi
                        rendition="#i">mosquiteros</hi>) formed of a tissue of fibres of<lb
                        break="yes"/>the palm tree, <hi rendition="#i">murichi</hi>. We had lately
                        seen,<lb break="yes"/>that at Higuerote, on the coast of Caraccas,<lb
                        break="yes"/>the people of a copper colour sleep buried in<lb break="yes"
                    />the sand. In the villages of the Rio Mag-<lb break="no"/>dalena the Indians
                    often invited us to<lb break="yes"/>stretch ourselves with them on ox-skins,<lb
                        break="yes"/>near the church, in the middle of the <hi rendition="#i"
                            >plaza<lb break="yes"/>grande</hi>, where they had assembled all the<lb
                        break="yes"/>cows in the neighbourhood. The proximity<lb break="yes"/>of
                    cattle give some repose to man. The<lb break="yes"/>Indians of the Upper
                    Oroonoko and the<lb break="yes"/>Cassiquiare, seeing that Mr. Bonpland could<lb
                        break="yes"/>not prepare his herbal, on account of the<lb break="yes"
                    />continual torment of the moschettoes, in-<lb break="no"/>vited him to enter
                    their oveus, (<hi rendition="#i">hornitos</hi>).<lb break="yes"/>Thus they call
                    little chambers, without<lb break="yes"/>doors or windows, into which they
                        creep<lb break="yes"/>horizontally through a very small opening.<lb
                        break="yes"/>When they have driven away the insects<lb break="yes"/>by means
                    of a fire of wet brush-wood,<lb break="yes"/>which emits a great deal of smoke,
                        they<lb break="yes"/>close the opening of the oven. The ab-<lb break="no"
                    />sence of moschettoes is purchased clearly<lb break="yes"/>enough by the
                    excessive heat of stagnant<lb break="yes"/>air, and the smoke of a torch of <hi
                        rendition="#i">copal</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>which lights the oven during your
                    stay in<lb break="yes"/>it. Mr. Bonpland, with courage and pa-<lb break="no"
                    />tience well worthy of praise, dried hundreds<lb break="yes"/>of plants, shut
                    up in these <hi rendition="#i">hornitos</hi> of the<lb break="yes"/>Indians.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;It is difficult not to smile at hearing the<lb break="yes"/>missionaries
                    dispute on the size and vora-<lb break="no"/>city of the moschettoes at
                    different parts of<lb break="yes"/>the same river. In the centre of a<lb
                        break="yes"/>country ignorant of what is passing in the<lb break="yes"/>rest
                    of the world, this is the favorite sub-<lb break="no"/>ject of conversation.
                    &#x2018;How I pity your si-<lb break="no"/>tuation!&#x2019; said the missionary
                    of the rau-<lb break="no"/>dales to the missionary of Cassiquiare, at<lb
                        break="yes"/>our departure: &#x2018;you are alone, like me, in<lb
                        break="yes"/>this country of tigers and monkeys; with<lb break="yes"/>you
                    fish is still more rare, and the heat<lb break="yes"/>more violent; but as for
                    my flies, (<hi rendition="#i">mia mos-<lb break="no"/>cas</hi>) I can boast,
                    that with one of mine I<lb break="yes"/>would beat three of yours.&#x2019;</p>
                <p>&#x201C;This voracity of insects in certain spots,<lb break="yes"/>the rage with
                    which they attack man,<lb break="yes"/>the activity of the venom varying in
                        the<lb break="yes"/>same species, are very remarkable facts;<lb break="yes"
                    />which find their analogy, however, in the<lb break="yes"/>classes of large
                    animals. The crocodile of<lb break="yes"/>Angostura pursues men, while at
                        Nueva<lb break="yes"/>Barcelona, in the Rio Neveri, you may<lb break="yes"
                    />bathe tranquilly in the midst of the car-<lb break="no"/>nivorous reptiles.
                    The jaguars of Maturin,<lb break="yes"/>Cumanacoa, and the isthmus of Panama,<lb
                        break="yes"/>are cowardly in comparison to those of the<lb break="yes"
                    />Upper Oroonoko. The Indians well know,<lb break="yes"/>that the monkey of some
                    valleys can easily<lb break="yes"/>be tamed, while others of the same
                        species,<lb break="yes"/>caught elsewhere, will rather die of hunger,<lb
                        break="yes"/>than submit to slavery.<note place="foot" n="*">&#x201C;I might
                        have added the example of the<lb break="yes"/>scorpion of Cumana, which it
                        is very difficult to<lb break="yes"/><cb/>distinguish from that of the
                        island of Trinidad,<lb break="yes"/>Jamaica, Carthagena, and Guayaquil; yet
                            the<lb break="yes"/>former is not more to be feared than the <hi
                            rendition="#i">scorpio<lb break="yes"/>europ&#x00E6;us</hi> (of the
                        south of France), while the<lb break="yes"/>latter produces consequences far
                        more alarming<lb break="yes"/>than the <hi rendition="#i">scorpio
                            occitanus</hi> (of Spain and Bar-<lb break="no"/>bary). At Carthagena
                        and Guayaquil, the sting<lb break="yes"/>of the scorpion (<hi rendition="#i"
                            >alacran</hi>) instantly causes the<lb break="yes"/>loss of speech.
                        Sometimes a singular torpor of<lb break="yes"/>the tongue is observed for
                        fifteen or sixteen<lb break="yes"/>hours. The patient, when stung in the
                            legs,<lb break="yes"/>stammers as if he had been struck with apo-<lb
                            break="no"/>plexy.&#x201D;</note>&#x201D;<cb/>
                </p>
                <p>By this time we fancy our readers are<lb break="yes"/>as well acquainted with the
                    habits of the<lb break="yes"/>moschettoes, as if they had been bitten by<lb
                        break="yes"/>them all over; and further knowledge being<lb break="yes"
                    />unnecessary, we shall advance to other<lb break="yes"/>subjects.</p>
                <p>Above the cataract of Atures, at the<lb break="yes"/>mouth of the Rio Calaniapo,
                    Mr. Humboldt<lb break="yes"/>gives the following account of an extinct<lb
                        break="yes"/>tribe:</p>
                <p>&#x201C;We were shown at a distance, on the<lb break="yes"/>right of the river,
                    the rocks that surround the<lb break="yes"/>cavern of Ataruipe; but we had not
                    time to<lb break="yes"/>visit the cemetry of the destroyed tribe of<lb
                        break="yes"/>the Atures. We regretted this so much the<lb break="yes"/>more,
                    as father Zea was never weary of<lb break="yes"/>talking to us of the skeletons
                    painted with<lb break="yes"/>anotta, which this cavern contained; of<lb
                        break="yes"/>the large vases of baked earth, in which the<lb break="yes"
                    />bones of separate families appeared to be<lb break="yes"/>collected; and of
                    many other curious ob-<lb break="no"/>jects, which we proposed to examine at
                        our<lb break="yes"/>return from the Rio Negro.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>At Maypure, higher up, we hear more of<lb break="yes"/>the pottery of the
                    Indians:</p>
                <p>&#x201C;In every part of the forests, far from<lb break="yes"/>any human
                    habitation, on digging the earth,<lb break="yes"/>fragments of pottery and delft
                    are found.<lb break="yes"/>The taste for this kind of fabrication seems<lb
                        break="yes"/>to have been common heretofore to the na-<lb break="no"/>tives
                    of both Americas. To the north of<lb break="yes"/>Mexico,&#x2014;on the banks of
                    the Rio Gala&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>among the ruins of an Azteck city&#x2014;in
                        the<lb break="yes"/>United States&#x2014;near the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >tumuli</hi> of the Mia-<lb break="no"/>mis; in Florida&#x2014;and in every
                    place where<lb break="yes"/>any trace of ancient civilization could be<lb
                        break="yes"/>found, the soil covers fragments of painted<lb break="yes"
                    />pottery; and the extreme resemblances of<lb break="yes"/>the ornaments they
                    display is striking.<lb break="yes"/>Savage nations, and those civilized
                        people,<lb break="yes"/>who are condemned by their political<lb break="yes"
                    />and religious institutions always to imi-<lb break="no"/>tate themselves,
                    strive, as if by instinct, to<lb break="yes"/>perpetuate the same forms, to
                    preserve a<lb break="yes"/>peculiar type or style, and to follow the<lb
                        break="yes"/>methods and processes which were employed<lb break="yes"/>by
                    their ancestors. In North America,<lb break="yes"/>fragments of delft have been
                    discovered in<lb break="yes"/>places where lines of fortification are found,<lb
                        break="yes"/>and the walls of towns constructed by an<lb break="yes"
                    />unknown nation, now entirely extinct.<lb break="yes"/>The paintings on these
                    fragments have a<lb break="yes"/>great similitude to those which are executed<lb
                        break="yes"/>in our days on earthenware by the natives<lb break="yes"/>of
                    Louisiana and Florida. Thus too the<lb break="yes"/>Indians of Maypure often
                    painted before<lb break="yes"/>our eyes the same ornaments as we had<lb
                        break="yes"/>observed in the cavern of <choice><sic>Ataroipe</sic><corr
                            type="editorial">Ataruipe</corr></choice>, on the<lb break="yes"/>vases
                    containing human bones. They are<lb break="yes"/>real <hi rendition="#i"
                        >grecques</hi>, <choice><sic>ineaudrites</sic><corr type="editorial"
                            >meandrites</corr></choice>, and figures of<lb break="yes"/>crocodiles,
                    of monkeys, and of a large qua-</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="376" facs="#f0006"/>
                <p>druped, which I could not recognize, though<lb break="yes"/>it has always the
                    same squat form.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>Above Maypure this is indeed a &#x201C;New<lb break="yes"/>World,&#x201D;: Mr.
                    Humboldt says:&#x2014;</p>
                <p>&#x201C;When the traveller has passed the<lb break="yes"/>great cataracts, he
                    feels as if he were in a<lb break="yes"/>new world; and had overstepped the
                        bar-<lb break="no"/>riers which nature seems to have raised be-<lb
                        break="no"/>tween the civilized countries of the coast and<lb break="yes"
                    />the savage and unknown interior. Toward<lb break="yes"/>the east, in the
                    bluish distance, appeared<lb break="yes"/>for the last time, the high chain of
                    the Cu-<lb break="no"/>navami mountains. Its long horizontal ridge<lb
                        break="yes"/>reminded us of the Mesa of Bergantin, near<lb break="yes"
                    />Cumana; but it terminates by a truncated<lb break="yes"/>summit. The peak of
                    Calitamini (the name<lb break="yes"/>given to this summit) glows at sun-set
                        as<lb break="yes"/>with reddish fire. This appearance is<lb break="yes"
                    />every day the same. No one ever ap-<lb break="no"/>proached the summit of this
                    mountain, the<lb break="yes"/>height of which does not exceed six hun-<lb
                        break="no"/>dred toises. I believe this splendor, com-<lb break="no"/>monly
                    reddish and sometimes silvery, to be<lb break="yes"/>a reflexion produced by
                    large plates of talc,<lb break="yes"/>or by gneiss passing into mica-slate.
                        The<lb break="yes"/>whole of this country contains granitic<lb break="yes"
                    />rocks, on which here and there, in little<lb break="yes"/>plains, an
                    argillaceous grit-stone immediately<lb break="yes"/>reposes, containing
                    fragments of quartz,<lb break="yes"/>and of brown iron ore.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;In going to the <hi rendition="#i">embarcadere</hi>&#x201D; he con-<lb
                        break="no"/>tinues, &#x201C;we caught on the trunk of a
                            hevea<choice><sic/><corr type="editorial">,</corr></choice><lb
                        break="yes"/>a new species of tree frog, remarkable for<lb break="yes"/>its
                    beautiful colours; it had a yellow belly,<lb break="yes"/>the back and head of a
                    fine velvetty purple,<lb break="yes"/>and a very narrow stripe of white from
                        the<lb break="yes"/>point of the nose to the hinder extremities.<lb
                        break="yes"/>This frog was two inches long, and allied to<lb break="yes"
                    />the <hi rendition="#i">rana tinctoria</hi>, the blood of which, it is<lb
                        break="yes"/>asserted, introduced into the skin of a<lb break="yes"/>parrot,
                    in places where the feathers have<lb break="yes"/>been plucked out, occasions
                    the growth of<lb break="yes"/>frizzled feathers of a yellow or red colour.</p>
                <p>But this is not only the region of real<lb break="yes"/>wonders; it has its
                    fictions also.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;The forests of Sipapo are altogether un-<lb break="no"/>known, and there
                    the missionaries place<lb break="yes"/>the nation of <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Rayas</hi>, who have their mouth<lb break="yes"/>in the navel. An old
                    Indian, whom we<lb break="yes"/>met at Carichano, and who boasted of<lb
                        break="yes"/>having often eaten human flesh, had seen<lb break="yes"/>these
                        <hi rendition="#i">acephali</hi> &#x2018;with his own eyes.&#x2019; These<lb
                        break="yes"/>absurd fables are spread as far as the Llanos,<lb break="yes"
                    />where you are not always permitted to doubt<lb break="yes"/>the existence of
                    the <hi rendition="#i">Raya</hi> Indians. In<lb break="yes"/>every zone
                    intolerance accompanies cre-<lb break="no"/>dulity; and it might be said, that
                    the fic-<lb break="no"/>tions of ancient geographers had passed from<lb
                        break="yes"/>one hemisphere to the other, did we not<lb break="yes"/>know,
                    that the most fantastic productions of<lb break="yes"/>the imagination, like the
                    works of nature,<lb break="yes"/>furnish every where a certain analogy of<lb
                        break="yes"/>aspect and form.&#x201D;</p>
            </div><!-- rc adding missing text from 23. Juni, S. 389 taken from 1822-A_v_Humboldts-2.xml
and also from Personal Narrative, Project Gutenberg -->
            
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#k">humboldt&#x2019;s travels,</hi><lb break="yes"
                    />(Continued.)</head>
                <p>We cannot, even in the midst of the in-<lb/>teresting works which are at present
                        almost<lb/>daily issuing from the press, do better than<lb/>continue
                        to devote a page or our Gazette to<lb/>the agreeable narrative of this
                        enterprising<lb/>and intelligent traveller. In a preceding<lb/>paper
                        we have remarked upon the extraor-<lb/>dinary degree of general
                        knowledge which<lb/>he brings to bear on any topic he is
                        illus-<lb/>trating. The following is an admirable<lb/>example of the
                        truth of this position:<lb/></p><p>&#x201C;Every hemisphere produces plants
                    of a different species; and it is not by the diversity of climates that we can
                    attempt to explain why equinoctial Africa has no laurineæ, and the New World no
                    heaths; why the calceolariæ are found only in the Southern hemisphere; why the
                    birds of the continent of India glow with colours less splendid than the birds
                    of the hot parts of America; finally, why the tiger is peculiar to Asia, and the
                    ornithorhincus to New Holland. In the vegetable, as well as in the animal
                    kingdom, the causes of the distribution of the species are among the number of
                    mysteries which natural philosophy cannot reach. This science is not occupied in
                    the investigation of the origin of beings, but of the laws according to which
                    they are distributed on the globe. It examines the things that are, the
                    coexistence of vegetable and animal forms, in each latitude, at different
                    heights, and at different degrees of temperature; it studies the relations under
                    which particular organizations are more vigorously developed, multiplied or
                    modified; but it approaches not problems, the solution of which is impossible,
                    since they touch the origin, the first existence of a germ of life. We may add,
                    that the attempts that have been made to explain the distribution of various
                    species on the globe, by the sole influence of climate, date at a period when
                    physical geography was still in its infancy; when, recurring incessantly to
                    pretended contrasts between the two worlds, it was imagined, that the whole of
                    Africa and of America resembled the deserts of Egypt, and the marshes of
                    Cayenne. At present, when men judge of the state of things not from one type
                    arbitrarily chosen, but from positive knowledge, it is ascertained that the two
                    continents, in their immense extent, contain countries that are altogether
                    analogous. There are regions of America, as barren and burning as the interior
                    of Africa. The islands that produce the spices of India are scarcely remarkable
                    for their dryness; and it is not on account of the humidity of the climate, as
                    it has been affirmed in recent works, that the New Continent is deprived of
                    those fine species of laurineæ and myristicæ, which are found united in one
                    little corner of the earth, in the archipelago of India. For some years past,
                    the real cinnamon has been cultivated with success in several parts of the New
                    Continent; and a zone that produces the coumarouna, the vanilla, the pucheri,
                    the pine-apple, the myrtus pimenta, the balsam of tolu, the myroxylon
                    peruvianum, the crotons, the citrosmas, the pejoa, the incienso of the silla of
                    Caraccas, the quereme, the pancratium, and so many majestic liliaceous plants,
                    cannot be considered as destitute of aromatics. Besides, a dry air favours the
                    developement of the aromatic, or exciting properties, only in certain species of
                    plants. The most cruel poisons are produced in the most humid zone of America:
                    and it is precisely under the influence of the long rains of the tropics that
                    the American pimento, capsicum baccatum, the fruit of which is often as caustic
                    and fiery as Indian pepper, vegetates best. From the whole of these
                    considerations, it follows, 1st, that the new continent possesses spices,
                    aromatics, and very active vegetable poisons that are peculiar to itself,
                    differing specifically from those of the ancient world; 2dly, that the primitive
                    distribution of species in the torrid zone cannot be explained by the influence
                    of climate solely, or by the distribution of temperature, which we observe in
                    the present state of our planet; but that this difference of climate leads us to
                    perceive, why a given type of organization developes itself more vigorously in
                    such or such local circumstances. We can conceive, that a small number of the
                    families of plants, for instance the musaceæ and the palms, cannot belong to
                    very cold regions, on account of their internal structure and the importance of
                    certain organs; but we cannot explain why no one of the family of melastomas
                    vegetates north of the parallel of thirty degrees, or why no rose tree belongs
                    to the southern hemisphere. Analogy of climates is often found in the two
                    continents, without identity of productions.&#x201D;</p><p>&#x201C;Its trunk,
                        armed with thorns, is more than sixty feet high; its leaves are pinnated,
                        very thin, undulated, and frizzled towards the points. The fruits of this
                        tree are very extraordinary; every cluster contains from fifty to eighty;
                        they are yellow like apples, grow purple in proportion as they ripen, two or
                        three inches thick, and generally, from abortion, without a kernel. Among
                        the eighty or ninety species of palm-trees peculiar to the New Continent,
                        which I have enumerated in the Nova Genera Plantarum Aequinoctialum, there
                        are none in which the sarcocarp is developed in a manner so extraordinary.
                        The fruit of the pirijao furnishes a farinaceous substance, as yellow as the
                        yolk of an egg, slightly saccharine, and extremely nutritious. It is eaten
                        like plantains or potatoes, boiled or roasted in the ashes, and affords a
                        wholesome and agreeable aliment. The Indians and the missionaries are
                        unwearied in their praises of this noble palm-tree, which might be called
                        the peach-palm. We found it cultivated in abundance at San Fernando, San
                        Balthasar, Santa Barbara, and wherever we advanced towards the south or the
                        east along the banks of the Atabapo and the Upper Orinoco. In those wild
                        regions we are involuntarily reminded of the assertion of Linnaeus, that the
                        country of palm-trees was the first abode of our species, and that man is
                        essentially palmivorous. On examining the provision accumulated in the huts
                        of the Indians, we perceive that their subsistence during several months of
                        the year depends as much on the farinaceous fruit of the pirijao, as on the
                        cassava and plantain. The tree bears fruit but once a year, but to the
                        amount of three clusters, consequently from one hundred and fifty to two
                        hundred fruits.&#x201D;</p><p>Here, also, is the gigantic bombax … they
                        landed to measure it. &#x201C;The height was nearly one hundred and twenty
                        feet, and the diameter between fourteen and fifteen. This enormous specimen
                        of vegetation surprised us the more, as we had till then seen on the banks
                        of the Atabapo only small trees with slender trunks, which from afar
                        resembled young cherry-trees. The Indians assured that these small trees do
                        not form a very extensive group. They are checked in their growth by the
                        inundations of the river; while the dry grounds near the Atabapo, the Temi,
                        and the Tuamini, furnish excellent timber for building.&#x201D;</p><p>Nor is
                    animal inferior to vegetable life.</p><p>&#x201C;The river Atabapo presents
                        throughout a peculiar aspect; you see nothing of its real banks formed by
                        flat lands eight or ten feet high; they are concealed by a row of palms, and
                        small trees with slender trunks, the roots of which are bathed by the
                        waters. There are many crocodiles from the point where you quit the Orinoco
                        to the mission of San Fernando, and their presence indicates that this part
                        of the river belongs to the Rio Guaviare and not to the Atabapo. In the real
                        bed of the latter river, above the mission of San Fernando, there are no
                        crocodiles: we find there some bavas, a great many fresh-water dolphins, but
                        no manatees. We also seek in vain on these banks for the thick-nosed tapir,
                        the araguato, or great howling monkey, the zamuro, or Vultur aura, and the
                        crested pheasant, known by the name of guacharaca. Enormous water-snakes, in
                        shape resembling the boa, are unfortunately very common, and are dangerous
                        to Indians who bathe. We saw them almost from the first day we embarked,
                        swimming by the side of our canoe; they were at most twelve or fourteen feet
                        long. The jaguars of the banks of the Atabapo and the Temi are large and
                        well fed; they are said, however, to be less daring than the jaguars of the
                        Orinoco.&#x201D;</p><p>Thus (as we have stated), interspersed<lb/>with
                anecdote, does Mr. Humboldt vary his<lb/>entertaining volumes; and that our
                    review<lb/>may partake of the character of its subject,<lb/>we shall conclude
                    the present division of it<lb/>by copying a very affecting story.
                    Where<lb/>the Atabapo enters the Rio Temi, the nar-<lb/>rative
                    says:</p><p>&#x201C;Before we reached its confluence, a granitic eminence on
                    the western bank, near the mouth of the Guasacavi, fixed our attention: it is
                    called Piedra de la Guahiba (Rock of the Guahiba woman), or the Piedra de la
                    Madre (Mother's Rock.) We inquired the cause of so singular a denomination.
                    Father Zea could not satisfy our curiosity; but some weeks after, another
                    missionary, one of the predecessors of that ecclesiastic, whom we found settled
                    at San Fernando as president of the missions, related to us an event which
                    excited in our minds the most painful feelings. If, in these solitary scenes,
                    man scarcely leaves behind him any trace of his existence, it is doubly
                    humiliating for a European to see perpetuated by so imperishable a monument of
                    nature as a rock, the remembrance of the moral degradation of our species, and
                    the contrast between the virtue of a savage, and the barbarism of civilized
                    man!</p><p>&#x201C;In 1797 the missionary of San Fernando had led his Indians to
                    the banks of the Rio Guaviare, on one of those hostile incursions which are
                    prohibited alike by religion and the Spanish laws. They found in an Indian hut a
                    Guahiba woman with her three children (two of whom were still infants), occupied
                    in preparing the flour of cassava. Resistance was impossible; the father was
                    gone to fish, and the mother tried in vain to flee with her children. Scarcely
                    had she reached the savannah when she was seized by the Indians of the mission,
                    who hunt human beings, like the Whites and the Negroes in Africa. The mother and
                    her children were bound, and dragged to the bank of the river. The monk, seated
                    in his boat, waited the issue of an expedition of which he shared not the
                    danger. Had the mother made too violent a resistance the Indians would have
                    killed her, for everything is permitted for the sake of the conquest of souls
                    (la conquista espirituel), and it is particularly desirable to capture children,
                    who may be treated in the Mission as poitos, or slaves of the Christians. The
                    prisoners were carried to San Fernando, in the hope that the mother would be
                    unable to find her way back to her home by land. Separated from her other
                    children who had accompanied their father on the day in which she had been
                    carried off, the unhappy woman showed signs of the deepest despair. She
                    attempted to take back to her home the children who had been seized by the
                    missionary; and she fled with them repeatedly from the village of San Fernando.
                    But the Indians never failed to recapture her; and the missionary, after having
                    caused her to be mercilessly beaten, took the cruel resolution of separating the
                    mother from the two children who had been carried off with her. She was conveyed
                    alone to the missions of the Rio Negro, going up the Atabapo. Slightly bound,
                    she was seated at the bow of the boat, ignorant of the fate that awaited her;
                    but she judged by the direction of the sun, that she was removing farther and
                    farther from her hut and her native country. She succeeded in breaking her
                    bonds, threw herself into the water, and swam to the left bank of the Atabapo.
                    The current carried her to a shelf of rock, which bears her name to this day.
                    She landed and took shelter in the woods, but the president of the missions
                    ordered the Indians to row to the shore, and follow the traces of the Guahiba.
                    In the evening she was brought back. Stretched upon the rock (la Piedra de la
                    Madre) a cruel punishment was inflicted on her with those straps of manatee
                    leather, which serve for whips in that country, and with which the alcaldes are
                    always furnished. This unhappy woman, her hands tied behind her back with strong
                    stalks of mavacure, was then dragged to the mission of Javita.</p><p>&#x201C;She
                    was there thrown into one of the caravanserais, called las Casas del Rey. It was
                    the rainy season, and the night was profoundly dark. Forests till then believed
                    to be impenetrable separated the mission of Javita from that of San Fernando,
                    which was twenty-five leagues distant in a straight line. No other route is
                    known than that by the rivers; no man ever attempted to go by land from one
                    village to another. But such difficulties could not deter a mother, separated
                    from her children. The Guahiba was carelessly guarded in the caravanserai. Her
                    arms being wounded, the Indians of Javita had loosened her bonds, unknown to the
                    missionary and the alcaldes. Having succeeded by the help of her teeth in
                    breaking them entirely, she disappeared during the night; and at the fourth
                    sunrise was seen at the mission of San Fernando, hovering around the hut where
                    her children were confined. "What that woman performed," added the missionary,
                    who gave us this sad narrative, "the most robust Indian would not have ventured
                    to undertake!" She traversed the woods at a season when the sky is constantly
                    covered with clouds, and the sun during whole days appears but for a few
                    minutes. Did the course of the waters direct her way? The inundations of the
                    rivers forced her to go far from the banks of the main stream, through the midst
                    of woods where the movement of the water is almost imperceptible. How often must
                    she have been stopped by the thorny lianas, that form a network around the
                    trunks they entwine! How often must she have swum across the rivulets that run
                    into the Atabapo! This unfortunate woman was asked how she had sustained herself
                    during four days. She said that, exhausted with fatigue, she could find no other
                    nourishment than those great black ants called vachacos, which climb the trees
                    in long bands, to suspend on them their resinous nests. We pressed the
                    missionary to tell us whether the Guahiba had peacefully enjoyed the happiness
                    of remaining with her children; and if any repentance had followed this excess
                    of cruelty. He would not satisfy our curiosity; but at our return from the Rio
                    Negro we learned that the Indian mother was again separated from her children,
                    and sent to one of the missions of the Upper Orinoco. There she died, refusing
                    all kind of nourishment, as savages frequently do in great
                    calamities.</p><p>&#x201C;Such is the remembrance annexed to this fatal rock,
                    the Piedra de la Madre.</p></div>
            <!-- rc adding missing text from 30. Juni, S. 405 taken from 1821-Indian_Rubber-2-neu.xml and also from Personal Narrative, Project Gutenberg -->
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#k">humboldt&#x2019;s travels,</hi><lb break="yes"/>(Continued.)</head>
            <p>This journal is so pregnant with instruc-<lb/>tive and interesting matter, that we
                    could<lb/>hardly, as we think, place any thing better<lb/>before our readers,
                    though we might be<lb/>more instant with a greater variety of
                    no-<lb/>velty. We therefore continue our extracts.<lb/>The following is
                    a curious account of the<lb/>Indian Rubber:&#x2014;&#x201C;Here (Says Mr. H. at
                the mission of St. Balthasar on the Atobapo) we saw, for the first time, that white
                and fungous<lb break="yes"/>substance, which I have made known by the name of<lb
                    break="yes"/>
                <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">zapis.</hi> We immediately
                perceived, that it<lb break="yes"/>was analogous to the <hi rendition="#i">elastic
                    resin;</hi> but, as the Indians<lb break="yes"/>made us understand by signs,
                that it was found under<lb break="yes"/>ground, we were inclined to think, till we
                arrived at<lb break="yes"/>the mission of Javita, that the <hi rendition="#i"
                    >dapicho</hi> was a fossil<lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="243" facs="#f0002"/> caoutchouc, though different from the elastic bitumen<lb
                    break="yes"/>of Derbyshire. A Poimisano Indian, seated by the<lb break="yes"
                />fire, in the hut of the missionary, was employed in<lb break="yes"/>reducing the
                    <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> into black caoutchouc. He had<lb break="yes"
                />spitted several bits on a slender stick, and was roast-<lb break="no"/>ing them
                like meat. The <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> blackens in propor-<lb break="no"
                />tion as it grows softer, and gains in elasticity. The<lb break="yes"/>resinous and
                aromatic smell, which filled the hut,<lb break="yes"/>seemed to indicate, that this
                coloration is the effect of<lb break="yes"/>the decomposition of a carburet of
                hydrogen, and that<lb break="yes"/>the carbon appears in proportion as the
                    hydrogen<lb break="yes"/>burns at a low heat. The Indian beat the softened<lb
                    break="yes"/>and blackened mass with a piece of brazil wood, end-<lb break="no"
                />ing in the form of a club; he then kneaded the <hi rendition="#i">dapi-<lb
                        break="no"/>cho</hi> into balls of three or four inches in diameter, and
                    let<lb break="yes"/>it cool. These balls exactly resemble the caoutchouc<lb
                    break="yes"/>of the shops, but their surface remains in general<lb break="yes"
                />slightly viscous. They are used at San Balthasar in<lb break="yes"/>the Indian
                game of tennis, which is so celebrated<lb break="yes"/>among the inhabitants of
                Uruana and Encaramada;<lb break="yes"/>they are cut into cylinders, to be used as
                corks, and<lb break="yes"/>are far preferable to those made of the bark of the<lb
                    break="yes"/>cork-tree.&#x201D;</p><lb break="yes"/><p>Soon after, we obtained
                precise information respect-<lb break="no"/>ing this substance:&#x2014;it was shown
                us at the depth of<lb break="yes"/>two or three feet, in a marshy soil, between the
                    roots<lb break="yes"/>of two trees known by the name of the <hi rendition="#i"
                    >jacio</hi> and the<lb break="yes"/>
                <hi rendition="#i">curvana.</hi> The first is the <hi rendition="#i">hevea</hi> of
                Aublet, or <hi rendition="#i">siphonia</hi>
                <lb break="yes"/>of the modern botanists, known to furnish the caout-<lb break="no"
                />chouc of commerce in Cayenne and the Grand Para;<lb break="yes"/>the second has
                pinnate leaves, and its juice is milky,<lb break="yes"/>but very thin, and almost
                destitute of viscocity. The<lb break="yes"/>
                <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> appears to be the result of an extravasation of<lb
                    break="yes"/>the sap from the roots. This extravasation takes<lb break="yes"
                />place more especially when the trees have attained a<lb break="yes"/>great age,
                and the interior of the trunk begins to<lb break="yes"/>decay. The bark and alburnum
                crack; and thus is<lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="244" facs="#f0003"/> effected naturally, what the art of man performs to<lb
                    break="yes"/>collect in abundance the milky juices of the hevea, the<lb
                    break="yes"/>castilloa, and the caoutchouc fig tree.&#x201D;</p><lb break="yes"
                /><p>The river Temi, near the banks of which this production is found in sufficient
                quantities to supply all<lb break="yes"/>Europe, runs through forests which
                overshadow it in<lb break="yes"/>so wild and luxuriant a manner as almost to
                    mingle<lb break="yes"/>together the creatures of the several elements of air,<lb
                    break="yes"/>earth, and water, and realize the classic images:</p><lb
                break="yes"/><lg type="poem">
                <l>S&#x00E6;culum Pyrrh&#x00E6;, nova monstra quest&#x00E6;;</l>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <l>Omne quum Proteus pecus egit altos</l>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <l>
                    <hi rendition="#et">Visere montes;</hi>
                </l>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <l>Piscium et summa genus h&#x00E6;sit ulmo,</l>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <l>Nota qu&#x00E6; sedes fuerat Columbis,</l>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <l>Et superjecto pavid&#x00E6; natarunt</l>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <l>
                    <hi rendition="#et">&#x00C6;quore dam&#x00E6;.</hi>
                </l>
            </lg><lb break="yes"/><p>&#x201C;The Indians (says Mr. H.) made us leave the bed of
                    the<lb break="yes"/>river; and we went up towards the south, across<lb
                    break="yes"/>the forest, through paths <hi rendition="#i">(sendas)</hi> that is,
                    through<lb break="yes"/>open channels of four or five feet broad. The<lb
                    break="yes"/>depth of the water seldom exceeds half a fathom.<lb break="yes"
                />These <hi rendition="#i">sendas</hi> are formed in the inundated forest-like<lb
                    break="yes"/>paths on dry ground. The Indians, in going from<lb break="yes"/>one
                mission to another, pass with their boats as much<lb break="yes"/>as possible by the
                same way; but the communications<lb break="yes"/>not being frequent, the force of
                vegetation sometimes<lb break="yes"/>produces unexpected obstacles. An Indian,
                    furnished<lb break="yes"/>with a <hi rendition="#i">machette</hi> (a great
                knife, the blade of which is<lb break="yes"/>fourteen inches long,) stood at the
                head of our boat,<lb break="yes"/>employed continually in chopping off the
                    branches<lb break="yes"/>that cross each other from the two sides of the
                    channel.<lb break="yes"/>In the thickest part of the forest we were
                    astonished<lb break="yes"/>by an extraordinary noise. On beating the bushes,<lb
                    break="yes"/>a shoal of <hi rendition="#i">toninas</hi> (fresh water dolphins)
                four feet<lb break="yes"/>long, surrounded our boat. These animals had con-<lb
                    break="no"/>cealed themselves beneath the branches of a fromager<lb break="yes"
                />or bombax ceiba. They fled across the forest, throw-<lb break="no"/>ing out those
                spouts of compressed air and water,<lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="245" facs="#f0004"/> which have given them in every language the name of<lb
                    break="yes"/>
                <hi rendition="#i">blowers.</hi> How singular was this spectacle in the mid-<lb
                    break="no"/>dle of the land, three or four hundred leagues from<lb break="yes"
                />the mouths of the Oroonoko and the Amazon! I am<lb break="yes"/>not ignorant, that
                the pleuronectes of the Atlantic go<lb break="yes"/>up the Loire as far as Orleans;
                but I persist in think-<lb break="no"/>ing, that the dolphins of the Temi, like
                those of the<lb break="yes"/>Ganges, and like the skate <hi rendition="#i"
                    >(raia)</hi> of the Oroonoko, are<lb break="yes"/>of a species essentially
                different from the dolphins and<lb break="yes"/>skates of the ocean. In the immense
                rivers of South<lb break="yes"/>America, and the great lakes of North America,<lb
                    break="yes"/>nature seems to repeat several pelagic forms. The<lb break="yes"
                />Nile has no porpoises: those of the sea go up the<lb break="yes"/>Delta no farther
                than Biana and Metonbis toward<lb break="yes"/>Selamoun.&#x201D;</p><p>But these …
                &#x2014;&#x201C;We felt an extraordinary irritation on the joints of our fingers,
                and on the backs of our hands. The missionary told us it was caused by the aradores,
                (ploughman insects), which get under the skin. We could distinguish with a lens
                nothing but streaks, or parallel and whitish furrows. It is the form of these
                furrows, that has obtained for the insect the name of ploughman. A mulatto woman was
                sent for, who professed to be thoroughly acquainted with all the little insects that
                burrow in the human skin; the chego, the nuche, the coya, and the arador; she was
                the curandera, or surgeon of the place. She promised to extirpate, one by one, the
                insects which caused this smarting irritation. Having heated at a lamp the point a
                little bit of hard wood, she dug with it into the furrows that marked the skin.
                After long examination, she announced with the pedantic gravity peculiar to the
                mulatto race, that an arador was found. I saw a little round bag, which I suspected
                to be the egg of an acarus. I was to find relief when the mulatto woman had
                succeeded in taking out three or four of these aradores. Having the skin of both
                hands filled with acari, I had not the patience to wait the end of an operation,
                which had already lasted till late at night. The next day an Indian of Javita cured
                us radically, and with surprising promptitude. He brought us the branch of a shrub,
                called uzao.</p><p>The annexed natives of the … &#x2014;&#x201C;The nations of the
                Upper Orinoco, the Atabapo, and the Inirida, like the ancient Germans and the
                Persians, have no other worship than that of the powers of nature. They call the
                good principle Cachimana; it is the Manitou, the Great Spirit, that regulates the
                seasons, and favours the harvests. Along with Cachimana there is an evil principle,
                Iolokiamo, less powerful, but more artful, and in particular more active. The
                Indians of the forest, when they occasionally visit the missions, conceive with
                difficulty the idea of a temple or an image. "These good people," said the
                missionary, "like only processions in the open air. When I last celebrated the
                festival of San Antonio, the patron of my village, the Indians of Inirida were
                present at mass. 'Your God,' said they to me, 'keeps himself shut up in a house, as
                if he were old and infirm; ours is in the forest, in the fields, and on the
                mountains of Sipapu, whence the rains come.'" Among the more numerous, and on this
                account less barbarous tribes, religious societies of a singular kind are formed.
                Some old Indians pretend to be better instructed than others on points regarding
                divinity; and to them is confided the famous botuto, of which I have spoken, and
                which is sounded under the palm-trees that they may bear abundance of fruit. On the
                banks of the Orinoco there exists no idol, as among all the nations who have
                remained faithful to the first worship of nature, but the botuto, the sacred
                trumpet, is an object of veneration. To be initiated into the mysteries of the
                botuto, it is requisite to be of pure morals, and to have lived single. The
                initiated are subjected to flagellations, fastings, and other painful exercises.
                There are but a small number of these sacred trumpets. The most anciently celebrated
                is that upon a hill near the confluence of the Tomo and the Guainia. It is
                pretended, that it is heard at once on the banks of the Tuamini, and at the mission
                of San Miguel de Davipe, a distance of ten leagues. Father Cereso assured us, that
                the Indians speak of the botuto of Tomo as an object of worship common to many
                surrounding tribes. Fruit and intoxicating liquors are placed beside the sacred
                trumpet. Sometimes the Great Spirit himself makes the botuto resound; sometimes he
                is content to manifest his will through him to whom the keeping of the instrument is
                entrusted. These juggleries being very ancient (from the fathers of our fathers, say
                the Indians), we must not be surprised that some unbelievers are already to be
                found; but they express their disbelief of the mysteries of the botuto only in
                whispers. Women are not permitted to see this marvellous instrument; and are
                excluded from all the ceremonies of this worship. If a woman have the misfortune to
                see the trumpet, she is put to death without mercy.&#x201D;</p><p>(To be
                    continued.)<lb break="yes"/></p>
            
            </div>
            <!-- rc adding missing text from 14. Juli, S. 441 taken from 1821-Humboldts_Personal_Narrative_Serpents-1 & #2 (& #3, Dutch lang?) which are exact copies, therefore need to be part of this Bündel. -->
            
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#k">humboldt&#x2019;s personal narrative.</hi><lb break="yes"/>(Continued.)</head>
            
            <p>M. Humboldt relates some remarkable<lb break="yes"/>particulars concerning the
                serpents in South<lb break="yes"/>America, and the following will show to what<lb
                    break="yes"/>perils, from them, the traveller is exposed.<lb break="yes"/>On
                taking up a night&#x2019;s lodging, we are<lb break="yes"/>told &#x2014;&#x201D;
                Before we took possession of the<lb break="yes"/>deserted hut, the Indians killed
                two great<lb break="yes"/>
                <choice><sic><hi rendition="#i">mapanarc</hi></sic><corr type="editorial"><hi
                            rendition="#i">mapanare</hi></corr></choice> serpents. These grow to
                four or<lb break="yes"/>five feet long. They appeared to me to be<lb break="yes"
                />the same species as those I described in<lb break="yes"/>the Rio Magdalena. It is
                a beautiful ani-<lb break="no"/>mal, but extremely venomous, white below<lb
                    break="yes"/>the belly, and spotted with brown and red<lb break="yes"/>on the
                back. As the inside of the hut was<lb break="yes"/>filled with grass, and as we lay
                upon the<lb break="yes"/>ground, there being no means of suspending<lb break="yes"
                />our hammocks, we were not without in-<lb break="no"/>quietude during the night. In
                the morn-<lb break="no"/>ing a large viper was found on lifting up<lb break="yes"
                />from the ground the jaguar skin, upon<lb break="yes"/>which one of our domestics
                had slept. The<lb break="yes"/>Indians say, that these reptiles, slow in their<lb
                    break="yes"/>movements when they are not pursued, creep<lb break="yes"/>near a
                man because they are fond of heat.<lb break="yes"/>In fact, on the banks of the
                Magdalena a<lb break="yes"/>serpent entered the bed of one of our fel-<lb break="no"
                />low travellers, where he remained a part of<lb break="yes"/>the night, without
                doing him any harm.<lb break="yes"/>Without wishing here to take up the de-<lb
                    break="no"/>fence of vipers and rattlesnakes, I believe<lb break="yes"/>it may
                be affirmed, that, if these venomous<lb break="yes"/>animals had such a disposition
                for offence<lb break="yes"/>as is supposed, the human species would<lb break="yes"
                />certainly not have resisted their numbers<lb break="yes"/>in some parts of
                America; for instance, on<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the Oroonoko, and the
                    humid<lb break="yes"/>mountains of Choco.&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>After this the wanderers entered the Rio<lb break="yes"/>Negro, and the view here
                taken is both<lb break="yes"/>geographically good and morally affecting.<lb
                    break="yes"/>&#x2014;&#x201C; After all we had endured (observes our<lb
                    break="yes"/>interesting author), I may be permitted,<lb break="yes"/>perhaps,
                to speak of the satisfaction we felt<lb break="yes"/>in having reached the tributary
                streams of<lb break="yes"/>the Amazon, having passed the isthmus that<lb break="yes"
                />separates two great systems of rivers, and<lb break="yes"/>in being sure of having
                fulfilled the most<lb break="yes"/>important object of our voyage, the deter-<lb
                    break="no"/>mining astronomically the course of that<lb break="yes"/>arm of the
                        <choice><sic>Oroonnko</sic><corr type="editorial">Oroonoko</corr></choice>,
                which falls into the<lb break="yes"/>Rio Negro, and of which the existence has<lb
                    break="yes"/>been alternately proved and denied during<lb break="yes"/>half a
                century. In proportion as we draw<lb break="yes"/>near to an object we have long had
                in view,<lb break="yes"/>its interest seems to augment. The unin-<lb break="no"
                />habited banks of the Cassiquiare, covered<lb break="yes"/>with forests, without
                memorials of times<lb break="yes"/>past, then occupied my imagination, as do<lb
                    break="yes"/>now the banks of the Euphrates, or the<lb break="yes"/>Oxus,
                celebrated in the annals of civilized<lb break="yes"/>nations. In that interior part
                of the New<lb break="yes"/>Continent we almost accustomed ourselves<lb break="yes"
                />to regard men as not being essential to the<lb break="yes"/>order of nature. The
                earth is loaded with<lb break="yes"/>plants, and nothing impedes their free de-<lb
                    break="no"/>velopement. An immense layer of mould<lb break="yes"/>manifests the
                uninterrupted action of or-<lb break="no"/>ganic powers. The crocodiles and the
                    boas<lb break="yes"/>are masters of the river; the jaguar, the<lb break="yes"
                />pecari, the dante, and the monkeys, tra-<lb break="no"/>verse the forest without
                fear, and without<lb break="yes"/>danger; there they dwell as in an ancient<lb
                    break="yes"/>inheritance. This aspect of animated na-<lb break="no"/>ture, in
                which man is nothing, has some-<lb break="no"/>thing in it strange and sad. To this
                    we<lb break="yes"/>reconcile ourselves with difficulty on the<lb break="yes"
                />ocean, and amid the sands of Africa; though<lb break="yes"/>in these scenes, where
                nothing recalls to<lb break="yes"/>mind our fields, our woods, and our streams,<lb
                    break="yes"/>we are less astonished at the vast solitude<lb break="yes"/>through
                which we pass. Here, in a fertile<lb break="yes"/>country adorned with eternal
                verdure, we<lb break="yes"/>seek in vain the traces of the power of<lb break="yes"
                />man; we seem to be transported into a<lb break="yes"/>world different from that
                which gave us<lb break="yes"/>birth. These impressions are so much the<lb
                    break="yes"/>more powerful, in proportion as they are of<lb break="yes"/>longer
                duration. A soldier, who had spent<lb break="yes"/>his whole life in the missions of
                the Upper<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko, slept with us on the bank of the<lb break="yes"
                />river. He was an intelligent man, who,<lb break="yes"/>during a calm and serene
                night, pressed me<lb break="yes"/>with questions on the magnitude of the<lb
                    break="yes"/>stars, on the inhabitants of the Moon, on a<lb break="yes"
                />thousand subjects of which I was as igno-<lb break="no"/>rant as himself. Being
                unable, by my an-<lb break="no"/>swers, to satisfy his curiosity, he said to me<lb
                    break="yes"/>in a firm tone: &#x2018;With respect to men, I<lb break="yes"
                />believe there are no more above, than you<lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="442" facs="#f0002"/> would have found, if you had gone by land<lb break="yes"
                />from Javita to Cassiquiare. I think I see<lb break="yes"/>in the stars, as here, a
                plain covered with<lb break="yes"/>grass, and a forest <hi rendition="#i">(mucho
                    monte)</hi> traversed<lb break="yes"/>by a river.&#x2019; In citing these words,
                I paint<lb break="yes"/>the impression produced by the monotonous<lb break="yes"
                />aspect of those solitary regions.&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>We have now conducted our readers to<lb break="yes"/>the 8th book, and, though this
                notice is<lb break="yes"/>very brief, find this a convenient place to<lb break="yes"
                />rest for the present.<lb break="yes"></lb></p>
            </div>
            <!-- rc adding missing text from 8. September, S. 563 taken from 1821-War_Poison_of-1.xml 
                which needs to be part of this Bündel. Plus text from Personal Narrative, Project Gutenberg-->
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#k">humboldt&#x2019;s personal narrative.</hi><lb break="yes"
                    />Vol. V. Part II.<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Indian Poisons</hi>&#x2014;<hi
                            rendition="#i">Festivals</hi>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Roasted
                            Monkeys</hi>&#x2014;<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Music</hi></head>
            
            
            <p><hi rendition="#k">A few</hi>A Few weeks since, when this addition … </p>
            <p>&#x201C;Esmeralda is the most celebrated spot on the Oroonoko for<lb break="yes"/>the
                fabrication of that active poison which is employed in war,<lb break="yes"/>in the
                chase, and, what is singular enough, as a remedy for gastric<lb break="yes"
                />obstructions. The poison of the ficunas of the Amazon, the upas-<lb break="no"
                />tieute of Java, and the <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi> of Guyana, are the most
                    deleterious<lb break="yes"/> substances that are known. Raleigh, toward the end
                of the six-<lb break="no"/>teenth century, had heard the name of <hi rendition="#i"
                    >curare</hi> pronounced as<lb break="yes"/>being a vegetable substance, with
                which arrows were envenomed;<lb break="yes"/>yet no fixed notions of this poison had
                reached Europe. The<lb break="yes"/>missionaries Gumilla and Gili had not been able
                to penetrate in-<lb break="no"/>to the country where the curare is manufactured.
                Gumilla as-<lb break="no"/>serts that this preparable was enveloped in great
                mystery; that<lb break="yes"/>its principal ingredient was furnished by a
                subterraneous plant,<lb break="yes"/>by a tuberose root, which never puts forth
                leaves, and which is<lb break="yes"/>called the root by way of eminence, <hi
                    rendition="#i">raiz de si misma;</hi> that the<lb break="yes"/>venomous
                exhalations, which arise from the pots, cause the old<lb break="yes"/>women (the
                most <hi rendition="#i">useless</hi>) to perish who are chosen to watch<lb
                    break="yes"/>over this operation; finally, that these vegetable juices never<lb
                    break="yes"/>appear sufficiently concentrated, till a few drops produce <hi
                    rendition="#i">at a<lb break="yes"/>distance</hi> a repulsive action on the
                blood. An Indian wounds him-<lb break="no"/>self slightly; and a dart dipped in the
                liquid <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi> is held near<lb break="yes"/>the wound. If it
                make the blood return to the vessels without<lb break="yes"/>having been brought
                into contact with them, the poison is judged<lb break="yes"/>to be sufficiently
                concentrated. I shall not stop to refute these<lb break="yes"/>popular tales
                collected by Father Gumilla.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>When we arrived at Esmeralda, the greater part of the In-<lb break="no"/>dians were
                returning from an excursion which they had made to<lb break="yes"/>the east beyond
                the Rio Padamo, to gather <hi rendition="#i">juvias</hi>, or the fruit<lb
                    break="yes"/>of the Bertholletia, and the liana which yields the curare.
                    Their<lb break="yes"/>return was celebrated by a festival, which is called in
                the Mission<lb break="yes"/>
                <hi rendition="#i">la fiesta de las juvias</hi>, and which resembles our harvest
                    homes<lb break="yes"/>and vintage feasts. The women had prepared a quantity of
                    fer-<lb break="no"/>mented liquor, and during two days the Indians were in a
                    state<lb break="yes"/>of intoxication. Among nations that attach great
                    importance<lb break="yes"/>to the fruits of the palm-trees and of some others
                useful for the<lb break="yes"/>nourishment of man, the period when these fruits are
                    gathered<lb break="yes"/>is marked by public rejoicings, and time is divided
                according to<lb break="yes"/>these festivals, which succeed one another in a course
                    invariably<lb break="yes"/>the same. We were fortunate enough to find an old
                Indian less<lb break="yes"/>drunk than the rest, who was employed in preparing the
                    <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi>
                <lb break="yes"/>poison from freshly gathered plants. He was the chemist of<lb
                    break="yes"/>the place. We found at his dwelling large earthen pots for<lb
                    break="yes"/>boiling vegetable juice, shallower vessels to favour the
                    evaporation<lb break="yes"/>by a larger surface, and leaves of the plane-tree
                rolled up in the<lb break="yes"/>shape of our filters, and used to filtrate the
                liquors more or less<lb break="yes"/>loaded with fibrous matter. The greatest order
                and neatness<lb break="yes"/>prevailed in this hut, which was transformed into a
                chemical la-<lb break="no"/>boratory. The Indian who was to instruct us, is known
                    through-<lb break="no"/>out the mission by the name of the <hi rendition="#i"
                    >master of poison</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">amo del<lb break="yes"
                    />curare</hi>)<hi rendition="#i">:</hi> he had that self-sufficient air and tone
                of pedantry, of<lb break="yes"/>which the pharmacopolists of Europe were formerly <choice>
                    <sic>accused;&#x201C;</sic>
                    <corr type="editorial">accused; &#x201C;</corr>
                </choice> I<lb break="yes"/> know,&#x201D; said he, &#x201C;that the whites have the
                secret of fabricating<lb break="yes"/>soap, and that black powder which has the
                effect of making a<lb break="yes"/>noise and killing animals, when they are wanted.
                The <hi rendition="#i">curare,</hi>
                <lb break="yes"/>which we prepare from father to son, is superior to any thing
                    you<lb break="yes"/>can make <hi rendition="#i">down yonder</hi> (beyond sea).
                It is the juice of an herb<lb break="yes"/>which <hi rendition="#i">kills
                    silently</hi> (without any one knowing whence the stroke<lb break="yes"
                />comes).&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>This chemical operation, to which the <hi rendition="#i">master of the curare</hi>
                <lb break="yes"/>attached so much importance, appears to us extremely simple.<lb
                    break="yes"/>The liana (<hi rendition="#i">bujuco</hi>), which is used at
                Esmeralda for the prepara-<lb break="no"/>tion of the poison, bears the same name as
                in the forest of Javita.<lb break="yes"/>It is the <hi rendition="#i">bejuco de
                    mavacure</hi>, which is gathered in abundance<lb break="yes"/>east of the
                Mission, on the left bank of the Oroonoko, beyond<lb break="yes"/>the Rio Amaguaca,
                in the mountains and granatic lands of Gua-<lb break="no"/>naya and Yumariquin.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>The juice of the liana, when it has been recently gathered, is<lb break="yes"/>not
                regarded as poisonous; perhaps it acts in a sensible manner<lb break="yes"/>only
                when it is strongly concentrated. It is the bark, and a part<lb break="yes"/>of the
                alburnum, which contains this terrible poison. Branches<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi
                    rendition="#i">mavacure</hi> four or five lines in diameter, are scraped with
                    a<lb break="yes"/>knife; and the bark that comes off is bruised, and reduced
                    into<lb break="yes"/>very thin filaments, on the stone employed for grinding
                    cassava.<lb break="yes"/>The venomous juice being yellow, the whole fibrous mass
                    takes<lb break="yes"/>this colour. It is thrown into a funnel nine inches high,
                with an<lb break="yes"/>opening four inches wide. This funnel was, of all the
                    instru-<lb break="no"/>ments of the Indian laboratory, that of which the <hi
                    rendition="#i">master of poi-<lb break="no"/>son</hi> seemed to be most proud.
                He asked us repeatedly, of <hi rendition="#i">por<lb break="yes"/>alla</hi> (<hi
                    rendition="#i">down yonder,</hi> that is in Europe) we had ever seen any
                    thing<lb break="yes"/>to be compared to his <hi rendition="#i">empudo.</hi> It
                was a leaf of a plantain tree<lb break="yes"/>rolled up in the form of a cone, and
                placed in another stronger<lb break="yes"/>cone made of the leaves of the palm-tree.
                The whole of this<lb break="yes"/>apparatus was supported by slight frame work made
                of the petioli<lb break="yes"/>and ribs of palm leaves. A cold infusion is first
                prepared by<lb break="yes"/>pouring water on the fibrous matter, which is the ground
                bark of<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">mavacure.</hi> A yellowish water
                filters during several hours,<lb break="yes"/>drop by drop, through the leafy
                funnel. This filtered water is the<lb break="yes"/>venomous liquor, but it acquires
                strength only when it is concen-<lb break="no"/>trated by evaporation, like molasses
                in a large earthen pot.<lb break="yes"/>The Indian from time to time invited us to
                taste the liquid; its<lb break="yes"/>taste, more or less bitter, decides when the
                concentration by fire<lb break="yes"/>has been carried sufficiently far. There is no
                danger in this ope-<lb break="no"/>ration, the <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi> being
                deleterious only when it comes into im-<lb break="no"/>mediate contact with the
                blood. The vapours, therefore, that<lb break="yes"/>are disengaged from the pans,
                are not hurtful, notwithstanding<lb break="yes"/>what has been asserted on this
                point by the Missionaries of the<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko. Fontana, in his fine
                experiments on the poison of the<lb break="yes"/>
                <hi rendition="#i">ticunas</hi> of the river of Amazons, long ago proved, that the
                    va-<lb break="no"/>pours arising from this poison when thrown on burning
                    charcoal,<lb break="yes"/>may be inhaled without apprehension; and that it is
                false, as<lb break="yes"/>M. de la Condamine has announced, that Indian women, when
                    con-<lb break="no"/>demned to death, have been killed by the vapours of the
                    poison<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i">ticunas.</hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>The juice is thickened with a glutinous substance to cause it<lb break="yes"/>to
                stick to the darts, which it renders mortal; but taken inter-<lb break="no"/>nally,
                the Indians consider the <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi> to be an excellent stoma-<lb
                    break="no"/>chic. Scarcely a fowl is eaten (adds our author) on the banks<lb
                    break="yes"/>of the Oroonoko, which has not been killed with a poisoned<lb
                    break="yes"/>arrow. The Missionaries pretend, that the flesh of animals is<lb
                    break="yes"/>never so good as when these means are employed. Father Zea,<lb
                    break="yes"/>who accompanied us, though ill of a tertian fever, caused every<lb
                    break="yes"/>morning the live fowl allotted for our repast to be brought to
                    his<lb break="yes"/>hammock, together with an arrow. Notwithstanding his
                    habi-<lb break="no"/>tual state of weakness, he would not confide this
                operation, to<lb break="yes"/>which he attached great importance, to any other
                person. Large<lb break="yes"/>birds, a guan (<hi rendition="#i">pava de monte</hi>)
                for instance, or a curassoa (<hi rendition="#i">alse-<lb break="no"/>tor,</hi>) when
                wounded in the thigh, perish in two or three minutes;<lb break="yes"/>but it is
                often ten or twelve before a pig or a pecari expires.&#x201D;</p><p>M. Humboldt does
                not seem to be acquainted with any certain antidote,<lb break="yes"/>if such exists,
                to this fatal poison. Sugar, garlic, the muriate of soda, &amp;c.<lb break="yes"
                />are mentioned doubtingly. ...</p>
            <p>&#x201C;The old Indian, who was called the master of poison, seemed flattered by the
                interest we had taken in his chemical processes. He found us sufficiently
                intelligent to lead him to the belief that we knew how to make soap, an art which,
                next to the preparation of curare, appeared to him one of the finest of human
                inventions. When the liquid poison had been poured into the vessels prepared for
                their reception, we accompanied the Indian to the festival of the juvias. The
                harvest of juvias, or fruits of the Bertholletia excelsa, was celebrated by dancing,
                and by excesses of wild intoxication. The hut where the natives were assembled,
                displayed during several days a very singular aspect. There was neither table nor
                bench; but large roasted monkeys, blackened by smoke, were ranged in regular order
                against the wall. These were the marimondes (Ateles belzebuth), and those bearded
                monkeys called capuchins, which must not be confounded with the weeper, or sai
                (Simia capucina of Buffon). The manner of roasting these anthropomorphous animals
                contributes to render their appearance extremely disagreeable in the eyes of
                civilized man. A little grating or lattice of very hard wood is formed, and raised
                one foot from the ground. The monkey is skinned, and bent into a sitting posture;
                the head generally resting on the arms, which are meagre and long; but sometimes
                these are crossed behind the back. When it is tied on the grating, a very clear fire
                is kindled below. The monkey, enveloped in smoke and flame, is broiled and blackened
                at the same time. On seeing the natives devour the arm or leg of a roasted monkey,
                it is difficult not to believe that this habit of eating animals so closely
                resembling man in their physical organization, has, to a certain degree, contributed
                to diminish the horror of cannibalism among these people. Roasted monkeys,
                particularly those which have very round heads, display a hideous resemblance to a
                child; and consequently Europeans who are obliged to feed on them prefer separating
                the head and the hands, and serve up only the rest of the animal at their tables.
                The flesh of monkeys is so lean and dry, that M. Bonpland has preserved in his
                collections at Paris an arm and hand, which had been broiled over the fire at
                Esmeralda; and no smell has arisen from them after the lapse of a great number of
                years.</p>
            <p>&#x201C;We saw the Indians dance. The monotony of their dancing is increased by the
                women not daring to take part in it. The men, young and old, form a circle, holding
                each others' hands; and turn sometimes to the right, sometimes to the left, for
                whole hours, with silent gravity. Most frequently the dancers themselves are the
                musicians. Feeble sounds, drawn from a series of reeds of different lengths, form a
                slow and plaintive accompaniment. The first dancer, to mark the time, bends both
                knees in a kind of cadence. Sometimes they all make a pause in their places, and
                execute little oscillatory movements, bending the body from one side to the other.
                The reeds ranged in a line, and fastened together, resemble the Pan's pipes, as we
                find them represented in the bacchanalian processions on Grecian vases. To unite
                reeds of different lengths, and make them sound in succession by passing them before
                the lips, is a simple idea, and has naturally presented itself to every nation. We
                were surprised to see with what promptitude the young Indians constructed and tuned
                these pipes, when they found reeds on the bank of the river. Uncivilized men, in
                every zone, make great use of these gramina with high stalks. The Greeks, with
                truth, said that reeds had contributed to subjugate nations by furnishing arrows, to
                soften men's manners by the charm of music, and to unfold their understanding by
                affording the first instruments for tracing letters. These different uses of reeds
                mark in some sort three different periods in the life of nations. We must admit that
                the tribes of the Orinoco are in the first stage of dawning civilization. The reed
                serves them only as an instrument of war and of hunting; and the Pan's pipes, of
                which we have spoken, have not yet, on those distant shores, yielded sounds capable
                of awakening mild and humane feelings.&#x201D;</p>
            <p>M.H. gives an interesting account ... </p>
            <p>&#x201C;We saw on the slope of the Cerra Duida shirt-trees fifty feet high. The
                Indians cut off cylindrical pieces two feet in diameter, from which they peel the
                red and fibrous bark, without making any longitudinal incision. This bark affords
                them a sort of garment, which resembles sacks of a very coarse texture, and without
                a seam. The upper opening serves for the head; and two lateral holes are cut for the
                arms to pass through. The natives wear these shirts of marima in the rainy season:
                they have the form of the ponchos and ruanas of cotton, which are so common in New
                Grenada, at Quito, and in Peru. In these climates the riches and beneficence of
                nature being regarded as the primary causes of the indolence of the inhabitants, the
                missionaries say in showing the shirts of marima, in the forests of the Orinoco
                garments are found ready-made on the trees. We may also mention the pointed caps,
                which the spathes of certain palm-trees furnish, and which resemble coarse
                network.</p>
            <p>&#x201C;At the festival of which we were the spectators, the women, who were excluded
                from the dance, and every sort of public rejoicing, were daily occupied in serving
                the men with roasted monkey, fermented liquors, and palm-cabbage. This last
                production has the taste of our cauliflowers, and in no other country had we seen
                specimens of such an immense size. The leaves that are not unfolded are united with
                the young stem, and we measured cylinders of six feet long and five inches in
                diameter. Another substance, which is much more nutritive, is obtained from the
                animal kingdom: this is fish-flour (manioc de pescado). The Indians throughout the
                Upper Orinoco fry fish, dry them in the sun, and reduce them to powder without
                separating the bones. I have seen masses of fifty or sixty pounds of this flour,
                which resembles that of cassava. When it is wanted for eating, it is mixed with
                water, and reduced to a paste. In every climate the abundance of fish has led to the
                invention of the same means of preserving them. Pliny and Diodorus Siculus have
                described the fish-bread of the ichthyophagous nations, that dwelt on the Persian
                Gulf and the shores of the Red Sea.&#x201D;</p><p>(To be
                Continued.)</p>
            </div>
                <!-- rc adding missing text from 15. September, S. 580 taken from Personal Narrative. 
Last part, mid-page 581, is exact copy of 1822-Visit_of_the-2-neu.xml so needs to be added to this Bündel.-->
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#k">humboldt&#x2019;s personal narrative.</hi><lb break="yes"
                            /><hi rendition="#i">Dwarf and Fair Indians.</hi>&#x2014;<hi
                            rendition="#i">Jaguars.</hi>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">The</hi><lb/><hi
                            rendition="#i">Tomb of a Nation!</hi></head>
                
            
            <p>The
                Following extract from our interest-<lb/>ing traveller refers to a subject of
                    much<lb/>remarkable speculation:&#x2014;</p>
            <p>&#x201C;I shall here proceed to give some information respecting the tribes of dwarf
                and fair Indians, which ancient traditions have placed near the sources of the
                Orinoco. I had an opportunity of seeing some of these Indians at Esmeralda, and can
                affirm that the short stature of the Guaicas, and the fair complexion of the
                Guaharibos, whom Father Caulin calls Guaribos blancos, have been alike exaggerated.
                The Guaicas, whom I measured, were in general from four feet seven inches to four
                feet eight inches high (old measure of France).* (* About five feet three inches
                English measure.) We were assured that the whole tribe were of this diminutive size;
                but we must not forget that what is called a tribe constitutes, properly speaking,
                but one family, owing to the exclusion of all foreign connections. The Indians of
                the lowest stature next to the Guaicas are the Guainares and the Poignaves. It is
                singular, that all these nations are found in near proximity to the Caribs, who are
                remarkably tall. They all inhabit the same climate, and subsist on the same
                aliments. They are varieties in the race, which no doubt existed previously to the
                settlement of these tribes (tall and short, fair and dark brown) in the same
                country. The four nations of the Upper Orinoco, which appeared to me to be the
                fairest, are the Guaharibos of the Rio Gehette, the Guainares of the Ocamo, the
                Guaicas of Cano Chiguire, and the Maquiritares of the sources of the Padamo, the
                Jao, and the Ventuari. It being very extraordinary to see natives with a fair skin
                beneath a burning sky, and amid nations of a very dark hue, the Spaniards have
                attempted to explain this phenomenon by the following hypotheses. Some assert, that
                the Dutch of Surinam and the Rio Essequibo may have intermingled with the Guaharibos
                and the Guainares; others insist, from hatred to the Capuchins of the Carony, and
                the Observantins of the Orinoco, that the fair Indians are what are called in
                Dalmatia muso di frate, children whose legitimacy is somewhat doubtful. In either
                case the Indios blancos would be mestizos, that is to say, children of an Indian
                woman and a white man. Now, having seen thousands of mestizos, I can assert that
                this supposition is altogether inaccurate. The individuals of the fair tribes whom
                we examined, have the features, the stature, and the smooth, straight, black hair
                which characterises other Indians. It would be impossible to take them for a mixed
                race, like the descendants of natives and Europeans. Some of these people are very
                little, others are of the ordinary stature of the copper-coloured Indians. They are
                neither feeble nor sickly, nor are they albinos; and they differ from the
                copper-coloured races only by a much less tawny skin.&#x201D; * * *</p>
            <p>&#x201C;The fair-complexioned tribes, which we had an opportunity of seeing at the
                mission of Esmeralda, inhabit part of a mountainous country lying between the
                sources of six tributaries of the Orinoco; that is to say, between the Padamo, the
                Jao, the Ventuari, the Erevato, the Aruy, and the Paraguay.* (* They are six
                tributary streams on the right bank of the Orinoco; the first three run towards the
                south, or the Upper Orinoco; the three others towards the north, or the Lower
                Orinoco.) The Spanish and Portuguese missionaries are accustomed to designate this
                country more particularly by the name of Parima.* (* The name Parima, which
                signifies water, great water, is applied sometimes, and more especially, to the land
                washed by the Rio Parima, or Rio Branco (Rio de Aguas Blancas), a stream running
                into the Rio Negro; sometimes to the mountains (Sierra Parima), which divide the
                Upper and Lower Orinoco.) Here, as in several other countries of Spanish America,
                the savages have reconquered what had been wrested from them by civilization, or
                rather by its precursors, the missionaries. The expedition of the boundaries under
                Solano, and the extravagant zeal displayed by a governor of Guiana for the discovery
                of El Dorado, partially revived in the latter half of the eighteenth century that
                spirit of enterprise which characterised the Spaniards at the period of the
                discovery of America. In going along the Rio Padamo, a road was observed across the
                forests and savannahs (the length of ten days' journey), from Esmeralda to the
                sources of the Ventuari; and in two days more, from those sources, by the Erevato,
                the missions on the Rio Caura were reached. Two intelligent and enterprising men,
                Don Antonio Santos and Captain Bareto, had established, with the aid of the
                Miquiritares, a chain of military posts on this line from Esmeralda to the Rio
                Erevato. These posts consisted of block-houses (casas fuertes), mounted with
                swivels, such as I have already mentioned. The soldiers, left to themselves,
                exercised all kinds of vexations on the natives (Indians of peace), who had
                cultivated pieces of ground around the casas fuertes; and the consequence was that,
                in 1776, several tribes formed a league against the Spaniards. All the military
                posts were attacked on the same night, on a line of nearly fifty leagues in length.
                The houses were burnt, and many soldiers massacred; a very small number only owing
                their preservation to the pity of the Indian women. This nocturnal expedition is
                still mentioned with horror. It was concerted in the most profound secrecy, and
                executed with that spirit of unity which the natives of America, skilled in
                concealing their hostile passions, well know how to practise in whatever concerns
                their common interests. Since 1776 no attempt has been made to re-establish the road
                which leads by land from the Upper to the Lower Orinoco, and no white man has been
                able to pass from Esmeralda to the Erevato.&#x201D;</p><p>In May, M. Humboldt and
                his compa-<lb/>nion left Esmeralda, and proceeded down<lb/>the Oroonoko to the
                    point of bifurcation.<lb/>Here, says the author, &#x201C;The cries of the
                    jaguars<note place="foot" n="*">&#x201C;This frequency of large jaguars is
                    somewhat remarkable in a country destitute of cattle. The tigers of the Upper
                    Orinoco are far less bountifully supplied with prey than those of the Pampas of
                    Buenos Ayres and the Llanos of Caracas, which are covered with herds of cattle.
                    More than four thousand jaguars are killed annually in the Spanish colonies,
                    several of them equalling the mean size of the royal tiger of Asia. Two thousand
                    skins of jaguars were formerly exported annually from Buenos Ayres alone; they
                    are called by the furriers of Europe skins of the great panther.&#x201D;</note>
                were heard during the whole night. These animals are very frequent in the tracts
                situated between the Cerro Maraguaca, the Unturan, and the banks of the Pamoni.
                There also is found that black tiger,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">&#x201C;Gmelin,
                    in his Synonyma, seems to confound this animal, under the name of Felis
                    discolor, with the great American lion, felis concolor, which is very different
                    from the little lion (puma) of the Andes of Quito. (lin. Syst. Nat. vol.I. p.
                    79. Cuvier, Regnc animal, vol. I. p. 160.)&#x201D;</note> of which I saw some
                fine skins at Esmeralda. This animal is celebrated for its strength and ferocity; it
                appears to be still larger than the common jaguar. The black spots are scarcely
                visible on the dark-brown ground of its skin. The Indians assert, that these tigers
                are very rare, that they never mingle with the common jaguars, and &#x2018;form
                another race.&#x2019;&#x201D;</p>
            <p>Descending still farther ... </p>
            <p>&#x201C;The nations of the Tamanac race, the ancient inhabitants of those countries,
                have a local mythology, and traditions connected with these sculptured rocks.
                Amalivaca, the father of the Tamanacs, that is, the creator of the human race (for
                every nation regards itself as the root of all other nations), arrived in a bark, at
                the time of the great inundation, which is called the age of water,* when the
                billows of the ocean broke against the mountains of Encaramada in the interior of
                the land. (* The Atonatiuh of the Mexicans, the fourth age, the fourth regeneration
                of the world.) All mankind, or, to speak more correctly, all the Tamanacs, were
                drowned, with the exception of one man and one woman, who saved themselves on a
                mountain near the banks of the Asiveru, called Cuchivero by the Spaniards. This
                mountain is the Ararat of the Aramean or Semitic nations, and the Tlaloc or
                Colhuacan of the Mexicans. Amalivaca, sailing in his bark, engraved the figures of
                the moon and the sun on the Painted Rock (Tepumereme) of Encaramada. Some blocks of
                granite piled upon one another, and forming a kind of cavern, are still called the
                house or dwelling of the great forefather of the Tamanacs. The natives show also a
                large stone near this cavern, in the plains of Maita, which they say was an
                instrument of music, the drum of Amalivaca. We must here observe, that this heroic
                personage had a brother, Vochi, who helped him to give the surface of the earth its
                present form. The Tamanacs relate that the two brothers, in their system of
                perfectibility, sought, at first, to arrange the Orinoco in such a manner, that the
                current of the water could always be followed either going down or going up the
                river. They hoped by this means to spare men trouble in navigating rivers; but,
                however great the power of these regenerators of the world, they could never
                contrive to give a double slope to the Orinoco, and were compelled to relinquish
                this singular plan. Amalivaca had daughters, who had a decided taste for travelling.
                The tradition states, doubtless with a figurative meaning, that he broke their legs,
                to render them sedentary, and force them to people the land of the Tamanacs. After
                having regulated everything in America, on that side of the great water, Amalivaca
                again embarked, and returned to the other shore, to the same place from whence he
                came. Since the natives have seen the missionaries arrive, they imagine that Europe
                is this other shore; and one of them inquired with great simplicity of Father Gili,
                whether he had there seen the great Amalivaca, the father of the Tamanacs, who had
                covered the rocks with symbolic figures.&#x201D;</p><p>Still lower down the great river, M. Hum-<lb/>boldt visited the cavern of Ataruipe, of<lb/>which
                    he gives the following curious ac-<lb/>count:&#x2014;</p>
                <p>&#x201C;We soon reckoned in this tomb of a whole extinct tribe near six hundred skeletons well preserved, and so regularly placed, that it would have been difficult to make an error in their number. Every skeleton reposes in a sort of basket, made of the petioles of the palm-tree. These baskets, which the natives call <hi rend="italic" >mapires</hi>, have the form of a square bag. Their size is proportioned to the age of the dead; there are some for infants cut off at the moment of their birth. We saw them from ten inches to three feet four inches long, the skeletons in them being bent together. They are all ranged near each other, and are so entire, that not a rib or a phalanx is wanting. The bones have been prepared in three different manners, either whitened in the air and the sun; dyed red with anoto, a coloring matter extracted from the bixa orellana; or like real mummies, varnished with odoriferous resins, and enveloped in leaves of the heliconia or of the plantain tree. The Indians related to us, that the fresh corpse is placed in damp ground, in order that the flesh may be consumed by degrees; some months after, it is taken out, and the flesh remaining on the bones is scraped off with sharp stones.&#x2014;Several hordes in Guyana still observe this custom. Earthen vases half-baked are found near the mapires, or baskets. They appear to contain the bones of the same family. The largest of these vases, or funeral urns, are three feet high, and five feet and a half long. Their color is greenish gray; and their oval form is sufficiently pleasing to the eye. The handles are made in the shape of crocodiles, or serpents; the edge is bordered with meanders, labyrinths, and real grecques, in straight lines variously combined. Such paintings are found in every zone, among nations the most remote from each other, either with respect to the spot which they occupy on the globe, or to the degree of civilization which they have attained. The inhabitants of the little mission of Maypures still execute them on their commonest pottery; they decorate the bucklers of the Otaheiteans, the fishing implements of the Eskimaux, the walls of the Mexican palace of Mitla, and the vases of ancient Greece. Every where a rhythmic repetition of the same forms flatters the eye, as the cadenced repetition of sounds soothes the ear. Analogies founded on the internal nature of our intellect, are not calculated to throw light on the filiation and the ancient connections of nations.</p><p>&#x201C;We could not acquire any precise idea of the period to which the origin of the mapires and the painted vases, contained in the ossuary cavern of Ataruipe, can be traced. The greater part seemed not to be more than a century old; but it may be supposed that, sheltered from all humidity, under the influence of a uniform temperature. The preservation of these articles would be no less perfect, if it dated from a period far more remote. A tradition circulates among the Guahiboes, that the warlike Atures, pursued by the Caribbees, escaped to the rocks that rise in the middle of the Great Cataracts; and there that nation, heretofore so numerous, became gradually extinct, as well as its language. The last families of the Atures still existed in 1767, in the time of the missionary Gili. At the period of our voyage an old parrot was shown at Maypures, of which the inhabitants related, and the fact is worthy of observation, that &#x201C;they did not understand what it said, because it spoke the language of the Atures.&#x201D;</p><p>&#x201C;We opened, to the great concern of our guides, several mapires, in order to examine attentively the form of the skulls; they all displayed the characteristics of the American race, with the exception of two or three, which approached indubitably to the Caucasian. * * * *</p> <p>&#x201C;We took several sculls, the skeleton of a child of six or seven years old, and two of full-grown men of the nation of the Atures, from the cavern of Ataruipe. All these bones partly painted red, partly varnished with odoriferous resins, were placed in the baskets (mapires or canastos,) which we have just described. They made almost the whole load of a mule; and as we knew the superstitious aversion of the Indians for dead bodies, when they have given them sepulture, we had carefully enveloped the canastos in mats recently woven. Unfortunately for us, the penetration of the Indians, and the extreme quickness of their senses, rendered all our precautions useless. Whenever we stopped, in the missions of the Caribbees, amid the Llanos, between Angostura and Nueva Barcelona, the natives assembled round our mules to admire the monkeys which we had purchased at the Oroonoko. These good people had scarcely touched our baggage, when they announced the approaching death of the beast of burden &#x201C;that carried the dead.&#x201D; In vain we told them that they were deceived in their conjectures, and that the baskets contained the bones of crocodiles and manatees; they persisted in repeating, that they smelt the resin, that surrounded the skeletons, and &#x201C;that they were their old relations.&#x201D; We were obliged to make the monks interpose their authority, in order to conquer the aversion of the natives, and procure for us a change of mules.</p><p>&#x201C;One of the sculls, which we took from the cavern of Ataruipe, has appeared in the fine work published by my old master, Blumenbach, on the varieties of the human species. The skeletons of the Indians were lost on the coast of Africa, together with a considerable part of our collections, in a shipwreck, in which perished our friend and fellow-traveller, Fray Juan Gonzales, a young monk of the order of Saint Francis.</p><p>&#x201C;We withdrew in silence from the cavern of Ataruipe. It was one of those calm and serene
                    nights which are so common in the torrid zone. The stars shone with a mild and
                    planetary light. Their scintillation was scarcely sensible at the horizon, which
                    seemed illumined by the great nebul&#x00E6; of the southern hemisphere. An
                    innumerable multitude of insects spread a reddish light upon the ground, loaded
                    with plants, and resplendent with these living and moving fires, as if the stars
                    of the firmament had sunk down on the savannah. On quitting the cavern, we
                    stopped several times to admire the beauty of this singular scene. The
                    odorifurous vanilla, and festoons of bignonia, decorated the entrance; and
                    above, on the summit of the hill, the arrowy branches of the palm-trees waved
                    murmuring in the air.&#x201D;<lb/></p>
            <p>(To be Continued.)</p>
            
                </div>
            <!-- rc adding missing text from 29. September, S. 615  
Last part, mid-page 581–582, 1821-Humboldts_Personal_Narrative-3-neu is exact copy of this so needs to be added to this Bündel.-->
            
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#k">humboldt&#x2019;s personal narrative.</hi><lb break="yes"
                /><hi rendition="#i">Dirt Eaters.</hi></head>
                
           
                <p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#in">T</hi>HE inhabitants of Uruana, be-<lb break="no"
                    />long to those <hi rendition="#i">nations of the sa-<lb break="no"
                        />vannahs</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">Indios andantes,</hi>) who, more<lb
                        break="yes"/>difficult to civilize than the <hi rendition="#i">nations of<lb
                            break="yes"/>the forest,</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">Indios del
                    monte,</hi>) have a<lb break="yes"/>decided aversion to cultivate the land,<lb
                        break="yes"/>and live almost exclusively on hunting<lb break="yes"/>and
                    fishing. They are men of very<lb break="yes"/>robust constitution; but ugly,
                        savage,<lb break="yes"/>vindictive, and passionately fond of<lb break="yes"
                    />fermented liquors. They are omnivo-<lb break="no"/>rous <hi rendition="#i"
                        >animals</hi> in the highest degree;<lb break="yes"/>and therefore the other
                    Indians, who<lb break="yes"/>consider them as barbarians, have a<lb break="yes"
                    />common saying, &#x2018;nothing is so disgust-<lb break="no"/>ing that an
                    Otomac will not eat it.&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>While the waters of the Oroonoko
                        and<lb break="yes"/>its tributary streams are low, the Oto-<lb break="no"
                    />macs subsist on fish and turtles. The<lb break="yes"/>former they kill with
                    surprising dexter-<lb break="no"/>ity, by shooting them with an arrow,<lb
                        break="yes"/>when they appear at the surface of the<lb break="yes"/>water.
                    When the rivers swell, which<lb break="yes"/>in South America as well as in
                        Egypt<lb break="yes"/>and in Nubia, is erroneously attributed<lb break="yes"
                    />to the melting of the snows, and which<lb break="yes"/>occurs periodically in
                    every part of the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone, fishing almost entirely<lb
                        break="yes"/>ceases. It is then as difficult to pro-<lb break="no"/>cure
                    fish in the rivers which are be-<lb break="no"/>come deeper, as when you are
                        sailing<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> on the open sea. It often fails the poor<lb break="yes"/>missionaries, on
                    fast-days as well as<lb break="yes"/>flesh days, though all the young Indians<lb
                        break="yes"/>are under the obligation of &#x2018;fishing for<lb break="yes"
                    />the convent.&#x2019; At the period of these<lb break="yes"/>inundations, which
                    lasts two or three<lb break="yes"/>months, the Otomacs swallow a prodi-<lb
                        break="no"/>gious quantity of earth. We found<lb break="yes"/>heaps of balls
                    in their huts, piled up in<lb break="yes"/>pyramids three or four feet high.
                        These<lb break="yes"/>balls were five or six inches in diame-<lb break="no"
                    />ter. The earth which the Otomacs eat<lb break="yes"/>is a very fine and
                    unctuous clay, of a<lb break="yes"/>yellowish grey colour; and, being slight-<lb
                        break="no"/>ly baked in the fire, the hardened crust<lb break="yes"/>has a
                    tint inclining to red, owing to the<lb break="yes"/>oxid of iron which is
                    mingled with it.<lb break="yes"/>We brought away some of this earth,<lb
                        break="yes"/>which we took from the winter provis-<lb break="no"/>ion of the
                    Indians; and it is absolutely<lb break="yes"/>false, that it is steatitic, and
                        contains<lb break="yes"/>magnesia. Mr. Vauquelin did not dis-<lb break="no"
                    />cover any traces of this earth in it; but<lb break="yes"/>he found that it
                    contained more silex than<lb break="yes"/>alumin, and three or four per cent of
                    lime.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The Otomacs do not eat every<lb break="yes"/>kind of clay indifferently;
                    they choose<lb break="yes"/>the alluvial beds or strata that contain<lb
                        break="yes"/>the most unctuous earth, and the<lb break="yes"/>smoothest to
                    the feel. I inquired of<lb break="yes"/>the missionary, whether the moistened<lb
                        break="yes"/>clay were made to undergo, as Father<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="199" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/> Gumilla asserts, that peculiar decom-<lb break="no"/>position, which is
                    indicated by a dis-<lb break="no"/>engagement of carbonic acid and sul-<lb
                        break="no"/>phuretted hydrogen, and which is de-<lb break="no"/>signated in
                    every language by the<lb break="yes"/>term of <hi rendition="#i"
                        >putrefaction;</hi> but he assured<lb break="yes"/>us, that the natives
                    neither cause the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">clay</hi> to <hi rendition="#i">rot,</hi> nor do they mingle
                    it with<lb break="yes"/>flour of maize, oil of turtles&#x2019; eggs, or fat<lb
                        break="yes"/>of the crocodile. We ourselves exam-<lb break="no"/>ined, both
                    at the Oroonoko and after our<lb break="yes"/>return to Paris, the balls of
                    earth which<lb break="yes"/>we brought away with us, and found<lb break="yes"
                    />no trace of the mixture of any organic<lb break="yes"/>substance, whether oily
                    or farinaceous.<lb break="yes"/>The savage regards every thing as nour-<lb
                        break="no"/>ishing that appeases hunger; when,<lb break="yes"/>therefore,
                    you inquire of an Otomac on<lb break="yes"/>what he subsists during the two
                        months<lb break="yes"/>when the river is the highest, he shows<lb
                        break="yes"/>you his balls of clayey earth. This he<lb break="yes"/>calls
                    his principal food; for all this pe-<lb break="no"/>riod he can seldom procure a
                    lizard, a<lb break="yes"/>root of fern, or a dead fish swimming at<lb
                        break="yes"/>the surface of the water. If the Indian<lb break="yes"/>eat
                    earth from want during two months,<lb break="yes"/>(and from three quarters to
                    five quar-<lb break="no"/>ters of a pound in twenty-four hours,)<lb break="yes"
                    />he does not the less regale himself with<lb break="yes"/>it during the rest of
                    the year. Every<lb break="yes"/>day in the season of drought, when fish-<lb
                        break="no"/>ing is most abundant, he scrapes his<lb break="yes"/>balls of
                        <hi rendition="#i">poya,</hi> and mingles a little clay<lb break="yes"/>with
                    his other aliment. What is most<lb break="yes"/>surprising is, that the Otomacs
                    do not<lb break="yes"/>become lean by swallowing such quan-<lb break="no"
                    />tities of earth; they are, on the contra-<lb break="no"/>ry, extremely robust,
                    and far from hav-<lb break="no"/>ing the belly tense and puffed up. The<lb
                        break="yes"/>missionary Fray Ramon Bueno asserts,<lb break="yes"/>that he
                    never remarked any alteration<lb break="yes"/>in the health of the natives at
                    the peri-<lb break="no"/>od of the great risings of the Oroonoko.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The following are the facts in all<lb break="yes"/>their simplicity,
                    which we were able to<lb break="yes"/>verify. The Otomacs during some<lb
                        break="yes"/>months, eat daily three quarters of a<lb break="yes"/>pound of
                    clay slightly hardened by fire,<lb break="yes"/>without their health being
                        materially<lb break="yes"/>affected by it. They moisten the earth<lb
                        break="yes"/>afresh when they are going to swallow<lb break="yes"/>it. It
                    has not been possible to verify<lb break="yes"/>hitherto with precision how much
                        nu-<lb break="no"/>tritious vegetable or animal matter the<lb break="yes"
                    />Indians take in a week at the same<lb break="yes"/>time; but it is certain
                    that they attri-<lb break="no"/>bute the sensation of satiety which they<lb
                        break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> feel, to the clay, and not to the wretch-<lb break="no"/>ed aliments which
                    they take with it<lb break="yes"/>occasionally. No physiological phe-<lb
                        break="no"/>nomenon being entirely insulated, it<lb break="yes"/>may be
                    interesting to examine several<lb break="yes"/>analogous phenomena, which I
                        have<lb break="yes"/>been able to collect.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;I observed every where within the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone, in a great
                    number of indi-<lb break="no"/>viduals, children, women, and some-<lb break="no"
                    />times even full-grown men, an inordi-<lb break="no"/>nate and almost
                    irresistible desire of<lb break="yes"/>swallowing earth; not an alkaline or<lb
                        break="yes"/>calcareous earth, to neutralize (as it is<lb break="yes"
                    />vulgarly said) acid juices, but a fat clay,<lb break="yes"/>unctuous, and
                    exhaling a strong smell.<lb break="yes"/>It is often found necessary to tie
                        the<lb break="yes"/>children&#x2019;s hands, or to confine them, to<lb
                        break="yes"/>prevent their eating earth when the rain<lb break="yes"/>ceases
                    to fall. At the village of Banco,<lb break="yes"/>on the bank of the river
                    Magdalena, I<lb break="yes"/>saw the Indian women who make pot-<lb break="no"
                    />tery continually swallowing great pieces<lb break="yes"/>of clay.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The author goes at some length into<lb break="yes"/>analogies and reasoning on
                    them, but<lb break="yes"/>we confine our quotation principally to<lb break="yes"
                    />the facts.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The negroes on the coast of Guinea<lb break="yes"/>delight in eating a
                    yellowish earth which<lb break="yes"/>they call <hi rendition="#i">caouac.</hi>
                    The slaves who are<lb break="yes"/>taken to America try to procure for<lb
                        break="yes"/>themselves the same enjoyment; but it<lb break="yes"/>is
                    constantly detrimental to their health.<lb break="yes"/>They say, &#x2018;that
                    the earth of the West<lb break="yes"/>Indies is not so easy of digestion as
                        that<lb break="yes"/>of their country.&#x2019;&#x201D; * * *</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In the Indian Archipelago, at the<lb break="yes"/>island of Java, Mr.
                    Labillardière saw,<lb break="yes"/>between Surabaya and Samarang, little<lb
                        break="yes"/>square and reddish cakes exposed to<lb break="yes"/>sale. These
                    cakes, called <hi rendition="#i">tanaampo,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>were cakes of clay, slightly baked,<lb break="yes"/>which the
                    natives eat with appetite.<lb break="yes"/>The attention of physiologists,
                        since<lb break="yes"/>my return from the Oroonoko, having<lb break="yes"
                    />been powerfully fixed on these phenom-<lb break="no"/>ena of <hi
                        rendition="#i">geophagy,</hi> Mr. Leschenault,<lb break="yes"/>(one of the
                    naturalists of the expedition<lb break="yes"/>to the Southern Lands under the
                        com-<lb break="no"/>mand of Captain Baudin) has published<lb break="yes"
                    />some curious details on the <hi rendition="#i">tanaampo,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>or <hi rendition="#i">ampo,</hi> of the Javanese. &#x2018;The
                        red-<lb break="no"/>dish and somewhat ferruginous clay,&#x2019;<lb
                        break="yes"/>he says, &#x2018;which the inhabitants of Java<lb break="yes"
                    />are fond of eating occasionally is spread<lb break="yes"/>on a plate of iron,
                    and baked, after<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="200" facs="#f0003"/>
                    <cb/> having been rolled into little cylinders<lb break="yes"/>in the form of
                    the bark of cinnamon.<lb break="yes"/>In this state it takes the name of <hi
                        rendition="#i">ampo,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and is sold in the public markets. This<lb break="yes"/>clay
                    has a peculiar taste, which is owing<lb break="yes"/>to the torrefaction; it is
                    very absorbent,<lb break="yes"/>and adheres to the tongue, which it<lb
                        break="yes"/>dries. In general it is only the Java-<lb break="no"/>nese
                    women who eat the <hi rendition="#i">ampo,</hi> either<lb break="yes"/>in the
                    time of their pregnancy, or in<lb break="yes"/>order to grow thin; the want of
                        plump-<lb break="no"/>ness being a kind of beauty in this<lb break="yes"
                    />country. The use of this earth is fatal<lb break="yes"/>to health; the women
                    lose their appe-<lb break="no"/>tite imperceptibly, and no longer take<lb
                        break="yes"/>without disgust a very small quantity<lb break="yes"/>of food:
                    but the desire of becoming<lb break="yes"/>lean, and of preserving a slender
                        shape,<lb break="yes"/>can brave these dangers, and maintains<lb break="yes"
                    />the credit of the <hi rendition="#i">ampo.</hi>&#x2019; The savage<lb
                        break="yes"/>inhabitants of New Caledonia also, to<lb break="yes"/>appease
                    their hunger in times of scar-<lb break="no"/>city, eat great pieces of a
                    friable <hi rendition="#i">lapis<lb break="yes"/>ollaris.</hi> Mr. Vauquelin
                    analysed this<lb break="yes"/>stone, and found in it, beside magnesia<lb
                        break="yes"/>and silex in equal portions, a small<lb break="yes"/>quantity
                    of oxid of copper. Mr. Gold-<lb break="no"/>berry had seen the negroes in
                        Africa,<lb break="yes"/>in the islands of Bunck and Los Idolos,<lb
                        break="yes"/>eat an earth of which he had himself<lb break="yes"/>eaten,
                    without being incommoded by it,<lb break="yes"/>and which also was a white and
                        friable<lb break="yes"/>steatite.&#x201D; * * * * *</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>&#x201C;When we reflect on the whole of<lb break="yes"/>these facts, we perceive
                    that this disor-<lb break="no"/>derly appetite for clayey, magnesian,<lb
                        break="yes"/>and calcareous earth, is most common<lb break="yes"/>among the
                    people of the torrid zone;<lb break="yes"/>that it is not always a cause of
                        disease;<lb break="yes"/>and that some tribes eat earth from<lb break="yes"
                    />choice, while others (the Otomacs in<lb break="yes"/>America, and the
                    inhabitants of New<lb break="yes"/>Caledonia, in the Pacific Ocean,) eat it<lb
                        break="yes"/>from want, and to appease hunger.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The observations, which I made on<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the
                            <choice><sic>Oroonoka</sic><corr type="editorial"
                        >Oroonoko</corr></choice>, have been<lb break="yes"/>recently confirmed by
                    the direct experi-<lb break="no"/>ments of two distinguished young phy-<lb
                        break="no"/>siologists, Messrs. Hippolite Cloquet<lb break="yes"/>and
                    Breschet. After long fasting, they<lb break="yes"/>ate as much as five ounces of
                    a silvery<lb break="yes"/>green and very fiexible laminar talc.<lb break="yes"
                    />Their hunger was completely satisfied,<lb break="yes"/>and they felt no
                    inconvenience from a<lb break="yes"/>kind of food, to which their organs were<lb
                        break="yes"/>unaccustomed. It is known that great<lb break="yes"/>use is
                    still made in the East of the bolar<lb break="yes"/>and sigillated earths of
                    Lemnos, which<lb break="yes"/>are clay mingled with oxid of iron. In<lb
                        break="yes"/>Germany, the workmen employed in<lb break="yes"/>the quarries
                    of sandstone worked at the<lb break="yes"/>mountain of Kiffh&#x00E6;user spread
                    a very<lb break="yes"/>fine clay upon their bread, instead of<lb break="yes"
                    />butter, which they call <hi rendition="#i">steinbutter,</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">&#x201C;This <hi rendition="#i">steinbutter</hi> must
                        not be confounded with the <hi rendition="#i">mountain butter,
                            bergbutter,</hi> which is a saline<lb break="yes"/>substance, owing to a
                        decomposition of aluminous schists.&#x201D;</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>stone butter; and they find it singularly<lb break="yes"
                    />filling, and easy of digestion<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;"
                        >&#x201C;Freiesleben, Kupferschiefer, vol. iv. p. 118. Kesler, in
                        Gilbert&#x2019;s Annalen, B. 28, p.
                        492.&#x201D;</note>.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/></p>
                
            </div>
                <!-- rc adding missing text from 20. Oktober, S. 662–663.  
 1821-Stories_of_Crocodiles-01-neu is listed as separate Stammtext, add all of those texts to this Bündel-->
            <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">humbolt&#x2019;s personal narrative</hi><lb break="yes"
                        />(Concluded.)<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Stories of Crocodiles.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Our</hi> latter extracts from this publication<lb break="yes"
                    />have been as desultory as the curious na-<lb break="no"/>ture of the
                    author&#x2019;s inquiries seemed to re-<lb break="no"/>quire, without servilely
                    following him<lb break="yes"/>through all his topographical details, and<lb
                        break="yes"/>philosophical <hi rendition="#i">generalizations.</hi> In the
                        same<lb break="yes"/>spirit, we shall now conclude our notice of<lb
                        break="yes"/>these volumes with a brief sequel relating<lb break="yes"/>to
                    the crocodiles of the Oroonoko.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;When the waters (says Mr. H.) are<lb break="yes"/>high, the river
                    inundates the keys; and it<lb break="yes"/>sometimes happens, that even in the
                        town<lb break="yes"/>imprudent men become the prey of croco-<lb break="no"
                    />diles. I shall transcribe from my journal a<lb break="yes"/>fact, that took
                    place during Mr. Bonpland&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>illness. A Guaykeri Indian,
                    from the island<lb break="yes"/>de la Margaretta, went to anchor his canoe<lb
                        break="yes"/>in a cove, where there were not three feet<lb break="yes"/>of
                    water. A very fierce crocodile, that ha-<lb break="no"/>bitually haunted that
                    spot, seized him by<lb break="yes"/>the leg, and withdrew from the shore, re-<lb
                        break="no"/>maining on the surface of the water. The<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> cries of the Indian drew together a crowd<lb break="yes"/>of spectators.
                    This unfortunate man was<lb break="yes"/>first seen seeking with astonishing
                        courage<lb break="yes"/>for a knife in the pocket of his pantaloons.<lb
                        break="yes"/>Not being able to find it, he seized the head<lb break="yes"
                    />of the crocodile, and thrust his fingers into<lb break="yes"/>its eyes. No man
                    in the hot regions of<lb break="yes"/>America is ignorant, that this
                        carnivorous<lb break="yes"/>reptile, covered with a buckler of hard and<lb
                        break="yes"/>dry scales, is extremely sensible in the only<lb break="yes"
                    />parts of his body which are soft and unpro-<lb break="no"/>tected, such as the
                    eyes, the hollow under-<lb break="no"/>neath the shoulders, the nostrils, and
                        be-<lb break="no"/>neath the lower jaw, where there are two<lb break="yes"
                    />glands of musk. The Guaykeri Indian had<lb break="yes"/>recourse to the same
                    means which saved<lb break="yes"/>the negro of Mungo Park, and the girl of<lb
                        break="yes"/>Uritucu, whom I have mentioned above;<lb break="yes"/>but he
                    was less fortunate than they had<lb break="yes"/>been, for the crocodile did not
                    open its<lb break="yes"/>jaws, and lose hold of its prey. The ani-<lb break="no"
                    />mal, yielding to the pain, plunged to the<lb break="yes"/>bottom of the river;
                    and, after having<lb break="yes"/>drowned the Indian, came up to the surface<lb
                        break="yes"/>of the water, dragging the dead body to an<lb break="yes"
                    />island opposite the port. I arrived at the<lb break="yes"/>moment when a great
                    number of the inha-<lb break="no"/>bitants of Angostura had witnessed this
                        me-<lb break="no"/>lancholy spectacle.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;As the crocodile, on account of the<lb break="yes"/>structure of its
                    larynx, of the hyoid bone,<lb break="yes"/>and of the folds of its tongue, can
                        seize,<lb break="yes"/>though not swallow, its prey under water;<lb
                        break="yes"/>a man seldom disappears without the ani-<lb break="no"/>mal
                    being perceived some hours after near<lb break="yes"/>the spot where the
                    misfortune has happened,<lb break="yes"/>devouring its prey on a neighbouring
                        beach.<lb break="yes"/>The number of individuals who perish an-<lb
                        break="no"/>nually, the victims of their own imprudence<lb break="yes"/>and
                    of the ferocity of these reptiles, is much<lb break="yes"/>greater than it is
                    believed to be in Europe.<lb break="yes"/>It is particularly so in villages,
                    where the<lb break="yes"/>neighbouring grounds are often inundated.<lb
                        break="yes"/>The same crocodiles remain long in the<lb break="yes"/>same
                    places. They become from year to<lb break="yes"/>year more daring, especially,
                    as the Indians<lb break="yes"/>assert, if they have once tasted of human<lb
                        break="yes"/>flesh. These animals are so wary, that they<lb break="yes"/>are
                    killed with difficulty. A ball does not<lb break="yes"/>pierce their skin, and
                    the shot is only mor-<lb break="no"/>tal when directed at the throat, or
                        beneath<lb break="yes"/>the shoulder. The Indians, who know<lb break="yes"
                    />little of the use of fire-arms, attack the cro-<lb break="no"/>codile with
                    lances, after it is caught with<lb break="yes"/>large pointed iron hooks, baited
                    with pieces<lb break="yes"/>of meat, and fastened by a chain to the<lb
                        break="yes"/>trunk of a tree. They do not approach the<lb break="yes"
                    />animal till it has struggled a long time to<lb break="yes"/>disengage itself
                    from the iron fixed in the<lb break="yes"/>upper jaw. There is little
                    probability that<lb break="yes"/>a country in which a labyrinth of rivers<lb
                        break="yes"/>without number brings every day new bands<lb break="yes"/>of
                    crocodiles from the eastern back of the<lb break="yes"/>Andes, by the Meta and
                    the Apure, towards<lb break="yes"/>the coast of Spanish Guyana, should ever<lb
                        break="yes"/>be delivered from these reptiles. All that<lb break="yes"/>will
                    be gained by civilization will be, to<lb break="yes"/>render them more timid,
                    and more easily<lb break="yes"/>put to flight.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Affecting instances are related of Afri-<lb break="no"/>can slaves, who
                    have exposed their lives<lb break="yes"/>to save those of their masters, who
                        had<lb break="yes"/>fallen into the jaws of the crocodile. A few<lb
                        break="yes"/>years ago, between Uritucu and the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Mission</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="663" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">de Abaxo,</hi> a negro, hearing the cries of his<lb
                        break="yes"/>master, flew to the spot, armed with a long<lb break="yes"
                    />knife, <hi rendition="#i">(machette,)</hi> and plunged into the<lb break="yes"
                    />river. He forced the crocodile, by putting<lb break="yes"/>out his eyes, to
                    let go his prey, and hide<lb break="yes"/>himself under the water. The slave
                        bore<lb break="yes"/>his expiring master to the shore, but all<lb
                        break="yes"/>succour was unavailing to restore him to<lb break="yes"/>life.
                    He died of suffocation, for his wounds<lb break="yes"/>were not deep; the
                    crocodile, like the<lb break="yes"/>dog, appears not to close its jaws firmly<lb
                        break="yes"/>while swimming. It is almost superfluous<lb break="yes"/>to
                    add, that the children of the deceased,<lb break="yes"/>though poor, gave the
                    slave his freedom.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Upon the whole, this portion of Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt&#x2019;s work is
                    equally entertaining<lb break="yes"/>with what has gone before, and throws<lb
                        break="yes"/>much light on Physics and Geography.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI> 