<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157">
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-31" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="314" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">humboldt&#x2019;s travels.</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">&#x201C;Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Con-<lb break="no"/>tinent, during the years 1799&#x2014;1804. By Alexander De Humboldt and Aimé<lb break="yes" />Bonpland; with maps, plans, &#x0026;c. Written in French by Alexander de Humboldt,<lb break="yes"/>and translated into English by Helen-Maria Williams.&#x201D; Vol. V.</note>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">There</hi> are some men whose names seem to irradiate the age in which<lb break="yes"/>they are born, whose every step in life forms an epoch in science, and<lb break="yes"/>who, as if Nature herself were sedulous to guard them as her histo-<lb break="no"/>rians, escape unhurt through perils that would alike appal the mind,<lb break="yes"/>and overwhelm the bodies, of less enthusiastic, less gifted individuals.<lb break="yes"/>Such is Humboldt, every addition to whose travels is an addition to<lb break="yes"/>our stock of knowledge. In him all the qualities that are requisite for<lb break="yes"/>a philosopher and a man of science are most happily combined, whilst<lb break="yes"/>the energies of his mind seem to transform themselves into physical<lb break="yes"/>powers of more than natural strength, to enable him to follow whither<lb break="yes"/>his ardour leads him. The termination of his &#x201C;Personal Narrative&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>has made its appearance, and the last part is no way inferior to the<lb break="yes"/>first, in vigour of research, truth of inference, and beauty of moral re-<lb break="no"/>flection. It is not easy for persons who stay quietly at home, to ima-<lb break="no"/>gine the exceeding energy of mind which must be called up, to bear<lb break="yes" />some of the torments, the privations, the perplexities, of a man exposed<lb break="yes"/>to every variation of climate, and to peculiarities attendant on each,<lb break="yes"/>of which he may be totally ignorant. The moschettoes, for instance,<lb break="yes"/>just beyond the mouth of the Rio Aranca, assume the appearance of<lb break="yes"/>an evil so formidable as to forbid all the attempts of man towards civi-<lb break="no"/>lization in the quarter which they infest, in a degree greater than is<lb break="yes"/>known in any other part of the habitable globe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The lower strata of air, from the surface of the ground to the<lb break="yes"/>height of fifteen or twenty feet, are filled with venomous insects like a<lb break="yes"/>condensed vapour. If in an obscure spot, for instance in the grottoes<lb break="yes"/>of the cataracts formed by superincumbent blocks of granite, you<lb break="yes"/>direct your eyes toward the opening enlightened by the sun, you see<lb break="yes"/>clouds of moschettoes more or less thick, according as these little ani-<lb break="no" />mals, in their slow and regular movements to their own music [<hi rendition="#i">mouve-<lb break="no"/>mens lents et cadencés</hi>], form into groups, or spread themselves abroad.<lb break="yes"/>At the mission of San Borja, the suffering from moschettoes is greater<lb break="yes"/>than at Carichana; but in the <hi rendition="#i">raudales,</hi> at Atures, and above all at<lb break="yes"/>Maypures, this suffering may be said to attain its <hi rendition="#i">maximum.</hi> I doubt<lb break="yes"/>whether there be a country upon earth, where man is exposed to more<lb break="yes"/>cruel torments in the rainy season. Having passed the fifth degree of<lb break="yes"/>latitude, you are somewhat less stung; but on the Upper Oroonoko<lb break="yes"/>the stings are more painful, because the heat, and the absolute want of<lb break="yes"/>wind, render the air more burning, and more irritating in its contact<lb break="yes"/>with the skin.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>No wonder that in the missions of the Oroonoko, in the villages<lb break="yes" />placed on the banks of the river, surrounded by immense forests,<lb break="yes"/>stations to which the unfortunate priests of Spain are condemned for<lb break="yes"/>twenty years together, the <hi rendition="#i" >plaga de los moscos,</hi> the plague of the flies,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="315" facs="#f0002"/> affords an inexhaustible subject of conversation, and that when two<lb break="yes"/>persons meet in the morning the first questions they address to each<lb break="yes"/>other are &#x201C;How did you find the zancudoes during the night? How<lb break="yes"/>are we to-day for the moschettoes?&#x201D; Some of these poor missionaries<lb break="yes"/>shewed their legs to Mr. Humboldt, which were so discoloured by the<lb break="yes" />repeated stinging of the different species of these tormentors (for their<lb break="yes"/>name is legion) that it was difficult to see a trace of the whiteness of<lb break="yes"/>the skin between the spots of coagulated blood. The different species<lb break="yes"/>do not congregate together, but occupy the air in succession, and<lb break="yes"/>sometimes there is a short interval of quiet between the changes, which<lb break="yes"/>is enjoyed with an ecstasy that must make the recommencement of the<lb break="yes"/>attack still more insupportable. It is a mistake to imagine that the<lb break="yes"/>Indians are less susceptible of the bites of these insects than the Eu-<lb break="no"/>ropeans. &#x201C;How comfortable must people be in the moon,&#x201D; said a<lb break="yes"/>Saliva Indian to father Gumilla; &#x201C;she looks so beautiful and so clear<lb break="yes"/>that she must be free from moschettoes.&#x201D; Mr. Humboldt&#x2019;s account of<lb break="yes"/>this plague of the deserts is minute and highly interesting; as is also<lb break="yes"/>his description of the missions in general, and of those whom God has<lb break="yes"/>ordained, as the monks despairingly express themselves, to inhabit<lb break="yes"/>them. But our limits forbid us to enter into particulars: instead of<lb break="yes"/>which we will present our readers with the following characteristic<lb break="yes" />sketch of a part of the travelling suite of Mr. Humboldt and his com-<lb break="no"/>panion Bonpland, in their passage up the Rio Negro.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In one of the huts of the Pacimonales we made the acquisition of<lb break="yes"/>two large fine birds, a toucan <hi rendition="#i" >(piapoco)</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Kiapoco,</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">aviapoco.</hi>
                    </note>, approaching the ramphastos<lb break="yes"/>erythrorhynchos, and an <hi rendition="#i">ana,</hi> a species of macaw, seventeen inches<lb break="yes" />long, having the whole body of a purple colour, like the p. macao.<lb break="yes"/>We had already in our canoe seven parrots, two manakins (pipra), a<lb break="yes"/>motmot, two <hi rendition="#i">guans,</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">pavas de monte,</hi> two manaviris (cercoleptes or<lb break="yes"/>viverra caudivolvula), and eight monkeys, namely, two ateles<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Marimonda</hi> of the Great Cataracts, simia belzebuth, Brisson.</note>, two<lb break="yes"/>titis <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;" >Simia sciurea, the saimiri of Buffon. (See my &#x201C;Rec. d&#x2019;Observ. de Zoologie,&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>vol. i. p. 327, 334, 353, and 357.)</note>, one viudita <note place="foot" n="§">Simia lugens. (Ib., p. 319).</note>, two douroucoulis or nocturnal monkeys <note place="foot" n="||">Cusicusi or simia trivirgata. (Ib. p. 307 and 358.) This is the aotus of Illiger.</note>, and the<lb break="yes"/>cacajao with a short tail <note place="foot" n="¶">Simia melanocephala, <hi rendition="#i">mono feo.</hi> (Ib. p. 317.) These last three species are<lb break="yes"/>new.</note>. Father Zea whispered some complaints<lb break="yes"/>at the daily augmentation of this ambulatory collection. The tou-<lb break="no"/>can resembles the raven in its manners and intelligence. It is a<lb break="yes"/>courageous animal, but easily tamed. Its long and stout beak serves<lb break="yes"/>to defend it at a distance. It makes itself master of the house, steals<lb break="yes"/>whatever it can come at, and loves to bathe often and fish on the banks<lb break="yes" />of the river. The toucan we had bought was very young; yet it took<lb break="yes"/>delight, during the whole voyage, in teazing the cusicusis, or nocturnal<lb break="yes"/>monkeys, which are sad and passionate. I did not observe what has<lb break="yes"/>been related in some works of natural history, that the toucan is forced,<lb break="yes"/>from the structure of its beak, to swallow its food by throwing it up<lb break="yes"/>into the air. It raises it indeed with some difficulty from the ground,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="316" facs="#f0003"/> but, having once seized it with the point of its enormous beak, it has<lb break="yes"/>only to lift it up by throwing back its head, and hold it perpendicularly<lb break="yes"/>as long as it is in the act of swallowing. This bird makes extraordinary<lb break="yes"/>gestures when preparing to drink. The monks say, that it makes the<lb break="yes"/>sign of the cross upon the water; and this popular belief has obtained<lb break="yes"/>for the toucan, from the creoles, the singular name of <hi rendition="#i" >diostede</hi> (God<lb break="yes"/>grant it thee.)</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Most of our animals were confined in small willow cages; others ran<lb break="yes"/>at full liberty all over the boat. At the approach of rain, the macaws<lb break="yes"/>sent forth frightful cries, the toucan wanted to gain the shore to fish,<lb break="yes"/>and the little monkeys, the titis, went in search of father Zea, to take<lb break="yes"/>shelter in the large sleeves of his Franciscan habit. These scenes were<lb break="yes"/>often repeated, and made us forget the torment of the <hi rendition="#i">moschettoes.</hi>&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Of many tribes of Indians being in the constant habit of eating<lb break="yes" />human flesh, M. Humboldt does not appear to entertain the smallest<lb break="yes"/>doubt; and, indeed, it would be folly to disbelieve what the missiona-<lb break="no"/>ries, though unwillingly, admit, and the Indians themselves boast of.<lb break="yes"/>Cocuy, a celebrated warrior, and chief of the Manitivitanoes, used to<lb break="yes"/>devour the finest and fattest of his wives, an instance of epicurism<lb break="yes"/>which scandalized no little the worthy missionaries, who converted<lb break="yes"/>him to christianity; though, without working that change in his appe-<lb break="no"/>tite which they did in his belief. &#x201C;It is a <hi rendition="#i">bad habit,</hi>&#x201D; says father Gili,<lb break="yes"/>of these people of Guyana, &#x201C;in other respects <hi rendition="#i">so good and so mild.</hi>&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;&#x2018;You cannot imagine,&#x2019; said the old missionary of Mandavaca,<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;all the perversity of this <hi rendition="#i">familia de Indios.</hi> You receive men of a<lb break="yes" />new tribe into the village; they appear to be mild, good, and labori-<lb break="no"/>ous; but, suffer them to take part in an incursion <hi rendition="#i">(entrada)</hi> to bring in<lb break="yes"/>the natives, and you can scarcely prevent them from murdering all they<lb break="yes"/>meet, and hiding some portions of the dead bodies.&#x2019; In reflecting on<lb break="yes" />the manners of these Indians, we are almost terrified at that combina-<lb break="no"/>tion of sentiments, which seem mutually to exclude each other; that<lb break="yes"/>faculty of nations to become but partially humanized; that pre-<lb break="no"/>ponderance of customs, prejudices, and traditions, over the natural<lb break="yes"/>reflections of the heart. We had a fugitive Indian from the Guaisia in<lb break="yes"/>our canoe, who had become sufficiently civilized in a few weeks, to be<lb break="yes"/>useful to us in placing the instruments necessary for our observations<lb break="yes"/>at night. He was no less mild than intelligent, and we had some de-<lb break="no"/>sire of taking him into our service. What was our regret, when,<lb break="yes"/>talking to him by means of an interpreter, we learned, &#x2018;that the flesh<lb break="yes" />of the marimonde monkeys, though blacker, appeared to him to have<lb break="yes"/>the taste of human flesh.&#x2019; He told us &#x2018;that his <hi rendition="#i">relations</hi> (that is, the peo-<lb break="no"/>ple of his tribe) preferred the inside of the hands in man, as in bears.&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>This assertion was accompanied with gestures of savage joy. We in-<lb break="no"/>quired of this young man, so calm and so affectionate in the little services<lb break="yes"/>which he rendered us, whether he still felt sometimes a desire to eat of<lb break="yes"/>a Cheruvichahena. He answered without discomposure, that, living<lb break="yes"/>in the mission, he would only eat what he saw was eaten by <hi rendition="#i">los Padres.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Reproaches addressed to the natives on the abominable practice, which<lb break="yes"/>we here discuss, produce no effect; it is as if a Bramin of the Ganges,<lb break="yes"/>travelling in Europe, reproached us with our habit of feeding on the<lb break="yes"/>flesh of animals. In the eyes of the Indian of the Guaisia, the Cheru-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="317" facs="#f0004"/> vichahena was a being entirely different from himself; and whom he<lb break="yes"/>thought it was no more unjust to kill, than the jaguars of the forest.<lb break="yes"/>It was merely from a sense of propriety, that, as long as he should re-<lb break="no"/>main in the mission, he would only eat the same food as <hi rendition="#i">los Padres.</hi> The<lb break="yes"/>natives, if they return to their tribe <hi rendition="#i">(al monte),</hi> or find themselves<lb break="yes"/>pressed by hunger, soon resume their ancient habits of anthropophagy.<lb break="yes"/>And why should we be so much astonished at this inconstancy in the<lb break="yes"/>tribes of the Oroonoko, when we are reminded, by terrible and well<lb break="yes"/>ascertained examples, of what has passed among civilized nations in<lb break="yes"/>times of great scarcity? In Egypt, in the thirteenth century, the habit<lb break="yes" />of eating human flesh pervaded all classes of society; extraordinary<lb break="yes"/>snares were spread for physicians in particular. They were called to<lb break="yes"/>attend persons, who pretended to be sick, but who were only hungry;<lb break="yes"/>and it was not in order to be consulted, but devoured. An historian<lb break="yes"/>of great veracity, Abd-Allatif, has related, how a practice, which at<lb break="yes"/>first inspired dread and horror, soon occasioned not the slightest<lb break="yes"/>surprise.<note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Account of Egypt by Abd-Allatif, Physician of Bagdad, translated into French by<lb break="yes"/>M. Silv. de Sacy,</hi> p. 360&#x2014;374. &#x201C;When the poor began to eat human flesh, the<lb break="yes"/>horror and astonishment caused by repasts so dreadful were such, that these crimes<lb break="yes"/>furnished the never ceasing subject of every conversation. But at length the peo-<lb break="no"/>ple became so accustomed to it, and conceived such a taste for this detestable food,<lb break="yes"/>that people of wealth and respectability were found to use it as their ordinary food,<lb break="yes"/>to eat it by way of regale, and even to lay in a stock of it. This flesh was pre-<lb break="no"/>pared in different ways, and the practice being once introduced, spread into the<lb break="yes"/>provinces, so that examples of it were found in every part of Egypt. It then no<lb break="yes"/>longer caused any surprise; the horror, it had at first inspired, vanished; and it<lb break="yes"/>was mentioned as an indifferent and ordinary thing. This fury of devouring one<lb break="yes" />another became so common among the poor, that the greater part perished in this<lb break="yes"/>manner. These wretches employed all sorts of artifices to seize men by surprise,<lb break="yes"/>or decoy them into their houses under false pretences. This happened to three<lb break="yes" />physicians among those who visited me; and a bookseller, who sold me books, an<lb break="yes"/>old and very corpulent man, fell into their snares, and escaped with great difficulty.<lb break="yes"/>All the facts which we relate as ocular witnesses fell under our observation acci-<lb break="no"/>dentally, for we generally avoided seeing spectacles, which inspired us with so<lb break="yes"/>much horror.&#x201D;</note>&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Next to the contemplation of this feast of the anthropophagi, we re-<lb break="no"/>commend the following for its singularity, to the imagination of our<lb break="yes"/>readers, to look upon with what appetite they may.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The hut, where the natives were assembled, displayed during seve-<lb break="no"/>ral days a very singular aspect. There was neither table nor bench,<lb break="yes"/>but large roasted monkeys, blackened by smoke, were ranged in order<lb break="yes"/>resting against the wall. These were the <hi rendition="#i">marimondes</hi> (ateles belzebuth),<lb break="yes"/>and those bearded monkeys called <hi rendition="#i">capuchins,</hi> which must not be con-<lb break="no"/>founded with the weeper, or sai (simia capucina of Buffon). The<lb break="yes"/>manner of roasting these anthropomorphous animals contributes singu-<lb break="no"/>larly to render their appearance disagreeable in the eyes of civilized<lb break="yes"/>man. A little grating, or lattice, of very hard wood, is formed, and<lb break="yes"/>raised one foot from the ground. The monkey is skinned, and bent<lb break="yes"/>into a sitting posture; the head generally resting on the arms, which<lb break="yes"/>are meagre and long; but sometimes these are crossed behind the back.<lb break="yes"/>When it is tied on the grating, a very clear fire is kindled below.<lb break="yes"/>The monkey, enveloped in smoke and flame, is broiled and blackened<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="318" facs="#f0005"/> at the same time. <note place="foot" n="*" >&#x201C;Soon after my return to Europe, an engraving was published at Weimar, from<lb break="yes"/>a drawing composed with great spirit by Mr. Schick at Rome, representing one of<lb break="yes"/>our resting-places on the banks of the Oroonoko. In the foreground some Indians<lb break="yes" />are occupied in roasting a monkey.&#x201D;</note> On seeing the natives devour the arm or leg of a<lb break="yes"/>roasted monkey, it is difficult not to believe, that this habit of eating<lb break="yes"/>animals, that so much resemble man in their physical organization, has,<lb break="yes"/>in a certain degree, contributed to diminish the horror of anthropo-<lb break="no"/>phagy among savages. Roasted monkeys, particularly those that have<lb break="yes"/>a very round head, display a hideous resemblance to a child; the Eu-<lb break="no" />ropeans therefore, who are obliged to feed on quadrumanes, prefer<lb break="yes"/>separating the head and the hands, and serve up only the rest of the<lb break="yes"/>animal at their tables. The flesh of monkeys is so lean and dry, that<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Bonpland has preserved in his collections at Paris an arm and<lb break="yes"/>hand, which had been broiled over the fire at Esmeralda; and no<lb break="yes"/>smell arises from them after a great number of years.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Whilst we are on the subject of <hi rendition="#i">taste,</hi> which is allowed to be mere<lb break="yes"/>matter of opinion, not of dispute, we will make mention of another<lb break="yes"/>diet, not exactly either animal or vegetable, but which we suppose may<lb break="yes"/>combine the flavours of both to those who indulge in it. We speak<lb break="yes"/>of the Otomacs, a tribe in the rudest state, who inhabit the pictu-<lb break="no"/>resque mission of Uruana, and who present one of the most extraor-<lb break="no"/>dinary physiological phenomena.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The Otomacs,&#x201D; says Mr. Humboldt, &#x201C;eat earth; that is, they<lb break="yes"/>swallow every day, during several months, very considerable quanti-<lb break="no"/>ties, to appease hunger, without injuring their health.&#x201D; And his ar-<lb break="no"/>guments on this singular custom are so curious, that though our<lb break="yes"/>limits forbid us from pursuing them further, we cannot but recommend<lb break="yes"/>them, with the whole of the work, to the attention of our readers, as<lb break="yes"/>very highly interesting.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 