<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="242" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>INDIAN RUBBER.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Here (at the mission of St. Balthasar on the Atoba-<lb break="no"/>po) we saw, for the first time, that white and fungous<lb break="yes"/>substance, which I have made known by the name of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">zapis.</hi> We immediately perceived, that it<lb break="yes"/>was analogous to the <hi rendition="#i">elastic resin;</hi> but, as the Indians<lb break="yes"/>made us understand by signs, that it was found under<lb break="yes"/>ground, we were inclined to think, till we arrived at<lb break="yes"/>the mission of Javita, that the <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> was a fossil<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="243" facs="#f0002"/> caoutchouc, though different from the elastic bitumen<lb break="yes"/>of Derbyshire. A Poimisano Indian, seated by the<lb break="yes"/>fire, in the hut of the missionary, was employed in<lb break="yes"/>reducing the <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> into black caomchouc. He had<lb break="yes"/>spitted several bits on a slender stick, and was roast-<lb break="no"/>ing them like meat. The <hi rendition="#i" >dapicho</hi> blackens in propor-<lb break="no"/>tion as it grows softer, and gains in elasticity. The<lb break="yes"/>resious and aromatic smell, which filled the hut,<lb break="yes"/>seemed to indicate, that this coloration is the effect of<lb break="yes"/>the decomposition of a carburet of hydrogen, and that<lb break="yes"/>the carbon appears in proportion as the hydrogen<lb break="yes"/>burns at a low heat. The Indian beat the softened<lb break="yes"/>and blackened mass with a piece of brazil wood, end-<lb break="no"/>ing in the form of a club; he then kneaded the <hi rendition="#i">dapi-<lb break="no"/>cho</hi> into balls of three or four inches in diameter, and let<lb break="yes"/>it cool. These balls exactly resemble the caoutchouc<lb break="yes"/>of the shops, but their surface remains in general<lb break="yes"/>slightly viscous. They are used at San Balthasar in<lb break="yes"/>the Indian game of tennis, which is so celebrated<lb break="yes"/>among the inhabitants of Uruana and Encaramada;<lb break="yes" />they are cut into cylinders, to be used as corks, and<lb break="yes"/>are far preferable to those made of the bark of the<lb break="yes"/>cork-tree.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Soon after, we obtained precise information respect-<lb break="no"/>ing this substance:&#x2014;it was shown us at the depth of<lb break="yes"/>two or three feet, in a marshy soil, between the roots<lb break="yes"/>of two trees known by the name of the <hi rendition="#i">jacio</hi> and the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">curvana.</hi> The first is the <hi rendition="#i">hevea</hi> of Aublet, or <hi rendition="#i">siphonia</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>of the modern botanists, known to furnish the caout-<lb break="no"/>chouc of commerce in Cayenne and the Grand Para;<lb break="yes" />the second has pinnate leaves, and its juice is milky,<lb break="yes"/>but very thin, and almost destitute of viscocity. The<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> appears to be the result of an extravasation of<lb break="yes"/>the sap from the roots. This extravasation takes<lb break="yes"/>place more especially when the trees have attained a<lb break="yes"/>great age, and the interior of the trunk begins to<lb break="yes"/>decay. The bark and alburnum crack; and thus is<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="244" facs="#f0003"/> effected naturally, what the art of man performs to<lb break="yes"/>collect in abundance the milky juices of the hevea, the<lb break="yes"/>castilloa, and the caoutchouc fig tree.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The river Temi, near the banks of which this pro-<lb break="no"/>duction is found in sufficient quantities to supply all<lb break="yes"/>Europe, runs through forests which overshadow it in<lb break="yes"/>so wild and luxuriant a manner as almost to mingle<lb break="yes"/>together the creatures of the several elements of air,<lb break="yes"/>earth, and water, and realize the classic images:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <lg type="poem">
                    <l>S&#x00E6;culum Pyrrh&#x00E6;, nova monstra quest&#x00E6;;</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Omne quum Proteus pecus egit altos</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>
                        <hi rendition="#et">Visere montes;</hi>
                    </l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Piscium et summa genus h&#x00E6;sit ulmo,</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Nota qu&#x00E6; sedes fuerat Colum bis,</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Et superjecto pavid&#x00E6; natarunt</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>
                        <hi rendition="#et">&#x00C6;quore dam&#x00E6;.</hi>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Indians made us leave the bed of the<lb break="yes"/>river; and we went up towards the south, across<lb break="yes"/>the forest, through paths <hi rendition="#i">(sendas)</hi> that is, through<lb break="yes"/>open channels of four or five feet broad. The<lb break="yes"/>depth of the water seldom exceeds half a fathom.<lb break="yes"/>These <hi rendition="#i">sendas</hi> are formed in the inundated forest-like<lb break="yes"/>paths on dry ground. The Indians, in going from<lb break="yes"/>one mission to another, pass with their boats as much<lb break="yes"/>as possible by the same way; but the communications<lb break="yes"/>not being frequent, the force of vegetation sometimes<lb break="yes"/>produces unexpected obstacles. An Indian, furnished<lb break="yes"/>with a <hi rendition="#i">machette</hi> (a great knife, the blade of which is<lb break="yes"/>fourteen inches long,) stood at the head of our boat,<lb break="yes"/>employed continually in chopping off the branches<lb break="yes"/>that cross each other from the two sides of the channel.<lb break="yes"/>In the thickest part of the forest we were astonished<lb break="yes"/>by an extraordinary noise. On beating the bushes,<lb break="yes"/>a shoal of <hi rendition="#i">toninas</hi> (fresh water dolphins) four feet<lb break="yes"/>long, surrounded our boat. These animals had con-<lb break="no"/>cealed themselves beneath the branches of a fromager<lb break="yes"/>or bombax ceiba. They fled across the forest, throw-<lb break="no"/>ing out those spouts of compressed air and water,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="245" facs="#f0004"/> which have given them in every language the name of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">blowers.</hi> How singular was this spectacle in the mid-<lb break="no"/>dle of the land, three or four hundred leagues from<lb break="yes"/>the mouths of the Oroonoko and the Amazon! I am<lb break="yes" />not ignorant, that the pleuronectes of the Atlantic go<lb break="yes"/>up the Loire as far as Orleans; but I persist in think-<lb break="no"/>ing, that the dolphins of the Temi, like those of the<lb break="yes"/>Ganges, and like the skate <hi rendition="#i">(raia)</hi> of the Oroonoko, are<lb break="yes"/>of a species essentially different from the dolphins and<lb break="yes"/>skates of the ocean. In the immense rivers of South<lb break="yes"/>America, and the great lakes of North America,<lb break="yes"/>nature seems to repeat several pelagic forms. The<lb break="yes"/>Nile has no porpoises: those of the sea go up the<lb break="yes"/>Delta no farther than Biana and Metonbis toward<lb break="yes" />Selamoun.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 