<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    MATERNAL ATTACHMENT.<lb/>From Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels.
                </head>
                <p>&#x201C;In 1797, the missionary of San Fernando had led<lb/>his Indians to the banks of the Rio Guaviare, on one<lb/>of those hostile incursions, which are prohibited<lb/>alike by religion and the Spanish laws. They found<lb/>in an Italian hut, a Guahiba mother with three chil-<lb/>dren, two of whom were still infants. They were<lb/>occupied in preparing the flour of Cassuva. Resis-<lb/>tance was impossible; the father was gone to fish,<lb/>and the mother tried in vain to flee with her children.<lb/>Scarcely had she reached the savannah, when she<lb/>was seized by the Indians of the mission, who go to<lb/>hunt men like the whites and the negroes in Africa.<lb/>The mother and her children were bound, and drag-<lb/>ged to the bank of the river. The monk seated in<lb/>his boat waited the issue of an expedition, of which<lb/>he partook not the danger. Had the mother made<lb/>too violent a resistance, the Indians would have kil-<lb/>led her, for every thing is permitted when they go<lb/>to the conquest of souls (<hi rendition="#i">a la conquista espiritual,</hi>)<lb/>and it is children in par-ticular they seek to capture,<lb/>in order to treat them, in the mission, as <hi rendition="#i">portos,</hi> or<lb/>slaves of the Christians. The prisoners were<lb/>carried to San Fernando in the hope, that the moth-<lb/>er would be unable to find her way back to her home,<lb/>by land. Far from those children who had accom-<lb/>panied their father on the day in which she had been<lb/>carried off, this unhappy woman showed signs of the<lb/>deepest despair. She attempted to take back to<lb/>her family the children who had been snatched away<lb/>by the missionary, and fled with them repeatedly<lb/>from the village of San Fernando, but the Indians<lb/>never failed to seize her anew; and the missionary,<lb/>after haying caused her to be mercilessly beaten,<lb/>took the cruel resolution of separating the mother<lb/>from the two children who had been carried off
 <cb/>
                    with her. She was conveyed alone towards the mis-<lb/>sions of the Rio Negro, going up the Atabapo&#x2014;<lb/>Slightly bound she was seated at the bow of the<lb/>boat, ignorant of the fate that awaited her; but she<lb/>judged by the direction of the sun that she was re-<lb/>moved farther and farther from her hut and her na<lb/>tive country. She succeeded in breaking her bonds,<lb/>threw herself into the water, and swam to the left<lb/>bank of the Atabapo.&#x2014;The current carried her to<lb/>a shelf of rock, which bears her name to this day.<lb/>She lauded and took shelter in the woods, but the<lb/>president of the missions ordered the Indians to row<lb/>to the shore, and follow the traces of the Guahibi.<lb/>In the evening she was brought back. Stretched up-<lb/>on the rack (<hi rendition="#i">la Piedra de la Madre</hi>) a cruel punish-<lb/>ment was inflicted on her with those straps of mana-<lb/>tee leather, which serve for whips in that country,<lb/>and with which the alcades are always furnished.<lb/>This unhappy woman, her hands tied behind her<lb/>back with strong stalks of <hi rendition="#i">maracure,</hi> was then drag-<lb/>ged to the mission of Javita.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;She was there thrown into one of the caravan-<lb/>seras that are called <hi rendition="#i">Casa del rey</hi>&#x2014;It was the rainy<lb/>season, and the night was profoundly dark. Forests,<lb/>till then believed to be impenetrable, separated the<lb/>mission of Javita from that of San Fernando, which<lb/>was 25 leagues distant in a straight line&#x2014;No other<lb/>part is known than that of the rivers; no man ever<lb/>attempted to go by land from one village to another<lb/>were they only a few leagues apart. But such diffi-<lb/>culties do not stop a mother, who is separated from<lb/>her children. Her children are at San Fernando de<lb/>Atabapo; she must find them again, she must exe-<lb/>cute her project of delivering them from the hands<lb/>of Christians, of bringing them back to their father<lb/>on the banks of the Guaviare. The Guahibi was<lb/>carelessly guarded in the caravansera. Her arms<lb/>being wounded, the Indians of Javita had loosened<lb/>her bonds, unknown to the missionary and the al-<lb/>cades. She succeeded by the help of her teeth in<lb/>breaking them entirely; disappeared during the<lb/>night; and at the fourth rising sun was seen at the<lb/>mission of San Fernando, hovering around the hut<lb/>where her children were confined. &#x201C;What that wo-<lb/>man performed.&#x2019; added the missionary who gavo us<lb/>this narrative. The most robust Indian would not have<lb/>ventured to undertake. She traversed the woods at<lb/>a season when the sky is constantly covered with<lb/>clouds, and the sun during whole days appears but<lb/>for a few minutes. Did the course of the waters di-<lb/>rect her way?&#x2014;The inundations of the rivers for-<lb/>ced her to go far from the banks of the main stream<lb/>through the midst of woods where the movement of<lb/>the waters is almost imperceptible. How often<lb/>must she have been stopped by the thorny lianes,<lb/>that form a net work around the trunks they entwine?<lb/>How often must she have swam across the rivulets,<lb/>that run into the Atabapo? This unfortunate wo-<lb/>man was asked how she had sustained herself during<lb/>the four days! She said, that exhausted with fa-<lb/>tigue, she could find no other nourishment than those<lb/>great black ants called <hi rendition="#i">vachacus</hi>, which climb the<lb/>trees in long bands, to suspend on them their resin-<lb/>ous nests.&#x2019; We pressed the missionary to tell us,<lb/>whether the Guahibi had peacefully enjoyed the<lb/>happiness of remaining with her children; and if<lb/>any repentance had followed this excess of cruelty.<lb/>He would not satisfy us; but at our return from Rio<lb/>Negro we learnet, that the Indian mother was not al-<lb/>lowed time to cure her wounds, but was again sepa-<lb/>rated from her children, and sent to one of the mis-<lb/>sions of the Upper Oroonoko. There she died, re-<lb/>fusing all kind of nourishment, as the savages do in<lb/>great calamities.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">National Gazette</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>