<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157">
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-31" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="662" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>HUMBOLDT&#x2019;S PERSONAL NARRATIVE<lb break="yes"/>(Concluded.)<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Stories of Crocodiles.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Our</hi> latter extracts from this publication<lb break="yes" />have been as desultory as the curious na-<lb break="no"/>ture of the author&#x2019;s inquiries seemed to re-<lb break="no"/>quire, without servilely following him<lb break="yes"/>through all his topographical details, and<lb break="yes"/>philosophical <hi rendition="#i">generalizations.</hi> In the same<lb break="yes"/>spirit, we shall now conclude our notice of<lb break="yes"/>these volumes with a brief sequel relating<lb break="yes"/>to the crocodiles of the Oroonoko.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;When the waters (says Mr. H.) are<lb break="yes"/>high, the river inundates the keys; and it<lb break="yes"/>sometimes happens, that even in the town<lb break="yes"/>imprudent men become the prey of croco-<lb break="no" />diles. I shall transcribe from my journal a<lb break="yes"/>fact, that took place during Mr. Bonpland&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>illness. A Guaykeri Indian, from the island<lb break="yes"/>de la Margaretta, went to anchor bis canoe<lb break="yes"/>in a cove, where there were not three feet<lb break="yes"/>of water. A very fierce crocodile, that ha-<lb break="no"/>bitually haunted that spot, seized him by<lb break="yes"/>the leg, and withdrew from the shore, re-<lb break="no"/>maining on the surface of the water. The<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> cries of the Indian drew together a crowd<lb break="yes"/>of spectators. This unfortunate man was<lb break="yes"/>first seen seeking with astonishing courage<lb break="yes"/>for a knife in the pocket of his pantaloons.<lb break="yes"/>Not being able to find it, he seized the head<lb break="yes" />of the crocodile, and thrust his fingers into<lb break="yes"/>its eyes. No man in the hot regions of<lb break="yes"/>America is ignorant, that this carnivorous<lb break="yes"/>reptile, covered with a buckler of hard and<lb break="yes"/>dry scales, is extremely sensible in the only<lb break="yes" />parts of his body which are soft and unpro-<lb break="no"/>tected, such as the eyes, the hollow under-<lb break="no"/>neath the shoulders, the nostrils, and be-<lb break="no"/>neath the lower jaw, where there are two<lb break="yes" />glands of musk. The Guaykeri Indian had<lb break="yes"/>recourse to the same means which saved<lb break="yes"/>the negro of Mungo Park, and the girl of<lb break="yes"/>Uritucu, whom I have mentioned above;<lb break="yes"/>but he was less fortunate than they had<lb break="yes"/>been, for the crocodile did not open its<lb break="yes"/>jaws, and lose hold of its prey. The ani-<lb break="no" />mal, yielding to the pain, plunged to the<lb break="yes"/>bottom of the river; and, after having<lb break="yes"/>drowned the Indian, came up to the surface<lb break="yes"/>of the water, dragging the dead body to an<lb break="yes" />island opposite the port. I arrived at the<lb break="yes"/>moment when a great number of the inha-<lb break="no"/>bitants of Angostura had witnessed this me-<lb break="no"/>lancholy spectacle.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;As the crocodile, on account of the<lb break="yes"/>structure of its larynx, of the hyoid bone,<lb break="yes"/>and of the folds of its tongue, can seize,<lb break="yes"/>though not swallow, its prey under water;<lb break="yes"/>a man seldom disappears without the ani-<lb break="no"/>mal being perceived some hours after near<lb break="yes"/>the spot where the misfortune has happened,<lb break="yes"/>devouring its prey on a neighbouring beach.<lb break="yes"/>The number of individuals who perish an-<lb break="no"/>nually, the victims of their own imprudence<lb break="yes"/>and of the ferocity of these reptiles, is much<lb break="yes"/>greater than it is believed to be in Europe.<lb break="yes"/>It is particularly so in villages, where the<lb break="yes"/>neighbouring grounds are often inundated.<lb break="yes"/>The same crocodiles remain long in the<lb break="yes"/>same places. They become from year to<lb break="yes"/>year more daring, especially, as the Indians<lb break="yes"/>assert, if they have once tasted of human<lb break="yes"/>flesh. These animals are so wary, that they<lb break="yes"/>are killed with difficulty. A ball does not<lb break="yes"/>pierce their skin, and the shot is only mor-<lb break="no"/>tal when directed at the throat, or beneath<lb break="yes"/>the shoulder. The Indians, who know<lb break="yes" />little of the use of fire-arms, attack the cro-<lb break="no"/>codile with lances, after it is caught with<lb break="yes"/>large pointed iron hooks, baited with pieces<lb break="yes"/>of meat, and fastened by a chain to the<lb break="yes"/>trunk of a tree. They do not approach the<lb break="yes" />animal till it has struggled a long time to<lb break="yes"/>disengage itself from the iron fixed in the<lb break="yes"/>upper jaw. There is little probability that<lb break="yes"/>a country in which a labyrinth of rivers<lb break="yes"/>without number brings every day new bands<lb break="yes"/>of crocodiles from the eastern back of the<lb break="yes"/>Andes, by the Meta and the Apure, towards<lb break="yes"/>the coast of Spanish Guyana, should ever<lb break="yes"/>be delivered from these reptiles. All that<lb break="yes"/>will be gained by civilization will be, to<lb break="yes"/>render them more timid, and more easily<lb break="yes"/>put to flight.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Affecting instances are related of Afri-<lb break="no"/>can slaves, who have exposed their lives<lb break="yes"/>to save those of their masters, who had<lb break="yes"/>fallen into the jaws of the crocodile. A few<lb break="yes"/>years ago, between Uritucu and the <hi rendition="#i" >Mission</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="663" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">de Abazo,</hi> a negro, hearing the cries of his<lb break="yes"/>master, flew to the spot, armed with a long<lb break="yes" />knife, <hi rendition="#i">(machette,)</hi> and plunged into the<lb break="yes" />river. He forced the crocodile, by putting<lb break="yes"/>out his eyes, to let go his prey, and hide<lb break="yes"/>himself under the water. The slave bore<lb break="yes"/>his expiring master to the shore, but all<lb break="yes"/>succour was unavailing to restore him to<lb break="yes"/>life. He died of suffocation, for his wounds<lb break="yes"/>were not deep; the crocodile, like the<lb break="yes"/>dog, appears not to close its jaws firmly<lb break="yes"/>while swimming. It is almost superfluous<lb break="yes"/>to add, that the children of the deceased,<lb break="yes"/>though poor, gave the slave his freedom.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Upon the whole, this portion of Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt&#x2019;s work is equally entertaining<lb break="yes"/>with what has gone before, and throws<lb break="yes"/>much light on Physics and Geography.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 