<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="38" facs="#f0001" />
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#k">Natural History I.</hi>&#x2014;Baron Humboldt, in a memoir read to<lb/>the Institute entitled, &#x00AB;New Observations on the Laws which<lb/>we observe in the Distribution of Vegetable Forms,&#x00BB; states,<lb/>that we already know nearly 56,000 species of cryptogamous<lb/>and phanerogamous <hi rendition="#i">plants</hi>, 44,000 insects, 2,500 fishes, 700<lb/>reptiles, 4,000 birds, and 500 species of mammifer&#x00E6;. In Europe<lb/>alone, according to the researches of M. Humboldt and M.<lb/>Valenciennes, there exist nearly 80 mammifer&#x00E6;, 400 birds,<lb/>and 30 reptiles. There are, of consequence, under this tem-<lb/>perate boreal zone, 5 times as many species of birds as of<lb/>mammifer&#x00E6;; as, in like manner, there are in Europe 5 times<lb/>as many composit&#x0153; as amentaceous and coniferous plants;<lb/>5 times as many leguminous as there are of orchideous and<lb/>euphorbiaceous. The fine collections recently brought from the<lb/>Cape of Good Hope by M. Delalande prove, (if we compare<lb/>them with the works of M. M. Temmink and Levaillant,) that<lb/>in that part of the temperate austral zone, the mammifer&#x00E6; are<lb/>also to the birds in the proportion of 1 to 4.3. Such an<lb/>accordance between two opposite zones is very striking. The<lb/>birds, and especially the reptiles, increase much more towards<lb/>the equatorial zone than the mammifer&#x00E6;. According to the<lb/>discoveries of M. Cuvier on fossil bones, we might believe,<lb/>that these proportions have not been the same at all times;<lb/>and that there have disappeared, in the ancient catastrophes<lb/>of our planet, many more mammifer&#x00E6; than birds. We can 
            </p>
            
            <pb n="39" facs="#f0002" />
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#k">Histoire naturelle I.</hi>&#x2014;Le baron Humboldt, dans un mé-<lb/>moire qu&#x2019;il a lu à l&#x2019;Institut de France et intitulé: <hi rendition="#i">Nouvelles<lb/>Observations sur les Lois que nous observons dans la distri-<lb/>bution de formes végétales,</hi> annonce qu&#x2019;on conna&#x00EE;t déjà en-<lb/>viron 56,000 espèces de plantes cryptogames et phanérogames;<lb/>44,000 insects, 2,500 poissons, 700 reptiles, 4000 oiseaux et<lb/>500 espèces de mammiferes. D&#x2019;après les recherches de MM.<lb/>Humboldt et Valenciennes, l&#x2019;Europe seule offre à peu près 80<lb/>mammiferes, 400 oiseaux et 30 reptiles; de fa&#x00E7;on que sous cette<lb/>z&#xF4;ne tempérée il existe cinq fois plus d&#x2019;espèces d&#x2019;oiseaux qu&#x2019;il<lb/>n&#x2019;en existe de mammiferes, de m&#x00EA;me qu&#x2019;on y trouve cinq fois<lb/>plus de plantes composées que d&#x2019;amentacées et de conifères,<lb/>et cinq fois plus de légumineuses que d&#x2019;orchidées et d&#x2019;euphor-<lb/>biées. Si nous comparons avec les ouvrages de MM. Le Vail-<lb/>lant et Temmink les belles collections rapportées récemment<lb/>du cap de Bonne-Espérance par M. Delalande, nous trouvons<lb/>que dans cette partie tempérée de la z&#xF4;nes opposées de-<lb/>vient frappant. Les oiseaux et sur-tout les reptiles augmentent,<lb/>en approchant de la z&#xF4;ne équitoriale, dans une progression<lb/>beaucoup plus grande que ne le font les mammiferes, tandis<lb/>que d&#x2019;après les découvertes de M. Cuvier sur les os fossiles,<lb/>il semblerait que ces proportions n&#x2019;ont pas été les m&#x00EA;mes dans<lb/>tous le tems, et que dans les anciennes catastrophes de notre<lb/>globe il disparut beaucoup plus de mammifères que d&#x2019;oiseaux.<lb/>Nous pouvons concevoir comment sur un espace donné de<lb/>territoire, les individus appartenant à différentes familles de<lb/>plantes et d&#x2019;animaux peuvent &#x00EA;tre <hi rendition="#i">numériquement</hi> déterminés;
            </p>
            
            <pb n="40" facs="#f0003" />
            <p>
                conceive how, on a given space of territory, the individuals<lb/>belonging to different tribes of plants and animals may be<lb/><hi rendition="#i">numerically limited;</hi> how, after an obstinate struggle and long<lb/>oscillations, a state of equilibrium comes to be established,<lb/>resulting from the necessities of nourishment and the habits<lb/>of life: but the causes which have <hi rendition="#i">limited the forms</hi> are<lb/>hid under an impenetrable veil, which withdraws from our<lb/>view whatever relates to the origin of things, or to the first<lb/>developement of organic life.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                On the preponderance of certain families of plants depends<lb/>the character of the landscape; the aspect of a smiling or ma-<lb/>jestic nature. The abundance of gramine&#x00E6; which form vast<lb/>savannahs, and that of palms and conifer&#x00E6;, have had a powerful<lb/>influence on the social conditon of nations, on their manners,<lb/>and the more or les srapid developement of the useful arts.<lb/>Sometimes a single species of plants, especially among those<lb/>styled, by M. Humboldt, <hi rendition="#i">social</hi>, covers a vast extent of country.<lb/>Such are, in the north, the heaths, and forests of pines; in<lb/>equinoctial America, the union of cactus, croton, bambusa,<lb/>and brathys of the same species. (<hi rendition="#i"> Extract from an English<lb/>Journal; to be continued.</hi>)
            </p>
            
            <pb n="41" facs="#f0004" />
            <p>
                comment, après des efforts continus et de longues oscillations,<lb/>il s&#x2019;établit un état d&#x2019;équilibre qui résulte de la nécessité de<lb/>la nourriture et du genre de vie; mais les causes qui ont<lb/>limité les formes sont cachées sous un voile impénétrable qui nous dérobe tout ce qui est relatif à l&#x2019;origine des choses ou<lb/>au premier développement de la vie organique.
            </p>
            <p>De la prépondérance de certaines familles de plantes dépend<lb/>le caractère du paysage, l&#x2019;aspect d&#x2019;une nature riante ou ma-<lb/>jestueuse. L&#x2019;abondance des graminées qui forment de vastes<lb/>savannes, et celle de palmiers et des conifères ont exercé<lb/>une grande influence sur la condition sociale des nations,<lb/>sur leurs m&#x0153;urs et sur le développement plus ou moins ra-<lb/>pide des arts utiles. Souvent une seule espèce de plantes<lb/>(particulièrement de celles que Humboldt a surnommées<lb/>sociales), couvre une vaste étendue; c&#x2019;est ainsi qu&#x2019;au nord on<lb/>voit des bruyères et des forets de pins, et que dans l&#x2019;Amé-<lb/>rique équinoxiale on trouve réunies plusieurs espèces de<lb/>cactus, de croton, de bambusa et de brathys. ( <hi rendition="#i">Extr. d&#x2019;une<lb/>feuille anglaise; la suite au numéro prochain </hi>)</p>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>