<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="260" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">EARTH-EATERS IN SOUTH<lb break="yes"/>AMERICA.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">By Baron Humboldt.</hi>)</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Since</hi> my return to Europe, the fact of eating<lb break="yes"/>earth has become a subject of warm dispute,<lb break="yes" />because two assertions have been confounded<lb break="yes"/>together, which are extremely different; that<lb break="yes"/>of eating earth, and that of being nourished<lb break="yes"/>by it. Though we could stay only one day<lb break="yes"/>at Uruana, this short space of time sufficed<lb break="yes"/>to instruct us in the preparation of the poya,<lb break="yes"/>or balls of earth. I also found some traces<lb break="yes"/>of this vitiated appetite among the Guamoes,<lb break="yes"/>and between the confluence of the Meta and<lb break="yes"/>the Apure, where every body speaks of geo-<lb break="no"/>phagy as of a thing anciently known. I shall<lb break="yes"/>here confine myself to an account of what<lb break="yes"/>we ourselves saw, or heard from the missionary<lb break="yes"/>whom an unhappy fatality had doomed to<lb break="yes"/>live for twelve years among the savage and<lb break="yes" />turbulent tribe of the Otomacs.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The inhabitants of Uruana belong to those<lb break="yes"/>nations of the savannahs, who, more difficult<lb break="yes"/>to civilize than the nations of the forest,<lb break="yes"/>have a decided aversion to cultivate the land,<lb break="yes"/>and live almost exclusively on hunting and<lb break="yes" />fishing. They are men of a very robust con-<lb break="no"/>stitution, but ugly, savage, vindictive, and<lb break="yes"/>passionately fond of fermented liquors.<lb break="yes"/>They are omnivorous animals in the highest<lb break="yes"/>degree; and therefore the other Indians<lb break="yes"/>who consider them as barbarians, have a<lb break="yes"/>common saying, &#x201C;Nothing is so disgusting,<lb break="yes"/>that an Otomac will not eat it.&#x201D; While the<lb break="yes"/>waters of the Orinoco and its tributary streams<lb break="yes"/>are low, the Otomacs subsist on fish and<lb break="yes"/>turtles. The former they kill with surprising<lb break="yes" />dexterity, by shooting them with an arrow<lb break="yes"/>when they appear at the surface of the water.<lb break="yes"/>When the rivers swell, which in South Ame-<lb break="no"/>rica, as well as in Egypt and in Nubia, is<lb break="yes"/>erroneously attributed to the melting of the<lb break="yes" />snows, and which occurs periodically in every<lb break="yes"/>part of the torrid zone, fishing almost entirely<lb break="yes"/>ceases. It is then as difficult to procure fish<lb break="yes"/>in the rivers, which are become deeper, as<lb break="yes"/>when you are sailing on the open sea. It<lb break="yes"/>often fails the poor missionaries on fast-days<lb break="yes" />as well as flesh-days, though all the young<lb break="yes"/>Indians are under the obligation of &#x201C;fishing<lb break="yes"/>for the convent.&#x201D; At the period of these<lb break="yes"/>inundations, which last two or three months,<lb break="yes"/>the Otomacs swallow a prodigious quantity of<lb break="yes"/>earth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="261" facs="#f0002"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>We found heaps of balls in their huts,<lb break="yes"/>piled up in pyramids three or four feet high.<lb break="yes"/>These balls were five or six inches in diameter.<lb break="yes"/>The earth which the Otomacs eat is a very<lb break="yes"/>fine and unctuous clay, of a yellowish-grey<lb break="yes" />colour; and being slightly baked in the fire,<lb break="yes"/>the hardened crust has a tint inclining to<lb break="yes"/>red, owing to the oxide of iron which is min-<lb break="no"/>gled with it. We brought away some of<lb break="yes"/>this earth, which we took from the winter<lb break="yes" />provision of the Indians; and it is absolutely<lb break="yes"/>false that it is steatitic, and contains magne-<lb break="no"/>sia. M. Vauquelin did not discover any<lb break="yes"/>traces of this earth in it; but he found that<lb break="yes"/>it contained mere silex than alumina, and<lb break="yes"/>three or four per cent of lime.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Otomacs do not eat every kind of clay<lb break="yes"/>indifferently: they choose the alluvial beds<lb break="yes"/>or strata that contain the most unctuous<lb break="yes"/>earth, and the smoothest to the feel. I in-<lb break="no"/>quired of the missionary, whether the moist-<lb break="no"/>ened clay were made to undergo, as Father<lb break="yes"/>Gumilla asserts, that peculiar decomposition<lb break="yes"/>which is indicated by a disengagement of<lb break="yes"/>carbonic acid and sulphuretted hydrogen, and<lb break="yes"/>which is designated in every language by<lb break="yes"/>the term putrefaction? but he assured us,<lb break="yes"/>that the natives neither cause the clay to rot,<lb break="yes"/>nor do they mingle it with flour of maize, oil<lb break="yes"/>of turtles&#x2019; eggs, or fat of the crocodile. We<lb break="yes"/>ourselves examined, both at the Orinoco and<lb break="yes"/>after our return to Paris, the balls of earth<lb break="yes" />which we brought away with us, and found<lb break="yes"/>no trace of the mixture of any organic sub-<lb break="no"/>stance, whether oily or farinaceous. The<lb break="yes"/>savage regards every thing as nourishing,<lb break="yes" />that appeases hunger. When therefore you<lb break="yes"/>inquire of an Otomac, on what he subsists<lb break="yes"/>during the two months when the river is the<lb break="yes"/>highest, he shows you his balls of clayey<lb break="yes" />earth. This he calls his principal food; for<lb break="yes"/>at this period he can seldom procure a lizard,<lb break="yes"/>a root of fern, or a dead fish swimming at<lb break="yes"/>the surface of the water.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If the Indian eat earth from want during<lb break="yes"/>two months, (and from three quarters to five<lb break="yes"/>quarters of a pound in twenty-four hours), he<lb break="yes"/>does not the less regale himself with it during<lb break="yes"/>the rest of the year. Every day in the season<lb break="yes" />of drought, when fishing is most abundant,<lb break="yes"/>he scrapes his balls of poya, and mingles a<lb break="yes"/>little clay with his other aliment. What is<lb break="yes"/>most surprising is, that the Otomacs do not<lb break="yes"/>become lean by swallowing such quantities of<lb break="yes" />earth: they are, on the contrary, extremely<lb break="yes"/>robust, and far from having the belly tense<lb break="yes"/>and puffed up. The missionary Fray Ramon<lb break="yes"/>Bueno asserts, that he never remarked any<lb break="yes"/>alteration in the health of the natives at the<lb break="yes" />period of the great risings of the Orinoco.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following are the facts in all their<lb break="yes"/>simplicity, which we were able to verify. The<lb break="yes"/>Otomacs during some months eat daily three<lb break="yes"/>quarters of a pound of clay, slightly hardened<lb break="yes"/>by fire, without their health being sensibly<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> affected by it. They moisten the earth<lb break="yes"/>afresh when they are going to swallow it.<lb break="yes"/>It has not been possible to verify hitherto<lb break="yes"/>with precision how much nutritious vegetable<lb break="yes"/>or animal matter the Indians take in a week<lb break="yes"/>at the same time; but it is certain, that they<lb break="yes"/>attribute the sensation of satiety which they<lb break="yes"/>feel, to the clay, and not to the wretched<lb break="yes"/>aliments which they take with it occasion-<lb break="no"/>ally. No physiological phenomenon being<lb break="yes"/>entirely insulated, it may be interesting to<lb break="yes"/>examine several analogous phenomena, which<lb break="yes"/>I have been able to collect.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I observed everywhere within the torrid<lb break="yes"/>zone, in a great number of individuals, chil-<lb break="no"/>dren, women, and sometimes even full grown<lb break="yes"/>men, an inordinate and almost irresistible<lb break="yes"/>desire of swallowing earth&#x2014;not an alkaline<lb break="yes"/>or calcareous earth, to neutralize (as it is<lb break="yes" />vulgarly said) acid juices, but a fat clay,<lb break="yes"/>unctuous, and exhaling a strong smell. It is<lb break="yes"/>often found necessary to tie the children&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>hands, or to confine them, to prevent their<lb break="yes"/>eating earth when the rain ceases to fall. At<lb break="yes"/>the village of Banco, on the bank of the<lb break="yes"/>river Magdalena, I saw the Indian women<lb break="yes"/>who make pottery, continually swallowing<lb break="yes"/>great pieces of clay. These women were<lb break="yes"/>not in a state of pregnancy; and they affirmed<lb break="yes" />that &#x201C;earth is an aliment which they do not<lb break="yes"/>find hurtful.&#x201D; In other American tribes,<lb break="yes"/>people soon fall sick, and waste away, when<lb break="yes"/>they yield too much to this mania of eating<lb break="yes"/>earth. We found at the mission of San<lb break="yes" />Borja, an Indian child of the Guahibo nation<lb break="yes"/>who was as thin as a skeleton. The mother<lb break="yes"/>informed us by an interpreter, that the little<lb break="yes"/>girl was reduced to this lamentable state of<lb break="yes"/>atrophy in consequence of a disordered appe-<lb break="no" />tite, having refused during four months to<lb break="yes"/>take almost any other food than clay. Yet<lb break="yes"/>San Borja is only twenty-five leagues distant<lb break="yes"/>from the mission of Uruana, inhabited by<lb break="yes"/>that tribe of the Otomacs, who, from the<lb break="yes"/>effect no doubt of a habit progressively ac-<lb break="no"/>quired, swallow the poya without experiencing<lb break="yes"/>any pernicious effects. Father Gumilla asserts,<lb break="yes"/>that the Otomacs purge themselves with oil,<lb break="yes"/>or rather with melted fat of the crocodile,<lb break="yes" />when they feel any gastric obstructions; but<lb break="yes"/>the missionary whom we found among them<lb break="yes"/>was little disposed to confirm this assertion.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Negroes on the coast of Guinea de-<lb break="no"/>light in eating a yellowish earth, which they<lb break="yes"/>call caouac. The slaves who are taken to<lb break="yes"/>America try to procure for themselves the<lb break="yes"/>same enjoyment; but it is constantly detri-<lb break="no"/>mental to their health. They say &#x201C;that the<lb break="yes"/>earth of the West Indies is not so easy of<lb break="yes"/>digestion as that of their country.&#x201D; Thibaut<lb break="yes"/>de Chanvalon, in his voyage to Martinico,<lb break="yes" />expresses himself very judiciously on that<lb break="yes"/>pathological phenomenon. &#x201C;Another cause,&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>he says, &#x201C;of this pain in the stomach is,<lb break="yes"/>that several of the Negroes who come from<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="562" facs="#f0003"/>
                    <cb/> the coast of Guinea eat earth, not from a<lb break="yes"/>depraved taste, or in consequence of a disease,<lb break="yes"/>but from a habit contracted at home in Africa,<lb break="yes"/>where, they eat, they say, a particular earth,<lb break="yes"/>the taste of which they find agreeable, with-<lb break="no"/>out suffering any inconvenience. They seek<lb break="yes"/>in our islands for the earth the most similar<lb break="yes"/>to this, and prefer a yellowish and volcanic<lb break="yes"/>tufa. It is sold secretly in our public mar-<lb break="no"/>kets; but this is an abuse which the police<lb break="yes"/>ought to correct. The Negroes who have<lb break="yes"/>this habit are so fond of caouac, that no<lb break="yes"/>chastisement will prevent their eating it.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the Indian Archipelago, at the island<lb break="yes"/>of Java, M. Labillardière saw, between Sura-<lb break="no"/>baga and Samarang, little square and reddish<lb break="yes"/>cakes exposed to sale. These cakes, called<lb break="yes"/>tanaampo, were cakes of clay, slightly baked,<lb break="yes" />which the natives eat with appetite.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The savage inhabitants of New Caledonia<lb break="yes"/>also, to appease their hunger in times of<lb break="yes"/>scarcity, eat great pieces of a friable lapis<lb break="yes"/>ollaris. M. Vauquelin analyzed this stone,<lb break="yes"/>and found in it, besides magnesia and silex<lb break="yes"/>in equal portions, a small quantity of oxide<lb break="yes"/>of copper. Mr. Goldberry had seen the<lb break="yes"/>Negroes in Africa, in the islands of Bunck<lb break="yes"/>and Los Idolos, eat an earth, of which he had<lb break="yes"/>himself eaten without being incommoded by<lb break="yes"/>it, and which also was a white and friable<lb break="yes"/>steatite.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In looking over these examples, which are<lb break="yes"/>all taken from the torrid zone, we are struck<lb break="yes"/>by the idea of finding a taste, which nature,<lb break="yes"/>it would seem, should have reserved for the<lb break="yes"/>inhabitants of the most sterile regions, prevail<lb break="yes" />among races of rude and indolent men, who<lb break="yes"/>live in the finest and most fertile countries<lb break="yes"/>on the globe. We saw at Popayan, and in<lb break="yes"/>several mountainous parts of Peru, lime re-<lb break="no" />duced to a very fine powder, sold in the<lb break="yes"/>public markets to the natives among other<lb break="yes"/>articles of provision. This powder, when<lb break="yes"/>used, is mingled with cocoa. It is well<lb break="yes"/>known that Indian messengers take no other<lb break="yes"/>aliment for whole days than lime and cocoa:<lb break="yes"/>both excite the secretion of spittle, and of the<lb break="yes"/>gastric juice, and they take away the appetite<lb break="yes"/>without giving any nourishment to the body.<lb break="yes"/>In other parts of South America, on the<lb break="yes"/>coast of Rio de la Hacha, the Guajiroes<lb break="yes"/>swallow lime alone, without adding any vege-<lb break="no"/>table matter to it. They always carry with<lb break="yes"/>them a little box filled with the lime, as we<lb break="yes"/>do snuff-boxes, and as in Asia people carry a<lb break="yes"/>betel box. This American custom excited<lb break="yes"/>the curiosity of the first Spanish navigators.<lb break="yes"/>Lime blackens the teeth; and in the Indian<lb break="yes" />Archipelago, as among several American<lb break="yes"/>hordes, to blacken the teeth is to beautify<lb break="yes"/>them. In the cold regions of the kingdom<lb break="yes"/>of Quito, the natives of Tigua eat habitually<lb break="yes" />from choice, and without being incommoded<lb break="yes"/>by it, a very fine clay, mixed with quartzose<lb break="yes"/>sand. This clay suspended in water renders<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> it milky. We find in their huts large vessels<lb break="yes"/>filled with this water, which serves as a bere-<lb break="no"/>rage, and which the Indians call <hi rendition="#i">agua</hi> or<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">leche de llanka,</hi> milk of clay.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When we reflect on the whole of these<lb break="yes"/>facts, we perceive that this disorderly appetite<lb break="yes"/>for clayey, magnesian, and calcareous earth,<lb break="yes"/>is most common among the people of the<lb break="yes" />torrid zone; that it is not always a cause of<lb break="yes"/>disease; and that some tribes eat earth from<lb break="yes"/>choice, while others, (the Otomacs in Ame-<lb break="no"/>rica, and the inhabitants of New Caledonia,<lb break="yes"/>in the Pacific Ocean), eat it from want, and<lb break="yes"/>to appease hunger. A great number of phy-<lb break="no"/>siological phenomena prove, that a temporary<lb break="yes"/>cessation of hunger may be produced, without<lb break="yes"/>the substances that are submitted to the<lb break="yes"/>organs of digestion being, properly speaking,<lb break="yes" />nutritive.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is known, that great use is still made in<lb break="yes"/>the East of the bolar and sigillated earths of<lb break="yes"/>Lemnos, which are clay mingled with oxide<lb break="yes"/>of iron. In Germany, the workmen employed<lb break="yes"/>in the quarries of sandstone worked at the<lb break="yes" />mountain of Kiffh&#x00E6;nser, spread a very fine<lb break="yes"/>clay upon their bread instead of butter, which<lb break="yes"/>they call stein butter, stone butter; and they<lb break="yes"/>find it singularly filling, and easy of diges-<lb break="no"/>tion.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Like man in a savage state, some animals<lb break="yes"/>also, when pressed by hunger in winter,<lb break="yes"/>swallow clay or friable steatites: such are the<lb break="yes"/>wolves in the north-east of Europe, the rein-<lb break="no"/>deer, and, according to the testimony of M.<lb break="yes" />Patrin, the kids in Siberia. The Russian<lb break="yes"/>hunters on the banks of the Jenisey and the<lb break="yes"/>Amour use a clayey matter, which they call<lb break="yes"/>rock butter, as a bait. The animals scent<lb break="yes"/>this clay from afar, and are fond of the smell<lb break="yes" />as the clays of Bucaros, known in Portugal<lb break="yes"/>and Spain by the name of odoriferous earths<lb break="yes"/>(tieras olorosas), have an odour agreeable to<lb break="yes"/>women.<note place="foot" n="*">Bucaro, <hi rendition="#i">vas fictile odoriferum.</hi> People are fond<lb break="yes"/>of drinking out of these vessels on account of the<lb break="yes"/>smell of the clay. The women of the province of<lb break="yes"/>Alentejo acquire a habit of chewing the Bucaro earth;<lb break="yes"/>and feel a great privation when they cannot indulge<lb break="yes"/>this vitiated taste.</note> Brown relates, in his History of<lb break="yes"/>Jamaica, that the crocodiles of South Ame-<lb break="no" />rica swallow small stones, and pieces of very<lb break="yes"/>hard wood, when the lakes which they inhabit<lb break="yes"/>are dry, or when they are in want of food.<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;M. Bonpland and I observed in a crocodile<lb break="yes"/>eleven feet long, which we dissected at Ba-<lb break="no" />talley, on the banks of the Rio Magdalena,<lb break="yes"/>that the stomach of this reptile contained fish<lb break="yes"/>half digested, and rounded fragments of gra-<lb break="no"/>nite three or four inches in diameter. It is<lb break="yes"/>difficult to admit that the crocodiles swallow<lb break="yes" />these stony masses accidentally, for they do<lb break="yes"/>not catch fish with their lower jaw resting on<lb break="yes"/>the ground at the bottom of the river. The<lb break="yes"/>Indians have framed the absurd hypothesis<lb break="yes"/>that these indolent animals like to augment<lb break="yes" />their weight, that they may have less trouble<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="563" facs="#f0004"/>
                    <cb/> in diving! I rather think, that they load<lb break="yes"/>their stomach with large pebbles, to excite an<lb break="yes"/>abundant secretion of gastric juice. The<lb break="yes"/>experiments of M. Magendie render this ex-<lb break="no"/>planation extremely probable. With respect<lb break="yes"/>to the habit of the granivorous birds, parti-<lb break="no"/>cularly the gallinace&#x00E6; and ostriches, of swal-<lb break="no"/>lowing sand and small pebbles, it has been<lb break="yes"/>hitherto attributed to an instinctive desire of<lb break="yes"/>accelerating the trituration of the aliments in<lb break="yes"/>a muscular and thick stomach.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 