<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="124" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#b">
                        <hi rendition="#g">THE GUAHIBI MOTHER.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> following affecting story is told by Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt:&#x2014;Where the Atabapo enters the Rio<lb break="yes" />Temi, but before we reached its confluence, a<lb break="yes"/>granitic hummock, that rises on the western<lb break="yes"/>bank, near the mouth of the Guasacavi, is called<lb break="yes"/>the rock of the Guahibi Woman, or the rock of<lb break="yes"/>the Mother Piedra de la Madre. We inquired<lb break="yes" />the cause of so singular a denomination. Father<lb break="yes"/>Zea could not satisfy our curiosity, but some<lb break="yes"/>weeks after, another missionary, one of the pre-<lb break="no"/>decessors of this ecclesiastic, whom we found<lb break="yes"/>settled at San Fernando, as president of the<lb break="yes" />missions, related to us an event which I recorded<lb break="yes"/>in my journal, and which excited in our minds<lb break="yes"/>the most painful feelings. If, in these solitary<lb break="yes"/>scenes, man scarcely leaves behind him any<lb break="yes"/>trace of his existence, it is doubly humiliating<lb break="yes"/>for a European to see perpetuated by the name<lb break="yes"/>of a rock, by one of those imperishable monu-<lb break="no" />ments of nature, the remembrance of the moral<lb break="yes"/>degradation of our species, and the contrast be-<lb break="no"/>tween the virtues of a savage and the barbarism<lb break="yes"/>of civilised man.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the year 1797, the missionary of San Fer-<lb break="no"/>nando had led his
                    Indians to the banks of the<lb break="yes"/>Rio <choice><sic>Guaviave</sic><corr
                            type="editorial">Guaviare</corr></choice>, on one of those hostile
                        incursions<lb break="yes"/>which are prohibited alike by religion and the<lb
                        break="yes"/>Spanish laws. They found in an Indian hut, a<lb break="yes"
                    />Guahibi mother with three children, two of<lb break="yes"/>whom were still
                    infants. They were occupied<lb break="yes"/>in preparing the flour of Cassava:
                        resistance<lb break="yes"/>was impossible; the father was gone to fish,<lb
                        break="yes"/>and the mother tried in vain to flee with her<lb break="yes"
                    />children. Scarcely had she reached the savan-<lb break="no"/>nah, when she was
                    seized by the Indians of the<lb break="yes"/>mission, who go to hunt men, like
                    the whites<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="125" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/> and the negroes in Africa. The mother and her<lb break="yes"/>children
                    were bound, and dragged to the bank<lb break="yes"/>of the river; the monk,
                    seated in his boat,<lb break="yes"/>waited the issue of an expedition, of which
                        he<lb break="yes"/>partook <choice><sic>of</sic><corr type="editorial"
                            >not</corr></choice> the danger. Had the mother made<lb break="yes"/>too
                    violent a resistance, the Indians would have<lb break="yes"/>killed her; for
                    every thing is permitted when<lb break="yes"/>they go to the conquest of souls,
                    and it is chil-<lb break="no"/>dren in particular they seek to capture, in
                        order<lb break="yes"/>to treat them in the mission as poitos, or slaves<lb
                        break="yes"/>of the Christians. The prisoners were carried<lb break="yes"
                    />to San Fernando, in the hope that the mother<lb break="yes"/>would be unable
                    to find her way back to her<lb break="yes"/>home by land. Far from those
                    children who<lb break="yes"/>had accompanied their father on the day in<lb
                        break="yes"/>which she had been carried off, this unhappy<lb break="yes"
                    />woman showed signs of the deepest despair.<lb break="yes"/>She attempted to
                    take back to her family the<lb break="yes"/>children who had been snatched away
                    by the<lb break="yes"/>missionary, and fled with them repeatedly from<lb
                        break="yes"/>the village of San Fernando, but the Indians<lb break="yes"
                    />never failed to seize her anew; and the mis-<lb break="no"/>sionary, after
                    having caused her to be merci-<lb break="no"/>lessly beaten, took the cruel
                    resolution of<lb break="yes"/>separating the mother from the two children<lb
                        break="yes"/>who had been carried off with her. She was<lb break="yes"
                    />conveyed alone towards the mission of the<lb break="yes"
                            /><choice><sic>Negroe</sic><corr type="editorial">Rio
                        Negro</corr></choice>, going up to the Atabapo; slightly<lb break="yes"
                    />bound, she was seated at the bow of the boat,<lb break="yes"/>ignorant of the
                    fate that awaited her; but she<lb break="yes"/>judged by the direction of the
                    sun, that she was<lb break="yes"/>removed farther and farther from her hut,
                        and<lb break="yes"/>her native country. She succeeded in breaking<lb
                        break="yes"/>her bonds, threw herself into the water, and<lb break="yes"
                    />swam to the left bank of the Atabapo; the cur-<lb break="no"/>rent carried her
                    to a shelf of rock, which<lb break="yes"/>bears her name to this day. She
                    landed, and<lb break="yes"/>took shelter in the woods, but the president<lb
                        break="yes"/>of the missions ordered the Indians to row<lb break="yes"/>to
                    shore, and follow the traces of the Guahibi.<lb break="yes"/>In the evening she
                    was brought back, stretched<lb break="yes"/>upon the rock (la Piedra de la
                    Madre), a cruel<lb break="yes"/>punishment was inflicted on her with those<lb
                        break="yes"/>straps of <choice><sic>menatee</sic><corr type="editorial"
                            >manatee</corr></choice> leather which serve for whips<lb break="yes"
                    />in that country, and with which the alcades are<lb break="yes"/>always
                    furnished. This unhappy woman, her<lb break="yes"/>hands tied back with strong
                    stalks of mavacure,<lb break="yes"/>was then dragged to the mission of
                    Javita.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>She was then thrown into one of the caravan-<lb break="no"/>seras, that are
                    called Casa <choice><sic>de Roy</sic><corr type="editorial">del
                        Rey</corr></choice>. It was the<lb break="yes"/>rainy season, and the night
                    was profoundly<lb break="yes"/>dark. Forests, till then believed to be
                        impene-<lb break="no"/>trable, separated the mission of Javita from<lb
                        break="yes"/>that of San Fernando, which was twenty-four<lb break="yes"
                    />leagues distant in a straight line. No other<lb break="yes"/>part is known
                    than that of the rivers; no man<lb break="yes"/>ever attempted to go by land
                    from one village<lb break="yes"/>to another, were they only a few leagues
                        apart;<lb break="yes"/>but such difficulties do not stop a mother who is<lb
                        break="yes"/>separated from her children. Her children are<lb break="yes"
                    />at San Fernando de <choice><sic>Antababe</sic><corr type="editorial"
                            >Atababo</corr></choice>; she must find<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> them again&#x2014;she must execute her project of<lb break="yes"
                    />delivering them from the hands of Christians&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>of
                    bringing them back to their father on the<lb break="yes"/>banks of the
                            <choice><sic>Guaviave</sic><corr type="editorial"
                        >Guaviare</corr></choice>. The Guahibi was<lb break="yes"/>carelessly
                    guarded in the caravansera. Her<lb break="yes"/>arms being wounded, the Indians
                    of Javita<lb break="yes"/>had loosened her bonds, unknown to the mis-<lb
                        break="no"/>sionary and the alcades: she succeeded by the<lb break="yes"
                    />help of her teeth in breaking them entirely;<lb break="yes"/>disappeared
                    during the night, and at the fourth<lb break="yes"/>rising sun, was seen at the
                    mission of San Fer-<lb break="no"/>nando, hovering around the hut where her
                        chil-<lb break="no"/>dren were confined. &#x201C;What that woman per-<lb
                        break="no"/>formed,&#x201D; added the missionary who gave us this<lb
                        break="yes"/>sad narrative, &#x201C;the most robust Indian would<lb
                        break="yes"/>not have ventured to undertake. She traversed<lb break="yes"
                    />the woods at a season when the sky is con-<lb break="no"/>stantly covered with
                    clouds, and the sun, during<lb break="yes"/>whole days, appears but for a few
                    minutes. Did<lb break="yes"/>the course of the waters direct her way? The in-<lb
                        break="no"/>undation of the river forced her to go far from<lb break="yes"
                    />the banks of the main stream, through the<lb break="yes"/>midst of woods,
                    where the movement of the<lb break="yes"/>waters is almost imperceptible. How
                        often<lb break="yes"/>must she have been stopped by the thorny lianas<lb
                        break="yes"/>that form a net-work around the trunks they<lb break="yes"
                    />entwine? How often must she have swam<lb break="yes"/>across the rivulets that
                    run into the Atabapo?<lb break="yes"/>This unfortunate woman was asked how she
                        had<lb break="yes"/>sustained herself during the four days. She said,<lb
                        break="yes"/>&#x2018;that exhausted with fatigue, she could find no<lb
                        break="yes"/>other nourishment than those great black ants<lb break="yes"
                    />called <choice><sic>Vachaos</sic><corr type="editorial"
                        >Vachacos</corr></choice>, which climb the trees in long<lb break="yes"
                    />bands, to suspend on them their resinous nests!&#x2019;&#x201D;<lb break="yes"
                    />We pressed the missionary to tell us, whether<lb break="yes"/>the Guahibi had
                    peacefully enjoyed the happi-<lb break="no"/>ness of remaining with her
                    children, and if any<lb break="yes"/>repentance had followed this excess of
                        cruelty;<lb break="yes"/>but at our return from the Rio
                            <choice><sic>Negroe</sic><corr type="editorial">Negro</corr></choice>,
                        we<lb break="yes"/>learned that the Indian mother was not allowed<lb
                        break="yes"/>time to dress her wounds, but was again sepa-<lb break="no"
                    />rated from her children, and sent to one of the<lb break="yes"/>missions of
                    the Upper Oronoko, where she died,<lb break="yes"/>refusing all kind of
                    nourishment, as the savages<lb break="yes"/>do in great calamities. Such is the
                        remem-<lb break="no"/>brance annexed to the fatal rock &#x201C;Piedra de
                        la<lb break="yes"/>Madre.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 