<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="198" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    HUMBOLDT&#x2019;S PERSONAL NARRATIVE.<lb break="yes"/>
                        (Literary Gazette.)
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Dirt-Eaters.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#in">T</hi>HE inhabitants of Uruana, be-<lb break="no"
                        />long to those <hi rendition="#i">nations of the sa-<lb break="no"
                            />vannahs</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">Indios andantes,</hi>) who, more<lb
                            break="yes"/>difficult to civilize than the <hi rendition="#i">nations
                                of<lb break="yes"/>the forest,</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">Indios del
                            monte,</hi>) have a<lb break="yes"/>decided aversion to cultivate the
                            land,<lb break="yes"/>and live almost exclusively on hunting<lb
                            break="yes"/>and fishing. They are men of very<lb break="yes"/>robust
                        constitution; but ugly, savage,<lb break="yes"/>vindictive, and passionately
                        fond of<lb break="yes"/>fermented liquors. They are omnivo-<lb break="no"
                        />rous <hi rendition="#i">animals</hi> in the highest degree;<lb break="yes"
                        />and therefore the other Indians, who<lb break="yes"/>consider them as
                        barbarians, have a<lb break="yes"/>common saying, &#x2018;nothing is so
                            disgust-<lb break="no"/>ing that an Otomac will not eat it.&#x2019;<lb
                            break="yes"/>While the waters of the Oroonoko and<lb break="yes"/>its
                        tributary streams are low, the Oto-<lb break="no"/>macs subsist on fish and
                        turtles. The<lb break="yes"/>former they kill with surprising dexter-<lb
                            break="no"/>ity, by shooting them with an arrow,<lb break="yes"/>when
                        they appear at the surface of the<lb break="yes"/>water. When the rivers
                        swell, which<lb break="yes"/>in South America as well as in Egypt<lb
                            break="yes"/>and in Nubia, is erroneously attributed<lb break="yes"/>to
                        the melting of the snows, and which<lb break="yes"/>occurs periodically in
                        every part of the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone, fishing almost entirely<lb
                            break="yes"/>ceases. It is then as difficult to pro-<lb break="no"/>cure
                        fish in the rivers which are be-<lb break="no"/>come deeper, as when you are
                            sailing<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> on the open sea. It often fails the poor<lb break="yes"/>missionaries,
                        on fast-days as well as<lb break="yes"/>flesh days, though all the young
                            Indians<lb break="yes"/>are under the obligation of &#x2018;fishing
                            for<lb break="yes"/>the convent.&#x2019; At the period of these<lb
                            break="yes"/>inundations, which lasts two or three<lb break="yes"
                        />months, the Otomacs swallow a prodi-<lb break="no"/>gious quantity of
                        earth. We found<lb break="yes"/>heaps of balls in their huts, piled up in<lb
                            break="yes"/>pyramids three or four feet high. These<lb break="yes"
                        />balls were five or six inches in diame-<lb break="no"/>ter. The earth
                        which the Otomacs eat<lb break="yes"/>is a very fine and unctuous clay, of
                            a<lb break="yes"/>yellowish grey colour; and, being slight-<lb
                            break="no"/>ly baked in the fire, the hardened crust<lb break="yes"/>has
                        a tint inclining to red, owing to the<lb break="yes"/>oxid of iron which is
                        mingled with it.<lb break="yes"/>We brought away some of this earth,<lb
                            break="yes"/>which we took from the winter provis-<lb break="no"/>ion of
                        the Indians; and it is absolutely<lb break="yes"/>false, that it is
                        steatitic, and contains<lb break="yes"/>magnesia. Mr. Vauquelin did not
                            dis-<lb break="no"/>cover any traces of this earth in it; but<lb
                            break="yes"/>he found that it contained more silex than<lb break="yes"
                        />alumin, and three or four per cent of lime.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The Otomacs do not eat every<lb break="yes"/>kind of clay
                        indifferently; they choose<lb break="yes"/>the alluvial beds or strata that
                            contain<lb break="yes"/>the most unctuous earth, and the<lb break="yes"
                        />smoothest to the feel. I inquired of<lb break="yes"/>the missionary,
                        whether the moistened<lb break="yes"/>clay were made to undergo, as
                            Father<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="199" facs="#f0002"/>
                        <cb/> Gumilla asserts, that peculiar decom-<lb break="no"/>position, which
                        is indicated by a dis-<lb break="no"/>engagement of carbonic acid and
                            sul-<lb break="no"/>phuretted hydrogen, and which is de-<lb break="no"
                        />signated in every language by the<lb break="yes"/>term of <hi
                            rendition="#i">putrefaction;</hi> but he assured<lb break="yes"/>us,
                        that the natives neither cause the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">clay</hi> to <hi rendition="#i">rot,</hi> nor do they
                        mingle it with<lb break="yes"/>flour of maize, oil of turtles&#x2019; eggs,
                        or fat<lb break="yes"/>of the crocodile. We ourselves exam-<lb break="no"
                        />ined, both at the Oroonoko and after our<lb break="yes"/>return to Paris,
                        the balls of earth which<lb break="yes"/>we brought away with us, and
                            found<lb break="yes"/>no trace of the mixture of any organic<lb
                            break="yes"/>substance, whether oily or farinaceous.<lb break="yes"/>The
                        savage regards every thing as nour-<lb break="no"/>ishing that appeases
                        hunger; when,<lb break="yes"/>therefore, you inquire of an Otomac on<lb
                            break="yes"/>what he subsists during the two months<lb break="yes"/>when
                        the river is the highest, he shows<lb break="yes"/>you his balls of clayey
                        earth. This he<lb break="yes"/>calls his principal food; for all this pe-<lb
                            break="no"/>riod he can seldom procure a lizard, a<lb break="yes"/>root
                        of fern, or a dead fish swimming at<lb break="yes"/>the surface of the
                        water. If the Indian<lb break="yes"/>eat earth from want during two
                            months,<lb break="yes"/>(and from three quarters to five quar-<lb
                            break="no"/>ters of a pound in twenty-four hours,)<lb break="yes"/>he
                        does not the less regale himself with<lb break="yes"/>it during the rest of
                        the year. Every<lb break="yes"/>day in the season of drought, when fish-<lb
                            break="no"/>ing is most abundant, he scrapes his<lb break="yes"/>balls
                        of <hi rendition="#i">poya,</hi> and mingles a little clay<lb break="yes"
                        />with his other aliment. What is most<lb break="yes"/>surprising is, that
                        the Otomacs do not<lb break="yes"/>become lean by swallowing such quan-<lb
                            break="no"/>tities of earth; they are, on the contra-<lb break="no"/>ry,
                        extremely robust, and far from hav-<lb break="no"/>ing the belly tense and
                        puffed up. The<lb break="yes"/>missionary Fray Ramon Bueno asserts,<lb
                            break="yes"/>that he never remarked any alteration<lb break="yes"/>in
                        the health of the natives at the peri-<lb break="no"/>od of the great
                        risings of the Oroonoko.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The following are the facts in all<lb break="yes"/>their simplicity,
                        which we were able to<lb break="yes"/>verify. The Otomacs during some<lb
                            break="yes"/>months, eat daily three quarters of a<lb break="yes"/>pound
                        of clay slightly hardened by fire,<lb break="yes"/>without their health
                        being materially<lb break="yes"/>affected by it. They moisten the earth<lb
                            break="yes"/>afresh when they are going to swallow<lb break="yes"/>it.
                        It has not been possible to verify<lb break="yes"/>hitherto with precision
                        how much nu-<lb break="no"/>tritious vegetable or animal matter the<lb
                            break="yes"/>Indians take in a week at the same<lb break="yes"/>time;
                        but it is certain that they attri-<lb break="no"/>bute the sensation of
                        satiety which they<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> feel, to the clay, and not to the wretch-<lb break="no"/>ed aliments
                        which they take with it<lb break="yes"/>occasionally. No physiological
                            phe-<lb break="no"/>nomenon being entirely insulated, it<lb break="yes"
                        />may be interesting to examine several<lb break="yes"/>analogous phenomena,
                        which I have<lb break="yes"/>been able to collect.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;I observed every where within the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone, in a
                        great number of indi-<lb break="no"/>viduals, children, women, and some-<lb
                            break="no"/>times even full-grown men, an inordi-<lb break="no"/>nate
                        and almost irresistible desire of<lb break="yes"/>swallowing earth; not an
                        alkaline or<lb break="yes"/>calcareous earth, to neutralize (as it is<lb
                            break="yes"/>vulgarly said) acid juices, but a fat clay,<lb break="yes"
                        />unctuous, and exhaling a strong smell.<lb break="yes"/>It is often found
                        necessary to tie the<lb break="yes"/>children&#x2019;s hands, or to confine
                        them, to<lb break="yes"/>prevent their eating earth when the rain<lb
                            break="yes"/>ceases to fall. At the village of Banco,<lb break="yes"/>on
                        the bank of the river Magdalena, I<lb break="yes"/>saw the Indian women who
                        make pot-<lb break="no"/>tery continually swallowing great pieces<lb
                            break="yes"/>of clay.&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The author goes at some length into<lb break="yes"/>analogies and reasoning
                        on them, but<lb break="yes"/>we confine our quotation principally to<lb
                            break="yes"/>the facts.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The negroes on the coast of Guinea<lb break="yes"/>delight in eating
                        a yellowish earth which<lb break="yes"/>they call <hi rendition="#i"
                            >caouac.</hi> The slaves who are<lb break="yes"/>taken to America try to
                        procure for<lb break="yes"/>themselves the same enjoyment; but it<lb
                            break="yes"/>is constantly detrimental to their health.<lb break="yes"
                        />They say, &#x2018;that the earth of the West<lb break="yes"/>Indies is not
                        so easy of digestion as that<lb break="yes"/>of their
                        country.&#x2019;&#x201D; * * *</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;In the Indian Archipelago, at the<lb break="yes"/>island of Java, Mr.
                        Labillardière saw,<lb break="yes"/>between Surabaya and Samarang, little<lb
                            break="yes"/>square and reddish cakes exposed to<lb break="yes"/>sale.
                        These cakes, called <hi rendition="#i">tanaampo,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>were cakes of clay, slightly baked,<lb break="yes"/>which
                        the natives eat with appetite.<lb break="yes"/>The attention of
                        physiologists, since<lb break="yes"/>my return from the Oroonoko, having<lb
                            break="yes"/>been powerfully fixed on these phenom-<lb break="no"/>ena
                        of <hi rendition="#i">geophagy,</hi> Mr. Leschenault,<lb break="yes"/>(one
                        of the naturalists of the expedition<lb break="yes"/>to the Southern Lands
                        under the com-<lb break="no"/>mand of Captain Baudin) has published<lb
                            break="yes"/>some curious details on the <hi rendition="#i"
                            >tanaampo,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>or <hi rendition="#i">ampo,</hi> of the Javanese.
                        &#x2018;The red-<lb break="no"/>dish and somewhat ferruginous
                            clay,&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>he says, &#x2018;which the inhabitants of
                            Java<lb break="yes"/>are fond of eating occasionally is spread<lb
                            break="yes"/>on a plate of iron, and baked, after<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="200" facs="#f0003"/>
                        <cb/> having been rolled into little cylinders<lb break="yes"/>in the form
                        of the bark of cinnamon.<lb break="yes"/>In this state it takes the name of
                            <hi rendition="#i">ampo,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>and is sold in the public markets. This<lb break="yes"
                        />clay has a peculiar taste, which is owing<lb break="yes"/>to the
                        torrefaction; it is very absorbent,<lb break="yes"/>and adheres to the
                        tongue, which it<lb break="yes"/>dries. In general it is only the Java-<lb
                            break="no"/>nese women who eat the <hi rendition="#i">ampo,</hi>
                            either<lb break="yes"/>in the time of their pregnancy, or in<lb
                            break="yes"/>order to grow thin; the want of plump-<lb break="no"/>ness
                        being a kind of beauty in this<lb break="yes"/>country. The use of this
                        earth is fatal<lb break="yes"/>to health; the women lose their appe-<lb
                            break="no"/>tite imperceptibly, and no longer take<lb break="yes"
                        />without disgust a very small quantity<lb break="yes"/>of food: but the
                        desire of becoming<lb break="yes"/>lean, and of preserving a slender
                            shape,<lb break="yes"/>can brave these dangers, and maintains<lb
                            break="yes"/>the credit of the <hi rendition="#i">ampo.</hi>&#x2019; The
                            savage<lb break="yes"/>inhabitants of New Caledonia also, to<lb
                            break="yes"/>appease their hunger in times of scar-<lb break="no"/>city,
                        eat great pieces of a friable <hi rendition="#i">lapis<lb break="yes"
                            />ollaris.</hi> Mr. Vauquelin analysed this<lb break="yes"/>stone, and
                        found in it, beside magnesia<lb break="yes"/>and silex in equal portions, a
                            small<lb break="yes"/>quantity of oxid of copper. Mr. Gold-<lb
                            break="no"/>berry had seen the negroes in Africa,<lb break="yes"/>in the
                        islands of Bunck and Los Idolos,<lb break="yes"/>eat an earth of which he
                        had himself<lb break="yes"/>eaten, without being incommoded by it,<lb
                            break="yes"/>and which also was a white and friable<lb break="yes"
                        />steatite.&#x201D; * * * * *</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/>
                    <p>&#x201C;When we reflect on the whole of<lb break="yes"/>these facts, we
                        perceive that this disor-<lb break="no"/>derly appetite for clayey,
                            magnesian,<lb break="yes"/>and calcareous earth, is most common<lb
                            break="yes"/>among the people of the torrid zone;<lb break="yes"/>that
                        it is not always a cause of disease;<lb break="yes"/>and that some tribes
                        eat earth from<lb break="yes"/>choice, while others (the Otomacs in<lb
                            break="yes"/>America, and the inhabitants of New<lb break="yes"
                        />Caledonia, in the Pacific Ocean,) eat it<lb break="yes"/>from want, and to
                        appease hunger.&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The observations, which I made on<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the
                        <choice><sic>Oroonoka</sic><corr type="editorial">Oroonoko</corr></choice>, have been<lb break="yes"/>recently confirmed by the direct
                            experi-<lb break="no"/>ments of two distinguished young phy-<lb
                            break="no"/>siologists, Messrs. Hippolite Cloquet<lb break="yes"/>and
                        Breschet. After long fasting, they<lb break="yes"/>ate as much as five
                        ounces of a silvery<lb break="yes"/>green and very fiexible laminar talc.<lb
                            break="yes"/>Their hunger was completely satisfied,<lb break="yes"/>and
                        they felt no inconvenience from a<lb break="yes"/>kind of food, to which
                        their organs were<lb break="yes"/>unaccustomed. It is known that great<lb
                            break="yes"/>use is still made in the East of the bolar<lb break="yes"
                        />and sigillated earths of Lemnos, which<lb break="yes"/>are clay mingled
                        with oxid of iron. In<lb break="yes"/>Germany, the workmen employed in<lb
                            break="yes"/>the quarries of sandstone worked at the<lb break="yes"
                        />mountain of Kiffh&#x00E6;user spread a very<lb break="yes"/>fine clay upon
                        their bread, instead of<lb break="yes"/>butter, which they call <hi
                            rendition="#i">steinbutter,</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="*">&#x201C;This <hi rendition="#i">steinbutter</hi>
                            must not be confounded with the <hi rendition="#i">mountain butter,
                                bergbutter,</hi> which is a saline<lb break="yes"/>substance, owing
                            to a decomposition of aluminous schists.&#x201D;</note>
                        <lb break="yes"/>stone butter; and they find it singularly<lb break="yes"
                        />filling, and easy of digestion.&#x201D;</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 