<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Affection of an indian mother</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:58</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.23</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-22-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-21-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-22-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-23-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-24-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Affection of an indian mother</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1840</date>
          <pubPlace>New York City, New York</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in:&lt;i&gt; The Cabinet of Curiosities, or Wonders of the World Displayed&lt;/i&gt; 2 Bände, New York: Piercy and Reed 1840, Band 2, S. 45–48.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Schmuck: Kapitälchen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="45" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>AFFECTION OF AN INDIAN MOTHER.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">In</hi> India, to prevent the missions from being wholly de-<lb break="no"/>serted, the fathers make hostile incursions into the villages<lb break="yes"/>of the independent Indians, under the name of <hi rendition="#i">entrados</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>which are avowedly undertaken for &#x201C;the conquest of souls,&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>though it is obviously necessary, in the first place, to secure<lb break="yes"/>the bodies. To effect this, the natives are usually attacked<lb break="yes"/>by night in their hovels, and their children seized and car-<lb break="no"/>ried off, to be distributed among the Indians of the missions<lb break="yes"/>as serfs. An affecting instance of maternal tenderness, dis-<lb break="no"/>played on an occasion of this inhuman practice, is related by<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="46" facs="#f0002"/> M. de Humboldt, which he justly observes &#x201C;proves how much<lb break="yes"/>the system calls for the care of the legislator.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In 1797 the missionary of San Fernando had led his<lb break="yes"/>Indians to the banks of the Rio Guaviare, on one of those<lb break="yes"/>hostile incursions, which are prohibited alike by religion and<lb break="yes"/>the Spanish laws. They found in an Indian hut a Guahiba<lb break="yes"/>mother, with three children, two of whom were still infants.<lb break="yes"/>They were occupied in preparing the flour of cassava. Re-<lb break="no"/>sistance was impossible; the father was gone to fish, and the<lb break="yes"/>mother tried in vain to flee with her children. Scarcely had<lb break="yes"/>she reached the savannah when she was seized by the Indians<lb break="yes"/>of the mission, who go to <hi rendition="#i">hunt men</hi>, like the whites and the<lb break="yes" />negroes in Africa. The mother and her children were bound,<lb break="yes"/>and dragged to the bank of the river. The monk, seated in<lb break="yes"/>his boat, waited the issue of an expedition of which he par-<lb break="no"/>took not the danger. Had the mother made too violent a<lb break="yes"/>resistance, the Indians would have killed her, for every thing<lb break="yes"/>is permitted when they go to the conquest of souls (<hi rendition="#i">a la con-<lb break="no" />quista espiritual,</hi>) and it is children in particular they seek<lb break="yes"/>to capture, in order to treat them in the mission as <hi rendition="#i">poitos</hi>, or<lb break="yes"/>slaves of the Christians. The prisoners were carried to San<lb break="yes"/>Fernando, in the hope that the mother would be unable to<lb break="yes"/>find her way back to her home by land. Far from those<lb break="yes"/>children who had accompanied their father on the day in<lb break="yes"/>which she had been carried off, this unhappy woman showed<lb break="yes"/>signs of the deepest despair. She attempted to take back<lb break="yes"/>to her family the children, who had been snatched away by<lb break="yes"/>the missionary, and fled with them repeatedly from the<lb break="yes"/>village of San Fernando; but the Indians never failed to seize<lb break="yes"/>her anew; and the missionary after having caused her to be<lb break="yes"/>mercilessly beaten, took the cruel resolution of separating the<lb break="yes"/>mother from the two children, who had been carried off with<lb break="yes"/>her. She was conveyed alone towards the missions of the Rio<lb break="yes"/>Negro, going up the Atabapo. Slightly bound, she was seated<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="47" facs="#f0003"/> at the bow of the boat, ignorant of the fate that awaited her;<lb break="yes"/>but she judged by the direction of the sun that she was re-<lb break="no"/>moving farther and farther from her hut and her native coun-<lb break="no"/>try. She succeeded in breaking her bonds, threw herself into<lb break="yes"/>the water, and swam to the left bank of the Atabapo. The<lb break="yes"/>current carried her to a shelf of rock, which bears her name<lb break="yes"/>to this day. She landed, and took shelter in the woods, but<lb break="yes"/>the president of the missions ordered the Indians to row to the<lb break="yes"/>shore, and follow the traces of the Guahiba. In the evening<lb break="yes"/>she was brought back. Stretched upon the rock (<hi rendition="#i">la Piedra<lb break="yes"/>de la Madre</hi>,) a cruel punishment was inflicted on her with<lb break="yes"/>those straps of manatee leather, which serve for whips in that<lb break="yes"/>country, and with which the alcades are always furnished.<lb break="yes"/>This unhappy woman, her hands tied behind her back with<lb break="yes"/>strong stalks of <hi rendition="#i" >mavacure</hi>, was then dragged to the mission<lb break="yes"/>of Javita.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>She was there thrown into one of the caravanseras that are<lb break="yes"/>called
                        <hi rendition="#i">Casa del Rey.</hi> It was the rainy season, and the
                        night<lb break="yes"/>was profoundly dark. Forests till then believed to be
                                <choice><sic>impene<lb break="yes"/>trable</sic><corr
                            type="editorial">impene-<lb break="no"/>trable</corr></choice> separated
                    the mission of Javita from that of San <sic>Fer<lb break="yes"/>nando</sic><corr
                        type="editorial">Fer-<lb break="no"/>nando</corr><lb break="yes"/>, which
                    was twenty-five leagues distant in a straight line.<lb break="yes"/>No other
                    path is known than that of the rivers; no man ever<lb break="yes"/>attempted to
                    go by land from one village to another, were<lb break="yes"/>they only a few
                    leagues apart. But such difficulties do not<lb break="yes"/>stop a mother who is
                    separated from her children. The<lb break="yes"/>Guahiba was carelessly guarded
                    in the caravansera. Her<lb break="yes"/>arms being wounded, the Indians of
                    Javita had loosened her<lb break="yes"/>bonds, unknown to the missionary and the
                    alcades. She<lb break="yes"/>succeeded by the help of her teeth, in breaking
                    them entirely,<lb break="yes"/>disappeared during the night, and at the fourth
                    rising sun<lb break="yes"/>was seen at the mission of San Fernando, hovering
                        around<lb break="yes"/>the hut where her children were confined.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;What that woman performed,&#x201D; added the missionary<lb break="yes" />who gave this sad narrative, &#x201C;the most robust Indian would<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="48" facs="#f0004"/> not have ventured to undertake. She traversed the woods<lb break="yes"/>at a season when the sky is constantly covered with clouds,<lb break="yes"/>and the sun during whole days appears but for a few minutes.<lb break="yes"/>Did the course of the waters direct her way? The inunda-<lb break="no"/>tions of the rivers forced her to go far from the banks of the<lb break="yes"/>main stream, through the midst of woods where the movement<lb break="yes"/>of the waters is almost imperceptible. How often must she<lb break="yes"/>have been stopped by the thorny lianas, that form a network<lb break="yes"/>around the trunks they entwine! How often must she have<lb break="yes"/>swam across the rivulets that run into the Atabapo! This<lb break="yes"/>unfortunate woman was asked how she had sustained herself<lb break="yes"/>during four days? She said that exhausted with fatigue, she<lb break="yes"/>could find no other nourishment than those great black ants<lb break="yes"/>called <hi rendition="#i">vachacos</hi>, which climb the trees in long bands, to sus-<lb break="no"/>pend on them their resinous nests.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We pressed the missionary to tell us whether the Guahiba<lb break="yes"/>had peacefully enjoyed the happiness of remaining with her<lb break="yes"/>children, and if any repentance had followed this excess of<lb break="yes"/>cruelty. He would not satisfy our curiosity; but at our<lb break="yes"/>return from the Rio Negro we learnt that the Indian mother<lb break="yes"/>was not allowed time to cure her wounds, but was again sepa-<lb break="no"/>rated from her children, and sent to one of the missions of<lb break="yes"/>the Upper Oroonoko. There she died, refusing all kind of<lb break="yes"/>nourishment, as the savages do in great calamities.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 