<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="2" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>STORIES OF CROCODILES.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/> (From Humboldt&#x2019;s Personal Narrative.)</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When the waters (says Mr. Humboldt) are high,<lb break="yes"/>the river inundates the keys; and it sometimes hap-<lb break="no"/>pens, that even in the town, imprudent men become<lb break="yes"/>the prey of crocodiles. I shall transcribe from my<lb break="yes"/>journal a fact that took place during Mr. Bonpland&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>illness. A Guaykeri Indian, from the island de la<lb break="yes"/>Margaretta, went to anchor his canoe in a cove where<lb break="yes"/>there were not three feet of water. A very fierce cro-<lb break="no"/>codile, that habitually haunted that spot, seized him<lb break="yes"/>by the leg, and withdrew from the shore, remaining<lb break="yes"/>on the surface of the water. The cries of the Indian<lb break="yes"/>drew together a crowd of spectators. This unfortu-<lb break="no"/>nate man was first seen seeking, with astonishing cou-<lb break="no"/>rage, for a knife in the pocket of his pantaloons. Not<lb break="yes"/>being able to find it, he seized the head of the cro-<lb break="no"/>codile, and thrust his fingers into its eyes. No man<lb break="yes"/>in the hot regions of America is ignorant, that this<lb break="yes"/>carnivorous reptile, covered with a buckler of hard<lb break="yes"/>and dry scales, is extremely sensible in the only<lb break="yes"/>parts of his body which are soft and unprotected,<lb break="yes"/>such as the eyes, the hollow underneath the shoul-<lb break="no"/>ders, the nostrils, and beneath the lower jaw, where<lb break="yes"/>there are two glands of musk. The Guaykeri Indian<lb break="yes"/>had recourse to the same means which saved the ne-<lb break="no"/>gro of Mungo Park, and the girl of Uritucu,&#x2014;but he<lb break="yes"/>was less fortunate than they had been, for the croco-<lb break="no"/>dile did not open its jaws, and lose hold of its prey.<lb break="yes"/>The animal, yielding to the pain, plunged to the<lb break="yes" />bottom of the river; and, after having drowned the<lb break="yes"/>Indian, came up to the surface of the water, drag-<lb break="no"/>ging the dead body to an island opposite the port.<lb break="yes"/>I arrived at the moment when a great number of the<lb break="yes"/>inhabitants of Angostura had witnessed this melan-<lb break="no"/>choly spectacle.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As the crocodile, on account of the structure of its<lb break="yes"/>larynx, of the hyoid bone, and of the folds of its<lb break="yes"/>tongue, can seize, though not swallow, its prey under<lb break="yes"/>water; a man seldom disappears without the animal<lb break="yes"/>being perceived some hours after near the spot where<lb break="yes"/>the misfortune has happened, devouring its prey on<lb break="yes"/>a neighbouring beach. The number of individuals<lb break="yes"/>who perish annually, the victims of their own impru-<lb break="no"/>dence and of the ferocity of these reptiles, is much<lb break="yes"/>greater than it is believed to be in Europe. It is par-<lb break="no"/>ticularly so in villages, where the neighbouring<lb break="yes" />grounds are often inundated. The same crocodiles<lb break="yes"/>remain long in the same places. They become from<lb break="yes"/>year to year more daring, especially, as the Indians<lb break="yes"/>assert, if they have once tasted of human flesh.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>These animals are so wary, that they are killed with<lb break="yes"/>difficulty. A ball does not pierce their skin, and the<lb break="yes"/>shot is only mortal when directed at the throat, or<lb break="yes"/>beneath the shoulder. The Indians, who know little<lb break="yes"/>of the use of fire arms, attack the crocodile with lances,<lb break="yes"/>after it is caught with large pointed iron hooks,<lb break="yes"/>baited with pieces of meat, and fastened by a chain<lb break="yes"/>to the trunk of a tree. They do not approach the<lb break="yes" />animal till it has struggled a long time to disengage<lb break="yes"/>itself from the iron fixed in the upper jaw. There is<lb break="yes"/>little probability that a country in which a laby-<lb break="no"/>rinth of rivers, without number, brings every day<lb break="yes"/>new bands of crocodiles from the eastern bank of the<lb break="yes"/>Andes, by the Meta and the Apure, towards the coast<lb break="yes"/>of Spanish Guyana, should ever be delivered from<lb break="yes"/>these reptiles. All that will be gained by civilization<lb break="yes"/>will be, to render them more timid, and more easily<lb break="yes"/>put to flight.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Affecting instances are related of African slaves,<lb break="yes"/>who have exposed their lives to save those of their<lb break="yes"/>masters, who had fallen into the jaws of the crocodile.<lb break="yes"/>A few years ago, between Uritucu and the Mission<lb break="yes"/>de Abaxo, a negro, hearing the cries of his master,<lb break="yes"/>flew to the spot, armed with a long knife (machette)<lb break="yes"/>and plunged into the river. He forced the crocodile,<lb break="yes"/>by putting out his eyes, to let go his prey, and hide<lb break="yes"/>himself under the water. The slave bore his expiring<lb break="yes"/>master to the shore, but all succour was unavailing<lb break="yes"/>to restore him to life. He died of suffocation, for his<lb break="yes"/>wounds were not deep. The crocodile, like the dog,<lb break="yes"/>appears not to close his jaws firmly while swimming.<lb break="yes"/>It is almost superfluous to add, that the children<lb break="yes"/>of the deceased, though poor, gave the slave his<lb break="yes" />freedom.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI> 