<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="201" facs="#f0001" />
<cb/>
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">crocodiles of the oroonoko.</hi></head><lb/><p>&#x201C;When the waters (says M. Humboldt,) are high, the river<lb/>inundates the keys; and it
                    sometimes happens, that even in<lb/>the town imprudent men become the prey of
                    crocodiles. I shall<lb/>transcribe from my journal a fact, that took place
                    during M.<lb/>Bonpland&#x2019;s iliness. A Guaykeri Indian, from the island de
                    la<lb/>Margaretta, went to anchor his canoe in a cove, where there<lb/>was not
                    three feet of water. A very fierce crocodile, that<lb/>habitually haunted that
                    spot, seized him by the leg, and with-<lb/>drew from the shore, remaining on the
                    surface of the water.<lb/>The cries of the Indian drew together a crowd of
                    spectators.<lb/><cb/> This unfortunate man was first seen seeking with
                    astonishing<lb/>courage for a knife in the pocket of his pantaloons. Not
                    being<lb/>able to find it, he seized the head of the crocodile, and
                    thrust<lb/>his fingers into its eyes. No man in the hot regions of
                    America<lb/>is ignorant, that this carnivorous reptile, covered with a
                    buckler<lb/>of hard and dry scales, is extremely sensible in the only
                    parts<lb/>of his body which are soft and unprotected, such as the eyes,<lb/>the
                    hollow underneath the shoulders, the nostrils, and beneath<lb/>the lower jaw,
                    where there are two glands of musk. The<lb/>Guaykeri Indian had recourse to the
                    same means which saved<lb/>the negro of Mungo Park, and a girl of Uritucu; but
                    he was<lb/>less fortunate than they had been, for the crocodile did not
                    open<lb/>its jaws, and lose hold of its prey. The animal, yielding to<lb/>the
                    pain, plunged to the bottom of the river; and, after having<lb/>drowned the
                    Indian, came up to the surface of the water,<lb/>dragging the dead body to an
                    island opposite the port. I<lb/>arrived at the moment when a great number of the
                    inhabitants<lb/>of Angostura had witnessed this melancholy
                    spectacle.&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
