<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    &#x201C;THE ROCK OF THE MOTHER.&#x201D;
                    <lb/>
                    (<hi rendition="#i">From the new Volume of Humboldt.)</hi>
                </head>
                <lb/>
                <p>Where the Atabapo enters the Rio Temi, the<lb/>narrative says:&#x2014;<lb/>Before we reached its confluence, a granatick<lb/>hammock, that rises on the western bank, near<lb/>the mouth of the Guasacavi, fixed our attention;<lb/>it is called the <hi rendition="#i">Rock of the Guahiba woman</hi>,<lb/>or the Rock of the Mother, <hi rendition="#i">Piedra de la Ma-<lb/>dre.</hi> We inquired the cause of so singular a<lb/>denomination. Father Zea<lb/>could not satisfy our<lb/>curiosty; but some weeks after, another mis-<lb/>sionary, one of the predecessors of this eccle-<lb/>siastic, whom we found settled at San Fernando<lb/>as president of the missions, related to us an<lb/>event, which I recorded in my journal, and<lb/>which excited in our minds the most painful<lb/>feelings. If, in these solitary scenes, man<lb/>scarcely leaves behind him any trace of his ex-<lb/>istence, it is doubly humiliating for a European<lb/>to see perpetuated, by the name of a rock by<lb/>one of those imperishable monuments of nature,<lb/>the remembrance of the moral degradation of<lb/>our species, and the contrast between the vir-<lb/>tue of a savage, and the barbarism of civilized<lb/>man!</p>
                <p>In 1797 the missionary of San Fernando had<lb/>led his Indians to the banks of the Rio Gua-<lb/>viare, on one of those hostile incursions, which<lb/>are prohibited alike by religion and the Spanish<lb/>laws. They found in an Italian hut, a Guahi-<lb/>ba mother with three children, two of whom<lb/>were still infants. They were occupied in pre-<lb/>paring the flour of Cassava. Resistance was<lb/>impossible; the father had gone to fish, and the<lb/>mother tried in vain to flee with her children.<lb/>Scarcely had she reached the savannah, when<lb/>she was seized by the Indians of the mission,<lb/>who go to <hi rendition="#i">hunt men</hi>, like the whites and the<lb/>negroes in Africa. The mother and her chil-<lb/>dren were bound, and dragged to the bank of<lb/>the river. The monk, seated in his boat, wait-<lb/>ed the issue of an expedition, of which he par-<lb/>took not the danger. Had the mother made<lb/>too violent a resistance, the Indians would have<lb/>killed her, for every thing is permitted when<lb/>they go to the conquest of souls <hi rendition="#i">(à la conquista<lb/>espiritual.)</hi> and it is children in particular they<lb/>seek to capture, in order to treat them, in the<lb/>mission, as <hi rendition="#i">poitos</hi>, or slaves of the Christians.<lb/>The prisoners were carried to San Fernando in<lb/>the hope that the mother would be unable to<lb/>find her way back to her home by land. Far<lb/>from those children who had accompanied their<lb/>father on the day in which she had been carried<lb/>off, this unhappy woman showed signs of<lb/>the deepest despair. She attempted to take<lb/>back to her family the children who had been<lb/>snatched away by the missionary, and fled with<lb/>them repeatedly from the village of San Fernan-<lb/>do, but the Indians never failed to seize her<lb/>anew; and the missionary, after having caused<lb/>her to be mercilessly beaten, took the cruel re-<lb/>solution of separating the mother from the two<lb/>children, who had been carried off with her.<lb/>She was conveyed alone toward the missions of<lb/>the Rio Negro, going up the Atabapo. Slightly<lb/>bound, she was seated at the bow of the boat,<lb/>
  <cb/> 
                    ignorant of the fate that awaited her; but she<lb/>judged from the direction of the sun, that she<lb/>was removed farther and farther from her hut<lb/>and her native country. She succeeded in break-<lb/>ing her bonds, threw herself into the water, and<lb/>swam to the left bank of the Atabapo. The<lb/>current carried her to a shelf of rock, which<lb/>bears her name to this day. She landed, and<lb/>took shelter in the woods, but the president of<lb/>the missions ordered the Indians to row to the<lb/>shore, and and follow the traces of the Guahibi.<lb/>In the evening she was brought back. Stretched<lb/>upon the rock (<hi rendition="#i">la Piedra de la Madre</hi>) a cruel<lb/>punishment was inflicted on her with those straps<lb/>of manatee leather, which serves for whips in<lb/>that country, and with which the alcades are<lb/>always furnished. This unhappy woman, her<lb/>hands tied behind her back with strong stalks<lb/>of <hi rendition="#i">mavacure</hi>, was then dragged to the mission<lb/>of Javita.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>&#x201C;She was there thrown into one of the ca-<lb/>ravanseras that are called <hi rendition="#i">Casa del Rey</hi>. It<lb/>was the rainy season, and the night was pro-<lb/>foundly dark. Forests, till then believed to be<lb/>impenetrable, separated the mission of Javita<lb/>from that of San Fernando, which was 25 leagues<lb/>distant in a straight line. Not one part is known<lb/>than that of the rivers? no man ever attempted<lb/>to go by land from one village to another, were<lb/>they only a few leagues apart. But such diffi-<lb/>culties do not stop a mother, who is separated<lb/>from her children. Her children are at San<lb/>Fernando de Atabapo; she must find them<lb/>again, she must execute her project of deliver-<lb/>ing them from the hands of Christians, of<lb/>bringing them back to their father on the banks<lb/>of the Guaviare. The Guahibi was carelessly<lb/>guarded in the caravansera. Her arms being<lb/>wounded, the Indians of Javita had loosened her<lb/>bonds, unknown to the missionary and the al-<lb/>caldes. She succeeded by the help of her teeth<lb/>in breaking them entirely; disappeared during<lb/>the night; and at the fourth rising sun was seen<lb/>at the mission of San Fernando, hovering around<lb/>the hut where her children were confined,<lb/>&#x2018;what that woman performed,&#x2019; added the Mis-<lb/>sionary who gave us this sad narrative, &#x2019;the<lb/>most robust Indian would not have ventured to<lb/>undertake. She traversed the woods at a sea-<lb/>son when the sky is constantly covered with<lb/>clouds, and the sun during whole days ap-<lb/>pears but for a few minutes. Did the course of<lb/>the waters direct her way? the inundations of<lb/>the river forced her to go from the banks of the<lb/>main stream, through the midst of woods where<lb/>the movement of the waters is almost imper-<lb/>ceptible. How often must she have been stop-<lb/>ped by the thorny lianas, that form a network<lb/>around the trunks they entwine? How often<lb/>must she have swam across the rivulets, that ran<lb/>into the Atabapo! This unfortunate woman was<lb/>asked how she had sustained herself during<lb/>the four days! She said, that, exhausted with<lb/>fatigue, she could find no other nourishment<lb/>than those great black ants called <hi rendition="#i">vachacos</hi>,<lb/>which climb the trees in long bands, to sus-<lb/>pend on them their resinous nests.&#x2019; We pres-<lb/>sed the Missionary to tell us, whether the Gua-</p>
                <cb/>
                <p>hibi had peacefully enjoyed the happiness of<lb/>remaining with her children; and if any repent-<lb/>ance had followed this excess of cruelty.&#x2014;<lb/>He would not satisfy our curiosity; but at<lb/>our return from the Rio Negro we learned<lb/>that the Indian mother was not allowed to cure<lb/>her wounds, but was again separated from her<lb/>children, and sent to one of the missions of the<lb/>upper Oronooko. There she died, refusing all<lb/>kind of nourishment, as the savages do in great<lb/>calamities.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;Such is the remembrance annexed to this<lb/>fatal rock, to <hi rendition="#i">Piedra de la Madre.</hi>&#x201D;
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>