<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#c">From the Personal Narrative of Baron Humboldt.</hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">SAVAGES ON THE ORONOKO.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Among the causes of the depopulation<lb break="yes"/>of the Raudales, I have not rockoned the<lb break="yes"/>small pox; that malady which, in other<lb break="yes"/>parts of America, makes such cruel rava-<lb break="no"/>ges, that the natives, seized with dismay,<lb break="yes"/>burn their huts, kill their children, and re-<lb break="no"/>nounce every kind of society.<note place="foot" n="*">As the Mabas in the plans of the Miszoury, according<lb break="yes"/>to the accounts of the American travel@ers, Clark and<lb break="yes"/>Lewis.</note> This<lb break="yes"/>scourge is almost unknown on the banks of<lb break="yes"/>the Oronoko What depopulates the Chris-<lb break="no"/>tian settlements is, the repugnance of the<lb break="yes"/>Indians for the regulations of the missions,<lb break="yes" />the insalubrity of a climate at once hot and<lb break="yes"/>damp, bad nourishment, want of care in the<lb break="yes"/>diseases of children, and the guilty prac-<lb break="no"/>tice of mothers of preventing pregnancy<lb break="yes"/>by the use of deleterious herbs. Among<lb break="yes"/>the barbarous people of Guyana, as well as<lb break="yes"/>those of the half-civilized islands of the<lb break="yes"/>South Sea, young wives will not become<lb break="yes"/>mothers. If they have children, their off-<lb break="no"/>spring are exposed, not only to the dangers<lb break="yes"/>of @avage@life, but also to the dangers ari-<lb break="no"/>sing from the strongest popular prejudices.<lb break="yes"/>When twins are born, false notions of pro-<lb break="no"/>priety and family honor require, that one of<lb break="yes"/>them should be destroyed. &#x2018;To bring twins<lb break="yes" />into the world, is to be exposed to public<lb break="yes"/>scorn; it is to resemble rats, opossums, and<lb break="yes"/>the vilest animals, which bring forth a great<lb break="yes"/>number of young at a time.&#x2019; Nay more:<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;two children born at the same time cannot<lb break="yes"/>belong to the same father.&#x2019; This is an ax-<lb break="no" />iom of physiology of the Salivas; and in ev-<lb break="no"/>ery zone, and in different states of society,<lb break="yes"/>when the vulgar seize upon an axiom, they<lb break="yes"/>adhere to it with more stedfastness than the<lb break="yes"/>better informed men, by whom it was first<lb break="yes" />hazarded. To avoid a disturbance of conju-<lb break="no"/>gal tranquillity, the old female relations of<lb break="yes"/>the mother, or the <hi rendition="#i">mure jappoice-nei</hi> [mid-<lb break="no"/>wives,] take care, that one of the twins shall<lb break="yes"/>disappear. If the new-born infant, though<lb break="yes"/>not a twin, have any physical deformity, the<lb break="yes"/>father instantly puts it to death. They will<lb break="yes" />have only rohust and well-made children,<lb break="yes"/>for deformities indicate some influ@ce of the<lb break="yes"/>evil spirit Ioloquiamo, or the bird <hi rendition="#i">Tikitiki</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>the enemy of the human race. Sometimes<lb break="yes"/>children of a feeble constitution undergo<lb break="yes"/>the same fate. When the father is asked,<lb break="yes"/>what is become of one of his sons, he will<lb break="yes"/>pretend that he has lost him by a natural<lb break="yes"/>death. He will disavow an action, that ap-<lb break="no"/>pears to him blameable, but not criminal.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The poor <hi rendition="#i">mure</hi>,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">In T@</note>&#x201D; he will tell you, &#x2018;could<lb break="yes"/>not follow us; we must have waited for him<lb break="yes"/>every moment; he has not been seen again,<lb break="yes"/>he did not come to sleep where we passed<lb break="yes"/>the night.&#x2019; Such is the <hi rendition="#i">candour</hi> and simpli-<lb break="no"/>city of manners, such the boasted happiness<lb break="yes"/>of man in the <hi rendition="#i">stats of nature</hi>! He kills his<lb break="yes"/>son, to escape the ridicule of having twins,<lb break="yes"/>or, to avoid journeying more slowly; in fact,<lb break="yes" />to avoid a little inconvenience.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The Indians of Aturcs,&#x201D; [says Mr. H.,]<lb break="yes"/>are mild, moderate, and accustomed, from<lb break="yes"/>the effects of their idleness, to the greatest<lb break="yes"/>privations. Formerly, excited to labour by<lb break="yes"/>the Jesuits, they did not want for food. The<lb break="yes" />fathers cultivated maize, French beans, (<hi rendition="#i">fri-<lb break="no" />soles</hi>) and other European vegetables; they<lb break="yes"/>even planted sweet oranges and tamarinds<lb break="yes"/>round the villages; and they possessed twen-<lb break="no"/>ty or thirty thousand head of cows and hor-<lb break="no"/>ses, in the savannahs of Atures and Carich-<lb break="no"/>ana. They had at their service a great<lb break="yes"/>number of slaves and servants [<hi rendition="#i">peones</hi>], to<lb break="yes"/>take care of their herds. Nothing is now<lb break="yes"/>cultivated but a little cassava, and a few<lb break="yes"/>plantains. The fertility of the soil however<lb break="yes"/>is such, that at Atures I counted on a single<lb break="yes" />branch of musa 108 fruits, 4 or 5 of which<lb break="yes"/>would almest suffice for the daily nourish-<lb break="no"/>ment of a man. The culture of maize is<lb break="yes"/>entirely neglected, and the horses and cows<lb break="yes"/>have disappeared. Near the <hi rendition="#i">raudal</hi>, a part<lb break="yes"/>of the village still bears the name of <hi rendition="#i">passo<lb break="yes"/>del ganado</hi> (ford of the cattle) while the de-<lb break="no"/>scendants of those very Indians, whom the<lb break="yes"/>Jesuits had assembled in a mission, speak of<lb break="yes" />herned cattle as of animals of a race that is<lb break="yes"/>lost. In going up the Oronoko, toward San<lb break="yes"/>Carlos del Rio Negro, we saw the last cow<lb break="yes"/>at Carichana. The fathers of the Obser-<lb break="no" />vance, who now govern these vast coun-<lb break="no"/>tries, did not immediately succeed the<lb break="yes"/>Jesuits. During an interregnum of eigh-<lb break="no"/>teen years the missions@ were visited only<lb break="yes"/>from time to time, and by Capuchin monks.<lb break="yes"/>The agents of the secular government, un-<lb break="no"/>der the title of <hi rendition="#i">Commissioners of the King</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>managed the <hi rendition="#i">hatos</hi> or faims of the Jesuits<lb break="yes"/>with culpable negligence. They killed the<lb break="yes"/>cattle is order to sell the hides. Many<lb break="yes"/>heifers were devoured by tigers, and a<lb break="yes"/>greater number perished in consequence of<lb break="yes" />wounds made by the bats of the <hi rendition="#i">raudales</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>which are much less, but far bolder than<lb break="yes"/>the bats of the Llanos. At the time of the<lb break="yes"/>expedition of the boundaries, the horses of<lb break="yes"/>Encaramada, Carichana, and Atures, were<lb break="yes"/>conveyed as far as San Jose of Maravita-<lb break="no" />nos, where, on the banks of the Rio Negro,<lb break="yes"/>the Portugueze could only procure them af-<lb break="no"/>ter a long passage, and of a very inferior<lb break="yes"/>quality, by the river Amazon and Grand<lb break="yes"/>Para. Since the year 1795, the cattle of<lb break="yes"/>the Jesuits have entirely disappeared.<lb break="yes"/>There now remains in testimony of the an-<lb break="no"/>cient cultivation of these countries, and the<lb break="yes"/>industrious activity of the first missionaries,<lb break="yes"/>only a few trunks of the orange and tama-<lb break="no"/>rind in the savannahs, surrounded by wild<lb break="yes"/>trees.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The tigers, or jaguars, which are less<lb break="yes"/>dangerous for the cattle than the bats,<lb break="yes"/>come into the village at Atures, and devour<lb break="yes"/>the pigs of the poor Indians. The mission-<lb break="no"/>ary related to us a striking instance of the<lb break="yes" />familiarity of these animals, upon the whole<lb break="yes"/>so ferocious. Some months before our ar-<lb break="no"/>rival, a jaguar, which was thought to be<lb break="yes"/>young, though of a large size, had wounded<lb break="yes" />a child in playing with him; I use confi-<lb break="no"/>dently this expression, which may seem<lb break="yes"/>strange, having on the spot verified facts<lb break="yes"/>which are not without interest in the his-<lb break="no"/>tory of the manners of animals. Two In-<lb break="no"/>dian children, a boy and a girl, about eight<lb break="yes"/>and nine years of age, were seated on the<lb break="yes"/>grass near the village of Atures, in the mid-<lb break="no"/>dle of a savannah, which we have often<lb break="yes" />traversed. At two o&#x2019;clock in the afternoon,<lb break="yes"/>a jaguar issued from the forest, and ap-<lb break="no"/>proached the children, bounding around<lb break="yes"/>them; sometimes he hid himself in the high<lb break="yes"/>grass, sometimes he sprang forward, his<lb break="yes"/>back bent, his head hung down, in the man-<lb break="no"/>ner of our cats. The little boy, ignorant<lb break="yes"/>of his danger, seemed to be sensible of it<lb break="yes"/>only when the jaguar with one of his paws<lb break="yes"/>gave him some blows on the head. These<lb break="yes"/>blows, at first slight, became ruder and<lb break="yes"/>ruder; the claws of the jaguar wounded<lb break="yes" />the child, and the blood flowed with vio-<lb break="no"/>lence. The little girl then took a branch<lb break="yes"/>of a tree, struck the animal, and it fled<lb break="yes"/>from her. The Indians ran up at the cries<lb break="yes"/>of the children, and saw the jaguar, which<lb break="yes" />retired bounding, without the least show of<lb break="yes"/>resistance.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The little boy was brought to us, who<lb break="yes"/>appeared lively and intelligent. The claw<lb break="yes"/>of the jaguar had taken away the skin from<lb break="yes"/>the lower part of the forehead, and there<lb break="yes"/>was a second scar at the top of the head.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Among the monkies,&#x201D; the author con-<lb break="no"/>tinues, &#x201C;which we saw at the mission of<lb break="yes"/>the Atures, we found one new species, of<lb break="yes"/>the tribe of <hi rendition="#i">sais</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">sajous</hi>, which the Cre-<lb break="no"/>oles vulgarly call <hi rendition="#i">machis.</hi> It is the <hi rendition="#i">ouara-<lb break="no"/>pavi</hi> with grey hair and a bluish face. It<lb break="yes"/>has the orbits of the eyes and forehead as<lb break="yes" />white as snow, which at first sight distin-<lb break="no"/>guishes it from the <hi rendition="#i">simia capucina</hi>, the <hi rendition="#i">simia<lb break="yes"/>apella</hi>, the <hi rendition="#i">simia trepida</hi>, and the other<lb break="yes"/>weeping monkeys bitherto so confusedly<lb break="yes" />described.&#x2014;This little animal is as gentle<lb break="yes"/>as it is ugly.&#x2014;Every day in the court-yard<lb break="yes"/>of the missionary it seized a pig, upon which<lb break="yes"/>it remained from morning till night, tra-<lb break="no"/>versing the savannahs. We have also seen<lb break="yes" />it upon the back of a large cat, which had<lb break="yes"/>been brought up with it in father Zea&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>house.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;It was among the cataracts that we<lb break="yes"/>began to hear of the hairy man of the<lb break="yes"/>woods, called salvaje, that carries off wo-<lb break="no"/>men, constructs huts, and sometimes eats<lb break="yes"/>human flesh. The Tamanacles call it <hi rendition="#i">achi</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>and the Maypures <hi rendition="#i">vasitri</hi>, or <hi rendition="#i">great devil.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>The natives and the missionaries have no<lb break="yes"/>doubt of the existence of this anthropomor-<lb break="no"/>phous monkey, which they singularly dread.<lb break="yes"/>Father Gili gravely relates the history of a<lb break="yes"/>lady in the town of San Carlos, who much<lb break="yes" />praised the gentle character and attentions<lb break="yes"/>of the man of the woods. She lived several<lb break="yes"/>years with one in great domestic harmony,<lb break="yes"/>and only requested some hunters to take<lb break="yes"/>her back &#x2018;because she was tired, she and<lb break="yes" />her children, (a little hairy also,) of living<lb break="yes"/>far from the church and the sacraments.&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>The same author, notwithstanding his cre-<lb break="no"/>dulity, confesses, that he had not been able<lb break="yes"/>to find an Indian who asserted positively<lb break="yes"/>that he had seen the <hi rendition="#i">salraje</hi> with his own<lb break="yes"/>eyes. This fable, which the missionaries,<lb break="yes" />the European planters, and the negroes of<lb break="yes"/>Africa, have no doubt embellished with ma-<lb break="no"/>ny features taken from the description of<lb break="yes"/>the manners of the ourang outang, the gib-<lb break="no" />bon, the jocko or chimpanzec, and the pon-<lb break="no"/>go, pursued us during five years from the<lb break="yes"/>northern to the southern hemisphere; and<lb break="yes"/>we were every where blamed, in the most<lb break="yes" />cultivated class of society, for being the<lb break="yes"/>only persons to doubt the existence of the<lb break="yes"/>groat anthropomorphous monkey of Ameri-<lb break="no"/>ca. We shall first observe, that there are<lb break="yes"/>certain regions where this belief is particu-<lb break="no" />larly prevalent among the people; such are<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the Upper Oronoko, the val-<lb break="no"/>ley of Upar near the lake of Maracaybo,<lb break="yes"/>the mountains of Santa Martha and of Me-<lb break="no"/>rida, the provinces of Quixos, and the banks<lb break="yes"/>of the Amazon near Tomependa. In all<lb break="yes"/>these places, so distant one from the other,<lb break="yes"/>it is repeafed, that the <hi rendition="#i" >salraje</hi> is casily re-<lb break="no"/>cognized by the traces of his feet, the toes<lb break="yes"/>of which are turned backward. But if<lb break="yes"/>there exist a monkey of a large size in the<lb break="yes"/>New Continent, how has it happened that<lb break="yes"/>during three centuries no man worthy of<lb break="yes"/>belief has been able to procure the skin of<lb break="yes"/>one? Several hypotheses present them-<lb break="no"/>selves to the mind in order to explain the<lb break="yes"/>source of so ancient an error or belief. Has<lb break="yes"/>the famous <hi rendition="#i">capuchin</hi> monkey of Esmeralda,<lb break="yes"/>the canine teeth of which are more than<lb break="yes"/>six lines and a half long, the physiognomy<lb break="yes"/>much more like man&#x2019;s than that of the ou-<lb break="no"/>rang outang, and which, when irritated,<lb break="yes"/>rubs its beard with its hand, given rise to<lb break="yes"/>the fable of the <hi rendition="#i">salraje?</hi> It is not so large<lb break="yes"/>indeed as the coaita (<hi rendition="#i">simia paniscus</hi>,) but<lb break="yes"/>when seen at the top of a tree, and the<lb break="yes"/>head only visible, it might easily be taken<lb break="yes"/>for a human being. It may be also (and<lb break="yes"/>this opinion appears to me the most proba-<lb break="no"/>ble) that the man of the woods was one of<lb break="yes"/>those large bears, the footsteps of which<lb break="yes"/>resemble those of a man, and which is be-<lb break="no"/>lieved in every country to attack women.<lb break="yes"/>The animal killed in my time at the foot of<lb break="yes"/>the mountains of Merida, and sent by the<lb break="yes"/>name of <hi rendition="#i">salvaje</hi> to Colonel Ungaro, the<lb break="yes"/>governor of the province Varinas, was in<lb break="yes" />fact a bear, with black and smooth fur.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These extraordinary accounts are suc-<lb break="no"/>ceeded by a detailed history of the Mes-<lb break="no"/>chettoes of this region; perhaps the most<lb break="yes"/>remarkable of all its animal phenomena.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Persons who have not navigated the<lb break="yes"/>great rivers of equinoctial America, for in-<lb break="no"/>stance, the Oronoko and the Rio Magdale-<lb break="no"/>na, can scarcely conceive, how without in-<lb break="no"/>terruntion, at every instant of life, you may<lb break="yes"/>be tormented by insects flying in the air,<lb break="yes"/>and how the multitude of these little an-<lb break="no"/>imals may render vast regions wholly unin-<lb break="no"/>habitable. However accustomed you may<lb break="yes"/>be to endure pain without complaint, how-<lb break="no"/>ever lively an interest you may take in the<lb break="yes"/>objects of your researches, it is impossible<lb break="yes"/>not to be constantly disturbed by the mos-<lb break="no" />chettoes, <hi rendition="#i">zanchdoes, jojens</hi>, and <hi rendition="#i" >tempraner-<lb break="no"/>oes</hi>, that cover the face and hands, pierce<lb break="yes"/>the clothes with their long suckers in the<lb break="yes"/>form of a needle, and, getting into the<lb break="yes"/>mouth and nostrils, set you coughing and<lb break="yes"/>sneezing whenever you attempt to speak in<lb break="yes"/>the open air. In the missions of the Oro-<lb break="no"/>noko, in the villages placed on the banks of<lb break="yes"/>the river, surrounded by immense forests,<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i" >plaga de las moscas</hi>, the plague of the<lb break="yes"/>flies, affords an inexhaustible subject of<lb break="yes"/>conversation. When two persons meet in<lb break="yes"/>the morning, the first questions they address<lb break="yes"/>to each other are, &#x2018;How did you find the<lb break="yes" />@ during the night? How are we<lb break="yes"/>to-day for the moschettoes?@ These ques-<lb break="no"/>tions remind us of a Chinese form of polite-<lb break="no"/>ness, which indicates the ancient state of<lb break="yes"/>the country where it took birth. Salutations<lb break="yes"/>were made heretofore in the <hi rendition="#i">celestial empire</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>in the following words, <hi rendition="#i">vou-@ou-hou</hi>, &#x2018;Have<lb break="yes"/>you been incommoded in the night by the<lb break="yes"/>serpents?&#x2019; We shall soon see, that on the<lb break="yes"/>banks of the Tuamini, in the river Magda-<lb break="no"/>lena, and still more at Choco, the country<lb break="yes"/>of gold and platina, the Chinese compliment<lb break="yes"/>on the serpents might be added to that of<lb break="yes"/>the moschettoes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;At Mandavaca we found an old Mis-<lb break="no"/>sionary, who told us with an air of sadness,<lb break="yes"/>that he had spent <hi rendition="#i">his twenty years of mos-<lb break="no"/>chettoes</hi> in America. He desired us to look<lb break="yes"/>well at his legs, that we might be able to tell<lb break="yes"/>one day, &#x2018;poor alla (beyond sea,) what the<lb break="yes"/>poor monks suffer in the forests of Cassiqui-<lb break="no" />are.&#x2019; Every sting leaving a small darkish<lb break="yes"/>brown point, his legs were so speckled, that<lb break="yes"/>it was difficult to recognize the whiteness<lb break="yes"/>of his skin through the spots of coagulated<lb break="yes"/>blood. If the insects of the simulium ge-<lb break="no"/>nus abound in the Cassiquiare, which has<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">white waters</hi>, the culices, or <hi rendition="#i" >zancudoes</hi>, are<lb break="yes"/>so much the more rare; you scarcely find<lb break="yes"/>any there, while on the rivers of <hi rendition="#i" >black wa-<lb break="no"/>lers</hi>, in the Ata@apo and the Rio Negro,<lb break="yes"/>there are generally some <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi> and no<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">moschettoes.</hi>&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 