<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">The rock of the Guahiba woman</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:58</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.23</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-02-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-02-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-21-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-22-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-23-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-24-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent&lt;/i&gt;, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 2, S. 410–412.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">The rock of the Guahiba woman</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1821</date>
          <pubPlace>Belfast</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Belfast Commercial Chronicle&lt;/i&gt; 2562 (11. Juli 1821), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" /><lb/>
<div n="1"><head>THE ROCK OF THE GUAHIBA WOMAN.</head><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">(From the newly published volume of Humboldt&#x2019;s
                            Travels.)</hi></hi></p><lb/><p>Before we reached the junction of the Atabapo<lb/>with the Rio Temi, a granitic hummock, that
                    rises<lb/>on the western bank, near the mouth of the Guasa-<lb/>cavi, fixed our
                    attention: it is called the Rock of<lb/>the Guahiba woman, or the Rock of the
                        Mother,<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Piedra de la Madre.</hi> We inquired the
                    cause of so<lb/>singular a denomination. Father Zea could not sa-<lb/>tisfy our
                    curiosity; but some weeks after, another<lb/>missionary, one of the predecessors
                    of this ecclesias-<lb/>tic, whom we found settled at San Fernando as
                    pre-<lb/>sident of the missions, related to us an event, which<lb/>I recorded in
                    my Journal, and which excited in our<lb/>minds the most painful feelings. If, in
                    these solitary<lb/>scenes, man scarcely leaves behind him any trace of<lb/>his
                    existence, it is doubly humiliating for a European<lb/>to see perpetuated by the
                    name of a rock, by one<lb/>of those imperishable monuments of nature, the
                    re-<lb/>membrance of the moral degradation of our species,<lb/>and the contrast
                                between the virtue of a savage, and<lb/>the barbarism of civilized man!</p><lb/><p>In 1797 the missionary of San Fernando had<lb/>led his Indians to the banks of the Rio
                    Guaviare,<lb/>on one of those hostile incursions, which are pro-<lb/>hibited
                    alike by religion and the Spanish laws.&#x2014;<lb/>They found in an <choice>
                        <sic>Italian</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Indian</corr>
                    </choice> hut, a Guahiba mother<lb/>with three children, two of whom were still
                    in-<lb/>fants. They were occupied in preparing the<lb/>flour of Cassava.
                    Resistance was impossible; the<lb/>father was gone to fish, and the mother tried
                    in<lb/>vain to flee with her children. Scarcely had she<lb/>reached the
                    Savannah, when she was seized by the<lb/>Indians of the mission, who go to <hi
                        rendition="#i">hunt men,</hi> like<lb/>the whites and the negroes in Africa.
                    The mo-<lb/>ther and her children were bound, and dragged<lb/>to the bank of the
                    river. The monk, seated in<lb/>his boat, waited the issue of an expedition,
                    of<lb/>which he partook not the danger. Had the mo-<lb/>ther made too violent a
                    resistance, the Indians<lb/>would have killed her, for every thing is
                    permit-<lb/>ted when they go in the conquest of souls <hi rendition="#i">(a
                        la<lb/>conquista espiritual,)</hi> and it is children in particu-<lb/>lar
                    they seek to capture, in order to treat them,<lb/>in the mission, as <hi
                        rendition="#i">poitos,</hi> or slaves of the Chris-<lb/>tians. The prisoners
                    were carried to San Fer-<lb/>nando in the hope, that the mother would
                    be<lb/>unable to find her way back to her home, by<lb/>land. Far from those
                    children who had accom-<lb/>panied their father on the day in which she
                    had<lb/>been carried off, this unhappy woman showed<lb/>signs of the deepest
                    despair. She attempted to<lb/>take back to her family the children who
                    had<lb/>been snatched away by the missionary, and fled<lb/>with them repeatedly
                    from the village of San<lb/>Fernando, but the Indians never failed to
                    seize<lb/>her anew; and the missionary, after having caused<lb/>her to be
                    mercilessly beaten, took the cruel re-<lb/>solution of separating the mother
                    from the two<lb/>children, who had been carried off with her. She<lb/>was
                    conveyed alone towards the missions of Rio<lb/>Negro, going up the Atabapo.
                    Slightly bound,<lb/>she was seated at the bow of the boat, ignorant<lb/>of the
                    fate that awaited her; but she judged, by<lb/>the direction of the sun, that she
                    was removed<lb/>farther and farther from her hut and her native<lb/>country. She
                    succeeded in breaking her bonds,<lb/>threw herself into the water, and swam to
                    the<lb/>left bank of the Atabapo. The current carried<lb/>her to a shelf of
                    rock, which bears her name to<lb/>this day. She landed and took shelter in
                    the<lb/>woods, but the president of the missions ordered<lb/>the Indians to row
                    to the shore, and follow the<lb/>traces of the Guahiba. In the evening she
                    was<lb/>brought back.&#x2014;Stretched upon the rock <hi rendition="#i"
                        >(la<lb/>Piedra de la Madre)</hi> a cruel punishment was in-<lb/>flicted on
                    her with those straps of manatee lea-<lb/>ther, which serve for whips in that
                    country, and<lb/>with which the alcades are always furnished.&#x2014;<lb/>This
                    unhappy woman, her hands tied behind her<lb/><pb facs="#f0002"/> back with
                    strong stalks of <hi rendition="#i">mavacure,</hi> was then<lb/>dragged to the
                    mission of Javita.</p><lb/><p>She was thrown into one of the caravanseras that<lb/>are called <hi rendition="#i">Casa del
                        Rey.</hi> It was the rainy sea-<lb/>son, and the night was profoundly dark.
                    Forests,<lb/>till then believed to be impenetrable, separated the<lb/>mission of
                    Javita from that of San Fernando, which<lb/>was twenty-five leagues distant in a
                    straight line.&#x2014;<lb/>No other part is known than that of the rivers;
                    no<lb/>man ever attempted to go by land from one village<lb/>to another, were
                    they only a few leagues apart.&#x2014;<lb/>But such difficulties do not stop a
                    mother, who is<lb/>separated from her children. Her children are at<lb/>San
                    Fernando de Atabapo; she must find them<lb/>again, she must execute her project
                    of delivering<lb/>them from the hands of Christians of bringing them<lb/>back to
                    their father on the banks of the Guaviare.<lb/>The Guahibi was carelessly
                    guarded in the cara-<lb/>vansera. Her arms being wounded, the Indians
                    of<lb/>Javita had loosened her bonds, unknown to the<lb/>missionary and the
                    alcades. She succeeded by the<lb/>help of her teeth in breaking them entirely;
                    dis-<lb/>appeared during the night; and at the fourth rising<lb/>sun was seen at
                    the mission of San Fernando, ho-<lb/>vering around the hut where her children
                    were con-<lb/>fined. &#x201C;What that woman performed,&#x201D; added
                    the<lb/>missionary who gave us this sad narrative, &#x201C;the<lb/>mast robust
                    Indian would not have ventured to<lb/>undertake. She traversed the words at the
                    season<lb/>when the sky is constantly covered with clouds, and<lb/>the sun
                    during whole days appears but for a few<lb/>minutes. Did the course of the
                    waters direct her<lb/>way? The inundations of the rivers forced her to<lb/>go
                    far from the banks of the main stream, through<lb/>the midst of woods where the
                    movement of the<lb/>waters is almost imperceptible. How often must<lb/>she have
                    been stopped by the thorny lianas, that<lb/>form a network around the trunks
                    they entwine?<lb/>How often must she have swam across the rivulets,<lb/>that run
                    into the Atabapo! This unfortunate<lb/>woman was asked how she had sustained
                    herself<lb/>during the four days! She said, that exhausted<lb/>with fatigue, she
                    could find no other nourishment<lb/>than those great black ants called <hi
                        rendition="#i">vachacos,</hi> which<lb/>climb the trees in long bands, to
                    suspend on them<lb/>their resinous nests.&#x201D; We pressed the
                    missionary<lb/>to tell us, whether the Guahiba had peacefully en-<lb/>joyed the
                    happiness of remaining with her children;<lb/>and if any repentance had followed
                    this excess of<lb/>cruelty. He would not satisfy our curiosity; but<lb/>at our
                    return from the Rio Negro we learnt, that<lb/>the Indian mother was not allowed
                    time to cure her<lb/>wounds, but was again separated from her children,<lb/>and
                    sent to one of the missions of the Upper Oroono-<lb/>ko. There she died,
                    refusing all kind of nourish-<lb/>ment, as the savages do in great
                    calamities.</p><lb/><p>Such is the remembrance annexed to this fatal<lb/>rock, to <hi rendition="#i">Piedra de la Madre.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
