<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>MATERNAL ATTACHMENT.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#k">from humboldt&#x2019;s travels.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;In 1797, the missionary of San Fernando<lb break="yes"/>had led his
                        Indians to the banks of the Rio Gua-<lb break="no"/>viare, on one of those
                        hostile incursions, which<lb break="yes"/>are prohibited alike by religion
                        and the Spanish<lb break="yes"/>laws. They found in an
                                <choice><sic>Italian</sic><corr type="editorial"
                            >Indian</corr></choice> hut, a Guahiba<lb break="yes"/>mother with three
                        children, two of whom were<lb break="yes"/>still infants. They were occupied
                        in preparing<lb break="yes"/>the flour of Cassava. Resistance was
                            impossible,<lb break="yes"/>the father was gone to fish, and the mother
                            tried<lb break="yes"/>in vain to flee with her children. Scarcely had<lb
                            break="yes"/>she reached the savannah, when she was seized<lb
                            break="yes"/>by the Indians of the mission, who go to <hi rendition="#i"
                                >hunt<lb break="yes"/>men,</hi> like the whites and the negroes in
                            Africa.<lb break="yes"/>The mother and her children were bound, and<lb
                            break="yes"/>dragged to the bank of the river. The monk,<lb break="yes"
                        />seated in his boat, waited the issue of an expedi-<lb break="no"/>tion, of
                        which he partook not the danger. Had<lb break="yes"/>the mother made too
                        violent a resistance, the In-<lb break="no"/>dians would have killed her,
                        for every thing is<lb break="yes"/>permitted when they go to the conquest of
                            souls,<lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">a la conquista
                            espiritual,</hi>) and it is children in<lb break="yes"/>particular they
                        seek to capture, in order to treat<lb break="yes"/>them, in the mission, as
                            <hi rendition="#i">poitos,</hi> or slaves of the<lb break="yes"
                        />Christians. The prisoners were carried to San<lb break="yes"/>Fernando, in
                        the hope that the mother would be<lb break="yes"/>unable to find her way
                        back to her home, by land.<lb break="yes"/>Far from those children who had
                            accompanied<lb break="yes"/>their father on the day in which she had
                            been<lb break="yes"/>carried off, this unhappy woman showed signs of<lb
                            break="yes"/>the deepest despair. She attempted to take back<lb
                            break="yes"/>to her family the children who had been snatch-<lb
                            break="no"/>ed away by the missionary, and fled with them<lb break="yes"
                        />repeatedly from the village of San Fernando, but<lb break="yes"/>the
                        Indians never failed to seize her anew; and<lb break="yes"/>the missionary,
                        after having caused her to be<lb break="yes"/>mercilessly beaten, took the
                        cruel resolution of<lb break="yes"/>separating the mother from the two
                            children,<lb break="yes"/>who had been carried off with her. She was
                            con-<lb break="no"/>veyed alone towards the missions of the Rio Ne-<lb
                            break="no"/>gro, going up the Atabapo. Slightly bound, she<lb
                            break="yes"/>was seated at the bow of the boat, ignorant of the<lb
                            break="yes"/>fate that awaited her; but she judged, by the di-<lb
                            break="no"/>rection of the sun, that she was removed farther<lb
                            break="yes"/>and farther from her hut, and her native country.<lb
                            break="yes"/>She succeeded in breaking her bonds, threw her-<lb
                            break="no"/>self into the water, and swam to the left bank of<lb
                            break="yes"/>the Atabapo. The current carried her to a shelf<lb
                            break="yes"/>of rock, which bears her name to this day. She<lb
                            break="yes"/>landed, and took shelter in the woods, but the<lb
                            break="yes"/>president of the missions ordered the Indians to<lb
                            break="yes"/>row to the shore, and follow the traces of the Gua-<lb
                            break="no"/>hibi. In the evening she was brought back.<lb break="yes"
                        />Stretched upon the rock, <hi rendition="#i">(la Piedra de la Ma-<lb
                                break="no"/>dre,)</hi> a cruel punishment was inflicted on her<lb
                            break="yes"/>with those straps of manatee leather, which serve<lb
                            break="yes"/>for whips in that country, and with which the<lb
                            break="yes"/>alcades are always furnished. This unhappy<lb break="yes"
                        />woman, her hands tied behind her back with<lb break="yes"/>strong stalks
                        of <hi rendition="#i">mavacure,</hi> was then dragged to<lb break="yes"/>the
                        mission of the Javita.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;She was there thrown into one of the cara-<lb break="yes"/>vanseras
                        that are called <hi rendition="#i">Casa del rey.</hi> It was the<lb
                            break="yes"/>rainy season, and the night was profoundly dark.<lb
                            break="yes"/>Forests, till then believed to be impenetrable, sep-<lb
                            break="yes"/>parated the mission of Javita from that of San<lb
                            break="yes"/>Fernando, which was twenty-five leagues distance<lb
                            break="yes"/>in a straight line. No other part is known than<lb
                            break="yes"/>that of the rivers; no man ever attempted to go<lb
                            break="yes"/>by land from one village to another, were they<lb
                            break="yes"/>only a few leagues apart. But such difficulties<lb
                            break="yes"/>do not stop a mother who is separated from her<lb
                            break="yes"/>children. Her children are at San Fernando de<lb
                            break="yes"/>Atabapo; she must find them again, she must<lb break="yes"
                        />execute her project of delivering them from the<lb break="yes"/>hands of
                        Christians, of bringing them back to<lb break="yes"/>their father on the
                        banks of the Guaviare. The<lb break="yes"/>Guahibi was carelessly guarded in
                        the caravanse-<lb break="no"/>ra. Her arms being wounded, the Indians of
                            Ja-<lb break="yes"/>vita had loosened her bonds, unknown to the<lb
                            break="yes"/>missionary and the alcades. She succeeded, by<lb
                            break="yes"/>the help of her teeth, in breaking them entirely;<lb
                            break="yes"/>disappeared during the night, and at the fourth<lb
                            break="yes"/>rising sun was seen at the mission of San Fernan-<lb
                            break="yes"/>do, hovering around the hut where her children<lb
                            break="yes"/>were confined.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;What that woman performed,&#x201D; added the<lb break="yes"
                        />missionary who gave us this sad narrative,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;the
                        most robust Indian would not have ventur-<lb break="no"/>ed to undertake.
                        She traversed the woods at<lb break="yes"/>a season when the sky is
                        constantly covered with<lb break="yes"/>clouds, and the sun during whole
                        days ap-<lb break="no"/>pears but for a few minutes. Did the course of<lb
                            break="yes"/>the waters direct her way? The inundations of<lb
                            break="yes"/>the rivers forced her to go far from the banks of<lb
                            break="yes"/>the main stream, through the midst of woods<lb break="yes"
                        />where the movement of the waters is almost im-<lb break="no"/>perceptible.
                        How often must she have been<lb break="yes"/>stopped by the thorny lianas,
                        that form a net<lb break="yes"/>work round the trunks they entwine? How
                            of-<lb break="no"/>ten must she have swam across the rivulets, that<lb
                            break="yes"/>run into the Atabapo! This unfortunate woman<lb break="yes"
                        />was asked how she had sustained herself during<lb break="yes"/>the four
                        days! She said that, exhausted with<lb break="yes"/>fatigue, she could find
                        no other nourishment<lb break="yes"/>than those great black ants called <hi
                            rendition="#i">vachacos,</hi> which<lb break="yes"/>climb the trees in
                        long bands, to suspend on them<lb break="yes"/>their resinous nests.&#x201D;
                        We pressed the mission-<lb break="no"/>ary to tell us whether the Guahibi
                        had peaceful-<lb break="no"/>ly enjoyed the happiness of remaining with
                            her<lb break="yes"/>children; and if any repentance had followed<lb
                            break="yes"/>this excess of cruelty. He would not satisfy<lb break="yes"
                        />our curiosity; but at our return from the Rio<lb break="yes"/>Negro we
                        learnt, that the Indian mother was not<lb break="yes"/>allowed time to cure
                        her wounds, but was again<lb break="yes"/>separated from her children, and
                        sent to one of<lb break="yes"/>the missions of the Upper Oroonoko. There<lb
                            break="yes"/>she died refusing all kind of nourishment, as the<lb
                            break="yes"/>savages do in great calamities.&#x201D;</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI> 