<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="426" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>ACCOUNTS OF CROCODILES.<lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">From</hi> M. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt&#x2019;s</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">&#x201C;Personal Narrative&#x201D; of his Travels in<lb break="yes"/>South America.</hi>)</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">When</hi> the waters are high, the river inundates<lb break="yes"/>the quays; and it sometimes happens, that even in<lb break="yes"/>the town, imprudent men become the prey of croco-<lb break="no" />diles. I shall transcribe from my journal a fact that<lb break="yes"/>took place during <hi rendition="#k">Mr. Boupland&#x2019;s</hi> illness. A Guay-<lb break="no"/>keri Indian, from the island de la Margaretta, went<lb break="yes"/>to anchor his canoe in a cove, where there were<lb break="yes" />not three feet of water. A fierce crocodile, that ha-<lb break="no"/>bitually haunted the spot, seized him by the leg, and<lb break="yes"/>withdrew from the shore, remaining on the surface of<lb break="yes"/>the water. The cries of the Indian drew together a<lb break="yes"/>crowd of spectators. This unfortunate man was first<lb break="yes"/>seen seeking, with astonishing courage, for a knife in<lb break="yes"/>the pocket of his pantaloons. Not being able to find<lb break="yes"/>it, he seized the head of the crocodile, and thrust his<lb break="yes"/>fingers into his eyes. No man in the hot regions of<lb break="yes"/>America is ignorant, that this carnivorous reptile,<lb break="yes"/>covered with a buckler of hard and dry scales, is ex-<lb break="no"/>tremely sensible in the only parts of the body which<lb break="yes"/>are soft and unprotected, such as the eyes, the hollow<lb break="yes"/>underneath the shoulders, the nostrils, and beneath<lb break="yes"/>the lower jaw, where there are two glands of musk.<lb break="yes"/>The Guaykeri Indian had recourse to the same means<lb break="yes"/>which saved the negro of <hi rendition="#k">Mungo Park,</hi> and the girl<lb break="yes"/>of Uritucu,&#x2014;but he was less fortunate than they had<lb break="yes"/>been, for the crocodile did not open its jaws, and lose<lb break="yes"/>hold of its prey. The animal, yielding to the pain,<lb break="yes"/>plunged to the bottom of the river; and, after having<lb break="yes"/>drowned the Indian, came up to the surface of the<lb break="yes"/>water, dragging the dead body to an island opposite<lb break="yes"/>the port. I arrived at the moment when a great<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="427" facs="#f0002"/> number of the inhabitants of Angostura had witnessed<lb break="yes"/>this melancholy spectacle.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;As the crocodile, on account of the structure of<lb break="yes"/>its larynx, of the hyoid bone, and of the folds of its<lb break="yes"/>tongue, can seize, though not swallow, its prey under<lb break="yes"/>water; a man seldom disappears, without the animal<lb break="yes"/>being peceived some hours after near the spot where<lb break="yes"/>the misfortune has happened, devouring its prey on a<lb break="yes"/>neighbouring beach.&#x2014;The number of individuals who<lb break="yes"/>perish annually, the victims of their own imprudence<lb break="yes"/>and of the ferocity of these reptiles, is much greater<lb break="yes"/>than it is believed to be in Europe. It is particularly<lb break="yes"/>so in villages, where the neighbouring grounds are<lb break="yes"/>often inundated. The same crocodiles remain long<lb break="yes" />in the same places. They become from year to year<lb break="yes"/>more daring, especially, as the Indians assert, if they<lb break="yes"/>have once tasted of human flesh. These animals are<lb break="yes"/>so wary, that they are killed with difficulty. A ball<lb break="yes"/>does not pierce their skin, and the shot is only mortal<lb break="yes"/>when directed at the throat, or beneath the shoulder.<lb break="yes"/>The Indians, who know little of the use of arms,<lb break="yes"/>attack the crocodile with lances, after it is caught with<lb break="yes"/>large pointed iron hooks, baited with pieces of meat,<lb break="yes"/>and fastened by a chain to the trunk of a tree. They<lb break="yes"/>do not approach the animal till it has struggled a long<lb break="yes"/>time to disengage itself from the iron fixed in the<lb break="yes"/>upper jaw. There is little probability that a country<lb break="yes"/>in which a labyrinth of rivers, without number, brings<lb break="yes"/>every day new bands of crocodiles from the eastern<lb break="yes"/>bank of the Andes, by the Meta and the Apure,<lb break="yes" />towards the coast of Spanish Guyana, should ever be<lb break="yes"/>delivered from these reptiles. All that will be gained<lb break="yes"/>by civilization will be, to render them more timid, and<lb break="yes"/>more easily put to flight.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="428" facs="#f0003"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Affecting instances are related of African slaves,<lb break="yes"/>who have exposed their lives to save those of their<lb break="yes"/>masters, who had fallen into the jaws of the crocodile.<lb break="yes"/>A few years ago, between Vritucu and the <hi rendition="#i">Mission de<lb break="yes"/>Abaxo,</hi> a negro, hearing the cries of his master, flew<lb break="yes"/>to the spot, armed with a long knife (<hi rendition="#i">machelte</hi>) and<lb break="yes"/>plunged into the river. He forced the crocodile, by<lb break="yes"/>putting out his eyes, to let go his prey, and hide<lb break="yes"/>himself under the water. The slave bore his expiring<lb break="yes"/>master to the shore, but all succour was unavailing to<lb break="yes"/>restore him to life. He died of suffocation, for his<lb break="yes"/>wounds were not deep. The crocodile, like the dog,<lb break="yes"/>appears not to close his jaws firmly while swimming.<lb break="yes"/>It is almost superfluous to add, that the children of the<lb break="yes"/>deceased, though poor, gave the slave his freedom.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 