<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
            <pb n="10" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <cb/>
            <lb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#k">shirt tree.</hi></head>
                <lb/>
                <p>The numerous and well-known voyages to<lb/>the South Sea islands, &#x0026;c.,
                    have made us all<lb/>well acquainted with what is called the <hi rendition="#i"
                            >bread-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>tree,</hi> as well as another kind known
                    under the<lb/>name of the <hi rendition="#i">butter-tree.</hi> But it remained
                    for<lb/>the indefatigable M. Humboldt to discover<lb/>in the wilds of South
                    America, a tree which<lb/>produces ready-made <hi rendition="#i">shirts.</hi>
                    &#x201C;We saw on<lb/>the slope of the Cerra <choice>
                        <sic>Dnida</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Duida</corr>
                    </choice>,&#x201D; says M. Hum-<lb/>boldt, &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">shirt-<choice>
                            <sic>tress</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">trees</corr>
                        </choice></hi> fifty feet high. The<lb/>Indians cut off cylindrical pieces
                    two feet in<lb/>diameter, from which they peel the red and<lb/>fibrous bark,
                    without making any longitudinal<lb/>incision. This bark, affords them a sort
                    of<lb/>garment, which resembles sacks of a very<lb/>coarse texture, and without
                    a seam. The up-<lb/>per opening serves for the head, and two la-<lb/>teral holes
                    are cut to admit the arms. The<lb/>natives wear these shirts of marima in
                    the<lb/>rainy season: they have the form of the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >pon-<lb/>chos</hi> and <choice>
                        <sic><hi rendition="#i">ruanos</hi></sic>
                        <corr type="editorial"><hi rendition="#i">ruanas</hi></corr>
                    </choice> of cotton, which are so com-<lb/>mon in New Grenada, at Quito, and in
                    Peru.<lb/>As in these climates the riches and benefi-<lb/>cence of nature are
                    regarded as the primary<lb/>causes of the indolence of the inhabitants,
                    the<lb/>missionaries do not fail to say in showing the<lb/>shirts of marima,
                    &#x2018;in the forests of the Oroo-<lb/>noko, garments are found ready made on
                    the<lb/>trees.&#x2019; We may add to this tale of the shirts,<lb/>the pointed
                    caps, which the spathes of certain<lb/>palm-trees furnish, and which resemble
                        coarse<lb/>network.&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Tilloch&#x2019;s
                        Mag.</hi></p>
                <lb/>
            </div>
        </body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
