<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="297" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>THE GUAHIBI MOTHER.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>The following affecting story is<lb break="yes"/>told by Humbolt.&#x2014;Where the Ata-<lb break="no"/>bapo enters the Rio Temi, but before<lb break="yes"/>we reached its confluence, a granitic<lb break="yes"/>hummoek, that rises on the western<lb break="yes"/>back, near the mouth of the Guasa-<lb break="no" />cavi, is called the rock of the Gua-<lb break="no"/>hibi Woman, or the rock of the<lb break="yes"/>Mother, Piedra de la Madre. We<lb break="yes"/>inquired the cause of so singular a<lb break="yes"/>denomination. Father Zea could not<lb break="yes"/>satisfy our curiosity, but some weeks<lb break="yes"/>after, another missionary, one of the<lb break="yes"/>predecessors of this ecclesiastic, whom<lb break="yes"/>we found settled at San Fernando, as<lb break="yes"/>president of the missions, related to<lb break="yes"/>as an event which I recorded in my<lb break="yes"/>journal, and which excited in our<lb break="yes"/>minds the most painful feelings. If,<lb break="yes"/>in these solitary scenes, man scarcely<lb break="yes"/>leaves behind him any trace of his<lb break="yes"/>existence, it is doubly humiliating<lb break="yes"/>for a European to see perpetuated by<lb break="yes"/>the name of a rock, by one of those<lb break="yes"/>imperishable monuments of nature,<lb break="yes"/>the remembrance of the moral degra-<lb break="no"/>dation of our species, and the con-<lb break="no"/>trast between the virtues of a savage<lb break="yes" />and the barbarism of civilized man.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In 1797, the missionary of San<lb break="yes"/>Fernando had led his Indians to the<lb break="yes"/>banks of the Rio Guaviave, on one<lb break="yes"/>of those hostile incursions which are<lb break="yes"/>prohibited alike by religion and the<lb break="yes"/>Spanish laws. They found in an<lb break="yes"/>Italian hut, a Guahibi mother with<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> three children, two of whom were<lb break="yes"/>still infants. They were occupied in<lb break="yes"/>preparing the flour of Cassava: re-<lb break="no" />sistance was impossible: the father<lb break="yes"/>was gone to fish, and the mother<lb break="yes"/>tried in vain to flee with her children.<lb break="yes"/>Scarcely had she reached the Savan-<lb break="no"/>nah, when she was seized by the<lb break="yes"/>Indians of the mission, who go to<lb break="yes"/>hunt men, like the whites and the<lb break="yes"/>negroes in Africa; the mother and<lb break="yes"/>her children were bound, and drag-<lb break="no"/>ged to the bank of the river: the<lb break="yes"/>the monk, seated in his boat, waited<lb break="yes"/>the issue of an expedition, of which<lb break="yes"/>he partook not the danger; had the<lb break="yes" />mother made too violent a resist-<lb break="no"/>ance, the Indians would have killed<lb break="yes"/>her; for every thing is permitted<lb break="yes" />when they go to the conquest of<lb break="yes"/>souls, and it is children in particular<lb break="yes"/>they seek to capture, in order to treat<lb break="yes"/>them in the mission as poitos, or<lb break="yes"/>slaves of the Christians. The pri-<lb break="no"/>soners were carried to San Fernando,<lb break="yes"/>in the hope that the mother would<lb break="yes"/>be unable to find her way back to<lb break="yes"/>her home by land. Far from those<lb break="yes"/>children who had accompanied their<lb break="yes"/>father on the day in which she had<lb break="yes"/>been carried off, this unhappy woman<lb break="yes"/>showed signs of the deepest despair.<lb break="yes"/>She attempted to take back to her<lb break="yes"/>family the children who had been<lb break="yes"/>snatched away by the missionary,<lb break="yes"/>and fled with them repeatedly from<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="298" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/> the village of San Fernando, but the<lb break="yes"/>Indians never failed to seize her<lb break="yes"/>anew; and the missionary, after<lb break="yes" />having caused her to be mercilessly<lb break="yes"/>beaten, took the cruel resolution of<lb break="yes"/>separating the mother from the two<lb break="yes" />children who had been carried off<lb break="yes"/>with her. She was conveyed alone<lb break="yes"/>toward the mission of the Negroe,<lb break="yes" />going up to the Atabapo; slightly<lb break="yes"/>bound, she was seated at the how of<lb break="yes"/>the boat, ignorant of the fate that<lb break="yes" />awaited her; but she judged by the<lb break="yes"/>direction of the sun, that she was<lb break="yes"/>removed farther and farther from her<lb break="yes" />hut, and her native country. She<lb break="yes"/>succeeded in breaking her bonds,<lb break="yes"/>threw herself into the water, and<lb break="yes" />awam to the left bank of the Atabapo,<lb break="yes"/>the current carried her to a shelf of<lb break="yes"/>rock, which bears her name to this<lb break="yes" />day. She landed, and took shelter<lb break="yes"/>in the woods, but the president of<lb break="yes"/>the missions ordered the Indians to<lb break="yes" />row to shore, and follow the traces of<lb break="yes"/>the Guahibi. In the evening she<lb break="yes"/>was brought back, stretched upon<lb break="yes"/>the rock (la Piedra de la Madre) a<lb break="yes"/>cruel punishment was inflicted on<lb break="yes"/>her with those straps of menatee<lb break="yes"/>leather which serve for whips in that<lb break="yes"/>country, and with which the alcades<lb break="yes"/>are always furnished. This unhappy<lb break="yes" />woman, her hands tied back with<lb break="yes"/>strong stalks of mavacure, was then<lb break="yes"/>dragged to the mission of Javita.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>She was then thrown into one of<lb break="yes"/>the Caravanseras, that are called<lb break="yes"/>Casa de Roy. It was the rainy sea-<lb break="no" />son, and the night was profound-<lb break="no"/>ly dark. Forests till then believ-<lb break="no"/>ed to be impenetrable, separated<lb break="yes"/>the mission of Javita from that of<lb break="yes"/>San Fernando, which was twenty-<lb break="no"/>four leagues distant in a straight<lb break="yes" />line. No other part is known than<lb break="yes"/>that of the rivers; no man ever at-<lb break="no"/>tempted to go by land from one vil-<lb break="no"/>lage to another were they only a few<lb break="yes"/>leagues apart. But such difficulties<lb break="yes"/>do not stop a mother who is separated<lb break="yes"/>from her children. Her children are<lb break="yes"/>at San Fernando de Atabapo: she<lb break="yes"/>must find them again, she must exe-<lb break="no"/>cute her project of delivering them<lb break="yes"/>from the hands of Christians, of<lb break="yes"/>bringing them back to their father<lb break="yes"/>on the banks of the Guaviave. The<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> Guahibi was carelessly guarded in<lb break="yes"/>the Caravansera. Her arms being<lb break="yes"/>wounded, the Indians of Javita had<lb break="yes" />loosened her bonds, unknown to the<lb break="yes"/>missionary and the alcades: she suc-<lb break="no"/>ceeded by the help of her teeth in<lb break="yes" />breaking them entirely; disappeared<lb break="yes"/>during the night, and, at the fourth<lb break="yes"/>rising sun was seen at the mission of<lb break="yes" />San Fernando, hovering around the<lb break="yes"/>hut where her children was confined.<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;What that woman performed,&#x2019; add-<lb break="no"/>ed the missionary who gave us this<lb break="yes"/>sad narrative, &#x2018;the most robust In-<lb break="no"/>dian would not have ventured to un-<lb break="no"/>dertake. She traversed the woods<lb break="yes" />at a season when the sky is constantly<lb break="yes"/>covered with clouds, and the sun<lb break="yes"/>during whole days appears but for a<lb break="yes" />few minutes. Did the course of the<lb break="yes"/>waters direct her way, the inunda-<lb break="no"/>tion of the river forced her to go far<lb break="yes" />from the banks of the main stream,<lb break="yes"/>through the midst of woods, where<lb break="yes"/>the movement of the waters is almost<lb break="yes" />imperceptible. How often must she<lb break="yes"/>have been stopped by the thorny<lb break="yes"/>lianas that form a net-work alound<lb break="yes" />the trunks they entwine! How often<lb break="yes"/>must she have swam across the rivu-<lb break="no"/>lets that run into the Atabapo! This<lb break="yes" />unfortunate woman was asked how<lb break="yes"/>she had sustained herself during<lb break="yes"/>the four days. She said, &#x2018;that ex-<lb break="no"/>hausted with fatigue, she could find<lb break="yes"/>no other nourishment than those<lb break="yes"/>great black ants called Vachacos,<lb break="yes"/>which climb the trees in long bands,<lb break="yes"/>to suspend on them their resinous<lb break="yes"/>nests?&#x2019; We pressed the missionary<lb break="yes"/>to tell us, whether the Guahibi had<lb break="yes"/>peacefully enjoyed the happiness of<lb break="yes"/>remaining with her children, and if<lb break="yes"/>any repentance had followed this ex-<lb break="no"/>cess of cruelty. He would not satisfy<lb break="yes"/>our curiosity; but at our return from<lb break="yes"/>the Rio Negroe we learnt, that the<lb break="yes"/>Indian mother was not allowed time<lb break="yes"/>to cure her wounds, but was again<lb break="yes"/>separated from her children, and sent<lb break="yes"/>to one of the missions of the Upper<lb break="yes" />Oroonoko, there she died, refusing<lb break="yes"/>all kind of nourishment, as the sa-<lb break="no"/>vages do in great calamities. Such is<lb break="yes"/>the remembrance annexed to the<lb break="yes"/>fatal rock, &#x2018;Piedra de la Madre.&#x2019;&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels in South America.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 