<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Savages on the Oronoko</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:56</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.15</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1821-Personal_Narrative_of-04-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-04-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-Personal_Narrative_of-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
          <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent&lt;i&gt;, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 2, S. 304–337.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Savages on the Oronoko</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1821</date>
          <pubPlace>Boston, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;Boston Weekly Messenger&lt;/i&gt; 2/11:10 (9. August 1821), S. [1].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <p><hi rendition="#k">from the london literary gazette.</hi></p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>From the Personal Narrative of Baron Humboldt.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    SAVAGES ON THE ORONOKO.
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Among the causes of the depopulation of the<lb break="yes"/>Raudales, I
                    have not reckoned the small pox;<lb break="yes"/>that malady which, in other
                    parts of America,<lb break="yes"/>makes such cruel ravages, that the natives,
                        seized<lb break="yes"/>with dismay, burn their huts, kill their children,
                        and<lb break="yes"/>renounce every kind of society.<note place="foot" n="*"
                        >As the Mahas in the plains of the Missouri,<lb break="yes"/>according to
                        the accounts of the American trav-<lb break="no"/>ellers, Clark and
                        Lewis.</note> This scourge is<lb break="yes"/>almost unknown on the banks of
                    the Oronoko.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>What depopulates the Christian settlements
                        is,<lb break="yes"/>the repugnance of the Indians for the regulations<lb
                        break="yes"/>of the missions, the insalubrity of a climate at<lb break="yes"
                    />once hot and damp, bad nourishment, want of<lb break="yes"/>care in the
                    diseases of children, and the guilty<lb break="yes"/>practice of mothers of
                    preventing pregnancy by<lb break="yes"/>the use of deleterious herbs. Among the
                        barba-<lb break="no"/>rous people of Guyana, as well as those of the half<lb
                        break="yes"/>civilized islands of the South Sea, young wives<lb break="yes"
                    />will not become mothers. If they have children,<lb break="yes"/>their
                    offspring are exposed, not only to the dan-<lb break="no"/>gers of savage life,
                    but also to the dangers arising<lb break="yes"/>from the strongest popular
                    prejudices. When<lb break="yes"/>twins are born, false notions of propriety and
                        fam-<lb break="no"/>ily honor require, that one of them should be de-<lb
                        break="no"/>stroyed. &#x2018;To bring twins into the world, is to be<lb
                        break="yes"/>exposed to public scorn; it is to resemble rats, <lb
                        break="yes"/>opossums, and the vilest animals, which bring forth<lb
                        break="yes"/>a great number of young at a time.&#x2019; Nay more:<lb
                        break="yes"/>&#x2018;two children born at the same time cannot belong<lb
                        break="yes"/>to the same father.&#x2019; This is an axiom of physiol-<lb
                        break="no"/>ogy of the Salivas; and in every zone, and in differ-<lb
                        break="no"/>ent states of society, when the vulgar seize upon<lb break="yes"
                    />an axiom, they adhere to it with more stedfastness<lb break="yes"/>than the
                    better informed men, by whom it was first<lb break="yes"/>hazarded. To avoid a
                    disturbance of conjugal<lb break="yes"/>tranquillity, the old female relations
                    of the mother,<lb break="yes"/>or the <hi rendition="#i">mure jappoice-nei</hi>
                    (midwives,) take care, that<lb break="yes"/>one of the twins shall disappear. If
                    the new-born<lb break="yes"/>infant, though not a twin, have any physical
                        defor-<lb break="no"/>mity, the father instantly puts it to death. They<lb
                        break="yes"/>will have only robust well-made children, for de-<lb break="no"
                    />formities indicate some influence of the evil spirit<lb break="yes"
                    />Ioloquiamo or the bird <hi rendition="#i">Tikitiki</hi>, the enemy of the<lb
                        break="yes"/>human race. Sometimes children of a feeble con-<lb break="no"
                    />stitution undergo the same fate. When the father<lb break="yes"/>is asked,
                    what is become of one of his sons, he<lb break="yes"/>will pretend, that he has
                    lost him by a natural death.<lb break="yes"/>He will disavow an action, that
                    appears to him<lb break="yes"/>blameable, but not criminal. &#x2018;The poor <hi
                        rendition="#i">mure</hi>,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">In Tamanack <hi
                            rendition="#i">mure</hi> signifies a child; <hi rendition="#i"
                            >omura</hi> a<lb break="yes"/>son.</note>&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>he
                    will tell you, &#x2018;could not follow us; we must<lb break="yes"/>have waited
                    for him every moment; he has not<lb break="yes"/>been seen again, he did not
                    come to sleep where<lb break="yes"/>we passed the night.&#x2019; Such is the
                    candour and<lb break="yes"/>simplicity of manners, such the boasted happiness<lb
                        break="yes"/>of man in the <hi rendition="#i">state of nature</hi>! He kills
                    his son, to<lb break="yes"/>escape the ridicule of having twins, or to avoid<lb
                        break="yes"/>journeying more slowly; in fact, to avoid a little<lb
                        break="yes"/>inconvenience.&#x2019;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The Indians of Atures,&#x201D; (says Mr. H.,) are<lb break="yes"/>mild,
                    moderate, and accustomed, from the effects<lb break="yes"/>of their idleness, to
                    the greatest privations. For-<lb break="no"/>merly, excited to labour by the
                    Jesuits, they did<lb break="yes"/>not want for food. The fathers cultivated
                        maize,<lb break="yes"/>French beans, (<hi rendition="#i">frisoles</hi>) and
                    other European veg-<lb break="no"/>etables; they even planted sweet oranges
                        and<lb break="yes"/>tamarinds round the villages; and they possessed<lb
                        break="yes"/>twenty or thirty thousand head of cows and horses,<lb
                        break="yes"/>in the savannahs of Atures and Carichana. They<lb break="yes"
                    />had at their service a great number of slaves and<lb break="yes"/>servants
                        (<hi rendition="#i">peones</hi>), to take care of their herds.&#x2014;<lb
                        break="yes"/>Nothing is now cultivated but a little cassava, and<lb
                        break="yes"/>a few plantains. The fertility of the soil however<lb
                        break="yes"/>is such, that at Atures I counted on a single branch<lb
                        break="yes"/>of musa 108 fruits, 4 or 5 of which would almost<lb break="yes"
                    />suffice for the daily nourishment of a man. The<lb break="yes"/>culture of
                    maize is entirely neglected, and the<lb break="yes"/>horses and cows have
                    disappeared. Near the<lb break="yes"/><hi rendition="#i">raudal</hi>, a part of
                    the village still bears the name of<lb break="yes"/><hi rendition="#i">Passo del
                        ganado</hi> (ford of the cattle,) while the de-<lb break="no"/>scendants of
                    those very Indians, whom the Jesuits<lb break="yes"/>had assembled in a mission,
                    speak of horned cattle<lb break="yes"/>as of animals of a race that is lost. In
                    going up the<lb break="yes"/>Oronoko, toward San Carlos del Rio Negro, we<lb
                        break="yes"/>saw the last cow at Carichana. The fathers of<lb break="yes"
                    />the Observance, who now govern these vast coun-<lb break="no"/>tries, did not
                    immediately succeed the Jesuits.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>During an interregnum
                    of eighteen years the mis-<lb break="no"/>sions were visited only from time to
                    time, and by<lb break="yes"/>Capuchin monks. The agents of the secular gov-<lb
                        break="no"/>ernment, under the title of <hi rendition="#i">Commissioners of
                            the<lb break="yes"/>King</hi>, managed the <hi rendition="#i">hatos</hi>
                    or farms of the Jesuits<lb break="yes"/>with culpable negligence. They killed
                    the cattle<lb break="yes"/>in order to sell the hides. Many heifers were de-<lb
                        break="no"/>voured by tigers, and a greater number perished<lb break="yes"
                    />in consequence of wounds made by the bats of the<lb break="yes"/><hi
                        rendition="#i">raudales</hi>, which are much less, but far bolder than<lb
                        break="yes"/>the bats of the Llanos. At the time of the expedi-<lb
                        break="no"/>tion of the boundaries, the horses of Encaramada,<lb break="yes"
                    />Carichana, and Atures, were conveyed as far as San<lb break="yes"/>Jose of
                    Maravitanos, where, on the banks of the<lb break="yes"/>Rio Negro, the
                    Portuguese could only procure<lb break="yes"/>them after a long passage, and of
                    a very inferior<lb break="yes"/>quality, by the river Amazon and Grand
                        Para.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Since the year 1795, the cattle of the Jesuits
                        have<lb break="yes"/>entirely disappeared. There now remains in tes-<lb
                        break="no"/>timony of the ancient cultivation of these countries<lb
                        break="yes"/>and the industrious activity of the first missionaries,<lb
                        break="yes"/>only a few trunks of the orange and tamarind in<lb break="yes"
                    />the savannahs, surrounded by wild trees.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The tigers, or jaguars, which are less danger-<lb break="no"/>ous for the cattle than the bats, come into the vil-<lb break="no"/>lage at Atures, and devour the pigs of the poor In-<lb break="no"/>dians. The missionary related to us a striking in-<lb break="no"/>stance of the familiarity of these animals, upon the<lb break="yes"/>whole so ferocious. Some months before our ar-<lb break="no"/>rival, a jaguar, which was thought to be young,<lb break="yes" />though of a large size, had wounded a child in<lb break="yes"/>playing with him; I use confidently this expression,<lb break="yes"/>which may seem strange, having on the spot veri-<lb break="no"/>fied facts which are not without interest in the<lb break="yes"/>history of the manners of animals. Two Indian<lb break="yes"/>children, a boy and a girl, about eight and nine<lb break="yes" />years of age, were seated on the grass near the<lb break="yes"/>village of Atures, in the middle of a savannah,<lb break="yes"/>which we have often traversed. At two o&#x2019;clock in<lb break="yes"/>the afternoon, a jaguar issued from the forest, and<lb break="yes"/>approached the children, bounding around them;<lb break="yes"/>sometimes he hid himself in the high grass, some-<lb break="no"/>times he sprang forward, his back bent, his head<lb break="yes"/>hung down, in the manner of our cats. The little<lb break="yes" />boy, ignorant of his danger, seemed to be sensible<lb break="yes"/>of it only when the jaguar with one of his paws<lb break="yes"/>gave him some blows on the head. These blows,<lb break="yes"/>at first slight, became ruder and ruder; the claws<lb break="yes"/>of the jaguar wounded the child, and the blood<lb break="yes"/>flowed with violence. The little girl then took a<lb break="yes"/>branch of a tree, struck the animal, and it fled<lb break="yes" />from her. The Indians ran up at the cries of the<lb break="yes"/>children, and saw the jaguar, which retired bound-<lb break="no"/>ing, without the least show of resistance.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The little boy was brought to us, who appeared<lb break="yes"/>lively and intelligent. The claw of the jaguar had<lb break="yes"/>taken away the skin from the lower part of the<lb break="yes"/>forehead, and there was a second scar at the top<lb break="yes"/>of the head.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Among the monkies,&#x201D; the author continues,<lb break="yes"
                    />&#x201C;which we saw at the mission of the Atures, we<lb break="yes"/>found
                    one new species, of the tribe of <hi rendition="#i">sais</hi> and<lb break="yes"
                        /><hi rendition="#i">sajous</hi>, which the Creoles vulgarly call <hi
                        rendition="#i">machis.</hi> It<lb break="yes"/>is the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >ouavapavi</hi> with grey hair and a bluish face.<lb break="yes"/>It has the
                    orbits of the eyes and forehead as white<lb break="yes"/>as snow, which at first
                    sight distinguishes it from<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">simia
                        capucina</hi>, the <hi rendition="#i">simia apella</hi>, the <hi
                        rendition="#i">simia trepi-<lb break="no"/>da</hi>, and the other weeping
                    monkeys hitherto so<lb break="yes"/>confusedly described.&#x2014;This little animal is as<lb break="yes"/>gentle as it is
                    ugly. Every day in the court-yard<lb break="yes"/>of the missionary it seized a
                    pig, upon which it re-<lb break="no"/>mained from morning till night, traversing
                    the sa-<lb break="no"/>vannahs. We have also seen it upon the back of a<lb
                        break="yes"/>large cat, which had been brought up with it in<lb break="yes"
                    />father Zea&#x2019;s house.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;It was among the cataracts that we began to<lb break="yes"/>hear of the
                    hairy man of the woods, called salvaje,<lb break="yes"/>that carries off women,
                    constructs huts, and some-<lb break="no"/><cb/>times eats human flesh. The
                    Tamanacks call it<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">achi</hi>, and the Maypures <hi rendition="#i">vasitri</hi>,
                    or <hi rendition="#i">great devil.</hi>&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>The natives and
                    the missionaries have no doubt of<lb break="yes"/>the existence of this
                    anthropomorphous monkey,<lb break="yes"/>which they singularly dread. Father
                    Gili gravely<lb break="yes"/>relates the history of a lady in the town of San<lb
                        break="yes"/>Carlos, who much praised the gentle character and<lb
                        break="yes"/>attentions of the man of the woods. She lived<lb break="yes"
                    />several years with one in great domestic harmony,<lb break="yes"/>and only
                    requested some hunters to take her back<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;because she was
                    tired, she and her children, (a<lb break="yes"/>little hairy also,) of living
                    far from the church and<lb break="yes"/>the sacraments.&#x2019; The same author,
                        notwithstand-<lb break="no"/>ing his credulity, confesses, that he had not
                        been<lb break="yes"/>able to find an Indian who asserted positively that<lb
                        break="yes"/>he had seen the <hi rendition="#i">salvaje</hi> with his own
                    eyes. This<lb break="yes"/>fable, which the missionaries, the European plan-<lb
                        break="no"/>ters, and the negroes of Africa, have no doubt<lb break="yes"
                    />embellished with many features taken from the de-<lb break="no"/>scription of
                    the manners of the ourang outang, the<lb break="yes"/>gibbon, the jacko or
                    chimpanzee, and the pongo,<lb break="yes"/>pursued us during five years from the
                    northern to<lb break="yes"/>the southern hemisphere; and we were every<lb
                        break="yes"/>where blamed, in the most cultivated class of so-<lb break="no"
                    />ciety, for being the only persons to doubt the exist-<lb break="no"/>ence of
                    the great anthropomorphous monkey of<lb break="yes"/>America. We shall first
                    observe, that there are<lb break="yes"/>certain regions in which this belief is
                        particularly<lb break="yes"/>prevalent among the people; such are the
                        banks<lb break="yes"/>of the Upper Oronoko, the valley of Upar near the<lb
                        break="yes"/>lake of Maracaybo, the mountains of Santa Mar-<lb break="no"
                    />tha and of Merida, the provinces of Quixos, and<lb break="yes"/>the banks of
                    the Amazon near Tomependa. In all<lb break="yes"/>these places, so distant one
                    from the other, it is<lb break="yes"/>repeated, that the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >salvaje</hi> is easily recognized by<lb break="yes"/>the traces of his
                    feet, the toes of which are turned<lb break="yes"/>backward. But if there exist
                    a monkey of a large<lb break="yes"/>size in the New Continent, how has it
                        happened<lb break="yes"/>that during three centuries no man worthy of be-<lb
                        break="no"/>lief has been able to procure the skin of one?&#x2014;<lb
                        break="yes"/>Several hypotheses present themselves to the mind<lb
                        break="yes"/>in order to explain the source of so ancient an er-<lb
                        break="no"/>ror or belief. Has the famous <hi rendition="#i">capuchin</hi>
                        monkey<lb break="yes"/>of Esmeralda, the canine teeth of which are more<lb
                        break="yes"/>than six lines and a half long, the physiognomy<lb break="yes"
                    />much more like man&#x2019;s than that of the ourang<lb break="yes"/>outang,
                    and which, when irritated, rubs its beard<lb break="yes"/>with its hand, given
                    rise to the fable of the <hi rendition="#i">salvaje?</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>It is not so large indeed as the coaita (<hi rendition="#i"
                        >simia panis-<lb break="no"/>cus</hi>,) but when seen at the top of a tree,
                    and the<lb break="yes"/>head only visible, it might easily be taken for a hu-<lb
                        break="no"/>man being. It may be also (and this opinion ap-<lb break="no"
                    />pears to me the most probable) that the man of<lb break="yes"/>the woods was
                    one of those large bears, the foot-<lb break="no"/>steps of which resemble those
                    of a man, and which<lb break="yes"/>is believed in every country to attack
                        women.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>The animal killed in my time at the foot of
                        the<lb break="yes"/>mountains of Merida, and sent by the name of<lb
                        break="yes"/><hi rendition="#i">salvaje</hi> to Colonel Ungaro, the governor
                    of the<lb break="yes"/>province Varinas, was in fact a bear, with black<lb
                        break="yes"/>and smooth fur.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These extraordinary accounts are succeeded by<lb break="yes"/>a detailed history of the Moschettoes of this re-<lb break="no"/>gion; perhaps the most remarkable of all its ani-<lb break="no"/>mal phenomena.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Persons who have not navigated the great riv-<lb break="no"/>ers of
                    equinoctial America, for instance, the Oro-<lb break="no"/>noko and the Rio
                    Magdalena, can scarcely con-<lb break="no"/>ceive, how without interruntion, at
                    every instant of<lb break="yes"/>life, you may be tormented by insects flying in
                        the<lb break="yes"/>air, and how the multitude of these little animals<lb
                        break="yes"/>may render vast regions wholly uninhabitable.&#x2014;<lb
                        break="yes"/>However accustomed you may be to endure pain<lb break="yes"
                    />without complaint, however lively an interest you<lb break="yes"/>may take in
                    the objects of your researches, it is<lb break="yes"/>impossible not to be
                    constantly disturbed by the<lb break="yes"/>moschettoes, <hi rendition="#i"
                        >zancudoes, jejens</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">tempraneroes</hi>,<lb
                        break="yes"/>that cover the face and hands, pierce the clothes<lb
                        break="yes"/>with their long sucker in the form of a needle,<lb break="yes"
                    />and, getting into the mouth and nostrils, set you<lb break="yes"/>coughing and
                    sneezing whenever you attempt to<lb break="yes"/>speak in the open air. In the
                    missions of the Oro-<lb break="no"/>noko, in the villages placed on the banks of
                        the<lb break="yes"/>river, surrounded by immense forests, the <hi
                        rendition="#i">plaga de<lb break="yes"/>las moscas</hi>, the plague of the
                    flies, affords an inex-<lb break="no"/>haustible subject of conversation. When
                        two<lb break="yes"/>persons meet in the morning, the first questions<lb
                        break="yes"/>they address to each other are, &#x2018;How did you find<lb
                        break="yes"/>the zancudoes during the night? How are we to-<lb break="no"
                    />day for the moschettoes?&#x2019; These questions remind<lb break="yes"/>us of
                    a Chinese form of politeness, which indi-<lb break="no"/>cates the ancient state
                    of the country where it<lb break="yes"/>took birth. Salutations were made
                    heretofore in<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">celestial empire</hi>, in
                    the following words, <hi rendition="#i">vou-tou-<lb break="maybe"/>hou</hi>,
                    &#x2018;Have you been incommoded in the night by<lb break="yes"/>the
                    serpents?&#x2019; We shall soon see, that on the<lb break="yes"/>banks of the
                    Tuamini, in the river Magdalena, and<lb break="yes"/>still more at Choco, the
                    country of gold and plati-<lb break="no"/>na, the Chinese compliment on the
                    serpents might<lb break="yes"/>be added to that of the moschettoes.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;At Mandavaca we found an old Missionary,<lb break="yes"/>who told us with an air of sadness, that he had<lb break="yes"/>spent <hi rendition="#i">his twenty years of moschettoes</hi> in America.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>He desired us to look well at his legs, that we<lb break="yes"/>might be able to tell one day, &#x2018;poor alla (beyond<lb break="yes"/>sea,) what the poor monks suffer in the forests of<lb break="yes"/>Cassiquiare.&#x2019; Every sting leaving a small darkish<lb break="yes"/>brown point, his legs were so speckled, that it was<lb break="yes"/>difficult to recognize the whiteness of his skin<lb break="yes"/>through the spots of coagulated blood. If the in-<lb break="no" />sects of the simulium genus abound in the Cassi-<lb break="no"/>quiare, which has <hi rendition="#i">white waters</hi>, the culices, or <hi rendition="#i" >zan-<lb break="no"/>cudoes</hi>, are so much the more rare; you scarcely<lb break="yes"/>find any there, while on the rivers of <hi rendition="#i">black waters</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>in the Atavapo and the Rio Negro, there are gen-<lb break="no"/>erally some <hi rendition="#i" >zancudoes</hi> and no <hi rendition="#i">moschettoes.</hi>&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 