<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="219" facs="#f0001" />
            <cb/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#b">MEMOIR OF DON JOSE CELESTINO<lb/>MUTIS.</hi>
                    <lb/>Translated from the French of the Baron de Humboldt, by Colonel<lb/>R. WRIGHT, late Governor of the Province of Loxa, Consul<lb/>General for the Republic of the Equator.</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Don Jose Celestino Mutis,</hi> director of the<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Botanical Expedition</hi> of the kingdom of New<lb/>Granada,<note place="foot" n="*">Now the republic.</note> and astronomer royal at Santa Fé<lb/>de Bogota, was born in Cadiz in 1732, of a<lb/>family in easy circumstances. He is best<lb/>known in Europe through his vast knowledge<lb/>and researches in Botany. Linn&#x00E6;us terms<lb/>him, &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">phytologorum Americanorum princeps;</hi>&#x201D;<lb/>but the services he has rendered to all the<lb/>branches of natural history, &#x2014; the discovery of<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">quinquinas</hi> in regions where their existence<lb/>was unknown, the beneficent influence which<lb/>he has exercised upon the civilisation and en-<lb/>lightenment of the Spanish colonies, assign to<lb/>him a distinguished station amongst the men<lb/>who have illustrated the new world.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>After having applied himself with un-<lb/>common ardour to the study of mathe-<lb/>matics, Mutis was forced by his parents to<lb/>direct his attention to practical medicine, and<lb/>pursued his courses at the college of San Fer-<lb/>nando de Cadiz; he took his degrees at Se-<lb/>villa, and, in 1757, was named substitute of a<lb/>chair of anatomy at Madrid. During a sojourn<lb/>of three years in the Spanish capital, he took<lb/>more delight in botanical excursions than in<lb/>visiting the hospitals, and he had the rare good<lb/>fortune of acquiring the acquaintance of the<lb/>celebrated naturalist of Upsal, who was desirous<lb/>of adding to his herbal collection the plants of<lb/>the Peninsula. This correspondence of Mutis<lb/>with Linn&#x00E6;us became of still greater import-<lb/>ance to science, inasmuch as the viceroy, Don<lb/>Pedro Mexia de la Cerda engaged the former<lb/>to accompany him to America in the quality<lb/>of physician, 1750. Our young botanist had<lb/>been named by the ministry amongst the per-<lb/>sons selected to terminate their studies at<lb/>Paris, Leyden and Bologna, but he did not<lb/>hesitate a moment in sacrificing the prospect<lb/>of visiting the most renowned universities of<lb/>Europe, to the advantages and attractions of a<lb/>distant expedition.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>On his arrival at New Granada, he was<lb/>vividly struck with the natural richness of a<lb/>country where different climates are encoun-<lb/>tered in progressive succession, one above an-<lb/>other, with the regularity of a flight of stairs.<lb/>After remaining for a long period in Cartha-<lb/>gena, Turbaco, and Honda, (chief port of the<lb/>river Magdelena), Mutis accompanied the<lb/>viceroy on his journey to Bogota, situate on<lb/>the table land <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Of the Andes.</note> 1365 toises above the level of<lb/>the sea, and possessing a temperature similar<lb/>to that of Bordeaux. Between Honda and<lb/>Bogota he passed through forests containing<lb/>precious species of the cinchona (<hi rendition="#i">quinquina</hi>),<lb/>but until the year 1772, he had not given his<lb/>attention to this useful production.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Named Professor of Mathematics in the<lb/>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Colegio Mayor de nuestra Senora del Rosario,</hi>&#x201D;<lb/>he circulated at Sante Fé de Bogota, the first<lb/>notions of the true planetary system. The<lb/>Dominican Friars did not behold without in-<lb/>quietude that &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">the Heresies of Copernicus,</hi>&#x201D;<lb/>already professed by Bouguer, Godin, and La<lb/>Condamine at Quito, should penetrate into<lb/>New Granada; but the viceroy protected Mu-<lb/>tis against the monks, who would have the<lb/>earth remain immoveable; they, however,<lb/>slowly accustomed themselves to what they yet<lb/>call the &#x201C;hypotheses of the new philosophy.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Mutis, anxious to examine the plants of the<lb/>warm region, and to visit the argentiferous<lb/>mines of New Granada, quitted the table land<lb/>
                    <cb/> of Bogota. He made a long stay, first at<lb/>La Montuosa, between Giron and Pamplona,<lb/>and subsequently (from 1777 to 1782) at Real<lb/>del Zapo, and Mariquita, situate at the foot of<lb/>the Quindio Andes and Paramo of Herveo. It<lb/>was at La Montuosa that he commenced the<lb/>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Grand Flore de la Nouvelle Grenade,</hi>&#x201D; a bo-<lb/>tanical work at which he laboured without<lb/>intermission for the space of forty years, and<lb/>which we have reason to fear, never will be<lb/>published in a complete form. Linn&#x00E6;us, in his<lb/>supplement of <hi rendition="#i">Species Plantarum,</hi> and in his<lb/>Mantissa, has named a great number of rare<lb/>species which Mutis remitted him from La<lb/>Montuosa, but by a strange, and for the geo-<lb/>graphy of plants, most unfortunate error, he<lb/>has noted them as coming from Mexico.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The trifling sums which our traveller earned<lb/>by the practice of his art, sometimes at the<lb/>mines, he expended in the formation of a bo-<lb/>tanic library, in the purchase of barometers,<lb/>geod&#x00E6;tical instruments, and glasses to observe<lb/>the occultations of Jupiter&#x2019;s satellites. He en-<lb/>gaged artists to draw the most curious plants, and<lb/>who painted in oil the indigenous animals almost<lb/>all as large as life. The author of this article<lb/>has seen a part of this collection, formed before<lb/>Mutis had become the object of his sovereign&#x2019;s<lb/>munificence. It was also during his sojourn at<lb/>Real del Zapo (1786), that he made the im-<lb/>portant discovery of a quicksilver mine near<lb/>Ibague Viejo, between the Nevada de Tolima<lb/>and the river Saldane. So much useful exer-<lb/>tion met at length with honourable encourage-<lb/>ment. The court of Madrid, at the instance<lb/>of the viceroy, Archbishop Don Antonio Ca-<lb/>ballero y Gongora, resolved (1782) upon found-<lb/>ing, first at Mariquita, and afterwards (1790)<lb/>at Santa Fé de Bogota, a grand establish-<lb/>ment of natural history, under the name<lb/>of &#x201C;Expedicion Real Botanica,&#x201D; at the head of<lb/>which was placed Don Celestino Mutis. An<lb/>immense edifice of the capital was destined for<lb/>this establishment. He included the herbaria,<lb/>school of design, and library, one of the richest<lb/>and most beautiful ever consecrated to such a<lb/>purpose even in Europe, in one sole branch of<lb/>natural history. Mutis had embraced the ec-<lb/>clesiastical state since the year 1772, and was<lb/>named canon of the metropolitan church of<lb/>Santa Fé and Confessor to a convent of nuns.<lb/>Zealous in the discharge of the duties he had<lb/>imposed upon himself, he found no leisure to<lb/>extend his excursions beyond the vicinity of the<lb/>capital, but he despatched the artists attached<lb/>to the &#x201C;Expedicion,&#x201D; to the warm and tem-<lb/>perate regions which surround the table land<lb/>of Bogota. Some Spanish artists, whose ta-<lb/>lents had been perfected by the councils of<lb/>Mutis, formed, in a very few years, a school of<lb/>young painters. The Indians, coloured, and<lb/>indigenous natives of mixed blood, shewed an<lb/>extraordinary disposition to imitate the form<lb/>and colour of the plants. The drawings of the<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Flore de Bogota</hi> were executed on the largest<lb/>sized paper; they chose the branches which<lb/>were most laden with flowers; the analysis or<lb/>anatomy of the fructified parts was subjoined at<lb/>the foot of the drawing&#x2014;generally, each plant<lb/>was represented on three or four large sheets in<lb/>colours and in black at the same time. The<lb/>colours were extracted partly from indigenous<lb/>colouring matter unknown in Europe. Never<lb/>was a collection of drawings executed with<lb/>greater splendour, nor, it may be said, on a<lb/>larger scale. Mutis had taken for his model<lb/>the most admired botanical works of his time,<lb/>those of Jacquin, of L&#x2019;Heritier, and the Abbé<lb/>Cavanilles. The aspect of the vegetation and<lb/>physiognomy of the plants, were pourtrayed<lb/>with astonishing fidelity. Modern botanists<lb/>who study the affinity of vegetables according<lb/>to the insertion and adherence of the organs<lb/>
                    <pb n="220" facs="#f0002" />
                    <cb/> would have wished for a more detailed analysis<lb/>of the fruit and seed. When MM. de Hum-<lb/>boldt and Bonpland were at Bogota in 1801,<lb/>and enjoyed the noble hospitality of Mutis, the<lb/>latter estimated the number of drawings already<lb/>finished at 2000, amongst which 43 species of<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">passiflora</hi> and 123 species of <hi rendition="#i">orchideous</hi>
                    <lb/>plants, deserved particular admiration. Those<lb/>travellers were the more surprised at the rich-<lb/>ness of Mutis&#x2019;s botanic collections (formed by<lb/>himself and his estimable pupils MM. Valen-<lb/>zuela, Zea, Caldas, and his chief painters MM.<lb/>Rizo and Mathis), as the most fertile countries<lb/>of New Granada, the plains of Tolu and San<lb/>Benito Abad, the Andes of Quindio, the pro-<lb/>vinces of Santa Martha, Antioquia, and Choco,<lb/>remained yet unexplored by any botanist. The<lb/>larger the mass of materials gathered by this<lb/>indefatigable <hi rendition="#i">savant</hi> grew, the greater the diffi-<lb/>culties he encountered to publish the fruits of<lb/>his labours. He had copies taken of the draw-<lb/>ings in his <hi rendition="#i">Flore de Bogota,</hi> with the view of<lb/>sending one to Spain, and of preserving the rest<lb/>at Santa Fé. But how could it be hoped the<lb/>scientific world should enjoy this immense<lb/>work, when the <hi rendition="#i">Flora Peruviana et Chilensis</hi>
                    <lb/>of Ruiz and Pavon, notwithstanding the pecu-<lb/>niary succour of the Government and Colonies,<lb/>hardly advanced at an extremely slow pace?<lb/>Mutis was too much attached to the establish-<lb/>ments he had founded&#x2014;he was too fond of<lb/>a country which had become his second home,<lb/>to undertake, at the age of 76, a return to<lb/>Europe.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>He continued, till his death, to accumulate<lb/>materials for his work without deciding on the<lb/>mode of its publication. Accustomed to over-<lb/>come apparently insurmountable obstacles, he<lb/>dwelt with pleasure on the idea of establishing<lb/>some day a press in his house, and of instruct-<lb/>ing his young indigenous pupils, who had<lb/>learned to paint so successfully, in the art of<lb/>engraving. Notwithstanding his advanced<lb/>age, he undertook, in 1802, the construction<lb/>of an observatory in the centre of his garden.<lb/>It is an octagon tower, 72 feet in height, which<lb/>contained, in 1808, a <hi rendition="#i">gnomon</hi> of 37 feet, a<lb/>quarter circle by Sisons, Graham&#x2019;s pendulum<lb/>which La Condamine had left at Quito, two<lb/>chronometers by Emery, and a few of Dollond&#x2019;s<lb/>telescopes.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Mutis had the good fortune not to witness<lb/>the bloody revolutions which have devastated<lb/>those lovely countries: he was overtaken by<lb/>death 11th September, 1808, at a period when<lb/>he was in the enjoyment of all the happiness<lb/>that can be derived from the esteem of honest<lb/>men, from literary glory, and from the cer-<lb/>tainty of having largely contributed to an im-<lb/>proved social state in the New World, by his<lb/>instruction, example, and the practice of every<lb/>virtue.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>We have given a brief sketch of the life of<lb/>Mutis; we shall proceed to a summary men-<lb/>tion of his labours, which embrace nearly all<lb/>the branches of natural science.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Nothing remains of him but a few disser-<lb/>tations, printed in the Memoirs of the Royal<lb/>Academy of Stockholm, for the year 1769, and<lb/>in an excellent journal published at Santa Fé<lb/>in 1794, under the title of <hi rendition="#i">Papel Periodico</hi>;<lb/>but Linn&#x00E6;us&#x2019;s Supplement&#x2014; the works of the<lb/>Abbé Cavanilles, and of M. de Humboldt&#x2014;the<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Seminario del Nuevo Reyno de Granada,</hi> edited<lb/>by M. Caldas, in 1808-9, have published a<lb/>part of his observations. We are ignorant of<lb/>the fate of the manuscripts which this cele-<lb/>brated man left to the care of his friends and<lb/>nearest relatives. M. Caldas, the director of<lb/>the observatory of Santa Fé,&#x2014;the favourite<lb/>pupil of Mutis, Don Salvader Rizo, chief<lb/>painter to the <hi rendition="#i">Botanic Expedition,</hi> and the<lb/>
                    <cb/> greater part of the inhabitants distinguished<lb/>for their talents and acquirements, were all<lb/>put to death<note place="foot" n="*">Note by <hi rendition="#k">Tr.</hi>&#x2014;By the Spanish general, Morillo,<lb/>Caldas requested a respite for a few days to re-<lb/>gulate &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">papers of interest to the world,</hi>&#x201D;&#x2014;the stern<lb/>tyrant refused.</note> during the unhappy reaction of<lb/>the metropolis. The precious collection of<lb/>paintings was sent to Spain, where had been<lb/>previously remitted the inedited matter of the<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Flore du Perou et du Mexique.</hi> We hope that<lb/>when political agitation shall cease in the<lb/>Peninsula, and in the colonies, the labours<lb/>of Mutis may not remain consigned to oblivion,<lb/>like those of Sesse and of Mocino.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>It was the communications which Mutis had<lb/>made to Linn&#x00E6;us that gave him celebrity in<lb/>Europe, long before the works he was pre-<lb/>paring were known to exist. Most of the<lb/>genera, <hi rendition="#i">alstonia, vallea, barnadesia, escallonia,<lb/>manettia, ac&#x00E6;na, brathys, myroxylon, befaria,<lb/>telipogon, brabejum, gomozia,</hi> and many others,<lb/>published in Linn&#x00E6;us&#x2019;s supplement, are due<lb/>to the sagacity of the botanist of Santa Fé.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Speaking of the genus <hi rendition="#i">mutisia,</hi> Linn&#x00E6;us<lb/>adds, <hi rendition="#i">nomen immortale quod nulla &#x00E6;tas unquam<lb/>delebit.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb/>
                <p>It was Mutis who first made known the<lb/>true characters of the genus cinchona. As<lb/>this last has become of great importance, we<lb/>shall endeavour to call to mind the opinions<lb/>heretofore entertained respecting the <hi rendition="#i">quinqui-<lb/>nas</hi> of the New World. La Condamine and<lb/>Joseph de Jussieu had examined, in 1738, the<lb/>trees of the forests of Loxa, which yield the<lb/>febrifuge <hi rendition="#i">quina,</hi> or bark. The first-named<lb/>has published a description and drawing of<lb/>the Peruvian quinquina in the <hi rendition="#i">Memoires de<lb/>l&#x2019;Academie,</hi> the same species made known by<lb/>MM. Humboldt and Bonpland, under the name<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">cinckona condaminea,</hi> and which botanists have<lb/>long confounded with many other kinds, under<lb/>the vague denomination of <hi rendition="#i">cinchona officinalis.</hi>
                    <lb/>This cinchona condaminea, also called <hi rendition="#i">casca-<lb/>rilla fina de Loxa,</hi>*<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">The cascarilla fina of Loxa (orange coloured<lb/>and primitive), called also by the natives of Loxa,<lb/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">cascarilla de Urituzinga,</hi> that is, in the Quichua<lb/>tongue, <hi rendition="#i">bear&#x2019;s nose,</hi> the highland forest in which<lb/>it grows, having a profile when viewed from the<lb/>vallies, somewhat resembling that of a bear.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Tr.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <hi rendition="#i">de Caxanuma,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">de Uritu-<lb/>zinga,</hi> is the species most rare, most precious,<lb/>and without doubt the kind originally em-<lb/>ployed. There are but 100 quintals exported<lb/>annually from Guayaquil, a port of the South<lb/>Sea. *<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">A Port of the Republic of the Equator on the<lb/>Pacific Ocean.</note> The whole exportation of the different<lb/>species of quina from America is annually<lb/>14,000 quintals. Linn&#x00E6;us had formed, since<lb/>1742, his genus <hi rendition="#i">cinchona,</hi> a name derived from<lb/>a vice-queen of Peru. He could only have<lb/>founded the <hi rendition="#i">genus</hi> on the imperfect descrip-<lb/>tion of La Condamine. In 1753, an intendant<lb/>of the mint of Bogota (Don Miguel de San-<lb/>testevan), visited the forests of Loxa, and dis-<lb/>covered on his route, between Popayan and<lb/>Quito, trees of quinquina in many quarters,<lb/>especially near the village of Guanacas and the<lb/>Sitio de los Corrales. He sent samples of<lb/>cinchona to Mutis, and it was upon those sam-<lb/>ples that the latter made the first exact descrip-<lb/>tion of the genus. He lost no time in trans-<lb/>mitting to Linn&#x00E6;us the flower and fruit of the<lb/>yellow quinquina (cinchona cordifolia,) but<lb/>the great naturalist of Upsal, on publishing<lb/>the observations of Mutis, (Syst. Nat. ed. 12,<lb/>page 164,) confounded the yellow quinquina<lb/>with that which La Condamine had described.<lb/>Up to that time, Europe only received the<lb/>febrifuge bark by the ports of the South Sea.<lb/>The tree which furnishes this precious pro-<lb/>
                    <cb/> duction was not yet known north of the paral-<lb/>lel of 2&#x00BD;° lat. boreal. In 1772, Mutis dis-<lb/>covered the quina within 6 leagues of Santa<lb/>Fé de Bogota, in the woods of Tena. This<lb/>important discovery was quickly followed,<lb/>1773, by another of the same plant on the<lb/>route from Honda to Villeta, and at the Mesa<lb/>de Chinga. We have entered into some de-<lb/>tails on this head, because the quinquina of<lb/>New Granada, exported by Carthagena, and<lb/>consequently by a port of the Caribbean Sea,<lb/>nearer to Europe, has had the most beneficial<lb/>influence on colonial industry, and on the<lb/>diminution of the price of febrifuge bark in<lb/>the markets of the old world. Mutis was<lb/>right when he attached great importance to<lb/>this discovery, for which he was never recom-<lb/>pensed by his government. An inhabitant of<lb/>Panama, Don Jose Lopez Ruiz, who himself<lb/>acknowledges, in <hi rendition="#i">Informes al Rey.,</hi> never to<lb/>have known the <hi rendition="#i">quinquinas</hi> of Honda until<lb/>1774, passed a long time for the original dis-<lb/>coverer of the quinas of Santa Fé. He en-<lb/>joyed as such a pension of 10,000 francs,<lb/>until, in 1775, the viceroy of Gongona made<lb/>known to the court the priority of Mutis&#x2019;s<lb/>rights. About the same period, (1776) Don<lb/>Francisco Renjifo found the quinquina in the<lb/>southern hemisphere on the slopes of the Peru-<lb/>vian Andes of Guanuco. It is now to be<lb/>found in the whole length of the Cordilleras,<lb/>at an elevation of from 700 to 1500 toises,<lb/>upon an extent of above 600 leagues, from La<lb/>Paz and Chuquisaca, to the mountains of<lb/>Santa Martha and Merida.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Mutis has the merit of having been the first<lb/>to distinguish the different species of Cinchona,<lb/>some of which, with downy petals, are much<lb/>more active than others whose surface is<lb/>smooth. He has proved, that the active<lb/>species, <hi rendition="#i">whose properties vary with the organic<lb/>structure and form, should not be indiscrimi-<lb/>nately employed.</hi> The <hi rendition="#i">Quinologia</hi> of Mutis,<lb/>which is about to be published at Madrid by<lb/>M. Lagasca, and of which a fragment only has<lb/>been inserted in the <hi rendition="#i">Papel Periodico de Santa<lb/>Fé de Bogota,</hi> Feb. 1794, comprises the whole<lb/>of his medical and botanical researches. That<lb/>work describes a preparation of fermented<lb/>quinquina, in great esteem at Bogota, Quito,<lb/>and Lima, under the name of cerveza de<lb/>quina (beer of quina.)</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Amongst the useful plants in medicine and<lb/>commerce, originally described by Mutis, we<lb/>must reckon the <hi rendition="#i">psychotria emetica,</hi> or ipeca-<lb/>cuanha, (<hi rendition="#i">raisilla</hi>) of the river Magdalena, the<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">toluifera,</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i">myroxylon,</hi> which yield the<lb/>balm of Tolu and of Peru&#x2014;the <hi rendition="#i">winteria gra-<lb/>nadensis,</hi> near neighbour of the <hi rendition="#i">canella alba</hi> of<lb/>our pharmacop&#x0153;ias, and the <hi rendition="#i">alstonia the&#x00E6;for-<lb/>mis,</hi> which furnishes the tea of Bogota, the<lb/>infusion of which cannot be too strongly re-<lb/>commended to travellers who remain any<lb/>length of time exposed to the rain of the<lb/>tropics.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>At Mariquita, in a temperate and delicious<lb/>climate, Mutis formed a small plantation of<lb/>quinquina, cinnamon, (<hi rendition="#i">laurus cinnamomoides,</hi>)<lb/>which abounds in the missions of Andaquies,<lb/>and of indigenous nutmeg (<hi rendition="#i">myristica otova.</hi>)<lb/>The name of this celebrated botanist is also<lb/>attached to a discovery which has greatly in-<lb/>terested the public mind in America. It was<lb/>known that the Indians and negroes who<lb/>worked at the <hi rendition="#i">lavaderos</hi> (washings) of gold<lb/>and platinum, in the province of Choco, were<lb/>possessed of what they called the secret of a<lb/>plant, the most powerful antidote against the<lb/>bite of venemous serpents. Mutis was enabled<lb/>to discover the mystery, and make the plant<lb/>known: it is of the family of the composit&#x00E6;,<lb/>and is known in its native country by the name<lb/>
                    <pb n="221" facs="#f0003" />
                    <cb/> of <hi rendition="#i">vejuco del guaco.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">Found chiefly in Zaruma, a canton of the<lb/>province of Loxa, abounding in venemous rep-<lb/>tiles.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Tr.</hi>
                    </note> MM. Humboldt and<lb/>Bonpland were the first to represent it,<lb/>(<hi rendition="#i">v. Mikania Guaco,</hi> in the <hi rendition="#i">Plant&#x00E6; &#x00C6;quinoc-<lb/>tiales,</hi> vol. 2, p. 85, pl. 105.) This plant has a<lb/>nauseous odour, which appears to affect the<lb/>olfactory organs of the vipers. The scent of the<lb/>guaco mixes itself, no doubt, with the cutane-<lb/>ous transpiration of man: one is considered<lb/>out of danger after a space of time, more or<lb/>less, when the patient has been <hi rendition="#i">curado,</hi> that<lb/>is, when inoculation of the juice of the guaco<lb/>into the dermoid system has been effected.<lb/>Bold experiments made in the house of Mutis<lb/>by MM. Zea, Vargas, and Mathis, and during<lb/>which they were seen to handle with impunity<lb/>the most venemous vipers, have been described<lb/>in the <hi rendition="#i">Seminario de Agricultura</hi> of Madrid,<lb/>1798, vol. 4, p. 397. As the guaco has been<lb/>found in several of the warm vallies of the<lb/>Andes, from Peru down to Carthagena, and<lb/>on the mountains of Varinas, a great number<lb/>of persons owe their recovery to this valuable<lb/>discovery of Mutis. It is to be regretted that<lb/>this plant, which has been frequently con-<lb/>founded with the <hi rendition="#i">Ayapana,</hi> loses its virtue<lb/>when the leaves and trunk are preserved in<lb/>alcohol. The guaco is not found everywhere<lb/>that serpents abound.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>We know but little of the zoological and<lb/>physical labours of Mutis; but we are aware<lb/>he studied for a long time the habits of the<lb/>ants and termites, which in America, as in<lb/>Senegal, construct mounds from five to six feet<lb/>in height. He had painted a number of the<lb/>mammiferous species, of the birds and fishes of<lb/>New Granada. He has described, according<lb/>to the Linn&#x00E6;an method, in the <hi rendition="#i">Memoires de<lb/>l&#x2019;Academie de Stockholm,</hi> of which he was a<lb/>member, a new species of marten, (<hi rendition="#i">viverra<lb/>mapurito.</hi>)</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The manuscripts of Mutis also contained a<lb/>great number of valuable observations on the<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">atmospheric currents,</hi> which appear much more<lb/>distinctly under the tropics than in the tem-<lb/>perate climates, by the horary variations of the<lb/>barometer. This instrument rises and falls, at<lb/>the level of the sea as on the highest table land,<lb/>four times in 24 hours under the torrid zone,<lb/>with such regularity, that one may tell, to<lb/>within a quarter of an hour, the time of day,<lb/>by the simple inspection of the column of<lb/>mercury. It appears that this curious obser-<lb/>vation, which has so much excited the attention<lb/>of scientific men, and the discovery of which<lb/>La Condamine (<hi rendition="#i">Voyage à l&#x2019;Equatcur,</hi> p. 50), has<lb/>so falsely attributed to Godin, had been already<lb/>made at Surinam in 1722, (<hi rendition="#i">Journal Litteraire<lb/>de la Haye</hi> for the year 1722, p. 234.) Father<lb/>Bondier (1742), employed it at Chandernagor;<lb/>Godin (1737), at Quito; Thibault de Chanva-<lb/>lon (1751), at Martinique; Lamanon, in 1786,<lb/>in the South Sea: Mutis avers having found<lb/>that the moon exercises a sensible influence on<lb/>the period and on the extent of the horary va-<lb/>riations, (Caldas, <hi rendition="#i">Seminario de la nuevo Reyno<lb/>de Granada,</hi> vol. 1, p. 55 and 361, No. 3.)</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The man who has displayed such astonish-<lb/>ing activity during forty-eight
                    years of labour<lb/>in the New World, was endowed by nature<lb/>with a most
                    happy physical constitution. He<lb/>was tall in stature; his features bore the
                    im-<lb/>print of nobleness; his air was grave, and his<lb/>manners easy and
                    polite. His conversation<lb/>was as varied as the objects of his studies.
                    If<lb/>he frequently spoke with warmth, he also loved<lb/>to practice that art
                    of listening to which Fon-<lb/>tenelle attached so much value, and which
                    he<lb/>found so rare in his days. Although much<lb/>occupied by a science which
                    requires the most<lb/>
                    <cb/> attentive study of organization, Mutis never<lb/>lost sight of the great
                    problems respecting the<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">physique</hi> of the universe. He travelled over<lb/>the
                    Cordilleras barometer in hand. He deter-<lb/>mined the medium temperature of
                    those table<lb/>lands, which appear, like islets, in the middle<lb/>of the
                    aerial ocean. He had been struck with<lb/>the aspect of the vegetation, which
                    varies ac-<lb/>cording as we descend towards the vallies, or<lb/>climb towards
                    the frozen summits of the Andes.<lb/>Every question connected with the
                    geography<lb/>of plants was to him of the most lively interest,<lb/>and he
                    sought to delineate the limits more or<lb/>less, betwixt which, on the mountain
                    declivi-<lb/>ties, grow the various species of Cinchona.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>This taste for the physical sciences&#x2014;this ac-<lb/>tive curiosity directed to the development of<lb/>the phenomena of organisation and meteorology,<lb/>maintained the empire of his mind to the last<lb/>moment of his life. Nothing proves better the<lb/>superiority of his talent, than the enthusiasm<lb/>with which he received the intelligence of any<lb/>important discovery. He had not seen a che-<lb/>mical laboratory since 1760; but the perusal<lb/>of the works of Lavoisier, of Guyton de Mor-<lb/>veau and Fourcroy, had offered him the most<lb/>valuable knowledge of the state of modern<lb/>chemistry. Mutis encouraged with great in-<lb/>terest the young people who manifested a dis-<lb/>position for study; he furnished them with<lb/>books and instruments, and sent many to travel<lb/>at his proper cost</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>After having spoken of his liberality, and of<lb/>the daily sacrifices he made to science, it is<lb/>unnecessary to extol his disinterestedness. He<lb/>enjoyed all his life the confidence of the vice-<lb/>roys, who exercised unlimited sway in those<lb/>countries; but he only employed his credit for<lb/>the benefit of science&#x2014;to make known modest<lb/>merit, or to plead with courage the cause of<lb/>the unfortunate. His only ambition was to<lb/>aid in the triumph of justice and of truth; he<lb/>fulfilled with zeal, it may be said with auste-<lb/>rity, the duties he had imposed on himself,<lb/>in embracing the ecclesiastical profession,<lb/>but his piety sought not the eclat of renown&#x2014;<lb/>it was mild and sincere, as it ever is, when<lb/>found combined with feeling and elevation of<lb/>character.</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>