<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">The Guahiba Mother</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:58</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.23</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-16-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-16-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-21-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-22-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-23-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-24-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">The Guahiba Mother</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1824</date>
          <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Cabinet; or the Selected Beauties of Literature&lt;/i&gt; (1824), S. 329–330.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="329" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">THE GUAHIBA MOTHER.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">From &#x201C;Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels.&#x201D;</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">where</hi> the Atabapo enters the Rio Temi, and before
                    reaching its<lb break="yes"/>confluence, a granitic hummock, that rises on the
                    western bank, near<lb break="yes"/>the mouth of the Guasacavi, fixed our
                    attention; it is called the <hi rendition="#i">Rock<lb break="yes"/>of the
                        Guahiba woman</hi>, or the Rock of the Mother, <hi rendition="#i">Piedra de
                        la Madre.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>We inquired the cause of so singular a denomination. Father
                        Zea<lb break="yes"/>could not satisfy our curiosity; but some weeks after,
                    another mission-<lb break="no"/>ary, one of the predecessors of this
                    ecclesiastic, whom we found settled<lb break="yes"/>at San Fernando as president
                    of the missions, related to us an event,<lb break="yes"/>which I recorded in my
                    journal, and which excited in our minds the<lb break="yes"/>most painful
                    feelings. If, in these solitary scenes, man scarcely leaves<lb break="yes"
                    />behind him any trace of his existence, it is doubly humiliating for a<lb
                        break="yes"/>European to see perpetuated by the name of a rock, by one of
                        those<lb break="yes"/>imperishable monuments of nature, the remembrance of
                    the moral de-<lb break="no"/>gradation of our species, and the contrast between
                    the virtue of a sa-<lb break="no"/>vage, and the barbarism of civilized man!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In 1797 the missionary of San Fernando had led his Indians to<lb break="yes"/>the
                    banks of the Rio Guaviare, on one of those hostile incursions<lb break="yes"
                    />which are prohibited alike by religion and the Spanish laws. They<lb
                        break="yes"/>found in an <choice><sic>Italian</sic><corr type="editorial"
                            >Indian</corr></choice> hut, a Guahiba mother with three children,
                        two<lb break="yes"/>of whom were still infants. They were occupied in
                    preparing the<lb break="yes"/>flour of Casava. Resistance was impossible; the
                    father was gone to<lb break="yes"/>fish, and the mother tried in vain to flee
                    with her children. Scarcely<lb break="yes"/>had she reached the Savannah, when
                    she was seized by the Indians of<lb break="yes"/>the mission, who go to <hi
                        rendition="#i">hunt men</hi>, like the whites and the negroes in<lb
                        break="yes"/>Africa. The mother and her children were bound, and dragged
                        to<lb break="yes"/>the bank of the river. The monk, seated in his boat,
                    waited the issue<lb break="yes"/>of an expedition, of which he partook not the
                    danger. Had the mo-<lb break="no"/>ther made too violent a resistance, the
                    Indians would have killed her,<lb break="yes"/>for every thing is permitted when
                    they go to the conquest of souls<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">(à la conquista espiritual)</hi>, and it is children in
                    particular they seek to<lb break="yes"/>capture, in order to treat them, in the
                    mission, as <hi rendition="#i">poitos</hi>, or slaves of<lb break="yes"/>the
                    Christians. The prisoners were carried to San Fernando in the<lb break="yes"
                    />hope, that the mother would be unable to find her way back to her<lb
                        break="yes"/>home by land. Far from those children who had accompanied
                        their<lb break="yes"/>father on the day in which she had been carried off,
                    this unhappy<lb break="yes"/>woman showed signs of the deepest despair. She
                    attempted to take<lb break="yes"/>back to her family the children who had been
                    snatched away by<lb break="yes"/>the missionary, and fled with them repeatedly
                    from the village<lb break="yes"/>of San Fernando, but the Indians never failed
                    to seize her anew;<lb break="yes"/>and the missionary, after having caused her
                    to be mercilessly beat-<lb break="no"/>en, took the cruel resolution of
                    separating the mother from the two<lb break="yes"/>children, who had been
                    carried off with her. She was conveyed<lb break="yes"/>alone toward the missions
                    of the Rio Negro, going up the Atabapo.<lb break="yes"/>Slightly bound, she was
                    seated at the bow of the boat, ignorant of the<lb break="yes"/>fate that awaited
                    her; but she judged by the direction of the sun, that<lb break="yes"/>she was
                    removed farther and farther from her hut and her native coun-<lb break="no"
                    />try. She succeeded in breaking her bonds, threw herself into the water,<lb
                        break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="330" facs="#f0002"/> and swam to the left bank of the Atabapo. The
                    current carried her to a<lb break="yes"/>shelf of rock, which bears her name to
                    this day. She landed and took<lb break="yes"/>shelter in the woods, but the
                    president of the missions ordered the In-<lb break="no"/>dians to row to the
                    shore, and follow the traces of the Guahibi. In the<lb break="yes"/>evening she
                    was brought back. Stretched upon the rock <hi rendition="#i">(la Piedra de<lb
                            break="yes"/>la Madre)</hi> a cruel punishment was inflicted on her with
                    those straps of<lb break="yes"/>Manatee leather, which serve for whips in that
                    country, and with which<lb break="yes"/>the alcades are always furnished. This
                    unhappy woman, her hands<lb break="yes"/>tied behind her back with strong stalks
                    of <hi rendition="#i">mavacure</hi>, was then dragged<lb break="yes"/>to the
                    mission of Javita.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>She was there thrown into one of the caravanseras that are called<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Casa del Rey.</hi> It was the rainy season, and the night was profoundly<lb break="yes"/>dark. Forests, till then believed to be impenetrable, separated the<lb break="yes"/>mission of Javita from that of San Fernando, which was twenty-five<lb break="yes"/>leagues distant in a straight line. No other part is known than that of<lb break="yes"/>the rivers; no man ever attempted to go by land from one village to<lb break="yes"/>another, were they only a few leagues apart. But such difficulties do<lb break="yes"/>not stop a mother, who is separated from her children. Her children<lb break="yes"/>are at San Fernando de Atabapo; she must find them again, she<lb break="yes"/>must execute her project of delivering them from the hands of Christ-<lb break="no" />ians, of bringing them back to their father on the banks of the Guaviare.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Guahibi was carelessly guarded in the caravansera. Her arms<lb break="yes" />being wounded, the Indians of Javita had loosened her bonds, unknown<lb break="yes"/>to the missionary and the alcades. She succeeded by the help of her<lb break="yes"/>teeth in breaking them entirely; disappeared during the night; and at<lb break="yes"/>the fourth rising sun was seen at the mission of San Fernando, hover-<lb break="no"/>ing around the hut where her children were confined. &#x201C;What that wo-<lb break="no"/>man performed,&#x201D; added the missionary who gave us this sad narrative,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;the most robust Indian would not have ventured to undertake. She<lb break="yes" />traversed the woods at a season when the sky is constantly covered with<lb break="yes"/>clouds, and the sun during whole days appears but for a few minutes.<lb break="yes"/>Did the course of the waters direct her way? The inundations of the<lb break="yes"/>rivers forced her to go far from the banks of the main stream, through<lb break="yes"/>the midst of woods where the movement of the waters is almost imper-<lb break="no"/>ceptible. How often must she have been stopped by the thorny lianas,<lb break="yes"/>that form a network around the trunks they entwine! How often must<lb break="yes"/>she have swum across the rivulets, that run into the Atabapo! This<lb break="yes"/>unfortunate woman was asked how she had sustained herself during the<lb break="yes"/>four days! She said, that, exhausted with fatigue, she could find no<lb break="yes"/>other nourishment than those great black ants called <hi rendition="#i">vachacos</hi>, which<lb break="yes"/>climb the trees in long bands, to suspend on them their resinous nests.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>We pressed the missionary to tell us, whether the Guahibi had peace-<lb break="no"/>fully enjoyed the happiness of remaining with her children; and if any<lb break="yes"/>repentance had followed this excess of cruelty. He would not satisfy<lb break="yes"/>our curiosity; but at our return from the Rio Negro we learnt, that the<lb break="yes"/>Indian mother was not allowed time to cure her wounds, but was again<lb break="yes" />separated from her children, and sent to one of the missions of the<lb break="yes"/>Upper Oronooko. There she died, refusing all kind of nourishment,<lb break="yes"/>as the savages do in great calamities.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Such is the remembrance annexed to this fatal rock, to <hi rendition="#i">Piedra de<lb break="yes"/>la Madre.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 