<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">The Guahibi mother</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:58</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.23</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-19-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-19-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-21-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-22-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-23-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-24-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">The Guahibi mother</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1828</date>
          <pubPlace>Albany, New York</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;American Masonick Record, and Albany Saturday Magazine&lt;/i&gt; 2:38 (19. Oktober 1828), S. 301.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="301" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#b">THE GUAHIBI MOTHER.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>From Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Where the Atabapo enters the Rio Temi, but be-<lb break="no"/>fore we reached its
                    confluence, a granitick hum-<lb break="no"/>mock, that rises on the western
                    bank, near the<lb break="yes"/>mouth of the Guasacavi, is called the Rock of
                        the<lb break="yes"/>Guahibi Woman, or the Rock of the Mother,<lb break="yes"
                        /><hi rendition="#i">Piedra de la Madre.</hi> We inquired the cause of so<lb
                        break="yes"/>singular a denomination. Father Zea could not<lb break="yes"
                    />satisfy our curiosity; but some weeks after, an-<lb break="no"/>other
                    missionary, one of the predecessors of this<lb break="yes"/>ecclesiastick, whom
                    we found settled at San Fer-<lb break="no"/>nando, as president of the missions,
                    related to us<lb break="yes"/>an event which I recorded in my journal, and
                        which<lb break="yes"/>excited in our minds the most painful feelings. If,<lb
                        break="yes"/>in these solitary scenes, man scarcely leaves be-<lb break="no"
                    />hind him any trace of his existence, it is doubly<lb break="yes"/>humiliating
                    for an European to see perpetuated by<lb break="yes"/>the name of a rock, by one
                    of those imperishable<lb break="yes"/>monuments of nature, the remembrance of
                        the<lb break="yes"/>moral degradation of our species, and the contrast<lb
                        break="yes"/>between the virtues of savage, and the barbarism<lb break="yes"
                    />of civilized men.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In 1797, the missionary of San Fernando had led<lb break="yes"/>his indians to
                    the banks of the Rio Guaviare, on<lb break="yes"/>one of those hostile
                    incursions which are prohibit-<lb break="no"/>ed alike by religion and the
                    Spanish laws. They<lb break="yes"/>found in an Indian hut a Guahibi mother
                        with<lb break="yes"/>three children, two of whom were still infants.<lb
                        break="yes"/>They were occupied in preparing the flour of Cas-<lb break="no"
                    />sava. Resistance was impossible: the father was<lb break="yes"/>gone to fish,
                    and the mother tried in vain to flee<lb break="yes"/>with her children. Scarcely
                    had she reached<lb break="yes"/>the savannah, when she was seized by the In-<lb
                        break="no"/>dians of the mission, who go to <hi rendition="#i">hunt
                        men,</hi> like the<lb break="yes"/>whites and the negroes in Africa. The
                    mother and<lb break="yes"/>her children were bound and dragged to the bank<lb
                        break="yes"/>of the river. The monk, seated in his boat, waited<lb
                        break="yes"/>the issue of an expedition of which he partook not<lb
                        break="yes"/>the danger. Had the mother made too violent a<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> resistance, the Indians would have killed her; for<lb break="yes"/>every
                    thing is permitted when they go to the con-<lb break="no"/>quest of souls, and
                    it is children in particular they<lb break="yes"/>seek to capture, in order to
                    treat them in the mis-<lb break="no"/>sion as <hi rendition="#i">poitos,</hi> or
                    slaves of the christians. The<lb break="yes"/>prisoners were carried to San
                    Fernando, in the hope<lb break="yes"/>that the mother would be unable to find
                    her way<lb break="yes"/>back to her home by land. Far from those chil-<lb
                        break="no"/>dren who had accompanied their father on the day<lb break="yes"
                    />in which she had been carried off, this unhappy<lb break="yes"/>woman showed
                    signs of the deepest despair. She<lb break="yes"/>attempted to take back to her
                    family the children<lb break="yes"/>who had been snatched away by the
                        missionary,<lb break="yes"/>and fled with them repeatedly from the village
                        of<lb break="yes"/>San Fernando, but the Indians never failed to seize<lb
                        break="yes"/>her anew; and the missionary, after having caused<lb
                        break="yes"/>her to be mercilessly beaten, took the cruel resolu-<lb
                        break="no"/>tion of separating the mother from the two children<lb
                        break="yes"/>who had been carried off with her. She was con-<lb break="no"
                    />veyed alone toward the missions of the Negro,<lb break="yes"/>going up the
                    Atabapo. Slightly bound, she was<lb break="yes"/>seated at the bow of the boat,
                    ignorant of the fate<lb break="yes"/>that awaited her; but she judged by the
                        direction<lb break="yes"/>of the sun, that she was removed farther and
                        far-<lb break="no"/>ther from her hut and her native country. She<lb
                        break="yes"/>succeeded in breaking her bonds, threw herself<lb break="yes"
                    />into the water, and swam to the left bank of the<lb break="yes"/>Atabapo. The
                    current carried her to a shelf of<lb break="yes"/>rock which bears her name to
                    this day. She land-<lb break="no"/>ed, and took shelter in the woods; but the
                        presi-<lb break="no"/>dent of the missions ordered the Indians to row to<lb
                        break="yes"/>the shore, and follow the traces of the Guahibi.<lb break="yes"
                    />In the evening she was brought back. Stretched<lb break="yes"/>upon the rock,
                        (<hi rendition="#i">la Piedra de la Madre</hi>) a cruel pun-<lb break="no"
                    />ishment was inflicted on her with those straps of<lb break="yes"/>manatee
                    leather, which serve for whips in that<lb break="yes"/>country, and with which
                    the alcades are always<lb break="yes"/>furnished. This unhappy woman, her hands
                        tied<lb break="yes"/>behind her back with strong stalks of <hi
                        rendition="#i">mavacure,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>was then dragged to the mission of Javita.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>She was there thrown into one of the caravanse-<lb break="no"/>ras that are
                    called <hi rendition="#i">Casa del Rey.</hi> It was the rainy<lb break="yes"
                    />season, and the night was profoundly dark. For-<lb break="no"/>ests till then
                    believed to be impenetrable, separa-<lb break="no"/>ted the mission of Javita
                    from that of San Fernan-<lb break="no"/>do, which was twenty-five leagues
                    distant in a<lb break="yes"/>straight line. No other part is known than that
                        of<lb break="yes"/>the rivers; no man ever attempted to go by land<lb
                        break="yes"/>from one village to another, were they only a few<lb
                        break="yes"/>leagues apart. But such difficulties do not stop a<lb
                        break="yes"/>mother who is separated from her children. Her<lb break="yes"
                    />children are at San Fernando de Atabapo; she<lb break="yes"/>must find them
                    again, she must execute her project<lb break="yes"/>of delivering them from the
                    hands of christians, of<lb break="yes"/>bringing them back to their father on
                    the banks of<lb break="yes"/>the Guaviare. The Guahibi was carelessly guard-<lb
                        break="no"/>ed in the caravansera. Her arms being wounded,<lb break="yes"
                    />the Indians of Javita had loosened her bonds, un-<lb break="no"/>known to the
                    missionary and the alcades. She suc-<lb break="no"/>ceeded by the help of her
                    teeth in breaking them<lb break="yes"/>entirely; disappeared during the night;
                    and at the<lb break="yes"/>fourth rising sun, was seen at the mission of San<lb
                        break="yes"/>Fernando, hovering around the hut where her chil-<lb break="no"
                    />dren were confined. &#x201C;What that woman per-<lb break="no"
                    />formed,&#x201D; added the missionary who gave us this<lb break="yes"/>sad
                    narrative, &#x201C;the most robust Indian would not<lb break="yes"/>have
                    ventured to undertake. She traversed the<lb break="yes"/>woods at a season when
                    the sky is constantly cov-<lb break="no"/>ered with clouds, and the sun during
                    whole days<lb break="yes"/>appears but for a few minutes. Did the course of<lb
                        break="yes"/>the waters direct her way, the inundations of the<lb
                        break="yes"/>rivers forced her to go far from the banks of the<lb
                        break="yes"/>main stream, through the midst of woods, where<lb break="yes"
                    />the movement of the waters is almost impercepti-<lb break="no"/>ble. How often
                    must she have been stopped by<lb break="yes"/>the thorny lianas that form a net
                    work around the<lb break="yes"/>trunks they entwine! How often must she have<lb
                        break="yes"/>swam across the rivulets that run into the Ataba-<lb break="no"
                    />po! This unfortunate woman was asked how she<lb break="yes"/>had sustained
                    herself during the four days. She<lb break="yes"/>said, that exhausted with
                    fatigue, she could find no<lb break="yes"/>other nourishment than those great
                    black ants<lb break="yes"/>called <hi rendition="#i">vachacos,</hi> which climb
                    the trees in long bands<lb break="yes"/>to suspend on them their resinous
                    nests!&#x201D; We<lb break="yes"/>pressed the missionary to tell us whether the
                        Gua-<lb break="no"/>hibi had peacefully enjoyed the happiness of re-<lb
                        break="no"/>maining with her children, and if any repentance<lb break="yes"
                    />had followed this excess of cruelty. He would<lb break="yes"/>not satisfy our
                    curiosity; but at our return from the<lb break="yes"/>Rio Negro we learnt, that
                    the Indian mother was<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> not allowed timo to cure her wounds, but was again<lb break="yes"
                    />separated from her children, and sent to one of the<lb break="yes"/>missions
                    of the Upper Oroonoko. There she died;<lb break="yes"/>refusing all kind of
                    nourishment, as the savages do<lb break="yes"/>in great calamities.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Such is the remembrance annexed to this fatal<lb break="yes"/>rock, &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Piedra de la Madre.</hi>&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 