<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Affecting anecdote of a Guahiba woman</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:58</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.23</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-07-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-07-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-21-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-22-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-23-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-24-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent&lt;/i&gt;, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 2, S. 410–412.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Affecting anecdote of a Guahiba woman</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1821</date>
          <pubPlace>Lexington, Kentucky</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in:&lt;i&gt; The Masonic Miscellany and Ladies’ Literary Magazine&lt;/i&gt; 1:5 (November 1821), S. 192–194.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="192" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>AFFECTING ANECDOTE OF A GUAHIBA WOMAN.<lb break="yes"/>From Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Before we reached its confluence, a granatic hummock, that<lb break="yes"/>rises
                    on the western bank, near the mouth of the Guasacavi, fix-<lb break="no"/>ed our
                    attention; it is called the <hi rendition="#i">Rock of the Guahiba woman,</hi>
                        or<lb break="yes"/>the Rock of the Mother, <hi rendition="#i">Piedra de la
                        Madre.</hi> We inquired the<lb break="yes"/>cause of so singular a
                    denomination. Father Zea could not sat-<lb break="no"/>isfy our curiosity; but
                    some weeks after another missionary, one<lb break="yes"/>of the predecessors of
                    this ecclesiastic, whom we found settled<lb break="yes"/>at San Fernando as
                    president of the missions, related to us an e-<lb break="no"/>vent, which I
                    recorded in my journal, and which excited in our<lb break="yes"/>minds the most
                    painful feelings. If, in these solitary scenes, man<lb break="yes"/>scarcely
                    leaves behind him any trace of his existence, it is doubly<lb break="yes"
                    />humiliating for a European to see perpetuated by the name of a<lb break="yes"
                    />rock, by one of those imperishable monuments of nature, the re-<lb break="no"
                    />membrance of the moral degradation of our species, and the<lb break="yes"
                    />contrast between the virtue of a savage, and the barbarism of<lb break="yes"
                    />civilized man!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In 1797, the missionary of San Fernando had led his Indians<lb break="yes"/>to
                    the banks of the Rio Guaviare, on one of those hostile incur-<lb break="no"
                    />sions, which are prohibited alike by religion and the Spanish<lb break="yes"
                    />laws. They found in an <choice><sic>Italian</sic><corr type="editorial"
                            >Indian</corr></choice> hut, a Guahiba mother with three<lb break="yes"
                    />children, two of whom were still infants. They were occupied<lb break="yes"
                    />in preparing the flour of Cassava. Resistance was impossible;<lb break="yes"
                    />the father was gone to fish and the mother tried in vain to flee<lb
                        break="yes"/>with her children. Scarcely had she reached the savannah,<lb
                        break="yes"/>when she was seized by the Indians of the mission, who go to<lb
                        break="yes"/>hunt men, like the whites and the negroes in Africa. The
                        moth-<lb break="no"/>er and the children were bound and dragged to the bank
                    of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="193" facs="#f0002"/> river. The monk, seated in his boat, waited the
                    issue of an ex-<lb break="no"/>pedition of which he partook not the danger. Had
                    the mother<lb break="yes"/>made too violent a resistance, the Indians would have
                    killed her,<lb break="yes"/>for every thing is permitted when they go to the
                    conquest of souls<lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">a la conquista
                        espiritual,</hi>) and it is children in particular they<lb break="yes"/>seek
                    to capture, in order to treat them in the mission, as <hi rendition="#i"
                        >poitos,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>or slaves to the Christians. The prisoners were carried to
                        San<lb break="yes"/>Fernando in the hope that the mother would be unable to
                    find her<lb break="yes"/>way back to her home, by land. Far from those children
                        who<lb break="yes"/>had accompanied their father on the day in which she had
                        been<lb break="yes"/>carried off, this unhappy woman showed signs of the
                        deepest<lb break="yes"/>despair. She attempted to take back to her family
                    the children<lb break="yes"/>who had been snatched away by the missionary, and
                    fled with<lb break="yes"/>them repeatedly from the village of San Fernando, but
                    the In-<lb break="no"/>dians never failed to seize her anew; and the missionary,
                        after<lb break="yes"/>having caused her to be mercilessly beaten, took the
                    cruel reso-<lb break="no"/>lution of separating the mother from the two
                    children, who had<lb break="yes"/>been carried off with her. She was conveyed
                    alone toward the<lb break="yes"/>mission of the Rio Negro, going up the Atabapo.
                    Slightly bound,<lb break="yes"/>she was seated at the bow of the boat, ignorant
                    of the fate that<lb break="yes"/>awaited her; but she judged, by the direction
                    of the sun, that she<lb break="yes"/>was removed farther and farther from her
                    hut and her native<lb break="yes"/>country. She succeeded in breaking her bonds,
                    threw herself<lb break="yes"/>into the water and swam to the left bank of the
                    Atabapo. The<lb break="yes"/>current carried her to a shelf of rock, which bears
                    her name to<lb break="yes"/>this day. She landed and took shelter in the woods,
                    but the pre-<lb break="no"/>sident of the missions ordered the Indians to row to
                    the shore and<lb break="yes"/>follow the traces of the Guahiba. In the evening
                    she was brought<lb break="yes"/>back. Stretched upon the rock (<hi
                        rendition="#i">la Piedra de la Madre</hi>) a cruel<lb break="yes"
                    />punishment was inflicted on her with those straps of manatee<lb break="yes"
                    />leather, which serve for whips in that country, and with which<lb break="yes"
                    />the alcades are always furnished. This unhappy woman, her<lb break="yes"
                    />hands tied behind her back with strong stalks of mavacure, was<lb break="yes"
                    />then dragged to the mission of Javita.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>She was there thrown into one of the caravanseras that are<lb break="yes"/>called
                    Casa del Rey. It was the rainy season, and the night<lb break="yes"/>was
                    profoundly dark. Forests, till then believed to be impene-<lb break="no"
                    />trable, separated the mission of Javita from that of San Fernan-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="194" facs="#f0003"/> do, which was twenty-five leagues distant in a
                    straight line. No<lb break="yes"/>other part is known than that of the rivers;
                    no man ever attempt-<lb break="no"/>ed to go by land from one village to
                    another, were they only a<lb break="yes"/>few leagues apart. But such
                    difficulties do not stop a mother;<lb break="yes"/>who is separated from her
                    children. Her children are at San<lb break="yes"/>Fernando de Atabapo; she must
                    find them again, she must exe-<lb break="no"/>cute her project of delivering
                    them from the hands of Christians;<lb break="yes"/>of bringing them back to
                    their father on the banks of the Gua-<lb break="no"/>viare. The Guahiba was
                    carelessly guarded in the caravanse-<lb break="no"/>ra. Her arms being wounded,
                    the Indians of Javita had loosen-<lb break="no"/>ed her bonds, unknown to the
                    missionary and the alcades. She<lb break="yes"/>succeeded by the help of her
                    teeth in breaking them entirely;<lb break="yes"/>disappeared during the night;
                    and at the fourth rising sun was<lb break="yes"/>seen at the mission of San
                    Fernando, hovering around the hut<lb break="yes"/>where her children were
                    confined. &#x201C;What that woman perform-<lb break="no"/>ed,&#x201D; added the
                    missionary who gave us this sad narrative, &#x201C;the<lb break="yes"/>most
                    robust Indian would not have ventured to undertake. She<lb break="yes"
                    />traversed the woods at a season when the sky is constantly cov-<lb break="no"
                    />ered with clouds, and the sun during whole days appears but for<lb break="yes"
                    />a few minutes. Did the course of the waters direct her way?<lb break="yes"
                    />The inundation of the rivers forced her to go far from the banks<lb
                        break="yes"/>of the main stream, through the midst of woods where the
                        move-<lb break="no"/>ment of the waters is almost imperceptible. How often
                        she<lb break="yes"/>must have been stopped by the thorny lianas, that form a
                        net-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>work around the trunks they entwine? How often
                    must she have<lb break="yes"/>swum across the rivulets that run into the
                    Atabapo! This un-<lb break="no"/>fortunate woman was asked how she had sustained
                    herself du-<lb break="no"/>ring the four days! She said, that, exhausted with
                    fatigue, she<lb break="yes"/>could find no other nourishment than those great
                    black ants call-<lb break="no"/>ed <hi rendition="#i">vachacos,</hi> which climb
                    the trees in long bands, to suspend on<lb break="yes"/>them their resinous
                    nests.&#x201D; We pressed the missionary to tell<lb break="yes"/>us, whether the
                    Guahiba had peacefully enjoyed the happiness<lb break="yes"/>of remaining with
                    her children; and if any repentance had fol-<lb break="no"/>lowed this excess of
                    cruelty. He would not satisfy our curiosity;<lb break="yes"/>but at our return
                    from the Rio Negro, we learnt that the Indian<lb break="yes"/>mother was not
                    allowed time to cure her wounds, but was again<lb break="yes"/>separated from
                    her children, and sent to one of the missions of<lb break="yes"/>the Upper
                    Oroonoko. There she died, refusing all kind of nour-<lb break="no"/>ishment, as
                    the savages do in great calamities.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 