<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
            <pb facs="#f0002"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#k">Shirt Tree.</hi></head>
                <p>&#x2014;The numerous and well-known voyages<lb/>to the South Sea Islands,
                    &#x0026;c., have made us all well ac-<lb/>quainted with what is called the <hi
                        rendition="#i">bread-tree,</hi> as well as another<lb/>kind, known under the
                    name of the <hi rendition="#i">butter-tree.</hi> But it re-<lb/>mained for the
                    indefatigable M. Humboldt to discover, in<lb/>the wilds of South America, a tree
                    which produces ready-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>made <hi rendition="#i">shirts.</hi>
                    &#x201C;We saw, on the slope of the Sierra <choice>
                        <sic>Dnida</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Duida</corr>
                    </choice>,&#x201D;<lb/>says M. Humboldt, &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i"
                        >shirt-trees</hi> fifty feet high. The In-<lb/>dians cut off cylindrical
                    pieces, two feet in diameter, from<lb/>which they peel the red and fibrous bark,
                    without making<lb/>any longitudinal incision. This bark affords them a sort
                    of<lb/>garment, which resembles sacks, of a very coarse texture,<lb/>and without
                    any seam. The upper opening serves for the<lb/>head, and two lateral holes are
                    cut to admit the arms. The<lb/>natives wear these shirts of marima in the rainy
                    season:<lb/>they have the form of the <hi rendition="#i">ponchos</hi> and <choice>
                        <sic><hi rendition="#i">ruanos</hi></sic>
                        <corr type="editorial"><hi rendition="#i">ruanas</hi></corr>
                    </choice> of cotton,<lb/>which are so common in New Granada, at Quito, and
                    in<lb/>Peru. As, in these climates, the riches and beneficence of<lb/>Nature are
                    regarded as the primary causes of the indolence<lb/>of the inhabitants, the
                    missionaries do not fall to say, in<lb/>shewing the shirts of marima, &#x2018;In
                    the forests of the Oroo-<lb/>noko, garments are found ready made on the
                    trees.&#x2019; We<lb/>may add to this tale of the shirts, the pointed caps,
                    which<lb/>the spathes of certain palm-trees furnish, and which resem-<lb/>ble
                    coarse network.&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Tilloch&#x2019;s
                        Magazine.</hi></p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
