<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="73" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <byline rendition="#k">from the quarterly review.</byline>
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k"> THE INDIAN MOTHER. </hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Many of the settlements formed by the Jesuits upon the<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko
                    are daily becoming less populous, from epidemic<lb break="yes"/>fevers, the
                    small-pox, &amp;c. To prevent the missions from being<lb break="yes"/>wholly
                    deserted, the fathers make hostile incursions into the<lb break="yes"/>villages
                    of the independent Indians, under the name of <hi rendition="#i"
                        >entrados</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>which are avowedly undertaken for
                    &#x201C;the conquest of souls,&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>though it is obviously
                    necessary, in the first place, to secure the<lb break="yes"/>bodies. To effect
                    this, the natives are usually attacked by night<lb break="yes"/>in their hovels,
                    and their children seized and carried off, to be<lb break="yes"/>distributed
                    among the Indians of the missions, as serfs. An<lb break="yes"/>affecting
                    instance of maternal tenderness, displayed on an occa-<lb break="no"/>sion of
                    this inhuman practice, is given by M. de Humboldt,<lb break="yes"/>which, he
                    justly observes, &#x201C;proves how much the system calls<lb break="yes"/>for
                    the care of the legislator.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In 1797 the missionary of San Fernando had led his Indians<lb break="yes"
                    />to the banks of the Rio Guaviare, on one of those hostile incur-<lb break="no"
                    />sions, which are prohibited alike by religion and the Spanish<lb break="yes"
                    />laws. They found in an Indian hut a Guahiba mother with<lb break="yes"/>three
                    children, two of whom were still infants. They were oc-<lb break="no"/>cupied in
                    preparing the flour of cassava. Resistance was im-<lb break="no"/>possible; the
                    father was gone to fish, and the mother tried in<lb break="yes"/>vain to flee
                    with her children. Scarcely had she reached the<lb break="yes"/>savannah, when
                    she was seized by the Indians of the mission,<lb break="yes"/>who go to <hi
                        rendition="#i">hunt men</hi>, like the whites and the negroes in Africa.<lb
                        break="yes"/>The mother and her children were bound, and dragged to the<lb
                        break="yes"/>bank of the river. The monk, seated in his boat, waited the<lb
                        break="yes"/>issue of an expedition, of which he partook not the danger.<lb
                        break="yes"/>Had the mother made too violent a resistance, the Indians
                        would<lb break="yes"/>have killed her, for every thing is permitted when
                    they go to the<lb break="yes"/><pb n="74" facs="#f0002"/>conquest of souls (<hi
                        rendition="#i">à la conquista espiritual</hi>,) and it is children<lb
                        break="yes"/>in particular they seek to capture, in order to treat them in
                        the<lb break="yes"/>mission as <hi rendition="#i">poitos</hi>, or slaves of
                    the Christians. The prisoners<lb break="yes"/>were carried to San Fernando in
                    the hope that the mother would<lb break="yes"/>be unable to find her way back to
                    her home by land. Far from<lb break="yes"/>those children who had accompanied
                    their father on the day in<lb break="yes"/>which she had been carried off, this
                    unhappy woman showed<lb break="yes"/>signs of the deepest despair. She attempted
                    to take back to<lb break="yes"/>her family the children, who had been snatched
                    away by the<lb break="yes"/>missionary; and fled with them repeatedly from the
                    village of<lb break="yes"/>San Fernando, but the Indians never failed to seize
                    her anew;<lb break="yes"/>and the missionary, after having caused her to be
                        mercilessly<lb break="yes"/>beaten, took the cruel resolution of separating
                    the mother from<lb break="yes"/>the two children, who had been carried off with
                    her. She was<lb break="yes"/>conveyed alone toward the missions of the Rio
                    Negro, going<lb break="yes"/>up the Atabapo. Slightly bound, she was seated at
                    the bow of<lb break="yes"/>the boat, ignorant of the fate that awaited her; but
                    she judged<lb break="yes"/>by the direction of the sun, that she was removing
                    farther and<lb break="yes"/>farther from her hut and her native country. She
                        succeeded<lb break="yes"/>in breaking her bonds, threw herself into the
                    water, and swam to<lb break="yes"/>the left bank of the Atabapo. The current
                    carried her to a shelf<lb break="yes"/>of rock, which bears her name to this
                    day. She landed, and<lb break="yes"/>took shelter in the woods, but the
                    president of the missions or-<lb break="no"/>dered the Indians to row to the
                    shore, and follow the traces of<lb break="yes"/>the Guahiba. In the evening she
                    was brought back. Stretched<lb break="yes"/>upon the rock (<hi rendition="#i">la
                        Piedra de la Madre</hi>) a cruel punishment was<lb break="yes"/>inflicted on
                    her with those straps of manatee leather, which<lb break="yes"/>serve for whips
                    in that country, and with which the alcades are<lb break="yes"/>always
                    furnished. This unhappy woman, her hands tied be-<lb break="no"/>hind her back
                    with strong stalks of <hi rendition="#i">mavacure</hi>, was then dragged<lb
                        break="yes"/>to the mission of Javita.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;She was there thrown into one of the caravanseras that are<lb break="yes"
                    />called <hi rendition="#i">Casa del Rey</hi>. It was the rainy season, and the
                        night<lb break="yes"/>was profoundly dark. Forests, till then believed to be
                        impene-<lb break="no"/>trable, separated the mission of Javita from that of
                    San Fer-<lb break="no"/>nando, which was twenty-five leagues distant in a
                    straight line.<lb break="yes"/>No other path is known than that of the rivers;
                    no man ever<lb break="yes"/>attempted to go by land from one village to another,
                    were they<lb break="yes"/>only a few leagues apart. But such difficulties do not
                    stop a<lb break="yes"/>mother who is separated from her children. The Guahiba
                        was<lb break="yes"/>carelessly guarded in the caravansera. Her arms being
                        wound-<lb break="no"/>ed, the Indians of Javita had loosened her bonds,
                    unknown to<lb break="yes"/>the missionary and the alcades. She succeeded by the
                    help of<lb break="yes"/>her teeth in breaking them entirely; disappeared during
                        the<lb break="yes"/>night; and at the fourth rising sun was seen at the
                    mission of<lb break="yes"/>San Fernando, hovering around the hut where her
                        children<lb break="yes"/>were confined. &#x2018;What that woman
                    performed,&#x2019; added the mis-<lb break="no"/><pb n="75" facs="#f0003"
                    />sionary who gave us this sad narrative, &#x2018;the most robust Indian<lb
                        break="yes"/>would not have ventured to undertake. She traversed the<lb
                        break="yes"/>woods at a season when the sky is constantly covered with<lb
                        break="yes"/>clouds, and the sun during whole days appears but for a few<lb
                        break="yes"/>minutes. Did the course of the waters direct her way? The<lb
                        break="yes"/>inundations of the rivers forced her to go far from the banks
                        of<lb break="yes"/>the main stream, through the midst of woods where the
                        move-<lb break="no"/>ment of the waters is almost imperceptible. How often
                        must<lb break="yes"/>she have been stopped by the thorny
                            <choice><sic>hanas</sic><corr type="editorial">lianas</corr></choice>,
                    that form a net-<lb break="no"/>work around the trunks they entwine! How often
                    must she<lb break="yes"/>have swam across the rivulets that run into the
                    Atabapo! This<lb break="yes"/>unfortunate woman was asked how she had sustained
                        herself<lb break="yes"/>during four days? She said that, exhausted with
                    fatigue, she<lb break="yes"/>could find no other nourishment than those great
                    black ants<lb break="yes"/>called <hi rendition="#i">vachacos</hi>, which climb
                    the trees in long bands, to suspend<lb break="yes"/>on them their resinous
                    nests.&#x2019; We pressed the missionary to<lb break="yes"/>tell us whether the
                    Guahiba had peacefully enjoyed the happi-<lb break="no"/>ness of remaining with
                    her children; and if any repentance had<lb break="yes"/>followed this excess of
                    cruelty. He would not satisfy our cu-<lb break="no"/>riosity; but at our return
                    from the Rio Negro we learnt, that<lb break="yes"/>the Indian mother was not
                    allowed time to cure her wounds,<lb break="yes"/>but was again separated from
                    her children, and sent to one of<lb break="yes"/>the missions of the Upper
                    Oroonoko. There she died, refusing<lb break="yes"/>all kind of nourishment, as
                    the savages do in great calamities.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 