<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">SERPENTS IN SOUTH AMERICA.</hi></head><lb/><p>M. Humboldt relates some remarkable particulars con-<lb/>cerning the serpents in South America,
                    and the following<lb/>will show to what perils, from them, the traveller is
                    expos-<lb/>ed. On taking up a night&#x2019;s lodging, we are
                    told&#x2014;&#x201C;Before<lb/>we took possession of the deserted hut, the
                    Indians killed<lb/>two great mapanarc serpents. These grow to four or
                    five<lb/>feet long. They appeared to me to be the same species as<lb/>those I
                    described in the Rio Magdalena. It is a beautiful<lb/>animal, but extremely
                    venomous, white below the belly,<lb/>and spotted with brown and red on the back.
                    As the inside<lb/>of the hut was filled with grass, and as we lay upon
                    the<lb/>ground, there being no means of suspending our hammocks,<lb/>we were not
                    without inquietude during the night. In the<lb/>morning a large viper was found
                    on lifting up from the<lb/>ground the jaguar skin, upon which one of our
                    domestics<lb/>had slept. The Indians say that these reptiles, slow in
                    their<lb/>movements when they are not pursued, creep near a man<lb/>because they
                    are fond of heat. In fact, on the banks of the<lb/>Magdalena, entered the bed of
                    one of our fellow<lb/>travellers, where he remained a part of the night
                    without<lb/>doing him any harm. Without wishing here to take up<lb/>the defence
                    of vipers and rattlesnakes, I believe it may be<lb/>affirmed, that, if these
                    venomous animals had such a dispo-<lb/>sition for offence, as is supposed, the
                    human species would<lb/>certainly not have resisted their numbers in some parts
                    of<lb/>America; for instance, on the banks of the Oroonoko, and<lb/>the humid
                    mountains of Choco.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;In the interior part of the New Continent we almost ac-<lb/>customed ourselves to regard
                    men as not being essential to<lb/>the order of nature. The earth is loaded with
                    plants, and<lb/>nothing impedes their free developement. An immense<lb/>layer of
                    mould manifests the uninterrupted action of orga-<lb/>nic powers. The crocodiles
                    and the boas are masters of<lb/>the river; the jaguar, the pecari, the dante,
                    and the<lb/>monkeys, traverse the forest without fear, and without<lb/>danger;
                        there they dwell as in an ancient inheritance. <choice><sic>Thi</sic><corr type="editorial">This</corr></choice><lb/>aspect of animated
                    nature, in which man is nothing, has<lb/>something in it strange and sad. To
                        this we reconcile <choice><sic>ours<lb break="no"/>selves</sic><corr type="editorial">our-<lb break="no"/>selves</corr></choice> with difficulty on the ocean, and amid the
                        sands <choice><sic>o-</sic><corr type="editorial">of</corr></choice><lb/>Africa; though in these scenes, where nothing recalls <choice><sic>tf</sic><corr type="editorial">to</corr></choice><lb/>mind
                        our fields, our woods, and our streams, we are <choice><sic>leso</sic><corr type="editorial">less</corr></choice><lb/>astonished at the vast
                    solitude through which we pass.<lb/>Here, in a fertile country adorned with
                    eternal verdure, we<lb/>seek in vain the traces of the power of man; we seem to
                    be<lb/>transported into a world different from that which gave us<lb/>birth.
                    These impressions are so much the more powerful<lb/>in proportion as they are of
                    longer duration. A soldier, who<lb/>had spent his whole life in the missions of
                    the Upper Oroo-<lb/>noko, slept with us on the bank of the river. He was
                    an<lb/>intelligent man, who, during a calm and serene night, press-<lb/>ed me
                    with questions on the magnitude of the stars, on the<lb/>inhabitants of the
                    moon, on a thousand subjects of which<lb/>I was as ignorant as himself. Being
                    unable, by my answers,<lb/>to satisfy his curiosity, he said to me in a firm
                    tone: &#x2018;With<lb/>respect to men, I believe there are no more above than
                    you<lb/>would have found if you had gone by land from Javita to<lb/>Cassiquaire.
                    I think I see the stars, as here, a plain cover-<lb/>ed with grass, and a forest
                    (mucho monte) traversed by a<lb/>river.&#x2019; In citing these words, I paint
                    the impression pro-<lb/>duced by the monotonous aspect of those solitary
                    regions.&#x201D;</p></div>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
