<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="4" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">From Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>MATERNAL ATTACHMENT.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In 1797, the missionary of San Fernando<lb break="yes"/>had led his
                    Indians to the Banks of the Rio Gua-<lb break="no"/>viare, on one of those
                    hostile incursions, which<lb break="yes"/>are prohibited, alike by religion and
                    the Spanish<lb break="yes"/>laws. They found in an
                            <choice><sic>Italian</sic><corr type="editorial">Indian</corr></choice>
                    hut, a Guahiba<lb break="yes"/>mother with three children, two of whom were<lb
                        break="yes"/>still infants. They were occupied in preparing<lb break="yes"
                    />the flour of Cassava. Resistance was impossi-<lb break="no"/>ble; the father
                    was gone to fish, and the mother<lb break="yes"/>tried in vain to flee with her
                    children. Scarcely<lb break="yes"/>had she reached the savannah, when she was<lb
                        break="yes"/>seized by the Indians of the mission, who go to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">hunt men,</hi> like the whites and the negroes in<lb
                        break="yes"/>Africa. The mother and her children were bound<lb break="yes"
                    />and dragged to the bank of the river. The monk<lb break="yes"/>seated in his
                    boat, waited the issue of an expe-<lb break="no"/>dition, of which he partook
                    not the danger. Had<lb break="yes"/>the mother made too violent a resistance,
                    the In-<lb break="no"/>dians would have killed her, for every thing is per-<lb
                        break="no"/>mitted when they go to the conquest of souls (<hi rendition="#i"
                            >a<lb break="yes"/>la conquista espiritual,</hi>) and it is children in
                        par-<lb break="no"/>ticular they seek to capture, in order to treat<lb
                        break="yes"/>them, in the mission, as <hi rendition="#i">poitos,</hi> or
                    slaves of the<lb break="yes"/>Christians. The prisoners were carried to San<lb
                        break="yes"/>Fernando in the hope, that the mother would be<lb break="yes"
                    />unable to find her way back to her home, by land.<lb break="yes"/>Far from
                    those children who had accompanied<lb break="yes"/>their father on the day in
                    which she had been car-<lb break="no"/>ried off, this unhappy woman showed signs
                    of the<lb break="yes"/>deepest despair. She attempted to take back to her<lb
                        break="yes"/>family the children who had been snatched away<lb break="yes"
                    />by the missionary, and fled with them repeatedly<lb break="yes"/>from the
                    village of San Fernando, but the Indians<lb break="yes"/>never failed to seize
                    her anew; and the missionary<lb break="yes"/>after having caused her to be
                        mercilessly<lb break="yes"/>beaten, took the cruel resolution of separating
                        the<lb break="yes"/>mother from the two children who had been car-<lb
                        break="no"/>ried off with her. She was conveyed alone to-<lb break="no"
                    />wards the missions of the Rio Negro, going up<lb break="yes"/>the Atabapo.
                    Slightly bound, she was seated at<lb break="yes"/>the bow of the boat, ignorant
                    of the fate that<lb break="yes"/>awaited her; but she judged, by the direction
                        of<lb break="yes"/>the sun, that she was removed farther and far-<lb
                        break="no"/>ther from her hut and her native country. She<lb break="yes"
                    />succeeded in breaking her bonds, threw herself<lb break="yes"/>into the water,
                    and swam to the left bank of the<lb break="yes"/>Atabapo. The current carried
                    her to a shelf of<lb break="yes"/>rock, which bears her name to this day. She<lb
                        break="yes"/>landed, and took shelter in the woods, but the<lb break="yes"
                    />president of the missions ordered the Indians to<lb break="yes"/>row to the
                    shore, and follow the traces of the<lb break="yes"/>Guahibi. In the evening she
                    was brought back.<lb break="yes"/>Stretched upon the rock (<hi rendition="#i">la
                        Piedra de la Madre</hi>)<lb break="yes"/>a cruel punishment was inflicted on
                    her with<lb break="yes"/>those straps of manatee leather, which serve for<lb
                        break="yes"/>whips in that country, and with which the alcades<lb
                        break="yes"/>are always furnished. This unhappy woman,<lb break="yes"/>her
                    hands tied behind her back with strong<lb break="yes"/>stalks of <hi
                        rendition="#i">maracure,</hi> was then dragged to the mis-<lb break="no"
                    />sion of Javita.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;She was there thrown into one of the caravan-<lb break="no"/>seras that
                    are called <hi rendition="#i">Casa del rey.</hi> It was the<lb break="yes"
                    />rainy season, and the night was profoundly dark.<lb break="yes"/>Forests, till
                    then believed to be impenetrable,<lb break="yes"/>separated the mission of
                    Javita from that of San<lb break="yes"/>Fernando, which was twenty-five leagues
                        distant<lb break="yes"/>la a straight line. No other part is known than<lb
                        break="yes"/>that of the rivers; no man ever attempted to go<lb break="yes"
                    />by land from one village to another, were they<lb break="yes"/>only a few
                    leagues apart. But such difficulties<lb break="yes"/>do not stop a mother, who
                    is separated from her<lb break="yes"/>children. Her children are at San Fernando
                        de<lb break="yes"/>Atabapo; she must find them again, she must<lb
                        break="yes"/>execute her project of delivering them from the<lb break="yes"
                    />hands of Christians, of bringing them back to their<lb break="yes"/>father on
                    the banks of the Guaviare. The Gua-<lb break="no"/>hibi was carelessly guarded
                    in the caravansera.<lb break="yes"/>Her arms being wounded, the Indians of
                        Javita<lb break="yes"/>had loosened her bonds, unknown to the mis-<lb
                        break="no"/>sionary and the alcades. She succeeded by the<lb break="yes"
                    />help of her teeth in breaking them entirely; dis-<lb break="no"/>appeared
                    during the night; and at the fourth ri-<lb break="no"/>sing sun was seen at the
                    mission of San Fernan-<lb break="no"/>do, hovering around the hut where her
                        children<lb break="yes"/>were confined. &#x2018;What that woman
                        performed,&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>added the missionary who gave us this sad
                        nar-<lb break="no"/>rative,  &#x2018;the most robust Indian would not
                        have<lb break="yes"/>ventured to undertake. She traversed the woods<lb
                        break="yes"/>at a season when the sky is constantly cov-<lb break="no"/>ered
                    with clouds, and the sun during whole<lb break="yes"/>days, appears but for a
                    few minutes.&#x2014;&#x2014;Did<lb break="yes"/>the course of the waters direct
                    her way?&#x2014;&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>The inundations of the rivers forced
                    her to go<lb break="yes"/>far from the banks of the main stream, through<lb
                        break="yes"/>the midst of woods where the movement of the<lb break="yes"
                    />waters is almost imperceptible. How often must<lb break="yes"/>she have been
                    stopped by the thorny lianas, that<lb break="yes"/>form a net work around the
                    trunks they entwine?<lb break="yes"/>How often must she have swum across the
                        rivu-<lb break="no"/>lets that run into the Atabapo! This unfortun-<lb
                        break="no"/>ate woman was asked how she had sustained her-<lb break="no"
                    />self during the four days. She said, that ex-<lb break="no"/>hausted with
                    fatigue, she could find no other<lb break="yes"/>nourishment than those great
                    black ants called<lb break="yes"/>vachacos, which climb the trees in long bands,
                        to<lb break="yes"/>suspend on them their resinous nests.&#x2019; We pres-<lb
                        break="no"/>sured the missionary to tell us whether the Guahibi<lb
                        break="yes"/>had peacefully enjoyed the happiness of remain-<lb break="no"
                    />ing with her children, and if any repentance had<lb break="yes"/>followed this
                    excess of cruelty. He would not<lb break="yes"/>satisfy our curiosity; but at
                    our return from the<lb break="yes"/>Rio Negro, we learned, that the Indian
                        mother<lb break="yes"/>was not allowed time to cure her wounds, but<lb
                        break="yes"/>was again separated from her children, and<lb break="yes"/>sent
                    to one of the missions of the Upper Oro-<lb break="no"/>noko. There she died,
                    refusing all kind of nour-<lb break="no"/>ishment, as the savages do in great
                    calamities.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 