<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="522" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1">

<div n="2"><head>FROM HUMBOLDT&#x2019;S TRAVELS.</head></div></div><lb/><div n="1"><head>INDIAN RUBBER.</head><lb/><p>&#x201C;Here (says Mr. H.) at the mission of St. Balthasar on the Atabapo, we saw,<lb/>for the first time, that white and fungous substance, which I have made<lb/>known by the name of <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">zapis.</hi> We immediately perceived,<lb/>that it was analogous to the <hi rendition="#i">elastic resin;</hi> but, as the Indians made us un-<lb/>derstand by signs, that it was found under ground, we were inclined to<lb/>think, till we arrived at the mission of Javita, that the <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> was a fossil<lb/>caoutchouc, though different from the elastic bitumen of Derbyshire. A<lb/>Poimisano Indian, seated by the fire, in the hut of the missionary, was em-<lb/>ployed in reducing the <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> into black caoutchouc. He had spitted<lb/>several bits on a slender stick, and was roasting them like meat. The <hi rendition="#i">dapi-<lb/>cho</hi> blackens in proportion as it grows softer, and gains in elasticity. The<lb/>resinous and aromatic smell, which filled the hut, seemed to indicate, that<lb/>this colouration is the effect of the decomposition of a carburet of hydrogen,<lb/>and that the carbon appears in proportion as the hydrogen burns at a low<lb/>heat. The Indian beat the softened and blackened mass with a piece of<lb/>brazil wood, ending in form of a club; he then kneaded the <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> into<lb/>balls of three or four inches in diameter, and let it cool. These balls exactly<lb/>resemble the caoutchouc of the shops, but their surface remains in general<lb/>slightly viscous. They are used at San Balthasar in the Indian game of<lb/>tennis, which is so celebrated among the inhabitants of Uruana and Encara-<lb/><pb n="523" facs="#f0002" />
mada; they are cut into cylinders, to be used as corks, and are far prefer-<lb/>able to those made of the bark of the cork-tree.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>Soon after, the travellers obtained precise information respecting this<lb/>substance: it was
                    shown them at the depth of two or three feet, in a<lb/>marshy soil,
                    &#x201C;between the roots of two trees known by the name of the <hi
                        rendition="#i">jacio</hi><lb/>and the <hi rendition="#i">curvana.</hi> The
                    first is the hevea of Aublet, or siphonia of the mo-<lb/>dern botanists, known
                    to furnish the caoutchouc of commerce in Cayenne<lb/>and the Grand Para; the
                    second has pinnate leaves, and its juice is milky,<lb/>but very thin, and almost
                    destitute of viscosity. The <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> appears to
                    be<lb/>the result of an extravasation of the sap from the roots. This
                    extravasa-<lb/>tion takes place more especially when the trees have attained a
                    great age,<lb/>and the interior of the trunk begins to decay. The bark and
                    alburnum<lb/>crack; and thus is effected naturally, what the art of man performs
                    to col-<lb/>lect in abundance the milky juices of the hevea, the castilloa, and
                    the caout-<lb/>chouc fig-tree.&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
