<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157">
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-18" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="441" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">humboldt&#x2019;s personal narrative.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. Humboldt relates some remarkable<lb break="yes"/>particulars concerning the serpents in South<lb break="yes"/>America, and the following will show to what<lb break="yes"/>perils, from them, the traveller is exposed.<lb break="yes"/>On taking up a night&#x2019;s lodging, we are<lb break="yes" />told &#x2014;&#x201D; Before we took possession of the<lb break="yes"/>deserted hut, the Indians killed two great<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">mapanare</hi> serpents. These grow to four or<lb break="yes" />five feet long. They appeared to me to be<lb break="yes"/>the same species as those I described in<lb break="yes"/>the Rio Magdalena. It is a beautiful ani-<lb break="no"/>mal, but extremely venomous, white below<lb break="yes" />the belly, and spotted with brown and red<lb break="yes"/>on the back. As the inside of the hut was<lb break="yes"/>filled with grass, and as we lay upon the<lb break="yes"/>ground, there being no means of suspending<lb break="yes"/>our hammocks, we were not without in-<lb break="no"/>quietude during the night. In the morn-<lb break="no"/>ing a large viper was found on lifting up<lb break="yes"/>from the ground the jaguar skin, upon<lb break="yes" />which one of our domestics had slept. The<lb break="yes"/>Indians say, that these reptiles, slow in their<lb break="yes"/>movements when they are not pursued, creep<lb break="yes"/>near a man because they are fond of heat.<lb break="yes"/>In fact, on the banks of the Magdalena a<lb break="yes" />serpent entered the bed of one of our fel-<lb break="no"/>low travellers, where he remained a part of<lb break="yes"/>the night, without doing him any harm.<lb break="yes"/>Without wishing here to take up the de-<lb break="no" />fence of vipers and rattlesnakes, I believe<lb break="yes"/>it may be affirmed, that, if these venomous<lb break="yes"/>animals had such a disposition for offence<lb break="yes"/>as is supposed, the human species would<lb break="yes"/>certainly not have resisted their numbers<lb break="yes"/>in some parts of America; for instance, on<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the Oroonoko, and the humid<lb break="yes"/>mountains of Choco.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After this the wanderers entered the Rio<lb break="yes"/>Negro, and the view here taken is both<lb break="yes"/>geographically good and morally affecting.<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;&#x201C; After all we had endured (observes our<lb break="yes"/>interesting author), I may be permitted,<lb break="yes" />perhaps, to speak of the satisfaction we felt<lb break="yes"/>in having reached the tributary streams of<lb break="yes"/>the Amazon, having passed the isthmus that<lb break="yes"/>separates two great systems of rivers, and<lb break="yes"/>in being sure of having fulfilled the most<lb break="yes" />important object of our voyage, the deter-<lb break="no"/>mining astronomically the course of that<lb break="yes"/>arm of the <choice><sic>Oroonnko</sic><corr type="editorial">Oroonoko</corr></choice>, which falls into the<lb break="yes"/>Rio Negro, and of which the existence has<lb break="yes"/>been alternately proved and denied during<lb break="yes"/>half a century. In proportion as we draw<lb break="yes"/>near to an object we have long had in view,<lb break="yes"/>its interest seems to augment. The unin-<lb break="no"/>habited banks of the Cassiquiare, covered<lb break="yes"/>with forests, without memorials of times<lb break="yes"/>past, then occupied my imagination, as do<lb break="yes"/>now the banks of the Euphrates, or the<lb break="yes"/>Oxus, celebrated in the annals of civilized<lb break="yes" />nations. In that interior part of the New<lb break="yes"/>Continent we almost accustomed ourselves<lb break="yes"/>to regard men as not being essential to the<lb break="yes"/>order of nature. The earth is loaded with<lb break="yes" />plants, and nothing impedes their free de-<lb break="no"/>velopement. An immense layer of mould<lb break="yes"/>manifests the uninterrupted action of or-<lb break="no"/>ganic powers. The crocodiles and the boas<lb break="yes"/>are masters of the river; the jaguar, the<lb break="yes"/>pecari, the dante, and the monkeys, tra-<lb break="no"/>verse the forest without fear, and without<lb break="yes"/>danger; there they dwell as in an ancient<lb break="yes"/>inheritance. This aspect of animated na-<lb break="no"/>ture, in which man is nothing, has some-<lb break="no"/>thing in it strange and sad. To this we<lb break="yes"/>reconcile ourselves with difficulty on the<lb break="yes"/>ocean, and amid the sands of Africa; though<lb break="yes"/>in these scenes, where nothing recalls to<lb break="yes"/>mind our fields, our woods, and our streams,<lb break="yes"/>we are less astonished at the vast solitude<lb break="yes"/>through which we pass. Here, in a fertile<lb break="yes"/>country adorned with eternal verdure, we<lb break="yes"/>seek in vain the traces of the power of<lb break="yes"/>man; we seem to be transported into a<lb break="yes"/>world different from that which gave us<lb break="yes"/>birth. These impressions are so much the<lb break="yes" />more powerful, in proportion as they are of<lb break="yes"/>longer duration. A soldier, who had spent<lb break="yes"/>his whole life in the missions of the Upper<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko, slept with us on the bank of the<lb break="yes"/>river. He was an intelligent man, who,<lb break="yes"/>during a calm and serene night, pressed me<lb break="yes"/>with questions on the magnitude of the<lb break="yes"/>stars, on the inhabitants of the Moon, on a<lb break="yes"/>thousand subjects of which I was as igno-<lb break="no"/>rant as himself. Being unable, by my an-<lb break="no"/>swers, to satisfy his curiosity, he said to me<lb break="yes"/>in a firm tone: &#x2018;With respect to men, I<lb break="yes"/>believe there are no more above, than you<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="442" facs="#f0002"/> would have found, if you had gone by land<lb break="yes"/>from Javita to Cassiquiare. I think I see<lb break="yes"/>in the stars, as here, a plain covered with<lb break="yes"/>grass, and a forest <hi rendition="#i">(mucho monte)</hi> traversed<lb break="yes"/>by a river.&#x2019; In citing these words, I paint<lb break="yes"/>the impression produced by the monotonous<lb break="yes"/>aspect of those solitary regions.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We have now conducted our readers to<lb break="yes"/>the 8th book, and, though this notice is<lb break="yes"/>very brief, find this a convenient place to<lb break="yes"/>rest for the present.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 