<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#c">From the Personal Narrative of Baron Humboldt.</hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">SAVAGES ON THE ORONOKO.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Among the causes of the depopulation<lb break="yes"/>of the Randales, I have not reckoned the<lb break="yes"/>small pox; that malady which, in other<lb break="yes"/>parts of America, makes such cruel rava-<lb break="no"/>ges, that the natives, seized with dismay,<lb break="yes"/>burn their huts, kill their children&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>and renounce every kind of society,<note place="foot" n="*">As the M@ in the plans of the M@ury ac-<lb break="no" />cording to the accounts of the American travellers,<lb break="yes"/>@rk and Lewis.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>This scourge is almost unknown on the<lb break="yes"/>baaks of the Or@noko. What depopulates<lb break="yes"/>the Christian settlements is, the repug-<lb break="no"/>nance of the Indians for the regulations<lb break="yes"/>of the missions, the insalubrity of a cli-<lb break="no"/>mate at once hot and damp, bad nourish-<lb break="no"/>ment, want of care in the diseases of chil-<lb break="no"/>dren, and the guilty practice of mothers<lb break="yes"/>of preventing pregdancy by the use of de-<lb break="no" />l@terious herbs. Among the bar@arous<lb break="yes"/>people of Guyana, as well as those of the<lb break="yes"/>half-civilized islands of the South Sea,<lb break="yes"/>young wives will not become mothers. If<lb break="yes"/>they have children, their offspring are ex-<lb break="no"/>posed, not only to the dangers arising<lb break="yes"/>from the strongest popular prejudices.<lb break="yes"/>When twins are born, false notions of<lb break="yes"/>propriety and family honor require, that<lb break="yes"/>one of them should be destroyed. To<lb break="yes"/>bring twins into the world, is to be expo-<lb break="no" />sed to public scorn; it is to rese@ie rats,<lb break="yes"/>opossum@, and the vilest animals, which<lb break="yes"/>bring forth a great number of young at a<lb break="yes"/>time.&#x2019; Nay more: &#x2018;two children born at<lb break="yes"/>the @ame time cannot belong to the same<lb break="yes" />father.&#x2019; This is an axiom of physiology<lb break="yes"/>of the Salivas; and in every zone, and in<lb break="yes"/>different states of society, when the vul-<lb break="no"/>gar seize upon an axiom, they @ere to<lb break="yes"/>it with more sted@astness than the better<lb break="yes"/>@formed men, by whom it was first haz-<lb break="no"/>orded. To avoid a @ of conju-<lb break="no"/>gal tranquility, the old female relations of<lb break="yes"/>the mother, or the <hi rendition="#i">mure jappoice-nei</hi> [mid-<lb break="no"/>wives] take care, that one of the twins<lb break="yes"/>@ disappear. If the new-born infant,<lb break="yes"/>though not a twin, have any physical de-<lb break="no" />formity, the father instantly, puts it to<lb break="yes"/>death. They will have only robust and<lb break="yes"/>@<lb break="yes"/>loquiamo, or the bird <hi rendition="#i">Tikitiki</hi>, the enemy<lb break="yes"/>of the human race. Sometimes children<lb break="yes"/>of a @ble constitution undergo the same<lb break="yes"/>fate. When the father is asked, what i@<lb break="yes"/>@ will pretend<lb break="yes"/>that @ death.<lb break="yes"/>He @ an action, that appears<lb break="yes"/>@ him blamtable, but not criminal.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The poor <hi rendition="#i">mure</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">@</note>&#x201D; he will tell you,<lb break="yes"/>@uld not follow us; we must have wait-<lb break="no"/>ed for him every moment; he has not<lb break="yes"/>been seen again, he did not come to sleep<lb break="yes"/>where we passed the night.&#x2019; Such is the<lb break="yes"/>@ and simplicity of @ers, such<lb break="yes"/>the boasted happiness of man in the <hi rendition="#i">state<lb break="yes"/>@!</hi> He kills his @on, to escape<lb break="yes"/>the @cule of having twins, or to avoid<lb break="yes"/>@ing more slowly; in fact, to avoid<lb break="yes"/>@ inconvenience.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The Indians of Atures,&#x201D; [says Mr.<lb break="yes"/>@ mild, moderate, and accustomed,<lb break="yes"/>from @ effect of their idleness, to the<lb break="yes"/>great@ privations. Formerly, excited to<lb break="yes" />labour by the Jasuits, they did not want<lb break="yes"/>for lood. The fathera cultivated maize,<lb break="yes"/>@, (<hi rendition="#i">frisoles</hi>) and other Euro-<lb break="no"/>pean vegetables; they even planted sweet<lb break="yes"/>orange and tamari@ds round the villages;<lb break="yes"/>@ they possessed twenty or thirty thou-<lb break="no"/>@ head of cows and horses, in, the sa-<lb break="no"/>@ of Atures and Garichana. They<lb break="yes"/>@ at their service a great number of<lb break="yes"/>@ and servants [<hi rendition="#i">peones</hi>] to take care<lb break="yes"/>of their herds. Nothing i@ now cultivat-<lb break="no"/>ed but a little cassava, and a few plantains.<lb break="yes"/>The fertility of the soil however is @uch,<lb break="yes"/>that at Atures I counted on a single<lb break="yes"/>branch of musa 108 @, 4 or 5 of which<lb break="yes"/>would almost suffice for the daily nourish-<lb break="no"/>ment of a man. The culture of maize is<lb break="yes"/>entirely neglected, and the horses and<lb break="yes"/>cows have disappeared. Near the <hi rendition="#i">rau-<lb break="no"/>d@</hi> a part of the village still bears the<lb break="yes"/>name or <hi rendition="#i">passo del ganado</hi> (ford of the cat-<lb break="no"/>tle) while the descend@nts of those very<lb break="yes"/>Indians, whom the Jesuits had as-<lb break="no" />@mbied in a mission, speak of horned<lb break="yes"/>cattle as of animals of a race that is lost.<lb break="yes"/>In going up the Oronoko, toward San<lb break="yes"/>Carlos del Rio Negro, we saw the last<lb break="yes"/>cow at Carichana. The fathers of the<lb break="yes"/>Observance, who now govern these vast<lb break="yes"/>countries, did not immediately succeed<lb break="yes" />the Jesuits. During an interregnum of<lb break="yes"/>eighteen years the missions were visited<lb break="yes"/>only from time to time, and by Capuchin<lb break="yes"/>monks. The agent@ of the secular gov-<lb break="no"/>erument, under the title of <hi rendition="#i">Commissioners<lb break="yes"/>of the King</hi>, managed the <hi rendition="#i">@</hi> or farms<lb break="yes"/>of the Jesuits with culpable negligence.<lb break="yes"/>They killed the cattle in order to sell the<lb break="yes"/>hides. Many heifers were devoured by<lb break="yes"/>tigers, and a greater number perished in<lb break="yes" />consequence of wounds made by the ba@<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i">raudales</hi> which are much less, @<lb break="yes"/>far bolder than the bats of the @<lb break="yes"/>At the time of the expedition of the boun-<lb break="no"/>daries, the @orses of Encaramada, Carich-<lb break="no" />ana, and Aturos, were conveyed as far as<lb break="yes"/>San Jose of Maravitanos, where, on the<lb break="yes"/>banks of the Rio Negro, the Portugueze<lb break="yes"/>could only procure them after a long pas-<lb break="no"/>sage, and of a very inferior quality, by the<lb break="yes" />river Amazon and grand Para. Since<lb break="yes"/>the year 1790, the cattle of the Jesuits<lb break="yes"/>have entirely disappeared. There now<lb break="yes"/>remains in testimony of the ancient culti-<lb break="no" />vation of these countries, and the indus-<lb break="no"/>trious activity of the first missionaries, on-<lb break="no"/>ly a few trunks of the orange and tama-<lb break="no"/>rind in the savannahs, surrounded by<lb break="yes" />wild trees.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The tigers, or jaguars, which are le@<lb break="yes"/>dangerous for the cattle than the bats,<lb break="yes"/>come into the village at Atures, and de-<lb break="no"/>vour the pigs of the poor Indians. The<lb break="yes" />missionary related to us a striking in-<lb break="no"/>stence of the familiarity of these animals,<lb break="yes"/>upon the whole so ferocious. Some<lb break="yes"/>months before our arrival, a jaguar, which<lb break="yes"/>was thought to be young, though of a<lb break="yes"/>large size, had wounded a child in playing<lb break="yes"/>with him; I use confidently this expres-<lb break="no"/>sion, which may seem strange, having on<lb break="yes"/>the spot verified facts which are not with-<lb break="no"/>out interest in the history of the manners<lb break="yes"/>of animals. Two Indian children, a boy<lb break="yes"/>and a girl, about eight and nine years of<lb break="yes"/>age, were seated on the grass near the<lb break="yes"/>village of Atures, in the middle of a sa-<lb break="no"/>vannah, which we have often traversed.<lb break="yes"/>At two o&#x2019;clock in the @<lb break="yes" />issued from the forest, and approached<lb break="yes"/>the children, bounding around them;<lb break="yes"/>sometimes he hid himself in the high<lb break="yes" />grass, sometimes he sprang forward, his<lb break="yes"/>back bent, his head hung down, in the<lb break="yes"/>manner of our cats. The little boy, ig-<lb break="no"/>norant of his danger, seemed to be sensi-<lb break="no"/>ble of it only when the jaguar with one of<lb break="yes"/>his paws gave him some blows on the<lb break="yes"/>head. These blows, at first slight, be-<lb break="no" />came ruder and ruder; the claws of the<lb break="yes"/>jaguar wounded the child, and the blood<lb break="yes"/>flowed with violence. The little girl then<lb break="yes"/>took a branch of a tre@, struck the animal<lb break="yes"/>a@ it fled from her. The Indians ran up<lb break="yes"/>at the cries of the children, and saw the<lb break="yes"/>jaguar, which retired bounding, without<lb break="yes"/>the least show of resistance.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The little boy was brought to us, who<lb break="yes"/>appeared lively and intelligent. The<lb break="yes"/>claw of the jaguar had taken away the<lb break="yes"/>skin from the lower part of the forehead,<lb break="yes"/>and there was a second scar at the top of<lb break="yes"/>the head.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;A mong the monkies,&#x201D; the author con<lb break="yes"/>tinues, &#x201C;which we saw at the mission of<lb break="yes"/>the Atures, we found one new species&#x2019; of<lb break="yes"/>the tribe of <hi rendition="#i">sais</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">sajous</hi>, which the Cre-<lb break="no"/>oles vulgarly call <hi rendition="#i">machis.</hi> It is the <hi rendition="#i">ouava-<lb break="no"/>pavi</hi> with grey hair and a bluish face. It<lb break="yes"/>has the orbits of the eyes and forehead as<lb break="yes" />white as snow, which at first sight distin-<lb break="no"/>guishes it from the <hi rendition="#i">simia sapucina</hi>, the <hi rendition="#i">si-<lb break="no"/>mia apella</hi>, the <hi rendition="#i">simia trepida</hi>, and the oth-<lb break="no"/>er weeping monkeys hitherto so confused-<lb break="no"/>ly described.&#x2014;This little animal is as<lb break="yes" />gentle as is it ugly.&#x2014;Every day in the<lb break="yes"/>court-yard of the missionary it seized a<lb break="yes"/>pig, upon which it remained from mor-<lb break="no"/>ning till night, traveraing the savannahs.<lb break="yes"/>We have also seen it upon the back of a<lb break="yes"/>large cat, which had been brought up with<lb break="yes"/>it in father Zea&#x2019;s house.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;It was among the cataracts that we be-<lb break="no"/>gan to hear of the hairy man of the woods,<lb break="yes"/>colled salvaje, that carries off women,<lb break="yes"/>constructs huts, and sometimes eats hu-<lb break="no" />mau flesh. The Tamanacks call it <hi rendition="#i">achi</hi>,<lb break="yes" />and the Maypures <hi rendition="#i">vasitri</hi>, or <hi rendition="#i">great devil.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>The natives and the missionaries have no<lb break="yes"/>doubt of the existence of this anthropo-<lb break="no"/>morphous monkey, which they singuiatly<lb break="yes"/>dread. Father Gili gravely relates the<lb break="yes"/>history of a lady in the town of San Car-<lb break="no"/>los, who much praised the gentle charac-<lb break="no"/>ter and attentions of the man of the woods.<lb break="yes"/>She lived several years with one in great<lb break="yes"/>@omestic harmony, and only requested<lb break="yes"/>some hunters to take her back &#x2018;because<lb break="yes"/>she was tired, she and her children, (a lit-<lb break="no"/>tle hairy also,) of living far from the<lb break="yes"/>church and the sacraments.&#x2019; The same<lb break="yes" />author, @ding his credulity, con-<lb break="no"/>fesses, that he had not been able to find an<lb break="yes"/>Indian who asserted positively that he<lb break="yes"/>had seen the <hi rendition="#i">salvaje</hi> with his own eyes.<lb break="yes"/>This fable, which the missiounries, the<lb break="yes" />European planters, and the negroes of<lb break="yes"/>@ doubt embellished with<lb break="yes"/>@ from the descrip-<lb break="no"/>tion of the @ the gibbon,<lb break="yes"/>the j@cko or chimpanzec, and the pongo,<lb break="yes"/>pursued us during five years from the<lb break="yes"/>northern to the southern he@phere; and<lb break="yes"/>we were every where blamed, in the mo@t<lb break="yes"/>cultivated class of society, for being the<lb break="yes"/>only persons to doubt the existence of the<lb break="yes" />great anthropomorphous monkey of A-<lb break="no"/>merica. We shall first observe, that there<lb break="yes"/>are certain regions where this belief is<lb break="yes"/>pa@icularly prevalent among the people;<lb break="yes"/>such are the banks of the Upper Oronoko,<lb break="yes"/>the valley of Upar near the lake of Mara-<lb break="no"/>caybo, the mountains of Sauta Martha and<lb break="yes"/>of Merida, the provinces of Quixos, and<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the Amazon near Tomepen-<lb break="no"/>da. In all these places, so distant one<lb break="yes"/>from the other, it is repeated, that the <hi rendition="#i">sal-<lb break="no"/>vaje</hi> is easily recognized by the traces of<lb break="yes"/>his feet, the toes of which are turned back-<lb break="no"/>ward. But if there exist a monkey of a<lb break="yes"/>large @ in the New Continent, how has<lb break="yes"/>it happened that during three centuries no<lb break="yes"/>man worthy of belief has been able to pro-<lb break="no"/>cure the skin of one? Several hypothe-<lb break="no"/>ses present themselves to the mind in or-<lb break="no"/>der to explain the source of so ancient an<lb break="yes"/>error or belief. Has the famous <hi rendition="#i">capuchin</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>monkey of Esmeralda, the canine teeth of<lb break="yes"/>which are, more than six lines and a half<lb break="yes"/>long, the physiognomy much more like<lb break="yes"/>man&#x2019;s than that of the ourang, and which,<lb break="yes"/>when, irritated, rubs its beard with its<lb break="yes"/>hand given rise to the fable of the <hi rendition="#i">salva-<lb break="no"/>je</hi> @ It is not so l@ in@d as the coa-<lb break="no"/>@<lb break="yes"/>might easily be taken for a human being.<lb break="yes"/>It may be also (and this opinion appears<lb break="yes"/>to me the most probable) that the man of<lb break="yes"/>the woods was one of those large bears,<lb break="yes"/>the footsteps of which resemble those of a<lb break="yes"/>man, and which is believed in every coun-<lb break="no"/>try to attack women. The animal killed<lb break="yes"/>in my time at the foot of the mountains<lb break="yes"/>of Merida, and sent by the name of <hi rendition="#i">salva-<lb break="no"/>je</hi> to Colonel Ungaro, the governor of the<lb break="yes"/>province Varinas, was in fact a bear with<lb break="yes"/>black and smooth fur.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These extraordinary accounts are suc-<lb break="no"/>cceded by a detailed history of the Mos-<lb break="no"/>chettoes of this region; perhaps the most<lb break="yes"/>remarkable of all its animal phenomena.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Persons who have not navigated the<lb break="yes"/>great rivers of equinoctial America, for<lb break="yes"/>instance, the Oronoko and the @io Mag-<lb break="no"/>dalena, can scarcely couceive, how with-<lb break="no" />out interruption, at every instant of life,<lb break="yes"/>you may be tormented by insects flying<lb break="yes"/>in the air, and how the multitude of these<lb break="yes"/>little animals may render vast regions<lb break="yes" />wholly uninhabitable. However accus-<lb break="no"/>tomed you may be to endure pain with-<lb break="no"/>out complaint, however lively an interest<lb break="yes"/>you may take in the objects of your re-<lb break="no" />searches, it is impossible not to be con-<lb break="no"/>stantly disturbed by the moschettoes,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">zanchdoes, jojens</hi>, and <hi rendition="#i" >tempraneroes</hi>, that<lb break="yes"/>cover the face and hands, pierce the clo-<lb break="no"/>@res with their long suckers in the form<lb break="yes" />of a needle, and, getting into the mouth<lb break="yes"/>and nostrils, set you coughing and @-<lb break="no"/>ing whenever you attempt to speak in the<lb break="yes"/>open air. In the missions of the Oro-<lb break="no"/>noko, in the villages placed on the banks<lb break="yes"/>of the river, surrounded by immense for-<lb break="no"/>ests, the <hi rendition="#i">plaga de las moscas</hi>, the plague of<lb break="yes"/>the flies, affords an inexhaustible subject<lb break="yes"/>of conversation. When two persons meet<lb break="yes"/>in the morning, the first questions they<lb break="yes" />address to each other are, &#x2018;How did you<lb break="yes"/>find the zancudoes during the night?<lb break="yes"/>How are we to-day for the moschettoes?<lb break="yes"/>These questions remind us of a Chinese<lb break="yes"/>form of politeness, which indicates the<lb break="yes"/>ancient state of the country where it took<lb break="yes"/>birth. Salutations were made heretofore<lb break="yes"/>in the <hi rendition="#i">celestial enpire</hi>, in the following<lb break="yes"/>words, <hi rendition="#i" >vou-@ou-hou</hi>,&#x2018; Have you been in-<lb break="no"/>commoded in the night by the banks of<lb break="yes"/>the Tuamini, in the river Magdalen, and<lb break="yes"/>still more at Choco, the country of gold<lb break="yes"/>and palatina, the Chinese compliment on<lb break="yes"/>the serpents might be added to that of the<lb break="yes"/>moschettoes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x2018;At Mandavaca we found an old Mis-<lb break="no"/>sionary, who told us with an air of sadness,<lb break="yes"/>that he had spent <hi rendition="#i">his twenty years of mas-<lb break="no"/>chettoes</hi> @ America. He desired us to<lb break="yes"/>look well at his lega, that we might be a-<lb break="no" />ble to tell one day, &#x2018;poor alla (beyond<lb break="yes"/>sea.) what the poor monks suffer in the<lb break="yes"/>forests of Cassiquiare&#x2019; Evety sting leav-<lb break="no"/>ing a small darkis@ brown point, his lega<lb break="yes"/>were so speckled, that it was difficult to<lb break="yes" />recognize the whiteness of his skin thro&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>the spots of coagulated blood. @ the<lb break="yes"/>insects of the simulium genus abound in<lb break="yes"/>the Cassiqui@re, which has <hi rendition="#i">white waters</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>the culices, or <hi rendition="#i" >zancudoes</hi>, are so much the<lb break="yes"/>more rare; you scarcely find any there,<lb break="yes"/>while on the rivers of <hi rendition="#i">black waters</hi>, in the<lb break="yes"/>Atabapo and the Rio Negro, there are<lb break="yes"/>generally some <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi> and no <hi rendition="#i">moschet-<lb break="no"/>toes.</hi>&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 