<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="60" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>ANECDOTES OF CROCODILES.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">from humboldt&#x2019;s narrative.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;When the waters (says Mr. H.) are<lb break="yes"/>high, the river inundates the keys; and<lb break="yes"/>it sometimes happens, that even in the<lb break="yes"/>town imprudent men become the prey<lb break="yes"/>of crocodiles. I shall transcribe from<lb break="yes"/>my journal a fact, that took place du-<lb break="no"/>ring Mr. Bonpland&#x2019;s illness. A Guay-<lb break="no"/>keri Indian, from the island de la Mar-<lb break="no"/>garetta, went to anchor his canoe in a<lb break="yes"/>cove, where there were not three feet<lb break="yes"/>of water. A very fierce crocodile, that<lb break="yes" />habitually haunted that spot, seized<lb break="yes"/>him by the leg, and withdrew from the<lb break="yes"/>shore, remaining on the surface of the<lb break="yes"/>water. The cries of the Indian drew<lb break="yes"/>together a crowd of spectators. This<lb break="yes"/>unfortunate man was first seen seeking<lb break="yes"/>with astonishing courage for a knife<lb break="yes" />in the pocket of his pantaloons. Not<lb break="yes"/>being able to find it, he seized the head<lb break="yes"/>of the crocodile, and thrust his fingers<lb break="yes"/>into its eyes. No man in the hot re-<lb break="no"/>gions of America is ignorant, that this<lb break="yes"/>carnivorous reptile, covered with a<lb break="yes"/>buckler of hard and dry scales, is ex-<lb break="no" />tremely sensible in the only parts of his<lb break="yes"/>body which are soft and unprotected,<lb break="yes"/>such as the eyes, the hollow under-<lb break="no"/>neath the shoulders, the nostrils, and<lb break="yes"/>beneath the lower jaw, where there are<lb break="yes"/>two glands of musk. The Guaykeri<lb break="yes"/>Indian had recourse to the same means<lb break="yes"/>which saved the negro of Mungo Park,<lb break="yes"/>and the girl of Uritucu, whom I have<lb break="yes"/>mentioned above; but he was less for-<lb break="no"/>tunate than they had been, for the cro-<lb break="no" />codile did not open its jaws, and lose<lb break="yes"/>hold of its prey. The animal, yielding<lb break="yes"/>to the pain, plunged to the bottom of<lb break="yes"/>the river; and, after having drowned<lb break="yes"/>the Indian, came up to the aurface of<lb break="yes"/>the water, dragging the dead body to<lb break="yes"/>an island opposite the port. I arrived<lb break="yes" />at the moment when a great number of<lb break="yes"/>the inhabitants of Angostura had wit-<lb break="no"/>nessed this melancholy spectacle.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;As the crocodile, on account of<lb break="yes"/>the structure of its larynx, of the<lb break="yes"/>hyoid bone, and of the folds of its<lb break="yes"/>tongue, can seize, though not swallow,<lb break="yes"/>its prey under water; a man seldom<lb break="yes"/>disappears without the animal being<lb break="yes"/>perceived some hours after near the<lb break="yes"/>spot where the misfortune has hap-<lb break="no"/>pened, devouring its prey on a neigh-<lb break="no"/>bouring beach. The number of indi-<lb break="no"/>viduals who perish annually, the vic-<lb break="no"/>tims of their own imprudence and of<lb break="yes"/>the ferocity of these reptiles, is much<lb break="yes"/>greater than it is believed to be in Eu-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/> rope. It is particularly so in villages,<lb break="yes"/>where the neighbouring grounds are<lb break="yes"/>often inundated. The same cr@odiles<lb break="yes"/>remain long in the same places. They<lb break="yes"/>become from year to year more daring,<lb break="yes"/>especially, as the Indians assert, if<lb break="yes"/>they have once tasted of human flesh.<lb break="yes" />These animals are so wary, that they<lb break="yes"/>are killed with difficulty. A ball does<lb break="yes"/>not pierce their skin, and the shot is<lb break="yes"/>only mortal when directed at the throat,<lb break="yes" />or beneath the shoulder. The In-<lb break="no"/>dians, who know little of the use of<lb break="yes"/>fire-arms, attack the crocodile with<lb break="yes" />lances, after it is caught with large<lb break="yes"/>pointed iron books, baited with pieces<lb break="yes"/>of meat, and fastened by a chain to<lb break="yes"/>the trunk of a tree. They do not ap-<lb break="no"/>proach the animal till it has struggled<lb break="yes"/>a long time to disengage itself from<lb break="yes"/>the iron fixed in the upper jaw. There<lb break="yes" />is little probability that a country in<lb break="yes"/>which a labyrinth of rivers without<lb break="yes"/>number brings every day new bands<lb break="yes" />of crocodiles from the eastern back of<lb break="yes"/>the Andes, by the Meta and the Apure,<lb break="yes"/>towards the coast of Spanish Guyana,<lb break="yes"/>should ever be delivered from these<lb break="yes"/>reptiles. All that will be gained by<lb break="yes"/>civilization will be, to render them<lb break="yes"/>more timid, and more easily put to<lb break="yes" />flight.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Affecting instances are related of<lb break="yes"/>African slaves, who have exposed<lb break="yes"/>their lives to save those of their mas-<lb break="no"/>ters, who had fallen into the jaws of<lb break="yes"/>the crocodile.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 