<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">The rock of the mother</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:58</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.23</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-06-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-06-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-21-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-22-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-23-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1821-xxx_The_Guahibi_Mother-24-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent&lt;/i&gt;, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 2, S. 410–412.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">The rock of the mother</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1821</date>
          <pubPlace>St. Thomas, Virgin Islands</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;Sanct Thomas Tidende&lt;/i&gt; 5:460 (16. November 1821), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <head> &#x201C;THE ROCK OF THE MOTHER.&#x201D; <lb/> (<hi rendition="#i">From the
                        new Volume of Humboldt.)</hi>
                </head>
                <lb/>
                <p>Where the Atabapo enters the Rio Temi, the<lb/>narrative says:&#x2014;<lb/>Before
                    we reached its confluence, a granatick<lb/>hummock, that rises on the western
                    bank, near<lb/>the mouth of the Guasacavi, fixed our attention;<lb/>it is called
                    the <hi rendition="#i">Rock of the Guahiba woman</hi>,<lb/>or the Rock of the
                    Mother, <hi rendition="#i">Piedra de la Ma-<lb/>dre.</hi> We inquired the cause
                    of so singular a<lb/>denomination. Father Zea could not satisfy
                            our<lb/><choice><sic>curiosty</sic><corr type="editorial"
                            >curiosity</corr></choice>; but some weeks after, another
                    mis-<lb/>sionary, one of the predecessors of this eccle-<lb/>siastic, whom we
                    found settled at San Fernando<lb/>as president of the missions, related to us
                    an<lb/>event, which I recorded in my journal, and<lb/>which excited in our minds
                    the most painful<lb/>feelings. If, in these solitary scenes, man<lb/>scarcely
                    leaves behind him any trace of his ex-<lb/>istence, it is doubly humiliating for
                    a European<lb/>to see perpetuated, by the name of a rock by<lb/>one of those
                    imperishable monuments of nature,<lb/>the remembrance of the moral degradation
                    of<lb/>our species, and the contrast between the vir-<lb/>tue of a savage, and
                    the barbarism of civilized<lb/>man!</p>
                <p>In 1797 the missionary of San Fernando had<lb/>led his Indians to the banks of
                    the Rio Gua-<lb/>viare, on one of those hostile incursions, which<lb/>are
                    prohibited alike by religion and the Spanish<lb/>laws. They found in an
                            <choice><sic>Italian</sic><corr type="editorial">Indian</corr></choice>
                    hut, a Guahi-<lb/>ba mother with three children, two of whom<lb/>were still
                    infants. They were occupied in pre-<lb/>paring the flour of Cassava. Resistance
                    was<lb/>impossible; the father had gone to fish, and the<lb/>mother tried in
                    vain to flee with her children.<lb/>Scarcely had she reached the savannah,
                    when<lb/>she was seized by the Indians of the mission,<lb/>who go to <hi
                        rendition="#i">hunt men</hi>, like the whites and the<lb/>negroes in Africa.
                    The mother and her chil-<lb/>dren were bound, and dragged to the bank of<lb/>the
                    river. The monk, seated in his boat, wait-<lb/>ed the issue of an expedition, of
                    which he par-<lb/>took not the danger. Had the mother made<lb/>too violent a
                    resistance, the Indians would have<lb/>killed her, for every thing is permitted
                    when<lb/>they go to the conquest of souls <hi rendition="#i">(à la
                        conquista<lb/>espiritual.)</hi> and it is children in particular
                    they<lb/>seek to capture, in order to treat them, in the<lb/>mission, as <hi
                        rendition="#i">poitos</hi>, or slaves of the Christians.<lb/>The prisoners
                    were carried to San Fernando in<lb/>the hope that the mother would be unable
                    to<lb/>find her way back to her home by land. Far<lb/>from those children who
                    had accompanied their<lb/>father on the day in which she had been
                    carried<lb/>off, this unhappy woman showed signs of<lb/>the deepest despair. She
                    attempted to take<lb/>back to her family the children who had been<lb/>snatched
                    away by the missionary, and fled with<lb/>them repeatedly from the village of
                    San Fernan-<lb/>do, but the Indians never failed to seize her<lb/>anew; and the
                    missionary, after having caused<lb/>her to be mercilessly beaten, took the cruel
                    re-<lb/>solution of separating the mother from the two<lb/>children, who had
                    been carried off with her.<lb/>She was conveyed alone toward the missions
                    of<lb/>the Rio Negro, going up the Atabapo. Slightly<lb/>bound, she was seated
                    at the bow of the boat,<lb/>
                    <cb/> ignorant of the fate that awaited her; but she<lb/>judged from the
                    direction of the sun, that she<lb/>was removed farther and farther from her
                    hut<lb/>and her native country. She succeeded in break-<lb/>ing her bonds, threw
                    herself into the water, and<lb/>swam to the left bank of the Atabapo.
                    The<lb/>current carried her to a shelf of rock, which<lb/>bears her name to this
                    day. She landed, and<lb/>took shelter in the woods, but the president of<lb/>the
                    missions ordered the Indians to row to the<lb/>shore, and and follow the traces
                    of the Guahibi.<lb/>In the evening she was brought back. Stretched<lb/>upon the
                    rock (<hi rendition="#i">la Piedra de la Madre</hi>) a cruel<lb/>punishment was
                    inflicted on her with those straps<lb/>of manatee leather, which serves for
                    whips in<lb/>that country, and with which the alcaldes are<lb/>always furnished.
                    This unhappy woman, her<lb/>hands tied behind her back with strong stalks<lb/>of
                        <hi rendition="#i">mavacure</hi>, was then dragged to the mission<lb/>of
                    Javita.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>&#x201C;She was there thrown into one of the ca-<lb/>ravanseras that are called
                        <hi rendition="#i">Casa del Rey</hi>. It<lb/>was the rainy season, and the
                    night was pro-<lb/>foundly dark. Forests, till then believed to
                    be<lb/>impenetrable, separated the mission of Javita<lb/>from that of San
                    Fernando, which was 25 leagues<lb/>distant in a straight line. No
                            <choice><sic>one</sic><corr type="editorial">other</corr></choice> part
                    is known<lb/>than that of the rivers<choice><sic>?</sic><corr type="editorial"
                            >;</corr></choice> no man ever attempted<lb/>to go by land from one
                    village to another, were<lb/>they only a few leagues apart. But such
                    diffi-<lb/>culties do not stop a mother, who is separated<lb/>from her children.
                    Her children are at San<lb/>Fernando de Atabapo; she must find them<lb/>again,
                    she must execute her project of deliver-<lb/>ing them from the hands of
                    Christians, of<lb/>bringing them back to their father on the banks<lb/>of the
                    Guaviare. The Guahibi was carelessly<lb/>guarded in the caravansera. Her arms
                    being<lb/>wounded, the Indians of Javita had loosened her<lb/>bonds, unknown to
                    the missionary and the al-<lb/>caldes. She succeeded by the help of her
                    teeth<lb/>in breaking them entirely; disappeared during<lb/>the night; and at
                    the fourth rising sun was seen<lb/>at the mission of San Fernando, hovering
                    around<lb/>the hut where her children were confined,<lb/>&#x2018;what that woman
                    performed,&#x2019; added the Mis-<lb/>sionary who gave us this sad narrative,
                    &#x2018;the<lb/>most robust Indian would not have ventured to<lb/>undertake. She
                    traversed the woods at a sea-<lb/>son when the sky is constantly covered
                    with<lb/>clouds, and the sun during whole days ap-<lb/>pears but for a few
                    minutes. Did the course of<lb/>the waters direct her way? the inundations
                    of<lb/>the river forced her to go from the banks of the<lb/>main stream, through
                    the midst of woods where<lb/>the movement of the waters is almost
                    imper-<lb/>ceptible. How often must she have been stop-<lb/>ped by the thorny
                    lianas, that form a network<lb/>around the trunks they entwine? How
                    often<lb/>must she have swam across the rivulets, that ran<lb/>into the Atabapo!
                    This unfortunate woman was<lb/>asked how she had sustained herself
                    during<lb/>the four days! She said, that, exhausted with<lb/>fatigue, she could
                    find no other nourishment<lb/>than those great black ants called <hi
                        rendition="#i">vachacos</hi>,<lb/>which climb the trees in long bands, to
                    sus-<lb/>pend on them their resinous nests.&#x2019; We pres-<lb/>sed the
                    Missionary to tell us, whether the Gua-</p>
                <cb/>
                <p>hibi had peacefully enjoyed the happiness of<lb/>remaining with her children; and
                    if any repent-<lb/>ance had followed this excess of cruelty.&#x2014;<lb/>He
                    would not satisfy our curiosity; but at<lb/>our return from the Rio Negro we
                    learned<lb/>that the Indian mother was not allowed to cure<lb/>her wounds, but
                    was again separated from her<lb/>children, and sent to one of the missions of
                    the<lb/>upper Oronooko. There she died, refusing all<lb/>kind of nourishment, as
                    the savages do in great<lb/>calamities.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;Such is the remembrance annexed to this<lb/>fatal rock, to <hi
                        rendition="#i">Piedra de la Madre.</hi>&#x201D; </p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>