<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Crocodiles.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Humboldt, in the volume of his Personal Narrative, thus<lb break="yes"/>speaks of these monsters of the Oroonoco:&#x2014;&#x201C;When the waters<lb break="yes" />are high, the river inundates the quays; and it sometimes<lb break="yes" />happens that, even in the town, imprudent men become the<lb break="yes"/>prey of crocodiles. I shall transcribe, from my journal, a fact,<lb break="yes"/>that took place during M. Bonpland&#x2019;s illness. A Guaykeri<lb break="yes" />Indian, from the Island de la Margaretta, went to anchor his<lb break="yes" />canoe where there were not three feet of water. A very fierce<lb break="yes" />crocodile, that habitually haunted that spot, seized him by the<lb break="yes" />leg, and withdrew from the shore, remaining on the surface of<lb break="yes" />the water. The cries of the Indian drew together a crowd of<lb break="yes" />spectators. This unfortunate man was first seen seeking, with<lb break="yes" />astonishing courage, for a knife in the pocket of his pantaloons.<lb break="yes"/>Not being able to find it, he seized the head of the crocodile,<lb break="yes"/>and thrust his fingers into its eyes. No man, in the hot regions<lb break="yes"/>of America, is ignorant, that this carnivorous reptile, covered<lb break="yes"/>with a buckler of hard and dry scales, is extremely sensible in<lb break="yes"/>the only-parts of his body which are soft and unprotected, such<lb break="yes"/>as the eyes, the hollow underneath the shoulders, the nostrils,<lb break="yes"/>and beneath the lower jaw, where there are two glands of<lb break="yes"/>musk. The Guaykeri Indian had recourse to the same<lb break="yes"/>means which saved the negro of Mungo Park, and the girl of<lb break="yes"/>Urituca, whom I have mentioned above; but he was less for-<lb break="no"/>tunate than they had been, for the crocodile did not open its<lb break="yes"/>jaw, and lose hold of its prey. The animal, yielding to the<lb break="yes"/>pain, plunged to the bottom of the river; and, after having<lb break="yes"/>drowned the Indian, came up to the surface of the water, drag-<lb break="no"/>ging the dead body to an island opposite the port. I arrived<lb break="yes"/>at the moment when a great number of the inhabitants of<lb break="yes"/>Angostura had witnessed this melancholy spectacle. As the<lb break="yes"/>crocodile, on account of the structure of its larynx, of the hyoid<lb break="yes"/>bone, and of the folds of its tongue, can seize, though not<lb break="yes"/>swallow, its prey, under water, a man seldom disappears with-<lb break="no"/>out the animal being perceived, some hours after, near the<lb break="yes"/>spot where the misfortune has happened, devouring its prey on<lb break="yes"/>a neighbouring beach. The number of individuals who perish-<lb break="no"/>ed annually, the victims of their own imprudence and of the<lb break="yes"/>ferocity of these reptiles, is much greater than it is believed to<lb break="yes"/>be in Europe. It is particularly so in villages, where the<lb break="yes"/>neighbouring grounds are often inundated. The same croco-<lb break="no"/>diles remain long in the same places. They become, from<lb break="yes"/>year to year, more daring, especially, as the Indians assert, if<lb break="yes"/>they have once tasted human flesh. These animals are so<lb break="yes"/>wary, that they are killed with difficulty.&#x2014;A ball does not<lb break="yes"/>pierce their skin, and the shot is only mortal when directed at<lb break="yes"/>the throat, or beneath the shoulder. The Indians, who know<lb break="yes"/>little of the use of fire-arms, attack the crocodile with lances,<lb break="yes"/>after it is caught with large pointed hooks, baited with pieces of<lb break="yes"/>meat, and fastened by a chain to the trunk of a tree. They do<lb break="yes"/>not approach the animal till it has struggled a long time to<lb break="yes"/>disengage itself from the iron fixed in the upper jaw. There<lb break="yes"/>is little probability that a country in which a labyrinth of rivers<lb break="yes"/>without number brings every day new bands of crocodiles from<lb break="yes"/>the eastern back of the Andes, by the Meta and the Apure,<lb break="yes"/>towards the coast of Spanish Guiana, should ever be delivered<lb break="yes"/>from these reptiles. All that will be gained by civilization will<lb break="yes"/>be to render them more timid, and more easily put to flight.<lb break="yes"/>Afflicting instances are related of African slaves, who have<lb break="yes"/>exposed their lives to save those of their masters, who had<lb break="yes"/>fallen into the jaws of the crocodile. A few years ago, between<lb break="yes"/>Urituca and the <hi rendition="#i">Mission de Abaxo,</hi> a negro, hearing the cries<lb break="yes"/>of his master, flew to the spot, armed with a long knife <hi rendition="#i">(ma-<lb break="no"/>chette),</hi> and plunged into the river. He forced the crocodile,<lb break="yes"/>by putting out his eyes, to let go his prey, and hide himself<lb break="yes"/>under the water. The slave bore his expiring master to the<lb break="yes"/>shore, but all succour was unavailing to restore him to life.<lb break="yes"/>He died of suffocation, for his wounds were not deep; the<lb break="yes"/>crocodile, like the dog, appears not to close his jaws firmly<lb break="yes"/>while swimming. It is almost superfluous to add, that the<lb break="yes"/>children of the deceased, though poor, gave the slave his<lb break="yes"/>freedom.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 