<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<pb facs="#f0002" />
<milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Shirt Tree.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;The numerous and well<lb/>known voyages to the South Sea Islands,<lb/>&#x0026;c., have made us well acquainted with<lb/>what is called the <hi rendition="#i">bread tree,</hi> as well as anoth@<lb/>er kind, known under the name of the <hi rendition="#i">butter<lb/>tree.</hi> But it remained for the indefatigable<lb/>M. Humbodlt to discover in the wilds of<lb/>South America a tree which produces rea-<lb/>dy made <hi rendition="#i">shirts.</hi></p><lb/><p>&#x201C;We saw on the slope of the Cerra Dui-<lb/>da,&#x201D; says M. Humboldt, &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">shirt trees</hi> fifty feet<lb/>high. The Indians cut off cylindrical pieces<lb/>two feet in diameter, from which they peel<lb/>the red and fibrous bark, without making<lb/>any longitudinal incision. This bark affords<lb/>them a sort of garment, which resembles<lb/>sacks of a very coarse texture, and without<lb/>a seam. The upper opening serves for the<lb/>head, and two lateral holes are cut to admit<lb/>the arms. The natives wear these shirts of<lb/>marima in the rainy season; they have the<lb/>form of the ponchos and ruanas of cotton,<lb/>which are so common in New Grenada, at<lb/>Quito, and in Peru. As in these climates<lb/>the riches and beneficence of nature are re-<lb/>garded as the primary cause of the indolence<lb/>of the inhabitants, the Missionaries do not<lb/>fail to say in showing the shirts of marima,<lb/>&#x2018;in the forests of the Oroonoko, garments are<lb/>found ready made on the trees.&#x2019; We may<lb/>add to this tale of the shirts the pointed caps<lb/>which the spathes of certain palm trees fur-<lb/>nish, and which resembles coarse net work.&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
