<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <teiHeader> <fileDesc> <titleStmt> <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title> <author> <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700"> <surname>Humboldt</surname> <forename>Alexander</forename> <nameLink>von</nameLink> </persName> </author> <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern"> <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"> <surname>Wernicke</surname> <forename>Norbert</forename> </persName> </editor> <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern"> <persName> <surname>Strobl</surname> <forename>Michael</forename> </persName> </editor> <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s"> <persName> <surname>Bärtschi</surname> <forename>Sarah</forename> </persName> <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/> <resp> <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note> </resp> </respStmt> <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd"> <persName> <surname>Wernicke</surname> <forename>Norbert D.</forename> </persName> <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/> <resp> <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note> <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/> </resp> </respStmt> </titleStmt> <editionStmt> <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition> </editionStmt> <publicationStmt> <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern"> <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName> <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName> <address> <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine> <country>Switzerland</country> </address> </publisher> <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace> <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date> <availability> <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p> </licence> </availability> <idno> <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno> <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno> <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno> <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno> <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno> <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno> <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno> <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno> <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno> <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno> </idno> </publicationStmt> <sourceDesc> <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p> </sourceDesc> </fileDesc> <encodingDesc> <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p> <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p> </encodingDesc> <profileDesc> <langUsage> <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language> </langUsage> </profileDesc> <revisionDesc> <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note> </change> <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-18" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note> </change> </revisionDesc> </teiHeader> 
    <text> 
        <front/> 
        <body><pb n="xxx" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng"><head><hi rendition="#i">Personal
                        Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent, during
                        the years</hi> 1799&#x2014;1804. By Alexander de Humboldt, and Aimé
                    Bonpland, &amp;c. &amp;c. London, 1821, 8vo. 2 Vols. pp. 864. </head><p> These
                    volumes, translated by H. Maria Williams, terminate the second volume (in
                    quarto) of M. Humboldt&#x2019;s personal narrative; and belong to a work so
                    universally celebrated, that we need only say, they are, if possible, more
                    thickly studded with pieces of valuable information and curious matter, than the
                    parts which have preceded them.</p><p>We never take up Humboldt but he reminds
                    us of Othello, who &#x2014;Spake of most disastrous chances, Of moving
                    accidents, by flood, and field; Of hair-breadth &#x2019;scapes&#x2014; And
                    portance in his travel&#x2019;s history; Wherein of antres vast, and
                            <choice><sic>desarts</sic><corr type="editorial">deserts</corr></choice>
                    idle, Rough quarries, rocks, and hills whose heads touch heaven,&#x2014; And of
                    the cannibals that each other eat; The Anthropophagi, and men whose heads Do
                    grow beneath their shoulders, he told the marvellous stories. Our author is
                    hardly a trace behind him; and, like the fair Desdemona, we, with greedy ear,
                    devour up his discourse; whence, without further preface, we shall now proceed
                    to draw for the benefit of our readers.</p><p>The natives near the cataracts or
                    raudales of the Oroonoko, up which river M. de Humboldt made his way to a height
                    little known to Europeans, are distinguished by several remarkable prejudices,
                    among which, none are more fatal than those narrated in the following:&#x2014;
                    </p><p>&#x201C;Among the causes of the depopulation of the Raudales, I have not
                    reckoned the small pox; that malady which, in other parts of America, makes such
                    cruel ravages, that the natives, seized with dismay, burn their huts, kill their
                    children, and renounce every kind of society.<note place="foot" n="*">As the
                        Mahas in the <choice><sic>planes</sic><corr type="editorial"
                            >plaines</corr></choice> of the Missoury, according to the accounts of
                        the American travellers, Clark and Lewis.</note> This scourge is almost
                    unknown on the banks of the Oronoko. What depopulates the Christian settlements
                    is, the repugnance of the Indians for the regulations of the missions, the
                    insalubrity of a climate at once hot and damp, bad nourishment, want of care in
                    the diseases of children, and the guilty practice of mothers of preventing
                    pregnancy by the use of deleterious herbs. Among the barbarous people of Guyana,
                    as well as those of the half-civilized islands of the <cb/>South Sea, young
                    wives will not become mothers. If they have children, their offspring are
                    exposed, not only to the dangers of savage life, but also to the dangers arising
                    from the strangest popular prejudices. When twins are born, false notions of
                    propriety and family honour require, that one of them should be destroyed.
                    &#x2018;To bring twins into the world, is to be exposed to public scorn; it is
                    to resemble rats, opossums, and the vilest animals, which bring forth a great
                    number of young at a time.&#x2019; Nay more: &#x2018;two children born at the
                    same time cannot belong to the same father.&#x2019; This is an axiom of
                    physiology of the Salivas; and in every zone, and in different states of
                    society, when the vulgar seize upon an axiom, they adhere to it with more
                    stedfastness than the better informed men, by whom it was first hazarded. To
                    avoid a disturbance of conjugal tranquillity, the old female relations of the
                    mother, or the <hi rendition="#i">mure japoic-nei</hi> (midwives,) take care,
                    that one of the twins shall disappear. If the new-born infant, though not a
                    twin, have any physical deformity, the father instantly puts it to death. They
                    will have only robust and well-made children, for deformities indicate some
                    influence of the evil spirit Ioloquiamo, or the bird <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Tikitiki</hi>, the enemy of the human race. Sometimes children of a feeble
                    constitution undergo the same fate. When the father is asked, what is become of
                    one of his sons, he will pretend, that he has lost him by a natural death. He
                    will disavow an action, that appears to him blameable, but not criminal.
                    &#x2019;The poor <hi rendition="#i">mure</hi>,<note place="foot" n="*">In
                        Tamanack <hi rendition="#i">mure</hi> signifies a child; <hi rendition="#i"
                            >emuru</hi>, a son.</note>&#x201D; he will tell you, &#x2019;could not
                    follow us; we must have waited for him every moment; he has not been seen again,
                    he did not come to sleep where we passed the night.&#x2019; Such is the candour
                    and simplicity of manners, such the boasted happiness of man in the <hi
                        rendition="#i">state of nature</hi>! He kills his son, to escape the
                    ridicule of having twins, or to avoid journeying more slowly; in fact, to avoid
                    a little inconvenience.&#x201D;</p><p>Amid the prodigality and magnificence of
                    nature, such are the moral evils which deform the scene; and we are often
                    compelled to leave the author&#x2019;s glowing descriptions of superb landscape
                    in the torrid zone, to vex our spirits with similar details. But, the able
                    manner in which distant objects and remote similitudes are brought to bear on
                    almost every subject discussed, is the great charm of this work; and we have so
                    vast a quantity of intelligence combined with so rich a fund of amusing
                    anecdote, that the mind never tires. It has been <cb/>alleged, that Mr. H. is
                    too prone to this sort of classification, and to theories built upon it; but
                    however that may be in a philosophical point of view, as a popular performance,
                    it wonderfully enhances the attractions of his narrative. He is, in truth, the
                    very Jacques of travellers; and his way is delectable, &#x201C; compounded of
                    many simples, extracted from many objects; and, indeed, the sundry contemplation
                    of his travels, in which his often rumination wraps him in a most humourous
                    sadness.&#x201D; He morals on every thing; for
                    example:&#x2014;</p><p>&#x201C;The inhabitants of Atures and Maypures, whatever
                    the missionaries may have asserted in their works, are not more struck with
                    deafness by the noise of the great cataracts, than the catadupes of the Nile.
                    When this noise is heard in the plain that surrounds the mission, at the
                    distance of more than a league, you seem to be near a coast skirted by reefs and
                    breakers. The noise is three times as loud by night as by day, and gives an
                    inexpressible charm to these solitary scenes. What can be the cause of this
                    increased intensity of sound in a desert, where nothing seems to interrupt the
                    silence of nature? The velocity of the propagation of sound, far from
                    augmenting, decreases with the lowering of the temperature. The intensity
                    diminishes in air, agitated by a wind, which is contrary to the direction of the
                    sound; it diminishes also by dilatation of the air, and is weaker in the higher
                    than in the lower regions of the atmosphere, where the number of particles of
                    air in motion is greater in the same radius. The intensity is the same in dry
                    air, and in air mingled with vapours; but it is feebler in carbonic acid gas,
                    than in mixtures of azot and oxygen. From these facts, which are all we know
                    with any certainty, it is difficult to explain a phenomenon observed near every
                    cascade in Europe, and which, long before our arrival in the village of Atures,
                    had struck the missionary and the Indians. The nocturnal temperature of the
                    atmosphere is 3° less than the temperature of the day; at the same time the
                    apparent humidity augments at night, and the mist that covers the cataracts
                    becomes thicker. We have just seen, that the hygroscopic state of the air has no
                    influence on the propagation of the sound, and that the cooling of the air
                    diminishes its swiftness.</p>&#x201C;It may be thought, that, even in places not
                inhabited by man, the hum of insects, the song of birds, the rustling of leaves
                agitated by the feeblest winds, occasion, during the day, a confused noise, which we
                perceive the less because it is uniform, and constantly strikes the ear. Now this
                noise, however slightly perceptible it may be, may diminish the intensity of a
                louder, noise; and this diminution may cease, if during the calm of the night the
                song of birds, the hum of insects, and the action of the wind upon the leaves, be
                interrupted. But this reasoning, even admitting its justness, can scarcely be
                applied to the forests of the Oroonoko, where the air is constantly filled by an
                innumerable quantity of moschettoes, where the hum of insects is much louder by
                night than by day, and where the breeze, if ever it be felt, blows only after
                sunset.&#x201D; <p>This hypothesis is well worth further investigations; but we must
                    surrender it to the scientific journals, and continue our more mixed
                    career.</p><p>&#x201C;The Indians of Atures,&#x201D; says Mr. H., &#x201C;are
                    mild, moderate, and accustomed, from the effects of their idleness, to the
                    greatest <cb/>privations. Formerly, excited to labour by the Jesuits, they did
                    not want for food. The fathers cultivated maize, French beans, (<hi
                        rendition="#i">frisoles</hi>), and other European vegetables; they even
                    planted sweet oranges and tamarinds round the villages ; and they possessed
                    twenty or thirty thousand head of cows and horses, in the savannahs of Atures
                    and Carichana. They had at their service a great number of slaves and servants
                        (<hi rendition="#i">peones</hi>), to take care of their herds. Nothing is
                    now cultivated but a little cassava, and a few plantains. The fertility of the
                    soil however is such, that at Atures I counted on a single branch of musa 108
                    fruits, 4 or 5 of which would almost suffice for the daily nourishment of a man.
                    The culture of maize is entirely neglected, and the horses and cows have
                    disappeared. Near the <hi rendition="#i">raudal</hi>, a part of the village
                    still bears the name of <hi rendition="#i">Passo del ganado</hi> (ford of the
                    cattle), while the descendants of those very Indians, whom the Jesuits had
                    assembled in a mission, speak of horned cattle as of animals of a race that is
                    lost. In going up the Oroonoko, toward San Carlos del Rio Negro, we saw the last
                    cow at Carichana. The fathers of the Observance, who now govern these vast
                    countries, did not immediately succeed the Jesuits. During an interregnum of
                    eighteen years, the missions were visited only from time to time, and by
                    Capuchin monks. The agents of the secular government, under the title of <hi
                        rendition="#i">Commissioners of the King</hi>, managed the <hi
                        rendition="#i">hatos</hi> or farms of the Jesuits with culpable negligence.
                    They killed the cattle in order to sell the hides. Many heifers were devoured by
                    tigers, and a greater number perished in consequence of wounds made by the bats
                    of the <hi rendition="#i">raudales</hi>, which are much less, but far bolder
                    than the bats of the Llanos. At the time of the expedition of the boundaries,
                    the horses of Encaramada, Carichana, and Atures, were conveyed as far as San
                    Jose of Maravitanos, where, on the banks of the Rio Negro, the Portugueze could
                    only procure them after a long passage, and of a very inferior quality, by the
                    river Amazon and Grand Para. Since the year 1795, the cattle of the Jesuits have
                    entirely disappeared. There now remains in testimony of the ancient cultivation
                    of these countries, and the industrious activity of the first missionaries, only
                    a few trunks of the orange and tamarind in the savannahs, surrounded by wild
                    trees.</p><p>&#x201C;The tigers, or jaguars, which are less dangerous for the
                    cattle than the bats, come into the village at Atures, and devour the pigs of
                    the poor Indians. The missionary related to us a striking instance of the
                    familiarity of these animals, upon the whole so ferocious. Some months before
                    our arrival, a jaguar, which was thought to be young, though of a large size,
                    had wounded a child in playing with him; I use confidently this expression,
                    which may seem strange, having on the spot verified facts which are not without
                    interest in the history of the manners of animals. Two Indian children, a boy
                    and a girl, about eight and nine years of age, were seated <cb/>on the grass
                    near the village of Atures, in the middle of a savannah, which we have often
                    traversed. At two o&#x2019;clock in the afternoon, a jaguar issued from the
                    forest, and approached the children, bounding around them; sometimes he hid
                    himself in the high grass, sometimes he sprang forward, his back bent, his head
                    hung down, in the manner of our cats. The little boy, ignorant of his danger,
                    seemed to be sensible of it only when the jaguar with one of bis paws gave him
                    some blows on the head. These blows, at first slight, became ruder and ruder;
                    the claws of the jaguar wounded the child, and the blood flowed with violence.
                    The little girl then took a branch of a tree, struck the animal, and it fled
                    from her. The Indians ran up at the cries of the children, and saw the jaguar,
                    which retired bounding, without the least show of resistance.</p><p> &#x201C;The
                    little boy was brought to us, who appeared lively and intelligent. The claw of
                    the jaguar had taken away the skin from the lower part of the forehead, and
                    there was a second scar at the top of the head.&#x201D;</p>&#x201C;It was among
                the cataracts that we began to hear of the hairy man of the woods, called salvaje,
                that carries off women, constructs huts, and sometimes eats human flesh. The
                Tamanacks call it <hi rendition="#i">achi</hi>, and the Maypures <hi rendition="#i"
                    >vasitri</hi>, or <hi rendition="#i">great devil</hi>. The natives and the
                missionaries have no doubt of the existence of this anthropomorphous monkey, which
                they singularly dread. Father Gili gravely relates the history of a lady in the town
                of San Carlos, who much praised the gentle character and attentions of the man of
                the woods. She lived several years with one in great domestic harmony, and only
                requested some hunters to take her back, &#x2018;because she was tired, she and her
                children (a little hairy also), of living far from the church and the
                sacraments.&#x201D; The same author, notwithstanding his credulity, confesses, that
                he had not been able to find an Indian, who asserted positively that he had seen the
                    <hi rendition="#i">salvaje</hi> with his own eyes. This fable, which the
                missionaries, the European planters, and the negroes of Africa, have no doubt
                embellished with many features taken from the description of the manners of the
                ourang outang, the gibbon, the jocko or chimpanzee, and the pongo, pursued us during
                five years from the northern to the southern hemisphere; and we were every where
                blamed, in the most cultivated class of society, for being the only persons to doubt
                the existence of the great anthropomorphous monkey of America. We shall first
                observe, that there are certain regions, where this belief is particularly prevalent
                among the people; such are the banks of the Upper Oroonoko, the valley of Upar near
                the Lake of Maracaybo, the mountains of Santa Martha and of Merida, the provinces of
                Quixos, and the banks of the Amazon near Tomependa. In all these places, so distant
                one from the other, it is repeated, that the <hi rendition="#i">salvaje</hi> is
                easily recognized by the traces of its feet, the toes of which are turned backward.
                But if there exist a monkey of a large size in the New Continent, how has it
                happened, that during three centuries no man worthy of belief has been able to
                procure the skin of one? Several hypotheses present themselves to the mind, in order
                to explain the source of so ancient an error or belief. Has the famous <hi
                    rendition="#i">capuchin</hi> monkey of Esmeralda, the canine teeth of which are
                more than six lines and a half long, the physiognomy much more like man&#x2019;s
                than that of the ourang outang, and which, when irritated, rubs its beard with its
                hand, give rise to the fable of the <hi rendition="#i">salvaje</hi>? It is not so
                large indeed as the coaita (<hi rendition="#i">simia paniscus</hi>); but when seen
                at the top of a tree, and the head only visible, it might easily be taken for a
                human being. It may be also (and this opinion appears to me the most probable), that
                the man of the woods was one of those large bears, the footsteps of which resemble
                those of a man, and which is believed in every country to attack women. The animal
                killed in my time at the foot of the mountains of Merida, and sent, by the name of
                    <hi rendition="#i">salvaje</hi>, to Colonel Ungaro, the governor of the province
                Varinas, was in fact a bear with black and smooth fur.&#x201D;<p>These extraordinary
                    accounts are succeeded by a detailed history of the Moschettoes of this region;
                    perhaps the most remarkable of all its animal phenomena.</p><p>&#x201C;Persons
                    who have not navigated the great rivers of equinoctial America, for instance,
                    the Oroonoko and the Rio Magdalena, can scarcely conceive, how without
                    interruption, at every instant of life, you may be tormented by insects flying
                    in the air, and how the multitude of these little animals may render vast
                    regions wholly uninhabitable. However accustomed you may be to endure pain
                    without complaint, however lively an interest you may take in the objects of
                    your researches, it is impossible not to be constantly disturbed by the
                    moschettoes, <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes, jejens</hi> and <hi rendition="#i"
                        >tempraneroes</hi>, that cover the face and hands, pierce the clothes with
                    their long sucker in the form of a needle, and, getting into the mouth and
                    nostrils, set you coughing and sneezing whenever you attempt to speak in the
                    open air. In the missions of the Oroonoko, in the villages placed on the banks
                    of the river, surrounded by immense forests, the <hi rendition="#i">plaga de las
                        moscas</hi>, the plague of the flies, affords an inexhaustible subject of
                    conversation. When <cb/>two persons meet in the morning, the first questions
                    they address to each other are, &#x2018;How did you find the zancudoes during
                    the night? How are we to day for the moschettoes.&#x2019; These questions remind
                    us of a Chinese form of politeness, which indicates the ancient state of the
                    country where it took birth. Salutations were made heretofore in the <hi
                        rendition="#i">celestial empire</hi>, in the following
                            <choice><sic>works</sic><corr type="editorial">words</corr></choice>,
                        <hi rendition="#i">vou-tou-<lb break="maybe"/>hou</hi>, &#x2018;Have you
                    been incommoded in the night by the serpents?<choice><sic/><corr
                            type="editorial">&#x2019;</corr></choice> We shall soon see, that on the
                    banks of the Tuamini, in the river Magdalena, and still more at Choco, the
                    country of gold and platina, the Chinese compliment on the serpents might be
                    added to that of the moschettoes.&#x201D;</p><p>Other curious facts are
                    recorded, and illustrate this subject. Mr. H. says&#x2014;</p><p>&#x201C;At
                    Mandavaca we found an old missionary, who told us with an air of sadness, that
                    he bad spent <hi rendition="#i">his twenty years of moschettoes</hi> in America.
                    He desired us to look well at his legs, that we might be able to tell one day,
                    &#x2018;poor alla (beyond sea), what the poor monks suffer in the forests of
                    Cassiquiare.&#x2019; Every sting leaving a small darkish brown point, his legs
                    were so speckled, that it was difficult to recognize the whiteness of his skin
                    through the spots of coagulated blood. If the insects of the simulium genus
                    abound in the Cassiquiare, which has <hi rendition="#i">white waters</hi>, the
                    culices, or <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi>, are so much the more rare; you
                    scarcely find any there, while on the rivers of <hi rendition="#i">black
                        waters</hi>, in the Atabapo and the Rio Negro, there are generally some <hi
                        rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi> and no <hi rendition="#i"
                    >moschettoes</hi>.&#x201D; </p>
                <p>&#x201C;I have just shown, from my own observations, how much the geographical
                    distribution of venomous insects varies in this labyrinth of rivers with white
                    and black waters. It were to be wished, that a learned entomologist could study
                    on the spot the specific differences of these noxious insects, which in the
                    torrid zone, in spite of their littleness, act an important part in the economy
                    of nature. What appeared to us very remarkable, and is a fact, known to all the
                    missionaries, is, that the different species do not associate together, and that
                    at different hours of the day you are stung by a distinct species. Every time
                    that the scene changes, and to use the simple expression of the missionaries,
                    other insects &#x2018;mount guard<choice><sic>.</sic><corr type="editorial"
                            >,</corr></choice>&#x2019; you have a few minutes, often a quarter of an
                    hour, of repose. The insects that disappear have not their places instantly
                    supplied in equal numbers by their successors. From half after six in the
                    morning till five in the afternoon, the air is filled with moschettoes; which
                    have not, as we find related in some travels, the form of our gnats, but that of
                    a small fly. They are simuliums of the family nemocer&#x00E6; of the system of
                    Latreille. Their sting is as painful as that of <hi rendition="#i"
                    >stomoxes</hi>. It leaves a little reddish-brown spot, which is extravasated and
                    coagulated blood, where their proboscis has pierced the skin. An hour before
                    sun-set a species of small gnats, called <hi rendition="#i">tempraneros</hi>,
                    because they appear also at sun-rise, take the place of the moschettoes. Their
                    presence scarcely lasts an hour and a half; they disappear between six and seven
                    in the evening, or, as they say here, after the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Angelus</hi>(<hi rendition="#i">a la oracion</hi>). After a few minutes
                    repose, you feel yourself stund by <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi>, another
                    species of gnat (culex) with very long legs. The zancudo, the proboscis of which
                    contains a sharp pointed sucker, causes the most acute pain, and a swelling that
                    remains several weeks. Its hum resembles that of our gnats in Europe, but is
                    louder and more prolonged. The Indians pretend to distinguish &#x2018;by their
                    song&#x2019; the <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >tempraneroes</hi>; the latter of which are real <hi rendition="#i">twilight
                        insects</hi>, while the <hi rendition="#i">zancudoes</hi> are most
                    frequently <hi rendition="#i">nocturnal insects</hi>, and disappear towards
                    sun-rise.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;The <hi rendition="#i">culices</hi> of South America, have generally the
                    wings, corselet, and legs of an azure colour, annulated, and variable from a
                    mixture of spots of a metallic lustre. Here, as in Europe, the males, which are
                    distinguished by their feathered antenn&#x00E6;, are extremely rare; you are
                    seldom stung except by females. The preponderance of this sex explains the
                    immense increase of the species, each female laying several hundred eggs. In
                    going up one of the great rivers of Ameriva, it is observed, that the appearance
                    of a new species of <hi rendition="#i">culex</hi> denotes the approximity of a
                    new stream flowing in.<choice><sic>j</sic><corr type="editorial"
                    /></choice>&#x2019;</p><p>&#x201C;The whites born in the torrid zone walk
                    barefoot with impunity in the same apartment where a European recently landed is
                    exposed to the attack of the <hi rendition="#i">niguas</hi> or <hi
                        rendition="#i">chegoes</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">pulex penetrans</hi>). These
                    animals, almost invisible to the eye, get under the nails of the feet, and there
                    acquire the size of a small pea by the quick increase of its eggs, which are
                    placed in a bag under the belly of the insect. The <hi rendition="#i"
                    >nigua</hi>, therefore, distinguishes, what the most delicate chemical analysis
                    could not distinguish, the cellular membrane and blood of a European from those
                    of a Creole white. It is not so with the moschettoes.</p><p>&#x201C;In the day,
                    even when labouring at the oar, the natives, in order to chase the insects, are
                    continually giving one another smart slaps with the palm of the hand. Rude in
                    all their movements, they strike themselves and their comrades mechanically
                    during their sleep. The violence of their blows reminds us of the Persian tale
                    of the bear, that tried to kill with his paw the insects on the forehead of his
                    sleeping master. Near Maypures we saw some young Indians seated in a circle and
                    rubbing cruelly each others backs with the bark of trees dried at the fire.
                    Indian women were occupied with a degree of patience, of which <cb/>the
                    copper-coloured race alone are capable, in extirpating by means of a sharp bone
                    the little mass of coagulated blood, that forms the centre of every sting, and
                    gives the skin a speckled appearance. One of the most barbarous nations of the
                    Oroonoko, that of the Otomacs, is acquainted with the use of moschetto curtains
                        (<hi rendition="#i">mosquiteros</hi>) formed of a tissue of fibres of the
                    palm tree, <hi rendition="#i">murichi</hi>. We had lately seen, that at
                    Higuerote, on the coast of Caraccas, the people of a copper colour sleep buried
                    in the sand. In the villages of the Rio Magdalena the Indians often invited us
                    to stretch ourselves with them on ox-skins, near the church, in the middle of
                    the <hi rendition="#i">plaza grande</hi>, where they had assembled all the cows
                    in the neighbourhood. The proximity of cattle give some repose to man. The
                    Indians of the Upper Oroonoko and the Cassiquiare, seeing that Mr. Bonpland
                    could not prepare his herbal, on account of the continual torment of the
                    moschettoes, invited him to enter their oveus, (<hi rendition="#i"
                    >hornitos</hi>). Thus they call little chambers, without doors or windows, into
                    which they creep horizontally through a very small opening. When they have
                    driven away the insects by means of a fire of wet brush-wood, which emits a
                    great deal of smoke, they close the opening of the oven. The absence of
                    moschettoes is purchased clearly enough by the excessive heat of stagnant air,
                    and the smoke of a torch of <hi rendition="#i">copal</hi>, which lights the oven
                    during your stay in it. Mr. Bonpland, with courage and patience well worthy of
                    praise, dried hundreds of plants, shut up in these <hi rendition="#i"
                        >hornitos</hi> of the Indians.</p>
                <p>By this time we fancy our readers are as well acquainted with the habits of the
                    moschettoes, as if they had been bitten by them all over; and further knowledge
                    being unnecessary, we shall advance to other subjects.</p>
                <p>Above the cataract of Atures, at the mouth of the Rio Calaniapo, Mr. Humboldt
                    gives the following account of an extinct tribe:</p><p>&#x201C;We were shown at
                    a distance, on the right of the river, the rocks that surround the cavern of
                    Ataruipe; but we had not time to visit the cemetry of the destroyed tribe of the
                    Atures. We regretted this so much the more, as father Zea was never weary of
                    talking to us of the skeletons painted with anotta, which this cavern contained;
                    of the large vases of baked earth, in which the bones of separate families
                    appeared to be collected; and of many other curious objects, which we proposed
                    to examine at our return from the Rio Negro.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>At Maypure, higher up, we hear more of the pottery of the Indians:</p>
                <p>&#x201C;In every part of the forests, far from any human habitation, on digging
                    the earth, fragments of pottery and delft are found. The taste for this kind of
                    fabrication seems to have been common heretofore to the natives of both
                    Americas. To the north of Mexico,&#x2014;on the banks of the Rio Gala&#x2014;
                    among the ruins of an Azteck city&#x2014;in the United States&#x2014;near the
                        <hi rendition="#i">tumuli</hi> of the Miamis; in Florida&#x2014;and in every
                    place where any trace of ancient civilization could be found, the soil covers
                    fragments of painted pottery; and the extreme resemblances of the ornaments they
                    display is striking. Savage nations, and those civilized people, who are
                    condemned by their political and religious institutions always to imitate
                    themselves, strive, as if by instinct, to perpetuate the same forms, to preserve
                    a peculiar type or style, and to follow the methods and processes which were
                    employed by their ancestors. In North America, fragments of delft have been
                    discovered in places where lines of fortification are found, and the walls of
                    towns constructed by an unknown nation, now entirely extinct. The paintings on
                    these fragments have a great similitude to those which are executed in our days
                    on earthenware by the natives of Louisiana and Florida. Thus too the Indians of
                    Maypure often painted before our eyes the same ornaments as we had observed in
                    the cavern of <choice><sic>Ataroipe</sic><corr type="editorial"
                        >Ataruipe</corr></choice>, on the vases containing human bones. They are
                    real <hi rendition="#i">grecques</hi>, <choice><sic>ineaudrites</sic><corr
                            type="editorial">meandrites</corr></choice>, and figures of crocodiles,
                    of monkeys, and of a large quadruped, which I could not recognize, though it has
                    always the same squat form.&#x201D; </p>
                <p>We cannot, even in the midst of the in-<lb>teresting works which are at present
                        almost</lb><lb>daily issuing from the press, do better than</lb><lb>continue
                        to devote a page or our Gazette to</lb><lb>the agreeable narrative of this
                        enterprising</lb><lb>and intelligent traveller. In a preceding</lb><lb>paper
                        we have remarked upon the extraor-</lb><lb>dinary degree of general
                        knowledge which</lb><lb>he brings to bear on any topic he is
                        illus-</lb><lb>trating. The following is an admirable</lb><lb>example of the
                        truth of this position:</lb>
                </p>
                <p>&#x201C;Every hemisphere produces plants of a different species; and it is not by
                    the diversity of climates that we can attempt to explain why equinoctial Africa
                    has no laurineæ, and the New World no heaths; why the calceolariæ are found only
                    in the Southern hemisphere; why the birds of the continent of India glow with
                    colours less splendid than the birds of the hot parts of America; finally, why
                    the tiger is peculiar to Asia, and the ornithorhincus to New Holland. In the
                    vegetable, as well as in the animal kingdom, the causes of the distribution of
                    the species are among the number of mysteries which natural philosophy cannot
                    reach. This science is not occupied in the investigation of the origin of
                    beings, but of the laws according to which they are distributed on the globe. It
                    examines the things that are, the coexistence of vegetable and animal forms, in
                    each latitude, at different heights, and at different degrees of temperature; it
                    studies the relations under which particular organizations are more vigorously
                    developed, multiplied or modified; but it approaches not problems, the solution
                    of which is impossible, since they touch the origin, the first existence of a
                    germ of life. We may add, that the attempts that have been made to explain the
                    distribution of various species on the globe, by the sole influence of climate,
                    date at a period when physical geography was still in its infancy; when,
                    recurring incessantly to pretended contrasts between the two worlds, it was
                    imagined, that the whole of Africa and of America resembled the deserts of
                    Egypt, and the marshes of Cayenne. At present, when men judge of the state of
                    things not from one type arbitrarily chosen, but from positive knowledge, it is
                    ascertained that the two continents, in their immense extent, contain countries
                    that are altogether analogous. There are regions of America, as barren and
                    burning as the interior of Africa. The islands that produce the spices of India
                    are scarcely remarkable for their dryness; and it is not on account of the
                    humidity of the climate, as it has been affirmed in recent works, that the New
                    Continent is deprived of those fine species of laurineæ and myristicæ, which are
                    found united in one little corner of the earth, in the archipelago of India. For
                    some years past, the real cinnamon has been cultivated with success in several
                    parts of the New Continent; and a zone that produces the coumarouna, the
                    vanilla, the pucheri, the pine-apple, the myrtus pimenta, the balsam of tolu,
                    the myroxylon peruvianum, the crotons, the citrosmas, the pejoa, the incienso of
                    the silla of Caraccas, the quereme, the pancratium, and so many majestic
                    liliaceous plants, cannot be considered as destitute of aromatics. Besides, a
                    dry air favours the developement of the aromatic, or exciting properties, only
                    in certain species of plants. The most cruel poisons are produced in the most
                    humid zone of America: and it is precisely under the influence of the long rains
                    of the tropics that the American pimento, capsicum baccatum, the fruit of which
                    is often as caustic and fiery as Indian pepper, vegetates best. From the whole
                    of these considerations, it follows, 1st, that the new continent possesses
                    spices, aromatics, and very active vegetable poisons that are peculiar to
                    itself, differing specifically from those of the ancient world; 2dly, that the
                    primitive distribution of species in the torrid zone cannot be explained by the
                    influence of climate solely, or by the distribution of temperature, which we
                    observe in the present state of our planet; but that this difference of climate
                    leads us to perceive, why a given type of organization developes itself more
                    vigorously in such or such local circumstances. We can conceive, that a small
                    number of the families of plants, for instance the musaceæ and the palms, cannot
                    belong to very cold regions, on account of their internal structure and the
                    importance of certain organs; but we cannot explain why no one of the family of
                    melastomas vegetates north of the parallel of thirty degrees, or why no rose
                    tree belongs to the southern hemisphere. Analogy of climates is often found in
                    the two continents, without identity of productions.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>&#x201C;Its trunk, armed with thorns, is more than sixty feet high; its leaves
                    are pinnated, very thin, undulated, and frizzled towards the points. The fruits
                    of this tree are very extraordinary; every cluster contains from fifty to
                    eighty; they are yellow like apples, grow purple in proportion as they ripen,
                    two or three inches thick, and generally, from abortion, without a kernel. Among
                    the eighty or ninety species of palm-trees peculiar to the New Continent, which
                    I have enumerated in the Nova Genera Plantarum Aequinoctialum, there are none in
                    which the sarcocarp is developed in a manner so extraordinary. The fruit of the
                    pirijao furnishes a farinaceous substance, as yellow as the yolk of an egg,
                    slightly saccharine, and extremely nutritious. It is eaten like plantains or
                    potatoes, boiled or roasted in the ashes, and affords a wholesome and agreeable
                    aliment. The Indians and the missionaries are unwearied in their praises of this
                    noble palm-tree, which might be called the peach-palm. We found it cultivated in
                    abundance at San Fernando, San Balthasar, Santa Barbara, and wherever we
                    advanced towards the south or the east along the banks of the Atabapo and the
                    Upper Orinoco. In those wild regions we are involuntarily reminded of the
                    assertion of Linnaeus, that the country of palm-trees was the first abode of our
                    species, and that man is essentially palmivorous. On examining the provision
                    accumulated in the huts of the Indians, we perceive that their subsistence
                    during several months of the year depends as much on the farinaceous fruit of
                    the pirijao, as on the cassava and plantain. The tree bears fruit but once a
                    year, but to the amount of three clusters, consequently from one hundred and
                    fifty to two hundred fruits.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>Here, also, is the gigantic bombax … they landed to measure it. &#x201C;The
                    height was nearly one hundred and twenty feet, and the diameter between fourteen
                    and fifteen. This enormous specimen of vegetation surprised us the more, as we
                    had till then seen on the banks of the Atabapo only small trees with slender
                    trunks, which from afar resembled young cherry-trees. The Indians assured that
                    these small trees do not form a very extensive group. They are checked in their
                    growth by the inundations of the river; while the dry grounds near the Atabapo,
                    the Temi, and the Tuamini, furnish excellent timber for building.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>Thus (as we have stated), interspersed<lb/>with anecdote, does Mr. Humboldt vary
                    his<lb/>entertaining volumes; and that our review<lb>may partake of the
                        character of its subject,</lb><lb>we shall conclude the present division of
                        it</lb><lb>by copying a very affecting story. Where</lb><lb>the Atabapo
                        enters the Rio Temi, the nar-</lb><lb>rative says:</lb></p>
                <p>&#x201C;Before we reached its confluence, a granitic eminence on the western
                    bank, near the mouth of the Guasacavi, fixed our attention: it is called Piedra
                    de la Guahiba (Rock of the Guahiba woman), or the Piedra de la Madre (Mother's
                    Rock.) We inquired the cause of so singular a denomination. Father Zea could not
                    satisfy our curiosity; but some weeks after, another missionary, one of the
                    predecessors of that ecclesiastic, whom we found settled at San Fernando as
                    president of the missions, related to us an event which excited in our minds the
                    most painful feelings. If, in these solitary scenes, man scarcely leaves behind
                    him any trace of his existence, it is doubly humiliating for a European to see
                    perpetuated by so imperishable a monument of nature as a rock, the remembrance
                    of the moral degradation of our species, and the contrast between the virtue of
                    a savage, and the barbarism of civilized man!</p><p>&#x201C;In 1797 the
                    missionary of San Fernando had led his Indians to the banks of the Rio Guaviare,
                    on one of those hostile incursions which are prohibited alike by religion and
                    the Spanish laws. They found in an Indian hut a Guahiba woman with her three
                    children (two of whom were still infants), occupied in preparing the flour of
                    cassava. Resistance was impossible; the father was gone to fish, and the mother
                    tried in vain to flee with her children. Scarcely had she reached the savannah
                    when she was seized by the Indians of the mission, who hunt human beings, like
                    the Whites and the Negroes in Africa. The mother and her children were bound,
                    and dragged to the bank of the river. The monk, seated in his boat, waited the
                    issue of an expedition of which he shared not the danger. Had the mother made
                    too violent a resistance the Indians would have killed her, for everything is
                    permitted for the sake of the conquest of souls (la conquista espirituel), and
                    it is particularly desirable to capture children, who may be treated in the
                    Mission as poitos, or slaves of the Christians. The prisoners were carried to
                    San Fernando, in the hope that the mother would be unable to find her way back
                    to her home by land. Separated from her other children who had accompanied their
                    father on the day in which she had been carried off, the unhappy woman showed
                    signs of the deepest despair. She attempted to take back to her home the
                    children who had been seized by the missionary; and she fled with them
                    repeatedly from the village of San Fernando. But the Indians never failed to
                    recapture her; and the missionary, after having caused her to be mercilessly
                    beaten, took the cruel resolution of separating the mother from the two children
                    who had been carried off with her. She was conveyed alone to the missions of the
                    Rio Negro, going up the Atabapo. Slightly bound, she was seated at the bow of
                    the boat, ignorant of the fate that awaited her; but she judged by the direction
                    of the sun, that she was removing farther and farther from her hut and her
                    native country. She succeeded in breaking her bonds, threw herself into the
                    water, and swam to the left bank of the Atabapo. The current carried her to a
                    shelf of rock, which bears her name to this day. She landed and took shelter in
                    the woods, but the president of the missions ordered the Indians to row to the
                    shore, and follow the traces of the Guahiba. In the evening she was brought
                    back. Stretched upon the rock (la Piedra de la Madre) a cruel punishment was
                    inflicted on her with those straps of manatee leather, which serve for whips in
                    that country, and with which the alcaldes are always furnished. This unhappy
                    woman, her hands tied behind her back with strong stalks of mavacure, was then
                    dragged to the mission of Javita.</p><p>&#x201C;She was there thrown into one of
                    the caravanserais, called las Casas del Rey. It was the rainy season, and the
                    night was profoundly dark. Forests till then believed to be impenetrable
                    separated the mission of Javita from that of San Fernando, which was twenty-five
                    leagues distant in a straight line. No other route is known than that by the
                    rivers; no man ever attempted to go by land from one village to another. But
                    such difficulties could not deter a mother, separated from her children. The
                    Guahiba was carelessly guarded in the caravanserai. Her arms being wounded, the
                    Indians of Javita had loosened her bonds, unknown to the missionary and the
                    alcaldes. Having succeeded by the help of her teeth in breaking them entirely,
                    she disappeared during the night; and at the fourth sunrise was seen at the
                    mission of San Fernando, hovering around the hut where her children were
                    confined. "What that woman performed," added the missionary, who gave us this
                    sad narrative, "the most robust Indian would not have ventured to undertake!"
                    She traversed the woods at a season when the sky is constantly covered with
                    clouds, and the sun during whole days appears but for a few minutes. Did the
                    course of the waters direct her way? The inundations of the rivers forced her to
                    go far from the banks of the main stream, through the midst of woods where the
                    movement of the water is almost imperceptible. How often must she have been
                    stopped by the thorny lianas, that form a network around the trunks they
                    entwine! How often must she have swum across the rivulets that run into the
                    Atabapo! This unfortunate woman was asked how she had sustained herself during
                    four days. She said that, exhausted with fatigue, she could find no other
                    nourishment than those great black ants called vachacos, which climb the trees
                    in long bands, to suspend on them their resinous nests. We pressed the
                    missionary to tell us whether the Guahiba had peacefully enjoyed the happiness
                    of remaining with her children; and if any repentance had followed this excess
                    of cruelty. He would not satisfy our curiosity; but at our return from the Rio
                    Negro we learned that the Indian mother was again separated from her children,
                    and sent to one of the missions of the Upper Orinoco. There she died, refusing
                    all kind of nourishment, as savages frequently do in great
                    calamities.</p><p>&#x201C;Such is the remembrance annexed to this fatal rock, to
                        <hi rend="italic">Piedra de la Madre.</hi></p>
            </div><div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#k">humboldt&#x2019;s and bonpland&#x2019;s travels.</hi><lb
                        break="yes"/></head>
                <p>This journal is so pregnant with instruc-<lb/>tive and interesting matter, that
                    we could<lb>hardly, as we think, place any thing better</lb><lb>before our
                        readers, though we might be</lb><lb>more instant with a greater variety of
                        no-</lb><lb>velty. We therefore continue our extracts.</lb><lb>The following
                        is a curious account of the</lb>Indian Rubber:&#x2014;&#x201C;Here (Says Mr.
                    H. at the mission of St. Balthasar on the Atobapo) we saw, for the first time,
                    that white and fungous<lb break="yes"/>substance, which I have made known by the
                    name of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">zapis.</hi> We
                    immediately perceived, that it<lb break="yes"/>was analogous to the <hi
                        rendition="#i">elastic resin;</hi> but, as the Indians<lb break="yes"/>made
                    us understand by signs, that it was found under<lb break="yes"/>ground, we were
                    inclined to think, till we arrived at<lb break="yes"/>the mission of Javita,
                    that the <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> was a fossil<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="243" facs="#f0002"/> caoutchouc, though different from the elastic
                        bitumen<lb break="yes"/>of Derbyshire. A Poimisano Indian, seated by the<lb
                        break="yes"/>fire, in the hut of the missionary, was employed in<lb
                        break="yes"/>reducing the <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> into black
                    caoutchouc. He had<lb break="yes"/>spitted several bits on a slender stick, and
                    was roast-<lb break="no"/>ing them like meat. The <hi rendition="#i"
                        >dapicho</hi> blackens in propor-<lb break="no"/>tion as it grows softer,
                    and gains in elasticity. The<lb break="yes"/>resinous and aromatic smell, which
                    filled the hut,<lb break="yes"/>seemed to indicate, that this coloration is the
                    effect of<lb break="yes"/>the decomposition of a carburet of hydrogen, and
                        that<lb break="yes"/>the carbon appears in proportion as the hydrogen<lb
                        break="yes"/>burns at a low heat. The Indian beat the softened<lb
                        break="yes"/>and blackened mass with a piece of brazil wood, end-<lb
                        break="no"/>ing in the form of a club; he then kneaded the <hi
                        rendition="#i">dapi-<lb break="no"/>cho</hi> into balls of three or four
                    inches in diameter, and let<lb break="yes"/>it cool. These balls exactly
                    resemble the caoutchouc<lb break="yes"/>of the shops, but their surface remains
                    in general<lb break="yes"/>slightly viscous. They are used at San Balthasar
                        in<lb break="yes"/>the Indian game of tennis, which is so celebrated<lb
                        break="yes"/>among the inhabitants of Uruana and Encaramada;<lb break="yes"
                    />they are cut into cylinders, to be used as corks, and<lb break="yes"/>are far
                    preferable to those made of the bark of the<lb break="yes"
                    />cork-tree.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Soon after, we obtained precise information respect-<lb break="no"/>ing this
                    substance:&#x2014;it was shown us at the depth of<lb break="yes"/>two or three
                    feet, in a marshy soil, between the roots<lb break="yes"/>of two trees known by
                    the name of the <hi rendition="#i">jacio</hi> and the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">curvana.</hi> The first is the <hi rendition="#i">hevea</hi>
                    of Aublet, or <hi rendition="#i">siphonia</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>of the modern botanists, known to furnish the caout-<lb
                        break="no"/>chouc of commerce in Cayenne and the Grand Para;<lb break="yes"
                    />the second has pinnate leaves, and its juice is milky,<lb break="yes"/>but
                    very thin, and almost destitute of viscocity. The<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">dapicho</hi> appears to be the result of an extravasation
                        of<lb break="yes"/>the sap from the roots. This extravasation takes<lb
                        break="yes"/>place more especially when the trees have attained a<lb
                        break="yes"/>great age, and the interior of the trunk begins to<lb
                        break="yes"/>decay. The bark and alburnum crack; and thus is<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="244" facs="#f0003"/> effected naturally, what the art of man performs
                        to<lb break="yes"/>collect in abundance the milky juices of the hevea,
                        the<lb break="yes"/>castilloa, and the caoutchouc fig tree.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The river Temi, near the banks of which this production is found in sufficient
                    quantities to supply all<lb break="yes"/>Europe, runs through forests which
                    overshadow it in<lb break="yes"/>so wild and luxuriant a manner as almost to
                        mingle<lb break="yes"/>together the creatures of the several elements of
                        air,<lb break="yes"/>earth, and water, and realize the classic images:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <lg type="poem">
                    <l>S&#x00E6;culum Pyrrh&#x00E6;, nova monstra quest&#x00E6;;</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Omne quum Proteus pecus egit altos</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>
                        <hi rendition="#et">Visere montes;</hi>
                    </l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Piscium et summa genus h&#x00E6;sit ulmo,</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Nota qu&#x00E6; sedes fuerat Columbis,</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Et superjecto pavid&#x00E6; natarunt</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>
                        <hi rendition="#et">&#x00C6;quore dam&#x00E6;.</hi>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The Indians (says Mr. H.) made us leave the bed of the<lb break="yes"
                    />river; and we went up towards the south, across<lb break="yes"/>the forest,
                    through paths <hi rendition="#i">(sendas)</hi> that is, through<lb break="yes"
                    />open channels of four or five feet broad. The<lb break="yes"/>depth of the
                    water seldom exceeds half a fathom.<lb break="yes"/>These <hi rendition="#i"
                        >sendas</hi> are formed in the inundated forest-like<lb break="yes"/>paths
                    on dry ground. The Indians, in going from<lb break="yes"/>one mission to
                    another, pass with their boats as much<lb break="yes"/>as possible by the same
                    way; but the communications<lb break="yes"/>not being frequent, the force of
                    vegetation sometimes<lb break="yes"/>produces unexpected obstacles. An Indian,
                        furnished<lb break="yes"/>with a <hi rendition="#i">machette</hi> (a great
                    knife, the blade of which is<lb break="yes"/>fourteen inches long,) stood at the
                    head of our boat,<lb break="yes"/>employed continually in chopping off the
                        branches<lb break="yes"/>that cross each other from the two sides of the
                        channel.<lb break="yes"/>In the thickest part of the forest we were
                        astonished<lb break="yes"/>by an extraordinary noise. On beating the
                        bushes,<lb break="yes"/>a shoal of <hi rendition="#i">toninas</hi> (fresh
                    water dolphins) four feet<lb break="yes"/>long, surrounded our boat. These
                    animals had con-<lb break="no"/>cealed themselves beneath the branches of a
                        fromager<lb break="yes"/>or bombax ceiba. They fled across the forest,
                        throw-<lb break="no"/>ing out those spouts of compressed air and water,<lb
                        break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="245" facs="#f0004"/> which have given them in every language the name
                        of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">blowers.</hi> How singular was this spectacle in the mid-<lb
                        break="no"/>dle of the land, three or four hundred leagues from<lb
                        break="yes"/>the mouths of the Oroonoko and the Amazon! I am<lb break="yes"
                    />not ignorant, that the pleuronectes of the Atlantic go<lb break="yes"/>up the
                    Loire as far as Orleans; but I persist in think-<lb break="no"/>ing, that the
                    dolphins of the Temi, like those of the<lb break="yes"/>Ganges, and like the
                    skate <hi rendition="#i">(raia)</hi> of the Oroonoko, are<lb break="yes"/>of a
                    species essentially different from the dolphins and<lb break="yes"/>skates of
                    the ocean. In the immense rivers of South<lb break="yes"/>America, and the great
                    lakes of North America,<lb break="yes"/>nature seems to repeat several pelagic
                    forms. The<lb break="yes"/>Nile has no porpoises: those of the sea go up the<lb
                        break="yes"/>Delta no farther than Biana and Metonbis toward<lb break="yes"
                    />Selamoun.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>But these … &#x2014;&#x201C;We felt an extraordinary irritation on the joints of
                    our fingers, and on the backs of our hands. The missionary told us it was caused
                    by the aradores, (ploughman insects), which get under the skin. We could
                    distinguish with a lens nothing but streaks, or parallel and whitish furrows. It
                    is the form of these furrows, that has obtained for the insect the name of
                    ploughman. A mulatto woman was sent for, who professed to be thoroughly
                    acquainted with all the little insects that burrow in the human skin; the chego,
                    the nuche, the coya, and the arador; she was the curandera, or surgeon of the
                    place. She promised to extirpate, one by one, the insects which caused this
                    smarting irritation. Having heated at a lamp the point a little bit of hard
                    wood, she dug with it into the furrows that marked the skin. After long
                    examination, she announced with the pedantic gravity peculiar to the mulatto
                    race, that an arador was found. I saw a little round bag, which I suspected to
                    be the egg of an acarus. I was to find relief when the mulatto woman had
                    succeeded in taking out three or four of these aradores. Having the skin of both
                    hands filled with acari, I had not the patience to wait the end of an operation,
                    which had already lasted till late at night. The next day an Indian of Javita
                    cured us radically, and with surprising promptitude. He brought us the branch of
                    a shrub, called uzao.</p>
                <p>The annexed natives of the … &#x2014;&#x201C;The nations of the Upper Orinoco,
                    the Atabapo, and the Inirida, like the ancient Germans and the Persians, have no
                    other worship than that of the powers of nature. They call the good principle
                    Cachimana; it is the Manitou, the Great Spirit, that regulates the seasons, and
                    favours the harvests. Along with Cachimana there is an evil principle,
                    Iolokiamo, less powerful, but more artful, and in particular more active. The
                    Indians of the forest, when they occasionally visit the missions, conceive with
                    difficulty the idea of a temple or an image. "These good people," said the
                    missionary, "like only processions in the open air. When I last celebrated the
                    festival of San Antonio, the patron of my village, the Indians of Inirida were
                    present at mass. 'Your God,' said they to me, 'keeps himself shut up in a house,
                    as if he were old and infirm; ours is in the forest, in the fields, and on the
                    mountains of Sipapu, whence the rains come.'" Among the more numerous, and on
                    this account less barbarous tribes, religious societies of a singular kind are
                    formed. Some old Indians pretend to be better instructed than others on points
                    regarding divinity; and to them is confided the famous botuto, of which I have
                    spoken, and which is sounded under the palm-trees that they may bear abundance
                    of fruit. On the banks of the Orinoco there exists no idol, as among all the
                    nations who have remained faithful to the first worship of nature, but the
                    botuto, the sacred trumpet, is an object of veneration. To be initiated into the
                    mysteries of the botuto, it is requisite to be of pure morals, and to have lived
                    single. The initiated are subjected to flagellations, fastings, and other
                    painful exercises. There are but a small number of these sacred trumpets. The
                    most anciently celebrated is that upon a hill near the confluence of the Tomo
                    and the Guainia. It is pretended, that it is heard at once on the banks of the
                    Tuamini, and at the mission of San Miguel de Davipe, a distance of ten leagues.
                    Father Cereso assured us, that the Indians speak of the botuto of Tomo as an
                    object of worship common to many surrounding tribes. Fruit and intoxicating
                    liquors are placed beside the sacred trumpet. Sometimes the Great Spirit himself
                    makes the botuto resound; sometimes he is content to manifest his will through
                    him to whom the keeping of the instrument is entrusted. These juggleries being
                    very ancient (from the fathers of our fathers, say the Indians), we must not be
                    surprised that some unbelievers are already to be found; but they express their
                    disbelief of the mysteries of the botuto only in whispers. Women are not
                    permitted to see this marvellous instrument; and are excluded from all the
                    ceremonies of this worship. If a woman have the misfortune to see the trumpet,
                    she is put to death without mercy.&#x201D;</p>
            </div><div n="1">
                <head>(Literary Gazette, Sept.)<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">TRAVELS OF ALEXANDER HUMBOLDT.<lb break="yes"/>translated by
                        helen maria williams.</hi></head>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">A few</hi>A Few weeks since, when this addition … </p>
                <p>&#x201C;Esmeralda is the most celebrated spot on the Oroonoko for<lb break="yes"
                    />the fabrication of that active poison which is employed in war,<lb break="yes"
                    />in the chase, and, what is singular enough, as a remedy for gastric<lb
                        break="yes"/>obstructions. The poison of the ficunas of the Amazon, the
                        upas-<lb break="no"/>tieute of Java, and the <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi>
                    of Guyana, are the most deleterious<lb break="yes"/> substances that are known.
                    Raleigh, toward the end of the six-<lb break="no"/>teenth century, had heard the
                    name of <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi> pronounced as<lb break="yes"/>being a
                    vegetable substance, with which arrows were envenomed;<lb break="yes"/>yet no
                    fixed notions of this poison had reached Europe. The<lb break="yes"
                    />missionaries Gumilla and Gili had not been able to penetrate in-<lb break="no"
                    />to the country where the curare is manufactured. Gumilla as-<lb break="no"
                    />serts that this preparable was enveloped in great mystery; that<lb break="yes"
                    />its principal ingredient was furnished by a subterraneous plant,<lb
                        break="yes"/>by a tuberose root, which never puts forth leaves, and which
                        is<lb break="yes"/>called the root by way of eminence, <hi rendition="#i"
                        >raiz de si misma;</hi> that the<lb break="yes"/>venomous exhalations, which
                    arise from the pots, cause the old<lb break="yes"/>women (the most <hi
                        rendition="#i">useless</hi>) to perish who are chosen to watch<lb
                        break="yes"/>over this operation; finally, that these vegetable juices
                        never<lb break="yes"/>appear sufficiently concentrated, till a few drops
                    produce <hi rendition="#i">at a<lb break="yes"/>distance</hi> a repulsive action
                    on the blood. An Indian wounds him-<lb break="no"/>self slightly; and a dart
                    dipped in the liquid <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi> is held near<lb break="yes"
                    />the wound. If it make the blood return to the vessels without<lb break="yes"
                    />having been brought into contact with them, the poison is judged<lb
                        break="yes"/>to be sufficiently concentrated. I shall not stop to refute
                        these<lb break="yes"/>popular tales collected by Father Gumilla.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When we arrived at Esmeralda, the greater part of the In-<lb break="no"/>dians
                    were returning from an excursion which they had made to<lb break="yes"/>the east
                    beyond the Rio Padamo, to gather <hi rendition="#i">juvias</hi>, or the fruit<lb
                        break="yes"/>of the Bertholletia, and the liana which yields the curare.
                        Their<lb break="yes"/>return was celebrated by a festival, which is called
                    in the Mission<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">la fiesta de las juvias</hi>, and which resembles our harvest
                        homes<lb break="yes"/>and vintage feasts. The women had prepared a quantity
                    of fer-<lb break="no"/>mented liquor, and during two days the Indians were in a
                        state<lb break="yes"/>of intoxication. Among nations that attach great
                        importance<lb break="yes"/>to the fruits of the palm-trees and of some
                    others useful for the<lb break="yes"/>nourishment of man, the period when these
                    fruits are gathered<lb break="yes"/>is marked by public rejoicings, and time is
                    divided according to<lb break="yes"/>these festivals, which succeed one another
                    in a course invariably<lb break="yes"/>the same. We were fortunate enough to
                    find an old Indian less<lb break="yes"/>drunk than the rest, who was employed in
                    preparing the <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>poison from freshly gathered plants. He was the chemist of<lb
                        break="yes"/>the place. We found at his dwelling large earthen pots for<lb
                        break="yes"/>boiling vegetable juice, shallower vessels to favour the
                        evaporation<lb break="yes"/>by a larger surface, and leaves of the
                    plane-tree rolled up in the<lb break="yes"/>shape of our filters, and used to
                    filtrate the liquors more or less<lb break="yes"/>loaded with fibrous matter.
                    The greatest order and neatness<lb break="yes"/>prevailed in this hut, which was
                    transformed into a chemical la-<lb break="no"/>boratory. The Indian who was to
                    instruct us, is known through-<lb break="no"/>out the mission by the name of the
                        <hi rendition="#i">master of poison</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">amo del<lb
                            break="yes"/>curare</hi>)<hi rendition="#i">:</hi> he had that
                    self-sufficient air and tone of pedantry, of<lb break="yes"/>which the
                    pharmacopolists of Europe were formerly <choice>
                        <sic>accused;&#x201C;</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">accused; &#x201C;</corr>
                    </choice> I<lb break="yes"/> know,&#x201D; said he, &#x201C;that the whites have
                    the secret of fabricating<lb break="yes"/>soap, and that black powder which has
                    the effect of making a<lb break="yes"/>noise and killing animals, when they are
                    wanted. The <hi rendition="#i">curare,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>which we prepare from father to son, is superior to any thing
                        you<lb break="yes"/>can make <hi rendition="#i">down yonder</hi> (beyond
                    sea). It is the juice of an herb<lb break="yes"/>which <hi rendition="#i">kills
                        silently</hi> (without any one knowing whence the stroke<lb break="yes"
                    />comes).&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This chemical operation, to which the <hi rendition="#i">master of the
                        curare</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>attached so much importance, appears to us extremely simple.<lb
                        break="yes"/>The liana (<hi rendition="#i">bujuco</hi>), which is used at
                    Esmeralda for the prepara-<lb break="no"/>tion of the poison, bears the same
                    name as in the forest of Javita.<lb break="yes"/>It is the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >bejuco de mavacure</hi>, which is gathered in abundance<lb break="yes"
                    />east of the Mission, on the left bank of the Oroonoko, beyond<lb break="yes"
                    />the Rio Amaguaca, in the mountains and granatic lands of Gua-<lb break="no"
                    />naya and Yumariquin.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The juice of the liana, when it has been recently gathered, is<lb break="yes"
                    />not regarded as poisonous; perhaps it acts in a sensible manner<lb break="yes"
                    />only when it is strongly concentrated. It is the bark, and a part<lb
                        break="yes"/>of the alburnum, which contains this terrible poison.
                        Branches<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i">mavacure</hi> four or
                    five lines in diameter, are scraped with a<lb break="yes"/>knife; and the bark
                    that comes off is bruised, and reduced into<lb break="yes"/>very thin filaments,
                    on the stone employed for grinding cassava.<lb break="yes"/>The venomous juice
                    being yellow, the whole fibrous mass takes<lb break="yes"/>this colour. It is
                    thrown into a funnel nine inches high, with an<lb break="yes"/>opening four
                    inches wide. This funnel was, of all the instru-<lb break="no"/>ments of the
                    Indian laboratory, that of which the <hi rendition="#i">master of poi-<lb
                            break="no"/>son</hi> seemed to be most proud. He asked us repeatedly, of
                        <hi rendition="#i">por<lb break="yes"/>alla</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">down
                        yonder,</hi> that is in Europe) we had ever seen any thing<lb break="yes"
                    />to be compared to his <hi rendition="#i">empudo.</hi> It was a leaf of a
                    plantain tree<lb break="yes"/>rolled up in the form of a cone, and placed in
                    another stronger<lb break="yes"/>cone made of the leaves of the palm-tree. The
                    whole of this<lb break="yes"/>apparatus was supported by slight frame work made
                    of the petioli<lb break="yes"/>and ribs of palm leaves. A cold infusion is first
                    prepared by<lb break="yes"/>pouring water on the fibrous matter, which is the
                    ground bark of<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">mavacure.</hi> A yellowish
                    water filters during several hours,<lb break="yes"/>drop by drop, through the
                    leafy funnel. This filtered water is the<lb break="yes"/>venomous liquor, but it
                    acquires strength only when it is concen-<lb break="no"/>trated by evaporation,
                    like molasses in a large earthen pot.<lb break="yes"/>The Indian from time to
                    time invited us to taste the liquid; its<lb break="yes"/>taste, more or less
                    bitter, decides when the concentration by fire<lb break="yes"/>has been carried
                    sufficiently far. There is no danger in this ope-<lb break="no"/>ration, the <hi
                        rendition="#i">curare</hi> being deleterious only when it comes into im-<lb
                        break="no"/>mediate contact with the blood. The vapours, therefore, that<lb
                        break="yes"/>are disengaged from the pans, are not hurtful,
                        notwithstanding<lb break="yes"/>what has been asserted on this point by the
                    Missionaries of the<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko. Fontana, in his fine experiments
                    on the poison of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">ticunas</hi> of the river of Amazons, long ago proved, that
                    the va-<lb break="no"/>pours arising from this poison when thrown on burning
                        charcoal,<lb break="yes"/>may be inhaled without apprehension; and that it
                    is false, as<lb break="yes"/>M. de la Condamine has announced, that Indian
                    women, when con-<lb break="no"/>demned to death, have been killed by the vapours
                    of the poison<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i">ticunas.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The juice is thickened with a glutinous substance to cause it<lb break="yes"/>to
                    stick to the darts, which it renders mortal; but taken inter-<lb break="no"
                    />nally, the Indians consider the <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi> to be an
                    excellent stoma-<lb break="no"/>chic. Scarcely a fowl is eaten (adds our author)
                    on the banks<lb break="yes"/>of the Oroonoko, which has not been killed with a
                        poisoned<lb break="yes"/>arrow. The Missionaries pretend, that the flesh of
                    animals is<lb break="yes"/>never so good as when these means are employed.
                    Father Zea,<lb break="yes"/>who accompanied us, though ill of a tertian fever,
                    caused every<lb break="yes"/>morning the live fowl allotted for our repast to be
                    brought to his<lb break="yes"/>hammock, together with an arrow. Notwithstanding
                    his habi-<lb break="no"/>tual state of weakness, he would not confide this
                    operation, to<lb break="yes"/>which he attached great importance, to any other
                    person. Large<lb break="yes"/>birds, a guan (<hi rendition="#i">pava de
                        monte</hi>) for instance, or a curassoa (<hi rendition="#i">alse-<lb
                            break="no"/>tor,</hi>) when wounded in the thigh, perish in two or three
                        minutes;<lb break="yes"/>but it is often ten or twelve before a pig or a
                    pecari expires.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>M. Humboldt does not seem to be acquainted with any certain antidote,<lb
                        break="yes"/>if such exists, to this fatal poison. Sugar, garlic, the
                    muriate of soda, &amp;c.<lb break="yes"/>are mentioned doubtingly. ...</p>
                <p>&#x201C;The old Indian, who was called the master of poison, seemed flattered by
                    the interest we had taken in his chemical processes. He found us sufficiently
                    intelligent to lead him to the belief that we knew how to make soap, an art
                    which, next to the preparation of curare, appeared to him one of the finest of
                    human inventions. When the liquid poison had been poured into the vessels
                    prepared for their reception, we accompanied the Indian to the festival of the
                    juvias. The harvest of juvias, or fruits of the Bertholletia excelsa, was
                    celebrated by dancing, and by excesses of wild intoxication. The hut where the
                    natives were assembled, displayed during several days a very singular aspect.
                    There was neither table nor bench; but large roasted monkeys, blackened by
                    smoke, were ranged in regular order against the wall. These were the marimondes
                    (Ateles belzebuth), and those bearded monkeys called capuchins, which must not
                    be confounded with the weeper, or sai (Simia capucina of Buffon). The manner of
                    roasting these anthropomorphous animals contributes to render their appearance
                    extremely disagreeable in the eyes of civilized man. A little grating or lattice
                    of very hard wood is formed, and raised one foot from the ground. The monkey is
                    skinned, and bent into a sitting posture; the head generally resting on the
                    arms, which are meagre and long; but sometimes these are crossed behind the
                    back. When it is tied on the grating, a very clear fire is kindled below. The
                    monkey, enveloped in smoke and flame, is broiled and blackened at the same time.
                    On seeing the natives devour the arm or leg of a roasted monkey, it is difficult
                    not to believe that this habit of eating animals so closely resembling man in
                    their physical organization, has, to a certain degree, contributed to diminish
                    the horror of cannibalism among these people. Roasted monkeys, particularly
                    those which have very round heads, display a hideous resemblance to a child; and
                    consequently Europeans who are obliged to feed on them prefer separating the
                    head and the hands, and serve up only the rest of the animal at their tables.
                    The flesh of monkeys is so lean and dry, that M. Bonpland has preserved in his
                    collections at Paris an arm and hand, which had been broiled over the fire at
                    Esmeralda; and no smell has arisen from them after the lapse of a great number
                    of years.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;We saw the Indians dance. The monotony of their dancing is increased by
                    the women not daring to take part in it. The men, young and old, form a circle,
                    holding each others' hands; and turn sometimes to the right, sometimes to the
                    left, for whole hours, with silent gravity. Most frequently the dancers
                    themselves are the musicians. Feeble sounds, drawn from a series of reeds of
                    different lengths, form a slow and plaintive accompaniment. The first dancer, to
                    mark the time, bends both knees in a kind of cadence. Sometimes they all make a
                    pause in their places, and execute little oscillatory movements, bending the
                    body from one side to the other. The reeds ranged in a line, and fastened
                    together, resemble the Pan's pipes, as we find them represented in the
                    bacchanalian processions on Grecian vases. To unite reeds of different lengths,
                    and make them sound in succession by passing them before the lips, is a simple
                    idea, and has naturally presented itself to every nation. We were surprised to
                    see with what promptitude the young Indians constructed and tuned these pipes,
                    when they found reeds on the bank of the river. Uncivilized men, in every zone,
                    make great use of these gramina with high stalks. The Greeks, with truth, said
                    that reeds had contributed to subjugate nations by furnishing arrows, to soften
                    men's manners by the charm of music, and to unfold their understanding by
                    affording the first instruments for tracing letters. These different uses of
                    reeds mark in some sort three different periods in the life of nations. We must
                    admit that the tribes of the Orinoco are in the first stage of dawning
                    civilization. The reed serves them only as an instrument of war and of hunting;
                    and the Pan's pipes, of which we have spoken, have not yet, on those distant
                    shores, yielded sounds capable of awakening mild and humane
                    feelings.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>M.H. gives an interesting account ... </p>
                <p>&#x201C;We saw on the slope of the Cerra Duida shirt-trees fifty feet high. The
                    Indians cut off cylindrical pieces two feet in diameter, from which they peel
                    the red and fibrous bark, without making any longitudinal incision. This bark
                    affords them a sort of garment, which resembles sacks of a very coarse texture,
                    and without a seam. The upper opening serves for the head; and two lateral holes
                    are cut for the arms to pass through. The natives wear these shirts of marima in
                    the rainy season: they have the form of the ponchos and ruanas of cotton, which
                    are so common in New Grenada, at Quito, and in Peru. In these climates the
                    riches and beneficence of nature being regarded as the primary causes of the
                    indolence of the inhabitants, the missionaries say in showing the shirts of
                    marima, in the forests of the Orinoco garments are found ready-made on the
                    trees. We may also mention the pointed caps, which the spathes of certain
                    palm-trees furnish, and which resemble coarse network.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;At the festival of which we were the spectators, the women, who were
                    excluded from the dance, and every sort of public rejoicing, were daily occupied
                    in serving the men with roasted monkey, fermented liquors, and palm-cabbage.
                    This last production has the taste of our cauliflowers, and in no other country
                    had we seen specimens of such an immense size. The leaves that are not unfolded
                    are united with the young stem, and we measured cylinders of six feet long and
                    five inches in diameter. Another substance, which is much more nutritive, is
                    obtained from the animal kingdom: this is fish-flour (manioc de pescado). The
                    Indians throughout the Upper Orinoco fry fish, dry them in the sun, and reduce
                    them to powder without separating the bones. I have seen masses of fifty or
                    sixty pounds of this flour, which resembles that of cassava. When it is wanted
                    for eating, it is mixed with water, and reduced to a paste. In every climate the
                    abundance of fish has led to the invention of the same means of preserving them.
                    Pliny and Diodorus Siculus have described the fish-bread of the ichthyophagous
                    nations, that dwelt on the Persian Gulf and the shores of the Red
                    Sea.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
    <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">HUMBOLDT&#x2019;S PERSONAL NARRATIVE.</hi><lb break="yes"/>
                    (Literary Gazette.)<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#">Dirt-Eaters.</hi><lb break="yes"/>
                </head>
                <p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#in">T</hi>HE inhabitants of Uruana, be-<lb break="no"
                    />long to those <hi rendition="#i">nations of the sa-<lb break="no"
                        />vannahs</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">Indios andantes,</hi>) who, more<lb
                        break="yes"/>difficult to civilize than the <hi rendition="#i">nations of<lb
                            break="yes"/>the forest,</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">Indios del
                    monte,</hi>) have a<lb break="yes"/>decided aversion to cultivate the land,<lb
                        break="yes"/>and live almost exclusively on hunting<lb break="yes"/>and
                    fishing. They are men of very<lb break="yes"/>robust constitution; but ugly,
                        savage,<lb break="yes"/>vindictive, and passionately fond of<lb break="yes"
                    />fermented liquors. They are omnivo-<lb break="no"/>rous <hi rendition="#i"
                        >animals</hi> in the highest degree;<lb break="yes"/>and therefore the other
                    Indians, who<lb break="yes"/>consider them as barbarians, have a<lb break="yes"
                    />common saying, &#x2018;nothing is so disgust-<lb break="no"/>ing that an
                    Otomac will not eat it.&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>While the waters of the Oroonoko
                        and<lb break="yes"/>its tributary streams are low, the Oto-<lb break="no"
                    />macs subsist on fish and turtles. The<lb break="yes"/>former they kill with
                    surprising dexter-<lb break="no"/>ity, by shooting them with an arrow,<lb
                        break="yes"/>when they appear at the surface of the<lb break="yes"/>water.
                    When the rivers swell, which<lb break="yes"/>in South America as well as in
                        Egypt<lb break="yes"/>and in Nubia, is erroneously attributed<lb break="yes"
                    />to the melting of the snows, and which<lb break="yes"/>occurs periodically in
                    every part of the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone, fishing almost entirely<lb
                        break="yes"/>ceases. It is then as difficult to pro-<lb break="no"/>cure
                    fish in the rivers which are be-<lb break="no"/>come deeper, as when you are
                        sailing<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> on the open sea. It often fails the poor<lb break="yes"/>missionaries, on
                    fast-days as well as<lb break="yes"/>flesh days, though all the young Indians<lb
                        break="yes"/>are under the obligation of &#x2018;fishing for<lb break="yes"
                    />the convent.&#x2019; At the period of these<lb break="yes"/>inundations, which
                    lasts two or three<lb break="yes"/>months, the Otomacs swallow a prodi-<lb
                        break="no"/>gious quantity of earth. We found<lb break="yes"/>heaps of balls
                    in their huts, piled up in<lb break="yes"/>pyramids three or four feet high.
                        These<lb break="yes"/>balls were five or six inches in diame-<lb break="no"
                    />ter. The earth which the Otomacs eat<lb break="yes"/>is a very fine and
                    unctuous clay, of a<lb break="yes"/>yellowish grey colour; and, being slight-<lb
                        break="no"/>ly baked in the fire, the hardened crust<lb break="yes"/>has a
                    tint inclining to red, owing to the<lb break="yes"/>oxid of iron which is
                    mingled with it.<lb break="yes"/>We brought away some of this earth,<lb
                        break="yes"/>which we took from the winter provis-<lb break="no"/>ion of the
                    Indians; and it is absolutely<lb break="yes"/>false, that it is steatitic, and
                        contains<lb break="yes"/>magnesia. Mr. Vauquelin did not dis-<lb break="no"
                    />cover any traces of this earth in it; but<lb break="yes"/>he found that it
                    contained more silex than<lb break="yes"/>alumin, and three or four per cent of
                    lime.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The Otomacs do not eat every<lb break="yes"/>kind of clay indifferently;
                    they choose<lb break="yes"/>the alluvial beds or strata that contain<lb
                        break="yes"/>the most unctuous earth, and the<lb break="yes"/>smoothest to
                    the feel. I inquired of<lb break="yes"/>the missionary, whether the moistened<lb
                        break="yes"/>clay were made to undergo, as Father<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="199" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/> Gumilla asserts, that peculiar decom-<lb break="no"/>position, which is
                    indicated by a dis-<lb break="no"/>engagement of carbonic acid and sul-<lb
                        break="no"/>phuretted hydrogen, and which is de-<lb break="no"/>signated in
                    every language by the<lb break="yes"/>term of <hi rendition="#i"
                        >putrefaction;</hi> but he assured<lb break="yes"/>us, that the natives
                    neither cause the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">clay</hi> to <hi rendition="#i">rot,</hi> nor do they mingle
                    it with<lb break="yes"/>flour of maize, oil of turtles&#x2019; eggs, or fat<lb
                        break="yes"/>of the crocodile. We ourselves exam-<lb break="no"/>ined, both
                    at the Oroonoko and after our<lb break="yes"/>return to Paris, the balls of
                    earth which<lb break="yes"/>we brought away with us, and found<lb break="yes"
                    />no trace of the mixture of any organic<lb break="yes"/>substance, whether oily
                    or farinaceous.<lb break="yes"/>The savage regards every thing as nour-<lb
                        break="no"/>ishing that appeases hunger; when,<lb break="yes"/>therefore,
                    you inquire of an Otomac on<lb break="yes"/>what he subsists during the two
                        months<lb break="yes"/>when the river is the highest, he shows<lb
                        break="yes"/>you his balls of clayey earth. This he<lb break="yes"/>calls
                    his principal food; for all this pe-<lb break="no"/>riod he can seldom procure a
                    lizard, a<lb break="yes"/>root of fern, or a dead fish swimming at<lb
                        break="yes"/>the surface of the water. If the Indian<lb break="yes"/>eat
                    earth from want during two months,<lb break="yes"/>(and from three quarters to
                    five quar-<lb break="no"/>ters of a pound in twenty-four hours,)<lb break="yes"
                    />he does not the less regale himself with<lb break="yes"/>it during the rest of
                    the year. Every<lb break="yes"/>day in the season of drought, when fish-<lb
                        break="no"/>ing is most abundant, he scrapes his<lb break="yes"/>balls of
                        <hi rendition="#i">poya,</hi> and mingles a little clay<lb break="yes"/>with
                    his other aliment. What is most<lb break="yes"/>surprising is, that the Otomacs
                    do not<lb break="yes"/>become lean by swallowing such quan-<lb break="no"
                    />tities of earth; they are, on the contra-<lb break="no"/>ry, extremely robust,
                    and far from hav-<lb break="no"/>ing the belly tense and puffed up. The<lb
                        break="yes"/>missionary Fray Ramon Bueno asserts,<lb break="yes"/>that he
                    never remarked any alteration<lb break="yes"/>in the health of the natives at
                    the peri-<lb break="no"/>od of the great risings of the Oroonoko.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The following are the facts in all<lb break="yes"/>their simplicity,
                    which we were able to<lb break="yes"/>verify. The Otomacs during some<lb
                        break="yes"/>months, eat daily three quarters of a<lb break="yes"/>pound of
                    clay slightly hardened by fire,<lb break="yes"/>without their health being
                        materially<lb break="yes"/>affected by it. They moisten the earth<lb
                        break="yes"/>afresh when they are going to swallow<lb break="yes"/>it. It
                    has not been possible to verify<lb break="yes"/>hitherto with precision how much
                        nu-<lb break="no"/>tritious vegetable or animal matter the<lb break="yes"
                    />Indians take in a week at the same<lb break="yes"/>time; but it is certain
                    that they attri-<lb break="no"/>bute the sensation of satiety which they<lb
                        break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> feel, to the clay, and not to the wretch-<lb break="no"/>ed aliments which
                    they take with it<lb break="yes"/>occasionally. No physiological phe-<lb
                        break="no"/>nomenon being entirely insulated, it<lb break="yes"/>may be
                    interesting to examine several<lb break="yes"/>analogous phenomena, which I
                        have<lb break="yes"/>been able to collect.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;I observed every where within the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone, in a great
                    number of indi-<lb break="no"/>viduals, children, women, and some-<lb break="no"
                    />times even full-grown men, an inordi-<lb break="no"/>nate and almost
                    irresistible desire of<lb break="yes"/>swallowing earth; not an alkaline or<lb
                        break="yes"/>calcareous earth, to neutralize (as it is<lb break="yes"
                    />vulgarly said) acid juices, but a fat clay,<lb break="yes"/>unctuous, and
                    exhaling a strong smell.<lb break="yes"/>It is often found necessary to tie
                        the<lb break="yes"/>children&#x2019;s hands, or to confine them, to<lb
                        break="yes"/>prevent their eating earth when the rain<lb break="yes"/>ceases
                    to fall. At the village of Banco,<lb break="yes"/>on the bank of the river
                    Magdalena, I<lb break="yes"/>saw the Indian women who make pot-<lb break="no"
                    />tery continually swallowing great pieces<lb break="yes"/>of clay.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The author goes at some length into<lb break="yes"/>analogies and reasoning on
                    them, but<lb break="yes"/>we confine our quotation principally to<lb break="yes"
                    />the facts.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The negroes on the coast of Guinea<lb break="yes"/>delight in eating a
                    yellowish earth which<lb break="yes"/>they call <hi rendition="#i">caouac.</hi>
                    The slaves who are<lb break="yes"/>taken to America try to procure for<lb
                        break="yes"/>themselves the same enjoyment; but it<lb break="yes"/>is
                    constantly detrimental to their health.<lb break="yes"/>They say, &#x2018;that
                    the earth of the West<lb break="yes"/>Indies is not so easy of digestion as
                        that<lb break="yes"/>of their country.&#x2019;&#x201D; * * *</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In the Indian Archipelago, at the<lb break="yes"/>island of Java, Mr.
                    Labillardière saw,<lb break="yes"/>between Surabaya and Samarang, little<lb
                        break="yes"/>square and reddish cakes exposed to<lb break="yes"/>sale. These
                    cakes, called <hi rendition="#i">tanaampo,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>were cakes of clay, slightly baked,<lb break="yes"/>which the
                    natives eat with appetite.<lb break="yes"/>The attention of physiologists,
                        since<lb break="yes"/>my return from the Oroonoko, having<lb break="yes"
                    />been powerfully fixed on these phenom-<lb break="no"/>ena of <hi
                        rendition="#i">geophagy,</hi> Mr. Leschenault,<lb break="yes"/>(one of the
                    naturalists of the expedition<lb break="yes"/>to the Southern Lands under the
                        com-<lb break="no"/>mand of Captain Baudin) has published<lb break="yes"
                    />some curious details on the <hi rendition="#i">tanaampo,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>or <hi rendition="#i">ampo,</hi> of the Javanese. &#x2018;The
                        red-<lb break="no"/>dish and somewhat ferruginous clay,&#x2019;<lb
                        break="yes"/>he says, &#x2018;which the inhabitants of Java<lb break="yes"
                    />are fond of eating occasionally is spread<lb break="yes"/>on a plate of iron,
                    and baked, after<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="200" facs="#f0003"/>
                    <cb/> having been rolled into little cylinders<lb break="yes"/>in the form of
                    the bark of cinnamon.<lb break="yes"/>In this state it takes the name of <hi
                        rendition="#i">ampo,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and is sold in the public markets. This<lb break="yes"/>clay
                    has a peculiar taste, which is owing<lb break="yes"/>to the torrefaction; it is
                    very absorbent,<lb break="yes"/>and adheres to the tongue, which it<lb
                        break="yes"/>dries. In general it is only the Java-<lb break="no"/>nese
                    women who eat the <hi rendition="#i">ampo,</hi> either<lb break="yes"/>in the
                    time of their pregnancy, or in<lb break="yes"/>order to grow thin; the want of
                        plump-<lb break="no"/>ness being a kind of beauty in this<lb break="yes"
                    />country. The use of this earth is fatal<lb break="yes"/>to health; the women
                    lose their appe-<lb break="no"/>tite imperceptibly, and no longer take<lb
                        break="yes"/>without disgust a very small quantity<lb break="yes"/>of food:
                    but the desire of becoming<lb break="yes"/>lean, and of preserving a slender
                        shape,<lb break="yes"/>can brave these dangers, and maintains<lb break="yes"
                    />the credit of the <hi rendition="#i">ampo.</hi>&#x2019; The savage<lb
                        break="yes"/>inhabitants of New Caledonia also, to<lb break="yes"/>appease
                    their hunger in times of scar-<lb break="no"/>city, eat great pieces of a
                    friable <hi rendition="#i">lapis<lb break="yes"/>ollaris.</hi> Mr. Vauquelin
                    analysed this<lb break="yes"/>stone, and found in it, beside magnesia<lb
                        break="yes"/>and silex in equal portions, a small<lb break="yes"/>quantity
                    of oxid of copper. Mr. Gold-<lb break="no"/>berry had seen the negroes in
                        Africa,<lb break="yes"/>in the islands of Bunck and Los Idolos,<lb
                        break="yes"/>eat an earth of which he had himself<lb break="yes"/>eaten,
                    without being incommoded by it,<lb break="yes"/>and which also was a white and
                        friable<lb break="yes"/>steatite.&#x201D; * * * * *</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>&#x201C;When we reflect on the whole of<lb break="yes"/>these facts, we perceive
                    that this disor-<lb break="no"/>derly appetite for clayey, magnesian,<lb
                        break="yes"/>and calcareous earth, is most common<lb break="yes"/>among the
                    people of the torrid zone;<lb break="yes"/>that it is not always a cause of
                        disease;<lb break="yes"/>and that some tribes eat earth from<lb break="yes"
                    />choice, while others (the Otomacs in<lb break="yes"/>America, and the
                    inhabitants of New<lb break="yes"/>Caledonia, in the Pacific Ocean,) eat it<lb
                        break="yes"/>from want, and to appease hunger.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The observations, which I made on<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the
                            <choice><sic>Oroonoka</sic><corr type="editorial"
                        >Oroonoko</corr></choice>, have been<lb break="yes"/>recently confirmed by
                    the direct experi-<lb break="no"/>ments of two distinguished young phy-<lb
                        break="no"/>siologists, Messrs. Hippolite Cloquet<lb break="yes"/>and
                    Breschet. After long fasting, they<lb break="yes"/>ate as much as five ounces of
                    a silvery<lb break="yes"/>green and very fiexible laminar talc.<lb break="yes"
                    />Their hunger was completely satisfied,<lb break="yes"/>and they felt no
                    inconvenience from a<lb break="yes"/>kind of food, to which their organs were<lb
                        break="yes"/>unaccustomed. It is known that great<lb break="yes"/>use is
                    still made in the East of the bolar<lb break="yes"/>and sigillated earths of
                    Lemnos, which<lb break="yes"/>are clay mingled with oxid of iron. In<lb
                        break="yes"/>Germany, the workmen employed in<lb break="yes"/>the quarries
                    of sandstone worked at the<lb break="yes"/>mountain of Kiffh&#x00E6;user spread
                    a very<lb break="yes"/>fine clay upon their bread, instead of<lb break="yes"
                    />butter, which they call <hi rendition="#i">steinbutter,</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">&#x201C;This <hi rendition="#i">steinbutter</hi> must
                        not be confounded with the <hi rendition="#i">mountain butter,
                            bergbutter,</hi> which is a saline<lb break="yes"/>substance, owing to a
                        decomposition of aluminous schists.&#x201D;</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>stone butter; and they find it singularly<lb break="yes"
                    />filling, and easy of digestion<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;"
                        >&#x201C;Freiesleben, Kupferschiefer, vol. iv. p. 118. Kesler, in
                        Gilbert&#x2019;s Annalen, B. 28, p. 492.&#x201D;</note>.&#x201D;<lb
                        break="yes"/></p>
            </div>
    <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">HUMBOLDT&#x2019;S NARRATIVE.</hi><lb break="yes"/>
                        Concluded.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#">Stories of Crocodiles.</hi><lb break="yes"/>
                </head>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Our</hi> latter extracts from this publication<lb break="yes"
                    />have been as desultory as the curious na-<lb break="no"/>ture of the
                    author&#x2019;s inquiries seemed to re-<lb break="no"/>quire, without servilely
                    following him<lb break="yes"/>through all his topographical details, and<lb
                        break="yes"/>philosophical <hi rendition="#i">generalizations.</hi> In the
                        same<lb break="yes"/>spirit, we shall now conclude our notice of<lb
                        break="yes"/>these volumes with a brief sequel relating<lb break="yes"/>to
                    the crocodiles of the Oroonoko.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;When the waters (says Mr. H.) are<lb break="yes"/>high, the river
                    inundates the keys; and it<lb break="yes"/>sometimes happens, that even in the
                        town<lb break="yes"/>imprudent men become the prey of croco-<lb break="no"
                    />diles. I shall transcribe from my journal a<lb break="yes"/>fact, that took
                    place during Mr. Bonpland&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>illness. A Guaykeri Indian,
                    from the island<lb break="yes"/>de la Margaretta, went to anchor his canoe<lb
                        break="yes"/>in a cove, where there were not three feet<lb break="yes"/>of
                    water. A very fierce crocodile, that ha-<lb break="no"/>bitually haunted that
                    spot, seized him by<lb break="yes"/>the leg, and withdrew from the shore, re-<lb
                        break="no"/>maining on the surface of the water. The<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> cries of the Indian drew together a crowd<lb break="yes"/>of spectators.
                    This unfortunate man was<lb break="yes"/>first seen seeking with astonishing
                        courage<lb break="yes"/>for a knife in the pocket of his pantaloons.<lb
                        break="yes"/>Not being able to find it, he seized the head<lb break="yes"
                    />of the crocodile, and thrust his fingers into<lb break="yes"/>its eyes. No man
                    in the hot regions of<lb break="yes"/>America is ignorant, that this
                        carnivorous<lb break="yes"/>reptile, covered with a buckler of hard and<lb
                        break="yes"/>dry scales, is extremely sensible in the only<lb break="yes"
                    />parts of his body which are soft and unpro-<lb break="no"/>tected, such as the
                    eyes, the hollow under-<lb break="no"/>neath the shoulders, the nostrils, and
                        be-<lb break="no"/>neath the lower jaw, where there are two<lb break="yes"
                    />glands of musk. The Guaykeri Indian had<lb break="yes"/>recourse to the same
                    means which saved<lb break="yes"/>the negro of Mungo Park, and the girl of<lb
                        break="yes"/>Uritucu, whom I have mentioned above;<lb break="yes"/>but he
                    was less fortunate than they had<lb break="yes"/>been, for the crocodile did not
                    open its<lb break="yes"/>jaws, and lose hold of its prey. The ani-<lb break="no"
                    />mal, yielding to the pain, plunged to the<lb break="yes"/>bottom of the river;
                    and, after having<lb break="yes"/>drowned the Indian, came up to the surface<lb
                        break="yes"/>of the water, dragging the dead body to an<lb break="yes"
                    />island opposite the port. I arrived at the<lb break="yes"/>moment when a great
                    number of the inha-<lb break="no"/>bitants of Angostura had witnessed this
                        me-<lb break="no"/>lancholy spectacle.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;As the crocodile, on account of the<lb break="yes"/>structure of its
                    larynx, of the hyoid bone,<lb break="yes"/>and of the folds of its tongue, can
                        seize,<lb break="yes"/>though not swallow, its prey under water;<lb
                        break="yes"/>a man seldom disappears without the ani-<lb break="no"/>mal
                    being perceived some hours after near<lb break="yes"/>the spot where the
                    misfortune has happened,<lb break="yes"/>devouring its prey on a neighbouring
                        beach.<lb break="yes"/>The number of individuals who perish an-<lb
                        break="no"/>nually, the victims of their own imprudence<lb break="yes"/>and
                    of the ferocity of these reptiles, is much<lb break="yes"/>greater than it is
                    believed to be in Europe.<lb break="yes"/>It is particularly so in villages,
                    where the<lb break="yes"/>neighbouring grounds are often inundated.<lb
                        break="yes"/>The same crocodiles remain long in the<lb break="yes"/>same
                    places. They become from year to<lb break="yes"/>year more daring, especially,
                    as the Indians<lb break="yes"/>assert, if they have once tasted of human<lb
                        break="yes"/>flesh. These animals are so wary, that they<lb break="yes"/>are
                    killed with difficulty. A ball does not<lb break="yes"/>pierce their skin, and
                    the shot is only mor-<lb break="no"/>tal when directed at the throat, or
                        beneath<lb break="yes"/>the shoulder. The Indians, who know<lb break="yes"
                    />little of the use of fire-arms, attack the cro-<lb break="no"/>codile with
                    lances, after it is caught with<lb break="yes"/>large pointed iron hooks, baited
                    with pieces<lb break="yes"/>of meat, and fastened by a chain to the<lb
                        break="yes"/>trunk of a tree. They do not approach the<lb break="yes"
                    />animal till it has struggled a long time to<lb break="yes"/>disengage itself
                    from the iron fixed in the<lb break="yes"/>upper jaw. There is little
                    probability that<lb break="yes"/>a country in which a labyrinth of rivers<lb
                        break="yes"/>without number brings every day new bands<lb break="yes"/>of
                    crocodiles from the eastern back of the<lb break="yes"/>Andes, by the Meta and
                    the Apure, towards<lb break="yes"/>the coast of Spanish Guyana, should ever<lb
                        break="yes"/>be delivered from these reptiles. All that<lb break="yes"/>will
                    be gained by civilization will be, to<lb break="yes"/>render them more timid,
                    and more easily<lb break="yes"/>put to flight.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Affecting instances are related of Afri-<lb break="no"/>can slaves, who
                    have exposed their lives<lb break="yes"/>to save those of their masters, who
                        had<lb break="yes"/>fallen into the jaws of the crocodile. A few<lb
                        break="yes"/>years ago, between Uritucu and the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Mission</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="663" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">de Abaxo,</hi> a negro, hearing the cries of his<lb
                        break="yes"/>master, flew to the spot, armed with a long<lb break="yes"
                    />knife, <hi rendition="#i">(machette,)</hi> and plunged into the<lb break="yes"
                    />river. He forced the crocodile, by putting<lb break="yes"/>out his eyes, to
                    let go his prey, and hide<lb break="yes"/>himself under the water. The slave
                        bore<lb break="yes"/>his expiring master to the shore, but all<lb
                        break="yes"/>succour was unavailing to restore him to<lb break="yes"/>life.
                    He died of suffocation, for his wounds<lb break="yes"/>were not deep; the
                    crocodile, like the<lb break="yes"/>dog, appears not to close its jaws firmly<lb
                        break="yes"/>while swimming. It is almost superfluous<lb break="yes"/>to
                    add, that the children of the deceased,<lb break="yes"/>though poor, gave the
                    slave his freedom.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Upon the whole, this portion of Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt&#x2019;s work is
                    equally entertaining<lb break="yes"/>with what has gone before, and throws<lb
                        break="yes"/>much light on Physics and Geography.</p>
            </div>
</body> 
<back/> 
</text> 
    </TEI>