<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">War Poison of the Indians</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:58</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.20</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1821-War_Poison_of-1</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent&lt;/i&gt;, 7 Bände, übersetzt von Helen Maria Williams, London 1814–1829, Band 5, London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, and Brown 1821, S. 514–517, 519–520, 522, 526.;</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Relation historique du Voyage aux régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent&lt;/i&gt;, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 2, S. 547–550, 551, 553.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">War Poison of the Indians</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1821</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Philosophical Magazine and Journal&lt;/i&gt; 58:281 (September 1821), S. 231–234. [Zuvor bereits in: „Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent, during the years 1799–1804. By Alexander de Humboldt, and Aimé Bonpland, &amp;amp;c. &amp;amp;c. London, 1821, 8vo. 2 Vols. pp. 864“, in: &lt;i&gt;The Literary Gazette; and Journal of Belles Lettres, Arts, Sciences, &amp;amp;c.&lt;/i&gt; 229 (9. Juni 1821), S. 353–355; 230 (16. Juni 1821), S. 374–376; 231 (23. Juni 1821), S. 389–391; 232 (30. Juni 1821), S. 405–406; 234 (14. Juli 1821), S. 441–442; 242 (8. September 1821), S. 563–565; 243 (15. September 1821), S. 580–582; 245 (29. September 1821), S. 615–616; 248 (20. Oktober 1821), S. 662–663, hier 242 (8. September 1821), S. 563–564.]</title>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <relatedItem type="reprint">
            <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Ueber die Urvölker von Amerika und die Denkmähler welche von ihnen übrig geblieben sind Anthropologische und ethnographische Schriften&lt;/i&gt;, herausgegeben von Oliver Lubrich, Hannover: Wehrhahn 2009, S. 45–48.</bibl>
          </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="231" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>WAR POISON OF THE INDIANS.<lb break="yes"/>[From Humboldt&#x2019;s Personal Narrative.]</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Esmeralda is the most celebrated spot on the Oroonoko for<lb break="yes"/>the fabrication of that active poison which is employed in war,<lb break="yes"/>in the chase, and, what is singular enough, as a remedy for gastric<lb break="yes" />obstructions. The poison of the <choice><sic>ficunas</sic><corr type="editorial">ticunas</corr></choice> of the Amazon, the upas-<lb break="no" />tieute of Java, and the <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi> of Guyana, are the most deleterious<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">substances</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="232" facs="#f0002"/> substances that are known. Raleigh, toward the end of the six-<lb break="no"/>teenth century, had heard the name of <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi> pronounced as<lb break="yes"/>being a vegetable substance, with which arrows were envenomed;<lb break="yes"/>yet no fixed notions of this poison had reached Europe. The<lb break="yes"/>missionaries Gumilla and Gili had not been able to penetrate in-<lb break="no"/>to the country where the curare is manufactured. Gumilla as-<lb break="no"/>serts that this preparable was enveloped in great mystery; that<lb break="yes"/>its principal ingredient was furnished by a subterraneous plant,<lb break="yes"/>by a tuberose root, which never puts forth leaves, and which is<lb break="yes" />called the root by way of eminence, <hi rendition="#i">raiz de si misma;</hi> that the<lb break="yes"/>venomous exhalations, which arise from the pots, cause the old<lb break="yes"/>women (the most <hi rendition="#i">useless</hi>) to perish who are chosen to watch<lb break="yes"/>over this operation; finally, that these vegetable juices never<lb break="yes"/>appear sufficiently concentrated, till a few drops produce <hi rendition="#i">at a<lb break="yes" />distance</hi> a repulsive action on the blood. An Indian wounds him-<lb break="no"/>self slightly; and a dart dipped in the liquid <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi> is held near<lb break="yes"/>the wound. If it make the blood return to the vessels without<lb break="yes"/>having been brought into contact with them, the poison is judged<lb break="yes"/>to be sufficiently concentrated. I shall not stop to refute these<lb break="yes"/>popular tales collected by Father Gumilla.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When we arrived at Esmeralda, the greater part of the In-<lb break="no"/>dians were returning from an excursion which they had made to<lb break="yes"/>the east beyond the Rio Padamo, to gather <hi rendition="#i">juvias</hi>, or the fruit<lb break="yes"/>of the Bertholletia, and the liana which yields the curare. Their<lb break="yes"/>return was celebrated by a festival, which is called in the Mission<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">la fiesta de las juvias</hi>, and which resembles our harvest homes<lb break="yes"/>and vintage feasts. The women had prepared a quantity of fer-<lb break="no"/>mented liquor, and during two days the Indians were in a state<lb break="yes"/>of intoxication. Among nations that attach great importance<lb break="yes"/>to the fruits of the palm-trees and of some others useful for the<lb break="yes"/>nourishment of man, the period when these fruits are gathered<lb break="yes"/>is marked by public rejoicings, and time is divided according to<lb break="yes"/>these festivals, which succeed one another in a course invariably<lb break="yes"/>the same. We were fortunate enough to find an old Indian less<lb break="yes"/>drunk than the rest, who was employed in preparing the <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>poison from freshly gathered plants. He was the chemist of<lb break="yes"/>the place. We found at his dwelling large earthen pots for<lb break="yes"/>boiling vegetable juice, shallower vessels to favour the evaporation<lb break="yes"/>by a larger surface, and leaves of the plane-tree rolled up in the<lb break="yes"/>shape of our filters, and used to filtrate the liquors more or less<lb break="yes"/>loaded with fibrous matter. The greatest order and neatness<lb break="yes"/>prevailed in this hut, which was transformed into a chemical la-<lb break="no"/>boratory. The Indian who was to instruct us, is known through-<lb break="no"/>out the mission by the name of the <hi rendition="#i">master of poison</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">amo del<lb break="yes"/>curare</hi>)<hi rendition="#i">:</hi> he had that self-sufficient air and tone of pedantry, of<lb break="yes"/>which the pharmacopolists of Europe were formerly accused<choice>
                        <sic>;&#x201C;</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">; &#x201C;</corr>
                    </choice> I<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">know,&#x201D;</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="233" facs="#f0003"/> know,&#x201D; said he, &#x201C;that the whites have the secret of fabricating<lb break="yes"/>soap, and that black powder which has the effect of making a<lb break="yes"/>noise and killing animals, when they are wanted. The <hi rendition="#i">curare,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>which we prepare from father to son, is superior to any thing you<lb break="yes"/>can make <hi rendition="#i">down yonder</hi> (beyond sea). It is the juice of an herb<lb break="yes"/>which <hi rendition="#i">kills silently</hi> (without any one knowing whence the stroke<lb break="yes" />comes).&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This chemical operation, to which the <hi rendition="#i">master of the curare</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>attached so much importance, appears to us extremely simple.<lb break="yes"/>The liana (<hi rendition="#i">bujuco</hi>), which is used at Esmeralda for the prepara-<lb break="no"/>tion of the poison, bears the same name as in the forest of Javita.<lb break="yes"/>It is the <hi rendition="#i" >bejuco de mavacure</hi>, which is gathered in abundance<lb break="yes" />east of the Mission, on the left bank of the Oroonoko, beyond<lb break="yes" />the Rio Amaguaca, in the mountains and granatic lands of Gua-<lb break="no" />naya and Yumariquin.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The juice of the liana, when it has been recently gathered, is<lb break="yes" />not regarded as poisonous; perhaps it acts in a sensible manner<lb break="yes" />only when it is strongly concentrated. It is the bark, and a part<lb break="yes"/>of the alburnum, which contains this terrible poison. Branches<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i">mavacure</hi> four or five lines in diameter, are scraped with a<lb break="yes"/>knife; and the bark that comes off is bruised, and reduced into<lb break="yes"/>very thin filaments, on the stone employed for grinding cassava.<lb break="yes"/>The venomous juice being yellow, the whole fibrous mass takes<lb break="yes"/>this colour. It is thrown into a funnel nine inches high, with an<lb break="yes"/>opening four inches wide. This funnel was, of all the instru-<lb break="no"/>ments of the Indian laboratory, that of which the <hi rendition="#i">master of poi-<lb break="no"/>son</hi> seemed to be most proud. He asked us repeatedly, if <hi rendition="#i">por<lb break="yes"/>alla</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">down yonder,</hi> that is in Europe) we had ever seen any thing<lb break="yes" />to be compared to his <hi rendition="#i">empudo.</hi> It was a leaf of a plantain tree<lb break="yes"/>rolled up in the form of a cone, and placed in another stronger<lb break="yes"/>cone made of the leaves of the palm-tree. The whole of this<lb break="yes"/>apparatus was supported by slight frame work made of the petioli<lb break="yes"/>and ribs of palm leaves. A cold infusion is first prepared by<lb break="yes"/>pouring water on the fibrous matter, which is the ground bark of<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">mavacure.</hi> A yellowish water filters during several hours,<lb break="yes"/>drop by drop, through the leafy funnel. This filtered water is the<lb break="yes"/>venomous liquor, but it acquires strength only when it is concen-<lb break="no"/>trated by evaporation, like molasses in a large earthen pot.<lb break="yes"/>The Indian from time to time invited us to taste the liquid; its<lb break="yes"/>taste, more or less bitter, decides when the concentration by fire<lb break="yes"/>has been carried sufficiently far. There is no danger in this ope-<lb break="no"/>ration, the <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi> being deleterious only when it comes into im-<lb break="no"/>mediate contact with the blood. The vapours, therefore, that<lb break="yes"/>are disengaged from the pans, are not hurtful, notwithstanding<lb break="yes"/>what has been asserted on this point by the Missionaries of the<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko. Fontana, in his fine experiments on the poison of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">
                        <hi rendition="#i">ticunas</hi>
                    </fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="234" facs="#f0004"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">ticunas</hi> of the river of Amazons, long ago proved, that the va-<lb break="no"/>pours arising from this poison when thrown on burning charcoal,<lb break="yes"/>may be inhaled without apprehension; and that it is false, as<lb break="yes"/>M. de la Condamine has announced, that Indian women, when con-<lb break="no"/>demned to death, have been killed by the vapours of the poison<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i">ticunas.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The juice is thickened with a glutinous substance to cause it<lb break="yes"/>to
          stick to the darts, which it renders mortal; but taken inter-<lb break="no"/>nally, the
          Indians consider the <hi rendition="#i">curare</hi> to be an excellent stoma-<lb
            break="no"/>chic. Scarcely a fowl is eaten (adds our author) on the banks<lb break="yes"
          />of the Oroonoko, which has not been killed with a poisoned<lb break="yes"/>arrow. The
          Missionaries pretend, that the flesh of animals is<lb break="yes"/>never so good as when
          these means are employed. Father Zea,<lb break="yes"/>who accompanied us, though ill of a
          tertian fever, caused every<lb break="yes"/>morning the live fowl allotted for our repast
          to be brought to his<lb break="yes"/>hammock, together with an arrow. Notwithstanding his
            habi-<lb break="no"/>tual state of weakness, he would not confide this operation, to<lb
            break="yes"/>which he attached great importance, to any other person. Large<lb
            break="yes"/>birds, a guan (<hi rendition="#i">pava de monte</hi>) for instance, or a
          curassoa (<hi rendition="#i">alse-<lb break="no"/>tor,</hi>) when wounded in the thigh,
          perish in two or three minutes;<lb break="yes"/>but it is often ten or twelve before a pig
          or a pecari expires.<note place="foot" n="*">M. Humboldt does not seem to be acquainted
            with any certain antidote,<lb break="yes"/>if such exists, to this fatal poison. Sugar,
            garlic, the muriate of soda, &amp;c.<lb break="yes"/>are mentioned
          doubtingly.</note></p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 