<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Visit of the ruins of Ataruipe</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:58</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.29</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1822-Visit_of_the-1-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1822-Visit_of_the-1-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1822-Visit_of_the-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1822-Visit_of_the-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1822-Visit_of_the-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent&lt;/i&gt;, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 2, S. 596–598, 600.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Visit of the ruins of Ataruipe</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1822</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Cento: A Selection of Approved Pieces, from Living Authors&lt;/i&gt;,&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt; London: John Richardson/C. and J. White 1822, S. 80–83. [Zuvor bereits in: „Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent, during the years 1799–1804. By Alexander de Humboldt, and Aimé Bonpland, &amp;amp;c. &amp;amp;c. London, 1821, 8vo. 2 Vols. pp. 864“, in: &lt;i&gt;The Literary Gazette; and Journal of Belles Lettres, Arts, Sciences, &amp;amp;c.&lt;/i&gt; 229 (9. Juni 1821), S. 353–355; 230 (16. Juni 1821), S. 374–376; 231 (23. Juni 1821), S. 389–391; 232 (30. Juni 1821), S. 405–406; 234 (14. Juli 1821), S. 441–442; 242 (8. September 1821), S. 563–565; 243 (15. September 1821), S. 580–582; 245 (29. September 1821), S. 615–616; 248 (20. Oktober 1821), S. 662–663, hier 243 (15. September 1821), S. 581–582.]</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="80" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>VISIT TO THE RUINS OF ATARUIPE.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">[From M. de Homboldt&#x2019;s Personal Narrative.]</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">We</hi> climbed with difficulty, and not without some danger,<lb break="yes"/>a steep rock of granite, entirely bare. It would have been<lb break="yes"/>almost impossible to fix the foot on its smooth and sloping<lb break="yes"/>surface, if large crystals of feldspar, resisting decomposi-<lb break="no"/>tion, did not stand out from the rock, and furnish points of<lb break="yes"/>support. Scarcely had we attained the summit of the<lb break="yes"/>mountain, when we beheld with astonishment the singular<lb break="yes"/>aspect of the surrounding country. The foamy bed of the<lb break="yes"/>waters is filled with an archipelago of islands covered with<lb break="yes"/>palm-trees. Toward the west, on the left bank of the<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko, stretch the savannahs of the Meta and the Ca-<lb break="no"/>sanare. They resembled a sea of verdure, the misty horizon<lb break="yes"/>of which was illumined by the rays of the setting sun. Its<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="81" facs="#f0002"/> orb, resembling a globe of fire, suspended over the plain;<lb break="yes"/>and the solitary Peak of Uniana, which appeared more lofty<lb break="yes"/>from being wrapped in vapours that softened its outline;<lb break="yes"/>all contributed to augment the majesty of the scene. Near<lb break="yes"/>us the eye looked down into a deep valley, enclosed on<lb break="yes"/>every side. Birds of prey and goatsuckers winged their<lb break="yes"/>lonely flight in this inaccessible circus. We found a plea-<lb break="no"/>sure in following with the eye their fleeting shadows as<lb break="yes"/>they glided slowly over the flanks of the rock.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A narrow ridge led us to a neighbouring mountain, the<lb break="yes"/>rounded summit of which supported immense blocks of<lb break="yes"/>granite. These masses are more than forty or fifty feet in<lb break="yes"/>diameter; and their form is so perfectly spherical, that,<lb break="yes"/>appearing to touch the soil only by a small number of<lb break="yes"/>points, it might be supposed, at the least shock of an earth-<lb break="no"/>quake, they would roll into the abyss. I do not remember<lb break="yes"/>to have seen any where else a similar phenomenon, amid<lb break="yes"/>the decompositions of granitic soils. If the balls rested on<lb break="yes"/>a rock of a different nature, as it happens in the blocks of<lb break="yes"/>Jura, we might suppose, that they had been rounded by<lb break="yes"/>the action of water, or thrown out by the force of an elastic<lb break="yes"/>fluid; but their position on the summit of a hill alike gra-<lb break="no"/>nitic makes it more probable, that they owe their origin to<lb break="yes"/>the progressive decomposition of the rock.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The most remote part of the valley is covered by a thick<lb break="yes"/>forest. In this shady and solitary spot, on the declivity of<lb break="yes"/>a steep mountain, the cavern of Ataruipe opens itself; it is<lb break="yes"/>less a cavern than a jutting rock, in which the waters have<lb break="yes"/>scooped a vast hollow, when, in the ancient revolutions of<lb break="yes"/>our planet, they attained that height. We soon reckoned<lb break="yes"/>in this tomb of a whole extinct tribe near six hundred<lb break="yes"/>skeletons well preserved, and so regularly placed, that it<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="82" facs="#f0003"/> would have been difficult to make an error in their number.<lb break="yes"/>Every skeleton reposes in a sort of basket, made of the<lb break="yes"/>petioles of the palm-tree. These baskets, which the na-<lb break="no"/>tives call <hi rendition="#i">mapires,</hi> have the form of a square bag. Their<lb break="yes"/>size is proportioned to the age of the dead; there are some<lb break="yes"/>for infant&#x2019;s cut off at the moment of their birth. We saw<lb break="yes"/>them from ten inches to three feet four inches long, the<lb break="yes"/>skeletons in them being bent together. They are all<lb break="yes"/>ranged near each other, and are so entire, that not a rib,<lb break="yes"/>or a phalanx is wanting. The bones have been prepared in<lb break="yes"/>three different manners, either whitened in the air and the<lb break="yes"/>sun; dyed red with onoto, a colouring matter extracted<lb break="yes"/>from the bixa orellana; or, like real mummies, varnished<lb break="yes"/>with odoriferous resins, and enveloped in leaves of the heli-<lb break="no"/>conia or of the plantain tree. The Indians related to us,<lb break="yes"/>that the fresh corpse is placed in damp ground, in order<lb break="yes"/>that the flesh may be consumed by degrees; some months<lb break="yes"/>after, it is taken out, and the flesh remaining on the bones<lb break="yes"/>is scraped off with sharp stones. Several hordes in Guya-<lb break="no"/>na still observe this custom. Earthen vases half-baked are<lb break="yes"/>found near the <hi rendition="#i">mapires,</hi> or baskets. They appear to con-<lb break="no"/>tain the bones of the same family. The largest of these<lb break="yes"/>vases, or funeral urns, are three feet high, and five feet and<lb break="yes"/>a half long. Their colour is greenish gray; and their oval<lb break="yes"/>form is sufficiently pleasing to the eye. The handles are<lb break="yes"/>made in the shape of crocodiles, or serpents; the edge is<lb break="yes"/>bordered with meanders, labyrinths, and real <hi rendition="#i">grecques,</hi> in<lb break="yes"/>straight lines variously combined. Such paintings are<lb break="yes"/>found in every zone, among nations the most remote from<lb break="yes"/>each other, either with respect to the spot which they<lb break="yes"/>occupy on the globe, or to the degree of civilization which<lb break="yes"/>they have attained. The inhabitants of the little mission<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="83" facs="#f0004"/> of Maypures still execute them on their commonest pot-<lb break="no"/>tery; they decorate the bucklers of the Otaheiteans, the<lb break="yes"/>fishing implements of the Eskimoes, the walls of the<lb break="yes"/>Mexican palace of Mitla, and the vases of ancient Greece.<lb break="yes"/>Every where a rhythmic repetition of the same forms flat-<lb break="no"/>ters the eye, as the cadenced repetition of sounds soothes<lb break="yes"/>the ear. Analogies founded on the internal nature of our<lb break="yes"/>feelings, on the natural dispositions of our intellect, are<lb break="yes"/>not calculated to throw light on the filiation and the an-<lb break="no"/>cient connexions of nations.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We withdrew in silence from the cavern of Ataruipe. It<lb break="yes"/>was one of those calm and serene nights, which are so com-<lb break="no"/>mon in the torrid zone. The stars shone with a mild and<lb break="yes"/>planetary light. Their scintillation was scarcely sensible<lb break="yes"/>at the horizon, which seemed illumined by the great ne-<lb break="no"/>bul&#x00E6; of the southern hemisphere. An innumerable mul-<lb break="no"/>titude of insects spread a reddish light on the ground,<lb break="yes"/>loaded with plants, and resplendent with these living and<lb break="yes"/>moving fires, as if the stars of the firmament had sunk<lb break="yes"/>down on the savannah. On quitting the cavern, we stopped<lb break="yes"/>several times to admire the beauty of this singular scene.<lb break="yes"/>The odoriferous vanilla, and festoons of bignonia, deco-<lb break="no"/>rated the entrance; and above, on the summit of the hill,<lb break="yes"/>the arrowy branches of the palm-trees waved murmuring in<lb break="yes"/>the air.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 