<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="133" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">THE ATURES.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the sources of the Orinoco,<note place="foot" n="*">Lat. 5° 39&#x2032; north.</note> among the forest solitudes of one of the<lb break="yes" />remotest European missions, Baron Humboldt discovered the cavern-sepulchre of<lb break="yes"/>an extinct, but once powerful tribe, called <hi rendition="#i">Atures.</hi> As the annexed drawing was<lb break="yes"/>made from one of the identical skulls brought by that distinguished traveller, I<lb break="yes"/>shall describe this remarkable cemetery in his own words.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The most remote part of the valley is covered by a thick forest. In this<lb break="yes"/>shady and solitary spot, on the declivity of a steep mountain, the cavern of<lb break="yes"/>Ataruipé opens itself. It is less a cavern than a jutting rock, in which the waters<lb break="yes"/>have scooped a vast hollow, when, in the ancient revolutions of our planet, they<lb break="yes" />attained that height. We soon reckoned in this tomb of a whole extinct tribe<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="134" facs="#f0002"/> near six hundred skeletons, well preserved, and so regularly placed, that it would<lb break="yes"/>have been difficult to make an error in their number. Every skeleton reposes<lb break="yes"/>in a sort of basket made of the petioles of the palm-tree. These baskets, which<lb break="yes"/>the natives call <hi rendition="#i">mapires</hi>, have the form of a square bag. Their sizes are<lb break="yes"/>proportioned to the age of the dead; there are some for infants cut off the moment<lb break="yes"/>of their birth. We saw them from ten inches to three feet four inches long, the<lb break="yes"/>skeletons in them being bent together. They are all ranged near each other, and<lb break="yes"/>are so entire, that not a rib, or a phalanx is wanting.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The bones have been prepared in three different manners, either whitened in<lb break="yes"/>the air and the sun; dyed red with onoto, a coloring matter extracted from the<lb break="yes"/>bixa orellana; or, like real mummies, varnished with odoriferous resins, and<lb break="yes"/>enveloped in leaves of the heliconea or the plantain tree. The Indians related<lb break="yes"/>to us, that the fresh corpse is placed in damp ground, in order that the flesh may<lb break="yes"/>be consumed by degrees; some months after, it is taken out, and the flesh remaining<lb break="yes"/>on the bones is scraped off with sharp stones. Several hordes in Guyana still<lb break="yes"/>observe this custom. Earthen vases, half baked, are found near the <hi rendition="#i">mapires</hi>, or<lb break="yes"/>baskets. They appear to contain the bones of the same family. The largest of<lb break="yes"/>these vases, or funeral urns are three feet high, and five feet and a half long.<lb break="yes"/>Their color is greenish gray, and their oval form is sufficiently pleasing to the eye.<lb break="yes"/>The handles are made in the shape of crocodiles, or serpents, the edge is bordered<lb break="yes"/>with meanders, labyrinths, and real <hi rendition="#i">grecques</hi>, in straight lines variously combined.<lb break="yes"/>Such paintings are found in every zone, among nations the most remote from<lb break="yes"/>each other either with respect to the spot which they occupy on the globe, or to<lb break="yes"/>the degree of civilisation which they have attained. The inhabitants of the little<lb break="yes"/>mission of Maypures still execute them on their commonest pottery; they decorate<lb break="yes"/>the bucklers of the Otaheiteans, the fishing implements of the Eskimoes, the<lb break="yes"/>walls of the Mexican palace of Mitla, and the vases of ancient Greece. Every<lb break="yes"/>where a rhythmic repetition of the same forms flatters the eye, as the cadenced<lb break="yes"/>repetition of sounds soothes the ear. Analogies founded on the internal nature of<lb break="yes"/>our feelings, on the natural dispositions of our intellect, are not calculated to throw<lb break="yes"/>light on the affiliation and the ancient connection of nations. We could not<lb break="yes"/>acquire any precise idea of the period to which the origin of the <hi rendition="#i">mapires</hi> and the<lb break="yes"/>painted vases, contained in the ossuary cavern of Ataruipé, can be traced. The<lb break="yes"/>greater part seemed not to be more than a century old, but it may be supposed,<lb break="yes"/>that, sheltered from all humidity, under the influence of an uniform temperature,<lb break="yes"/>the preservation of these articles would be no less perfect, if it dated from a period<lb break="yes"/>far more remote. A tradition circulates among the Guahiboes, that the warlike<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="135" facs="#f0003"/> Atures, pursued by the Caribbees, escaped to the rocks that rise in the middle of<lb break="yes"/>the Great Cataracts; and there that nation, heretofore so numerous, became<lb break="yes"/>gradually extinct, as well as its language. The last families of the Atures still<lb break="yes" />existed, in 1767, in the time of the missionary Gili. At the period of our voyage<lb break="yes"/>an old parrot was shown at Maypures, of which the inhabitants related, and the<lb break="yes"/>fact is worthy of observation, that, &#x201C;they did not understand what it said, because<lb break="yes"/>it spoke the language of the Atures.&#x201D;<note place="foot" n="*">Personal Narr. 5, p. 617.</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#k">aturian of the orinoco.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>This cranium presents the large face and ponderous jaw so common in the<lb break="yes"/>American race, together with the retreating forehead, prominent cheek bones and<lb break="yes"/>large orbits of that people. The head is more elongated than usual, and less<lb break="yes"/>flattened in the occipital region. This skull never came under my personal<lb break="yes" />inspection, for which reason I am unable to add any measurements, or other<lb break="yes"/>precise observations. The original is preserved in the Museum of the Jardin du<lb break="yes"/>Roi, in Paris: Professor Flourens kindly permitted a drawing to be made from<lb break="yes"/>it, which was taken by M. Werner, an excellent artist, under the supervision of<lb break="yes"/>my friend Dr. Edmund C. Evans, of this city.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Baron Humboldt procured several of these skulls, but the vessel in which<lb break="yes"/>several of them were shipped, was lost at sea, and I believe but two reached<lb break="yes"/>Europe. One of these is figured by Professor Blumenbach<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Decad. Cran. Tab. XLVI.</note>, and presents a much<lb break="yes"/>higher head and flatter occiput than the one represented above.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 