<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="313" facs="#f0001" />
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Description of the Muschelkalk and Quader-<lb/>sandstein. By A. <hi rendition="#k">von Humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb/>(Extracted from his Essai sur les Gisement des Roches, &#x0026;c.)</head>
                <lb/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Muschelkalk.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>A <hi rendition="#k">formation</hi> which varies but slightly, and whose vague<lb/>denomination of <hi rendition="#i">shelly limestone</hi> has caused it to be con-<lb/>founded out of Germany, with the lower or upper strata of<lb/>the oolite formation (with the lias or forest marble). It is<lb/>well characterized by its more simple structure, by the pro-<lb/>digious quantity of shells, that are partly broken, which it<lb/>contains, and by its position above the Nebra sandstone<lb/>(new red sandstone), and beneath the quadersandstein which<lb/>separates it from the oolite formation. It covers a vast por-<lb/>tion of northern Germany (Hanover, Heinberg near Gottin-<lb/>gen, Eichfeld, Cobourg, Westphalia, Pyrmont, and Biel-<lb/>feld), where it is much thicker than the zechstein or Alpine<lb/>limestone (magnesian limestone).</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>It extends in southern Germany throughout the platform<lb/>between Hanau and Stutgard. In France, where, notwith-<lb/>standing the labours of Omalius d&#x2019;Halloy, the secondary<lb/>formations beneath the chalk have been so long neglected,<lb/>
                        <pb n="314" facs="#f0002" /> Messrs. de Beaumont and Boué have recognised it round the<lb/>Vosges chain. The muschelkalk generally possesses pale,<lb/>whitish, grey or yellow tints: its fracture is compact and<lb/>dull, but the mixture of small lamin&#x00E6; of calcareous spar,<lb/>arising perhaps from fossil remains, sometimes renders it<lb/>granular and brilliant. Many beds are marly, arenaceous,<lb/>or passing into the oolite structure. (Seeberg near Gotha;<lb/>Weper near Gottingen; Preussisch-Minden; Hildesheim.<lb/>Chert (hornstein) passing into flint and jasper (Dransfeld,<lb/>Kandern, Saarbrück), are either disseminated in nodules<lb/>in the muschelkalk, or form beds of small continuity. The<lb/>inferior strata of this formation alternate with the new red<lb/>sandstone (between Bennstedt and Kelme), or insensibly<lb/>pass into the sandstone, by becoming charged with sand,<lb/>clay, and even (to the E. of Cobourg) with magnesia (mag-<lb/>nesian beds of the muschelkalk).</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>Subordinate beds. The Marls and clays so frequent in<lb/>the oolite formation, the new red sandstone, and the zech-<lb/>stein (magnesian limestone) are rare in the muschelkalk. In<lb/>Germany, this rock contains hydrate of iron, a little fibrous<lb/>gypsum (Sulzbourg near Naumbourg), and coal (letten-<lb/>kohle of Voigt; at Mattstedt and Eckardsberg near Wei-<lb/>mar) mixed with aluminous schist and carbonized fruits<lb/>(conifer&#x00E6;?). The nearer coal is found to the tertiary for-<lb/>mations, the more do at least some of its strata approach the<lb/>state of lignite and aluminous earth.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>Fossils. From the researches of M. von Schlotheim, and<lb/>rejecting the beds which do not belong to the muschelkalk,<lb/>the fossils are: Chamites striatus, Belemnites paxillosus,<lb/>Ammonites amalteus, A. nodosus, A. angulatus, A. papyra-<lb/>ceus, Nautilites binodatus, Buccinites gregarius, Trochilites<lb/>l&#x00E6;vis, Turbinites cerithius, Myacites ventricosus, Pectinites<lb/>reticulatus, Ostracites spondyloides, Terebratulites fragilis,<lb/>T. vulgaris, Gryphites cymbium, G. suillus, Mytulites socia-<lb/>lis, Pentacrinites vulgaris, Encrinites liliiformis, &#x0026;c. Some<lb/>isolated beds of the oolite formation perhaps contain more<lb/>fossils than the muschelkalk; but in no secondary forma-<lb/>tion do organic remains so uniformly abound as in that<lb/>
                        <pb n="315" facs="#f0003" /> which now occupies us. An immense quantity of shells,<lb/>partly broken, and partly well preserved, but strongly ad-<lb/>hering to the stone (entrochi, turbinites, strombites, mytul-<lb/>ites) is accumulated in many strata from 20 to 25 milli-<lb/>metres (about 1 in.) thick, which occur in the muschelkalk.<lb/>Many species occur united in families (belemnites, terebra-<lb/>tulites, chamites). Between these very shelly strata are<lb/>disseminated ammonites, turbinites, some terebratulites, with<lb/>their nacreous shells, the Gryph&#x00E6;a cymbium, and superb<lb/>pentacrinites. Corals, echinites, and pectinites are rare.<lb/>From the abundance of entrochi in the muschelkalk, this<lb/>formation has received the name of entrochite limestone<lb/>(trochitenkalk) in some parts of Germany. As a bed of<lb/>entrochi often also characterizes the zechstein, and separates<lb/>it from the coal measures, this name may lead us to confound<lb/>two very distinct formations. The denomination of gryphite<lb/>limestone (calaire à gryphites of the zechstein and of the<lb/>oolite formation) and all those which allude to fossils, with-<lb/>out indicating the species, expose us to the same danger.<lb/>It is stated that the muschelkalk contains the bones of large<lb/>animals (oviparous? quadrupeds, Friesleben, T. 1, p. 74;<lb/>T. iv, p. 24, 305) and birds (ornitholithes of the Heimberg;<lb/>Blumenbach, <hi rendition="#i">Naturgesch</hi>; 3<hi rendition="#sup">te.</hi> Aufl. p. 663); but these<lb/>bones may belong, as also the teeth of fish, to the breccias<lb/>and marls resting on the muschelkalk.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>Messrs. Buckland and Conybeare, during their tour in Ger-<lb/>many, considered the muschelkalk of Werner as identical<lb/>with the lias. I am inclined to think that there is rather a<lb/>parallelism than an identity of formation. The muschel-<lb/>kalk occupies the same place as the lias, it equally abounds<lb/>in ammonites, terebratul&#x00E6;, and encrinites; but the fossil<lb/>species differ, and its structure is much more simple and uni-<lb/>form. The muschelkalk strata are not separated by the<lb/>blue clays which abound in the lias. The middle strata of<lb/>the latter possess a dull compact and even fracture, much<lb/>more resembling the lithographic varieties of the oolite<lb/>formation than the muschelkalk of Gottingen, Jena, and<lb/>Eichsfeld. M. Boué has recongnised the muschelkalk in<lb/>
                        <pb n="316" facs="#f0004" /> France, in the platform of Burgundy, near Viteaux and<lb/>Coussy-les-Forges, near Dax, in the commune of St. Pan de<lb/>Lon, &#x0026;c. I have not observed this formation in the equi-<lb/>noxial part of America.</p>
                </div>
                <lb/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Quadersandstein (Sandstone of Königstein).</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>A very distinct formation (Banks of the Elbe, above<lb/>Dresden, between Pirna, Schandau, and Königstein; be-<lb/>tween Nuremberg and Weissenburg; Staffelstein in Fran-<lb/>conia; Heuscheune, Adersbach; Teufelsmauer at the foot<lb/>of the Hartz; valley of the Moselle and near Luxembourg;<lb/>Vic in Lorraine; Nalzen in the Pays de Foy, and Navar-<lb/>reins, at the foot of the Pyrenees) characterized by M.<lb/>Hausmann, and for a long time confounded either with the<lb/>quartzose varieties of the new red sandstone, the sandstone<lb/>of the plastic clay, or with the sandstone of Fontainebleau,<lb/>above the calcaire grossier of Paris: it is the white sandstone<lb/>of M. de Bonnard, and the third formation sandstone of<lb/>M. d&#x2019;Aubuisson. Preferring geographical names, I often<lb/>call this formation the Königstein sandstone, the new red<lb/>sandstone the Nebra sandstone, and the muschelkalk the<lb/>Gottingen limestone.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>The quadersandstein has a white, yellowish, or grey colour,<lb/>with very fine grains, which are agglutinated together by a<lb/>nearly invisible argillaceous or quartzose cement. Mica is<lb/>not abundant in it, and is always silvery and disseminated<lb/>in isolated plates. It neither contains the included oolite<lb/>beds, nor the flattened lenticular masses of clay (thongallen)<lb/>which characterise the new red sandstone. It is never<lb/>schistose; but is divided into very thick beds, which are cut<lb/>at a right angle by fissures, and of which some easily decom-<lb/>pose into a very fine sand. It contains hydrate of iron (Metz)<lb/>disposed in nodules. The organic remains disseminated in<lb/>this formation present, according to Messrs. von Schlotheim,<lb/>Haussmann, and Raumer, an extraordinary mixture of sea<lb/>shells (very analogous to those of the muschelkalk) and<lb/>
                        <pb n="318" facs="#f0005" /> dicotyledonous phytolithes. In it have been found mytu-<lb/>lites, tellinites, pectinites, turritell&#x00E6;, and ostre&#x00E6;, (with<lb/>cerithia, but no ammonites; Habelschwerd, Alt-Lomnitz in<lb/>Silesia), and at the same time the wood of palms, the im-<lb/>pressions of leaves belonging to the class of the dicotyledons,<lb/>and small deposites of coal (Deister, and Wefersleben near<lb/>Quedlinbourg), very well described by Messrs. Rettberg<lb/>and Schulze, and passing into lignite.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>M. von Raumer had observed that the quadersandstein is<lb/>separated from the new red sandstone by the muschelkalk;<lb/>it is placed between this limestone and the Jura limestone,<lb/>and consequently beneath the oolite formations of England<lb/>and the continent. In this position we cannot consider it,<lb/>with M. Keferstein (see his Essay on the mineral geography<lb/>of Germany, T. 1. p. 12. and 48.), as parallel to the molasse<lb/>of Argovy (mergelsandstein), which represents the plastic<lb/>clay beneath the chalk. The nature of the vegetable remains<lb/>contained in the quadersandstein, and its resemblance to the<lb/>plänerkalk which belongs to the chloritous and sandy strata<lb/>of the chalk, have caused it to be regarded by many cele-<lb/>brated geologists as a formation posterior to the oolite for-<lb/>mation: thus Messrs. Buckland, Conybeare, and Phillips<lb/>place it between the chalk and the upper beds of the oolites.<lb/>But, according to the observations of M. Boué and many<lb/>other celebrated German geologists, the quadersandstein,<lb/>sometimes alternating with marly and conglomerate beds,<lb/>rests immediately on gneiss near Freyberg, on the coal mea-<lb/>sures in Silesia, and in Bohemia; on the new red sandstone<lb/>near Nuremberg in Franconia; on the muschelalk between<lb/>Hildesheim and Dickholzen near Helmstädt, and near<lb/>Schweinfurt on the Mein. It is covered by the oolite for-<lb/>mation, and alternates with marly beds of this limestone in<lb/>Westphalia, between Osnabrück, Bielfeld, and Bückebourg.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>