<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On Rock Formations</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:58</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.26</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1822-Independance_des_formations-2</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1822-Independance_des_formations-1.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1822-Independance_des_formations-2.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1822-Independance_des_formations-3.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1822-Independance_des_formations-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1822-Independance_des_formations-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On Rock Formations</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1824</date>
          <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Edinburgh Philosophical Journal&lt;/i&gt; 10:19 (Januar 1824), S. 40–53, 10:20 (April 1824), S. 224–239.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung, Kapitälchen; Fußnoten mit Asterisken; Schmuck: Initialen; Besonderes: mathematische Sonderzeichen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="40" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">On Rock Formations.</hi> By Baron <hi rendition="#k">Alexander<lb/>Humboldt</hi> <note place="foot" n="*">Translated from <hi rendition="#i">Essai Geognostique</hi> par Alexandre de Humboldt.</note>.</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#in">T</hi>HE word <hi rendition="#i">formation</hi> designates, in Geognosy, either the man-<lb/>ner in which a rock has been produced, or an assemblage of<lb/>mineral masses, which are so connected together, that they are<lb/>supposed to have been formed at the same period, and present,<lb/>in the most distant parts of the world, the same general rela-<lb/>tions of situation and position. It is thus that the <hi rendition="#i">formation</hi><lb/>of obsidian and basalt is attributed to subterranean fires; and<lb/>thus also that we say the formation of transition clay-slate con-<lb/>tains lydian-stone, chiastolite, alum-slate, and alternating beds of<lb/>black limestone and porphyry. The first acceptation of the<lb/>word is better adapted to the genius of the language; but it<lb/>has relation to the origin of things, to an uncertain science found-<lb/>ed upon geogonic hypothesis. The second acceptation, now<lb/><pb n="41" facs="#f0002" />
    generally adopted by the French mineralogists, has been bor-<lb/>rowed from the celebrated school of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Werner</persName>: it indicates what<lb/>is, not what is supposed to have been.</p><lb/><p>In the geognostical description of the globe, we may distin-<lb/>guish different degrees of aggregation of mineral substances,<lb/>simple or compound, according as we rise to more general ideas.<lb/>Rocks which alternate with one another, which are usually asso-<lb/>ciated, and which present the same relations of position, consti-<lb/>tute a <hi rendition="#i">formation;</hi> the union of several formations constitutes a<lb/>district or <hi rendition="#i">terrain;</hi> but these different terms of rocks, Forma-<lb/>tion and Terrain, are employed as synonymous in many works<lb/>of geognosy.</p><lb/><p>The diversity of the rocks, and the relative disposition of the<lb/>beds which form the oxidised crust of the earth, have, from the<lb/>most remote times, fixed the attention of men. Wherever the<lb/>working of a mine was directed upon a deposit of salt, of coal,<lb/>or of clay-iron, which was covered with a great number of beds<lb/>of different natures, it gave rise to ideas more or less precise re-<lb/>garding the system of rocks peculiar to a district of small ex-<lb/>tent. Furnished with these local details, and full of prejudices<lb/>which arise from custom, the miners of a country would disperse<lb/>themselves over the neighbouring districts. They would do<lb/>what geognosts have often done in our days; they would judge<lb/>of the position of rocks of whose nature they were ignorant, ac-<lb/>cording to imperfect analogies, according to the circumscribed<lb/>ideas which they had acquired in their native country. This<lb/>error must have had a fatal influence upon the success of<lb/>their new researches. In place of examining the connection<lb/>of two contiguous districts, by following some generally ex-<lb/>tended bed,&#x2014;in place of enlarging and extending, so to speak,<lb/>the first <hi rendition="#i">type of formations</hi> which had remained impressed<lb/>upon their minds,&#x2014;they would be persuaded that each por-<lb/>tion of the globe had an entirely different geological constitu-<lb/>tion. This very old popular opinion has been adopted and sup-<lb/>ported, in different countries, by very distinguished men; but<lb/>since geognosy has been elevated to the rank of a science, the<lb/>art of interrogating nature brought to perfection, and journeys<lb/>made into distant countries, have presented a more exact com-<lb/>parison of different districts, great and immutable laws have<lb/>been discovered in the structure of the globe, and in the super-<lb/><pb n="42" facs="#f0003" />
position of rocks. Since, then, the most striking analogies of situa-<lb/>tion, of composition, and of organic bodies contained in contem-<lb/>poraneous beds, have manifested themselves in the two worlds, in<lb/>proportion as we become accustomed to consider the formations<lb/>under a more general point of view, even their <hi rendition="#i">identity</hi> becomes<lb/>every day more probable.</p><lb/><p>In fact, on examining the solid mass of our planet, we per-<lb/>ceive that some of those substances with which oryctognosy (de-<lb/>scriptive mineralogy), makes us acquainted in their individual<lb/>capacities, are met with in <hi rendition="#i">constant associations</hi>, and that these<lb/>associations, which are designated by the name of Compound<lb/>Rocks, do not vary, like organic beings, according to the diffe-<lb/>rences of the latitudes, or of the isothermal lines in which they<lb/>occur. The geognosts who have travelled over the most re-<lb/>mote countries, have not only met in the two hemispheres with<lb/>the same simple substances, quartz, felspar, mica, garnet or horn-<lb/>blende; but they have also found that the great mountain mas-<lb/>ses present almost everywhere the same rocks, that is to say, the<lb/>same assemblages of mica, quartz and felspar in the granite; of<lb/>mica, quartz, and garnets in the mica-slate; of felspar and horn-<lb/>blende in the syenite. If it has sometimes been thought at first<lb/>that a rock belonged exclusively to a single portion of the globe,<lb/>it has been constantly found by later researches, in regions the<lb/>most remote from its first locality. We are tempted to admit<lb/>that the formation of rocks has been independent of the diver-<lb/>sity of climates; that perhaps it has even been anterior to them,<lb/>(<bibl>Humboldt, <hi rendition="#i">Geographie des Plantes</hi>, 1807, p. 115.</bibl>; <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Vues des<lb/>Cordilleres</hi>, vol. i. p. 122</bibl>). Rocks are found to be identical<lb/>where organic beings have undergone the most varied modifica-<lb/>tions.</p><lb/><p>But this identity of composition, this analogy which is obser-<lb/>ved in the association of certain simple mineral substances, might<lb/>be independent of the analogy of relative situation and of super-<lb/>position. One may have brought from the <placeName>Islands of the<lb/>Pacific Ocean</placeName>, or from the <placeName>Cordilleras of the Andes</placeName>, the same<lb/>rocks which are observed in <placeName>Europe</placeName>, without his being permit-<lb/>ted to conclude that these rocks are superimposed in the same<lb/>manner, and that after the discovery of one of them it might be<lb/>predicted with some degree of certainty what are the other rocks<lb/><pb n="43" facs="#f0004" />
    which occur in the same places. It is to discover these analo-<lb/>gics of situation and relative position, that the labours of geo-<lb/>gnosts should tend, who delight to investigate the laws of inor-<lb/>ganic nature. In the following tables, we have attempted to<lb/>unite all that is known with certainty, regarding the superposi-<lb/>tion of rocks in the two Continents, to the north and south of<lb/>the <placeName>Equator</placeName>. These <hi rendition="#i">types of <choice><sic>formatians</sic><corr type="editorial">formations</corr></choice></hi> will not only be extend-<lb/>ed, but also variously modified, in proportion as the number of<lb/>travellers qualified to make geognostical observations shall be-<lb/>come increased, and as complete monographs of different dis-<lb/>tricts at great distances from each other shall furnish more pre-<lb/>cise results.</p><lb/><p>The exposition of the laws observed in the superposition of<lb/>rocks, forms the most solid part of the science of geognosy. It<lb/>must not be denied, that the observations of geognostical situa-<lb/>tion often present great difficulties, when the point of contact of<lb/>two neighbouring formations cannot be reached, or when they<lb/>do not present a regular stratification, or when their relative situa-<lb/>tion is not <hi rendition="#i">uniform</hi>, that is to say, when the strata of the upper<lb/>deposits are not parallel to the strata of the lower. But these<lb/>difficulties (and this is one of the great advantages of observa-<lb/>tions which embrace a considerable part of our planet), diminish<lb/>in number, or disappear entirely, on comparing several districts<lb/>of great extent. The superposition and relative age of rocks,<lb/>are facts susceptible of being established immediately, like the<lb/>structure of the organs of a vegetable, like the proportions of<lb/>elements in chemical analysis, or like the elevation of a moun-<lb/>tain above the level of the sea. True geognosy makes known<lb/>the outer crust of the globe, such as it exists at the present<lb/>day. It is a science as capable of certainty as any of the physi-<lb/>cal descriptive sciences can be. On the other hand, all that re-<lb/>lates to the ancient state of our planets, to those fluids which, it<lb/>is said, held all the mineral substances in a state of revolution,<lb/>to those seas which we have raised to the summit of the <placeName>Cordil-<lb/>leras</placeName>, to make them again disappear, is as uncertain as are the<lb/>formation of the atmosphere of planets, the migrations of vege-<lb/>tables, and the origin of different varieties of our species. Yet<lb/>the period is not very remote when geologists occupied them-<lb/>selves by preference with the solution of these almost impossi-<lb/><pb n="44" facs="#f0005" />
        ble problems, with those fabulous times of the physical history<lb/>of our planet.</p><lb/><p>In order to render the principles better understood, accord-<lb/>ing to which the following <hi rendition="#i">table of the superposition of rocks</hi> is<lb/>constructed, it becomes necessary to premise observations fur-<lb/>nished by the practical examination of different districts. We<lb/>shall begin with remarking, that it is not easy to circum-<lb/>scribe the limits of a formation. The Jura limestone and the<lb/>Alpine limestone, which are separated to a great distance in one<lb/>country, sometimes appear closely connected in another. What<lb/>announces the independence of a formation, as has been very<lb/>justly observed by M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Buch</persName>, is its immediate superposition<lb/>upon rocks of a different nature, and which consequently ought<lb/>to be considered as more ancient. The red sandstone is an in-<lb/>dependent formation, because it is superimposed indifferently<lb/>upon black (transition) limestone, upon mica-slate, or upon<lb/>primitive granites; but in a country where the great formation<lb/>of syenite and porphyry predominates, these two rocks constant-<lb/>ly alternate. There results that the syenite rock is dependent<lb/>upon the porphyry, and scarcely any where covers by itself the<lb/>transition clay-slate or primitive gneiss. The independence of<lb/>formations does not, besides, by any means exclude the <hi rendition="#i">uniformi-<lb/>ty</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">concordance of position;</hi> it rather excludes the oryctognos-<lb/>tic passage of two superimposed formations. The transition dis-<lb/>tricts have very often the same direction and the same inclina-<lb/>tion as the primitive ones; and yet, whatever approximation<lb/>there may be between their origin, we are not the less warrant-<lb/>ed to consider the anthracitic mica-slate or the grey-wacke, al-<lb/>ternating with porphyry, as two formations independent of the<lb/>primitive granites and gneisses which they cover. The confor-<lb/>mity of position is in no way incompatible with the indepen-<lb/>dence of formations, that is to say, it does not prevent the right<lb/>which one has of regarding a rock as a distinct formation. It<lb/>is because the independent formations are placed indifferently<lb/>on all the older rocks, (the chalk upon the granite, the red sand-<lb/>stone upon the primitive mica-slate), that the assemblage of a<lb/>great number of observations made upon very distant points,<lb/>becomes eminently useful in the determination of the <hi rendition="#i">relative<lb/>age</hi> of rocks. In order to determine that the zircon-sienite is<lb/><pb n="45" facs="#f0006" />
            a transition rock, it must have been seen resting upon formations<lb/>posterior to the black limestone with orthoceratites. Observations<lb/>made upon the porphyries and syenites of <placeName>Hungary</placeName> by M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Beu-<lb/>dant</persName>, one of the most distinguished geologists of the present<lb/>times, may throw much light upon the formations of the <placeName>Mexi-<lb/>can Andes</placeName>. It is thus that a new vegetable discovered in In-<lb/>dia, elucidated the natural affinity between two families of plants<lb/>belonging to <placeName>Equinoctial America</placeName>.</p><lb/><p>The order which has been followed in the table of formations,<lb/>is that of the situation and relative position of rocks. I do not<lb/>pretend that this position is observed in all the countries of the<lb/>globe; I merely point it out such as it has appeared the most<lb/>probable, after the comparison of a great number of facts which<lb/>I have collected. It is by the idea of the relative age of for-<lb/>mation, that I have been guided in this work, imperfect as it<lb/>still is. I had begun it long before my journey to the <placeName>Cordille-<lb/>ras of the New Continent</placeName>, from the year 1792, when, on leav-<lb/>ing the Freyberg School, I was appointed to the direction of<lb/>the Mines in the mountains of the <placeName>Fichtelgebirge</placeName>. The same<lb/>rock may vary in composition, integrant parts may have been<lb/>abstracted, and new substances may occur disseminated, without<lb/>the rock&#x2019;s changing its denomination in the eyes of the geognost<lb/>who is engaged with the superposition of formations. Un-<lb/>der the equator, as in the <placeName>north of Europe</placeName>, strata of a true tran-<lb/>sition syenite lose their hornblende, without the mass becom-<lb/>ing another rock. The granites of the banks of the <placeName>Ori-<lb/>noco</placeName> sometimes assume hornblende as an integrant part, and<lb/>yet do not cease to be primitive granite, although this may not<lb/>be of the first or oldest formation. These facts have been ob-<lb/>served by all practical geologists. The essential character of<lb/>the identity of an independent formation is its relative position,<lb/>the place which it occupies in the general series of formations.<lb/>(See the classical Memoir of M. <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Buch</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Ueber den Begriff<lb/>einer,</hi> in the <hi rendition="#i">Mag. der Naturf.,</hi> 1810, p. 128&#x2013;133</bibl>.) It is on<lb/>this account that an isolated fragment, a specimen of rock found<lb/>in a collection, cannot be determined geognostically, that is to<lb/>say, it cannot be referred with certainty to a particular forma-<lb/>tion, constituting one of the numerous beds of which the crust<lb/>of our planet is composed. The presence of chiastolite, the ac-<lb/><pb n="46" facs="#f0007" />
                cumulation of carbon or nodules of compact limestone in the<lb/>clay-slates, nigrine and epidote in the syenites, (alternating with<lb/>granite and porphyries), conglomerates or pudding-stones, ha-<lb/>ving a basis of anthracitic mica-slate, may, without doubt, be<lb/>characteristic of transition formations; in the same way as, ac-<lb/>cording to the useful labours of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>, petrifactions of<lb/>shells, in a good state of preservation, sometimes indicate direct-<lb/>ly such or such a bed of tertiary deposits. But these cases,<lb/>where we are guided by disseminated substances or by charac-<lb/>ters purely geological, comprehend but a small number of<lb/>rocks of a recent origin, and observations of this kind often lead<lb/>only to negative facts. The characters taken from the colour,<lb/>from the grain, and from small veins of carbonate of lime,<lb/>which traverse calcareous rocks; those which are furnished by<lb/>the fissility and silky lustre of clay-slate, the aspect and undu-<lb/>lations more or less marked of the scales of mica in mica-slate;<lb/>and, lastly, the size and colouring of the crystals of felspar in<lb/>the granites of different formations, may, like all that is con-<lb/>nected simply with the <hi rendition="#i">physiognomy</hi> of minerals, lead the most<lb/>expert observer into error. The white and black tints un-<lb/>doubtedly in most instances distinguish the primitive and tran-<lb/>sition limestones; the <placeName>Jura</placeName> formation, especially in its upper<lb/>beds, is also without doubt generally divided into thin whitish<lb/>beds, having a dull, even, or conchoidal fracture, with very<lb/>flat cavities: but in the mountains of transition limestone there<lb/>are isolated masses which, in colour and texture, resemble the<lb/>oryctognostic characters of the <placeName>Jura</placeName> limestone; and to the south<lb/>of the <placeName>Alps</placeName> there are hills belonging to tertiary deposits, where<lb/>we find rocks analogous to the slaty and dull <placeName>Jura</placeName> limestone<lb/>(in as far as regards appearance,) in formations placed above the<lb/>chalk, and which resemble the limestone used for lithographic<lb/>purposes. Were names taken from their oryctognostical cha-<lb/>racters alone to be preferred in distinguishing formations, the<lb/>different strata of the same compound rock having a consider-<lb/>able thickness, and extended to a great length in a particular<lb/>direction, would often seem to belong to different rocks, accord-<lb/>ing to the points at which specimens were taken. Consequent-<lb/>ly we can only determine geognostically in collections, <hi rendition="#i">suites of<lb/>rocks</hi> of which the mutual superposition is known.</p><lb/><pb n="47" facs="#f0008" />
    <p>In announcing these ideas regarding the sense which should<lb/>be attached to the words <hi rendition="#i">independent formations</hi>, when treating<lb/>of the order of their position, we are very far from undervaluing<lb/>the eminent services which the most rigorous oryctognostic exa-<lb/>mination, the minute investigation of the composition of rocks,<lb/>have rendered to modern geognosy, and especially to the know-<lb/>ledge of the relative position of formations. Although, accord-<lb/>ing to the discoveries of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Haüy</persName>, regarding the intimate<lb/>nature of inorganic and crystallized substances, there does not<lb/>exist, properly speaking, a passage or transition of one mineral<lb/>species to another; (<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Cordier</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">sur les Roches volcan.,</hi> p. 33</bibl>., and<lb/><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Berzelius</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Nouv. Syst. de Mineral,</hi> p. 119</bibl>.), the passages of<lb/><hi rendition="#i">masses or pastes of rocks,</hi> are not limited to formations which<lb/>are commonly distinguished by the name of Compound Rocks.<lb/>Those which are thought simple, for example, the transition or<lb/>secondary limestones, are partly amorphous varieties of mineral<lb/>species, of which there exists a crystallized type, partly of aggre-<lb/>gates of clay, carbon, &amp;c., which cannot be submitted to any<lb/>fixed determination. It is upon the variable proportions of<lb/>these heterogeneous mixtures, that the passage of marly lime-<lb/>stones to other schistose formations is founded. (<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Haüy</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Tableau<lb/>comparatif de la Cristallographie,</hi> p. 27.&#x2014;30</bibl>.) All the amor-<lb/>phous pastes of rocks, however homogeneous they appear at first<lb/>sight, the bases of porphyries and euphotides (serpentines), as<lb/>well as those problematical black masses which constitute the <hi rendition="#i">ba-<lb/>sanite</hi> (basalt) of the ancients, and which are not all greenstones<lb/>surcharged with hornblende, are susceptible of being subjected to<lb/>mechanical analysis. M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Cordier</persName> has applied this analysis in an<lb/>ingenious manner to the diabases, dolerites, and other more re-<lb/>cent volcanic productions. The most apparently minute orycto-<lb/>gnostic examination, cannot be indifferent to the geognost who ex-<lb/>amines the age of formations. It is by this examination that we<lb/>are enabled to form a just idea of the progressive manner in which,<lb/>by <hi rendition="#i">internal development,</hi> that is to say, by a very gradual change<lb/>in the proportions of the elements of the <hi rendition="#i">mass</hi>, the passage is<lb/>made from one rock to a neighbouring. The transition slates,<lb/>whose structure appears at first so different from that of the gra-<lb/>nites or porphyries, present to the attentive observer striking ex-<lb/>amples of insensible passages to granular rocks of porphyritic<lb/><pb n="48" facs="#f0009" />
        or granitic nature. These slates become at first greenish and<lb/>harder. In proportion as the amorphous paste receives horn-<lb/>blende, it passes into those hornblendic traps which in former<lb/>times were confounded with basalt. In other cases, the mica,<lb/>which is at first concealed in the amorphous paste, becomes de-<lb/>veloped, and separates into distinct and clearly crystallized<lb/>spangles; at the same time, the felspar and quartz become visi-<lb/>ble; and the mass assumes a granular aspect, with very elon-<lb/>gated grains: this is a true transition gneiss. By degrees, the<lb/>grains lose their common direction; the crystals arrange them-<lb/>selves around many centres; the rock becomes a transition gra-<lb/>nite or syenite. In other cases, the quartz alone is developed;<lb/>it augments, and becomes rounded into nodules, and the slate<lb/>passes to the best characterized grey-wackes. By these certain<lb/>signs, geognosts, to whom the appearances of nature have become<lb/>familiar by long examination, become aware beforehand of the<lb/>proximity of granular, granitic and arenaceous rocks. Analo-<lb/>gous passages of primitive mica-slate to a porphyritic rock, and<lb/>the return of this rock to gneiss, are observed in the eastern parts<lb/>of <placeName>Switzerland</placeName>. (See the luminous developments given by M.<lb/><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Raumer</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Fragmente,</hi> p. 10. and 47</bibl>.; M. <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Leopold de Buch</persName>,<lb/>in his <hi rendition="#i">Voyage de Glaris à Chiavenna, fait en</hi> 1803</bibl>, and inserted<lb/>in the <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Magaz. der Berl. Naturf.,</hi> vol. iii. p. 115</bibl>). But these pass-<lb/>ages are not always insensible and progressive; the rocks often<lb/>also succeed each other quickly, and in a very abrupt manner;<lb/>often (for example, at <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, between <placeName>Guanaxuato</placeName> and <placeName>Ovex-<lb/>eras</placeName>), the limits between the slates, the porphyries and syenites,<lb/>are as distinct as the limits between the porphyries and lime-<lb/>stones; but even in this case, geognostical relations with the su-<lb/>perimposed rocks are indicated by additional heterogeneous<lb/>beds. It is thus that the transition granite of the syenitic for-<lb/>mation presents beds of basanite, by becoming charged with<lb/>hornblende: it is thus, also, that these same granites sometimes<lb/>pass to euphotide. (<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Buch</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Voyages en Norwege,</hi> vol. i. p. 138.,<lb/>vol. ii. p. 83</bibl>.)</p><lb/><p>There results from these considerations, that the mechanical<lb/>analysis of amorphous pastes, by means of demi-triturations and<lb/>washings, (an analysis of which, M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Fleuriau de Bellevue</persName> made<lb/>the first attempt, that was crowned with success; <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Journ. de</hi><lb/><pb n="49" facs="#f0010" />
            <hi rendition="#i">Physique,</hi> vol. li. p. 162</bibl>.), throws light at once, 1<hi rendition="#i">st,</hi> Upon the<lb/>large crystals which are isolated and separated from the micro-<lb/>scopic crystals entangled in the <hi rendition="#i">mass;</hi> 2<hi rendition="#i">dly,</hi> On the mutual pass-<lb/>ages of some rocks, superimposed the one upon the other; 3<hi rendition="#i">dly,</hi><lb/>On the subordinate beds, which are of the same nature as one of<lb/>the elements of the amorphous mass. All these phenomena are<lb/>produced, if we may so speak, by internal development; by<lb/>variation in the constituent parts of a heterogeneous mass.<lb/>Crystalline molecules, invisible to the eye, occur enlarged and<lb/>disengaged from the compact tissue of the paste; by their as-<lb/>semblage and mixture with new substances, they insensibly be-<lb/>come intercalated beds of considerable thickness; and not un-<lb/>frequently they even become new rocks.</p><lb/><p>It is the intercalated beds which especially merit the greatest<lb/>attention. (<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Leonhard</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Kopp</persName> and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">G&#x00E6;rtner</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Prop&#x00E6;d. der Miner.,</hi><lb/>p. 158</bibl>.) When two formations succeed each other imme-<lb/>diately, it happens that the beds of the one begin at first to alter-<lb/>nate with the beds of the other, until (after these precursors of<lb/>a great change) the newest formation shows itself without any<lb/>mixture of subordinate beds. (<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Buch</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Geogn. Beob.</hi> vol. i.<lb/>p. 104. 156</bibl>.; <bibl>Humboldt, <hi rendition="#i">Rel. Hist.</hi> vol. ii. p. 140</bibl>.) The pro-<lb/>gressive developments of the elements of a rock, may, conse-<lb/>quently, have a great degree of influence upon the relative posi-<lb/>tion of the mineral masses. Their effects belong to the province<lb/>of geology; but, in order to discover and appreciate them, the<lb/>observer must call to his assistance oryctognosy.</p><lb/><p>In exposing the intimate relations by which we often see the<lb/>phenomena of <hi rendition="#i">composition</hi> connected with those of relative <hi rendition="#i">situa-<lb/>tion</hi>, it has not been my intention to speak of the purely oryc-<lb/>tognostic method, which considers rocks according to the ana-<lb/>logy of their composition alone. (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Journal des Mines,</hi> vol. xxxiv.<lb/>No. 199.</bibl>) In the classifications of this method, abstraction is<lb/>made of every idea of superposition; but they do not the less<lb/>give rise to interesting observations regarding the constant assem-<lb/>blage of certain minerals. A purely oryctognostic classification,<lb/>multiplies the names of rocks more than is required by geognosy,<lb/>when occupied with superposition alone. According to the<lb/>changes which the mixed rocks undergo, a stratum of great ex-<lb/>tent and thickness may contain (we must repeat it here) parts<lb/><pb n="50" facs="#f0011" />
                to which the oryctognost, who classes rocks according to their<lb/>composition, would give entirely different denominations. These<lb/>remarks have not escaped the learned author of the <hi rendition="#i"><bibl>Classifica-<lb/>tion Mineralogique des Roches</bibl></hi>; they must have presented them-<lb/>selves to an experienced geognost, who has so successfully in-<lb/>vestigated the superposition of the deposites of which he has<lb/>treated. &#x201C;We must not confound,&#x201D; says M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>, in his<lb/>late <bibl>Memoir on the position of the Ophiolites</bibl>, &#x201C;the relative po-<lb/>sitions, the orders of superposition of the deposites and of the<lb/>rocks which compose them, with purely mineralogical descrip-<lb/>tions. The neglect of making the proper distinction in this<lb/>case, would necessarily be productive of confusion in the science,<lb/>and would retard its progress.&#x201D; The arrangement which we<lb/>give at the end of this article, is by no means what is called a<lb/>classification of rocks; there will not even be found united, un-<lb/>der the title of particular sections (as in the old geognostical<lb/>method of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Werner</persName>, or in the excellent <hi rendition="#i"><bibl>Traité de Geognosie</bibl></hi> of<lb/>M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">D&#x2019;Aubuisson</persName>), all the primitive formations of granite, nor<lb/>all the secondary formations of sandstone and limestone. It<lb/>has been attempted, on the contrary, to place each rock as it oc-<lb/>curs in nature, according to the order of its superposition or of<lb/>its respective age. The different formations of granite are se-<lb/>parted by gneisses, mica-slates, black-limestones and grey-<lb/>wackes. In the transition rocks, we have separated the forma-<lb/>tions of porphyries and syenites of <placeName>Mexico</placeName> and <placeName>Peru</placeName>, which are<lb/>anterior to the grey-wacke, and to the limestone with orthocera-<lb/>tites, from the much more recent formation of the zircon-porphy-<lb/>ries and syenites of <placeName>Scandinavia</placeName>. In the secondary rocks, we have<lb/>separated the oolitic sandstone of <placeName>Nebra</placeName>, which is posterior to<lb/>the alpine limestone or zechstein, from the red-sandstone, which<lb/>belongs to the same formation with the secondary porphyry and<lb/>amygdaloid. According to the principle which we follow, the<lb/>same names of rocks occur several times in the same table. An-<lb/>thracitic mica-slate is separated, by a great number of older<lb/>formations, from the mica-slate anterior to the primitive clay-<lb/>slate.</p><lb/><p>Instead of a classification of granitic, schistose, calcareous and<lb/>arenaceous rocks, it has been my object to present a sketch of<lb/>the geognostical structure of the globe; a table in which the<lb/><pb n="51" facs="#f0012" />
                    superimposed rocks succeed each other, from below upwards, as<lb/>in those <hi rendition="#i">ideal sections</hi> which I designed in 1804, for the benefit<lb/>of the <hi rendition="#i">Mexican School of Mines</hi>, and of which many copies<lb/>have been distributed since my return to <placeName>Europe</placeName>. <hi rendition="#i">(<bibl>Bosquejo<lb/>de una Pasigrafia geognostica, con tablas que ensenan la es-<lb/>tratificacion y el <choice><sic>paiallelismo</sic><corr type="editorial">parallelismo</corr></choice> de las rocas en ambos Continentes,<lb/>para el uso del Real Seminario de Mineria de Mexico</bibl>.)</hi> These<lb/>Pasigraphic tables united to my own observations made in <placeName>both<lb/>Americas</placeName> what had at that period been known with precision re-<lb/>garding the relative position of the primitive, intermediary and<lb/>secondary rocks in the <placeName>Old Continent</placeName>. They presented, together<lb/>with the type which might be considered as the most general,<lb/>the secondary types, that is to say, the beds which I have named<lb/><hi rendition="#i">parallel</hi>. This same method has been followed in the work<lb/>which I now publish. My parallel formations are geognostical<lb/><hi rendition="#i">equivalents;</hi> they are rocks which represent each other. (See the<lb/><bibl><hi rendition="#i">Traité de Geologie de M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">d&#x2019;Aubuisson</persName>,</hi> vol. ii. p. 255</bibl>.) In <placeName>Eng-<lb/>land</placeName>, and on the opposite Continent, there does not exist an iden-<lb/>tity of all the formations: there exist equivalents or parallel for-<lb/>mations. That of our coal situated between the transition masses<lb/>and the red-sandstone, the position of the rock-salt which occurs<lb/>on the Continent in the alpine limestone, and the position of our<lb/>oolites in the Nebra sandstone and Jura limestone, may guide<lb/>the geognost in the approximation of remote formations. In<lb/><placeName>England</placeName>, we observe the coals placed upon transition formations;<lb/>for example, upon the mountain-limestone of <placeName>Derbyshire</placeName> and of<lb/><placeName>South Wales</placeName>, and upon the transition sandstone, or old red-<lb/>sandstone of <placeName>Herefordshire</placeName>. I have thought that I recognised<lb/>in the magnesian-limestone the red marl, the lias and white<lb/>oolites of Bath, the <hi rendition="#i">united formations</hi> of the alpine limestone,<lb/>of the oolitic sandstone and Jura limestone. In comparing the<lb/>formations of countries more or less distant from each other,<lb/>those of <placeName>England</placeName> and of <placeName>France</placeName>, for instance, of <placeName>Mexico</placeName> and<lb/><placeName>Hungary</placeName>, of the secondary basin of <placeName>Santa Fe de Bogota</placeName> and of<lb/><placeName>Thuringia</placeName>, we must not think of opposing to each individual<lb/>rock a <hi rendition="#i">parallel</hi> one; it must be recollected, that a single forma-<lb/>tion may <hi rendition="#i">represent</hi> several others. It is according to this princi-<lb/>ple that beds of clay, lying beneath the chalk, may, in <placeName>France</placeName>,<lb/><pb n="52" facs="#f0013" />
                    be separated in the most distinct manner from the oolitic lime-<lb/>stone beds; while in <placeName>Switzerland</placeName>, in <placeName>Germany</placeName>, and in <placeName>South<lb/>America</placeName>, they have for <hi rendition="#i">equivalents</hi> beds of marls subordinate to<lb/>the Jura limestone. The gypsums, which, in one district, are<lb/>sometimes only intercalated beds in the alpine limestone or ooli-<lb/>tic sandstone, in another district, assume all the appearance of<lb/>independent formations, and occur interposed between the alpine<lb/>limestone and the oolitic sandstone, between this sandstone and<lb/>the muschelkalk. The learned <placeName>Oxford</placeName> Professor, Mr <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Buckland</persName>,<lb/>whose extensive researches have been equally useful to the geo-<lb/>gnosts of <placeName>England</placeName> and of the <placeName>Continent</placeName>, has lately published a<lb/>table of parallel formations, or, as he calls them, <hi rendition="#i">equivalents of<lb/>rocks</hi>, which only extends from the 44th to the 54th degree of<lb/>north latitude, but which merits the greatest attention. (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">On the<lb/>Structure of the Alps, and their relation with the rocks of Eng-<lb/>land,</hi> 1821</bibl>.)</p><lb/><p>As in the history of ancient nations, it is easier to verify the<lb/>series of events in each country, than to determine their mutual<lb/>coincidence; so also more accuracy can be attained in estima-<lb/>ting the superposition of formations in isolated regions, than in<lb/>determining the relative age or parallelism of formations which<lb/>belong to different systems of rocks. Even in countries which<lb/>are not widely separated, in <placeName>France</placeName>, in <placeName>Switzerland</placeName>, and in <placeName>Ger-<lb/>many</placeName>, it is not easy to fix the relative antiquity of the muschel-<lb/>kalk, of the molasse of <placeName>Argovie</placeName>, and of the quadersandstein of<lb/>the <placeName>Hartz</placeName>; because rocks of general occurrence are here most<lb/>commonly wanting, which, according to the happy expression of<lb/>of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Grüner</persName>, serve as a <hi rendition="#i">geognostical horizon,</hi> and with<lb/>which we might compare the three formations in question.<lb/>When rocks are not in immediate contact, we can only judge of<lb/>their parallelism by the relations of age existing between them<lb/>and other formations by which they are united.</p><lb/><p>These inquiries of <hi rendition="#i">comparative geognosy</hi>, will long occu-<lb/>py the sagacity of observers; and it is not surprising that those<lb/>who set out with the idea of retracing each formation in all the<lb/>individuality of its relative position, interior structure and subor-<lb/>dinate beds, should finish with utterly denying all analogy of<lb/>superposition. I had the advantage of visiting, previous to my<lb/>journey to the <placeName>Equator</placeName>, a great part of <placeName>Germany</placeName>, of <placeName>France</placeName>, of<lb/><pb n="53" facs="#f0014" />
                        <placeName>Switzerland</placeName>, of <placeName>England</placeName>, of <placeName>Italy</placeName>, of <placeName>Poland</placeName>, and of <placeName>Spain</placeName>. Du-<lb/>ring these excursions, my attention was particularly directed to<lb/>the relative position of formations, a phenomenon which I cal-<lb/>culated upon discussing in a special work. On my arrival in<lb/><placeName>South America</placeName>, and while at first traversing in different direc-<lb/>tions the vast deposites which stretch from the maritime chain of<lb/>Venezuela to the basin of the <placeName>Amazon</placeName>, I was singularly struck<lb/>with the conformity of position which the two Continents present.<lb/>(See <bibl>my first sketch of a Geological Table of Equinoctial Ameri-<lb/>ca, in the <hi rendition="#i">Journal de Phys.</hi>, vol. liii. p. 38</bibl>.) Subsequent obser-<lb/>vations, which included the <placeName>Cordilleras of Mexico</placeName>, of <placeName>New Grena-<lb/>da</placeName>, of <placeName>Quito</placeName>, and of <placeName>Peru</placeName>, from the 21st degree of north latitude<lb/>to the 12th degree of south latitude, have confirmed these first<lb/>perceptions. But in speaking of analogies which are observed<lb/>in the relative position of rocks, and of the uniformity of those<lb/>laws which reveal to us the order of Nature, I might adduce a tes-<lb/>timony otherwise of more weight than mine, that of the great<lb/>geognost whose works have thrown the greatest light upon the<lb/>structure of our globe. M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Leopold de Buch</persName> has pushed his<lb/>researches from the <placeName>Archipelago of the Canary Isles</placeName> to beyond<lb/>the Polar Circle to the 71st degree of latitude. He has discovered<lb/>new formations situated between others already known; and, in<lb/>the primitive as in the transition deposites, in the secondary as well<lb/>as in the volcanic, he has been struck with the great features by<lb/>which the table of formations is characterized in the most distant<lb/>regions.</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#c">(<hi rendition="#i">To be continued.</hi>)</hi></p><lb/><pb n="224" facs="#f0015" />
<div n="2"><head><hi rendition="#i">On Rock Formations.</hi> By Baron <hi rendition="#k">Alexander<lb/>Humboldt.</hi> (Concluded from p. 53.)</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k"><hi rendition="#in">F</hi>rom</hi> that scepticism which would deny the existence of any<lb/>kind of regular order in the position of rocks, it is proper to dis-<lb/>tinguish an opinion which has sometimes found supporters<lb/>among experienced observers. According to this opinion, the for-<lb/>mations of gneiss-granite, of greywacke, of alpine limestone,<lb/>and of chalk, which have a uniform superposition in different<lb/>countries, do not very well correspond among themselves as to<lb/>the age of the homonymous elements of each series. It is thought<lb/>that a secondary rock may have been formed on one spot of the<lb/>globe, while transition rocks did not yet exist on another spot.<lb/>In this supposition, no allusion is had to those granitic rocks<lb/>which are found lying above limestone containing orthoceratites,<lb/>and which are consequently newer than the primitive rocks. It<lb/>is a fact generally admitted at this day, that formations of <hi rendition="#i">ana-<lb/>logous composition</hi> have been repeatedly deposited at epochs far<lb/>removed from each other. The doubt which we are now consi-<lb/>dering, (though we do not partake in it), bears on a point much<lb/>less clearly established,&#x2014;the ascertaining whether certain mica-<lb/>slate rocks, evidently situate in the midst of a country of primi-<lb/><pb n="225" facs="#f0016" />
    tive rocks, and placed below those in which the vestiges of or-<lb/>ganic life begin to appear, are newer than the secondary rocks<lb/>of another country. I confess, that, in the part of the globe which<lb/>I have had an opportunity of examining, I have not seen any<lb/>thing that might tend to confirm this opinion. Granular syeni-<lb/>tic rocks repeated twice, perhaps even three times, in primitive,<lb/>intermediary (and secondary) deposits, are analogous phenome-<lb/>na with which we have become acquainted within these fifteen<lb/>years. The disagreement in regard to age of great homonymous<lb/>formations, does not by any means seem to me to be proved as<lb/>yet by direct observations, made upon the contact of superim-<lb/>posed formations. The chalk or Jura limestone may, on one<lb/>hand, immediately cover primitive granite, and, on the other, be<lb/>separated from it by numerous secondary and transition rocks:<lb/>these very common facts demonstrate only the abstraction, the<lb/>absence, or non-development of several intermediary members<lb/>of the geognostical series. The greywacke may, on one hand,<lb/>dip beneath a felspar rock, or rock of which felspar forms a<lb/>principal constituent; for example, beneath transition granite or<lb/>zircon syenite; and, on the other hand, be superimposed upon<lb/>the black limestone containing madrepores; but this position<lb/>shows only the intercalation of a bed of greywacke between fel-<lb/>spar rocks. Since the minute investigation of fossil organic bo-<lb/>dies has, through the important labours of Messrs <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Cuvier</persName> and<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>, diffused a new life as it were in the study of the<lb/>tertiary formations, the discovery of the same fossils in analogous<lb/>beds of very distant countries, has rendered the isochronism of<lb/>very generally extended formations still more probable.</p><lb/><p>It is this isochronism alone, this admirable order of succession,<lb/>which seems given to man to investigate with some degree of<lb/>certainty. The attempts which theological geologists have made<lb/>to subject the periods to absolute measurements of time, and to<lb/>connect the chronology of ancient cosmogonic narrations with<lb/>the observations of nature, could not possibly have been produc-<lb/>tive of satisfactory results. &#x201C;It has been more than once,&#x201D; says<lb/>M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Ramond</persName>, in a discourse replete with philosophical views,<lb/>&#x201C;thought that a supplement to our short annals might be found<lb/>in the monuments of Nature. There is, however, enough of his-<lb/>torical ages, to let us see that the succession of physical and mo-<lb/><pb n="226" facs="#f0017" />
        ral events, is not regulated by the uniform progress of time, and<lb/>could not consequently give it measure. We see behind us a<lb/>series of creations and destructions, by means of the strata of<lb/>which the crust of the earth is composed. They give rise to the<lb/>idea of so many distinct periods; but these periods, so fertile in<lb/>events, may have been very short, in comparison with the num-<lb/>ber and importance of the results. Between the creations and<lb/>destructions, on the other hand, we see nothing, however vast<lb/>the intervals may be. There, where all is lost in the void of un-<lb/>determined antiquity, the degrees of relative age have no appre-<lb/>ciable value; because the succession of phenomena has no longer<lb/>the scale which relates to the division of time.&#x201D; <bibl><hi rendition="#i">(Memoires de<lb/>l&#x2019;Institut</hi>, for the year 1815, p. 47</bibl>.<hi rendition="#i">)</hi></p><lb/><p>In the geognostical monography of a deposit of small extent,<lb/>for example, the environs of a city, one cannot distinguish with<lb/>sufficient minuteness the different beds which compose the local<lb/>formations, shelving banks of sand and clay, the subdivisions of<lb/>gypsums, the strata of marly and oölitic limestone, designated<lb/>in <placeName>England</placeName> by the names of <placeName>Purbeck Beds</placeName>, <placeName>Portland Stone</placeName>,<lb/><placeName>Coral Rag</placeName>, <placeName>Kelloway Rock</placeName>, and <placeName>Corn Brash</placeName>, then acquire a great<lb/>degree of importance. Thin beds of secondary and tertiary for-<lb/>mations, containing assemblages of very characteristic fossil bo-<lb/>dies, have furnished, as it were, a <hi rendition="#i">horizon</hi> to the geognost. In<lb/>their prolongation, whatever occurs placed above or beneath in<lb/>the order of the whole series, has been referred to one of them.<lb/>Even the particular denominations by which beds are distin-<lb/>guished, are of much importance in a geognostical description,<lb/>however whimsical or improper may be their signification or<lb/>their origin as taken from the language of miners. But while<lb/>treating of the relative position of rocks on a surface of great<lb/>extent, it is indispensably necessary to consider the formations<lb/>or habitual associations of certain beds in a more general point<lb/>of view. It is then that discretion and circumspection are more<lb/>necessary in the distinction of rocks, and in their nomenclature.<lb/>The work of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Freiesleben</persName> on the Plains of <placeName>Saxony</placeName>, which<lb/>are upwards of 700 square leagues in extent (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Geogr. Beschr. des<lb/>Kupferschiefergebirges,</hi> 1807&#x2014;15</bibl>), presents a beautiful model<lb/>of the union of local observations and geognostical generaliza-<lb/>tions. These generalizations, these attempts to simplify the system<lb/><pb n="227" facs="#f0018" />
of formations, and to direct the attention more especially to great<lb/>characteristic features, should be more or less cautiously con-<lb/>ducted, according as one describes the basin of a river, an iso-<lb/>lated province, a great country such as <placeName>France</placeName> or <placeName>Germany</placeName>, or<lb/>an entire continent.</p><lb/><p>The more minute the investigation of districts becomes, the<lb/>more does the connection between formations which appear at<lb/>first perfectly independent, manifest itself by the great pheno-<lb/>menon of <hi rendition="#i">alternation;</hi> that is to say, by a periodical succession<lb/>of beds which present a certain analogy in their composition, and<lb/>sometimes even in certain fossil organic bodies. It is thus that,<lb/>in the transition-mountains, for example, in <placeName>America</placeName> (at the en-<lb/>trance of the <placeName>plains of Calabozo</placeName>), beds of greenstone and eupho-<lb/>tide, in <placeName>Saxony</placeName> (near <placeName>Friedrichswalde</placeName> and <placeName>Meissen</placeName>) the clay-slates<lb/>with glance-coal, the greywackes, porphyries, black limestones,<lb/>and greenstones, constitute, from their frequent and repeated<lb/><hi rendition="#i">alternation</hi>, a single formation. It often happens that subordi-<lb/>nate beds appear only at the extreme limits of a formation, and<lb/>assume the aspect of an independent formation. The cupreous<lb/>and bituminous marls (<hi rendition="#i">Kupferschiefer</hi>), which occur in <placeName>Thu-<lb/>ringia</placeName> between the alpine limestone (<hi rendition="#i">zechstein</hi>) and the red sand-<lb/>stone (<hi rendition="#i">rothes liegende</hi>), and which have for ages been extensively<lb/>wrought, are represented in several parts of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, of <placeName>New<lb/>Andalusia</placeName>, and of <placeName>Southern Bavaria</placeName>, by multiplied beds of<lb/>marly clay, more or less carburetted, and included within the<lb/>alpine limestone. Similar circumstances often give to gypsums,<lb/>sandstones, and small beds of compact limestones, the appear-<lb/>ance of particular formations. Their dependence on <hi rendition="#i">subordina-<lb/>tion</hi> is known by their frequent association with other rocks, by<lb/>their want of extent and of thickness, or by their total suppres-<lb/>sion, which is frequently observed. It must not be forgot (and<lb/>this fact has struck me much in the two hemispheres) that the<lb/>great formations of limestones, for example, the alpine lime-<lb/>stone, have <hi rendition="#i">their sandstones</hi>, as the very generally extended<lb/>sandstones have <hi rendition="#i">their limestone beds</hi>. Thin beds of sandstones,<lb/>of limestones, and of gypsums, characterize, in all the zones,<lb/>the deposites of coal and rock-salt or muriatiferous clay (<hi rendition="#i">salzthon</hi>),<lb/>isolated deposites, which are most commonly only covered by<lb/>these small local formations. It is by overlooking these consi-<lb/><pb n="228" facs="#f0019" />
    derations, which should be familiar to every practical geologist,<lb/>that the type of the great independent formations has been ren-<lb/>dered too complicated.</p><lb/><p>The phenomenon of <hi rendition="#i">alternation</hi> manifests itself, either locally<lb/>in rocks, superimposed several times upon each other, and con-<lb/>stituting a single compound formation, or in the series of forma-<lb/>tions considered in their aggregate. It is either greenstones and<lb/>syenites, slates and transition limestones, beds of limestones and<lb/>of marl, that alternate immediately, or the whole is a system of<lb/>mica-slates, and of granular feldspathic rocks (granites, gneisses,<lb/>and syenites), which reappear among the transition deposits,<lb/>and which separate from the primitive homonymous system the<lb/>greywackes and limestones with orthoceratites. For the first<lb/>knowledge of this fact, one of the most important and least<lb/>studied of modern geognosy, we are indebted to the beautiful<lb/>observations of Messrs <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Leopold von Buch</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brochant</persName>, and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Hauss-<lb/>mann</persName>. From the circumstance that, in the transition system,<lb/>granular rocks, perfectly destitute of organic remains, succeed<lb/>to compact rocks which contain these same remains, it has been<lb/>concluded by geognosts of great name, that this alternation of<lb/>shelly and not-shelly rocks, might extend beyond the deposites<lb/>which we call primitive. It has not been merely asked if the<lb/>clay-slates, mica-slates, and gneisses, support the granites which<lb/>have been considered as the oldest; the question has also been<lb/>agitated, whether greywackes and black limestones with madre-<lb/>pores might not recur beneath those same granites. According<lb/>to this idea, the primitive and transition rocks would only form<lb/>a single deposite; and the first might be regarded as intercalated<lb/>in a deposite posterior to the development of organic beings,<lb/>and which might penetrate to an unknown depth into the inte-<lb/>rior of the globe. I confess, that no direct observation can be<lb/>as yet adduced in support of these opinions. The fragments of<lb/>rocks which I have seen contained in the lithoid lavas of the vol-<lb/>canoes of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, <placeName>Quito</placeName>, and <placeName>Vesuvius</placeName>, and which are thought<lb/>to have been torn from the bowels of the earth, seem to belong<lb/>to altered rocks of granite, mica-slate, syenite, and granular<lb/>limestone, and not to greywackes and limestone with madre-<lb/>pores.</p><lb/><p>We have preserved in the arrangement of rocks the great<lb/>divisions known by the name of primitive, transition or inter-<lb/><pb n="229" facs="#f0020" />
        mediary, secondary and tertiary deposites. The natural limits<lb/>of these four <hi rendition="#i">systems of rocks</hi> are the clay-slate with glance-<lb/>coal or ampelite and lydian stone, alternating with compact<lb/>limestones and greywackes, the coal formation, and the forma-<lb/>tions which immediately succeed the chalk. In geognosy, as<lb/>in descriptive botany, the subdivisions or small groups of<lb/>families have more distinct characters than the great divisions<lb/>or classes. It is the case with all the sciences; in which we rise<lb/>from individuals to species, from species to genera, and from<lb/>these to still higher degrees of abstraction. A method neces-<lb/>sarily rests upon <hi rendition="#i">differently graduated abstractions</hi>, and the pas-<lb/>sages become more frequent in proportion as the characters are<lb/>more complex. The transition or intermediary formations of<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Werner</persName>, which M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Buch</persName> has first limited with the sagacity<lb/>for which he is distinguished (<bibl>Moll&#x2019;s Jahrb. 1798, b. ii. p. 254</bibl>.),<lb/>are connected by the ampelitic clay-slates, the syenites with zir-<lb/>cons, the granite sometimes destitute of hornblende, and the an-<lb/>thracitic mica-slate, with the primitive deposite; while the small-<lb/>grained greywackes and madreporous and compact limestones,<lb/>connect them with the coal sandstones and limestones of the se-<lb/>condary deposites.</p><lb/><p>Porphyries of very different formations have their principal<lb/>seat among the transition rocks; but they break out, if we may<lb/>so speak, in considerable masses towards the secondary depo-<lb/>sites, where they are connected with the coal sandstone, while<lb/>they penetrate into the primitive class only as subordinate rocks,<lb/>and of little thickness. The progressive motion, or, if I may<lb/>be allowed to use the expression, the extent of the <hi rendition="#i">oscilla-<lb/>tion</hi> of the serpentine and euphotide, is very different. Those<lb/>diallage rocks, constituting many distinct formations, rarely co-<lb/>vered with other rocks, stop short nearly at the lower boundary<lb/>of the secondary formations; towards the bottom they penetrate<lb/>into the primitive deposites to beyond the mica-schist. The<lb/>chalk seems to present a natural limit to the tertiary formations,<lb/>which were first characterised by Messrs <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Cuvier</persName> and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>,<lb/>and justly, as deposites entirely different from the last secon-<lb/>dary formations, described by the <placeName>Freyberg</placeName> School (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Géogr.<lb/>Miner. des Environs des Paris,</hi> p. 8. and 9</bibl>.) Struck with<lb/>the relations which exist between the tertiary deposites and<lb/><pb n="230" facs="#f0021" />
            the beds beneath the chalk, M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName> has even recently<lb/>proposed to designate the tertiary formations by the name of<lb/><hi rendition="#i">upper</hi> secondary deposites, (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Sur le gisement des Ophiolithes,</hi><lb/>p. 37</bibl>). Compare also the very interesting geognostical discussions<lb/>contained in <bibl><hi rendition="#i">M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Bonnard</persName>&#x2019;s Traité des Roches,</hi> p. 138, 210,<lb/>and 212</bibl>.)</p><lb/><p>The distinction of four deposites which we have successively<lb/>named, and of which three are posterior to the development of<lb/>organic life upon the globe, appears to me worthy of being re-<lb/>tained, notwithstanding the passage of some formations to others<lb/>of a very different character, and notwithstanding the doubts<lb/>which several very distinguished geognosts have founded upon<lb/>these passages. The classification of deposites marks great<lb/>epochs of nature; for example, the first appearance of some pe-<lb/>lagic animals (zoophytes, cephalopodous mollusca), and the si-<lb/>multaneous destruction of an enormous mass of monocotyle-<lb/>dons. It presents as it were points of rest to the mind, and by<lb/>keeping in view that the formations themselves are much less<lb/>important than the great divisions, we have often an opportu-<lb/>nity, on advancing from high mountains toward the plains, of<lb/>observing the varied influence which the association of primi-<lb/>tive and transition rocks, and that of secondary and tertiary<lb/>ones, have exercised upon the inequality and configuration of the<lb/>ground. It is owing to this influence, that the aspect of the<lb/>landscape, the form of mountains and platforms, and the cha-<lb/>racter of the vegetation, vary less, when we travel parallel to the<lb/>direction of the beds, than on cutting them at a right angle.<lb/>(<bibl>Greenough, Crit. Exam. of Geology, p. 38</bibl>.)</p><lb/><p>I continue, by following Messrs <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Buch</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Freiesleben</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Bro-<lb/>chant</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Beudant</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Buckland</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Raumer</persName> (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Geb.</hi> von Nieder-Schles.,<lb/>1819</bibl>), and other celebrated geognosts, to group the indepen-<lb/>dent formations according to the divisions, into primitive, transi-<lb/>tion, secondary, and tertiary deposites, without troubling myself<lb/>about the impropriety of the greater number of these denomi-<lb/>nations. I continue to separate the clay (with lignites) super-<lb/>imposed upon the chalk, from that which is beneath it, and the<lb/>chalk itself from the more ancient secondary formations. But<lb/>these distinctions, by beds and groups of beds, so useful in the<lb/>description of a deposite of small extent, ought not to prevent<lb/><pb n="231" facs="#f0022" />
                the geognost, when he tries to rise to a more general point of<lb/>view, from connecting these clays and the chalk with the Jura<lb/>limestone, and from regarding them as the last strata of this<lb/>great formation, composed of calcareous and marly beds.<lb/>The inferior beds of the chalk (tuffeau) contain ammonites.<lb/>The limestone of the <placeName>mountain of St Peter</placeName> of <placeName>Maestricht</placeName> indi-<lb/>cates, as has already been observed by Messrs <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Omalius</persName> and<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName> (<bibl>Geogr. Miner., p. 13</bibl>), the passage of the chalk to<lb/>older secondary limestones. Near Caen, according to the<lb/>beautiful observations of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Prevost</persName>, the clays beneath the chalk<lb/>contain those same lignites which occur, in greater quantity, in<lb/>the clay which is situated immediately above the chalk: cerites,<lb/>which bring to mind the coarse limestone of <placeName>Paris</placeName>, are seen in a<lb/>limestone with trigonias, placed between clays inferior to the<lb/>chalk and the oolitic beds. I do not insist upon these particu-<lb/>lar facts; I mention them only to prove, by a striking example,<lb/>how, on bringing together facts observed in different points of<lb/>the same country, the great phenomenon of <hi rendition="#i">alternation</hi> reveals<lb/>to us the connections between formations which at first sight<lb/>appear to have nothing in common. It is the property of those<lb/>beds which alternate with one another, of those rocks which<lb/>succeed each other in <hi rendition="#i">periodical series</hi>, to present the most mark-<lb/>ed contrast in the two beds which immediately follow each<lb/>other. In geognosy, as in the different parts of descriptive na-<lb/>tural history, the advantage of classifications of variously gra-<lb/>duated sections must be recognised, without losing sight of the<lb/>unity of nature; and those who have contributed the most to<lb/>the advancement of natural philosophy, have possessed at once<lb/>both the tendency to generalize, and the exact knowledge of a<lb/>mass of particular facts.</p><lb/><p>It has been customary to terminate the series of deposites by<lb/>the volcanic rocks, and to make them succeed the secondary and<lb/>tertiary, and even the alluvial deposites. In a system constructed<lb/>upon the principle of relative antiquity, this arrangement seems<lb/>to me to have little to recommend it. It is without doubt the<lb/>case that lithoid lavas are spread over the most recent forma-<lb/>tions, even over beds of gravel; nor can it be denied that there<lb/>exist volcanic productions of different epochs: but, from what<lb/>I have observed in the <placeName>Cordilleras of Peru</placeName>, of <placeName>Quito</placeName>, and of<lb/><pb n="232" facs="#f0023" />
    <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, in a part of the world so celebrated for the frequency<lb/>of volcanoes, it seems to me, that the chief site of subterranean<lb/>fires is in the transition rocks, and beneath those rocks. I have ob-<lb/>served, that all the burning or extinct craters of the <placeName>Andes</placeName> open<lb/>in the midst of trap porphyries or trachytes, (<bibl>Berl. Abhandl.<lb/>der Kön. Acad., 1813, p. 131</bibl>), and that these trachytes are<lb/>connected with the great transition <hi rendition="#i">porphyry</hi>, and <hi rendition="#i">syenite forma-<lb/>tion</hi>. According to this observation, it appears more natural to<lb/>me to make the secondary and volcanic deposites to follow the<lb/>transition deposite in a parallel manner, and as by bisection. By<lb/>this new arrangement, the formation of porphyries, syenites and<lb/>greywackes, or that of transition porphyries, syenites and granites,<lb/>occurs connected at the same time; 1<hi rendition="#i">st</hi>, With the porphyries of<lb/>the red sandstone in the secondary coal-deposite; 2<hi rendition="#i">dly</hi>, With the<lb/>trachytes or trap porphyries which are destitute of quartz, and<lb/>mixed with pyroxene. I employ with regret the term <hi rendition="#i">volcanic<lb/>terrain,</hi> not that I doubt, like those who designate the trachytes,<lb/>basalts and phonolites (porphyrschiefer), by the name of <hi rendition="#i">trap<lb/>terrain</hi>, that all which I have associated in the volcanic terrain<lb/>has not been produced or altered by fire; but because several<lb/>rocks, intercalated between the (primitive?) transition and se-<lb/>condary rocks, might also be volcanic. I would rather wish to<lb/>avoid every (historical) idea of the origin of things, in a (sta-<lb/>tistical) view of relative situation or superposition. At <placeName>Skeen</placeName>,<lb/>in <placeName>Norway</placeName>, a basaltic and porous syenite, containing pyroxenes,<lb/>is placed, according to the observation of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Buch</persName>, between<lb/>the transition limestone and the syenite with zircons. It is a<lb/>bed, not a dike; and this is a much less problematical pheno-<lb/>menon than the basalt (<bibl>Urgrünstein, Buch. <hi rendition="#i">Geogn. Beob.</hi> p.<lb/>124</bibl>, and <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Raumer</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Granit des Riesengebirges,</hi> p. 70</bibl>.) contained<lb/>in the mica-schist of <placeName>Krobsdorf</placeName> in <placeName>Silesia</placeName>. The trachytes, with<lb/>obsidian of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, are intimately connected with the transition<lb/>porphyries which alternate with syenites. The amygdaloid be-<lb/>longing to the red sandstone, assumes, on the Continent of<lb/><placeName>Europe</placeName>, and in <placeName>Equinoctial America</placeName>, all the appearance of an<lb/>amygdaloid of the basaltic formation. M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Boué</persName>, in his interest-<lb/>ing <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Essai Geologique sur l&#x2019;Ecosse,</hi> p. 126, 162</bibl>, has described<lb/>pyroxenic rocks (dolerites) included in the red sandstone. With-<lb/>out prejudging any thing regarding the origin of these masses,<lb/><pb n="233" facs="#f0024" />
                    or in general regarding that of all the primitive and transition<lb/>rocks, we designate here, by the name of Volcanic Terrains, <hi rendition="#i">the<lb/>least interrupted series</hi> of rocks altered by fire.</p><lb/><p>In drawing up the enumeration of the different rocks, I have<lb/>made use of the names most generally employed by the geo-<lb/>gnosts of <placeName>France</placeName>, <placeName>Germany</placeName>, <placeName>England</placeName>, and <placeName>Italy</placeName>: in attempt-<lb/>ing to perfect the nomenclature of formations, I should be ap-<lb/>prehensive of adding new difficulties to those which the discus-<lb/>sion of relative positions already present. I have, however, care-<lb/>fully avoided the denominations, too long preserved, of <hi rendition="#i">under</hi><lb/>and <hi rendition="#i">upper limestone;</hi> of gypsum of the <hi rendition="#i">first</hi>, <hi rendition="#i">second</hi>, or <hi rendition="#i">third<lb/>formation</hi>, of <hi rendition="#i">old</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">new red sandstone</hi>, &amp;c. These denomina-<lb/>tions without doubt present a true geognostical character; they<lb/>have relation, not to the composition of rocks, but to their rela-<lb/>tive age. However, as the general type of the formations of<lb/><placeName>Europe</placeName> cannot be modelled after that of a single district, the<lb/>necessity of admitting parallel formations <hi rendition="#i">(sich vertretende Ge-<lb/>birgsarten)</hi>, renders the names of <hi rendition="#i">first</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">second</hi> gypsum, of <hi rendition="#i">old</hi><lb/>or <hi rendition="#i">middle</hi> sandstone, extremely vague and obscure. In one<lb/>country it is proper to consider a bed of gypsum or of common<lb/>sandstone as a particular formation; while in another, it should<lb/>be regarded as subordinate to neighbouring formations. The<lb/><hi rendition="#i">geographical denominations</hi> are without doubt the best; they<lb/>give rise to precise ideas of superposition. When it is said that<lb/>a formation is identical with the porphyry of <placeName>Christiania</placeName>, the<lb/>lias of <placeName>Dorsetshire</placeName>, the sandstone of <placeName>Nebra</placeName> (bunter sandstein),<lb/>the coarse limestone of <placeName>Paris</placeName>, these assertions leave no doubt<lb/>in the mind of an experienced geognost, regarding the position<lb/>which is to be assigned to the formation in question. It is also<lb/>by silent convention, as it were, that the words <hi rendition="#i">zechstein of<lb/><placeName>Thuringia</placeName>, <placeName>Derbyshire</placeName> Limestone, <placeName>Paris</placeName> Formation,</hi> &amp;c. have<lb/>been introduced into mineralogical language. They express a<lb/>limestone which immediately succeeds the red sandstone of the<lb/>coal deposite, a transition limestone placed beneath the coal sand-<lb/>stone, and lastly formations of more recent origin than the chalk.<lb/>The only difficulties which the multiplicity of these geographical<lb/>denominations presents, consist in the choice of names, and in<lb/>the degree of certainty which may have been acquired, regard-<lb/>ing the position or relative age of the rock to which the others<lb/><pb n="234" facs="#f0025" />
    are referred. The English geognosts look upon the continent<lb/>for their <hi rendition="#i">lias</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">red marl;</hi> the German for their <hi rendition="#i">bunte sand-<lb/>stein</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">muschelkalk</hi>. These words present themselves in the<lb/>minds of travellers associated with remembrances of localities. It<lb/>is not of so much importance, therefore, to produce precise ideas,<lb/>as to make choice of localities generally known, and which are<lb/>celebrated, either by the working of mines, or by descriptive<lb/>works.</p><lb/><p>In order to diminish the effects of national vanity, and to at-<lb/>tach new names to more important objects, I proposed a long<lb/>time ago, (<bibl>1795</bibl>), the denominations of <hi rendition="#i">Alpine Limestone</hi>, and<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Jura Limestone</hi>. A portion of the <placeName>High Alps of Switzerland</placeName>,<lb/>and the greater part of <placeName>Jura</placeName>, are without doubt formed of these<lb/>two rocks: the names, however, generally received at the present<lb/>day, of Alpine Limestone (Zechstein), and Jura Limestone,<lb/>should in my opinion be modified or entirely abandoned. The<lb/>lower beds of the <placeName>Jura mountains</placeName>, filled with gryphites, belong<lb/>to an older formation, perhaps to the zechstein; and a great<lb/>part of the limestone of the <placeName>Alps of Switzerland</placeName> assuredly is<lb/>not zechstein; but, according to Messrs <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Buch</persName> and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Escher</persName>,<lb/>transition limestone. It would therefore be better to choose the<lb/>geographical names of rocks from among the names of isolated<lb/>mountains, the whole visible mass of which belongs only to a<lb/>single formation, than to derive them, as I have erroneously<lb/>done, from entire chains. I have thought, and many geognosts<lb/>have formed the same opinion, that the Jura limestone (cavern-<lb/>ous limestone of <placeName>Franconia</placeName>) was generally placed upon the con-<lb/>tinent, beneath the Nebra sandstone, (bunte sandstein), between<lb/>this sandstone and the zechstein. Subsequent observations<lb/>have proved, that the name of Jura Limestone had with reason<lb/>been applied to rocks which are very distant from the moun-<lb/>tains of <placeName>Western Switzerland</placeName>; but that the true geognostical<lb/>place of this formation, (when there is not a <hi rendition="#i">suppression</hi> of the<lb/>inferior formations), occurs above the Nebra sandstone, between<lb/>the shell-limestone (muschelkalk, or the quadersandstein), and<lb/>the chalk. A geographical name, justly applied to several ana-<lb/>logous rocks, renders us attentive to their identity of relative<lb/>position; but the place which homonymous rocks ought to oc-<lb/>cupy in the total series, is not well determined except when the<lb/><pb n="235" facs="#f0026" />
        geographical name has been selected, after having acquired a<lb/>perfect certainty regarding their position. Circumstances are<lb/>the same with regard to the relative age of the molasse of <placeName>Ar-<lb/>govia</placeName><choice><sic>,</sic><corr type="editorial"></corr></choice> (<choice><sic>nagelfluhe</sic><corr type="editorial">nagelfluhe)</corr></choice> and of the <placeName>Pirna</placeName> quadersandstein (grès blanc<lb/>of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Bonnard</persName>), two rocks of very recent origin, which have<lb/>been very well examined separately, but whose relations to each<lb/>other, and to the chalk and Jura limestone, have only been illus-<lb/>trated of late. One may therefore be pretty sure of having met<lb/>in the <placeName>New Continent</placeName> with rocks identical with the molasse or<lb/>quadersandstein, without being able to pronounce with certain-<lb/>ty upon their relations with all the secondary or tertiary rocks.<lb/>When rocks are not immediately in contact, and are not covered<lb/>by deposites of known position, their relative age can only be<lb/>conjectured from simple analogies.</p><lb/><p>The <hi rendition="#i">terms</hi> of the geognostical series are either <hi rendition="#i">simple</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">com-<lb/>plex</hi>. To the simple terms belong the greater number of the<lb/>primitive formations: the granites, gneisses, mica-slates, clay-<lb/>slates, &amp;c. The complex terms occur in greater numbers<lb/>among the transition rocks: there, each formation includes an<lb/>entire group of rocks, which alternate periodically. The terms<lb/>of the series are not transition limestones or greywackes, consti-<lb/>tuting independent formations; they are associations of clay-<lb/>slate, greenstone, and greywacke; of porphyry and greywacke;<lb/>of granular steatitic limestone, and of conglomerates, composed<lb/>of primitive rocks; of clay-slate and black limestone. When<lb/>these associations are formed of three or four rocks which alter-<lb/>nate, it is difficult to give them significant names,&#x2014;names indi-<lb/>cative of the whole composition of the group,&#x2014;of all the partial<lb/>members of the complex term of the series. It may then assist<lb/>in fixing the groups in the memory, to retrace the rocks which<lb/>predominate in them, without being absolutely wanting in the<lb/>neighbouring groups. It is in this manner that the granular<lb/>steatitic limestone characterises the <placeName>Tarantaise</placeName> formation; the<lb/>greywacke, the great transition formation of the <placeName>Hartz</placeName> and of<lb/>the <placeName>banks of the Rhine</placeName>; the metalliferous porphyries rich in<lb/>hornblende, and almost destitute of quartz, the formation of<lb/><placeName>Mexico</placeName> and of <placeName>Hungary</placeName>. If these phenomena of alternation<lb/>attain their <hi rendition="#i">maximum</hi> in the transition districts, still they are not<lb/>entirely excluded from the primitive and secondary terrain. In<lb/><pb n="236" facs="#f0027" />
        both of these terrains, complex terms are mixed with the simple<lb/>terms of the geognostical series. I shall mention among the se-<lb/>condary formations, the sandstone placed below the alpine lime-<lb/>stone, (the Nebra sandstone, bunte sandstein), which is an asso-<lb/>ciation of marly clay, sandstone and oolites; the limestone which<lb/>covers the red-sandstone of the coal-formation (the zechstein or<lb/>alpen-kalkstein), which is a less constant association of limestone,<lb/>of (muriatiferous) gypsum, of stinkstone and of pulverulent<lb/>bituminous marl. In the primitive class we find the three<lb/>first terms of the series; the oldest rocks either isolated, or al-<lb/>ternating two and two, according as they are geognostically<lb/>more approximated by their relative age, or the whole three al-<lb/>ternating. The granite sometimes forms constant associations with<lb/>the gneiss, and the gneiss with the mica-slate. These alterna-<lb/>tions follow particular laws: we see, (for example in <placeName>Brazil</placeName>, and,<lb/>although less distinctly, in the maritime chain of <placeName>Venezuela</placeName>), the<lb/>granite, gneiss and mica schist in a triple association; but I have<lb/>not found granite alternating alone with mica-slate, or gneiss and<lb/>mica-slate alternating by themselves with clay-slate.</p><lb/><p>We must not confound, and on this point I have often in-<lb/>sisted in the present article, rocks passing insensibly to those<lb/>which are in immediate contact with them; for example, mica-<lb/>slates, which <hi rendition="#i">oscillate</hi> between gneiss and clay-slate, with rocks<lb/>which alternate with one another, and which preserve all their<lb/>distinctive characters of composition and of structure. M.<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">D&#x2019;Aubuisson</persName> has long ago shewn how chemical analysis approxi-<lb/>mates the clay-slate to mica. <bibl><hi rendition="#i">(Journal de Physique</hi>, vol. 68.<lb/>p. 128</bibl>.; <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Traité de Geognosie</hi>, vol. ii. p. 97</bibl>.<hi rendition="#i">)</hi> The first, it is<lb/>true, has not the metallic lustre of mica-slate; it contains a lit-<lb/>tle less potash, and more carbon; the silex does not unite into<lb/>nodules or thin lamin&#x00E6; of quartz, as in the mica-slate; but it<lb/>cannot be doubted, that scales of mica form the principal base<lb/>of the clay-slate. These scales are so joined together, that the<lb/>eye cannot distinguish them in the mass. It is perhaps this<lb/>same affinity which prevents the alternation of clay-slates and<lb/>mica-slates: for in these alternations Nature seems to favour the<lb/>association of heterogeneous rocks; or, to make use of a figura-<lb/>tive expression, she delights in the associations whose alternating<lb/>rocks present a great contrast of crystallization, of mixture and<lb/><pb n="237" facs="#f0028" />
of colour. At <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, I have seen dark greenstones, al-<lb/>ternate thousands of times with reddish-white syenites, abound-<lb/>ing more in quartz than in felspar. In this greenstone there<lb/>were veins of syenite, and in the syenite veins of greenstone;<lb/>but none of the two rocks passed into the other. <bibl><hi rendition="#i">(Essai poli-<lb/>tique sur la Nouvelle Espagne,</hi> v. ii. p. 523</bibl>.<hi rendition="#i">)</hi> They present at<lb/>the limit of their mutual contact, differences as marked as the<lb/>porphyries which alternate with the greywackes or with the sye-<lb/>nites, as the black limestones which alternate with the transition<lb/>clay-slates, and so many other rocks of entirely heterogeneous<lb/>composition and aspect. Further, when, in primitive deposites,<lb/>rocks more related by the nature of their composition than by<lb/>their structure or mode of aggregation, for example, the granites<lb/>and gneisses, or the gneisses and mica-schists, alternate; these<lb/>rocks do not by any means show the same tendency to pass in-<lb/>to each other, as they present, when isolated in formations which<lb/>are not of a complex character. We have already observed, that<lb/>often a bed &#x03B2;, becoming more frequent in the rock &#x03B1;, announces<lb/>to the traveller that the simple formation &#x03B1;, is to be succeeded<lb/>by a compound formation, in which &#x03B1; and &#x03B2; alternate. Farther<lb/>on, it happens, that &#x03B2; assumes a greater development; that &#x03B1; is<lb/>no longer an alternating rock, but a simple bed subordinate to &#x03B2;,<lb/>and that this rock &#x03B2; shows itself alone, until, by the frequent<lb/>repetition of beds &#x03B3;, it becomes the precursor of a compound for-<lb/>mation of &#x03B2;, alternating with &#x03B3;. We might substitute for these<lb/>signs the words granite, gneiss, and mica-slate; those of por-<lb/>phyry, greywacke and syenite; of gypsum, marl and fetid lime-<lb/>stone (stinkstein). <hi rendition="#i">Pasigraphic</hi> language has the advantage of<lb/>generalizing the problems; it is more conformable to the wants<lb/>of <hi rendition="#i">geognostical philosophy</hi>, of which I attempt to present here<lb/>the first elements, in so far as they have relation to the study of<lb/>the superposition of rocks. Now, if often between formations<lb/>which are simple and very closely allied, in the order of their<lb/>relative antiquity, between the formations &#x03B1;, &#x03B2;, &#x03B3;, there occur<lb/>compound formations interposed, &#x03B1;&#x03B2; and &#x03B2;&#x03B3;, (that is to say &#x03B1; al-<lb/>ternating with &#x03B2;, and &#x03B2; alternating with &#x03B3;); we observe, also,<lb/>although less frequently, that a formation (for example &#x03B1;,) as-<lb/>sumes so extraordinary an increase, that it envelopes the forma-<lb/><pb n="238" facs="#f0029" />
            tion &#x03B2;; and that &#x03B2;, instead of showing itself as an indepen-<lb/>dent rock, placed between &#x03B1; and &#x03B3;, is now nothing but a bed in<lb/>&#x03B1;. It is thus, that, in <placeName>Lower Silesia</placeName>, the red-sandstone contains<lb/>the formation of zechstein; for the limestone of <placeName>Runzendorf</placeName>,<lb/>filled with impressions of fishes, and analogous to the bitumi-<lb/>nous marl abounding in fishes of <placeName>Thuringia</placeName>, is entirely de-<lb/>veloped in the coal-formation. (<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Buch</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Beob.</hi> vol. i. p. 104. 157.;<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Id.</hi> <choice><sic>Reisenach</sic><corr type="editorial">Reise nach</corr></choice> Norwegen, vol. i. p. 158</bibl>.; <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Raumer</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Gebirge von<lb/>Nieder-schlesien,</hi> p. 79</bibl>.) M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Beudant</persName>, <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Voy. Miner.,</hi> vol. iii.<lb/>p. 183</bibl>., has observed a similar phenomenon in <placeName>Hungary</placeName>. In<lb/>other districts, for example, in <placeName>Switzerland</placeName>, at the southern ex-<lb/>tremity of <placeName>Saxony</placeName>, the red-sandstone disappears entirely; be-<lb/>cause it is replaced, and, so to speak, overcome, by a prodigious<lb/>development of greywacke or of alpine limestone. (<bibl><choice><sic>Friesleben</sic><corr type="editorial">Freiesleben</corr></choice>,<lb/>Kupfersch. p. 109</bibl>.) These effects of the alternation or unequal<lb/>development of rocks, are so much the more worthy of attention,<lb/>that their study may throw light upon some apparent deviations<lb/>from a generally acknowledged type of superposition, and that<lb/>it may serve to refer to a common type the series of position ob-<lb/>served in very distant countries.</p><lb/><p>In order to designate the formations composed of two rocks<lb/>which alternate with another, I have generally preferred the<lb/>words <hi rendition="#i">granite and gneiss, syenite and greenstone</hi>, to the<lb/>more commonly adopted expressions of <hi rendition="#i">granite-gneiss, syenite-<lb/>greenstone</hi>. I was apprehensive that this last method of desig-<lb/>nating formations composed of alternating rocks, might rather<lb/>give rise to the idea of a passage from granite to gneiss, from<lb/>syenite to greenstone. In fact, a geognost, whose works upon<lb/>the trachytes of <placeName>Germany</placeName> have not been sufficiently appreciated,<lb/>M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Nose</persName>, has already made use of the words <hi rendition="#i">granite-porphyries</hi><lb/>and <hi rendition="#i">porphyry-granites,</hi> to indicate varieties of structure and as-<lb/>pect, to separate the porphyritic granites from porphyries,<lb/>which, from the frequency of crystals imbedded in the mass,<lb/>presents an aggregational, a true granitic structure. By adopt-<lb/>ing the denominations of granite and gneiss, of syenite and por-<lb/>phyry, of greywacke and porphyry, of limestone and clay-slate,<lb/>no doubt is left regarding the nature of the complex terms of<lb/>the geognostical series <note place="foot" n="*">Translated from Essai Geognostique par Baron Alexandre de Humboldt.</note>.</p><lb/><pb n="239" facs="#f0030" />
<p>M. Humboldt next proceeds to consider the natural history of<lb/>fossil organic remains, as connected with formations. This very<lb/>interesting paper on petrifactions, has already appeared in <bibl>No.<lb/>xvii. of our Journal</bibl>.</p></div></div><lb/></body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>