<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="81" facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <head>M. de Humboldt&#x2019;s <hi rendition="#i">View of the various Productions of the different<lb/>Countries of the Earth.</hi> [Personal Narrative.]</head>
                <lb/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Every</hi> hemisphere produces plants of a different species; and it is not<lb/>by the diversity of climates that we can attempt to explain why equinoctial<lb/>Africa has no laurine&#x00E6;, and the New World no heaths; why the calceolari&#x00E6;<lb/>are found only in the Southern hemisphere; why the birds of the continent<lb/>of India glow with colours less splendid than the birds of the hot parts of<lb/>America; finally, why the tiger is peculiar to Asia, and the ornithorhincus<lb/>to New Holland. In the vegetable, as well as in the animal kingdom, the<lb/>causes of the distribution of the species are among the number of mysteries<lb/>which natural philosophy cannot reach. This science is not occupied in the<lb/>investigation of the origin of beings, but of the laws according to which they<lb/>are distributed on the globe. It examines the things that are, the co-<lb/>existence of vegetable and animal forms, in each latitude, at different<lb/>heights, and at different degrees of temperature; it studies the relations<lb/>under which particular organizations are more vigorously developed, multi-<lb/>plied or modified; but it approaches not problems, the solution of which is<lb/>impossible, since they touch the origin, the first existence of a germ of life.<lb/>We may add, that the attempts that have been made to explain the distri-<lb/>bution of various species on the globe, by the sole influence of climate, date<lb/>at a period when physical geography was still in its infancy; when, recurring<lb/>incessantly to pretended contrasts between the two worlds, it was imagined,<lb/>that the whole of Africa and of America resembled the deserts of Egypt,<lb/>and the marshes of Cayenne. At present, when men judge of the state of<lb/>things not from one type arbitrarily chosen, but from positive knowledge, it<lb/>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">
                        <hi rendition="#g">
                            <hi rendition="#k">vol. xvii.&#x2014;no.</hi>
                        </hi> 97. <hi rendition="#k">m</hi>
                    </fw>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="82" facs="#f0002" /> is ascertained that the two continents, in their immense extent, contain<lb/>countries that are altogether analogous. There are regions of America,<lb/>as barren and burning as the interior of Africa. The islands that produce<lb/>the spices of India are scarcely remarkable for their dryness; and it is not<lb/>on account of the humidity of the climate, as it has been affirmed in recent<lb/>works, that the New Continent is deprived of those fine species of laurine&#x00E6;<lb/>and myristic&#x00E6;, which are found united in one little corner of the earth, in<lb/>the archipelago of India. For some years past, the real cinnamon has been<lb/>cultivated with success in several parts of the New Continent; and a zone<lb/>that produces the coumarouna, the vanilla, the pucheri, the pine-apple,<lb/>the myrtus pimenta, the balsam of tolu, the myroxylon peruvianum, the<lb/>crotons, the citrosmas, the pejoa, the <hi rendition="#i">incienso</hi> of the silla of Caraccas, the<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">quereme,</hi> the pancratium, and so many majestic liliaceous plants, cannot<lb/>be considered as destitute of aromatics. Besides, a dry air favours the<lb/>developement of the aromatic, or exciting properties, only in certain species<lb/>of plants. The most cruel poisons are produced in the most humid zone of<lb/>America: and it is precisely under the influence of the long rains of the<lb/>tropics that the American pimento, capsicum baccatum, the fruit of which<lb/>is often as caustic and fiery as Indian pepper, vegetates best.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>From the whole of these considerations, it follows, 1st, that the new<lb/>continent possesses spices, aromatics, and very active vegetable poisons<lb/>that are peculiar to itself, differing specifically from those of the ancient<lb/>world; 2dly, that the primitive distribution of species in the torrid zone<lb/>cannot be explained by the influence of climate solely, or by the distri-<lb/>bution of temperature, which we observe in the present state of our planet;<lb/>but that this difference of climate leads us to perceive, why a given type of<lb/>organization developes itself more vigorously in such or such local circum-<lb/>stances. We can conceive, that a small number of the families of plants,<lb/>for instance the musace&#x00E6; and the palms, cannot belong to very cold regions,<lb/>on account of their internal structure and the importance of certain organs;<lb/>but we cannot explain why no one of the family of melastomas vegetates<lb/>north of the parallel of thirty degrees, or why no rose tree belongs to the<lb/>southern hemisphere. Analogy of climates is often found in the two conti-<lb/>nents, without identity of productions.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Personal Narrative,</hi> vol. v. p. 180.</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>