<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-09" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>THE TOMB OF A NATION</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">[From Humboldt&#x2019;s Personal Narrative.]</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. Humboldt visited the cavern of Atar-<lb break="no"/>uipe, on the Oroonoko, of which he gives<lb break="yes"/>the following curious account:</p>
                <p>&#x201C;We soon reckoned in this tomb of a<lb break="yes"/>whole extinct tribe near six hundred skele-<lb break="no"/>tons well preserved, and so regularly plac-<lb break="no"/>ed, that it would have been difficult to make<lb break="yes"/>an error in their number. Every skeleton<lb break="yes" />reposes in a sort of basket, made of the pe-<lb break="no"/>ti@ of the palm-tree. These baskets,<lb break="yes"/>which the natives call mapires, have the<lb break="yes"/>form of a square bag. Their size is propor-<lb break="no"/>tioned to the age of the dead ; there are<lb break="yes"/>some for infants cut off at the moment of<lb break="yes"/>their birth. We saw them from ten inches<lb break="yes"/>to three feet four inches long, the skeletons<lb break="yes"/>in them being bent together. They are all<lb break="yes" />ranged near each other, and are so entire,<lb break="yes"/>that not a rib or a phalanx is wanting. The<lb break="yes"/>bones have been prepared in three different<lb break="yes"/>manners, either whitened in the air and the<lb break="yes"/>sun; dyed red with anoto, a coloring matter<lb break="yes" />extracted from the bixa orellana; or like<lb break="yes"/>real mummies, varnished with odoriferous<lb break="yes"/>resins, and enveloped in leaves of the heli-<lb break="no"/>conia or of the plantain tree. The Indians<lb break="yes"/>related to us,that the fresh corpse is plac-<lb break="no"/>ed in damp ground, in order that the flesh<lb break="yes"/>may be consumed by degrees ; some months<lb break="yes"/>after, it is taken out, and the flesh remain-<lb break="no"/>ing on the bones is scraped off with sharp<lb break="yes"/>stones.&#x2014;Several hordes in Guyana still ob-<lb break="no" />serve this custom. Earthen vases half-bak-<lb break="no"/>ed are found near the mapires, or baskets.<lb break="yes"/>They appear to contain the bones of the<lb break="yes"/>same family. The largest of these vases,<lb break="yes" />or funeral urns, are three feet high, and five<lb break="yes"/>feet and a half long. Their color is green-<lb break="no"/>ish gray; and their oval form is sufficiently<lb break="yes"/>pleasing to the eye. The handles are made<lb break="yes"/>in the shape of crocodiles, or serpents; the<lb break="yes" />edge is bordered with meanders, labyrinths,<lb break="yes"/>and real grecques, in straight lines various-<lb break="no"/>ly combined. Such paintings are found in<lb break="yes"/>every zone, among nations the most remote<lb break="yes" />from each other, either with respect to the<lb break="yes"/>spot which they occupy on the globe, or to<lb break="yes"/>the degree of civilization which they have<lb break="yes"/>attained. The inhabitants of the little mis-<lb break="no"/>sion of Maypures still execute them on their<lb break="yes" />commonest pottery; they decorate the buck-<lb break="no"/>lers of the Otaheiteans, the fishing imple-<lb break="no"/>ments of the Eskimaux, the walls of the Me-<lb break="no"/>xican palace of Mitla, and the vases of anci-<lb break="no"/>ent Greece. Every where a rhythmic re-<lb break="no"/>petition of the same forms flatters the eye,<lb break="yes"/>as the @ repetition of sounds soothes<lb break="yes"/>the ear. Analogies founded on the inter-<lb break="no"/>nal nature of our intellect, are not calculat-<lb break="no"/>ed to throw light on the filiation and the<lb break="yes"/>ancient connections of nations.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;We could not acquire any precise idea<lb break="yes"/>of the period to which the origin of the ma-<lb break="no"/>pires and the painted vases, contained in<lb break="yes"/>the ossuary cavern of Ataruipe, can be<lb break="yes"/>traced. The greater part seemed not to be<lb break="yes"/>more than a century old; but it may be sup-<lb break="no"/>posed that, sheltered from all humidity,<lb break="yes"/>under the influence of a uniform tempera-<lb break="no"/>ture. The preservation of these articles<lb break="yes"/>would be no less perfect, if it dated from a<lb break="yes"/>period far more remote. A tradition cir-<lb break="no"/>culates among the Guahiboes, that the war-<lb break="no"/>like Atures, pursued by the Caribbees, es-<lb break="no"/>caped to the rocks that rise in the middle<lb break="yes"/>of the Great Cataracts; and there that na-<lb break="no"/>tion, heretofore so numerous, became gra-<lb break="no"/>dually extinct, as well as its language. The<lb break="yes" />last families of the Atures still existed in<lb break="yes"/>1767, in the time of the missionary Gili.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>At the period of our voyage an old parrot<lb break="yes"/>was shown at Maypures, of which the inha-<lb break="no"/>bitants related, and the fact is worthy of ob-<lb break="no" />servation, that &#x201C;they did not understand<lb break="yes"/>what it said, because it spoke the language<lb break="yes"/>of the Atures.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>&#x201C;We opened, to the great concern of our<lb break="yes"/>guides, several mapires, in order to exa-<lb break="no"/>mine attentively the form of the skulls; they<lb break="yes"/>all displayed the characteristics of the A-<lb break="no"/>merican race, with the exception of two or<lb break="yes" />three, which approached indubitably to the<lb break="yes"/>Caucasian.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;We took several sculls, the skeleton of<lb break="yes"/>a child of six or seven years old, and two of<lb break="yes"/>full-grown men of the nation of the Atures,<lb break="yes"/>from the cavern of Ataruipe. All these bones<lb break="yes"/>partly painted red, partly varnished with<lb break="yes" />odoriferous resins, were placed in the bask-<lb break="no"/>ets (mapires or canastos,) which we have<lb break="yes"/>just described. They made almost the<lb break="yes"/>whole load of a mule; and as we knew the<lb break="yes" />superstitious aversion of the Indians for<lb break="yes"/>dead bodies, when they have given them @-<lb break="no"/>pu@ture, we had carefully enveloped the<lb break="yes"/>canastos in mats recently woven. Unfor-<lb break="no" />tunately for us, the penetration of the In-<lb break="no"/>dians, and the extreme quickness of their<lb break="yes"/>senses, rendered all our precautions useless.<lb break="yes"/>Whenever we stopped, in the missions of<lb break="yes"/>the Caribbees, amid the Llanos, between<lb break="yes" />Angostura and Nueva Barcelona, the na-<lb break="no"/>tives assembled round our mules to admire<lb break="yes"/>the monkeys which we had purchased at the<lb break="yes"/>Oroonoko. These good people had scarcely<cb/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>touched our baggage, when they announced<lb break="yes"/>the approaching death of the beast of bur-<lb break="no"/>den &#x201C;that carried the dead.&#x201D; In vain we<lb break="yes"/>told them that they were deceived in their<lb break="yes"/>conjectures, and that the baskets contained<lb break="yes"/>the bones of crocodiles and manatees; they<lb break="yes" />persisted in repeating, that they smelt the<lb break="yes"/>resin, that surrounded the skeletons, and<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;that they were their old relations.&#x201D; We<lb break="yes"/>were obliged to make the monks interpose<lb break="yes"/>their authority, in order to conquer the a-<lb break="no"/>version of the natives, and procure for us a<lb break="yes" />change of mules.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;One of the sculls, which we took from<lb break="yes"/>the cavern of Ataruipe, has appeared in the<lb break="yes"/>fine work published by my old master, Blu-<lb break="no"/>menbach, on the varieties of the human<lb break="yes"/>species. The skeletons of the Indians were<lb break="yes"/>lost on the coast of Africa, together with a<lb break="yes"/>considerable part of our collections, in a<lb break="yes"/>shipwreck, in which perished our friend and<lb break="yes"/>fellow-traveller, Fray Juan Gonzales, a<lb break="yes"/>young monk of the order of Saint Francis.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;We withdrew in silence from the cavern<lb break="yes"/>of Ataruipe. It was one of those calm and<lb break="yes"/>serene nights which are so common in the<lb break="yes"/>torrid zone. The stars shone with a mild<lb break="yes" />and planetary light. Their scintillation<lb break="yes"/>was scarcely sensible at the horizon, which<lb break="yes"/>seemed illumined by the great nebul&#x00E6; of<lb break="yes"/>the southern hemisphere. An innumera-<lb break="no"/>ble multitude of insects spread a reddish<lb break="yes"/>light upon the ground, loaded with plants, and<lb break="yes"/>resplendent with these living and moving<lb break="yes"/>fires, as if the stars of the firmament had<lb break="yes"/>sunk down on the savannah. On quitting<lb break="yes"/>the cavern, we stopped several times to ad-<lb break="no"/>mire the beauty of this singular scene.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>The odorifurous vanilla, and festoons of<lb break="yes"/>bignonia, decorated the entrance; and a-<lb break="no" />bove, on the summit of the hill, the arrowy<lb break="yes"/>branches of the palm-trees waved murmur-<lb break="no"/>ing in the air.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 