<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On Rock Formations</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:58</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.26</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1822-Independance_des_formations-3</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1822-Independance_des_formations-1.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1822-Independance_des_formations-2.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1822-Independance_des_formations-3.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1822-Independance_des_formations-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1822-Independance_des_formations-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On Rock Formations</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication" from="1824" to="1825">1824</date>
          <pubPlace>Boston, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Boston Journal of Philosophy and the Arts, intended to exhibit a view of the progress of discovery in natural philosophy, mechanics, chemistry, geology and mineralogy, natural history, comparative anatomy and physiology, geography, statistics, and the fine and useful arts&lt;/i&gt; 2:1 (Juli 1824–Juli 1825), S. 15–27; 2:2 (Juli 1824–Juli 1825), S. [105]–118.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Fußnoten mit Asterisken; Schmuck: Kapitälchen; Besonderes: mathematische Sonderzeichen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="15" facs="#f0001" /><lb/><div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">On Rock Formations.</hi> By Baron <hi rendition="#k">Alexander<lb/>Humboldt.</hi> <note place="foot" n="*">Translated from <hi rendition="#i">Essai Géognostique</hi> par Alexandre de Humboldt.</note></head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k"><hi rendition="#in">T</hi>he</hi> word <hi rendition="#i">formation</hi> designates, in Geognosy, either the<lb/>manner in which a rock has been produced, or an assem-<lb/>blage of mineral masses, which are so connected together,<lb/>that they are supposed to have been formed at the same<lb/>period, and present, in the most distant parts of the world,<lb/>the same general relations of situation and position. It is<lb/>thus that the <hi rendition="#i">formation</hi> of obsidian and basalt is attributed to<lb/>subterranean fires; and thus also that we say the formation<lb/>of transition clay-slate contains lydian-stone, chiastolite, alum-<lb/>slate, and alternating beds of black limestone and porphyry.<lb/>The first acceptation of the word is better adapted to the<lb/>genius of the language; but it has relation to the origin of<lb/>things, to an uncertain science founded upon geogonic hypo-<lb/>thesis. The second acceptation, now generally adopted<lb/>by the French mineralogists, has been borrowed from the<lb/>celebrated school of Werner: it indicates what is, not what<lb/>is supposed to have been.</p><lb/><p>In the geognostical description of the globe, we may distin-<lb/>guish different degrees of aggregation of mineral substances,<lb/>simple or compound, according as we rise to more general<lb/>ideas. Rocks which alternate with one another, which are<lb/>usually associated, and which present the same relations of<lb/>position, constitute a <hi rendition="#i">formation</hi>; the union of several forma-<lb/><pb n="16" facs="#f0002" />
tions constitutes a district or <hi rendition="#i">terrain;</hi> but these different terms<lb/>of rocks, Formation and Terrain, are employed as synony-<lb/>mous in many works of geognosy.</p><lb/><p>The diversity of the rocks, and the relative disposition of<lb/>the beds which form the oxidised crust of the earth, have,<lb/>from the most remote times, fixed the attention of men.<lb/>Wherever the working of a mine was directed upon a de-<lb/>posit of salt, of coal, or of clay-iron, which was covered with<lb/>a great number of beds of different natures, it gave rise to<lb/>ideas more or less precise regarding the system of rocks pe-<lb/>culiar to a district of small extent. Furnished with these<lb/>local details, and full of prejudices which arise from custom,<lb/>the miners of a country would disperse themselves over the<lb/>neighbouring districts. They would do what geognosts have<lb/>often done in our days; they would judge of the position<lb/>of rocks of whose nature they were ignorant, according to<lb/>imperfect analogies, according to the circumscribed ideas<lb/>which they had acquired in their native country. This<lb/>error must have had a fatal influence upon the success of<lb/>their new researches. In place of examining the connection<lb/>of two contiguous dictricts, by following some generally ex-<lb/>tended bed,&#x2014;in place of enlarging and extending, so to speak,<lb/>the first <hi rendition="#i">type of formations</hi> which had remained impressed<lb/>upon their minds,&#x2014;they would be persuaded that each por-<lb/>tion of the globe had an entirely different geological consti-<lb/>tution. This very old popular opinion has been adopted and<lb/>supported, in different countries, by very distinguished men;<lb/>but since geognosy has been elevated to the rank of a science,<lb/>the art of interrogating nature brought to perfection, and<lb/>journeys made into distant countries, have presented a more<lb/>exact comparison of different districts, great and immutable<lb/>laws have been discovered in the structure of the globe, and<lb/>in the superposition of rocks. Since, then, the most striking<lb/>analogies of situation, of composition, and of organic bodies<lb/>contained in contemporaneous beds, have manifested them-<lb/>selves in the two worlds, in proportion as we become accus-<lb/>tomed to consider the formations under a more general<lb/>point of view, even their <hi rendition="#i">identity</hi> becomes every day more<lb/>probable.</p><lb/><p>In fact, on examining the solid mass of our planet, we per-<lb/>ceive that some of those substances with which oryctognosy<lb/>(descriptive mineralogy), makes us acquainted in their indi-<lb/>vidual capacities, are met with in <hi rendition="#i">constant associations</hi>, and<lb/>that these associations, which are designed by the name of<lb/>Compound Rocks, do not vary like organic beings, accord-<lb/><pb n="17" facs="#f0003" />
    ing to the differences of the latitudes, or of the isothermal<lb/>lines in which they occur. The geognosts who have travel-<lb/>led over the most remote countries, have not only met in the<lb/>two hemispheres with the same simple substances, quartz,<lb/>felspar, mica, garnet or hornblende; but they have also found<lb/>that the great mountain masses present almost every where<lb/>the same rocks, that is to say, the same assemblages of mica,<lb/>quartz, and felspar in the granite; of mica, quartz, and gar-<lb/>nets in the mica-slate; of felspar and hornblende in the<lb/>syenite. If it has sometimes been thought at first that a<lb/>rock belonged exclusively to a single portion of the globe, it<lb/>has been constantly found by later researches, in regions the<lb/>most remote from its first locality. We are tempted to admit<lb/>that the formation of rocks has been independent of the diver-<lb/>sity of climates; that perhaps it has even been anterior to<lb/>them, (<bibl>Humboldt, <hi rendition="#i">Geographie des Plantes,</hi> 1807, p. 115</bibl>; <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Vues<lb/>des Cordilleres,</hi> vol. i. p. 122</bibl>). Rocks are found to be iden-<lb/>tical where organic beings have undergone the most varied<lb/>modifications.</p><lb/><p>But this identity of composition, this analogy which is ob-<lb/>served in the association of certain simple mineral substances,<lb/>might be independent of the analogy of relative situation and<lb/>of superposition. One may have brought from the <placeName>islands of<lb/>the Pacific Ocean</placeName>, or from the <placeName>Cordilleras of the Andes</placeName>, the<lb/>same rocks which are observed in <placeName>Europe</placeName>, without his being<lb/>permitted to conclude that these rocks are superimposed in<lb/>the same manner, and that after the discovery of one of them<lb/>it might be predicted with some degree of certainty what are<lb/>the other rocks which occur in the same places. It is to dis-<lb/>cover these analogies of situation <choice><sic>aud</sic><corr type="editorial">and</corr></choice> relative position, that<lb/>the labours of geognosts should tend, who delight to investi-<lb/>gate the laws of inorganic nature. In the following tables,<lb/>we have attempted to unite all that is known with certainty,<lb/>regarding the superposition of rocks in the <placeName>two Continents</placeName>,<lb/>to the north and south of the <placeName>Equator</placeName>. These <hi rendition="#i">types of forma-<lb/>tions</hi> will not only be extended, but also variously modified,<lb/>in proportion as the number of travellers qualified to make<lb/>geognostical observations shall become increased, and as<lb/>complete monographs of different districts at great distances<lb/>from each other shall furnish more precise results.</p><lb/><p>The exposition of the laws observed in the superposition of<lb/>rocks, forms the most solid part of the science of geognosy.<lb/>It must not be denied, that the observations of geognostical<lb/>situation often present great difficulties, when the point of<lb/>contact of two neighbouring formations cannot be reached,<lb/><pb n="18" facs="#f0004" />
        or when they do not present a regular stratification, or when<lb/>their relative situation is not <hi rendition="#i">uniform</hi>, that is to say, when the<lb/>strata of the upper deposits are not parallel to the strata of<lb/>the lower. But these difficulties (and this is one of the great<lb/>advantages of observations which embrace a considerable<lb/>part of our planet), diminish in number, or disappear entirely,<lb/>on comparing several districts of great extent. The super-<lb/>position and relative age of rocks, are facts susceptible of<lb/>being established immediately, like the structure of the organs<lb/>of a vegetable, like the proportions of elements in chemical<lb/>analysis, or like the elevation of a mountain above the level<lb/>of the sea. True geognosy makes known the outer crust of<lb/>the globe, such as it exists at the present day. It is a science<lb/>as capable of certainty as any of the physical descriptive sci-<lb/>ences can be. On the other hand, all that relates to the ancient<lb/>state of our planet, to those fluids which, it is said, held all<lb/>the mineral substances in a state of revolution, to those seas<lb/>which we have raised to the summit of the <placeName>Cordilleras</placeName>, to<lb/>make them again disappear, is as uncertain as are the forma-<lb/>tion of the atmosphere of planets, the migrations of vegetables,<lb/>and the origin of different varieties of our species. Yet the<lb/>period is not very remote when geologists occupied themselves<lb/>by preference with the solution of these almost impossible<lb/>problems, with those fabulous times of the physical history<lb/>of our planet.</p><lb/><p>In order to render the principles better understood, accord-<lb/>ing to which the following <hi rendition="#i">table of the superposition of rocks</hi> is<lb/>constructed, it becomes necessary to premise observations<lb/>furnished by the practical examination of different districts.<lb/>We shall begin with remarking, that it is not easy to circum-<lb/>scribe the limits of a formation. The Jura limestone and the<lb/>Alpine limestone, which are separated to a great distance in<lb/>one country, sometimes appear closely connected in another.<lb/>What announces the independence of a formation, as has<lb/>been very justly observed by M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Buch</persName>, is its immediate<lb/>superposition upon rocks of a different nature, and which<lb/>consequently ought to be considered as more ancient. The<lb/>red sandstone is an independent formation, because it is super-<lb/>imposed indifferently upon black (transition) limestone, upon<lb/>mica-slate, or upon primitive granites; but in a country where<lb/>the great formation of syenite and porphyry predominates,<lb/>these two rocks constantly alternate. There results that the<lb/>syenite rock is dependent upon the porphyry, and scarcely<lb/>any where covers by itself the transition clay-slate or primi-<lb/>tive gneiss. The independence of formations does not, be-<lb/><pb n="19" facs="#f0005" />
            sides, by any means exclude the <hi rendition="#i">uniformity</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">concordance of<lb/>position;</hi> it rather excludes the oryctognostic passage of two<lb/>superimposed formations. The transition districts have very<lb/>often the same direction and the same inclination as the primi-<lb/>tive ones; and yet, whatever approximation there may be<lb/>between their origin, we are not the less warranted to con-<lb/>sider the anthracitic mica-slate or the grey-wacke, alternating<lb/>with porphyry, as two formations independent of the primi-<lb/>tive granites and gneisses which they cover. The confor-<lb/>mity of position is in no way incompatible with the indepen-<lb/>dence of formations, that is to say, it does not prevent the<lb/>right which one has of regarding a rock as a distinct forma-<lb/>tion. It is because the independent formations are placed<lb/>indifferently on all the older rocks, (the chalk upon the<lb/>granite, the red sandstone upon the primitive mica-slate), that<lb/>the assemblage of a great number of observations made upon<lb/>very distant points, becomes eminently useful in the deter-<lb/>mination of the <hi rendition="#i">relative age</hi> of rocks. In order to determine<lb/>that the zircon-sienite is a transition rock, it must have been<lb/>seen resting upon formations posterior to the black lime-<lb/>stone with orthoceratites. Observations made upon the por-<lb/>phyries and sienites of <placeName>Hungary</placeName> by M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Beudant</persName>, one of the<lb/>most distinguished geologists of the present times, may throw<lb/>much light upon the formations of the <placeName>Mexican Andes</placeName>. It<lb/>is thus that a new vegetable discovered in India, elucidated<lb/>the natural affinity between two families of plants belonging<lb/>to <placeName>Equinoctial America</placeName>.</p><lb/><p>The order which has been followed in the table of forma-<lb/>tions, is that of the situation and relative position of rocks.<lb/>I do not pretend that this position is observed in all the<lb/>countries of the globe; I merely point it out such as it has<lb/>appeared the most probable, after the comparison of a great<lb/>number of facts which I have collected. It is by the idea of<lb/>the relative age of formation, that I have been guided in this<lb/>work, imperfect as it still is. I had begun it long before my<lb/>journey to the <placeName>Cordilleras of the New Continent</placeName>, from the<lb/>year 1792, when, on leaving the <placeName>Freyberg</placeName> School, I was ap-<lb/>pointed to the direction of the Mines in the mountains of the<lb/><placeName>Fichtelgebirge</placeName>. The same rock may vary in composition,<lb/>integrant parts may have been abstracted, and new sub-<lb/>stances may occur disseminated, without the rock&#x2019;s changing<lb/>its denomination in the eyes of the geognost who is engaged<lb/>with the superposition of formations. Under the equator, as<lb/>in the <placeName>north of Europe</placeName>, strata of a true transition syenite lose<lb/>their hornblende, without the mass becoming another rock.<lb/><pb n="20" facs="#f0006" />
                The granites of the banks of the <placeName>Orinoco</placeName> sometimes assume<lb/>hornblende as an integral part, and yet do not cease to be<lb/>primitive granite, although this may not be of the first or<lb/>oldest formation. These facts have been observed by all<lb/>practical geologists. The essential character of the identity<lb/>of an independent formation is its relative position, the place<lb/>which it occupies in the general series of formations. (See<lb/>the classical Memoir of M. <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Buch</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Ueber den Begriff einer,</hi><lb/>in the <hi rendition="#i">Mag. der Naturf.,</hi> 1810, p. 128&#x2014;133</bibl>.) It is on this<lb/>account that an isolated fragment, a specimen of rock found<lb/>in a collection, cannot be determined geognostically, that is<lb/>to say, it cannot be referred with certainty to a particular<lb/>formation, constituting one of the numerous beds of which the<lb/>crust of our planet is composed. The presence of chiastolite,<lb/>the accumulation of carbon or nodules of compact limestone<lb/>in the clay-slates, nigrine and epidote in the syenites, (alter-<lb/>nating with granite and porphyries), conglomerates or pud-<lb/>ding-stones, having a basis of anthracitic mica-slate, may,<lb/>without doubt, be characteristic of transition formations; in<lb/>the same way as, according to the useful labours of M.<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>, petrifactions of shells, in a good state of pre-<lb/>servation, sometimes indicate directly such or such a bed of<lb/>tertiary deposits. But these cases, where we are guided by<lb/>disseminated substances or by characters purely geological,<lb/>comprehend but a small number of rocks of a recent origin,<lb/>and observations of this kind often lead only to negative facts.<lb/>The characters taken from the colour, from the grain, and<lb/>from small veins of carbonate of lime, which traverse calca-<lb/>reous rocks; those which are furnished by the fissility and<lb/>silky lustre of clay-slate, the aspect and undulations more or<lb/>less marked of the scales of mica in mica-slate; and, lastly,<lb/>the size and colouring of the crystals of felspar in the granites<lb/>of different formations, may, like all that is connected simply<lb/>with the <hi rendition="#i">physiognomy</hi> of minerals, lead the most expert ob-<lb/>server into error. The white and black tints undoubtedly<lb/>in most instances distinguish the primitive and transition lime-<lb/>stones; the <placeName>Jura</placeName> formation, especially in its upper beds, is<lb/>also without doubt generally divided into thin whitish beds,<lb/>having a dull, even, or conchoidal fracture, with very flat<lb/>cavities: but in the mountains of transition limestone there<lb/>are isolated masses which, in colour and texture, resemble<lb/>the oryctognostic characters of the Jura limestone; and to<lb/>the <placeName>south of the Alps</placeName> there are hills belonging to tertiary<lb/>deposits, where we find rocks analogous to the slaty and dull<lb/>Jura limestone (in as far as regards appearance), in formations<lb/><pb n="21" facs="#f0007" />
    placed above the chalk, and which resemble the limestone<lb/>used for lithographic purposes. Were names taken from<lb/>their oryctognostical characters alone to be preferred in dis-<lb/>tinguishing formations, the different strata of the same com-<lb/>pound rock having a considerable thickness, and extended to<lb/>a great length in a particular direction, would often seem to<lb/>belong to different rocks, according to the points at which<lb/>specimens were taken. Consequently we can only determine<lb/>geognostically in collections, <hi rendition="#i">suites of rocks</hi> of which the mu-<lb/>tual superposition is known.</p><lb/><p>In announcing these ideas regarding the sense which should<lb/>be attached to the words <hi rendition="#i">independent formations</hi>, when treating<lb/>of the order of their position, we are very far from under-<lb/>valuing the eminent services which the most rigorous oryc-<lb/>tognostic examination, the minute investigation of the com-<lb/>position of rocks, have rendered to modern geognosy, and<lb/>especially to the knowledge of the relative position of forma-<lb/>tions. Although, according to the discoveries of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Haüy</persName>,<lb/>regarding the intimate nature of inorganic and crystallized<lb/>substances, there does not exist, properly speaking, a passage<lb/>or transition of one mineral species to another; (<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Cordier</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">sur<lb/>les Roches volcan.</hi>, p. 33</bibl>, and <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Berzelius</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Nouv. Syst. de Mineral</hi>,<lb/>p. 119</bibl>) the passages of <hi rendition="#i">masses or pastes of rocks</hi>, are not limited<lb/>to formations which are commonly distinguished by the name<lb/>of Compound Rocks. Those which are thought simple, for<lb/>example, the transition or secondary limestones, are partly<lb/>amorphous varieties of mineral species, of which there exists<lb/>a crystallized type, partly of aggregates of clay, carbon, &amp;c.,<lb/>which cannot be submitted to any fixed determination. It is<lb/>upon the variable proportions of these heterogeneous mix-<lb/>tures, that the passage of marly limestones to other schistose<lb/>formations is founded. (<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Haüy</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Tableau comparatif de la Cris-<lb/>tallographie</hi>, p. 27&#x2014;30</bibl>). All the amorphous pastes of rocks,<lb/>however homogenous they appear at first sight, the bases of<lb/>porphyries and euphotides (serpentines), as well as those<lb/>problematical black masses which constitute the <hi rendition="#i">basanite</hi><lb/>(basalt) of the ancients, and which are not all greenstones<lb/>surcharged with hornblende, are susceptible of being sub-<lb/>jected to mechanical analysis. M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Cordier</persName> has applied this<lb/>analysis in an ingenious manner to the diabases, dolerites,<lb/>and other more recent volcanic productions. The most ap-<lb/>parently minute oryctognostic examination, cannot be indif-<lb/>ferent to the geognost who examines the age of formations.<lb/>It is by this examination that we are enabled to form a just<lb/>idea of the progressive manner in which, by <hi rendition="#i">internal develop-</hi><lb/><pb n="22" facs="#f0008" />
        <hi rendition="#i">ment</hi>, that is to say, by a very gradual change in the proportions<lb/>of the elements of the <hi rendition="#i">mass</hi>, the passage is made from one<lb/>rock to a neighbouring. The transition slates, whose struc-<lb/>ture appears at first so different from that of the granites or<lb/>porphyries, present to the attentive observer striking exam-<lb/>ples of insensible passages to granular rocks of porphyritic<lb/>or granitic nature. These slates become at first greenish and<lb/>harder. In proportion as the amorphous paste receives horn-<lb/>blende, it passes into those hornblendic traps which in former<lb/>times were confounded with basalt. In other cases, the mica,<lb/>which is at first concealed in the amorphous paste, becomes<lb/>developed, and separates into distinct and clearly crystallized<lb/>spangles; at the same time, the felspar and quartz become<lb/>visible; and the mass assumes a granular aspect, with very<lb/>elongated grains: this is a true transition gneiss. By degrees,<lb/>the grains lose their common direction; the crystals arrange<lb/>themselves around many centres; the rock becomes a transi-<lb/>tion granite or syenite. In other cases, the quartz alone is<lb/>developed; it augments, and becomes rounded into nodules,<lb/>and the slate passes to the best characterized grey-wackes.<lb/>By these certain signs, geognosts, to whom the appearances of<lb/>nature have become familiar by long examination, become<lb/>aware beforehand of the proximity of granular, granitic, and<lb/>arenaceous rocks. Analogous passages of primitive mica-<lb/>slate to a porphyritic rock, and the return of this rock to<lb/>gneiss, are observed in the <placeName>eastern parts of Switzerland</placeName>.<lb/>(See the luminous developments given by M. <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Raumer</persName>,<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Fragments</hi>, p. 10, and 47</bibl>; M. <bibl>Leopold de Buch, in his <hi rendition="#i">Voyage<lb/>de Glaris à Chiavenna, fait en</hi> 1803, and inserted in the <hi rendition="#i">Magaz.<lb/>der Berl. Naturf.</hi>, vol. iii. p. 115</bibl>). But these passages are not<lb/>always insensible and progressive; the rocks often also suc-<lb/>ceed each other quickly, and in a very abrupt manner; often<lb/>(for example, at <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, between <placeName>Guanaxuato</placeName> and <placeName>Ovexeras</placeName>),<lb/>the limits between the slates, the porphyries and syenites, are<lb/>as distinct as the limits between the porphyries and lime-<lb/>stones; but even in this case, geognostical relations with the<lb/>superimposed rocks are indicated by additional heterogeneous<lb/>beds. It is thus that the transition granite of the syenitic for-<lb/>mation presents beds of basanite, by becoming charged with<lb/>hornblende: it is thus, also, that these same granites some-<lb/>times pass to euphotide. (<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Buch</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Voyages en Norwege</hi>, vol. i.<lb/>p. 138, vol. ii. p. 83</bibl>).</p><lb/><p>There results from these considerations, that the mechanical<lb/>analysis of amorphous pastes, by means of demi-triturations,<lb/>and washings, (an analysis of which, M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Fleuriau de Bellevue</persName><lb/><pb n="23" facs="#f0009" />
            made the first attempt, that was crowned with success: <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Journ.<lb/>de Physique</hi>, vol. li. p. 162</bibl>), throws light at once, 1<hi rendition="#i">st</hi>, Upon<lb/>the large crystals which are isolated and separated from the<lb/>microscopic crystals entangled in the <hi rendition="#i">mass</hi>; 2<hi rendition="#i">dly</hi>, On the<lb/>mutual passages of some rocks, superimposed the one upon<lb/>the other; 3<hi rendition="#i">dly</hi>, On the subordinate beds, which are of the<lb/>same nature as one of the elements of the amorphous mass.<lb/>All these phenomena are produced, if we may so speak, by<lb/>internal development; by variation in the constituent parts<lb/>of a heterogeneous mass. Crystalline molecules, invisible<lb/>to the eye, occur enlarged and disengaged from the compact<lb/>tissue of the paste; by their assemblage and mixture with<lb/>new substances, they insensibly become intercalated beds of<lb/>considerable thickness; and not unfrequently they even be-<lb/>come new rocks.</p><lb/><p>It is the intercalated beds which especially merit the<lb/>greatest attention. (<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Leonhard</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Kopp</persName>, and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">G&#x00E6;rtner</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Prop&#x00E6;d.<lb/>der Miner.</hi>, p. 158</bibl>.) When two formations succeed each other<lb/>immediately, it happens that the beds of the one begin at first<lb/>to alternate with the beds of the other, until (after these pre-<lb/>cursors of a great change) the newest formation shows itself<lb/>without any mixture of subordinate beds. (<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Buch</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Geogn.<lb/>Beob.</hi> vol. i. p. 104, 156</bibl>; <bibl>Humboldt, <hi rendition="#i">Rel. Hist.</hi> vol. ii. p. 140</bibl>).<lb/>The progressive developments of the elements of a rock, may,<lb/>consequently, have a great degree of influence upon the rela-<lb/>tive position of the mineral masses. Their effects belong to<lb/>the province of geology; but, in order to discover and<lb/>appreciate them, the observer must call to his assistance<lb/>oryctognosy.</p><lb/><p>In exposing the intimate relations by which we often see<lb/>the phenomena of <hi rendition="#i">composition</hi> connected with those of rela-<lb/>tive <hi rendition="#i">situation</hi>, it has not been my intention to speak of the<lb/>purely oryctognostic method, which considers rocks accord-<lb/>ing to the analogy of their composition alone. (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Journal des<lb/>Mines</hi>, vol. xxxiv., No. 199</bibl>). In the classifications of this<lb/>method, abstraction is made of every idea of superposition;<lb/>but they do not the less give rise to interesting observations<lb/>regarding the constant assemblage of certain minerals. A<lb/>purely oryctognostic classification, multiplies the names of<lb/>rocks more than is required by geognosy, when occupied<lb/>with superposition alone. According to the changes which<lb/>the mixed rocks undergo, a stratum of great extent and<lb/>thickness may contain (we must repeat it here) parts to<lb/>which the oryctognost, who classes rocks according to their<lb/>composition, would give entirely different denominations.<lb/><pb n="24" facs="#f0010" />
                These remarks have not escaped the learned author of the<lb/><hi rendition="#i"><bibl>Classification Mineralogique des Roches</bibl>;</hi> they must have pre-<lb/>sented themselves to an experienced geognost, who has so<lb/>successfully investigated the superposition of the deposits of<lb/>which he has treated. &#x201C;We must not confound,&#x201D; says M.<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>, in his late <bibl>Memoir on the position of the Ophi-<lb/>olites</bibl>, &#x201C;the relative positions, the orders of superposition of<lb/>the deposites and of the rocks which compose them, with<lb/>purely mineralogical descriptions. The neglect of making<lb/>the proper distinction in this case, would necessarily be pro-<lb/>ductive of confusion in the science, and would retard its<lb/>progress.&#x201D; The arrangement which we give at the end of<lb/>this article, is by no means what is called a classification of<lb/>rocks; there will not even be found united, under the title<lb/>of particular sections (as in the old geognostical method of<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Werner</persName>, or in the excellent <hi rendition="#i"><bibl>Traité de Geognosie</bibl></hi> of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">D&#x2019;Au-<lb/>buisson</persName>), all the primitive formations of granite, nor all the<lb/>secondary formations of sandstone and limestone. It has<lb/>been attempted, on the contrary, to place each rock as it<lb/>occurs in nature, according to the order of its superposition<lb/>or of its respective age. The different formations of granite<lb/>are separated by gneisses, mica-slates, black-limestones, and<lb/>grey-wackes. In the transition rocks, we have separated<lb/>the formations of porphyries and syenites of <placeName>Mexico</placeName> and<lb/><placeName>Peru</placeName>, which are anterior to the grey-wacke, and to the lime-<lb/>stone with orthoceratites, from the much more recent forma-<lb/>tion of the zircon-porphyries and syenites of <placeName>Scandinavia</placeName>.<lb/>In the secondary rocks, we have separated the oolitic sand-<lb/>stone of Nebra, which is posterior to the alpine limestone or<lb/>zechstein, from the red-sandstone, which belongs to the same<lb/>formation with the secondary porphyry and amygdaloid.<lb/>According to the principle which we follow, the same names<lb/>of rocks occur several times in the same table. Anthracitic<lb/>mica-slate is separated, by a great number of older forma-<lb/>tions, from the mica-slate anterior to the primitive clay-slate.</p><lb/><p>Instead of a classification of granitic, schistose, calcareous<lb/>and arenaceous rocks, it has been my object to present a<lb/>sketch of the geognostical structure of the globe; a table in<lb/>which the superimposed rocks succeed each other, from be-<lb/>law upwards, as in those <hi rendition="#i">ideal sections</hi> which I designed in<lb/>1804, for the benefit of the <hi rendition="#i">Mexican School of Mines</hi>, and of<lb/>which many copies have been distributed since my return to<lb/><placeName>Europe</placeName>. (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Bosquejo de una Pasigrafia geognostica, con tablas<lb/>que ensenan la estratificacion y el <choice><sic>paiallelismo</sic><corr type="editorial">parallelismo</corr></choice> de las rocas en<lb/>ambos Continentes, para el uso del Real Seminario de Mineria de</hi><lb/><pb n="25" facs="#f0011" />
                    <hi rendition="#i"><placeName>Mexico</placeName></hi></bibl>). These Pasigraphic tables united to my own obser-<lb/>vations made in <placeName>both Americas</placeName> what had at that period been<lb/>known with precision regarding the relative position of the<lb/>primitive, intermediary and secondary rocks in the <placeName>Old<lb/>Continent</placeName>. They presented, together with the type which<lb/>might be considered as the most general, the secondary<lb/>types, that is to say, the beds which I have named <hi rendition="#i">parallel</hi>.<lb/>This same method has been followed in the work which I<lb/>now publish. My parallel formations are geognostical <hi rendition="#i">equiva-<lb/>lents;</hi> they are rocks which represent each other. (See<lb/>the <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Traité de Geologie de M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">d&#x2019;Aubuisson</persName></hi>, vol. ii. p. 255</bibl>).<lb/>In <placeName>England</placeName>, and on the opposite Continent, there does not<lb/>exist an identity of all the formations: there exist equivalents<lb/>or parallel formations. That of our coal situated between<lb/>the transition masses and the red-sandstone, the position of<lb/>the rock-salt which occurs on the Continent in the alpine<lb/>limestone, and the position of our oolites in the Nebra sand-<lb/>stone and Jura limestone, may guide the geognost in the<lb/>approximation of remote formations. In <placeName>England</placeName>, we ob-<lb/>serve the coals placed upon transition formations; for exam-<lb/>ple, upon the mountain-limestone of <placeName>Derbyshire</placeName> and of <placeName>South<lb/>Wales</placeName>, and upon the transition sandstone, or old red-sandstone<lb/>of <placeName>Herefordshire</placeName>. I have thought that I recognized in the<lb/>magnesian-limestone the red marl, the lias and white oolites<lb/>of <placeName>Bath</placeName>, the <hi rendition="#i">united formations</hi> of the alpine limestone, of the<lb/>oolitic sandstone and Jura limestone. In comparing the for-<lb/>mations of countries more or less distant from each other,<lb/>those of <placeName>England</placeName> and of <placeName>France</placeName>, for instance, of <placeName>Mexico</placeName> and<lb/><placeName>Hungary</placeName>, of the secondary basin of <placeName>Santa Fe de Bogota</placeName> and<lb/>of <placeName>Thuringia</placeName>, we must not think of opposing to each individual<lb/>rock a <hi rendition="#i">parallel</hi> one; it must be recollected, that a single for-<lb/>mation may <hi rendition="#i">represent</hi> several others. It is according to this<lb/>principle that beds of clay, lying beneath the chalk, may, in<lb/><placeName>France</placeName>, be separated in the most distinct manner from the<lb/>oolitic limestone beds: while in <placeName>Switzerland</placeName>, in <placeName>Germany</placeName>,<lb/>and in <placeName>South America</placeName>, they have for <hi rendition="#i">equivalents</hi> beds of marls<lb/>subordinate to the Jura limestone. The gypsums, which, in<lb/>one district, are sometimes only intercalated beds in the<lb/>alpine limestone or oolitic sandstone, in another district, as-<lb/>sume all the appearance of independent formations, and<lb/>occur interposed between the alpine limestone and the oolitic<lb/>sandstone, between this sandstone and the muschelkalk. The<lb/>learned <placeName>Oxford</placeName> Professor, Mr. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Buckland</persName>, whose extensive<lb/>researches have been equally useful to the geognosts of<lb/><placeName>England</placeName> and of the <placeName>Continent</placeName>, has lately published a table<lb/><pb n="26" facs="#f0012" />
                    of parallel formations, or, as he calls them, <hi rendition="#i">equivalents of<lb/>rocks</hi>, which only extends from the 44th to the 54th degree<lb/>of north latitude, but which merits the greatest attention.<lb/>(<bibl><hi rendition="#i">On the Structure of the Alps, and their relation with the rocks of<lb/>England,</hi> 1821</bibl>.)</p><lb/><p>As in the history of ancient nations, it is easier to verify<lb/>the series of events in each country, than to determine their<lb/>mutual coincidence; so also more accuracy can be attained<lb/>in estimating the superposition of formations in isolated re-<lb/>gions, than in determining the relative age or parallelism of<lb/>formations which belong to different systems of rocks. Even<lb/>in countries which are not widely separated, in <placeName>France</placeName>, in<lb/><placeName>Switzerland</placeName>, and in <placeName>Germany</placeName>, it is not easy to fix the relative<lb/>antiquity of the muschelkalk, of the molasse of <placeName>Argovie</placeName>, and<lb/>of the quadersandstein of the <placeName>Hartz</placeName>; because rocks of gen-<lb/>eral occurrence are here most commonly wanting, which,<lb/>according to the happy expression of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Grüner</persName>, serve as<lb/>a <hi rendition="#i">geognostical horizon</hi>, and with which we might compare the<lb/>three formations in question. When rocks are not in imme-<lb/>diate contact, we can only judge of their parallelism by the<lb/>relations of age existing between them and other formations<lb/>by which they are united.</p><lb/><p>These inquiries of <hi rendition="#i">comparative geognosy</hi>, will long occupy<lb/>the sagacity of observers; and it is not surprising that those<lb/>who set out with the idea of retracing each formation in all<lb/>the individuality of its relative position, interior structure,<lb/>and subordinate beds, should finish with utterly denying all<lb/>analogy of superposition. I had the advantage of visiting,<lb/>previous to my journey to the Equator, a great part of <placeName>Ger-<lb/>many</placeName>, of <placeName>France</placeName>, of <placeName>Switzerland</placeName>, of <placeName>England</placeName>, of <placeName>Italy</placeName>, of<lb/><placeName>Poland</placeName>, and of <placeName>Spain</placeName>. During these excursions, my attention<lb/>was particularly directed to the relative position of forma-<lb/>tions, a phenomenon which I calculated upon discussing in a<lb/>special work. On my arrival in <placeName>South America</placeName>, and while at<lb/>first traversing in different directions the vast deposites which<lb/>stretch from the maritime chain of <placeName>Venezuela</placeName> to the basin of<lb/>the <placeName>Amazon</placeName>, I was singularly struck with the conformity of<lb/>position which the <placeName>two Continents</placeName> present. (See my first<lb/>sketch of a <bibl>Geological Table of Equinoctial America, in the<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Journal de Phys.</hi>, vol. liii. p. 38</bibl>). Subsequent observations,<lb/>which included the <placeName>Cordilleras of Mexico</placeName>, of <placeName>New Grenada</placeName>,<lb/>of <placeName>Quito</placeName>, and of <placeName>Peru</placeName>, from the 21st degree of north latitude<lb/>to the 12th degree of south latitude, have confirmed these<lb/>first perceptions. But in speaking of analogies which are<lb/>observed in the relative position of rocks, and of the unifor-<lb/><pb n="27" facs="#f0013" />
                        mity of those laws which reveal to us the order of Nature, I<lb/>might adduce a testimony otherwise of more weight than<lb/>mine, that of the great geognost whose works have thrown<lb/>the greatest light upon the structure of our globe. M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Leo-<lb/>pold de Buch</persName> has pushed his researches from the <placeName>Archipelago<lb/>of the Canary Isles</placeName> to beyond the Polar Circle to the 71st de-<lb/>gree of latitude. He has discovered new formations situated<lb/>between others already known; and, in the primitive as in<lb/>the transition deposites, in the secondary as well as in the<lb/>volcanic, he has been struck with the great features by which<lb/>the table of formations is characterized in the most distant<lb/>regions.</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#c">(To be continued.)</hi></p></div><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<pb n="105" facs="#f0014" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">On Rock Formations.</hi> By <hi rendition="#k">Baron Alexander Hum-<lb/>boldt.</hi> [<hi rendition="#i">Edin. Jour.</hi>]<lb/>[Concluded from page 21.]</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k"><hi rendition="#in">F</hi>rom</hi> that scepticism which would deny the existence of<lb/>any kind of regular order in the position of rocks, it is proper<lb/>to distinguish an opinion which has sometimes found supporters<lb/>among experienced observers. According to this opinion, the<lb/>formations of gneiss-granite, of greywacke, of alpine limestone,<lb/>and of chalk, which have a uniform superposition in different<lb/>countries, do not very well correspond among themselves as to<lb/>the age of the homonymous elements of each series. It is<lb/>thought that a secondary rock may have been formed on one<lb/>spot of the globe, while transition rocks did not yet exist on<lb/>another spot. In this supposition, no allusion is<choice><sic> is</sic><corr type="editorial"></corr></choice> had to those<lb/>granitic rocks which are found lying above limestone con-<lb/>taining orthoceratites, and which are consequently newer<lb/>than the primitive rocks. It is a fact generally admitted at<lb/>this day, that formations of <hi rendition="#i">analogous composition</hi> have been<lb/>repeatedly deposited at epochs far removed from each other.<lb/>The doubt which we are now considering, (though we do not<lb/>partake in it), bears on a point much less clearly established,&#x2014;<lb/>the ascertaining whether certain mica-slate rocks, evidently<lb/>situated in the midst of a country of primitive rocks, and<lb/><pb n="106" facs="#f0015" />
        placed below those in which the vestiges of organic life begin<lb/>to appear, are newer than the secondary rocks of another<lb/>country. I confess, that, in the part of the globe which I have<lb/>had an opportunity of examining, I have not seen any thing<lb/>that might tend to confirm this opinion. Granular syenitic<lb/>rocks repeated twice, perhaps even three times, in primitive<lb/>intermediary (and secondary) deposits, are analogous phe-<lb/>nomena with which we have become acquainted within these<lb/>fifteen years. This disagreement in regard to age of great<lb/>homonymous formations, does not by any means seem to me<lb/>to be proved as yet by direct observations, made upon the<lb/>contact of superimposed formations. The chalk or Jura lime-<lb/>stone may, on one hand, immediately cover primitive granite,<lb/>and, on the other, be separated from it by numerous secondary<lb/>and transition rocks: these very common facts demonstrate<lb/>only the abstraction, the absence, or non-development of seve-<lb/>ral intermediary members of the geognostical series. The<lb/>greywacke may, on one hand, dip beneath a felspar rock, or<lb/>rock of which felspar forms a principal constituent; for ex-<lb/>ample, beneath transition granite or zircon syenite; and, on<lb/>the other hand, be superimposed upon the black limestone<lb/>containing madrepores; but this position shows only the inter-<lb/>colation of a bed of greywacke between felspar rocks. Since<lb/>the minute investigation of fossil organic bodies has, through<lb/>the important labours of Messrs <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Cuvier</persName> and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>, dif-<lb/>fused a new life as it were in the study of the tertiary forma-<lb/>tions, the discovery of the same fossils in analogous beds of<lb/>very distant countries, has rendered the isochronism of very<lb/>generally extended formations still more probable.</p><lb/><p>It is this isochronism alone, this admirable order of succes-<lb/>sion, which seems given to man to investigate with some degree<lb/>of certainty. The attempts which theological geologists have<lb/>made to subject the periods to absolute measurements of time,<lb/>and to connect the chronology of ancient cosmogonic narra-<lb/>tions with the observations of nature, could not possibly have<lb/>been productive of satisfactory results. &#x201C;It has been more<lb/>than once,&#x201D; says M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Ramond</persName>, in a discourse replete with<lb/>philosophical views, &#x201C;thought that a supplement to our short<lb/>annals might be found in the monuments of Nature. There<lb/>is, however, enough of historical ages, to let us see that the<lb/>succession of physical and moral events, is not regulated by<lb/>the uniform progress of time, and could not consequently give<lb/>it measure. We see behind us a series of creations and de-<lb/>structions, by means of the strata of which the crust of the<lb/>earth is composed. They give rise to the idea of so many<lb/><pb n="107" facs="#f0016" />
            distinct periods; but these periods, so fertile in events, may<lb/>have been very short, in comparison with the number and<lb/>importance of the results. Between the creations and de-<lb/>structions, on the other hand, we see nothing, however vast<lb/>the intervals may be. There, where all is lost in the void of<lb/>undetermined antiquity, the degrees of relative age have no<lb/>appreciable value; because the succession of phenomena has<lb/>no longer the scale which relates to the division of time.&#x201D;<lb/>(<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Mémoires de l&#x2019;Institut, for the year</hi> 1815, <hi rendition="#i">p.</hi> 47</bibl>.)</p><lb/><p>In the geognostical monography of a deposit of small extent,<lb/>for example, the environs of a city, one cannot distinguish with<lb/>sufficient minuteness the different beds which compose the local<lb/>formations, shelving banks of sand and clay, the subdivisions<lb/>of gypsums, the strata of marly and oölitic limestone, desig-<lb/>nated in <placeName>England</placeName> by the names of Purbeck Beds, Portland<lb/>Stone, Coral Rag, Kelloway Rock, and Corn Brash, then<lb/>acquire a great degree of importance. Thin beds of second-<lb/>ary and tertiary formations, containing assemblages of very<lb/>characteristic fossil bodies, have furnished, as it were, a <hi rendition="#i">horizon</hi><lb/>to the geognost. In their prolongation, whatever occurs placed<lb/>above or beneath in the order of the whole series, has been<lb/>referred to one of them. Even the particular denominations<lb/>by which beds are distinguished, are of much importance in a<lb/>geognostical description, however whimsical or improper may<lb/>be their signification or their origin as taken from the language<lb/>of miners. But while treating of the relative position of rocks<lb/>on a surface of great extent, it is indispensably necessary to con-<lb/>sider the formations, or habitual associations of certain beds,<lb/>in a more general point of view. It is then that discretion and<lb/>circumspection are more necessary in the distinction of rocks,<lb/>and in their nomenclature. The work of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Freiesleben</persName> on the<lb/><placeName>Plains of Saxony</placeName>, which are upwards of seven hundred square<lb/>leagues in extent (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Geogr. Beschr. des Kupferschiefergebirges,</hi><lb/>1807&#x2014;15</bibl>), presents a beautiful model of the union of local<lb/>observations and geognostical generalizations. These generali-<lb/>zations, these attempts to simplify the system of formations,<lb/>and to direct the attention more especially to great charac-<lb/>teristic features, should be more or less cautiously conducted,<lb/>according as one describes the basin of a river, an isolated<lb/>province, a great country such as <placeName>France</placeName> or <placeName>Germany</placeName>, or an<lb/>entire continent.</p><lb/><p>The more minute the investigation of districts becomes, the<lb/>more does the connexion between formations which appear at<lb/>first perfectly independent, manifest itself by the great phe-<lb/>nomenon of <hi rendition="#i">alternation;</hi> that is to say, by a periodical succes-<lb/><pb n="108" facs="#f0017" />
sion of beds which present a certain analogy in their compo-<lb/>sition, and sometimes even in certain fossil organic bodies. It<lb/>is thus that, in the transition-mountains, for example, in <placeName>America</placeName><lb/>(at the entrance of the <placeName>plains of Calabozo</placeName>), beds of greenstone<lb/>and euphotide, in <placeName>Saxony</placeName> (near <placeName>Friedrichswalde</placeName> and <placeName>Meissen</placeName>)<lb/>the clay-slates with glance-coal, the greywackes, porphyries,<lb/>black limestones, and greenstones, constitute, from their fre-<lb/>quent and repeated <hi rendition="#i">alternation</hi>, a single formation. It often<lb/>happens that subordinate beds appear only at the extreme<lb/>limits of a formation, and assume the aspect of an independent<lb/>formation. The cupreous and bituminous marls (<hi rendition="#i">Kupferschiefer</hi>),<lb/>which occur in <placeName>Thuringia</placeName> between the alpine limestone (<hi rendition="#i">zechstein</hi>)<lb/>and the red sandstone (<hi rendition="#i">rothes liegende</hi>), and which have for ages<lb/>been extensively wrought, are represented in several parts of<lb/><placeName>Mexico</placeName>, of <placeName>New Andalusia</placeName>, and of <placeName>Southern Bavaria</placeName>, by mul-<lb/>tiplied beds of marly clay, more or less carburetted, and in-<lb/>cluded within the alpine limestone. Similar circumstances<lb/>often give to gypsums, sandstones, and small beds of compact<lb/>limestones, the appearance of particular formations. Their<lb/>dependence on <hi rendition="#i">subordination</hi> is known by their frequent asso-<lb/>ciation with other rocks, by their want of extent and of thick-<lb/>ness, or by their total suppression, which is frequently observed.<lb/>It must not be forgot (and this fact has struck me much in the<lb/>two hemispheres) that the great formations of limestones, for<lb/>example, the alpine limestone, have <hi rendition="#i">their sandstones</hi>, as the<lb/>very generally extended sandstones have <hi rendition="#i">their limestone beds</hi>.<lb/>Thin beds of sandstones, of limestones, and of gypsums, char-<lb/>acterize, in all the zones, the deposites of coal and rock-salt<lb/>or muriatiferous clay (<hi rendition="#i">salzthon</hi>), isolated deposites, which are<lb/>most commonly only covered by these small local formations.<lb/>It is by overlooking these considerations, which should be<lb/>familiar to every practical geologist, that the type of the great<lb/>independent formations has been rendered too complicated.</p><lb/><p>The phenomenon of <hi rendition="#i">alternation</hi> manifests itself, either locally<lb/>in rocks, superimposed several times upon each other, and<lb/>constituting a single compound formation, or in the series of<lb/>formations considered in their aggregate. It is either green-<lb/>stones and syenites, slates and transition limestones, beds of<lb/>limestones and of marl, that alternate immediately, or the<lb/>whole is a system of mica-slates, and of granular feldspathic<lb/>rocks (granites, gneisses, and syenites), which reappear among<lb/>the transition deposites, and which separate from the primitive<lb/>homonymous system the greywackes and limestones with<lb/>orthoceratites. For the first knowledge of this fact, one of the<lb/>most important and least studied of modern geognosy, we are<lb/><pb n="109" facs="#f0018" />
    indebted to the beautiful observations of Messrs <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Leopold von<lb/>Buch</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brochant</persName>, and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Haussmann</persName>. From the circumstance<lb/>that, in the transition, granular rocks, perfectly destitute of<lb/>organic remains, succeed to compact rocks which contain<lb/>these same remains, it has been concluded by geognosts of<lb/>great name, that this alternation of shelly and not-shelly rocks,<lb/>might extend beyond the deposites which we call primitive.<lb/>It has not been merely asked if the clay-slates, mica-slates,<lb/>and gneisses, support the granites which have been considered<lb/>as the oldest; the question has also been agitated, whether<lb/>greywackes and black limestones with madrepores might not<lb/>recur beneath those same granites. According to this idea,<lb/>the primitive and transition rocks would only form a single<lb/>deposite; and the first might be regarded as intercalated in a<lb/>deposite posterior to the development of organic beings, and<lb/>which might penetrate to an unknown depth into the interior<lb/>of the globe. I confess, that no direct observation can be as<lb/>yet adduced in support of these opinions. The fragments of<lb/>rocks which I have seen contained in the lithoid lavas of the<lb/>volcanoes of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, <placeName>Quito</placeName>, and <placeName>Vesuvius</placeName>, and which are<lb/>thought to have been torn from the bowels of the earth, seem<lb/>to belong to altered rocks of granite, mica-slate, syenite, and<lb/>granular limestone, and not to greywackes and limestone with<lb/>madrepores.</p><lb/><p>We have preserved in the arrangement of rocks the great<lb/>divisions known by the name of primitive, transition or inter-<lb/>mediary and tertiary deposites. The natural limits of these<lb/>four <hi rendition="#i">systems of rocks</hi> are the clay-slate with glance-coal or<lb/>ampelite and lydian stone, alternating with compact limestones<lb/>and greywackes, the coal formation, and the formations which<lb/>immediately succeed the chalk. In geognosy, as in descriptive<lb/>botany, the subdivisions or small groups of families have more<lb/>distinct characters than the great divisions or classes. It is<lb/>the case with all the sciences; in which we rise from indi-<lb/>viduals to species, from species to genera, and from these to<lb/>still higher degrees of abstraction. A method necessarily<lb/>rests upon <hi rendition="#i">differently graduated abstractions,</hi> and the passages<lb/>become more frequent in proportion as the characters are more<lb/>complex. The transition or intermediary formations of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Werner</persName>,<lb/>which M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Buch</persName> has first limited with the sagacity for which<lb/>he is distinguished (<bibl>Moll&#x2019;s Jahrb. 1798, b. ii. p. 254</bibl>), are con-<lb/>nected by the ampelitic clay-slates, the syenites with zircons,<lb/>the granite sometimes destitute of hornblende, and the anthra-<lb/>citic mica-slate, with the primitive deposite; while the small-<lb/>grained greywackes and madreporous and compact limestones,<lb/><pb n="110" facs="#f0019" />
        connect them with the coal sandstones and limestones of the<lb/>secondary desposites.</p><lb/><p>Porphyries of very different formations have their principal<lb/>seat among the transition rocks; but they break out, if we may<lb/>so speak, in considerable masses towards the secondary depo-<lb/>sites, where they are connected with the coal sandstone, while<lb/>they penetrate into the primitive class only as subordinate<lb/>rocks, and of little thickness. The progressive motion, or, if I<lb/>may be allowed to use the expression, the extent of the <hi rendition="#i">oscil-<lb/>lation</hi> of the serpentine and euphotide, is very different. Those<lb/>diallage rocks, constituting many distinct formations, rarely<lb/>covered with other rocks, stop short nearly at the lower boun-<lb/>dary of the secondary formations; towards the bottom they<lb/>penetrate into the primitive deposites to beyond the mica-<lb/>schist. The chalk seems to present a natural limit to the<lb/>tertiary formations, which were first characterised by Messrs<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Cuvier</persName> and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>, and justly, as deposites entirely dif-<lb/>ferent from the last secondary formations, described by the<lb/>Freyberg School (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Géogr. Miner. des Environs des Paris</hi>, p. 8<lb/>and 9</bibl>.) Struck with the relations which exist between the<lb/>tertiary deposites and the beds beneath the chalk, M. Brong-<lb/>niart has even recently proposed to designate the tertiary for-<lb/>mations by the name of <hi rendition="#i">upper</hi> secondary deposites, (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Sur le<lb/>gisement des Ophiolithes</hi>, p. 37</bibl>). Compare also the very inter-<lb/>esting geognostical discussions contained in <bibl><hi rendition="#i">M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Bonnard</persName>&#x2019;s<lb/>Traité des Roches</hi>, p. 138, 210, and 212</bibl>.)</p><lb/><p>The distinction of four deposites which we have successively<lb/>named, and of which three are posterior to the development<lb/>of organic life upon the globe, appears to me worthy of being<lb/>retained, notwithstanding the passage of some formations to<lb/>others of a very different character, and notwithstanding the<lb/>doubts which several very distinguished geognosts have founded<lb/>upon these passages. The classification of deposites marks<lb/>great epochs of nature; for example, the appearance of some<lb/>pelagic animals (zoophytes, cephalopodous mollusca), and the<lb/>simultaneous destruction of an enormous mass of monocotyle-<lb/>dons. It presents as it were points of rest to the mind, and<lb/>by keeping in view that the formations themselves are much<lb/>less important than the great divisions, we have often an oppor-<lb/>tunity, on advancing from high mountains toward the plains,<lb/>of observing the varied influence which the association of<lb/>primitive and transition rocks, and that of secondary and ter-<lb/>tiary ones, have exercised upon the inequality and configura-<lb/>tion of the ground. It is owing to this influence, that the aspect<lb/>of the landscape, the form of mountains and platforms, and the<lb/><pb n="111" facs="#f0020" />
            character of the vegetation, vary less, when we travel parallel<lb/>to the direction of the beds, than on cutting them at a right<lb/>angle. (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Greenough, Crit. Exam. of Geology</hi>, p. 38</bibl>).</p><lb/><p>I continue by following Messrs <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Buch</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Freiesleben</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Bro-<lb/>chant</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Beudant</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Buckland</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Raumer</persName>, (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Geb.</hi> von Nieder-Schles.,<lb/>1819</bibl>), and other celebrated geognosts, to group the indepen-<lb/>dent formations according to the divisions, into primitive transi-<lb/>tion, secondary, and tertiary deposites, without troubling my-<lb/>self about the impropriety of the greater number of these<lb/>denominations. I continue to separate the clay (with lignites)<lb/>superimposed upon the chalk, from that which is beneath it,<lb/>and the chalk itself from the more ancient secondary forma-<lb/>tions. But these distinctions, by beds and groups of beds, so<lb/>useful in the description of a deposite of small extent, ought<lb/>not to prevent the geognost, when he tries to rise to a more<lb/>general point of view, from connecting these clays and the<lb/>chalk with the Jura limestone, and from regarding them as the<lb/>last strata of this great formation, composed of calcareous and<lb/>marly beds. The inferior beds of the chalk (tuffeau) contain<lb/>ammonities. The limestone of the mountain of <placeName>St Peter of<lb/>Maestricht</placeName> indicates, as has already been observed by Messrs<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Omalius</persName> and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName> (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Geogr. Miner.</hi>, p. 13</bibl>), the passage of<lb/>the chalk to older secondary limestones. Near <placeName>Caen</placeName>, accord-<lb/>ing to the beautiful observations of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Prevost</persName>, the clays be-<lb/>neath the chalk contain those same lignites which occur, in<lb/>greater quantity, in the clay which is situated immediately<lb/>above the chalk: cerites, which bring to mind the coarse<lb/>limestone of <placeName>Paris</placeName>, are seen in a limestone with trigonias,<lb/>placed between clays inferior to the chalk and the oolitic<lb/>beds. I do not insist upon these particular facts; I mention<lb/>them only to prove, by a striking example, how, on bringing<lb/>together facts observed in different points of the same country,<lb/>the great phenomenon of <hi rendition="#i">alternation</hi> reveals to us the connexions<lb/>between formations which at first sight appear to have nothing<lb/>in common. It is the property of those beds which alternate<lb/>with one another, of those rocks which succeed each other in<lb/><hi rendition="#i">periodical series</hi>, to present the most marked contrast in the two<lb/>beds which immediately follow each other. In geognosy, as<lb/>in the different parts of descriptive natural history, the advan-<lb/>tage of classifications of variously graduated sections must be<lb/>recognized, without losing sight of the unity of nature; and<lb/>those who have contributed the most to the advancement of<lb/>natural philosophy, have possessed at once both the tendency<lb/>to generalize, and the exact knowledge of a mass of particu-<lb/>lar facts.</p><lb/><pb n="112" facs="#f0021" />
        <p>It has been customary to terminate the series of deposites<lb/>by the volcanic rocks, and to make them succeed the second-<lb/>ary and tertiary, and even the alluvial deposites. In a sys-<lb/>tem constructed upon the principle of relative antiquity, this<lb/>arragement seems to me to have little to recommend it. It is<lb/>without doubt the case that lithoid lavas are spread over the<lb/>most recent formations, even over beds of gravel; nor can it<lb/>be denied that there exist volcanic productions of different<lb/>epochs: but, from what I have observed in the <placeName>Cordilleras of<lb/>Peru</placeName>, of <placeName>Quito</placeName>, and of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, in a part of the world so cele-<lb/>brated for the frequency of volcanoes, it seems to me, that the<lb/>chief site of subterranean fires is in the transition rocks, and<lb/>beneath those rocks. I have observed, that all the burning<lb/>or extinct craters of the <placeName>Andes</placeName> open in the midst of trap<lb/>porphyries or trachytes, (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Berl. Abhandl. der Kön. Acad.</hi> 1813,<lb/>p. 131</bibl>), and that these trachytes are connected with the great<lb/>transition <hi rendition="#i">porphyry</hi>, and <hi rendition="#i">syenite formation</hi>, According to this<lb/>observation, it appears more natural to me to make the second-<lb/>ary and volcanic deposites to follow the transition deposite in<lb/>a parallel manner, and as by bisection. By this new arrange-<lb/>ment, the formation of porphyries, syenites, and greywackes,<lb/>or that of transition porphyries, syenites, and granites, occurs<lb/>connected at the same time; 1<hi rendition="#i">st</hi>, With the porphyries of the<lb/>red sandstone in the secondary coal-deposite; 2<hi rendition="#i">dly</hi>, With the<lb/>trachytes or trap porphyries which are destitute of quartz,<lb/>and mixed with pyroxene. I employ with regret the term<lb/><hi rendition="#i">volcanic terrain</hi>, not that I doubt, like those who designate the<lb/>trachytes, basalts <choice><sic>snd</sic><corr type="editorial">and</corr></choice> phonolites (porphyrschiefer), by the<lb/>name of <hi rendition="#i">trap terrain</hi>, that all which I have associated in the<lb/>volcanic terrain has not been produced or altered by fire;<lb/>but because several rocks, intercalated between the (primi-<lb/>tive?) transition and secondary rocks, might also be volcanic.<lb/>I would rather wish to avoid every (historical) idea of the<lb/>origin of things, in a (statistical) view of relative situation or<lb/>superposition. At <placeName>Skeen</placeName>, in <placeName>Norway</placeName>, a basaltic and porous<lb/>syenite, containing pyroxenes, is placed, according to the obser-<lb/>vation of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Buch</persName>, between the transition limestone and<lb/>the syenite with zircons. It is a bed, not a dike; and this<lb/>is a much less problematical phenomenon than the basalt<lb/>(<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Urgrünstein, Buch. Geogn. Beob. p.</hi> 124</bibl>, <bibl><hi rendition="#i">and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Raumer</persName>, Granit<lb/>des Riesengebirges, p.</hi> 70</bibl>), contained in the mica-schist of<lb/><placeName>Krobsdorf</placeName> in <placeName>Silesia</placeName>. The trachytes, with obsidian of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>,<lb/>are intimately connected with the transition porphyries which<lb/>alternate with syenites. The amygdaloid belonging to the<lb/>red sandstone, assumes, on the <placeName>Continent of Europe</placeName>, and in<lb/><pb n="113" facs="#f0022" />
            <placeName>Equinoctial America</placeName>, all the appearance of an amygdaloid of<lb/>the basaltic formation. M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Boué</persName>, in his interesting <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Essai<lb/>Geologique sur l&#x2019;Ecosse</hi>, p. 126, 162</bibl>, has described pyroxenic<lb/>rocks (dolerites) included in the red sandstone. Without<lb/>prejudging any thing regarding the origin of these masses, or<lb/>in general regarding that of all the primitive and transition<lb/>rocks, we designate here, by the name of Volcanic Terrains,<lb/><hi rendition="#i">the least interrupted series</hi> of rocks altered by fire.</p><lb/><p>In drawing up the enumeration of the different rocks, I have<lb/>made use of the names most generally employed by the geo-<lb/>gnosts of <placeName>France</placeName>, <placeName>Germany</placeName>, <placeName>England</placeName>, and <placeName>Italy</placeName>: in attempt-<lb/>ing to perfect the nomenclature of formations, I should be<lb/>apprehensive of adding new difficulties to those which the<lb/>discussion of relative positions already presents. I have, how-<lb/>ever, carefully avoided the denominations, too long preserved,<lb/>of <hi rendition="#i">under</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">upper limestone;</hi> of gypsum of the <hi rendition="#i">first, second</hi>, or<lb/><hi rendition="#i">third formation</hi>, of <hi rendition="#i">old</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">new red sandstone</hi>, &amp;c. These de-<lb/>nominations without doubt present a true geognostical charac-<lb/>ter; they have relation, not to the composition of rocks, but<lb/>to their relative age. However, as the general type of the<lb/>formations of <placeName>Europe</placeName> cannot be modelled after that of a single<lb/>district, the necessity of admitting parallel formations (<hi rendition="#i">sich<lb/>vertretende Gebirgsarten</hi>), renders the names of <hi rendition="#i">first</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">second</hi><lb/>gypsum, of <hi rendition="#i">old</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">middle</hi> sandstone, extremely vague and ob-<lb/>scure. In one country it is proper to consider a bed of gyp-<lb/>sum or of common sandstone as a particular formation; while<lb/>in another, it should be regarded as subordinate to neighbor-<lb/>ing formations. The <hi rendition="#i">geographical denominations</hi> are without<lb/>doubt the best; they give rise to precise ideas of superposi-<lb/>tion. When it is said that a formation is identical with the<lb/>porphyry of <placeName>Christiania</placeName>, the lias of <placeName>Dorsetshire</placeName>, the sandstone<lb/>of <placeName>Nebra</placeName> (bunter sandstein), the coarse limestone of Paris,<lb/>these assertions leave no doubt in the mind of an experienced<lb/>geognost, regarding the position which is to be assigned to the<lb/>formation in question. It is also by silent convention, as it<lb/>were, that the words <hi rendition="#i">zechstein of <placeName>Thuringia</placeName>, <placeName>Derbyshire</placeName> Limestone,<lb/><placeName>Paris</placeName> Formations,</hi> &amp;c. have been introduced into mineralogi-<lb/>cal language. They express a limestone which immediately<lb/>succeeds the red sandstone of the coal deposite, a transition<lb/>limestone placed beneath the coal sandstone, and lastly, for-<lb/>mations of more recent origin than the chalk. The only dif-<lb/>ficulties which the multiplicity of these geographical denomi-<lb/>nations presents, consist in the choice of names, and in the<lb/>degree of certainty which may have been acquired, regarding<lb/>the position or relative age of the rock to which the others are<lb/><pb n="114" facs="#f0023" />
                referred. The English geognosts look upon the continent for<lb/>their <hi rendition="#i">lias</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">red marl;</hi> the German for their <hi rendition="#i">bunte sandstein</hi><lb/>and <hi rendition="#i">muschelkalk</hi>. These words present themselves in the<lb/>minds of travellers associated with remembrances of localities.<lb/>It is not of so much importance, therefore, to produce precise<lb/>ideas, as to make choice of localities generally known, and<lb/>which are celebrated, either by the working of mines, or by<lb/>descriptive works.</p><lb/><p>In order to diminish the effects of national vanity, and to<lb/>attach new names to more important objects, I proposed a long<lb/>time ago, (1795), the denomination of <hi rendition="#i">Alpine Limestone</hi>, and<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Jura Limestone</hi>. A portion of the <placeName>High Alps of Switzerland</placeName>,<lb/>and the greater part of <placeName>Jura</placeName>, are without doubt formed of<lb/>these two rocks: the names, however, generally received at<lb/>the present day, of Alpine Limestone (Zechstein), and Jura<lb/>Limestone, should in my opinion be modified or entirely aban-<lb/>doned. The lower beds of the <placeName>Jura mountains</placeName>, filled with<lb/>gryphites, belong to an older formation, perhaps to the zech-<lb/>stein; and a great part of the limestone of the <placeName>Alps of Swit-<lb/>zerland</placeName> assuredly is not zechstein; but, according to Messrs<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Buch</persName> and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Escher</persName>, transition limestone. It would therefore<lb/>be better to choose the geographical names of rocks from<lb/>among the names of isolated mountains, the whole visible mass<lb/>of which belongs only to a single formation, than to derive<lb/>them, as I have erroneously done, from entire chains. I have<lb/>thought, and many geognosts have formed the same opinion,<lb/>that the Jura limestone (cavernous limestone of <placeName>Franconia</placeName>)<lb/>was generally placed upon the continent, beneath the Nebra<lb/>sandstone, (bunte sandstein), between this sandstone and the<lb/>zechstein. Subsequent observations have proved, that the<lb/>name of Jura Limestone had with reason been applied to<lb/>rocks which are very distant from the <placeName>mountains of Western<lb/>Switzerland</placeName>; but that the true geognostical place of this for-<lb/>mation, (when there is not a <hi rendition="#i">suppression</hi> of the inferior forma-<lb/>tions), occurs above the Nebra sandstone, between the shell-<lb/>limestone (muschelkalk, or the quadersandstein), and the<lb/>chalk. A geographical name, justly applied to several analo-<lb/>gous rocks, renders us attentive to their identity of relative<lb/>position; but the place which homonymous rocks ought to<lb/>occupy in the total series, is not well determined except when<lb/>the geographical name has been selected, after having ac-<lb/>quired a perfect certainty regarding their position. Circum-<lb/>stances are the same with regard to the relative age of the<lb/>molasse of <placeName>Argovia</placeName><choice><sic>,</sic><corr type="editorial"></corr></choice> (<choice><sic>nagelfluhe</sic><corr type="editorial">nagelfluhe)</corr></choice> and of the Pirna quadersand-<lb/>stein (grès blanc of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Bonnard</persName>), two rocks of very recent<lb/><pb n="115" facs="#f0024" />
origin, which have been very well examined separately, but<lb/>whose relations to each other, and to the chalk and Jura<lb/>limestone, have only been illustrated of late. One may there-<lb/>fore be pretty sure of having met in the New Continent with<lb/>rocks identical with the molasse or quadersandstein, without<lb/>being able to pronounce with certainty upon their relations<lb/>with all the secondary or tertiary rocks. When rocks are<lb/>not immediately in contact, and are not covered by deposites<lb/>of known position, their relative age can only be conjectured<lb/>from simple analogies.</p><lb/><p>The <hi rendition="#i">terms</hi> of the geognostical series are either <hi rendition="#i">simple</hi> or<lb/><hi rendition="#i">complex</hi>. To the simple terms belong the greater number of<lb/>the primitive formations: the granites, gneisses, mica-slates,<lb/>clay-slates, &amp;c. The complex terms occur in greater num-<lb/>bers among the transition rocks: there, each formation includes<lb/>an entire group of rocks, which alternate periodically. The<lb/>terms of the series are not transition limestones or greywackes,<lb/>constituting independent formations; they are associations of<lb/>clay-slate, green-stone, and greywacke; of porphyry and grey-<lb/>wacke; of granular and steatitic limestone, and of conglomerates,<lb/>composed of primitive rocks; of clay-slate and black limestone.<lb/>When these associations are formed of three or four rocks<lb/>which alternate, it is difficult to give them significant names,&#x2014;<lb/>names indicative of the whole composition of the group,&#x2014;of<lb/>all the partial members of the complex term of the series. It<lb/>may then assist in fixing the groups in the memory, to retrace<lb/>the rocks which predominate in them, without being absolutely<lb/>wanting in the neighbouring groups. It is in this manner that the<lb/>granular steatitic limestone characterises the Tarantaise forma-<lb/>tion; the greywacke, the great transition formation of the <placeName>Hartz</placeName><lb/>and of the banks of the <placeName>Rhine</placeName>; the metalliferous porphyries<lb/>rich in hornblende, and almost destitute of quartz, the forma-<lb/>tion of <placeName>Mexico</placeName> and of <placeName>Hungary</placeName>. If these phenomena of alter-<lb/>nation attain their <hi rendition="#i">maximum</hi> in the transition districts, still<lb/>they are not entirely excluded from the primitive and second-<lb/>ary terrain. In both of these terrains, complex terms are<lb/>mixed with the simple terms of the geognostical series. I<lb/>shall mention among the secondary formations, the sandstone<lb/>placed below the alpine limestone, (the Nebra sandstone, bunte<lb/>sandstein), which is an association of marly clay, sandstone<lb/>and oolites; the limestone which covers the red-sandstone of<lb/>the coal-formation (the zechstein or alpen-kalkstein), which is<lb/>a less constant association of limestone, of (muriatiferous) gyp-<lb/>sum, of stinkstone and of pulverulent bituminous marl. In the<lb/>primitive class we find the three first terms of the series; the<lb/><pb n="116" facs="#f0025" />
    oldest rocks either isolated, or alternating two and two, ac-<lb/>cording as they are geognostically more approximated by<lb/>their relative age, or the whole three alternating. The granite<lb/>sometimes forms constant associations with the gneiss, and the<lb/>gneiss with the mica-slate. These alternations follow particu-<lb/>lar laws: we see, (for example in <placeName>Brazil</placeName>, and, although less<lb/>distinctly, in the maritime chain in <placeName>Venezuela</placeName>), the granite,<lb/>gneiss, and mica-schist in a triple association; but I have not<lb/>found granite alternating alone with mica-slate, or gneiss and<lb/>mica-slate alternating by themselves with clay-slate.</p><lb/><p>We must not confound, and on this point I have often in-<lb/>sisted in the present article, rocks passing insensibly to those<lb/>which are in immediate contact with them; for example, mica-<lb/>slates, which <hi rendition="#i">oscillate</hi> between gneiss and clay-slate, with rocks<lb/>which alternate with one another, and which preserve all their<lb/>distinctive characters of composition and of structure. M.<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">D&#x2019;Aubuisson</persName> has long ago shewn how chemical analysis<lb/>approximates the clay-slate to mica. (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Journal de Physique</hi>,<lb/>vol. lxviii. p. 128</bibl>; <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Traité de Geognosie</hi>, vol. ii. p. 97</bibl>). The<lb/>first, it is true, has not the metallic lustre of mica-slate; it<lb/>contains a little less potash, and more carbon; the silex does<lb/>not unite into nodules or thin lamin&#x00E6; of quartz, as in the mica-<lb/>slate; but it cannot be doubted, that scales of mica form the<lb/>principal base of the clay-slate. These scales are so joined<lb/>together, that the eye cannot distinguish them in the mass.<lb/>It is perhaps this same affinity which prevents the alternation<lb/>of clay-slates and mica-slates: for in these alternations Nature<lb/>seems to favor the association of heterogeneous rocks; or, to<lb/>make use of a figurative expression, she delights in the asso-<lb/>ciations whose alternating rocks present a great contrast of<lb/>crystallization, of mixture, and of colour. At <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, I have<lb/>seen dark greenstones, alternate thousands of times with<lb/>reddish-white syenites, abounding more in quartz than in fel-<lb/>spar. In this greenstone there were veins of syenite, and in<lb/>the syenite veins of greenstone; but none of the two rocks<lb/>passed into the other. (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Essai politique sur la Nouvelle Espagne</hi>,<lb/>v. ii. p. 523</bibl>). They present at the limit of their mutual con-<lb/>tact, differences as marked as the porphyries which alternate<lb/>with the greywackes or with the syenites, as the black lime-<lb/>stones which alternate with the transition clay-slates, and so<lb/>many other rocks of entirely heterogeneous composition and<lb/>aspect. Further, when, in primitive deposites, rocks more<lb/>related by the nature of their composition than by their struc-<lb/>ture or mode of aggregation, for example, the granites and<lb/>gneisses, or the gneisses and mica-schists, alternate; these<lb/><pb n="117" facs="#f0026" />
        rocks do not by any means show the same tendency to pass<lb/>into each other, as they present, when isolated in formations<lb/>which are not of a complex character. We have already<lb/>observed, that often a bed &#x03B2;, becoming more frequent in the<lb/>rock &#x03B1;, announces to the traveller that the simple formation &#x03B1;,<lb/>is to be succeeded by a compound formation, in which &#x03B1; and<lb/>&#x03B2; alternate. Farther on, it happens, that &#x03B2; assumes a greater<lb/>development; that &#x03B1; is no longer an alternating rock, but a<lb/>simple bed subordinate to &#x03B2;, and that this rock &#x03B2; shows itself<lb/>alone, until, by the frequent repetition of beds &#x03B3;, it becomes<lb/>the precursor of a compound formation &#x03B2;, alternating with &#x03B3;.<lb/>We might substitute for these signs the words granite, gneiss,<lb/>and mica-slate; those of porphyry, greywacke, and syenite;<lb/>of gypsum, marl, and fetid limestone (stinkstein). <hi rendition="#i">Pasigraphic</hi><lb/>language has the advantage of generalizing the problems; it<lb/>is more conformable to the wants of <hi rendition="#i">geognostical philosophy</hi>, of<lb/>which I attempt to present here the <choice><sic>flrst</sic><corr type="editorial">first</corr></choice> elements, in so far as<lb/>they have relation to the study of the superposition of rocks.<lb/>Now, if often between formations which are simple and very<lb/>closely allied, in the order of their relative antiquity, between<lb/>the formations &#x03B1;, &#x03B2;, &#x03B3;, there occur compound formations inter-<lb/>posed, &#x03B1;&#x03B2; and &#x03B2;&#x03B3;, (that is to say, &#x03B1; alternating with &#x03B2;, and &#x03B2;<lb/>alternating with &#x03B3;); we observe, also, although less frequently,<lb/>that a formation (for example &#x03B1;), assumes so extraordinary an<lb/>increase, that it envelopes the formation &#x03B2;; and that &#x03B2;, instead<lb/>of showing itself as an independent rock, placed between &#x03B1; and<lb/>&#x03B3;, is now nothing but a bed in &#x03B1;. It is thus, that, in <placeName>Lower<lb/>Silesia</placeName>, the red-sandstone contains the formation zechstein; for<lb/>the limestone of <placeName>Runzendorf</placeName>, filled with impressions of fishes,<lb/>and analogous to the bituminous marl, abounding in fishes, of<lb/>Thuringia, is entirely developed in the coal-formation. (<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Buch</persName>,<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Beob.</hi> vol. i. p. 104, 157</bibl>; <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Id.</hi> <choice><sic>Reisenach</sic><corr type="editorial">Reise nach</corr></choice> Norwegen, vol. i. p.<lb/>158</bibl>; <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Raumer</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Gebirge von Nieder-schlesien</hi>, p. 79</bibl>). M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Beudant</persName>,<lb/><bibl><hi rendition="#i">Voy. Miner.</hi>, vol. iii. p. 183</bibl>., has observed a similar phenome-<lb/>non in <placeName>Hungary</placeName>. In other districts, for example, in <placeName>Switzer-<lb/>land</placeName>, at the southern extremity of <placeName>Saxony</placeName>, the red-sandstone<lb/>disappears entirely; because it is replaced, and, so to speak,<lb/>overcome by a prodigious development of greywacke or of<lb/>alpine limestone. (<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/"><choice><sic>Friesleben</sic><corr type="editorial">Freiesleben</corr></choice></persName>, Kupfersch. p. 109</bibl>). These<lb/>effects of the alternation or unequal development of rock, are<lb/>so much the more worthy of attention, that their study may<lb/>throw light upon some apparent deviations from a generally<lb/>acknowledged type of superposition, and that it may serve to<lb/>a common type the series of position observed in very distant<lb/>countries.</p><lb/><pb n="118" facs="#f0027" />
        <p>In order to designate the formations composed of two rocks<lb/>which alternate with another, I have generally preferred the<lb/>words <hi rendition="#i">granite and gneiss, syenite and greenstone,</hi> to the more<lb/>commonly adopted expressions of <hi rendition="#i">granite-gneiss, syenite-green-<lb/>stone.</hi> I was apprehensive that this last method of designating<lb/>formations composed of alternating rocks, might rather give<lb/>rise to the idea of a passage from granite to gneiss, from<lb/>syenite to greenstone. In fact, a geognost, whose works upon<lb/>the trachytes of <placeName>Germany</placeName> have not been sufficiently appre-<lb/>ciated, M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Nose</persName>, has already made use of the words <hi rendition="#i">granite-<lb/>porphyries</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">porphyry-granites</hi>, to indicate varieties of struc-<lb/>ture and aspect, to separate the porphyritic granites from<lb/>porphyries, which, from the frequency of crystals imbedded<lb/>in the mass, presents an aggregational, a true granitic structure.<lb/>By adopting the denominations of granite and gneiss, of syenite<lb/>and porphyry, of greywacke and porphyry, of limestone and<lb/>clay-slate, no doubt is left regarding the nature of the complex<lb/>terms of the geognostical series.<note place="foot" n="*">Translated from Essai Geognostique par Baron Alexandre de Humboldt.</note></p><lb/><p>M. Humboldt next proceeds to consider the natural history<lb/>of fossil organic remains, as connected with formations.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>