<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="229" facs="#f0001" />
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Constitution and Mode of Action of<lb/>Volcanoes, in different Parts of the<lb/>Earth.</hi> By Alexander Von Humboldt.<lb/>Read before the Royal Academy of Sciences of Berlin,<lb/>Jan. 24, 1823.</head>
                <lb/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>No. I.</head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>When we consider the influence which<lb/>scienti@c travels into distant regions, and<lb/>a more extended geographical knowledge,<lb/>have for some centuries past exerted<lb/>upon the study of nature, we soon dis-<lb/>cover how this influence has varied ac-<lb/>cording to the objects of inquiry, which<lb/>have been, on the one hand, the forms of<lb/>the organic world, and, on the other, the<lb/>inanimate formation of the earth;&#x2014;the<lb/>knowledge of rocks, their relative ages,<lb/>and origin. Different forms of plants<lb/>and animals enliven the earth in every<lb/>zone, as well in the plains, where the<lb/>heat of the atmosphere is determined by<lb/>the geographical latitude and the different<lb/>inflexions of the isothermal lines, as where<lb/>it changes suddenly on the steep declivi-<lb/>ties of the mountains. Organic nature<lb/>gives a peculiar physiognomical character<lb/>to every zone, which is not the case with<lb/>the inorganic world where the solid crust<lb/>of the earth is divested of its vegetable<lb/>covering. The same rocks approach-<lb/>ing to and receding from each other in<lb/>groups occur in both hemispheres, from<lb/>the equator to the poles. On a distant<lb/>island, surrounded by strange plants, un-<lb/>der a sky where the well-known stars do<lb/>not shine, the sailor recognises, often<lb/>with glad surprise, the clayslate which is<lb/>the common rock of his native country.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>This independence of the geognostical<lb/>relations of places on the present con-<lb/>stitution of their climate, does not diminish,<lb/>but only gives a particular direction to the<lb/>favourable effect upon the progress of<lb/>geology and physical geognosy, which is<lb/>produced by numerous observations made<lb/>in foreign countries. Every expedition<lb/>enriches natural history with new plants,<lb/>and new genera of animals; at one time<lb/>they are organic forms ranging them-<lb/>selves with well-known types, and repre-<lb/>senting to us, in its original perfection, a<lb/>regularly woven, though often apparently<lb/>interrupted texture of animated crea-<lb/>tures; at another, they are forms which<lb/>appear to be insolated, as vestiges of<lb/>genera which have been destroyed, or as<lb/>
                        <cb/> surprising members of groups still to be<lb/>discovered. Such a variety is not pre-<lb/>sented by the examination of the solid<lb/>crust of the earth; it rather reveals to<lb/>us an agreement, which excites the admi-<lb/>ration of the geognost, between the parts<lb/>of which it is composed, in the superpo-<lb/>sition of masses of different natures, and<lb/>in their periodical repetition. In the<lb/>chain of the Andes, as well as in the<lb/>central mountains of Europe, one forma-<lb/>tion seems, as it were, to occasion the<lb/>existence of another; masses of the same<lb/>character assume similar forms: moun-<lb/>tains are formed by basalt and dolerite;<lb/>steep declivities by dolomite, porphyry,<lb/>and quadersandstein; bell-shaped emi-<lb/>nences and high-vaulted domes by vitre-<lb/>ous trachyte rich in felspar.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>In the most distant zones, larger crys-<lb/>tals, as it were by internal evolution out<lb/>of the more compact texture of the greater<lb/>mass, aggregate into subordinate beds,<lb/>and thus frequently announce the vicinity<lb/>of a new and independent formation.<lb/>Thus is the whole inorganic world re-<lb/>flected, more or less clearly, in every<lb/>mountain of considerable extent; but in<lb/>order to ascertain completely the most<lb/>important phenomena respecting the com-<lb/>position, the relative age, and the origin<lb/>of the different species of rocks, observa-<lb/>tions from the most distant parts of the<lb/>earth must be compared together. Pro-<lb/>blems which had appeared enigmatical to<lb/>the geognost in his mother country are<lb/>solved near the equator. If distant<lb/>zones do not furnish new species of<lb/>rocks, that is to say, unknown arrange-<lb/>ments of simple substances, as has already<lb/>been remarked, they yet teach us how<lb/>to discover the great laws which are<lb/>every where the same, and according to<lb/>which, the different strata of the earth<lb/>support each other, appear in the form<lb/>of veins, or are elevated by elastic pow-<lb/>ers.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>We need not be surprised, that not-<lb/>withstanding the great assistance which<lb/>our geological information derives from<lb/>inquiries, having whole countries for<lb/>their object, an extensive class of phe-<lb/>nomena (with which I venture to enter-<lb/>tain this assembly,) has been treated,<lb/>during so long a period, in a confined<lb/>manner; the points of comparison being<lb/>more difficult, and, I might say, more<lb/>troublesome to find. Whatever we be-<lb/>lieved we knew, until the end of the last<lb/>century, respecting the form of volcanoes,<lb/>and the action of their subterraneous<lb/>forces, had been derived from two moun-<lb/>tains of the south of Italy, from &#x00C6;tna and<lb/>from Vesuvius. The first being more<lb/>accessible, and having, like all low volca-<lb/>noes, more frequent eruptions, has served<lb/>for a type, according to which a whole<lb/>distant world.&#x2014;the powerful volcanoes<lb/>of Mexico, South America, and the Asi-<lb/>atic Islands, has been considered. Such<lb/>a method recalls to our remembrance<lb/>the shepherd of Virgil, who expected his<lb/>narrow cottage to contain the ideal of the<lb/>eternal city, imperial Rome.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>A careful examination of the whole<lb/>Mediterranean, and principally of its<lb/>easterly islands and shores, where man-<lb/>kind first awakened to mental culture,<lb/>and to noble feelings, might certainly<lb/>have dispelled such a narrow idea of<lb/>nature. Out of the deep bed of the sea,<lb/>among the Sporades, rocks of trachyte<lb/>have arisen, like the Azoric island,<lb/>which has thrice reappeared during three<lb/>centuries, the intervening periods being<lb/>almost equal. Between Epidaurus and<lb/>Troezene, near Methone, the Pelopon-<lb/>nesus has a Monte Nuovo, which has<lb/>been described by Strabo, and seen by<lb/>Dodwell, higher than the Monte Nuovo<lb/>of the Campi Phlegr&#x00E6;i, near Baia; per-<lb/>haps higher than the new volcano of<lb/>Xorullo in the plains of Mexico, which I<lb/>have found among a thousand basaltic<lb/>cones, raised out of the earth, and still<lb/>smoking. In the basin of the Mediter-<lb/>ranean Sea also, the volcanic fire bursts<lb/>
                        <cb/> forth, and not only from permanent cra-<lb/>ters, from insolated mountains which pre-<lb/>serve a lasting communication with the<lb/>interior of the earth, like Stromboli,<lb/>Vesuvius, and &#x00C6;tna;&#x2014;on Ischia, near<lb/>the Epom&#x00E6;us, and also, as it would ap-<lb/>pear from the reports of the ancients,<lb/>near Chalcis in the Lelantic plains, has<lb/>lava flowed out of fissures which have<lb/>suddenly opened. Besides these phe-<lb/>nomena, which have taken place in the<lb/>period of history within the narrow limits<lb/>of certain traditions, and which Ritter<lb/>will collect and explain in his masterly<lb/>Geography, the shores of the Mediterra-<lb/>nean contain abundant remains of more<lb/>ancient igneous effects. The south of<lb/>France shows, in Auvergne, a range of<lb/>hills, in which <hi rendition="#i">bells</hi> of trachyte occur<lb/>alternately with cones of eruption, from<lb/>which currents of lava have descended.<lb/>The Lombardic plain, which forms the<lb/>innermost bay of the Adriatic Sea, sur-<lb/>rounds the trachyte of the Euganean<lb/>Hills, where domes of granular trachyte,<lb/>of obsidian, and of pearlstone, rise, which,<lb/>passing into each other, break through<lb/>the Jura limestone, but never occur in<lb/>narrow streams which have flowed.<lb/>Similar evidences of former revolutions<lb/>may be found in many parts of the Gre-<lb/>cian continent, and in Asia Minor, coun-<lb/>tries which will afford the geognost copi-<lb/>ous subjects for examination, when the<lb/>light once returns to the land whence it<lb/>first beamed over the western world&#x2014;<lb/>when tormented mankind ceases to sink<lb/>under the savage lethargy of the Ottoman.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>I mention the geographical neighbour-<lb/>hood of so many phenomena, in order to<lb/>prove, that the bed of the Mediterranean,<lb/>with all its chains of islands, might have<lb/>afforded to the attentive observer, every<lb/>thing that has been discovered, in latter<lb/>periods, under the most varied forms, in<lb/>South America, on Teneriffe, or on the<lb/>Aleutian islands, near the polar regions.<lb/>There were accumulated objects for<lb/>observation, but tours into distant re-<lb/>gions, and the comparison of large tracts<lb/>of country within and beyond Europe,<lb/>were necessary, in order to discover<lb/>what was common to all these phenomena,<lb/>and to learn, clearly, their dependence<lb/>on each other.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="237" facs="#f0002" />
                    <cb/>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Constitution and Mode of Action of<lb/>Volcanoes, in different Parts of the<lb/>Earth.</hi> By Alexander Von Humboldt.<lb/>Read before the Royal Academy of Sciences of Berlin,<lb/>Jan. 24. 1823.</head>
                <lb/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>No. II.</head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>By the usage of language, which often<lb/>gives stability and respect to the first<lb/>erroneous views of things, but often, as it<lb/>were, by instinct, distinguishes the truth,<lb/>we apply the term volcanic to all erup-<lb/>tions of subterranean and melted matter;<lb/>to columns of smoke and steam, which<lb/>rise sporadically out of rocks, as at Co-<lb/>lares after the great earthquake at Lis-<lb/>bon; to Sals&#x00E6;, or conical hills of clay<lb/>which emit mud, asphaltum, and hydro-<lb/>gen, as those near Girgenti, in Sicily, and<lb/>near Turbaco, in South America; to hot<lb/>Geyser springs which rise by the pressure<lb/>of elastic vapours; and, in general, to all<lb/>violent powers of nature which have<lb/>their seat deep in the interior of our<lb/>planets. In the Spanish main of America,<lb/>and in the Philippine islands, the inhabi-<lb/>tants make a distinction between igneous<lb/>
                        <cb/> and aqueous volcanoes, <hi rendition="#i">vulcunes de agua<lb/>y de fuego:</hi> they apply the first name to<lb/>mountains, which, during violent earth-<lb/>quakes, from time to time, eject subter-<lb/>raneous water, and with a dull noise.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>Without denying the connexion be-<lb/>tween the different phenomena just men-<lb/>tioned, it seems advisable to give a dis-<lb/>tinct language to the physical as well as<lb/>to the oryctognostic branch of geognosy;<lb/>and not to apply the term volcano in one<lb/>instance to a mountain that terminates in<lb/>a permanent crater; and in another, to<lb/>every subterranean cause of volcanic<lb/>phenomena.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>In the present state of the earth, the<lb/>most common form of volcanic eminences<lb/>is that of isolated cones; such are Vesu-<lb/>vius, &#x00C6;tna, the Peak of Teueriffe, Tun-<lb/>guragna, and Cotopaxi. I have seen<lb/>them of every magnitude, from the low-<lb/>est hills to mountains rising to the height<lb/>of 17,700 feet above the level of the sea.<lb/>Besides these conical mountains, there<lb/>are other craters, permanently communi-<lb/>cating with the interior of the earth, situ-<lb/>ated upon lengthened craggy ranges of<lb/>mountains, not always in the middle of<lb/>their wall-like summits, but towards the<lb/>end, and near their declivities. Such is<lb/>Pichincha which rises between the Paci-<lb/>fic Ocean and the town of Quito, and which<lb/>has become celebrated by Bouguer&#x2019;s<lb/>earliest formula for the barometer; such<lb/>also are the volcanoes that rise in the<lb/>plain de los Pastos, at the elevation of<lb/>10,000 feet. All these differently formed<lb/>summits consist of trachyte, or trap-<lb/>porphyry, a granular rock, full of cracks<lb/>and fissures, and composed of glassy fel-<lb/>spar and hornblende, but often containing<lb/>in addition, augite, mica, laminar felspar,<lb/>and quartz.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>Where the evidence of the first erup-<lb/>tion, and where the first scaffolding, I<lb/>might say, has been entirely preserved,<lb/>the isolated conical hills are surrounded<lb/>by a high wall of rocks forming a circus,<lb/>consisting of superposed strata; such<lb/>walls, or annular surrounding masses, are<lb/>called <hi rendition="#i">craters of elevation;</hi> of these very<lb/>important phenomena, Leopold von<lb/>Buch, the first geognost of our times,<lb/>from whose works I have taken several<lb/>views contained in this paper, read a re-<lb/>markable account, five years ago.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>The volcanoes which communicate<lb/>with the atmosphere by means of craters,<lb/>and the conical hills of basalt and bell-<lb/>shaped trachytic hills without craters,<lb/>the latter either low like Sarcouy, or<lb/>high like Chimborazo, form different<lb/>groups. A geographical comparison<lb/>shows, in one place, small Archipelagi,<lb/>or, as it were, classed systems of moun-<lb/>tains, either with craters and currents of<lb/>lava, as in the Canaries and Azores, or<lb/>devoid of craters and real currents of<lb/>lava in the Euganeans, and the Sieben-<lb/>gebirge near Bonn; or it shows, in other<lb/>places, single and double chains of vol-<lb/>canoes, connected with each other, and<lb/>forming tracts of many hundred miles in<lb/>length, which are either parallel to the<lb/>direction of the mountains, as in Guati-<lb/>mala, Peru, and Java, or in directions<lb/>perpendicular to their axis, as in the land<lb/>of the Aztekes, where none but volcanic<lb/>trachyte-mountains attain the limits of<lb/>eternal snow, and those, probably, have<lb/>been thrust out of a fissure nearly 500<lb/>miles in length, which divides the whole<lb/>continent, from the Pacific Ocean to<lb/>the Atlantic.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>This aggregation of volcanoes either in<lb/>single round groups, or in double ranges,<lb/>affords the most determinate proof that<lb/>volcanic effects do not depend upon slight<lb/>causes existing near the surface of the<lb/>earth, but that they are great and deeply<lb/>founded phenomena. The whole eastern<lb/>part of the American continent, which is<lb/>poor in metals, is at present without cra-<lb/>ters, without trachyte, probably even<lb/>without basalt. All the volcanoes are<lb/>situated in the part opposite to Asia, in<lb/>the meridian line of the Andes chain,<lb/>
                        <cb/> 1800 geographical miles long; the whole<lb/>of the elevated district of Quito is nothing<lb/>but a single volcanic hearth, the summits<lb/>of which are Pichincha, Cotopaxi, and<lb/>Tunguragua. The volcanic fire now<lb/>bursts from one, and then from another<lb/>of these apertures, which we are accus-<lb/>tomed to consider as separate volcanoes.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>The progressive motion of the fire<lb/>here, in the space of three centuries,<lb/>turned from north to south. The earth-<lb/>quakes with which this part of the world<lb/>is so terribly visited, furnish remarkable<lb/>evidences of the existence of subter-<lb/>raneous communication, not only be-<lb/>tween countries without volcanoes, as<lb/>was known long ago, but even between<lb/>craters which are far distant from each<lb/>other. Thus the volcano of Pasto, situ-<lb/>ated to the east of the river Guaytara, un-<lb/>interruptedly vomited a high column of<lb/>smoke, during the three months of the<lb/>year 1797; and this column disappeared<lb/>at the very moment, when, at the dis-<lb/>tance of nearly 300 miles, the great<lb/>earthquake of Riobamba and the mud<lb/>eruption of the Moya, killed from 30,000 to<lb/>40,000 Indians. The sudden appearance<lb/>of the Azoric island Sabrina, on the 30th<lb/>of January, 1811, was the forerunner of<lb/>those dreadful shocks, which, further to<lb/>the west, shook, almost uninterruptedly,<lb/>from the month of May, 1811, to that<lb/>of June, 1813, first the Antilles, after-<lb/>wards the plains of the Ohio and the Mis-<lb/>sissippi, and at last the opposite coast of<lb/>Venezuela. Thirty days after the com-<lb/>plete destruction of the town of Carac-<lb/>cas, the eruption of the volcano of St.<lb/>Vincent in the neighbouring Antilles<lb/>took place; at the same moment when<lb/>this explosion happened, on the 30th of<lb/>April, 1811, a subterranean noise was<lb/>heard throughout a country of 2200<lb/>geographical square miles, or 47,900<lb/>English square miles, in extent.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>The inhabitants near the Apure, where<lb/>it is joined by the Rio Nula, as well as<lb/>those of the most distant part of the<lb/>coast, compared this noise to that of ar-<lb/>tillery. From where the Rio Nula falls<lb/>into the Apure, through which river I<lb/>came into the Orinoco, to the volcano of<lb/>St. Vincent, the distance, in a direct line,<lb/>is 731 English miles. The noise just<lb/>alluded to, which certainly was not com-<lb/>municated through the air, must, there-<lb/>fore, have had a deep internal cause. Its<lb/>intensity on the coast of the Antillic sea<lb/>was scarcely greater than in the interior<lb/>of the country.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>It would be useless to augment the<lb/>number of examples, but for the purpose<lb/>of recalling to memory a phenomenon<lb/>which has become historically interesting<lb/>to Europe, I will mention the earthquake<lb/>at Lisbon. At the same time with this,<lb/>on the 1st of November, 1755, not only<lb/>were the Swiss lakes, and the sea on the<lb/>Swedish shores violently agitated, but<lb/>even in the easternly Antilles, around<lb/>Martinque, Antigua, and Barbadoes,<lb/>where the tide never exceeds 28 inches,<lb/>it suddenly rose to 20 feet. All these<lb/>phenomena prove, that the subterranean<lb/>powers act either dynamically, by pro-<lb/>ducing tension and vibration, as in earth-<lb/>quakes; or chemically, by producing or<lb/>altering substances, as in volcanoes.<lb/>They prove, likewise, that these powers<lb/>do not act from superficial causes, from<lb/>the exterior crust of the earth; but from<lb/>deeply-seated causes, from the interior<lb/>of our planet; extending their simulta-<lb/>neous effects to the most distant parts of<lb/>the earth, through fissures and empty<lb/>veins.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="245" facs="#f0003" />
                    <cb/>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Constitution and Mode of Action of<lb/>Volcanoes, in different Parts of the<lb/>Earth.</hi> By Alexander Von Humboldt.<lb/>Read before the Royal Academy of Sciences of Berlin.<lb/>Jan. 24. 1823.</head>
                <lb/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>No. III.</head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>The more different the structure of<lb/>volcanoes; that is to say, of those raised<lb/>masses which surround the canal through<lb/>which the melted substances proceed<lb/>from the interior of the earth to its sur-<lb/>face, the more important is it to become<lb/>thoroughly acquainted with that struc-<lb/>ture by exact measurement. The in-<lb/>terest attached to this measurement,<lb/>which has been a particular object of my<lb/>examination in another part of the world,<lb/>is heightened by the consideration, that<lb/>that which is to be measured is a varia-<lb/>ble magnitude. The physiognomy of<lb/>nature consists in the change of pheno-<lb/>mena tending to connect the present with<lb/>the past. In order to ascertain a periodi-<lb/>cal return, or the laws of progressive natu-<lb/>ral changes in general, certain fixed points<lb/>are neces@ary; and observations @<lb/>ly made at stated periods, may serve for<lb/>numerical comparison. Had the mean<lb/>temperature of the atmosphere in differ-<lb/>ent latitudes been observed for a few thou-<lb/>sand years, and the mean height of the<lb/>barometer at the level of the sea, we<lb/>might now know in what proportion the<lb/>heat of different climates has increased,<lb/>or diminished, and whether the height of<lb/>the atmosphere has undergone any<lb/>changes. Similar points for comparison<lb/>are required, for the variation and the<lb/>declination of the magnetic needle, and<lb/>for the intensity of the electromagnetic<lb/>power, upon which two excellent philo-<lb/>sophers of this Academy have thrown so<lb/>much light. If it be a praiseworthy un-<lb/>dertaking of learned societies to inquire<lb/>assiduously into the changes of tempera-<lb/>ture undergone by the globe, into those<lb/>which take place in the pressure of the<lb/>atmosphere, and in the magnetic varia-<lb/>tion,&#x2014;it is the duty of a travelling ge-<lb/>ognost, in ascertaining the inequality<lb/>of the earth&#x2019;s surface, to consider, prin-<lb/>cipally, the variable height of the vol-<lb/>canoes. What I formerly attempted on<lb/>the mountains of Mexico, on the Tolu-<lb/>ca Nauhiampatepetl and Xorullo, and in<lb/>the Andes of Quito, on the Pichincha, I<lb/>have found opportunity, since my return<lb/>to Europe, to repeat at different periods<lb/>on Vesuvius. Saussure measured this<lb/>mountain in 1773, at the time when both<lb/>sides of the crater, the south-eastern<lb/>and north-western, appeared to be of<lb/>equal altitude; he found their height to<lb/>be 609 toises (3894 feet) above the level<lb/>of the sea. The eruption of 1794 occa-<lb/>sioned a fall on the south side, which<lb/>even the unaccustomed eye discovers at<lb/>a great distance. In 1805. I measured<lb/>Vesuvius three times, in conjunction with<lb/>M. von Buch, and M. Gay-Lussac; we<lb/>found the elevation of the northern edge,<lb/>opposite to Monte Somma, la Rocca del<lb/>Palo, to be exactly the same as Saussure<lb/>had before determined it; the southern<lb/>
                        <cb/> edge we found 71 toises (454 feet) low-<lb/>er than it was in 1773; the total height<lb/>of the volcano on the side opposite Tor-<lb/>re del Greco (towards which side the<lb/>fire seems to have acted the most power-<lb/>fully, during the last 30 years,) had di-<lb/>minished one-ninth part.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>The cone of ashes on Vesuvius bears<lb/>the proportion of one-third to the height<lb/>of the whole mountain, that on Pichincha<lb/>is as 1 to 10, and that on the Peak of<lb/>Teneriffe as 1 to 22; Vesuvius has,<lb/>therefore, the largest cone of ashes<lb/>in proportion, because, probably, as a<lb/>low volcano, it has acted principally<lb/>through its summit. A few months ago,<lb/>I succeeded not only in repeating my for-<lb/>mer measurements on Vesuvius, but also<lb/>in ascertaining the elevation of all the<lb/>edges of the crater. This work, per-<lb/>haps, deserves some consideration, for<lb/>the periods at which it was executed in-<lb/>clude those of the great eruptions from<lb/>1805 to 1822, and it is, perhaps, the only<lb/>admeasurement yet published of any vol-<lb/>cano which may be compared in all its<lb/>parts. It proves that the edges of the<lb/>craters, not only where they evidently<lb/>consist of trachyte, as in the volcanoes of<lb/>the Andes, but likewise every where<lb/>else, are much more constant phenomena<lb/>than has hitherto been believed. Simple<lb/>angles of elevation ascertained from the<lb/>same points are more proper for these<lb/>examinations than barometrical and tri-<lb/>gonometrical measurement. According to<lb/>my last determination, the north-western<lb/>edge of the crater of Vesuvius has not<lb/>changed its form in the least since Saus-<lb/>sure&#x2019;s time, a period of 49 years. The<lb/>south-eastern edge towards Bosche tre<lb/>Case, which became about 450 feet low-<lb/>er in 1794, has sunk very little since that<lb/>time.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>If in the description of great eruptions,<lb/>in the public papers, the completely<lb/>changed form of Vesuvius has frequently<lb/>been mentioned, if this opinion often<lb/>@ to be corroborated by the pictu-<lb/>resque views of the mountain made at<lb/>Naples, the cause of this mistake may be<lb/>found in the circumstance, that the out-<lb/>lines of the edges of the crater have<lb/>been confounded with those of the cone<lb/>of eruption which is accidentally formed<lb/>in the middle of the crater, upon a bot-<lb/>tom that has been raised by vapours.<lb/>Such a cone of eruption, consisting of<lb/>rapilli and slags loosely heaped together,<lb/>has become visible over the south-east-<lb/>ern edge of the crater, since 1816 and<lb/>1818. The eruption of February, 1822,<lb/>had so much increased it that it had be-<lb/>come from 70 to 80 feet higher than the<lb/>north-eastern edge of the crater, Rocca<lb/>del Palo. This remarkable cone, which,<lb/>at Naples, they were accustomed to con-<lb/>sider as the true summit of Vesuvius,<lb/>fell in with a tremendous noise, during the<lb/>eruption of the 22d of October, so that<lb/>the bottom of the crater, which had been<lb/>uninterruptedly accessible from the year<lb/>1811, now lies 850 English feet beneath<lb/>the northern edge, and about 213 feet<lb/>deeper than the southern edge of the vol-<lb/>cano. The variable form and relative<lb/>situation of the crater of eruption, the<lb/>opening of which must not be taken for<lb/>the real crater of the volcano, as fre-<lb/>quently has been done, gives, at different<lb/>times, a peculiar physiognomy to Vesu-<lb/>vius; and the historiographer of that<lb/>volcano, from the mere outline of the<lb/>summit, and the relative height of the<lb/>northern or southern side of the moun-<lb/>tain, as it is drawn in Hackert&#x2019;s Views in<lb/>the palace Portici, would guess the year<lb/>in which the artist made the sketch of<lb/>his picture.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>In the night between the 23d and 24th<lb/>of October, one day after the fall of the<lb/>cone of slags 400 feet in height, when<lb/>small but numerous currents of lava had<lb/>already flowed, the fiery eruption of ashes<lb/>and rapilli began. It continued uninter-<lb/>ruptedly for twelve days, but was most<lb/>violent during the first four. During this<lb/>
                        <pb n="246" facs="#f0004" /> time the detonations in the interior of the<lb/>volcano were so violent, that the mere<lb/>concussion of the air (no earthquake had<lb/>been observed) caused the roofs to burst<lb/>in the palace of Portici. In the sur-<lb/>rounding villages of Resina, Torre del<lb/>Greco, Torre del Annonciata, and Bosche<lb/>tre Case, an interesting phenomenon<lb/>was observed; the atmosphere was so<lb/>thickly filled with ashes, that the most<lb/>intense darkness overspread the whole<lb/>country for several hours in the middle<lb/>of the day. The people walked in the<lb/>streets with lanterns, as is often done at<lb/>Quito when Pichincha is in eruption.<lb/>The flight of the inhabitants was never<lb/>more general; currents of lava were<lb/>less feared than a fall of ashes, a pheno-<lb/>menon which was unknown there with<lb/>such violence, and in consequence of the<lb/>relations respecting the destruction of<lb/>Herculaneum, Pompeii, and Stabi&#x00E6;, filled<lb/>the minds of the people with frightful<lb/>images.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>The hot steam which rose from the<lb/>crater during the eruption and passed<lb/>into the atmosphere, formed on cooling a<lb/>thick mass of clouds, around the column<lb/>of ashes and fire, 9000 feet in height.<lb/>This sudden condensation of steam, and,<lb/>as Gay-Lussac has shown, the very for-<lb/>mation of the clouds, increases the elec-<lb/>tric tension. Lightnings burst forth in all<lb/>directions from the column of ashes, and<lb/>the rolling thunder might clearly be dis-<lb/>tinguished from the interior noise of the<lb/>volcano. At no former eruption had the<lb/>play of electric charges been so sur-<lb/>prising.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>On the morning of the 26th of Octo-<lb/>ber, a singular account was circulated,<lb/>that a current of boiling water had issued<lb/>from the crater, and rushed down from<lb/>the cone of ashes. Monticelli, the zea-<lb/>lous and learned observer of the volca-<lb/>no, soon discerned that the rumour had<lb/>been occasioned by an optical deception.<lb/>The supposed current of water was<lb/>nothing but a dry mass of ashes, which<lb/>flowed down, like quicksand, from a @<lb/>sure in the superior edge of the crater.<lb/>A drought, which had completely desolat-<lb/>ed the fields, preceded the eruption, but<lb/>the volcanic thunderstorm occasioned,<lb/>towards its termination, a very heavy<lb/>and continued rain. Such a phenomenon<lb/>characterizes the conclusion of an erup-<lb/>tion in every zone. On account of the<lb/>cone of ashes being generally covered<lb/>with clouds during this time, and likewise<lb/>because the torrents of rain are heaviest<lb/>in its neighbourhood, currents of mud<lb/>flow down on all sides. The affrighted<lb/>peasant considers it to be water which<lb/>has risen from the interior of the crater,<lb/>and the deceived geognost conceives that<lb/>he recognises in it either sea-water, or<lb/>mud-like volcanic productions, which are<lb/>called <hi rendition="#i">eruptions boueses,</hi> or, as the old<lb/>French systematic writers termed them,<lb/>products of a fiery-aqueous liquefaction.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="253" facs="#f0005" />
                    <cb/>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Constitution and Mode of Action of<lb/>Volcanoes, in different Parts of the<lb/>Earth.</hi> By Alexander Von Humboldt.<lb/>Read before the Royal Academy of Sciences of Berlin.<lb/>Jan. 24. 1823.</head>
                <lb/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>No. IV.</head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>When the summits of volcanoes (as is<lb/>generally the case in the chain of the An-<lb/>des,) extend into the region of eternal<lb/>snow, or even to double the height of<lb/>&#x00C6;tna, the melted snow renders the in-<lb/>undations amazingly frequent and destruc-<lb/>tive. They are phenomena meteorologi-<lb/>cally connected with volcanic eruptions,<lb/>and are multifariously modified by the<lb/>altitude of the mountains, the extent of<lb/>their summits covered with eternal snow,<lb/>and the calefaction of the sides of the cone<lb/>of ashes; but they should never be con-<lb/>sidered as real volcanic phenomena.<lb/>Subterranean lakes, in connexion with<lb/>alpine rivers, are formed both on the<lb/>slopes and at the foot of the mountains.<lb/>When the earthquakes which precede<lb/>every eruption in the chain of the Andes,<lb/>shake with mighty force the entire mass<lb/>of the volcano, the subterranean vaults<lb/>are opened, and emit, at the same time,<lb/>water, fishes, and tufa-mud. This is the<lb/>singular phenomenon that furnishes the<lb/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">pimelodes cyclopum,</hi> which the inhabitants<lb/>of the high lands of Quito call <hi rendition="#i">prenadilla,</hi>
                        <lb/>and which was described by me soon af-<lb/>ter my return. When the summit of the<lb/>mountain Carguairazo, to the north of<lb/>
                        <cb/> Chimborazo, and 18,000 feet high, fell,<lb/>in the night between the 19 and 20th of<lb/>June, 1698, the surrounding fields, to the<lb/>extent of about 43 English square miles,<lb/>were covered with mud and fishes. The<lb/>fever which raged in the town of Ibarra,<lb/>seven years before, had been ascribed to<lb/>a simular eruption of fishes from the vol-<lb/>cano Imbaburu. I recur to these facts,<lb/>because they throw some light on the dif-<lb/>ference between the eruption of ashes,<lb/>and that of mud-like masses of tufa and<lb/>trass, which contain wood, coal, and<lb/>shells.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>The quantity of ashes ejected by Ve-<lb/>suvius in the late eruptions like all other<lb/>things which are connected with great and<lb/>appalling phenomena, has been enor-<lb/>mously exaggerated in the public papers;<lb/>and two Neapolitan chemists, Vincenzo<lb/>Pepe, and Giuseppe di Nobili, have af-<lb/>firmed, that they contain gold and silver,<lb/>notwithstanding the contradiction of Mon-<lb/>ticelli and Covelli. According to my ex-<lb/>amination, the stratum of ashes which had<lb/>fallen in twelve days, towards Bosche tre<lb/>Case, on the slope of the cone, where<lb/>rapilli were mixed with it, was only three<lb/>feet in thickness, and in the plain, it did<lb/>not exceed from 15 to 18 inches. Mea-<lb/>surements of this kind must not be made<lb/>in places where the ashes have been<lb/>drifted by wind, like snow, or sand, nor<lb/>in those where they have been accumu-<lb/>lated by water. The times are past<lb/>in which we sought only for the marvel-<lb/>lous in volcanic phenomena, and, like<lb/>Ctesias, made the ashes of &#x00C6;tna fly to the<lb/>Indian peninsula. Some of the Mexican<lb/>gold and silver mines are certainly in<lb/>trachytic porphyry, but in the ashes of<lb/>Vesuvius which I collected, and which,<lb/>at my desire, have been analyzed by<lb/>Henry Rose, of Berlin, an excellent che-<lb/>mist, no traces of either metal could be<lb/>discovered.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>However great may be the discrepan-<lb/>cy between the results that I have here<lb/>given, but which agree with Monticelli&#x2019;s<lb/>more exact observations, and those<lb/>which have been circulated during sever-<lb/>al months past, yet the eruption of ashes<lb/>from Vesuvius, from the 24th to the 28th<lb/>of October, still remains the most re-<lb/>markable of which we have any certain<lb/>account since the death of the elder<lb/>Pliny. Its quantity perhaps was three<lb/>times as great as that of all the ashes,<lb/>collectively, which have been @bserved<lb/>to fall, during the time in which volcanic<lb/>phenomena have been attentively con-<lb/>sidered. A stratum of from 15 to 18 in-<lb/>ches in thickness, seems at first view<lb/>unimportant, if compared to the mass<lb/>with which we find Pompeii to be cover-<lb/>ed; but without speaking of the torrents<lb/>and inundations which certainly may<lb/>have increased this mass for centuries,<lb/>without renewing the violent dispute<lb/>concerning the cause of the destruction<lb/>of the Campanian towns, which have been<lb/>carried on with so much skepticism on<lb/>the other side of the Alps, it may be af-<lb/>firmed that the eruptions of one and<lb/>the same volcano at distant periods can<lb/>by no means be compared with respect<lb/>to their intensity. All conclusions found-<lb/>ed on analogy are insufficient, when the<lb/>question is about quantitative propor-<lb/>tions,&#x2014;the quantity of ashes and lava, the<lb/>height of the column of smoke, or the<lb/>violence of the detonation.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>From the geographical description of<lb/>Strabo, and from an opinion of Vitruvius<lb/>concerning the volcanic origin of pumice,<lb/>we see that until the year in which Ves-<lb/>pasian died, that is to say, until the erup-<lb/>tion which overwhelmed Pompeii, Ve-<lb/>suvius was more like an extinguished<lb/>volcane than a solfataro.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>When after long rest the subterranean<lb/>powers suddenly open new passages, and<lb/>again break through beds of primitive<lb/>rocks and of trachyte, effects must<lb/>necessarily take place, for which all the<lb/>phenomena subsequently observed do<lb/>not afford any standard of comparison.<lb/>
                        <pb n="254" facs="#f0006" /> It may be clearly seen from the well-<lb/>known letter in which the younger Pliny<lb/>announces the death of his uncle to Ta-<lb/>citus, that the recommencement of the<lb/>eruptions, I might say, the awakening of<lb/>the dormant volcano, began with an<lb/>eruption of ashes. The same circum-<lb/>stance was observed at Xorullo, in Sept.<lb/>1759, when the new volcano, breaking<lb/>through beds of syenite and trachyte,<lb/>suddenly arose in the plain. The pea-<lb/>sants fled, because they found in their<lb/>huts, ashes that had been ejected from<lb/>the fissures of the earth, which was burst<lb/>in every place. Every partial eruption,<lb/>in the periodical general eruptions of<lb/>volcanoes, terminates with a shower of<lb/>ashes.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>There is a passage in Pliny&#x2019;s letter,<lb/>which shows, that the dry ashes which<lb/>had fallen from the air had already at-<lb/>tained a height of from four to five feet,<lb/>in the commencement of the eruption,<lb/>and without the effect of accumulation by<lb/>water. &#x201C;The court which led to his<lb/>[uncle&#x2019;s] apartment,&#x201D; he says, &#x201C;being<lb/>now almost filled with ashe@ and pumice,<lb/>would have been impossible for him, if<lb/>he had continued there any longer, to<lb/>have made his way out.&#x201D; In the narrow<lb/>space of a court, the wind could not<lb/>have had any great effect in accumulat-<lb/>ing the ashes.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>I have ventured to interrupt my com-<lb/>parative view of volcanoes by observa-<lb/>tions solely on Vesuvius, partly on ac-<lb/>count of the great interest which the last<lb/>eruption has excited, and partly because<lb/>every great fall of ashes almost involun-<lb/>tarily reminds us of the classic ground of<lb/>Pompeii and Herculaneum. We have<lb/>hitherto considered the form and the ef-<lb/>fects of those volcanoes which are in<lb/>permanent communication with the in-<lb/>terior of the earth, by means of a crater<lb/>Their summits are raised masses of tra-<lb/>chyte and lava, intersected by numerous<lb/>veins; the duration of their effects<lb/>causes us to believe that they have a<lb/>very stable and undisturbed structure.<lb/>They posess, I may say, a more indivi-<lb/>dual character, which remains the same<lb/>during long periods. Neighbouring<lb/>mountains often furnish completely dif-<lb/>ferent products, leucite-lava, and felspar-<lb/>lava; obsidian, with pumice, and basaltic<lb/>masses containing olivine. They belong<lb/>to the newer phenomena of the earth,<lb/>pass generally through all the strata of<lb/>secondary rocks, and their eruptions and<lb/>currents of lava are of later origin than<lb/>our valleys. Their life, if I may use<lb/>that expression, depends upon the man-<lb/>ner and duration of their connexion with<lb/>the interior of the earth. They often<lb/>rest for centuries, suddenly take fire<lb/>again, and terminate as solfataras, which<lb/>emit steam, gases, and acids. Some-<lb/>times, as on the Peak of Teneriffe, their<lb/>summit has already become such a de-<lb/>pository of reproduced sulphur, while<lb/>mighty currents of lava flow from the<lb/>sides of the mountain, like the basalt be-<lb/>low, and above, where the pressure is<lb/>less, like obsidian with pumice.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb/>
            <pb n="261" facs="#f0007" />
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Constitution and Mode of Action of<lb/>Volcanoes, in different Parts of the<lb/>Earth.</hi> By Alexander Von Humboldt.<lb/>Read before the Royal Academy of Sciences of Berlin.<lb/>Jan. 24. 1823.</head>
                <lb/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>No. V.</head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>Independently of these with perma-<lb/>nent craters, volcanic phenomena of<lb/>another kind exist, which have been ob-<lb/>served less frequently, but are princi-<lb/>pally interesting in geognosy, and remind<lb/>us of the primitive world; that is to say,<lb/>of the earliest revolutions of our earth.<lb/>Mountains of trachyte suddenly open, eject<lb/>lava and ashes, and close again, perhaps,<lb/>for ever; thus was it with the mighty An-<lb/>tisana; and thus with the Epom&#x00E6;us, in Is-<lb/>chia, in 1302. Such an eruption sometimes<lb/>takes place even in the plain as in the high<lb/>lands of Quito; in Iceland, far from<lb/>Hecla; and in Eub&#x0153;a, in the Lelantic<lb/>fields. Many of the islands which have<lb/>been raised up are owing to these tem-<lb/>porary phenomena. In these cases the<lb/>communication with the interior of the<lb/>earth is not permanent, and the effect<lb/>ceases as soon as the fissure, which is the<lb/>communicating channel, is closed again.<lb/>The veins of basalt, dolerite, and por-<lb/>phyry, which, in different parts of the<lb/>world, pass through every formation;<lb/>and those of syenite, augite-porphyry,<lb/>and amygdaloid, which are characteristic<lb/>of the newest strata of the transition for-<lb/>mation, and of the oldest rocks of the se-<lb/>condary strata, have probably been form-<lb/>ed in a similar manner. In the first age<lb/>of our planet, the yet liquid substances<lb/>penetrated through the crust of the earth,<lb/>which was every where intersected by<lb/>fissures, and assumed the form of granu-<lb/>lar rocks, either in veins, or spreading<lb/>over and expanding themselves in strata.<lb/>The rocks strictly volcanic which the<lb/>primitive ages have afforded us, have<lb/>not flowed in currents like the lava of<lb/>our insulated conical hills; the same<lb/>mixture of augite, titaniferous iron, glassy<lb/>felspar, and hornblende, may have ex-<lb/>isted at different periods, but at one time<lb/>it may have approached nearer to basalt,<lb/>and at others to trachyte; the chemical<lb/>substances may have combined in a crys-<lb/>talline form, in distinct proportions, as<lb/>we are taught by M. Mitscherlich&#x2019;s new<lb/>and important labours, and by the analo-<lb/>gy of artificial products of fire: we find<lb/>that substances similarly formed have ar-<lb/>rived at the surface of the earth in very<lb/>different ways; they have either been<lb/>
                        <pb n="262" facs="#f0008" />
                        <cb/> merely raised, or protruded by tempo-<lb/>rary fissures through the older strata;<lb/>that is to say, through the already oxi-<lb/>dized surface of the earth; or they have<lb/>flowed, as currents of lava, from conical<lb/>hills with a permanent crater. By con-<lb/>founding such different phenomena toge-<lb/>ther, the geognosy of volcanoes is carried<lb/>back to that darkness from which a great<lb/>number of comparative observations are<lb/>beginning to extricate it.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>The question has often been asked,<lb/>What is it that burns in volcanoes?<lb/>What was it that excited the heat by<lb/>which earths and metals were melted?<lb/>Modern chemistry answers, that the sub-<lb/>stances which melt are the metals of the<lb/>earths and alkalies. The solid crust of<lb/>the earth, already oxidized, separated<lb/>the surrounding air with its oxygen, from<lb/>the combustible unoxidized substances<lb/>of the interior of our planet. The ob-<lb/>servations which have been made in<lb/>mines and caves in every zone, and<lb/>which, in conjunction with M. Arago, I<lb/>have collected in a particular paper, de-<lb/>monstrate that the heat of the mass of the<lb/>earth is yet much greater than the mean<lb/>temperature of the atmosphere at the<lb/>same place. Such a remarkable and al-<lb/>most generally proved fact, is closely<lb/>connected with those which are proved<lb/>by volcanic phenomena. Laplace has<lb/>even gone so far as to endeavour to cal-<lb/>culate the depth at which the body of<lb/>the earth may be considered to be a melt-<lb/>ed mass. Whatever doubts may be en-<lb/>tertained, notwithstanding the veneration<lb/>due to so great a name, with respect to<lb/>the numerical certainty of such a calcu-<lb/>lation, thus much remains probable; that<lb/>all volcanic phenomena originate in a<lb/>very simple cause, in a permanent or in<lb/>a variable communication between the<lb/>interior and the exterior of our planet.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>The pressure of elastic vapour forces<lb/>the melted substances upwards through<lb/>deep fissures while they are undergoing<lb/>oxidation; volcanoes, if I may so speak,<lb/>are intermitting springs of the earth; the<lb/>liquid mixtures of metals, alkalies, and<lb/>earths, which on cooling become currents<lb/>of lava, flow quietly when they are rais-<lb/>ed, and find a vent. The ancients ima-<lb/>gined, according to Plato&#x2019;s Ph&#x00E6;don, that<lb/>all volcanic currents of fire flowed in a<lb/>similar way, from the Periphlegeton.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>It may be permitted me, perhaps, to<lb/>add to these considerations one which is<lb/>still more hazardous. In this interior<lb/>heat of the earth, indicated by experi-<lb/>ments with the thermometer, and by ob-<lb/>servations on volcanoes, the cause, per-<lb/>haps, may be found, of one of the most<lb/>wonderful phenomena which the exami-<lb/>nation of fossils presents to us. Tropi-<lb/>cal forms of animals, arboriform ferns,<lb/>palms, and bamboo-like plants, lie inter-<lb/>red in the cold north. The primitive<lb/>world every where shows a distribution<lb/>of organic forms at variance with the<lb/>then existing nature of the climate. In<lb/>order to solve this important problem,<lb/>several hypotheses have been invented;<lb/>as the neighbourhood of a comet, the<lb/>altered inclination of the ecliptic, the in-<lb/>creased intensity of the solar light. Nei-<lb/>ther of these has been sufficient to satisfy<lb/>at once the astronomer, the natural phi-<lb/>losopher, and the geognost. For my<lb/>part, I leave the axis of the earth unal-<lb/>tered, as well as the light of the solar<lb/>disc, by the spots on which, a celebrated<lb/>astronomer has explained both the fertili-<lb/>ty and the unfruitfulness of the fields;<lb/>but I believe, that in every planet, inde-<lb/>pendently of its relation to a central body,<lb/>and of its astronomical situation, various<lb/>causes exist of the production of heat;<lb/>oxidation, precipitation, and a change in<lb/>the capacity of bodies; by increase of<lb/>electromagnetic charge, by the opening<lb/>of a communication between the interior<lb/>and the exterior part of the earth.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>Where the deeply cleft crust of the<lb/>earth in the primitive world radiated<lb/>heat from its fissures, whole countries,<lb/>
                        <cb/> perhaps, could produce for centuries,<lb/>palms and aborescent ferns, and sustain<lb/>all the animals of the torrid zone. Ac-<lb/>cording to this view, to which I have al-<lb/>ready alluded in a work just published,<lb/>&#x201C;Essai Géognostique sur le Gissement<lb/>des Roches dans les deux Hemispheres,&#x201D;<lb/>the temperature of volcanoes would be<lb/>that of the interior of the earth itself, and<lb/>the same cause which now occasions such<lb/>dreadful destruction, would once have<lb/>occasioned, on the newly oxidated crust<lb/>of the earth, upon the deeply cleft strata<lb/>of rocks, the most luxuriant growth of<lb/>plants in every zone.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>Even if any one should be inclined to<lb/>suppose, in order to explain the marvel-<lb/>lous distribution of tropical forms in their<lb/>ancient graves, that shaggy animals of the<lb/>elephant tribe now imbedded in icebergs,<lb/>were once peculiar to a northern cli-<lb/>mate, and that similar forms belonging to<lb/>the same primary types, like lions and<lb/>lynxes, could live in very different climates,<lb/>such an explanation could not, however,<lb/>be extended to the products of vegeta-<lb/>tion. For reasons which the physiology<lb/>of plants explains, palms, and arboriform<lb/>monocoty ledones cannot sustain the<lb/>northern cold, and in the geological pro-<lb/>blem we here speak of, it seems difficult<lb/>to me to separate plants and animals.<lb/>The same explanation must be applied to<lb/>both.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>Towards the end of this paper, I have<lb/>combined uncertain hypothetical suppo-<lb/>sitions with facts collected from the most<lb/>different parts of the world. The philo-<lb/>sophical knowledge of nature rises above<lb/>a mere description of nature. It does<lb/>not consist in a sterile aggregation of iso-<lb/>lated observations. It may sometimes be<lb/>allowed, therefore, to the curious and<lb/>ever-active mind of man, to look back<lb/>upon the past, to imagine what cannot<lb/>be clearly known, and to amuse himself<lb/>with the ancient, and, under many forms,<lb/>returning mysteries of geogony.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>