<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="41" facs="#f0001" />
<cb/>
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">Extent and Population of America.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;<lb/>The following estimate of the extent,<lb/>in square leagues, and population, of the<lb/>continent of America in 1822, was lately<lb/>transmitted by Baron de Humboldt from<lb/>Paris, to President Bolivar, with the ac-<lb/>companying letter:</p><lb/><list><item>_ _ <hi rendition="#i">Square Leagues.</hi> _ _ <hi rendition="#i">Population.</hi></item><lb/><item>Mexico, or New Spain _ _ 75,330 _ _ 6,800,000</item><lb/><item>Guatamala _ _ 16,740 _ _ 1,600,000</item><lb/><item>Cuba and Puerto Rico _ _ 4,430 _ _ 800,000</item><lb/><item>Colombia @Venezuela _ _ 33,600 _ _ 900,000</item><lb/><item>@New Grenada _ _ 58,250 _ _ 1,800,000</item><lb/><item>Peru _ _ 42,240 _ _ 1,400,000</item><lb/><item>Chi@ _ _ 14,240 _ _ 1,100,000</item><lb/><item>Buenos Ayres _ _ <hi rendition="#u">126,770</hi> _ _ <hi rendition="#u">2,000,000</hi></item><lb/><item>Total formerly Spanish _ _ 372,110 _ _ 16,400,000</item><lb/><item>United States _ _ 125,440 _ _ 10,200,000</item><lb/><item>Brazil _ _ 256,990 _ _ 4,000,000</item></list><lb/><p>The above surfaces have been calcu-<lb/>lated with great care, on maps rectified by<lb/>astronomical observations. The calcula-<lb/>tions have been several times repeated by<lb/>M. Mathieu, Member of the Board of<lb/>Longitude and of the Institute, as well as<lb/>by myself. The results differ from those<lb/><cb/>
published in 1809 in the Political Essay<lb/>on Mexico. Then the inhabited parts<lb/>alone had been calculated, without in-<lb/>cluding the desert regions, over which<lb/>the independent tribes of the indigenous<lb/>inhabitants wander. Now the whole ex-<lb/>tent of each country, to its furthest li-<lb/>mits, has been measured.</p><lb/><p>The population of the different parts of<lb/>Spanish America is very uncertain, never-<lb/>theless each portion has been calculated<lb/>according to the latest data which have<lb/>reached me. The present estimate ought<lb/>to be considered in the same light as all<lb/>my other works on America; they are no<lb/>other than essays, in which every thing<lb/>will have to be done over again. Statis-<lb/>tical calculations can only be rendered<lb/>perfect by degrees, in like manner as the<lb/>elements of meteorological and astrono-<lb/>mical tables.</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#i">Comparison.</hi>&#x2014;Spain contains 16,094<lb/>square leagues&#x2014;Europe contains 304,710<lb/>square leagues, and the whole of South-<lb/>ern America, 581,891 square leagues.</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#c">(Signed)</hi></p><closer><salute><hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi></salute></closer></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
