<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On Petrifications, or Fossil Organic Remains</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:59</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.34</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1823-On_Petrifications_or-1</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On Petrifications, or Fossil Organic Remains</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1823</date>
          <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Edinburgh Philosophical Journal&lt;/i&gt; 9:17 (Juli 1823), S. 20–35.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <relatedItem type="reprint">
            <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Essai géognostique sur le gisement des roches dans les deux hémisphères&lt;/i&gt;, Paris: Levrault 1823, S. 35–54.</bibl>
          </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="20" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On Petrifactions, or Fossil Organic Remains.</hi> By<lb break="yes"/>Baron <hi rendition="#k">Alexander Humboldt.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#in">O</hi>f</hi> the various proofs of the identity of formations in the most<lb break="yes"/>distant regions of the globe, one of the most striking, and for<lb break="yes"/>which we are indebted to the assistance of zoology, is the iden-<lb break="no"/>tity of the organic bodies contained in strata having a similar<lb break="yes"/>geological position. The researches which lead to this kind of<lb break="yes"/>proofs, have exercised the skill of the learned, since Messrs<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">De Lamarck</persName> and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Defrance</persName> began to determine the fossil<lb break="yes"/>shells of the neighbourhood of <placeName>Paris</placeName>, and since Messrs <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Cuvier</persName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName> published their memorable works on the fossil<lb break="yes"/>bones and tertiary formations. As the greater portion of the<lb break="yes"/>formations which compose the crust of our planet contain no<lb break="yes"/>organic remains, and as these remains are of very rare occur-<lb break="no"/>rence in the transition formations, and are often broken and<lb break="yes"/>difficult to detach from the rock in the older secondary forma-<lb break="no"/>tions, the study of fossil organic bodies comprehends but a small<lb break="yes"/>part of geognosy,&#x2014;a part, however, very worthy of the attention<lb break="yes" />of the philosopher. The problems which present themselves in<lb break="yes" />this department, are numerous: They bear relation to the geogra-<lb break="no" />phy of animals, whose races are extinct, and which, for this rea-<lb break="no"/>son, already belong to the history of our planet: They render<lb break="yes"/>necessary the discussion of the zoological characters, by which we<lb break="yes"/>would distinguish the different formations. To remain faithful<lb break="yes"/>to the plan which I have proposed to myself, of only consider-<lb break="no"/>ing the various objects in the most general way, I shall now<lb break="yes"/>mention those questions of <hi rendition="#i" >Geognostical Zoology</hi>, which appear<lb break="yes"/>the most important in the present state of science, and whose<lb break="yes"/>solution has been tried with more or less success. What are the<lb break="yes"/>Genera, and (if the state of preservation and degree of attach-<lb break="no"/>ment to the rock permit a more complete determination) what<lb break="yes"/>are the Species, to which the fossil remains may be referred?<lb break="yes"/>Does an exact determination of the species discover any which<lb break="yes"/>are identical with the plants and animals of the present world?<lb break="yes"/>What are the classes, the orders, and families of organized be-<lb break="no"/>ings, which present the greatest number of these analogies? In<lb break="yes"/>what proportion does the number of identical genera and species<lb break="yes" />increase, with the newness of rocks or of earthy deposits? Is the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="21" facs="#f0002"/> order observed in the superposition of transition, secondary, ter-<lb break="no"/>tiary, and alluvial formations, every where in harmony with the<lb break="yes"/>increasing analogy which the types of organization present? Do<lb break="yes"/>these types succeed each other from below upwards, passing from<lb break="yes"/>the grey-wackes and black transition limestone, through the coal<lb break="yes"/>sandstone, Alpine limestone, Jura limestone, chalk, the tertiary<lb break="yes"/>gypsum, to the fresh water and modern alluvial formations, in the<lb break="yes"/>same order which we have adopted in our systems of natural his-<lb break="no"/>tory, by arranging animals according as their structure becomes<lb break="yes"/>more complicated, and as other systems of organs are added to<lb break="yes"/>those of nutrition? Does the distribution of fossil organic bodies<lb break="yes"/>indicate a progressive development of vegetable and animal life<lb break="yes"/>upon the globe,&#x2014;a successive appearance of acotyledonous and<lb break="yes" />monocotyledonous plants, of zoophytes, crustacea, mollusca;<lb break="yes" />(cephalopoda, acephala, gasteropoda), of fishes; oviparous qua-<lb break="no" />drupeds; of dicotyledonous plants; of marine mammifera and of<lb break="yes" />terrestrial mammifera? Considering fossil organic bodies, not in<lb break="yes"/>their relation with such or such a rock in which they have been<lb break="yes"/>discovered, but simply with regard to their climacteric distribu-<lb break="no"/>tion, is an appreciable difference to be observed between the spe-<lb break="no"/>cies which predominate in the old and in the new continent, in the<lb break="yes"/>temperate climates, and under the torrid zone, in the northern<lb break="yes"/>and in the southern hemisphere? Is there a certain number of<lb break="yes"/>tropical species which are found every where, and which seem<lb break="yes"/>to announce, that, independently of a distribution of climates<lb break="yes"/>similar to the present, they have experienced, in the first age of<lb break="yes"/>the world, the high temperature which the cracked crust of the<lb break="yes"/>globe, strongly heated in its interior, had given to the ambient<lb break="yes"/>atmosphere? Can the fresh-water shells be distinguished with<lb break="yes"/>certainty, by means of precise characters, from those of marine<lb break="yes"/>origin? Is the determination of the genus sufficient for this<lb break="yes"/>purpose, or are there not (as among fishes) certain genera, the<lb break="yes"/>species of which live both in the sea and in rivers? Although,<lb break="yes"/>in some of the tertiary rocks, the fluviatile shells occur mixed<lb break="yes"/>(for example, at the mouths of our rivers) with the pelagic<lb break="yes"/>shells, do we not observe, that the first form particular de-<lb break="no"/>posits, characterizing formations, the examination of which has<lb break="yes"/>been hitherto neglected, and which are of very recent origin?<lb break="yes"/>Have fresh-water shells ever been discovered under the <placeName>Jura</placeName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="22" facs="#f0003"/> limestone, among reputed fluviatile fishes, in the bituminous<lb break="yes"/>slate of the <placeName>Alpine</placeName> limestone? Do identical species of petrifac-<lb break="no"/>tions or fossils occur in the same formations in different points of<lb break="yes"/>the globe? Are they capable of furnishing zoological characters<lb break="yes"/>for distinguishing the different formations? Or, should it not<lb break="yes" />rather be admitted, that species which the zoologist is entitled to<lb break="yes"/>consider as identical, following the methods usually adopted,<lb break="yes"/>penetrate across several formations; that they are even seen in<lb break="yes"/>those which are not in immediate contact? Should not the<lb break="yes"/>zoological characters be taken both from the total absence of<lb break="yes"/>certain species, and from their relative frequency or <hi rendition="#i">predomi-<lb break="no"/>nance</hi>, as well as from their constant association with a certain<lb break="yes"/>number of other species? Is it right to divide a formation,<lb break="yes"/>whose unity has been determined from relations of position, and<lb break="yes"/>from the identity of the beds, which are equally interposed be-<lb break="no"/>tween upper and lower strata, merely because the first of these<lb break="yes"/>strata contain fresh-water shells, while the last contain marine<lb break="yes"/>ones? Is the total absence of organic bodies in certain masses<lb break="yes"/>of secondary and tertiary formations, a sufficient reason for con-<lb break="no"/>sidering these masses as particular formations, if other geognos-<lb break="no"/>tical relations do not justify this separation?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Some of these problems engaged the attention of geologists at an<lb break="yes" />early period. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Lister</persName> had already maintained, upwards of 150 years<lb break="yes"/>ago, that each rock was characterized by different fossil shells,&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>(<bibl>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Philosophical Trans.</hi>, No. 76, p. 2283.</bibl>) With the view of pro-<lb break="no"/>ving that the shells of our seas and lakes are specifically different<lb break="yes"/>from fossil shells (<hi rendition="#i" >lapides sui generis),</hi> he affirms, &#x201C;that the<lb break="yes" />latter, for example, those of the Northamptonshire quarries,<lb break="yes" />have all the characters of our <hi rendition="#i">murices, tellin&#x00E6;,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">trochi;</hi> but<lb break="yes" />that naturalists, who are not accustomed to content themselves<lb break="yes" />with a vague and general perception of things, will find the fos-<lb break="no"/>sil shells <hi rendition="#i">specifically</hi> different from those of the present world.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>Nearly at the same period, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Nicolas Stenon</persName>, (<bibl>
                        <hi rendition="#i">De solido intra<lb break="yes"/>solidum contento</hi>, 1669, p. 2, 17, 28, 63, 69, fig. 20, 25,</bibl>)<lb break="yes"/>first distinguished &#x201C;the (primitive) rocks anterior to the<lb break="yes" />existence of plants and animals upon the globe, and conse-<lb break="no" />quently never containing organic remains, and the (secondary)<lb break="yes" />rocks superimposed upon the first, and abounding with these<lb break="yes" />remains (<hi rendition="#i">turbidi maris sedimenta sibi invicem imposita</hi>).&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="23" facs="#f0004"/> He considered each bed of secondary rock &#x201C;as a sediment de-<lb break="no"/>posited by an aqueous fluid;&#x201D; and, exposing a system perfectly<lb break="yes"/>similar to that of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Deluc</persName>, &#x201C;On the formation of valleys by longi-<lb break="no"/>tudinal sinkings, and on the inclination of beds originally all<lb break="yes"/>horizontal,&#x201D; he admits, with regard to <placeName>Tuscany</placeName>, in the manner<lb break="yes"/>of our modern geologists, &#x201C;six great epochs of nature (<hi rendition="#i">sex dis-<lb break="no"/>tinct&#x00E6; <placeName>Etruri&#x00E6;</placeName> facies, ex pr&#x00E6;sente facie <placeName>Etruri&#x00E6;</placeName> collect&#x00E6;</hi>), ac-<lb break="no"/>cording as the sea periodically inundated the continent, or re-<lb break="no"/>tired within its ancient limits.&#x201D; In those times, when the obser-<lb break="no"/>vation of nature gave rise in <placeName>Italy</placeName> to the first ideas regarding<lb break="yes"/>the relative age and succession of the primitive and secondary<lb break="yes"/>strata, zoology and geognosy could not yet be of mutual assist-<lb break="no"/>ance, because the zoologists of those days were not acquainted<lb break="yes"/>with the rocks, and the geognosts were entirely strangers to the<lb break="yes"/>natural history of animals. Naturalists confined themselves to<lb break="yes"/>vague perceptions; they regarded as specifically identical all<lb break="yes"/>that presented any analogy of form; but, at the same time, and<lb break="yes"/>this was a step made in the true road, they were attentive to<lb break="yes"/>the fossils found in such or such rocks. Hence the denomina-<lb break="no"/>tions <hi rendition="#i">limestone with gryphites, limestone with trochites, slates<lb break="yes"/>with ferns,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">slates with trilobites,</hi> (Gryphiten und Trochiten-<lb break="maybe"/>Kalk, Kräuter und Trilobiten-Schiefer), were long ago em-<lb break="no"/>ployed by the mineralogists of <placeName>Germany</placeName>. The determination<lb break="yes"/>of genera whose characters are derived from the teeth, and<lb break="yes"/>other parts of the hinge, and from the opening of the shell, is<lb break="yes"/>much more difficult in the oldest secondary rocks than in the<lb break="yes"/>tertiary formations, the former being in general harder, and ad-<lb break="no"/>hering more closely to the body of the shell. This difficulty<lb break="yes" />increases, when it is attempted to distinguish the species; it be-<lb break="no"/>comes almost insurmountable in some limestone-rocks of the<lb break="yes"/>Transition class, and in the shell-limestone or muschelkalk,<lb break="yes"/>which contains broken shells. Could the zoological characters<lb break="yes"/>of a certain number of formations be taken from very distinct<lb break="yes"/>genera, and did the trilobites and orthoceratites belong exclu-<lb break="no"/>sively to the transition formations, the gryphites to the alpine<lb break="yes"/>limestone (zechstein), the pectinites to the variegated sandstone<lb break="yes"/>or <hi rendition="#i">bunter</hi> sandstone (grès de Nebra), the trochites and mytilites<lb break="yes"/>to the shell-limestone (muschelkalk), the tellin&#x00E6; to the quader-<lb break="no" />sandstein, the ammonites and turritell&#x00E6; to the Jura limestone<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="24" facs="#f0005"/> and its marls, the ananchytes and spatangi to the chalk, the ceri-<lb break="no"/>thia to the coarse limestone; the knowledge of these genera<lb break="yes"/>would prove an easy and effectual aid in the determination of<lb break="yes"/>rocks: it would no longer be requisite to examine the super-<lb break="no"/>position of formations on the spot, for they could be distin-<lb break="no"/>guished without stirring from one&#x2019;s cabinet, by the mere exami-<lb break="no"/>nation of specimens. But it is far from being the case that na-<lb break="no"/>ture has rendered the study of the shelly masses which compose<lb break="yes"/>the crust of the earth so easy to man. The same types of orga-<lb break="no"/>nization are repeated at very different epochs. The same<lb break="yes"/>genera occur in different formations. There are orthoceratites<lb break="yes"/>in the transition-limestones, the Alpine limestones, and the<lb break="yes"/>variegated sandstone; terebratulites in the Jura limestone and<lb break="yes"/>shell-limestone (muschelkalk); trilobites in the transition clay-<lb break="no"/>slates (thonschiefer), in the bituminous marl-slate, and, ac-<lb break="no"/>cording to an excellent geognost, M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Schlottheim</persName>, even<lb break="yes"/>in the Jura limestone. There are pentacrinites in the transi-<lb break="no"/>tion clay-slate and the newest shell-limestone (muschelkalk).<lb break="yes"/>The ammonites penetrate across many of the limestone and<lb break="yes"/>marl formations, from the greywackes to the lower beds of the<lb break="yes"/>chalk. Trunks of monocotyledonous plants are found both in<lb break="yes"/>the red sandstone and in the marls of the fresh-water gypsum,<lb break="yes"/>formed at a period when the world was already filled with mo-<lb break="no"/>nocotyledonous vegetables.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But at a period when naturalists are no longer satisfied with<lb break="yes" />vague and uncertain notions, it has been discovered that the<lb break="yes" />greater number of those petrifactions or fossils (gryphites, tere-<lb break="no"/>bratulites, ammonites, trilobites, &amp;c.) imbedded in different for-<lb break="no"/>mations, are not specifically the same; and that a great number<lb break="yes"/>of species which have been determined with precision, vary with<lb break="yes"/>the superimposed rocks. The fishes which are observed in the<lb break="yes"/>transition-slates (<placeName>Glaris</placeName>), in the zechstein or bituminous marl-<lb break="no"/>slate, in the Jura limestone, in the tertiary limestone with ceri-<lb break="no"/>thia of <placeName>Paris</placeName> and <placeName>Monte Bolca</placeName>, and in the gypsum of <placeName>Mont-<lb break="no"/>martre</placeName>, are distinct species, partly pelagic and partly fluviatile.<lb break="yes"/>Might it be concluded, from these facts, that all the formations<lb break="yes"/>are characterised by particular species; that the fossil-shells of<lb break="yes"/>the chalk, of the shell-limestone (muschelkalk), of the Jura<lb break="yes"/>limestone, and of the alpine limestone, are all different from<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="25" facs="#f0006"/> each other? I am <choice><sic>of</sic><corr type="editorial">of the</corr></choice> opinion that this would be pushing the<lb break="yes"/>induction too far; and even M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>, who was so well ac-<lb break="no"/>quainted with the value of zoological characters, has limited<lb break="yes"/>their absolute application to cases where the superposition (the<lb break="yes"/>circumstances of relative situation) do not oppose it. I might<lb break="yes"/>mention the cerithia of the coarse limestone, which occur (near<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName>Caen</placeName>) beneath the chalk, and which seem, like the repetition of<lb break="yes"/>the clays with lignites above and below the chalk, to shew a certain<lb break="yes"/>connection between formations which at first sight might be con-<lb break="no"/>sidered entirely distinct. I might adduce other species of shells,<lb break="yes"/>which belong at once to several tertiary formations, and observe,<lb break="yes"/>that should species, which at the present day are believed to be<lb break="yes"/>identical, be separated at some future time by means of charac-<lb break="no"/>ters not readily observable, and by slight shades of difference,<lb break="yes"/>even the delicacy of these distinctions would not prove too great<lb break="yes"/>an inducement to believe in the universality, otherwise so desi-<lb break="no"/>rable, of zoological characters in geognosy. Another objection,<lb break="yes"/>taken from the influence exercised by climate even upon the<lb break="yes"/>pelagic animals, appears to me more important still. Although<lb break="yes"/>the seas, from well-known physical causes, present at great<lb break="yes"/>depths the same temperature under the equator and in the tem-<lb break="no"/>perate zone, we find, however, that, in the present state of our<lb break="yes"/>planet, the shells of the Tropics (among which the univalves<lb break="yes"/>predominate, as among the fossil testacea) differ much from<lb break="yes"/>those of the temperate climates. The greater number of these<lb break="yes"/>animals live upon reefs and shoals; whence it follows that the<lb break="yes"/>specific differences are often very sensible, under the same paral-<lb break="no"/>lel, on opposite coasts. Now, were the same formations repeated<lb break="yes"/>and extended, so to speak, to prodigious distances, from east to<lb break="yes" />west, and from north to south, from one hemisphere to the other,<lb break="yes"/>is it not probable, whatever may have been the complicated<lb break="yes"/>causes of the ancient temperature of our globe, that variations<lb break="yes"/>of climate have modified, in ancient times as at the present, the<lb break="yes"/>types of organisation, and that one and the same formation<lb break="yes"/>(that is to say, a rock of the same nature placed, in the two<lb break="yes"/>hemispheres, between homogeneous formations) may have en-<lb break="no"/>veloped distinct species? It no doubt often happens, that super-<lb break="no"/>imposed beds present a very striking contrast of fossil bodies;<lb break="yes"/>but should it be concluded from this, that, after a deposit was<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="26" facs="#f0007"/> formed, the beings which then inhabited the surface of the globe<lb break="yes"/>were all destroyed?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is incontestible, that generations of different types have<lb break="yes" />succeeded one another. The ammonites, which scarcely occur<lb break="yes" />among the transition rocks, attain their <hi rendition="#i">maximum</hi> in the strata<lb break="yes"/>which on different points of the globe represent the shell-lime-<lb break="no"/>stone (muschelkalk) and Jura limestone; they disappear in the<lb break="yes"/>upper beds of the chalk, and above this formation. The echi-<lb break="no"/>nites, which are very rare in the alpine limestone, and even in<lb break="yes"/>the shell-limestone (muschelkalk), become, on the contrary, very<lb break="yes"/>common in the Jura limestone, in the chalk and the tertiary<lb break="yes"/>formations. But nothing proves to us that this succession of<lb break="yes"/>different organic types, this gradual destruction of genera and<lb break="yes"/>of species, necessarily coincides with the periods when each for-<lb break="no"/>mation was deposited. &#x201C;The consideration of similarity, or of<lb break="yes"/>discrepancy between organic remains, is not of great import-<lb break="no"/>ance,&#x201D; says M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Beudant</persName> (<bibl>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Voyages Min.</hi> v. iii. p. 278.</bibl>), &#x201C;when<lb break="yes"/>we compare deposits formed in countries very remote from each<lb break="yes"/>other; but it is of much importance, when we compare those<lb break="yes"/>which are very near.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In combating the two absolute conclusions which might be<lb break="yes" />attempted to be derived from the validity of zoological charac-<lb break="no" />ters, I am far from denying the important services which the<lb break="yes" />study of fossil bodies renders to geognosy, if we consider this<lb break="yes" />science under a philosophical point of view. Geognosy does not<lb break="yes" />limit itself to the searching for diagnostical characters; it em-<lb break="no"/>braces the aggregate of relations under which each formation<lb break="yes"/>may be considered: 1<hi rendition="#i">st</hi>, Its relative position; 2<hi rendition="#i">dly</hi>, Its oryc-<lb break="no"/>tognostic constitution (that is to say, its chemical composition,<lb break="yes"/>and the particular mode of aggregation, more or less crystalline,<lb break="yes"/>of its molecules); 3<hi rendition="#i">dly</hi>, The association of different organic bo-<lb break="no"/>dies which occur imbedded in it. If the superposition of hete-<lb break="no"/>rogeneous rocky masses reveals to us the successive order of<lb break="yes"/>their formation, is it not also interesting to know the state of or-<lb break="no"/>ganic nature at the different periods when these deposits were<lb break="yes"/>formed? Can it be questioned, that, over a surface of many<lb break="yes"/>thousands of square leagues (in <placeName>Thuringia</placeName>, and in all the north-<lb break="no"/>ern part of <placeName>Germany</placeName>), nine superimposed formations, those,<lb break="yes"/>namely, of the transition limestone, greywacke, red sandstone,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="27" facs="#f0008"/> zechstein with bituminous marl-slate, (muriatiferous gypsum,)<lb break="yes"/>oolitic sandstone, (argillaceous gypsum,) shell limestone or<lb break="yes"/>muschelkalk, and white sandstone (quadersandstein), have been<lb break="yes"/>recognised as distinct, without having any recourse to geological<lb break="yes"/>characters; but it does not follow from thence, that the most mi-<lb break="no"/>nute investigation of these characters, or, to speak more correctly,<lb break="yes"/>the most intimate knowledge of the petrifactions or fossils con-<lb break="no"/>tained in each of the formations, is not indispensable for present-<lb break="no"/>ing a complete and truly geognostical picture. It is with the study<lb break="yes"/>of formations as with that of organic beings. Botany and zoology,<lb break="yes"/>which are now considered under a higher point of view, are no<lb break="yes"/>longer confined to the investigation of some external characters<lb break="yes"/>distinctive of the species; these sciences investigate the whole of<lb break="yes"/>vegetable and animal organization. The characters taken from<lb break="yes"/>the forms of the shell, suffice to distinguish the different species<lb break="yes"/>of acephalous testacea; but, for all this, could the knowledge of<lb break="yes" />the animals which inhabit these shells be regarded as superflu-<lb break="no" />ous? Such is the connexion of phenomena, and of their natu-<lb break="no"/>ral relations, that, if some be neglected, there is produced not<lb break="yes" />only an incomplete image, but also a false one.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the case of the conformity of position, there may be iden-<lb break="no"/>tity of mass (that is to say, of mineralogical composition) and<lb break="yes" />diversity of petrifactions, or diversity of mass and identity of pe-<lb break="no"/>trifactions. The rocks &#x03B2; and &#x03B2;&#x2032;, placed at great horizontal dis-<lb break="no"/>tances, between two identical formations &#x03B1; and &#x03B3;, either belong<lb break="yes"/>to the same formation, or are of parallel formations. In the<lb break="yes"/>former case, their mineral composition is similar; but, from the<lb break="yes"/>distance of the places, and the effects of climate, the organic re-<lb break="no"/>mains which they contain may differ considerably. In the other<lb break="yes"/>case, the mineralogical composition is different, but the organic<lb break="yes"/>remains may be analogous. I am of opinion that the words<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">identical formations, parallel formations,</hi> vindicate the confor-<lb break="no"/>mity or non-conformity of mineralogical composition; but that<lb break="yes"/>they determine nothing with regard to the identity of petrifac-<lb break="no"/>tions. If it is pretty probable that the deposits &#x03B2; and &#x03B2;&#x2032;, placed<lb break="yes"/>at great horizontal distances between the same rocks &#x03B1; and &#x03B3;,<lb break="yes"/>have been formed <hi rendition="#i">at the same period</hi>, because they contain the<lb break="yes"/>same fossils, and an analogous mass; it is not equally probable,<lb break="yes"/>on the other hand, that when the fossils are distinct, the periods<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="28" facs="#f0009"/> of formation have been very remote from each other. We<lb break="yes"/>may conceive that, under the same zone, in a country of but<lb break="yes"/>little extent, generations of animals have succeeded each other,<lb break="yes"/>and have characterised, as by particular types, the <hi rendition="#i">periods</hi> of<lb break="yes"/>formation; but, at great horizontal distances, beings of very dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent forms, may, in different climates, have simultaneously<lb break="yes"/>occupied the surface of the globe, or the basin of the ocean.<lb break="yes"/>Further still, the position of &#x03B2;, between &#x03B1; and &#x03B3;, proves that the<lb break="yes"/>formation of &#x03B2; is anterior to that of &#x03B3;, and posterior to that of<lb break="yes"/>&#x03B1;; but nothing gives us the precise measure of the interval be-<lb break="no"/>tween the epochal limits, and different isolated deposits of &#x03B2; can-<lb break="no"/>not be simultaneous.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There seems to result from the facts which the zeal and saga-<lb break="no"/>city of naturalists have united within these few years, that, if<lb break="yes"/>we should not always expect to find, as <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/" >Lister</persName> pretended, in<lb break="yes"/>each different formation different organic remains, yet that most<lb break="yes"/>commonly formations which are shewn to be distinct by their<lb break="yes"/>relative situation and composition, contain in the most remote<lb break="yes"/>countries of the globe associations of entirely similar species.<lb break="yes"/>M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>, whose labours, together with those of other ce-<lb break="no"/>lebrated mineralogists, have so much advanced the study of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">subterranean conchology</hi>, has lately made known the striking<lb break="yes"/>analogies which certain formations of <placeName>Europe</placeName> and of <placeName>North Ame-<lb break="no" />rica</placeName> present with regard to fossil organic bodies. He has endea-<lb break="no"/>voured to prove that a formation is sometimes so disguised, that<lb break="yes"/>it is only by its zoological characters that it can be recognised,<lb break="yes"/>(<bibl>
                        <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Hist. Nat. des Crust. Fossiles,</hi> p. 57, 62</bibl>). In<lb break="yes"/>the study of formations, as in all the descriptive physical scien-<lb break="no"/>ces, it is the assemblage of many characters which should alone<lb break="yes"/>guide us in our search after truth. The specific description of<lb break="yes"/>the remains of plants and animals contained in the different for-<lb break="no"/>mations, presents us, so to speak, their <hi rendition="#i">Flora</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">Fauna</hi>. Now, in<lb break="yes"/>the primordial, as in the present world, the vegetation and the<lb break="yes"/>animal productions of different portions of the globe, appear to<lb break="yes"/>have been less characterised by some isolated forms of an extra-<lb break="no"/>ordinary aspect, than by the association of many forms specifi-<lb break="no"/>cally different, but analogous to each other, notwithstanding<lb break="yes"/>the distance of the places. On discovering a new land near<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName>Torres Straits</placeName>, it would not be easy to determine, from a small<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="29" facs="#f0010"/> number of productions, whether this land were contiguous to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName>New Holland</placeName>, or to one of the <placeName>Molucca Islands</placeName>, or to <placeName>New<lb break="yes" />Guinea</placeName>. To compare formations with relation to petrifactions,<lb break="yes"/>is to compare <hi rendition="#i">Floras</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Faunas</hi> of different countries and of<lb break="yes" />different epochs; it is to resolve a problem so much the more<lb break="yes" />complicated, that it is modified at the same time by space and<lb break="yes" />by time.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Among the zoological characters applied to geognosy, the<lb break="yes"/>absence of certain fossils often afford a better characteristic than<lb break="yes" />their presence. This applies particularly to the transition rocks;<lb break="yes"/>in general there only occur in them, madrepores, encrinites, trilo-<lb break="no"/>bites, orthoceratites, and shells of the family of terebratules,<lb break="yes"/>that is to say shells of which some species, not identical but<lb break="yes"/>analogous, are met with in very modern secondary beds; but<lb break="yes"/>these transition rocks are destitute of many other organic re-<lb break="no"/>mains, which appear abundantly above the red sandstone. The<lb break="yes"/>judgment which we form regarding the absence of certain<lb break="yes"/>species, or the total absence of fossil organic bodies, may, how-<lb break="no"/>ever, be founded upon an error which it will be of importance<lb break="yes"/>to explain here. On examining the formations which contain<lb break="yes"/>imbedded shells in a general manner, we observe that the or-<lb break="no"/>ganic bodies are not always equally distributed in the mass;<lb break="yes"/>but, 1<hi rendition="#i">st</hi>, That strata entirely destitute of shells alternate with<lb break="yes"/>others which are provided with them; 2<hi rendition="#i">dly</hi>, That, in the same<lb break="yes" />formation, particular associations of fossils characterize certain<lb break="yes"/>strata, which alternate with other strata having distinct fossils.<lb break="yes"/>This phenomenon, which has been long since observed, occurs in<lb break="yes"/>the shell limestone (muschelkalk,) and in the alpine limestone<lb break="yes"/>(zechstein), which are often separated by a bed of trochites from<lb break="yes"/>the coal sandstone, (<bibl>
                        <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Buch</persName>, Beob. v. i. p. 135, 146, 171</bibl>); it is<lb break="yes"/>found also in the Jura limestone, and in several tertiary forma-<lb break="no"/>tions. On examining the chalk of the neighbourhood of <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                    <lb break="yes"/>only, it might almost be thought that the univalve shells are<lb break="yes"/>entirely awanting in this formation. The polythalamous uni-<lb break="no"/>valves, however, the ammonites, as we have already mentioned,<lb break="yes"/>are very common in <placeName>England</placeName>, in the oldest beds of the chalk.<lb break="yes" />Even in <placeName>France</placeName>, (coast of <placeName>St Catherine</placeName> near <placeName>Caen</placeName>), the tuface-<lb break="no"/>ous and chloritic chalk, contains many fossils which are not met<lb break="yes"/>with in the white chalk. (<bibl>
                        <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>, Caractères Zool. p. 12.</bibl>)<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="30" facs="#f0011"/> As in different countries the formations are not equally deve-<lb break="no"/>loped, and shreds of formations may be taken for complete and<lb break="yes"/>entire ones, those which are destitute of shells in one region<lb break="yes"/>may present them in another. This consideration is important in<lb break="yes"/>obviating the pretty general tendency of multiplying formations<lb break="yes"/>in too great a degree; for when, in a particular point of the<lb break="yes"/>globe, a formation (sandstone for example) abounds in its lower<lb break="yes"/>part with petrifactions, while its upper part is entirely destitute<lb break="yes"/>of them, this absence of petrifactions or fossils does not of itself<lb break="yes"/>justify the splitting of the deposit into two distinct formations.<lb break="yes"/>In the geological description of the neighbourhood of <placeName>Paris</placeName>, M.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName> has very properly united the millstones without<lb break="yes"/>shells, with those which are in a manner studded with fresh-<lb break="no"/>water shells.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We have seen that a formation may contain in different<lb break="yes"/>strata, petrifactions specifically different, but that most commonly<lb break="yes" />some species of the lower stratum mingle with the great mass of<lb break="yes" />heterogeneous species which occur united in the superimposed<lb break="yes" />stratum. When this difference relates to genera, of which some<lb break="yes" />are pelagic and others fresh-water shells, the problem of the<lb break="yes" />unity or indivisibility of a formation becomes still more puzzling.<lb break="yes"/>Two cases must first be distinguished, that in which some fluvi-<lb break="no"/>atile shells occur, mixed with a great mass of marine shells, and<lb break="yes"/>that where marine and fluviatile shells may alternate bed by<lb break="yes"/>bed. Messrs <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Gilet de Laumont</persName> and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Beudant</persName>, have made interest-<lb break="no"/>ing observations regarding the admixture of marine and fresh-<lb break="no"/>water productions, in one and the same bed. M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Beudant</persName> has<lb break="yes"/>proved, by ingenious experiments, how many of the fluviatile<lb break="yes"/>mollusca gradually habituate themselves to live in a fluid which<lb break="yes"/>has all the saltness of the ocean. The same geologist has, to-<lb break="no"/>gether with M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Marcel de Serres</persName>, examined certain species of<lb break="yes"/>paludin&#x00E6;, which, preferring brackish waters, are found near our<lb break="yes"/>coasts, sometimes with pelagic shells, sometimes with fluviatile<lb break="yes"/>ones. (<bibl>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Journ. de Phys.</hi> t. lxxxiii. p. 137</bibl>; <bibl>t. lxxxviii. p. 211</bibl>;<lb break="yes"/>
                    <bibl>
                        <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Geogr. Min.</hi> p. 27, 54, 89.</bibl>) To these curious facts<lb break="yes"/>are joined others, which I have published in the account of my<lb break="yes"/>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Journey to the Equatorial Regions</hi>, (v. i. p. 535, and v. ii.<lb break="yes"/>p. 606</bibl>), and which seem to explain what has formerly taken<lb break="yes"/>place upon the globe, according to what we still see taking place<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="31" facs="#f0012"/> at the present day. On the coast of <placeName>Terra Firma</placeName>, between<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName>Cumana</placeName> and <placeName>Nueva Barcelona</placeName>, I have seen crocodiles advance<lb break="yes"/>far into the sea. Pigafetta has made the same observation re-<lb break="no"/>garding the crocodiles of <placeName>Borneo</placeName>. To the south of the <placeName>Island<lb break="yes"/>of Cuba</placeName>, in the <placeName>Gulph of Xagua</placeName>, there are lamantines in the<lb break="yes"/>sea, at a point where springs of fresh water issue in the midst<lb break="yes"/>of the salt water. When we reflect upon these facts, we be-<lb break="no"/>come less surprised at the mixture of some terrestrial produc-<lb break="no"/>tions with many others indisputably marine. The second case<lb break="yes"/>which we have adverted to, that of alternation, is never present,<lb break="yes"/>I believe, in a manner so distinct as the alternation of clay-slate<lb break="yes"/>and of black limestone, in the same transition formation, or (to<lb break="yes"/>adduce a fact relative to the distribution of organic bodies) as<lb break="yes"/>the alternation of two great marine formations, (limestone with<lb break="yes" />cerithia, and the sandstone of <placeName>Romainville</placeName>), with two great fresh-<lb break="no"/>water formations, (gypsum and millstone of the plain of <placeName>Mont-<lb break="no"/>morency</placeName>). The result of an attentive examination of the super-<lb break="no"/>positions is merely this; that there are alternating beds of gyp-<lb break="no"/>sum and marl placed between two marine formations, and con-<lb break="no"/>taining at the centre (in their largest mass), terrestrial and<lb break="yes"/>fresh-water productions, and towards the upper and inferior<lb break="yes"/>limits, as well in the gypsum as in the marls, marine produc-<lb break="no"/>tions. Such is the geological constitution of the gypsum of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName>Montmartre</placeName>. The specific variation in the petrifactions, the<lb break="yes"/>mixture observed at <placeName>Pierrelaie</placeName>, and the phenomenon of alterna-<lb break="no"/>tion which <placeName>Montmartre</placeName> presents, are not sufficient to justify the<lb break="yes"/>division of the same formation into fragments. The marls and<lb break="yes"/>gypsum which contain marine shells, (No. 26. of the third<lb break="yes"/>mass), cannot be geognostically separated from the marls and<lb break="yes"/>gypsums which contain fresh-water productions. Nor have<lb break="yes"/>Messrs <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/" >Cuvier</persName> and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/" >Brongniart</persName> hesitated to consider the general<lb break="yes" />mass of these marine and fresh-water marls and gypsums as of<lb break="yes" />one and the same formation. These geologists have even cited<lb break="yes" />this union of alternating beds as one of the clearest examples of<lb break="yes"/>what the word <hi rendition="#i">formation</hi> should be intended to express. (<placeName>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Geogr.<lb break="yes"/>Miner.</hi>, p. 31, 39, 189</placeName>). In fact, different systems of beds<lb break="yes"/>may be contained in the same formation: they are groups, sub-<lb break="no"/>divisions, or as the geognosts of the Freyberg School express it,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="32" facs="#f0013"/> members more or less developed of the same formation, (<bibl>
                        <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Freies-<lb break="no" />leben</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Kupf.</hi> v. i. p. 17. v. iii. p. 1</bibl>).</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Notwithstanding the mixture of pelagic and fluviatile shells<lb break="yes" />which is sometimes observed at the point of contact of two forma-<lb break="no"/>tions of different origin, the name of <hi rendition="#i">Marine Limestone</hi>, or of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Marine Sandstone</hi>, may be given to the one of these formations,<lb break="yes"/>when the denomination of the rocks could only be taken from the<lb break="yes"/>species which constitute the greatest mass and the centre of the<lb break="yes"/>beds. This terminology recalls a fact which bears relation, so to<lb break="yes"/>speak, to geogony, to the ancient history of our planet; it fixes<lb break="yes"/>(and perhaps a little too much) the alternation of the fresh and of<lb break="yes"/>the salt waters. I do not dispute the utility of the denominations<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">marine limestone</hi>, or <hi rendition="#i">marine sandstone</hi>, with regard to local descrip-<lb break="no"/>tions; but, according to the principles which I have proposed to<lb break="yes"/>follow, in the general classification of formations, characterized,<lb break="yes" />according to the place which they occupy, as terms of a series, I<lb break="yes"/>have deemed it necessary to avoid them with care. Are all the<lb break="yes"/>formations beneath the chalk, or even beneath the limestone,<lb break="yes"/>with cerithia (coarse limestone of the basin of <placeName>Paris</placeName>), without ex-<lb break="no"/>ception, <hi rendition="#i">marine limestones</hi> and <hi rendition="#i" >sandstones?</hi> or do the monitors<lb break="yes"/>and fishes of the bituminous copper-slate in the alpine limestone<lb break="yes"/>of <placeName>Thuringia</placeName>; the ichthyosauri of Mr Home, placed beneath the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName>Oxford</placeName> and <placeName>Bath</placeName> oolites, in the lias of <placeName>England</placeName>, (which, on the<lb break="yes" />Continent, is represented by a part of the Jura limestone); the<lb break="yes" />crocodiles of <placeName>Honfleur</placeName>, contained in clays, with limestone-beds<lb break="yes"/>above the oolites of <placeName>Dive</placeName> and <placeName>Isigny</placeName> limestone, and consequent-<lb break="no"/>ly superior to the Jura limestone,&#x2014;do all these prove, that there<lb break="yes"/>are already beneath the chalk, between that formation and the red<lb break="yes"/>sandstone, small fresh-water formations superadded to the great<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">marine formations?</hi> Do not the coals containing ferns, situated<lb break="yes"/>beneath the red-sandstone and beneath the secondary porphyry,<lb break="yes"/>present an evident example of a very ancient formation, not of<lb break="yes"/>marine origin? These circumstances show the necessity of much<lb break="yes"/>caution in the present state of science, when, from characters<lb break="yes"/>purely zoological, it is attempted to divide formations, whose uni-<lb break="no"/>ty has appeared confirmed by the alternation of the same beds,<lb break="yes"/>and by other phenomena of relative position. (<bibl>
                        <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Engelhard</persName> und<lb break="yes"/>
                        <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Raumer</persName>, <hi rendition="#i" >Geogn. Vers.</hi> p. 125.&#x2013;133.</bibl>) This caution is so much<lb break="yes"/>the more necessary, that, according to the testimony of a mine-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="33" facs="#f0014"/> ralogist who has long attended to this matter, M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>,<lb break="yes" />&#x201C;there exists a kind of transition between the marine limestone,<lb break="yes"/>and the fresh water gypsum which follows this limestone; and<lb break="yes"/>that these two formations do not present, in an abrupt man-<lb break="no"/>ner, the separation which is seen, in the same places, between the<lb break="yes"/>chalk and coarse limestone; that is to say, between two marine<lb break="yes"/>formations. It cannot be doubted,&#x201D; adds the same observer,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;that the first beds of gypsum have been deposited in a liquid<lb break="yes"/>analogous to the sea, while the following ones have been depo-<lb break="no"/>sited in a liquid analogous to fresh water.&#x201D; (<bibl>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Geogr. Min.</hi>, p. 168.<lb break="yes"/>and 193.</bibl>)</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In announcing the motives which prevent me from general-<lb break="no"/>izing a terminology founded upon the contrast between fresh-<lb break="no"/>water productions and marine ones, I am far from disputing the<lb break="yes" />existence of a fresh-water formation, superior to all the other ter-<lb break="no"/>tiary formations, and which contains only bulim&#x00E6;, limne&#x00E6;, cy-<lb break="no"/>clostomata and potamides. Recent observations have demon-<lb break="no"/>strated, that this formation is more general than was at first be-<lb break="no"/>lieved. It is a new and last term to add to the geognostical se-<lb break="no"/>ries. We are indebted for the knowledge of this fresh-water<lb break="yes"/>limestone, to the useful labours of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>. The pheno-<lb break="no" />mena which the fresh-water formations present, whose existence<lb break="yes" />was formerly known only by the tufas of <placeName>Thuringia</placeName>, and by the<lb break="yes"/>Travertine of the plains of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, (<bibl>
                        <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Reuss</persName>, <hi rendition="#i" >Geogn.</hi> v. ii. p. 642.</bibl>;<lb break="yes"/>
                    <bibl>
                        <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Buch</persName>, <hi rendition="#i" >Geog. Beob.</hi> v. ii. p. 21.&#x2013;30.</bibl>), are conformable, in the<lb break="yes"/>most satisfying manner, to the admirable laws discovered by M.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Cuvier</persName>, in the position of the bones of viviparous quadrupeds.<lb break="yes"/>(<bibl>
                        <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brongniart</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Annales du Museum</hi>, vol. <choice>
                            <sic>xv</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">xv.</corr>
                        </choice> p. 357.&#x2013;581.</bibl>; <bibl>
                        <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Cu-<lb break="no"/>vier</persName>, <hi rendition="#i">Rech. sur les Ossemens fossiles</hi>, vol. i. p. 54<choice>
                            <sic>.</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">.)</corr>
                        </choice>
                    </bibl>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The distinction between fluviatile and marine shells is the<lb break="yes" />object of very delicate inquiries; for it may happen, when the<lb break="yes" />remains of organic bodies are, with difficulty, detached from the<lb break="yes"/>siliceous limestone in which they are contained, that ampullari&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>may be confounded with natic&#x00E6;, potamides with cerithia, and so<lb break="yes"/>forth. In the family of Conch&#x00E6;, the cyclades and cyren&#x00E6;, the<lb break="yes"/>venuses and lucin&#x00E6;, cannot be separated with certainty, but by<lb break="yes"/>the examination of the teeth of the hinge. The work which M.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Ferussac</persName> has undertaken, on the terrestrial and fluviatile shells,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="34" facs="#f0015"/> will throw much light on this important subject. Besides, when a<lb break="yes"/>genus of pelagic shells is supposed to be seen in the midst of a ge-<lb break="no"/>nus of fresh water ones, it may be asked, if, in fact, the same ge-<lb break="no"/>neric types might not occur in the lakes and in the seas. We<lb break="yes"/>are already acquainted with the example of a true fluviatile my-<lb break="no"/>tilus. Perhaps the ampullari&#x00E6; and corbul&#x00E6;, may be found to<lb break="yes"/>present analogous mixtures of marine forms and of fresh-water<lb break="yes"/>ones. (See a <bibl>Memoir of <hi rendition="#i">M. Valenciennes</hi>, inserted in my <hi rendition="#i">Re-<lb break="no"/>cueil d&#x2019;Obs. de Zoologie et d&#x2019;Anatomie comparée</hi>, v. ii. p. 218</bibl>).</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It results from these general considerations regarding the<lb break="yes" />zoological characters and examination of fossil bodies, that, not-<lb break="no"/>withstanding the beautiful and old works of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Camper</persName>, of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Blu-<lb break="no"/>menbach</persName> and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Sömmering</persName>, the exact specific determination of<lb break="yes"/>species, and the examination of their relations with very mo-<lb break="no"/>dern beds, was only commenced about twenty years ago. I am<lb break="yes"/>of opinion, that this examination of fossil bodies applied to all<lb break="yes"/>the other secondary and transition strata by geognosts, who, at<lb break="yes"/>the same time, consult the relative situation and mineral com-<lb break="no"/>position of rocks, far from overturning the system of formations<lb break="yes"/>already established, would rather serve to confirm it, to perfect<lb break="yes"/>it, and to complete the vast picture which it presents. The geo-<lb break="no"/>gnostical knowledge of formations may, without doubt, be con-<lb break="no"/>sidered under very different points of views, according as the<lb break="yes"/>preference is given to the superposition of mineral masses, to<lb break="yes"/>their composition (that is to say, their chemical and mechani-<lb break="no"/>cal analysis), or to the fossils which are found contained in many<lb break="yes"/>of those masses. The denominations, <hi rendition="#i">geognosy of situation,</hi> or<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">of superposition, oryctognostic geognosy</hi> (analysing the texture<lb break="yes"/>of masses), <hi rendition="#i">geognosy of fossils,</hi> designate, I shall not say branches<lb break="yes"/>of one and the same science, but different classes of relations which<lb break="yes"/>are attempted to be isolated for their more particular examina-<lb break="no"/>tion. <hi rendition="#i">This unity of the science, and the vast field which it com-<lb break="no"/>prehends, were well known to <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Werner</persName>, the creator of positive<lb break="yes"/>geognosy.</hi> Although he did not possess the necessary means for<lb break="yes"/>giving himself up to a rigorous determination of fossil species,<lb break="yes"/>he did not cease, in his lectures, to fix the attention of his pu-<lb break="no"/>pils upon the relations which exist between certain petrifactions<lb break="yes"/>and the formations of different ages. I have been witness of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="35" facs="#f0016"/> lively satisfaction which he experienced, when, in 1792, M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de<lb break="yes" />Schlottheim</persName>, one of the most distinguished geognosts of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <placeName>Freyberg</placeName> School, began to make these relations the principal ob-<lb break="no"/>ject of his investigation. Positive geognosy enriches itself with<lb break="yes"/>all the discoveries which have been made regarding the mineral<lb break="yes"/>constitution of the globe; it contributes the most precious mate-<lb break="no"/>rials to another science, improperly called <hi rendition="#i">Theory of the Earth;</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and which embraces the first history of the catastrophes of our<lb break="yes"/>planet. It reflects more light upon this science than it receives<lb break="yes"/>from it in return; and, without calling in question the ancient flui-<lb break="no"/>dity or softening of all the rocky beds (a phenomenon which is<lb break="yes"/>manifested by fossil organic remains, by the crystalline aspect of<lb break="yes"/>the masses, and by the rolled pebbles or fragments imbedded in<lb break="yes"/>the transition and secondary rocks), positive geognosy does not<lb break="yes"/>pronounce on the nature of those liquids in which the deposits are<lb break="yes"/>alleged to have been formed, on those <hi rendition="#i">waters of granite, por-<lb break="no"/>phyry and gypsum,</hi> which, according to hypothetical geology,<lb break="yes"/>have successively covered the same points of the globe <note place="foot" n="*" >Translated from <bibl>Humboldt&#x2019;s &#x201C;Essai Geognostique sur le Gisement des Roches<lb break="yes"/>dans les deux hemispheres.&#x201D; 8vo, Paris, 1823.</bibl>
                    </note>.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 