<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Phenomena connected with an Eruption of<lb/>Vesuvius.</hi>&#x2014;</head>
                <p>In the last eruption, in the night of the<lb/>23d to the 24th of October, twenty-four hours after the<lb/>falling in of the great cone of scori@ which has been<lb/>mentioned, and when the small but numerous currents<lb/>of lava had already flowed off, the fiery eruption of<lb/>ashes and rapilli commenced; it continued without<lb/>ntermission for twelve days, but was greateat in the<lb/>first four days. During this period the d@onation@ in<lb/>the interior of the volcano were so violent that the mere<lb/>concussion of the air, (for no earthquake movement was<lb/>perceived,) rent the ceilings of the rooms in the palace<lb/>of Portici. In the neighbouring villages of Resina,<lb/>Torre del Greco, Torre del Annunziata, and Bosche<lb/>Tre Case, a remarkable phenomenon was witnessed.<lb/>Throughout the whole of that part of the country the<lb/>air was so filled with ashes as to cause in the middle<lb/>of the day profound darkness, lasting for several<lb/>hours. Lanterns were carried in the streets, as has<lb/>so often been done at Quito during the eruptions of<lb/>Pichion@. The flight of the inhabitants had never<lb/>been more general. Lava currents are regarded by<lb/>those who dwell near Vesuvius with less dread than<lb/>an eruption of ashes&#x2014;a phenomenon which had never<lb/>been known to such a degree in modern times; and<lb/>the obscure tradition of the manner in which the<lb/>destruction of Herculaneum, Pompeii, and Stabi@ took<lb/>place filled the imagination of men with appalling<lb/>images. The hot aqueous vapours which rose from<lb/>the orater during the eruption, and spread themselves<lb/>in the atmosphere, formed, in cooling, a dense cloud,<lb/>surrounding the column of fire and ashes, which rose<lb/>to a height of between nine and ten thousand feet. So<lb/>sudden a condensation of vapour, and even, as Gay-<lb/>Lussac has shown, the formation of the cloud itself,<lb/>augmented the electric tension. Flashes of forked<lb/>lightning, issuing from the column of ashes, darted<lb/>in every direction; and the rolling thunders were<lb/>distinctly heard and distinguished from the sounds<lb/>which proceeded from the interior of the volcano.<lb/>In no other eruption had the play of the electric<lb/>forces formed so striking a feature. On the morning<lb/>of the 26th of October a surprising rumour prevailed,<lb/>to the effect that a torrent of boiling water was gush-<lb/>ing from the crater, and pouring down the alope of the<lb/>cone of ashes. The learned and zealous observer<lb/>of the volcano, Monticelli, soon discovered that<lb/>this erroneous rumour had arisen from an optical<lb/>illusion. The supposed torrent of water was in<lb/>reality a flow of dry ashes, which, being as loose<lb/>and moveable as shifting sands, issued in large quan-<lb/>tities from a crevice in the upper margin of the<lb/>crater. The cultivated fields had suffered much<lb/>from a long-continued drought which had preceded<lb/>the eruption: towards its close the &#x201C;volcanic thun-<lb/>derstorm&#x201D; which has been described produced an<lb/>exceedingly violent and abundant fall of rain. This<lb/>phenomenon is associated in all climates with the<lb/>close of a volcanio eruption. As during the eruption<lb/>the cone of ashes is generally enveloped in cloud, and<lb/>as it is in its immediate vicinity that the rain is most<lb/>violent, torrents of mud are seen to descend from it in<lb/>all directions, which the terrified husbandman ima-<lb/>gines to consist of waters which have risen from the<lb/>interior of the volcano and overflowed the crater.&#x2014;<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Aspects of Nature.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>