<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On the Constitution and Mode of Action of Volcanoes, in different Parts of the Earth</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:08:59</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.37</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1823-Ueber_den_Bau-02</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1823-Ueber_den_Bau-01.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1823-Ueber_den_Bau-02.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1823-Ueber_den_Bau-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1823-Ueber_den_Bau-04.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1823-Ueber_den_Bau-05.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1823-Ueber_den_Bau-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1823-Ueber_den_Bau-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1823-Ueber_den_Bau-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1823-Ueber_den_Bau-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1823-Ueber_den_Bau-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1823-Ueber_den_Bau-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1823-Ueber_den_Bau-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1823-Ueber_den_Bau-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1823-Ueber_den_Bau-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On the Constitution and Mode of Action of Volcanoes, in different Parts of the Earth</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1823</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Annals of Philosophy&lt;/i&gt; 6:2 (August 1823), S. 121–135.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Fußnoten mit Asterisken; Schmuck: Kapitälchen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="121" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">On the Constitution and Mode of Action of Volcanoes, in differ-<lb/>ent Parts of the Earth.</hi> By Alexander Von Humboldt.<note place="foot" n="*">Read before the Royal Academy of Sciences of <placeName>Berlin</placeName>, <date>Jan. 24, 1823</date>.</note></head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#g"><hi rendition="#k">When</hi></hi> we consider the influence which scientific travels into<lb/>distant regions, and a more extended geographical knowledge, have<lb/>for some centuries past exerted upon the study of nature, we soon<lb/>discover how this influence has varied according to the objects of<lb/>inquiry, which have been, on the one hand, the forms of the organic<lb/>world, and, on the other, the inanimate formation of the earth; &#x2014;<lb/>the knowledge of rocks, their relative ages, and origin. Differ-<lb/>ent forms of plants and animals enliven the earth in every zone,<lb/>as well in the plains, where the heat of the atmosphere is deter-<lb/>mined by the geographical latitude and the different inflexions of<lb/>the isothermal lines, as where it changes suddenly on the steep<lb/>declivities of the mountains. Organic nature gives a peculiar<lb/>physiognomical character to every zone, which is not the case<lb/>with the inorganic world where the solid crust of the earth is<lb/>divested of its vegetable covering. The same rocks approaching<lb/><pb n="122" facs="#f0002" />
to and receding from each other in groups occur in both hemi-<lb/>spheres, from the equator to the poles. On a distant island,<lb/>surrounded by strange plants, under a sky where the well-<lb/>known stars do not shine, the sailor recognises, often with glad<lb/>surprise, the clayslate which is the common rock of his native<lb/>country.</p><lb/><p>This independence of the geognostical relations of places on<lb/>the present constitution of their climate, does not diminish, but<lb/>only gives a particular direction to the favourable effect upon the<lb/>progress of geology and physical geognosy, which is produced<lb/>by numerous observations made in foreign countries. Every<lb/>expedition enriches natural history with new plants, and new<lb/>genera of animals; at one time they are organic forms ranging<lb/>themselves with well-known types, and representing to us, in its<lb/>original perfection, a regularly woven, though often apparently<lb/>interrupted texture of animated creatures; at another, they are<lb/>forms which appear to be isolated, as vestiges of genera which<lb/>have been destroyed, or as surprising members of groups still to<lb/>be discovered. Such a variety is not presented by the examina-<lb/>tion of the solid crust of the earth; it rather reveals to us an<lb/>agreement, which excites the admiration of the geognost,<lb/>between the parts of which it is composed, in the superposition<lb/>of masses of different natures, and in their periodical repetition.</p><lb/><p>In the chain of the <placeName>Andes</placeName>, as well as in the central mountains<lb/>of <placeName>Europe</placeName>, one formation seems, as it were, to occasion the<lb/>existence of another; masses of the same character assume<lb/>similar forms: <note place="foot" n="*">In an imperfect translation of this paper, which has been forwarded to the Editor<lb/>from the Continent, a word here occurs which cannot be decyphered; and on account of<lb/>other inaccuracies which it has been necessary to correct, unaided by the original, the<lb/>translation, as now given, is not to be regarded as exact in every particular.</note> mountains are formed by basalt and<lb/>dolerite; steep declivities by dolomite, porphyry, and quader-<lb/>sandstein; bell-shaped eminences and high-vaulted domes by<lb/>vitreous trachyte rich in felspar.</p><lb/><p>In the most distant zones, larger crystals, as it were by inter-<lb/>nal evolution out of the more compact texture of the greater<lb/>mass, aggregate into subordinate beds, and thus frequently<lb/>announce the vicinity of a new and independent formation.<lb/>Thus is the whole inorganic world reflected, more or less clearly,<lb/>in every mountain of considerable extent; but in order to ascer-<lb/>tain completely the most important ph&#x00E6;nomena respecting the<lb/>composition, the relative age, and the origin of the different<lb/>species of rocks, observations from the most distant parts of the<lb/>earth must be compared together. Problems which had appeared<lb/>enigmatical to the geognost in his mother country are solved<lb/>near the equator. If distant zones do not furnish new species<lb/>of rocks, that is to say, unknown arrangements of simple sub-<lb/>stances, as has already been remarked, they yet teach us how to<lb/>discover the great laws which are every where the same, and<lb/>according to which, the different strata of the earth support each<lb/><pb n="123" facs="#f0003" />
    other, appear in the form of veins, or are elevated by elastic<lb/>powers.</p><lb/><p>We need not be surprised, that, notwithstanding the great<lb/>assistance which our geological information derives from inqui-<lb/>ries, having whole countries for their object, an extensive class<lb/>of ph&#x00E6;nomena (with which I venture to entertain this assembly),<lb/>has been treated, during so long a period, in a confined manner;<lb/>the points of comparison being more difficult, and, I might say,<lb/>more troublesome to find. Whatever we believed we knew,<lb/>until the end of the last century, respecting the form of volca-<lb/>noes, and the action of their subterraneous forces, had been<lb/>derived from two mountains of the south of <placeName>Italy</placeName>,&#x2014;from <placeName>&#x00C6;tna</placeName>,<lb/>and from <placeName>Vesuvius</placeName>. The first being more accessible, and hav-<lb/>ing, like all low volcanoes, more frequent eruptions, has served<lb/>for a type, according to which a whole distant world,&#x2014;the<lb/>powerful volcanoes of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, <placeName>South America</placeName>, and the <placeName>Asiatic<lb/>Islands</placeName>, has been considered. Such a method recalls to our<lb/>remembrance the shepherd of <placeName>Virgil</placeName>, who expected his narrow<lb/>cottage to contain the ideal of the eternal city, imperial <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p><lb/><p>A careful examination of the whole Mediterranean, and princi-<lb/>pally of its easterly islands and shores, where mankind first<lb/>awakened to mental culture, and to noble feelings, might cer-<lb/>tainly have dispelled such a narrow idea of nature. Out of the<lb/>deep bed of the sea, among the <placeName>Sporades</placeName>, rocks of trachyte have<lb/>arisen, like the <placeName>Azoric island</placeName>, which has thrice reappeared dur-<lb/>ing three centuries, the intervening periods being almost equal.<lb/>Between <placeName>Epidaurus</placeName> and <placeName>Troezene</placeName>, near <placeName>Methone</placeName>, the <placeName>Pelopon-<lb/>nesus</placeName> has a <placeName>Monte Nuovo</placeName> which has been described by <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Strabo</persName>,<lb/>and seen by <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Dodwell</persName>, higher than the <placeName>Monte Nuovo</placeName> of the<lb/><placeName>Campi Phlegr&#x00E6;i</placeName>, near <placeName>Baia</placeName>; perhaps higher than the new vol-<lb/>cano of <placeName>Xorullo</placeName> in the plains of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, which I have found<lb/>among a thousand basaltic cones, raised out of the earth, and<lb/>still smoking. In the bason of the <placeName>Mediterranean Sea</placeName> also, the<lb/>volcanic fire bursts forth, and not only from permanent craters,<lb/>from isolated mountains which preserve a lasting communication<lb/>with the interior of the earth, like <placeName>Stromboli</placeName>, <placeName>Vesuvius</placeName>, and <placeName>&#x00C6;tna</placeName>;<lb/>&#x2014;on <placeName>Ischia</placeName>, near the <placeName>Epom&#x00E6;us</placeName>, and also, as it would appear from<lb/>the reports of the ancients, near <placeName>Chalcis</placeName> in the <placeName>Lelantic plains</placeName>, has<lb/>lava flowed out of fissures which have suddenly opened. Besides<lb/>these ph&#x00E6;nomena, which have taken place in the period of history<lb/>within the narrow limits of certain traditions, and which <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Ritter</persName><lb/>will collect and explain in his masterly Geography, the shores of<lb/>the <placeName>Mediterranean</placeName> contain abundant remains of more ancient<lb/>igneous effects. The south of <placeName>France</placeName> shows, in <placeName>Auvergne</placeName>, a<lb/>range of hills, in which <hi rendition="#i">bells</hi> of trachyte occur alternately with<lb/>cones of eruption, from which currents of lava have descended.<lb/>The <placeName>Lombardic plain</placeName>, which forms the innermost bay of the<lb/><placeName>Adriatic Sea</placeName>, surrounds the trachyte of the <placeName>Euganean Hills</placeName>,<lb/>where domes of granular trachyte, of obsidian, and of pearlstone,<lb/>rise, which, passing into each other, break through the Jura<lb/><pb n="124" facs="#f0004" />
limestone, but never occur in narrow streams which have flowed.<lb/>Similar evidences of former revolutions may be found in many<lb/>parts of the <placeName>Grecian continent</placeName>, and in <placeName>Asia Minor</placeName>, countries<lb/>which will afford the geognost copious subjects for examination,<lb/>when the light once returns to the land whence it first beamed<lb/>over the western world&#x2014;when tormented mankind ceases to<lb/>sink under the savage lethargy of the Ottoman.</p><lb/><p>I mention the geographical neighbourhood of so many ph&#x00E6;no-<lb/>mena, in order to prove, that the bed of the <placeName>Mediterranean</placeName>,<lb/>with all its chains of islands, might have afforded to the atten-<lb/>tive observer, every thing that has been discovered, in latter<lb/>periods, under the most varied forms, in <placeName>South America</placeName>, on<lb/><placeName>Teneriffe</placeName>, or on the <placeName>Aleutian islands</placeName>, near the polar regions.<lb/>There were accumulated objects for observation, but tours into<lb/>distant regions, and the comparison of large tracts of country<lb/>within and beyond <placeName>Europe</placeName>, were necessary, in order to discover<lb/>what was common to all these ph&#x00E6;nomena, and to learn,<lb/>clearly, their dependence on each other.</p><lb/><p>By the usage of language, which often gives stability and<lb/>respect to the first erroneous views of things, but often, as it<lb/>were, by instinct, distinguishes the truth, we apply the term<lb/>volcanic to all eruptions of subterranean and melted matter; to<lb/>columns of smoke and steam, which rise sporadically out of<lb/>rocks, as at <placeName>Colares</placeName> after the great earthquake at <placeName>Lisbon</placeName>; to<lb/><placeName>Sals&#x00E6;</placeName>, or conical hills of clay which emit mud, asphaltum, and<lb/>hydrogen, as those near <placeName>Girgenti</placeName>, in <placeName>Sicily</placeName>, and near <placeName>Turbaco</placeName>,<lb/>in <placeName>South America</placeName>; to hot Geyser springs which rise by the<lb/>pressure of elastic vapours; and, in general, to all violent powers<lb/>of nature which have their seat deep in the interior of our planet.<lb/>In the Spanish main of <placeName>America</placeName>, and in the <placeName>Philippine islands</placeName>,<lb/>the inhabitants make a distinction between igneous and aqueous<lb/>volcanoes, <hi rendition="#i">vulcanes de agua y de fuego:</hi> they apply the first name<lb/>to mountains, which, during violent earthquakes, from time to<lb/>time, eject subterraneous water, and with a dull noise.</p><lb/><p>Without denying the connexion between the different ph&#x00E6;no-<lb/>mena just mentioned, it seems advisable to give a distinct<lb/>language to the physical as well as to the oryctognostic branch<lb/>of geognosy; and not to apply the term volcano in one instance<lb/>to a mountain that terminates in a permanent crater; and in<lb/>another, to every subterranean cause of volcanic ph&#x00E6;nomena.</p><lb/><p>In the present state of the earth, the most common from of<lb/>volcanic eminences is that of isolated cones; such are <placeName>Vesuvius</placeName>,<lb/><placeName>&#x00C6;tna</placeName>, the <placeName>Peak of Teneriffe</placeName>, <placeName>Tunguragna</placeName>, and <placeName>Cotopaxi</placeName>. I<lb/>have seen them of every magnitude, from the lowest hills to<lb/>mountains rising to the height of 17,700 feet above the level of<lb/>the sea. Besides these conical mountains, there are other cra-<lb/>ters, permanently communicating with the interior of the earth,<lb/>situated upon lengthened craggy ranges of mountains, not<lb/>always in the middle of their wall-like summits, but towards the<lb/>end, and near their declivities. Such is <placeName>Pichincha</placeName> which rises<lb/><pb n="125" facs="#f0005" />
    between the <placeName>Pacific Ocean</placeName> and the town of <placeName>Quito</placeName>, and which<lb/>has become celebrated by <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Bouguer&#x2019;s</persName> earliest formula for the<lb/>barometer; such also are the volcanoes that rise in the <placeName>plain de<lb/>los Pastos</placeName>, at the elevation of 10,000 feet.</p><lb/><p>All these differently formed summits consist of trachyte, or<lb/>trap-porphyry, a granular rock, full of cracks and fissures, and<lb/>composed of glassy felspar and hornblende, but often containing<lb/>in addition, augite, mica, laminar felspar, and quartz.</p><lb/><p>Where the evidence of the first eruption, and where the first<lb/>scaffolding, I might say, has been entirely preserved, the isolated<lb/>conical hills are surrounded by a high wall of rocks forming a<lb/>circus, consisting of superposed strata; such walls, or annular<lb/>surrounding masses, are called <hi rendition="#i">craters of elevation;</hi> of these very<lb/>important ph&#x00E6;nomena, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Leopold von Buch</persName>, the first geognost of<lb/>our times, from whose works I have taken several views con-<lb/>tained in this paper, read a remarkable account, five years ago.</p><lb/><p>The volcanoes which communicate with the atmosphere by<lb/>means of craters, and the conical hills of basalt and bell-shaped<lb/>trachytic hills without craters, the latter either low like <placeName>Sarcouy</placeName>,<lb/>or high like <placeName>Chimborazo</placeName>, form different groups. A geographical<lb/>comparison shows, in one place, small <placeName>Archipelagi</placeName>, or, as it were,<lb/>classed systems of mountains, either with craters and currents<lb/>of lava, as in the <placeName>Canaries</placeName> and <placeName>Azores</placeName>, or devoid of craters and<lb/>real currents of lava in the <placeName>Euganeans</placeName>, and the <placeName>Siebengebirge</placeName><lb/>near <placeName>Bonn</placeName>; or it shows, in other places, single and double<lb/>chains of volcanoes, connected with each other, and forming<lb/>tracts of many hundred miles in length, which are either<lb/>parallel to the direction of the mountains, as in <placeName>Guatimala</placeName>,<lb/><placeName>Peru</placeName>, and <placeName>Java</placeName>, or in directions perpendicular to their axis, as<lb/>in the land of the Aztekes, where none but volcanic trachyte-<lb/>mountains attain the limits of eternal snow, and those, probably,<lb/>have been thrust out of a fissure nearly 500 miles in length,<lb/>which divides the whole continent, from the <placeName>Pacific Ocean</placeName> to<lb/>the <placeName>Atlantic</placeName>.</p><lb/><p>This aggregation of volcanoes either in single round groups,<lb/>or in double ranges, affords the most determinate proof that<lb/>volcanic effects do not depend upon slight causes existing near<lb/>the surface of the earth, but that they are great and deeply<lb/>founded ph&#x00E6;nomena. The whole eastern part of the American<lb/>continent, which is poor in metals, is at present without craters,<lb/>without trachyte, probably even without basalt. All the volca-<lb/>noes are situated in the part opposite to <placeName>Asia</placeName>, in the meridian<lb/>line of the <placeName>Andes chain</placeName>, 1800 geographical miles long; the<lb/>whole of the elevated district of <placeName>Quito</placeName> is nothing but a single<lb/>volcanic hearth, the summits of which are <placeName>Pichincha</placeName>, <placeName>Cotopaxi</placeName>,<lb/>and <placeName>Tunguragua</placeName>. The volcanic fire now bursts forth from one,<lb/>and then from another of these apertures, which we are accus-<lb/>tomed to consider as separate volcanoes.</p><lb/><p>The progressive motion of the fire here, in the space of three<lb/>centuries, turned from north to south. The earthquakes with<lb/><pb n="126" facs="#f0006" />
which this part of the world is so terribly visited, furnish remark-<lb/>able evidences of the existence of subterraneous communication,<lb/>not only between countries without volcanoes, as was known<lb/>long ago, but even between craters which are far distant from<lb/>each other. Thus the volcano of <placeName>Pasto</placeName>, situated to the east of<lb/>the river <placeName>Guaytara</placeName>, uninterruptedly vomited a high column of<lb/>smoke, during three months of the year 1797; and this column<lb/>disappeared at the very moment, when, at the distance of<lb/>nearly 300 miles, the great earthquake of <placeName>Riobamba</placeName> and<lb/>the mud eruption of the <placeName>Moya</placeName>, killed from 30,000 to 40,000<lb/>Indians. The sudden appearance of the <placeName>Azoric island Sabrina</placeName>,<lb/>on the 30th of January, 1811, was the forerunner of those dread-<lb/>ful shocks, which, further to the west, shook, almost uninterrupt-<lb/>edly, from the month of May, 1811, to that of June, 1813, first<lb/>the <placeName>Antilles</placeName>, afterwards the plains of the <placeName>Ohio</placeName> and the <placeName>Missis-<lb/>sippi</placeName>, and at last the opposite coast of <placeName>Venezuela</placeName>. Thirty days<lb/>after the complete destruction of the town of <placeName>Caraccas</placeName>, the erup-<lb/>tion of the volcano of <placeName>St. Vincent</placeName> in the neighbouring <placeName>Antilles</placeName><lb/>took place; at the same moment when this explosion happened,<lb/>on the 30th of April, 1811, a subterranean noise was heard<lb/>throughout a country of 2200 geographical square miles, or<lb/>47,900 English square miles, in extent.</p><lb/><p>The inhabitants near the <placeName>Apure</placeName>, where it is joined by the<lb/><placeName>Rio Nula</placeName>, as well as those of the most distant part of the coast,<lb/>compared this noise to that of artillery. From where the <placeName>Rio<lb/>Nula</placeName> falls into the <placeName>Apure</placeName>, through which river I came into the<lb/><placeName>Orinoco</placeName>, to the volcano of <placeName>St. Vincent</placeName>, the distance, in a direct<lb/>line, is 731 English miles. The noise just alluded to, which<lb/>certainly was not communicated through the air, must, there-<lb/>fore, have had a deep internal cause. Its intensity on the coast<lb/>of the <placeName>Antillic sea</placeName> was scarcely greater than in the interior of the<lb/>country.</p><lb/><p>It would be useless to augment the number of examples, but<lb/>for the purpose of recalling to memory a phenomenon which has<lb/>become historically interesting to <placeName>Europe</placeName>, I will mention the<lb/>earthquake at <placeName>Lisbon</placeName>. At the same time with this, on the 1st<lb/>of November, 1755, not only were the <placeName>Swiss lakes</placeName>, and the sea<lb/>on the <placeName>Swedish shores</placeName> violently agitated, but even in the easterly<lb/><placeName>Antilles</placeName>, around <placeName>Martinique</placeName>, <placeName>Antigua</placeName>, and <placeName>Barbadoes</placeName>, where the<lb/>tide never exceeds 28 inches, it suddenly rose to 20 feet. All<lb/>these ph&#x00E6;nomena prove, that the subterranean powers act either<lb/>dynamically, by producing tension and vibration, as in earth-<lb/>quakes; or chemically, by producing or altering substances, as<lb/>in volcanoes. They prove, likewise, that these powers do not<lb/>act from superficial causes, from the exterior crust of the earth;<lb/>but from deeply-seated causes, from the interior of our planet;<lb/>extending their simultaneous effects to the most distant parts of<lb/>the earth, through fissures and empty veins.</p><lb/><p>The more different the structure of volcanoes; that is to say,<lb/>of those raised masses which surround the canal through which<lb/><pb n="127" facs="#f0007" />
    the melted substances proceed from the interior of the earth to<lb/>its surface, the more important is it to become thoroughly<lb/>acquainted with that structure, by exact measurement. The<lb/>interest attached to this measurement, which has been a parti-<lb/>cular object of my examination in another part of the world, is<lb/>heightened by the consideration, that that which is to be mea-<lb/>sured is a variable magnitude. The physiognomy of nature con-<lb/>sists in the change of ph&#x00E6;nomena tending to connect the present<lb/>with the past. In order to ascertain a periodical return, or the<lb/>laws of progressive natural changes in general, certain fixed<lb/>points are necessary; and observations carefully made at stated<lb/>periods, may serve for numerical comparison. Had the mean<lb/>temperature of the atmosphere in different latitudes been<lb/>observed for a few thousand years, and the mean height of the<lb/>barometer at the level of the sea, we might now know in what<lb/>proportion the heat of different climates has increased, or dimi-<lb/>nished, and whether the height of the atmosphere has undergone<lb/>any changes. Similar points for comparison are required, for<lb/>the variation and the declination of the magnetic needle, and<lb/>for the intensity of the electromagnetic power, upon which two<lb/>excellent philosophers of this Academy have thrown so much<lb/>light. If it be a praiseworthy undertaking of learned societies<lb/>to inquire assiduously into the changes of temperature undergone<lb/>by the globe, into those which take place in the pressure of the atmo-<lb/>sphere, and in the magnetic variation, &#x2014; it is the duty of a travelling<lb/>geognost, in ascertaining the inequality of the earth&#x2019;s surface, to<lb/>consider, principally, the variable height of the volcanoes. What<lb/>I formerly attempted on the mountains of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, on the <placeName>Toluca<lb/>Nauhiampatepetl</placeName> and <placeName>Xorullo</placeName>, and in the <placeName>Andes of Quito</placeName>, on<lb/>the <placeName>Pichincha</placeName>, I have found opportunity, since my return to<lb/><placeName>Europe</placeName>, to repeat at different periods on <placeName>Vesuvius</placeName>. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Saussure</persName><lb/>measured this mountain in 1773, at the time when both sides of<lb/>the crater, the south-eastern and north-western, appeared to be<lb/>of equal altitude; he found their height to be 609 toises (3894<lb/>feet) above the level of the sea. The eruption of 1794 occa-<lb/>sioned a fall on the south side, which even the unaccustomed<lb/>eye discovers at a great distance. In 1805, I measured <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Vesu-<lb/>vius</persName> three times, in conjunction with M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">von Buch</persName>, and M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Gay-<lb/>Lussac</persName>; we found the elevation of the northern edge, opposite<lb/>to <placeName>Monte Somma</placeName>, la <placeName>Rocca del Palo</placeName>, to be exactly the same as<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Saussure</persName> had before determined it; the southern edge we found<lb/>71 toises (454 feet) lower than it was in 1773; the total height<lb/>of the volcano on the side opposite <placeName>Torre del Greco</placeName> (towards<lb/>which side the fire seems to have acted the most powerfully,<lb/>during the last 30 years), had diminished one-ninth part.</p><lb/><p>The cone of ashes on <placeName>Vesuvius</placeName> bears the proportion of one-<lb/>third to the height of the whole mountain, that on <placeName>Pichincha</placeName> is<lb/>as 1 to 10, and that on the <placeName>Peak of Teneriffe</placeName> as 1 to 22; <placeName>Vesu-<lb/>vius</placeName> has, therefore, the largest cone of ashes in proportion,<lb/><pb n="128" facs="#f0008" />
        because, probably, as a low volcano, it has acted principally<lb/>through its summit. A few months ago, I succeeded not only<lb/>in repeating my former measurements on <placeName>Vesuvius</placeName>, but also in<lb/>ascertaining the elevation of all the edges of the crater. This<lb/>work, perhaps, deserves some consideration, for the periods at<lb/>which it was executed include those of the great eruptions from 1805<lb/>to 1822, and it is, perhaps, the only admeasurement yet published<lb/>of any volcano which may be compared in all its parts. It proves<lb/>that the edges of the craters, not only where they evidently consist<lb/>of trachyte, as in the volcanoes of the <placeName>Andes</placeName>, but likewise every-<lb/>where else, are much more constant ph&#x00E6;nomena than has<lb/>hitherto been believed. Simple angles of elevation ascertained<lb/>from the same points are more proper for these examinations than<lb/>barometrical and trigonometrical measurements. According to<lb/>my last determination, the north-western edge of the crater of<lb/>Vesuvius has not changed its form in the least since <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Saussure&#x2019;s</persName><lb/>time, a period of 49 years. The south-eastern edge towards<lb/><placeName>Bosche tre Case</placeName>, which became about 450 feet lower in 1794,<lb/>has sunk very little since that time.</p><lb/><p>If in the description of great eruptions, in the public papers,<lb/>the completely changed form of <placeName>Vesuvius</placeName> has frequently been<lb/>mentioned, if this opinion often seems to be corroborated by the<lb/>picturesque views of the mountain made at <placeName>Naples</placeName>, the cause of<lb/>this mistake may be found in the circumstance, that the outlines<lb/>of the edges of the crater have been confounded with those of<lb/>the cone of eruption which is accidentally formed in the middle<lb/>of the crater, upon a bottom that has been raised by vapours.<lb/>Such a cone of eruption, consisting of rapilli and slags loosely<lb/>heaped together, has become visible over the south-eastern edge<lb/>of the crater, since 1816 and 1818. The eruption of February,<lb/>1822, had so much increased it that it had become from 70 to<lb/>80 feet higher than the north-eastern edge of the crater, <placeName>Rocca<lb/>del Palo</placeName>. This remarkable cone, which, at <placeName>Naples</placeName>, they were<lb/>accustomed to consider as the true summit of <placeName>Vesuvius</placeName>, fell in<lb/>with a tremendous noise, during the eruption of the 22d of<lb/>October, so that the bottom of the crater, which had been unin-<lb/>terruptedly accessible from the year 1811, now lies 850 English feet<lb/>beneath the northern edge, and about 213 feet deeper than the<lb/>southern edge of the volcano. The variable form and relative<lb/>situation of the crater of eruption, the opening of which must<lb/>not be taken for the real crater of the volcano, as frequently has<lb/>been done, gives, at different times, a peculiar physiognomy to<lb/><placeName>Vesuvius</placeName>; and the historiographer of that volcano, from the mere<lb/>outline of the summit, and the relative height of the northern<lb/>or southern side of the mountain, as it is drawn in <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Hackert&#x2019;s</persName><lb/>Views in the palace of <placeName>Portici</placeName>, would guess the year in which<lb/>the artist made the sketch of his picture.</p><lb/><p>In the night between the 23d and 24th of October, one day<lb/>after the fall of the cone of slags 400 feet in height, when small<lb/><pb n="129" facs="#f0009" />
            but numerous currents of lava had already flowed, the fiery<lb/>eruption of ashes and rapilli began. It continued uninterrupt-<lb/>edly for twelve days, but was most violent during the first four.<lb/>During this time the detonations in the interior of the volcano<lb/>were so violent, that the mere concussion of the air (no earth-<lb/>quake had been observed) caused the roofs to burst in the palace<lb/>of <placeName>Portici</placeName>. In the surrounding villages of <placeName>Resina</placeName>, <placeName>Torre del<lb/>Greco</placeName>, <placeName>Torre del Annonciata</placeName>, and <placeName>Bosche tre Case</placeName>, an interest-<lb/>ing <choice><sic>ph&#x0153;nomenon</sic><corr type="editorial">ph&#x00E6;nomenon</corr></choice> was observed; the atmosphere was so thickly<lb/>filled with ashes, that the most intense darkness overspread the<lb/>whole country for several hours in the middle of the day. The<lb/>people walked in the streets with lanterns, as is often done at<lb/><placeName>Quito</placeName> when <placeName>Pichincha</placeName> is in eruption. The flight of the inhabi-<lb/>tants was never more general; currents of lava were less feared<lb/>than a fall of ashes, a phenomenon which was unknown there<lb/>with such violence, and in consequence of the relations respect-<lb/>ing the destruction of <placeName>Herculaneum</placeName>, <placeName>Pompeii</placeName>, and <placeName>Stabi&#x00E6;</placeName>, filled<lb/>the minds of the people with frightful images.</p><lb/><p>The hot steam which rose from the crater during the eruption<lb/>and passed into the atmosphere, formed on cooling a thick mass<lb/>of clouds, around the column of ashes and fire, 9000 feet in<lb/>height. This sudden condensation of steam, and, as <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Gay-<lb/>Lussac</persName> has shown, the very formation of the clouds, increases<lb/>the electric tension. Lightnings burst forth in all directions<lb/>from the column of ashes, and the rolling thunder might clearly<lb/>be distinguished from the interior noise of the volcano. At no<lb/>former eruption had the play of electric charges been so sur-<lb/>prising.</p><lb/><p>On the morning of the 26th of October, a singular account<lb/>was circulated, that a current of boiling water had issued from<lb/>the crater, and rushed down from the cone of ashes. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Monticelli</persName>,<lb/>the zealous and learned observer of the volcano, soon discerned<lb/>that the rumour had been occasioned by an optical deception.<lb/>The supposed current of water was nothing but a dry mass of<lb/>ashes, which flowed down, like quicksand, from a fissure in the<lb/>superior edge of the crater. A drought, which had completely<lb/>desolated the fields, preceded the eruption, but the volcanic<lb/>thunderstorm occasioned, towards its termination, a very heavy<lb/>and continued rain. Such a phenomenon characterizes the<lb/>conclusion of an eruption in every zone. On account of the cone<lb/>of ashes being generally covered with clouds during this time,<lb/>and likewise because the torrents of rain are heaviest in its<lb/>neighbourhood, currents of mud flow down on all sides. The<lb/>affrighted peasant considers it to be water which has risen from<lb/>the interior of the crater, and the deceived geognost conceives<lb/>that he recognizes in it either sea-water, or mud-like volcanic<lb/>productions, which are called <hi rendition="#i">eruptions boueuses</hi>, or, as the old<lb/>French systematic writers termed them, products of a fiery-<lb/>aqueous liquefaction.</p><lb/><pb n="130" facs="#f0010" />
    <p>When the summits of volcanoes (as is generally the case in<lb/>the chain of the <placeName>Andes</placeName>), extend into the region of eternal snow,<lb/>or even to double the height of <placeName>&#x00C6;tna</placeName>, the melted snow renders<lb/>the inundations amazingly frequent and destructive. They are<lb/>ph&#x00E6;nomena meteorologically connected with volcanic eruptions,<lb/>and are multifariously modified by the altitude of the mountains,<lb/>the extent of their summits covered with eternal snow, and the<lb/>calefaction of the sides of the cone of ashes; but they should<lb/>never be considered as real volcanic ph&#x00E6;nomena. Subterranean<lb/>lakes, in connexion with alpine rivers, are formed both on the<lb/>slopes and at the feet of the mountains. When the earthquakes<lb/>which precede every eruption in the chain of the <placeName>Andes</placeName>, shake<lb/>with mighty force the entire mass of the volcano, the subterra-<lb/>nean vaults are opened, and emit, at the same time, water, fishes,<lb/>and tufa-mud. This is the singular phenomenon that fur-<lb/>nishes the fish <hi rendition="#i">pimelodes cyclopum</hi>, which the inhabitants of<lb/>the high lands of <placeName>Quito</placeName> call <hi rendition="#i">pren&#x0303;adilla</hi>, and which was described<lb/>by me soon after my return. When the summit of the mountain<lb/><placeName>Carguairazo</placeName>, to the north of <placeName>Chimborazo</placeName>, and 18,000 feet<lb/>high, fell, in the night between the 19th and 20th of June,<lb/>1698, the surrounding fields, to the extent of about 43 Eng-<lb/>lish square miles, were covered with mud and fishes. The<lb/>fever which raged in the town of <placeName>Ibarra</placeName>, seven years before, had<lb/>been ascribed to a similar eruption of fishes from the volcano<lb/><placeName>Imbaburu</placeName>. I recur to these facts, because they throw some<lb/>light on the difference between the eruption of ashes, and that<lb/>of mud-like masses of tufa and trass, which contain wood,<lb/>coal, and shells.</p><lb/><p>The quantity of ashes ejected by <placeName>Vesuvius</placeName> in the late erup-<lb/>tions, like all other things which are connected with great and<lb/>appalling ph&#x00E6;nomena, has been enormously exaggerated in the<lb/>public papers; and two Neapolitan chemists, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Vincenzo Pepe</persName>,<lb/>and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Giuseppe di Nobili</persName>, have affirmed, that they contain gold<lb/>and silver, notwithstanding the contradiction of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Monticelli</persName> and<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Covelli</persName>.<note place="foot" n="*">See <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Annals,</hi> v. 236.</bibl></note> According to my examination, the stratum of ashes<lb/>which had fallen in twelve days, towards <placeName>Bosche tre Case</placeName>, on<lb/>the slope of the cone, where rapilli were mixed with it, was<lb/>only three feet in thickness, and in the plain, it did not<lb/>exceed from 15 to 18 inches. Measurements of this kind<lb/>must not be made in places where the ashes have been drifted<lb/>by wind, like snow, or sand, nor in those where they have been<lb/>accumulated by water. The times are past in which we sought<lb/>only for the marvellous in volcanic ph&#x00E6;nomena, and, like <placeName>Ctesias</placeName>,<lb/>made the ashes of <placeName>&#x00C6;tna</placeName> fly to the <placeName>Indian peninsula</placeName>. Some of<lb/>the Mexican gold and silver mines are certainly in trachytic<lb/>porphyry, but in the ashes of <placeName>Vesuvius</placeName> which I collected, and<lb/>which, at my desire, have been analyzed by <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Henry Rose</persName>, of<lb/><pb n="131" facs="#f0011" />
        <placeName>Berlin</placeName>, an excellent chemist, no traces of either metal, could be<lb/>discovered.</p><lb/><p>However great may be the discrepancy between the results that<lb/>I have here given, but which agree with <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Monticelli&#x2019;s</persName> more exact<lb/>observations, and those which have been circulated during<lb/>several months past, yet the eruption of ashes from <placeName>Vesuvius</placeName>,<lb/>from the 24th to the 28th of October, still remains the most re-<lb/>markable of which we have any certain account since the death<lb/>of the elder <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Pliny</persName>. Its quantity, perhaps, was three times as<lb/>great as that of all the ashes, collectively, which have been<lb/>observed to fall, during the time in which volcanic ph&#x00E6;nomena<lb/>have been attentively considered. A stratum of from 15 to 18<lb/>inches in thickness, seems at first view unimportant, if compared<lb/>to the mass with which we find <placeName>Pompeii</placeName> to be covered; but<lb/>without speaking of the torrents and inundations which certainly<lb/>may have increased this mass for centuries, without renewing<lb/>the violent dispute concerning the cause of the destruction of<lb/>the Campanian towns, which has been carried on with so much<lb/>scepticism on the other side of the <placeName>Alps</placeName>, it may be affirmed that<lb/>the eruptions of one and the same volcano at distant periods can<lb/>by no means be compared with respect to their intensity. All<lb/>conclusions founded on analogy are insufficient, when the ques-<lb/>tion is about quantitative proportions,&#x2014;the quantity of ashes<lb/>and lava, the height of the column of smoke, or the violence of<lb/>the detonation.</p><lb/><p>From the geographical description of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Strabo</persName>, and from an<lb/>opinion of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Vitruvius</persName> concerning the volcanic origin of pumice,<lb/>we see that until the year in which <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Vespasian</persName> died, that is to<lb/>say, until the eruption which overwhelmed <placeName>Pompeii</placeName>, Vesuvius<lb/>was more like an extinguished volcano than a solfatara.</p><lb/><p>When after long rest the subterranean powers suddenly<lb/>open new passages, and again break through beds of pri-<lb/>mitive rocks and of trachyte, effects must necessarily take<lb/>place, for which all the ph&#x00E6;nomena subsequently observed do<lb/>not afford any standard of comparison. It may be clearly seen<lb/>from the well-known letter in which the <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">younger Pliny</persName> announces<lb/>the death of his uncle to <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Tacitus</persName>, that the recommencement of<lb/>the eruptions, I might say, the awakening of the dormant vol-<lb/>cano, began with an eruption of ashes. The same circumstance<lb/>was observed at <placeName>Xorullo</placeName>, in Sept. 1759, when the new volcano,<lb/>breaking through beds of syenite and trachyte, suddenly arose<lb/>in the plain. The peasants fled, because they found in their<lb/>huts, ashes that had been ejected from the fissures of the earth,<lb/>which was burst in every place. Every partial eruption, in the<lb/>periodical general eruptions of volcanoes terminates with a shower<lb/>of ashes.</p><lb/><p>There is a passage in <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Pliny&#x2019;s</persName> letter, which shows, that the dry<lb/>ashes which had fallen from the air had already attained a height<lb/>of from four to five feet, in the commencement of the eruption,<lb/><pb n="132" facs="#f0012" />
and without the effect of accumulation by water. &#x201C;The court<lb/>which led to his [uncle&#x2019;s] apartment,&#x201D; he says, &#x201C;being now<lb/>almost filled with ashes and pumice, it would have been impos-<lb/>sible for him, if he had continued there any longer, to have made<lb/>his way out.&#x201D; In the narrow space of a court, the wind could<lb/>not have had any great effect in accumulating the ashes.</p><lb/><p>I have ventured to interrupt my comparative view of volca-<lb/>noes by observations solely on <placeName>Vesuvius</placeName>, partly on account of<lb/>the great interest which the last eruption has excited, and partly<lb/>because every great fall of ashes almost involuntarily reminds us<lb/>of the classic ground of <placeName>Pompeii</placeName> and <placeName>Herculaneum</placeName>.<note place="foot" n="*">The author here mentions a paper on the data of his measurements at <placeName>Vesuvius</placeName>,<lb/>which was unsuitable for reading; and then proceeds to notice a collection of minerals<lb/>that he brought with him, and which will be added to the Royal Museum at <placeName>Berlin</placeName>.</note> We have<lb/>hitherto considered the form and the effects of those volcanoes<lb/>which are in permanent communication with the interior of the<lb/>earth, by means of a crater. Their summits are raised masses<lb/>of trachyte and lava, intersected by numerous veins; the dura-<lb/>tion of their effects causes us to believe that they have a very<lb/>stable and undisturbed structure. They possess, I may say, a<lb/>more individual character, which remains the same during long<lb/>periods. Neighbouring mountains often furnish completely<lb/>different products, leucite-lava, and felspar-lava; obsidian, with<lb/>pumice, and basaltic masses containing olivine. They belong<lb/>to the newer ph&#x00E6;nomena of the earth, pass generally through all<lb/>the strata of secondary rocks, and their eruptions and currents<lb/>of lava are of later origin than our valleys. Their life, if I may<lb/>use that expression, depends upon the manner and duration of<lb/>their connexion with the interior of the earth. They often rest<lb/>for centuries, suddenly take fire again, and terminate as solfa-<lb/>taras, which emit steam, gases, and acids. Sometimes, as on<lb/>the <placeName>Peak of Teneriffe</placeName>, their summit has already become such a<lb/>depository of reproduced sulphur, while mighty currents of lava<lb/>flow from the sides of the mountain, like basalt below, and<lb/>above, where the pressure is less, like obsidian with pumice.</p><lb/><p>Independently of these with permanent craters, volcanic<lb/>ph&#x00E6;nomena of another kind exist, which have been observed<lb/>less frequently, but are principally interesting in geognosy, and<lb/>remind us of the primitive world; that is to say, of the earliest<lb/>revolutions of our earth. Mountains of trachyte suddenly<lb/>open, eject lava and ashes, and close again, perhaps, for<lb/>ever: thus was it with the mighty <placeName>Antisana</placeName>; and thus with the<lb/><placeName>Epom&#x00E6;us</placeName>, in <placeName>Ischia</placeName>, in 1302. Such an eruption sometimes<lb/>takes place even in the plain, as in the high lands of <placeName>Quito</placeName>; in<lb/><placeName>Iceland</placeName>, far from <placeName>Hecla</placeName>; and in <placeName>Eub&#x0153;a</placeName>, in the <placeName>Lelantic fields</placeName>.<lb/>Many of the islands which have been raised up are owing to these<lb/>temporary ph&#x00E6;nomena. In these cases the communication with<lb/>the interior of the earth is not permanent, and the effect ceases<lb/>as soon as the fissure, which is the communicating channel, is<lb/><pb n="133" facs="#f0013" />
    closed again. The veins of basalt, dolerite, and porphyry,<lb/>which, in different parts of the world, pass through every forma-<lb/>tion; and those of syenite, augite-porphyry, and amygdaloid,<lb/>which are characteristic of the newest strata of the transition<lb/>formation, and of the oldest rocks of the secondary strata, have<lb/>probably been formed in a similar manner. In the first age of<lb/>our planet, the yet liquid substances penetrated through the<lb/>crust of the earth, which was every where intersected by<lb/>fissures, and assumed the form of granular rocks, either in veins,<lb/>or spreading over and expanding themselves in strata. The rocks<lb/>strictly volcanic which the primitive ages have afforded us, have<lb/>not flowed in currents like the lava of our insulated conical hills;<lb/>the same mixture of augite, titaniferous iron, glassy felspar, and<lb/>hornblende, may have existed at different periods, but at one<lb/>time it may have approached nearer to basalt, and at others to<lb/>trachyte; the chemical substances may have combined in a<lb/>crystalline form, in distinct proportions, as we are taught by<lb/>M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Mitscherlich&#x2019;s</persName> new and important labours, and by the ana-<lb/>logy of artificial products of fire: we find that substances<lb/>similarly formed have arrived at the surface of the earth<lb/>in very different ways; they have either been merely raised, or<lb/>protruded by temporary fissures through the older strata; that<lb/>is to say, through the already oxidized surface of the earth; or<lb/>they have flowed, as currents of lava, from conical hills with a<lb/>permanent crater. By confounding such different ph&#x00E6;nomena<lb/>together, the geognosy of volcanoes is carried back to that dark-<lb/>ness from which a great number of comparative observations are<lb/>beginning to extricate it.</p><lb/><p>The question has often been asked, What is it that burns in<lb/>volcanoes? What was it that excited the heat by which earths<lb/>and metals were melted? Modern chemistry answers, that<lb/>the substances which melt are the metals of the earths and<lb/>alkalies. The solid crust of the earth, already oxidized, se-<lb/>parated the surrounding air with its oxygen, from the com-<lb/>bustible unoxidized substances of the interior of our planet.<lb/>The observations which have been made in mines and caves<lb/>in every zone, and which, in conjunction with M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Arago</persName>, I have<lb/>collected in a particular paper, demonstrate that the heat of the<lb/>mass of the earth is yet much greater than the mean temperature<lb/>of the atmosphere at the same place. Such a remarkable and<lb/>almost generally proved fact, is closely connected with those<lb/>which are proved by volcanic ph&#x00E6;nomena. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Laplace</persName> has even<lb/>gone so far as to endeavour to calculate the depth at which the<lb/>body of the earth may be considered to be a melted mass.<lb/>Whatever doubts may be entertained, notwithstanding the vene-<lb/>ration due to so great a name, with respect to the numerical<lb/>certainty of such a calculation, thus much remains probable;<lb/>that all volcanic ph&#x00E6;nomena originate in a very simple cause, in<lb/><pb n="134" facs="#f0014" />
        a permanent or in a variable communication between the interior<lb/>and the exterior of our planet.</p><lb/><p>The pressure of elastic vapour forces the melted substances<lb/>upwards through deep fissures while they are undergoing oxida-<lb/>tion; volcanoes, if I may so speak, are intermitting springs of<lb/>the earth; the liquid mixtures of metals, alkalies, and earths,<lb/>which on cooling become currents of lava, flow quietly when<lb/>they are raised, and find a vent. The ancients imagined,<lb/>according to <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Plato&#x2019;s</persName> <bibl>Ph&#x00E6;don</bibl>, that all volcanic currents of fire<lb/>flowed, in a similar way, from the Periphlegeton.</p><lb/><p>It may be permitted me, perhaps, to add to these considerations<lb/>one which is still more hazardous. In this interior heat of the<lb/>earth, indicated by experiments with the thermometer, and by<lb/>observations on volcanoes, the cause, perhaps, may be found, of<lb/>one of the most wonderful ph&#x00E6;nomena which the examination of<lb/>fossils presents to us. Tropical forms of animals, arboriform ferns,<lb/>palms, and bamboo-like plants, lie interred in the cold north.<lb/>The primitive world every where shows a distribution of organic<lb/>forms at variance with the then existing nature of the cli-<lb/>mate. In order to solve this important problem, several hypo-<lb/>theses have been invented; as the neighbourhood of a comet,<lb/>the altered inclination of the ecliptic, the increased intensity<lb/>of the solar light. Neither of these has been sufficient to<lb/>satisfy at once the astronomer, the natural philosopher, and<lb/>the geognost. For my part, I leave the axis of the earth un-<lb/>altered, as well as the light of the solar disc, by the spots<lb/>on which, a celebrated astronomer has explained both the ferti-<lb/>lity and the unfruitfulness of the fields; but I believe, that in<lb/>every planet, independently of its relation to a central body, and<lb/>of its astronomical situation, various causes exist of the produc-<lb/>tion of heat; oxidation, precipitation, and a change in the<lb/>capacity of bodies; by increase of electromagnetic charge, by<lb/>the opening of a communication between the interior and the<lb/>exterior part of the earth.</p><lb/><p>Where the deeply cleft crust of the earth in the primitive<lb/>world radiated heat from its fissures, whole countries, perhaps,<lb/>could produce for centuries, palms and arborescent ferns, and sus-<lb/>tain all the animals of the torrid zone. According to this view, to<lb/>which I have already alluded in a work just published, &#x201C;<bibl>Essai<lb/>Géognostique sur le Gissement des Roches dans les deux<lb/>Hemispheres</bibl>,&#x201D; the temperature of volcanoes would be that of the<lb/>interior of the earth itself, and the same cause which now occa-<lb/>sions such dreadful destruction, would once have occasioned,<lb/>on the newly oxidated crust of the earth, upon the deeply cleft<lb/>strata of rocks, the most luxuriant growth of plants in every<lb/>zone.</p><lb/><p>Even if any one should be inclined to suppose, in order to<lb/>explain the marvellous distribution of tropical forms in their<lb/><pb n="135" facs="#f0015" />
ancient graves, that shaggy animals of the elephant tribe now<lb/>imbedded in icebergs, were once peculiar to a northern climate,<lb/>and that similar forms belonging to the same primary types, like<lb/>lions and lynxes, could live in very different climates, such an<lb/>explanation could not, however, be extended to the products of<lb/>vegetation. For reasons which the physiology of plants<lb/>explains, palms, and arboriform monocotyledones cannot sustain<lb/>the northern cold, and in the geological problem we here speak<lb/>of, it seems difficult to me to separate plants and animals. The<lb/>same explanation must be applied to both.</p><lb/><p>Towards the end of this paper, I have combined uncertain<lb/>hypothetical suppositions with facts collected from the most<lb/>different parts of the world. The philosophical knowledge of<lb/>nature rises above a mere description of nature. It does not<lb/>consist in a sterile aggregation of isolated observations. It may<lb/>sometimes be allowed, therefore, to the curious and ever-active<lb/>mind of man, to look back upon the past, to imagine what cannot<lb/>be clearly known, and to amuse himself with the ancient, and,<lb/>under many forms, returning mysteries of geogony.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>