<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <dateline>APRIL...SEPTEMBER 1828.</dateline>
            <lb/>
            <pb n="222" facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Essay on the Structure and Action of Volcanoes in different re-<lb/>gions of the Earth.</hi> By Baron <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">Translated from the Tableaux de la Nature, par Humboldt, t. ii.</note>.</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#in">W</hi>hen</hi> we reflect upon the influence which, for many ages,<lb/>has been exercised upon the study of nature, by the improve-<lb/>ments of geography, and by scientific journeys made into dis-<lb/>tant regions, we quickly perceive how different this influence<lb/>
                    <pb n="223" facs="#f0002" /> has been, according as the researches have been directed toward<lb/>the forms of the organic world, or toward the inanimate mass<lb/>of the earth. Different forms of plants and animals enliven the<lb/>earth&#x2019;s surface in each zone, however much the heat of the at-<lb/>mosphere may change, whether according to the geographical<lb/>latitude, or the numerous curves of the isothermal lines, in the<lb/>extended plains, level as the surface of the sea, or in an almost<lb/>vertical direction on the steep slopes of the mountain chains.<lb/>Organic nature gives to each region of the earth the peculiar<lb/>physiognomy by which it is distinguished. The case is different<lb/>with inorganic nature in the places where the solid envelope of<lb/>the earth is deprived of vegetation. The same species of rocks,<lb/>attracting and repelling each other by groups, disclose them-<lb/>selves in the two hemispheres, from the equator to the poles.<lb/>In a distant isle, surrounded by unknown plants, in a clime<lb/>where the stars to which his eye is habituated no longer shine,<lb/>the voyager often recognises with joy the granite of his native<lb/>country, and the rocks which he has been accustomed to see.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>This independence upon the present constitution of climates,<lb/>which is peculiar to inorganic nature, does not diminish the be-<lb/>neficial influence which numerous observations, made in distant<lb/>countries, have upon the progress of geognosy; it only gives<lb/>them a particular direction. Each succeeding expedition en-<lb/>riches natural history with new species of animals and plants.<lb/>Sometimes organic forms are discovered which connect them-<lb/>selves with types long known, and which present in its original<lb/>perfection the regularly woven, and often apparently interrupt-<lb/>ed, net-work of animated natural forms. Sometimes the dis-<lb/>coveries consist of forms which present themselves isolated, like<lb/>the remains of extinct races; sometimes of members of yet un-<lb/>known groups. The examination of the solid crust of the earth<lb/>exhibits no such diversity. On the contrary, it discloses, in the<lb/>constituent parts, in the relative position, and in the periodical<lb/>recurrence of the different masses, a similarity which strikes the<lb/>geologist with astonishment. In the chain of the Andes, as in<lb/>the central mountains of Europe, one formation seems, as it<lb/>were, to recal another. Masses of the same name assume simi-<lb/>lar forms; the basalt and greenstone form twin mountains;<lb/>dolomite, white sandstone and porphyry, form masses broken<lb/>
                    <pb n="224" facs="#f0003" /> into cliffs; trachyte, rich in vitreous felspar, rises into domes.<lb/>In the most distant zones, large crystals separate similarly,<lb/>as by an internal development, from the compact texture of<lb/>the primitive mass, form themselves into groups, appear as<lb/>subordinate masses, and often announce the vicinity of indepen-<lb/>dent new formations. In this manner the whole inorganic world<lb/>is evidently pictured in every mountain chain of any extent.<lb/>To become perfectly acquainted, however, with the most im-<lb/>portant phenomena of the composition, relative age, and origin<lb/>of the formations, it is necessary to compare, with each other,<lb/>observations made in countries the most widely separated, pro-<lb/>blems which have long seemed enigmatical to geologists living in<lb/>the north, find their solution near the equator. If, as has been<lb/>observed, the distant zones do not furnish us with new forma-<lb/>tions, that is to say, unknown groups of simple substances, they<lb/>yet enable us to understand the uniform laws of nature, by<lb/>which the various strata support each other, penetrate into each<lb/>other&#x2019;s substance in the form of veins, or raise each other in<lb/>obedience to elastic powers.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>If it be true that our geognostical knowledge derives the<lb/>greatest advantage from researches made over vast expanses of<lb/>country, it ought not to excite surprise that the class of pheno-<lb/>mena which forms the principal object of this memoir should,<lb/>till lately, have been examined in a very imperfect manner, be-<lb/>cause the points of comparison are very difficult, and may even<lb/>be said laborious, to find. Until the end of the eighteenth<lb/>century, all that was known of the form of volcanoes, and of the<lb/>action of their subterranean powers, was derived from two moun-<lb/>tains in the south of Italy, Vesuvius and Etna. The former<lb/>being the most accessible, and, like all volcanoes of inferior ele-<lb/>vation, having more frequent eruptions, a small hill became, in<lb/>some measure, the type according to which a whole distant<lb/>world was represented, containing the great volcanoes of Mexi-<lb/>co, South America, and the Asiatic Isles. This mode of rea-<lb/>soning might naturally bring to our recollection Virgil&#x2019;s shep-<lb/>herd, who, in his humble cabin, imagined he saw the image of<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">eternal city.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb/>
                <p>An attentive examination of the whole Mediterranean, espe-<lb/>cially its islands and eastern shores, where the human race has<lb/>
                    <pb n="225" facs="#f0004" /> begun to rise in the progress of intellect, and in the cultivation<lb/>of generous feelings, might, however, reform this imperfect man-<lb/>ner of studying nature. Among the Sporades, trachyte rocks<lb/>have risen from the bottom of the sea, and formed islands, like<lb/>that among the Azores, which, in the space of three centuries,<lb/>has shewn itself at nearly equal intervals. Between Epidaurus<lb/>and Trèzéne, near Methone, in the Peleponnesus, there occurs<lb/>a Monte Nuovo, which was described by Strabo, and has been<lb/>seen again by Dodwell. It is higher than the Monte Nuovo of<lb/>the Phlegrean Fields, near Bai&#x00E6;, perhaps even higher than the<lb/>new Volcano of Jorullo, in the Plains of Mexico, which I found<lb/>surrounded with many thousands of small basaltic cones, that<lb/>had issued from the ground, and were still smoking. In the<lb/>basin of the Mediterranean, not only does the volcanic fire es-<lb/>cape from permanent craters of isolated mountains, which have<lb/>a constant communication with the interior of the earth, as<lb/>Stromboli, Vesuvius, and Etna; but at Ischia, on Mount Epo-<lb/>mée; and, according to the accounts of the ancients, in the Plains<lb/>of Lelantis, near Chalcis, lavas have flowed from fissures which<lb/>have suddenly opened at the surface of the ground.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Independently of these phenomena which belong to historical<lb/>times, to the limited domain of sure tradition, the shores of the<lb/>Mediterranean contain numerous remains of more ancient effects<lb/>of the action of fire. The south of France, in Auvergne, dis-<lb/>plays a particular and entire system of volcanoes, arranged in<lb/>series, of trachytic domes, alternating with cones perforated with<lb/>craters, from which torrents of lava have flowed in narrow<lb/>stripes. The Plain of Lombardy, which, smooth as the surface<lb/>of the waters, forms the most remote gulf of the Adriatic Sea,<lb/>surrounds the trachyte of the Euganean Hills, in which there<lb/>rise domes of granular trachyte, obsidian, and perlite, forming<lb/>three masses proceeding from each other, which have forced<lb/>their way through the Juraic limestone, filled with flints, but<lb/>which have never run in narrow torrents. Similar evidences of<lb/>ancient revolutions of the earth occur in various parts of the<lb/>Continent of Greece and of Asia Minor, a country which will<lb/>one day present rich materials for geological research, when<lb/>light shall have returned to those countries whence it began to<lb/>
                    <pb n="226" facs="#f0005" /> shine on the west, when outraged humanity shall no longer<lb/>groan beneath the savage barbarity of the Ottomans.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>I bring forward the geographical proximity of these numerous<lb/>phenomena, to shew that the basin of the Mediterranean, with<lb/>its islands, is capable of presenting to the attentive observer all<lb/>that has recently been discovered, under various forms, in South<lb/>America, in Teneriffe, or in the Aleutian Isles, in the vicinity<lb/>of the polar regions. The objects to be observed were united<lb/>together; but travels into distant regions, and comparisons of<lb/>extensive countries in Europe and out of it, were necessary for<lb/>clearly shewing the mutual resemblance of volcanic phenomena,<lb/>and their dependence upon one another.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Common language, which often gives consistency and dura-<lb/>tion to ideas arising from the most erroneous views of things,<lb/>but which also frequently indicates the truth instinctively,<lb/>gives the name of Volcanic to all the eruptions of subterranean<lb/>fires and melted substances; to the columns of smoke and va-<lb/>pour which issue from the heart of rocks, as at Colares, after the<lb/>great earthquake at Lisbon; to the salses or cones of clay which<lb/>vomit mud, asphaltes, and hydrogen, as at Girgenti, in Sicily,<lb/>and at Turbaco, in South America; to the hot springs of the<lb/>Geyser, which, impelled by elastic vapours, rise to an immense<lb/>height; in a word, to all the effects of the mighty powers of na-<lb/>ture, which have their seat in the interior of our planet. In<lb/>central America, or in the country of Guatemala, and in the<lb/>Philippine Isles, the natives make an essential difference between<lb/>water volcanoes and fire volcanoes (<hi rendition="#i">volcanes de agua y de fuego</hi>).<lb/>By the former name they designate the mountains, from which,<lb/>amid violent earthquakes, subterranean waters issue from time<lb/>to time.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Without denying the connection of the phenomena just men-<lb/>tioned, it would yet appear expedient to give a more precise lan-<lb/>guage to the physical and oryctognostical department of geo-<lb/>gnosy, in order to prevent the application of the name of Volcano,<lb/>sometimes to a mountain which is terminated by a permanent<lb/>furnace, and sometimes to each subterranean cause of volcanic<lb/>phenomena. In the present state of the terrestrial globe, the<lb/>most common form of volcanoes, in all parts of the world, is<lb/>that of an isolated cone, such as Vesuvius, Etna, the Peak of<lb/>
                    <pb n="227" facs="#f0006" /> Teyde, Tunguragua, and Cotopaxi. I have observed them<lb/>rising from the size of the lowest hills to 17,700 feet above the<lb/>level of the sea. But close to these conical mountains, there al-<lb/>so occur permanent apertures, forming regular communications<lb/>with the interior of the earth, on long serrated chains, not at the<lb/>middle of their mural summit, but at their extremity, and near<lb/>the declivity. Of this kind is Pichincha, which rises between<lb/>the great ocean and the city of Quito, and which Bouguer&#x2019;s ba-<lb/>rometrical formul&#x00E6; have long rendered celebrated. Such also<lb/>are the volcanoes which rise on the Steppe de los Pastos, which<lb/>is 10,000 feet high. All these summits, of varied forms, are<lb/>composed of trachyte, formerly named trap porphyry, a granu-<lb/>lar fissured rock, formed of glassy felspar and hornblende, and<lb/>in which augite, mica, laminar felspar, and quartz, also occur.<lb/>In places where the evidences of the first eruption I might say<lb/>of the ancient volcanic scaffolding, are preserved entire, the iso-<lb/>lated conical mountain is surrounded, in the form of an amphi-<lb/>theatre, with a great wall, constructed of rocky strata, super-<lb/>imposed upon each other. These walls or circumvallations are<lb/>the remains of <hi rendition="#i">craters of elevation,</hi> a phenomenon worthy of<lb/>attention, respecting which the first geologist of our times, M.<lb/>Leopold Von Buch, in his writings, from which I have borrowed<lb/>several ideas stated in the present memoir, has presented such<lb/>interesting views.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The volcanoes which communicate with the atmosphere by<lb/>permanent apertures, the basaltic cones or domes of trachyte,<lb/>destitute of crater, sometimes low like Sarcouy, and sometimes<lb/>elevated like Chimborazo, form various groups. Comparative<lb/>geography shews us, on the one hand, small archipelagoes, and<lb/>entire systems of volcanic mountains, with their oraters and cur-<lb/>rents of lava, resembling those of the Canary Islands, and the<lb/>Azores; and, on the other, mountains without craters, and with-<lb/>out currents of lava, properly so called, as the Euganeans, and<lb/>the (Siebengebirge) seven mountains of Bonn. Moreover, it<lb/>shews us volcanoes arranged in single or double lines, and extend-<lb/>ing to several hundreds of leagues, sometimes parallel to the axis<lb/>of the chain, as in Guatemala, Peru, and Java; sometimes cutting<lb/>it perpendicularly, as in the country of the Azteques, where tra-<lb/>chytic mountains, which vomit fire, alone attain the height of<lb/>
                    <pb n="228" facs="#f0007" /> perpetual snow, and are probably situated upon a crevice tra-<lb/>versing the whole continent, over an extent of 105 geographical<lb/>leagues from the Pacific Ocean to the Atlantic.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>This association of volcanoes, whether in isolated and rounded<lb/>groups, or in longitudinal bands, demonstrates, in the most de-<lb/>cisive manner, that volcanic effects do not depend upon slight<lb/>causes existing near the surface of the earth, but are phenomena<lb/>whose origin is to be found at a great depth in the interior of<lb/>the globe. The whole eastern part of the American continent,<lb/>which is poor in metals, is, in its present state, destitute of vol-<lb/>canic mountains, of masses of trachyte, and probably even basalt,<lb/>with olivine. All the American volcanoes are collected together<lb/>in the chain of the Andes, which is situated in the part of that<lb/>continent opposite to Asia, and which extends, in the direction<lb/>of the meridians, over a space of 1800 leagues. The whole<lb/>plain of Quito, of which Pichincha, Cotopaxi, and Tunguraqua<lb/>form the cymes, is a volcanic focus. The subterranean fire<lb/>escapes, sometimes by one, sometimes by another, of those aper-<lb/>tures which it has been customary to consider as distinct vol-<lb/>canoes. The progressive march of the fire in them has, for the<lb/>last three centuries, been from north to south. The very earth-<lb/>quakes, which produce such terrible ravages in this part of the<lb/>world, afford remarkable proofs of the existence of subterranean<lb/>communications, not only with countries destitute of volcanoes,<lb/>which has been long known, but also between ignivomous<lb/>mountains placed at very great distances from each other.<lb/>Thus, in 1797, the volcano of Pasto, to the east of the course of<lb/>the Guaytara, vomited, unremittingly, for three months, a high<lb/>column of smoke. This column disappeared at the very mo-<lb/>ment, when, at a distance of sixty leagues, the great carthquake<lb/>of Riobamba, and the muddy eruption of Moya, destroyed<lb/>about forty thousand Indians. The sudden appearance of the<lb/>Island of Sabrina, to the east of the Azores, on the 30th Janu-<lb/>ary 1811, was announced by the dreadful earthquake, which,<lb/>at a much greater distance to the west, from May 1811 to June<lb/>1812, shook, almost without intermission, first the West India<lb/>Islands, then the plains of the Ohio and Missisippi, and, lastly,<lb/>the coasts of Venezuela, situated on the opposite side. Thirty<lb/>days after the total destruction of the city of Caraccas, the ex-<lb/>
                    <pb n="229" facs="#f0008" /> plosion of the volcano of St Vincent, in the Lesser Antilles,<lb/>took place at a distance of 130 leagues. At the same moment<lb/>when this eruption happened, on the 30th April 1811, a sub-<lb/>terranean noise was propagated, and carried terror over an ex-<lb/>tent of country of 2200 square leagues. The inhabitants of the<lb/>banks of the Apuré, at the confluence of the Rio Nula, as well<lb/>as those of the sea coast, compared the noise to that produced<lb/>by the discharge of large pieces of artillery. Now, from the<lb/>confluence of the Rio Nula and Apure, by which I arrived at the<lb/>Oronocco, to the volcano of St Vincent, the distance is 157<lb/>leagues in a straight line. This noise, which assuredly was not<lb/>propagated by the air, must have had its cause deep in the earth.<lb/>Its intensity was scarcely greater on the shores of the Antilles,<lb/>near the volcano in action, than in the interior of the country.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>It would be useless to multiply examples; but in order to<lb/>recall to mind a phenomenon which has acquired a historical<lb/>importance with reference to Europe, I shall now mention the<lb/>famous earthquake of Lisbon. It took place on the 1st Novem-<lb/>ber 1755. Not only were the waters of the Swiss Lakes, and<lb/>of the sea on the coasts of Sweden, violently agitated; but also<lb/>those of the sea around the eastern Antilles. At Martinique,<lb/>Antigua, and Barbadoes, where the tide does not commonly rise<lb/>more than eighteen inches, it suddenly rose twenty feet. All<lb/>these phenomena prove, that the subterranean powers manifest<lb/>themselves, either dynamically, by earthquakes, or chemically,<lb/>by occasioning changes in the form of volcanic eruptions. They<lb/>also demonstrate, that these powers act, not superficially in the<lb/>outer crust of the earth, but at immense depths in the interior<lb/>of our planet, by crevices and unfilled veins, which lead to points<lb/>of the earth&#x2019;s surface, at the greatest distances from each other.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The more numerous the diversities in the structure of volca-<lb/>noes, or in other words, of the elevations surrounding the canals<lb/>by which the melted masses of the interior of the globe arrive<lb/>at its surface, so much the more important is it to submit this<lb/>structure to accurate measurements. The interest of these mea-<lb/>surements, which, in another part of the world, have formed<lb/>the object of my researches, increases if we consider that the<lb/>magnitude to be measured varies in several points. The phi-<lb/>losophical examination of nature applies itself, in the vicissitude<lb/>
                    <pb n="230" facs="#f0009" /> of phenomena, to connect the present with the past. To esta-<lb/>blish a periodical return, or to fix the laws of progressive and<lb/>variable phenomena, it is necessary to have some well determined<lb/>points of departure, observations made with care, and which,<lb/>being conneoted with determined epochs, may furnish numeri-<lb/>cal comparisons. Had only the mean temperature of the atmo-<lb/>sphere, and of the earth in different latitudes, or the mean tempe-<lb/>rature of the barometer on the edge of the sea, been determined<lb/>from one century to another, we should have known in what pro-<lb/>portion the heat of climates has increased or diminished, and<lb/>whether or not the height of the atmosphere has undergone<lb/>changes. These points of comparison are required for the decli-<lb/>nation and inclination of the magnetic needle, as well as for the<lb/>intensity of the electro-magnetic forces. If it be a praiseworthy<lb/>occupation for societies to follow, with assiduity, the cosmic vicis-<lb/>situdes of heat, of the pressure of the air, and of the magnetic<lb/>direction and intensity; it is, on the other hand, the duty of the<lb/>geologist, in determining the inequalities of the earth&#x2019;s surface, to<lb/>take into consideration the change of height of volcanoes. What<lb/>I attempted at the time, in the mountains of Mexico, at To-<lb/>luca, Nauhamputeptel and Jorullo, and in the Andes of Quito at<lb/>Pichincha, I have had an opportunity, since my return to Eu-<lb/>rope, of repeating several times at Vesuvius.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In 1773, Saussure measured that mountain at a period when<lb/>the two edges of the crater, the north-west and south-west, ap-<lb/>peared to him of equal height. He found their elevation 609<lb/>toises above the level of the sea. The eruption of 1794 occa-<lb/>sioned a falling in of the southern part, and an inequality of the<lb/>edges of the crater which the most inexperienced eye distin-<lb/>guishes at a considerable distance. In 1805, M. von Buch, M.<lb/>Gay Lussac and myself, measured Vesuvius three times. The<lb/>result of our operations was, that the height of the north<lb/>edge, the Rocca del Palo, which is opposite the Somma, agreed<lb/>with Saussure&#x2019;s measurement, but that the south edge was 75<lb/>toises lower than in 1773. The total elevation of the volcano,<lb/>towards the Torre del Greco, the side towards which the fire<lb/>had principally directed its action for thirty years, had diminish-<lb/>ed an eighth part. The cone of ashes is, to the total height of<lb/>the mountain, on Vesuvius, as one to ten; on the Peak of Te-<lb/>
                    <pb n="231" facs="#f0010" /> neriffe as one to twenty-two. Vesuvius, therefore, has the cone<lb/>of ashes proportionally higher, probably because, as a volcano of<lb/>little height, it has acted principally by its summit. I succeed-<lb/>ed lately not only in repeating my barometrical measurements on<lb/>Vesuvius, but also in ascending that mountain three times, in<lb/>order to take a complete survey of all the edges of the crater.<lb/>This undertaking is perhaps deserving of some interest, because<lb/>it embraces the period of the great eruptions from 1805 to 1822;<lb/>and because it affords, perhaps, the only measurement of the<lb/>volcano, made with reference to all its parts, that has hitherto<lb/>been published. It shews that the edges of the crater, not only<lb/>in the places where they are visibly composed of trachyte, as in<lb/>the Peak of Teneriffe, and in all the volcanoes of the chain of<lb/>the Andes, but also every where else, present a phenomenon<lb/>much more constant than had previously been supposed from ob-<lb/>servations hastily made. Simple angles of height, determined from<lb/>the same point, answer much better for researches of this kind<lb/>than trigonometrical and barometrical measurements, otherwise<lb/>very complete. According to my last determination, the north-<lb/>west edge of Vesuvius has not perhaps undergone any diminu-<lb/>tion of height since the time of Saussure, that is to say for the<lb/>last forty-nine years, and the south-east edge, on the Bosche Tre-<lb/>Case side, which, in 1794, was 400 feet lower than the preced-<lb/>ing, has undergone a diminution of 10 toises.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>If the public journals, in describing the great eruptions, very<lb/>frequently relate that the form of Vesuvius has totally changed,<lb/>and if these assertions are confirmed by the picturesque views<lb/>of that mountain which are painted at Naples, the cause of<lb/>error exists in the circumstance that the contour of the edges of<lb/>the crater is confounded with those of the heaps of scori&#x00E6; which<lb/>are accidentally formed in the centre of the crater, on the bot-<lb/>tom of the ignivomous mouth raised up by vapours. One of<lb/>these heaps, consisting of rapilli and scori&#x00E6;, became gradually<lb/>visible in 1816 and 1818, above the south-east edge of the<lb/>crater. The eruption of February 1822 increased it to such a<lb/>degree, that it even exceeded the Rocca del Palo, or the north-<lb/>west edge of the crater, by 100 or 110 feet. In the last erup-<lb/>tion, the remarkable cone, which was usually considered as the<lb/>true summit of Vesuvius, fell down with a terrible noise, so that<lb/>
                    <pb n="232" facs="#f0011" /> the bottom of the crater, which, since 1811, was always acces-<lb/>sible, is now 750 feet lower than the northern edge of the vol-<lb/>cano, and 200 feet lower than the southern. The variable<lb/>form and relative position of the cones of eruption, whose aper-<lb/>ture ought not, as is too often done, to be confounded with the<lb/>crater of the volcano, give a particular aspect to Vesuvius at<lb/>different periods, and the historiographer of this volcano might,<lb/>from the contours of the summit, and from the simple inspection<lb/>of the landscapes painted by Hackert, which are at Portici, ac-<lb/>cording as the northern or southern side of the mountain is re-<lb/>presented higher or lower, guess the year in which the artist<lb/>made the drawing from which he composed his picture.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>A day after the cone of scori&#x00E6;, 400 feet high, had fallen in,<lb/>when already small but numerous torrents of lava had flowed,<lb/>in the night of the 23d October, commenced the luminous erup-<lb/>tion of ashes and rapilli. It lasted twelve days without inter-<lb/>ruption; but it was more intense during the first four. All this<lb/>time, the detonations in the interior of the volcano were so vio-<lb/>lent, that the mere concussion of the air (for no commotion was<lb/>observed in the earth), cracked the ceilings of the apartments in<lb/>the palace of Portici. The villages of Resina, Torre-del-Greco,<lb/>Torre del Anunziata, and Bosche-Tre-Case, which are close up-<lb/>on the mountain, witnessed a remarkable phenomenon. The<lb/>atmosphere was so filled with ashes, that the whole district was<lb/>for several hours in the middle of the day enveloped in profound<lb/>darkness. People used lanterns in the streets, as often hap-<lb/>pens at Quito, during the eruptions of Pichincha. The inhabi-<lb/>tants never fled in such numbers. The torrents of lava were<lb/>much less dreaded than an eruption of ashes,&#x2014;a phenomenon<lb/>which had not before been known to such a degree, and which,<lb/>from the obscure tradition of the manner in which Hercula-<lb/>neum, Pompeii and Stabi&#x00E6; were destroyed, filled the imagination<lb/>of men with terrifying images.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The watery and hot vapour which shot up from the crater<lb/>during the eruption, and diffused itself in the atmosphere, form-<lb/>ed, on cooling, a thick cloud round the column of ashes and<lb/>flame which rose to the height of 9000 feet. So rapid a con-<lb/>densation of the vapours, and, as M. Gay Lussac has shewn, the<lb/>very formation of the cloud, augmented the electrical intensity.<lb/>
                    <pb n="233" facs="#f0012" /> Flashes issued from the column of ashes in all directions, and<lb/>the thunder, which was easily distinguished from the noises of<lb/>the volcano, was distinctly heard. In no other eruption was<lb/>the manifestation of the electric powers so astonishing.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>On the morning of the 26th October, a surprising noise was<lb/>heard, which seemed to arise from a torrent of boiling water that<lb/>was ejected from the crater, and descended along the declivity of<lb/>the cone of the ashes. Monticelli, the learned and zealous ob-<lb/>server of the volcano, immediately discovered that an optical il-<lb/>lusion had occasioned this erroneous rumour. The supposed<lb/>torrent was a great heap of dry ashes, which issued from a<lb/>crevice in the upper edge of the crater. A drought which<lb/>spread desolation in the fields, had preceded the eruption of Ve-<lb/>suvius. Toward the end of this phenomenon, the volcanic<lb/>thunder storm which we have just been describing, occasioned an<lb/>extremely heavy and long continued rain. In all countries, the<lb/>cessation of an eruption is characterized by a similar meteor.<lb/>So long as the present one lasted, the cone of ashes being gene-<lb/>rally enveloped with clouds, and the rain being heaviest in its<lb/>vicinity, torrents of mud were seen flowing on all sides. The<lb/>affrighted husbandman thought it was water, that, after ascend-<lb/>ing from the bottom of the volcano, issued by the crater. The<lb/>geologist thought he discovered in it sea water, or muddy<lb/>productions of the volcano, or, to use the expression of the<lb/>French old systematic writers, products of an igno-aqueous li-<lb/>quefaction.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>When the summit of the volcano, as is almost always the case<lb/>in the Andes, rises above the region of snow, or attains a height<lb/>double that of Etna, the snow, by melting and flowing toward<lb/>the lower regions, produces frequent and disastrous inunda-<lb/>tions. These are phenomena which the meteors connect with<lb/>the eruptions of volcanoes, and which are variously modified by<lb/>the height of the mountain, the extent of its summit covered with<lb/>perpetual snows, and the heating of the walls of the cone of<lb/>cinders. They cannot at all be regarded as true volcanic phe-<lb/>nomena, being merely the effects of such phenomena. In vast<lb/>cavities, sometimes on the declivity, sometimes at the foot of<lb/>volcanoes, are found subterranean lakes which communicate in<lb/>various ways with the alpine torrents. When the commotions<lb/>
                    <pb n="234" facs="#f0013" /> of the earth which always precede all the igneous eruptions in the<lb/>chain of the Andes, have violently shaken the whole mass of the<lb/>volcano, then the subterranean gulfs open, and there issue at the<lb/>same time water, fishes, and clay tufa. Such is the singular phe-<lb/>nomenon which brings to light the <hi rendition="#i">Pimelodes cyclopum,</hi> a fish to<lb/>which the inhabitants of the plain of Quito gave the name of<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Prenadilla,</hi> and which I described shortly after my return.<lb/>When to the north of Chimborazo, in the night of the 19th<lb/>June 1698. the summit of Carguaraizo, a mountain of the height<lb/>of 18,000 feet, broke down, the whole country round, to the ex-<lb/>tent of nearly two square leaguges, was covered with mud<lb/>and fishes. Seven years before, a pernicious fever, which de-<lb/>solated the city of Iburra, was attributed to a similar eruption<lb/>of fishes from the volcano of Imbaburu.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>I mention these facts, because they throw some light on the<lb/>difference which exists between the eruptions of dry ashes and<lb/>those of mud, wood, charcoal, or shells, serving to explain the<lb/>formation of tufa and trass. The quantity of ashes thrown<lb/>out by Vesuvius of late years, like all the circumstances con-<lb/>nected with volcanoes, and other great phenomena of nature<lb/>calculated to inspire terror, has been excessively exaggerated in<lb/>the public journals. Two chemists of Naples, Vicenzo Pepe<lb/>and Giuseppe di Nobili, have even affirmed, notwithstanding<lb/>the contrary assertions of Monticelli and Covelli, that the ashes<lb/>contain gold and silver. According to my inquiries, the bed of<lb/>ashes that fell during twelve days on the Bosch-Tre-Case side,<lb/>on the declivity of the cone, in the places where rapillo was<lb/>mingled with them, was only three feet deep, and in the plain,<lb/>did not rise higher than from fifteen to eighteen inches. Mea-<lb/>surements of this kind should not be taken in places where the<lb/>ashes are heaped up, like snow or sand, by the wind, or aceu-<lb/>mulated by water in the form of mud. The times are gone<lb/>when wonders only were looked for in volcanic phenomena, or<lb/>when the ashes of Etna were represented as being carried by<lb/>the winds as far as the peninsula of India. Some of the gold<lb/>and silver veins of Mexico certainly occur in a trachytic por-<lb/>phyry; but the ashes of Vesuvius, which I carried along with<lb/>me, and which were analysed by an excellent chemist M. Henry<lb/>Rose, afford not the slightest traces of gold or silver.</p>
                <lb/>
                <pb n="235" facs="#f0014" />
                <p>Although the results of which I speak, and which are in per-<lb/>fect accordance with the accurate observations of Monticelli,<lb/>differ much from those published some months ago, the eruption<lb/>of ashes from Vesuvius which took place on the 24th and 28th of<lb/>October 1822, is undoubtedly the most remarkable of which we<lb/>have any authentic accounts since the death of the elder Pliny<lb/>in the year 70. The quantity of ashes which then fell was per-<lb/>haps three times as great as any that has been observed since<lb/>volcanic phenomena first began to be studied with attention.<lb/>A layer of fifty or eighty inches appears at first sight insignifi-<lb/>cant in comparison of the mass which covered Pompeii; but,<lb/>without speaking of torrents of rain, and of the effects of detri-<lb/>tion, which, in the course of ages, may have accumulated this<lb/>mass, and without reviving the keen discussion which arose be-<lb/>yond the Alps, and which was conducted with a great degree<lb/>of scepticism, respecting the causes of the destruction of the cities<lb/>of Campania, it is perhaps to the purpose to mention here, that<lb/>the eruptions of a volcano at periods very remote from each<lb/>other, can by no means be compared together with reference to<lb/>their intensity. All the consequences founded upon analogies<lb/>are insufficient, when the objects to be compared are such as the<lb/>mass of lava and cinders, the height of the columns of smoke,<lb/>and the loudness of the detonations.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The geographical description of Vesuvius by Strabo, and<lb/>Vitruvius&#x2019;s opinion respecting the volcanic origin of pumice,<lb/>shew, that, until the year of Vespasian&#x2019;s death, that is to say,<lb/>until the eruption which overwhelmed Pompeii, that mountain<lb/>resembled more an extinct volcano than a solfaterra. After a<lb/>long repose, the subterranean forces opened up new paths, and<lb/>penetrated through the strata of primitive rocks and trachyte.<lb/>Then must have been manifested effects of which those that<lb/>have since followed could furnish no idea. The celebrated let-<lb/>ter, in which the younger Pliny relates to Tacitus the death of<lb/>his uncle, clearly shews that the renewal of the eruptions, and it<lb/>might even be said the awakening of the dormant volcano, com-<lb/>menced with an explosion of ashes. The same thing was ob-<lb/>served at Jorullo, when, in September 1759, the new volcano,<lb/>piercing through the strata of syenite and trachyte, rose sudden-<lb/>ly in the plain. The country people fled, because they found<lb/>
                    <pb n="236" facs="#f0015" /> on their huts ashes which the earth had vomited by opening up<lb/>on all sides. On the contrary, in the periodical and ordinary<lb/>explosions of volcanoes, the ashes terminate each partial erup-<lb/>tion. Besides, the younger Pliny&#x2019;s letter contains a passage,<lb/>which clearly shews, that, from the commencement, without the<lb/>influence of any cause that could have heaped them up, the dry<lb/>ashes that fell directly from above, had attained a height of four<lb/>or five feet. &#x201C;The court,&#x201D; says he in the course of his narra-<lb/>tive, which had to be passed in order to enter the chamber<lb/>in which Pliny reposed, &#x201C;was so filled with ashes and pumice,<lb/>that, if he had delayed his coming out any longer, he would<lb/>have found the entrance shut up.&#x201D; In an inclosed space, like<lb/>that of a court, the action of the wind, by which the ashes are<lb/>collected, could not by any means have been very considerable.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>I have ventured to interrupt my comparative examination of<lb/>volcanoes by particular observations made on Vesuvius, both on<lb/>account of the great interest which the last eruption has excit-<lb/>ed, and on account of the remembrance of the catastrophe of<lb/>Pompeii and Herculaneum, which every considerable fall of<lb/>ashes involuntarily brings to the mind. I have brought toge-<lb/>ther, in a supplement, all the elements of the barometrical mea-<lb/>surements and notices respecting geological collections that I<lb/>have had an opportunity of making, towards the end of 1822, at<lb/>Vesuvius and in the Phlegrean fields, near Pouzzuolo. This small<lb/>collection, together with the rocks which I brought from the<lb/>Euganean mountains, and those which M. von Buch collected on<lb/>a journey to the valley of Flemme, between Cavalere and Pre-<lb/>dazzo, in the southern Tyrol, are deposited in the Royal Mu-<lb/>seum of Berlin, an establishment which, by its utility, perfectly<lb/>corresponds to the noble intentions of the monarch, and of which,<lb/>the geognostical department, containing specimens from the most<lb/>remote regions, is, in this respect, superior to any collection of<lb/>this kind in existence.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>We have been considering the form and action of those vol-<lb/>canoes which keep up a regular communication with the interior<lb/>of the earth, by means of craters. Their summits are masses of<lb/>trachyte and lava, raised up by elastic powers, and traversed by<lb/>veins. The permanence of their action gives rise to the conclu-<lb/>sion, that their structure is very complicated. They have, so<lb/>
                    <pb n="237" facs="#f0016" /> to speak, an individual character, which remains always the<lb/>same through long periods. The neighbouring mountains<lb/>most commonly afford entirely different products, lavas of<lb/>leucite and felspar, obsidian and pumice, and basaltic masses<lb/>containing olivine. They belong to the most recent forma-<lb/>tions of the globe, and traverse nearly all the strata of the<lb/>secondary mountains. Their eruptions and their torrents of la-<lb/>va are of a more recent origin than our valleys. Their life, if<lb/>we may be permitted to make use of such an expression, de-<lb/>pends upon the mode and duration of their communication with<lb/>the interior of the earth. They frequently remain quiet for<lb/>ages, suddenly kindle again, and end with being solfaterras, ex-<lb/>haling aqueous vapours, gases and acids. Sometimes, as in the<lb/>Peak of Teneriffe, their summit has already become a laborato-<lb/>ry of regenerated sulphur; while from their sides there yet flow<lb/>great torrents of lava, basaltic and lithoid in their lower parts,<lb/>vitreous, in the form of obsidian and pumice, in their upper<lb/>part, where the pressure is less.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Independently of these volcanoes provided with permanent<lb/>craters, there is another species of volcanic phenomena, which is<lb/>more rarely observed, but which is peculiarly calculated to throw<lb/>light on geology, because it recalls the primitive world, or, in<lb/>other words, the most ancient revolutions of our globe. Moun-<lb/>tains of trachyte, opening of a sudden, vomit forth lava and<lb/>ashes, and again shut perhaps for ever. This is what took place in<lb/>the gigantic Antisana, in the Chain of the Andes, and at Mount<lb/>Epomeus in the island of Ischia, in 1302. An eruption of this<lb/>kind sometimes takes place in the plains; for example, on the<lb/>plain of Quito; in Iceland, at a distance from Hecla; in Eu-<lb/>beus, in the fields of Lelantée. Many islands, suddenly ele-<lb/>vated from the bottom of the sea, belong to these transitory<lb/>phenomena. In these cases, the communication with the inte-<lb/>rior of the earth is not permanent; the action ceases as soon as<lb/>the aperture of the canal of communication is closed anew.<lb/>Veins of basalt, greenstone, and porphyry, which in the different<lb/>zones of the earth traverse almost all the formations, masses<lb/>of syenite, augite, porphyry and amygdaloid, which characte-<lb/>rize the newest strata of the transition, and the oldest strata of<lb/>the secondary rocks, have probably been formed in this manner.<lb/>
                    <pb n="238" facs="#f0017" /> In the early stages of our planet, the substances of the interior,<lb/>still in a state of fluidity, penetrated through the envelope of the<lb/>earth which was fissured in all parts; sometimes condensing as<lb/>masses of veins with a granulated texture, sometimes spreading<lb/>out into sheets and stratified torrents. The volcanic rocks which<lb/>the primitive world has transmitted to us, have nowhere flowed<lb/>in narrow bands like the lavas that issue from the volcanic cones<lb/>existing at present. The mixtures of augite, titanitic iron,<lb/>glassy felspar, and hornblende, may have been the same at differ-<lb/>ent periods, sometimes more allied to basalt, and sometimes to<lb/>trachyte. The chemical substances, as we learn from the im-<lb/>portant labours of M. Mitscherlich, and the similarity of the<lb/>products of high furnaces, may have been united under a crys-<lb/>talline form, according to definite proportions. It is not the less<lb/>true, that substances, composed in the same manner, have ar-<lb/>rived by very different ways at the earth&#x2019;s surface, whether by<lb/>being raised up by elastic forces, or by being insinuated through<lb/>crevices into the strata of the older rocks; in other words,<lb/>through the already oxidized envelope of our planet, or by issu-<lb/>ing under the form of lava from conical mountains, which have<lb/>a permanent crater. If phenomena so different as these be con-<lb/>founded together, the geognosy of volcanoes is thrown back in-<lb/>to the darkness, from which numerous comparative experiments<lb/>have begun gradually to rescue it.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The question has often been asked, What is it that burns in<lb/>volcanoes? What is it that produces the heat in them by which<lb/>the earth and metals are melted and intermingled? The new<lb/>chemistry replies: What burns is the earth, the metals, and even<lb/>the alkalies, that is to say, the metaloids of these substances.<lb/>The already oxidized envelope of the earth separates the atmo-<lb/>sphere, rich in oxygen, from the unoxidised inflammable princi-<lb/>ples which reside in the interior of our planet. Observations<lb/>made in all countries, in mines, and caves, and which, in concert<lb/>with M. Arago, I have detailed in a memoir on the subject,<lb/>prove that, even at a small depth, the earth&#x2019;s heat is much su-<lb/>perior to the mean temperature of the surrounding atmosphere.<lb/>A fact so remarkable, and elicited from observations made in al-<lb/>most every part of the globe, connects itself with what we learn<lb/>
                    <pb n="239" facs="#f0018" /> from the phenomena of volcanoes. La Place has even attempted<lb/>to determine the depth at which the earth may be considered as<lb/>a melted mass. Whatever doubts may be entertained, notwith-<lb/>standing the respect due to so great a name, as to the numerical<lb/>accuracy of such a calculation, it is not the less probable, that<lb/>all volcanic phenomena arise from a single cause, which is the<lb/>communication, constant or interrupted, that exists between the<lb/>interior of our planet and the external atmosphere. Elastic va-<lb/>pours, by their pressure, raise through deep crevices the sub-<lb/>stances which are in a state of fusion, and which are oxidized.<lb/>Volcanoes are, so to speak, intermittent springs of earthy mat-<lb/>ters. The fluid mixtures of metals, alkalies and earths, which<lb/>condense into currents of lava, flow gently and slowly, when,<lb/>on being raised up, they once find an issue. It was in this man-<lb/>ner that, according to Plato&#x2019;s <hi rendition="#i">Ph&#x0153;dos,</hi> the ancients represented<lb/>all the torrents of fire as emanations of the Pyriphlegeton.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>To these considerations may I be permitted to add another of<lb/>a bolder character. It is perhaps in the internal heat of the<lb/>earth, a heat which is indicated by experiments made with the<lb/>thermometer, and the phenomena of volcanoes, that the cause of<lb/>one of the most astonishing phenomena which the knowledge of<lb/>petrifactions presents to us resides. Tropical forms of animals,<lb/>arborescent ferns, palms and bamboos, occur imbedded in the<lb/>frozen regions of the north. The primitive world every where<lb/>discloses to us a distribution of organic forms, which is in oppo-<lb/>sition to the presently existing state of climates. To solve so im-<lb/>portant a problem, recourse has been had to a great number of<lb/>hypotheses, such as the approach of a comet, the change of ob-<lb/>liquity of the ecliptic, the increase of intensity of the solar heat.<lb/>None of these hypotheses has been able to satisfy at the same<lb/>time the astronomer, the natural philosopher and the geologist.<lb/>As to my own opinion on the subject, I leave the earth&#x2019;s axis in<lb/>its position, I admit no change in the radiation of the solar disk,<lb/>a change by which a celebrated astronomer thought he could ex-<lb/>plain the good and bad harvests of our fields; but I ima-<lb/>gine that in each planet, independently of its relations to a cen-<lb/>tral body, and independently of its astronomical position, there<lb/>exist numerous causes of developement of heat, whether by the<lb/>chemical processes of oxidation, or by the precipitation and<lb/>changes of capacity of bodies, or by the augmentation of the<lb/>
                    <pb n="240" facs="#f0019" /> electro-magnetic intensity, or the communication between the<lb/>internal and external parts of the globe.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>When, in the primitive world, the deeply fissured crust of the<lb/>earth exhaled heat by these apertures, perhaps during many<lb/>centuries, palms, arborescent ferns, and the animals of warm cli-<lb/>mates, lived in vast expanses of country. According to this sys-<lb/>tem of things, which I have already indicated in my work en-<lb/>titled <hi rendition="#i">Essai Geognostique sur le Gisement des Roches dans les<lb/>deux Hemispheres,</hi> the temperature of volcanoes is the same as<lb/>that of the interior of the earth, and the same cause which now<lb/>produces such frightful ravages, would formerly have made the<lb/>richest vegetation to spring in every zone, from the newly oxi-<lb/>dised envelope of the earth, and from the deeply fissured strata<lb/>of rocks.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>If, in order to account for the distribution of the tropical<lb/>forms that occur buried in the northern regions of the globe, it<lb/>is assumed that elephants covered with long hair, now immersed<lb/>in the polar ice, were originally natives of those climates, and<lb/>that forms resembling the same principal type, such as that of<lb/>lions and lynxes, may have lived at the same time in very dif-<lb/>ferent climates, such a mode of explanation would yet be inap-<lb/>plicable to the vegetable productions. For reasons which ve-<lb/>getable physiology discloses, palms, bananas, and arborescent<lb/>monocotyledonous plants, are unable to support the cold of the<lb/>northern countries; and in the geognostical problem which we<lb/>are here examining, it appears to me difficult to separate the<lb/>plants from the animals; the same explanation ought to embrace<lb/>the two forms.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>At the end of this memoir, I have added to the facts collected<lb/>in countries the most remote from each other, some purely hypo-<lb/>thetical suppositions<note place="foot" n="*">The facts alluded to do not appear in the Appendix to the Memoir.</note>. The philosophical study of nature rises<lb/>above the wants of descriptive natural history; it does not consist<lb/>of the mere accumulation of isolated observations. May it one<lb/>day be permitted to the curious and active mind of man, to dart<lb/>from the present into the future, to interpret what cannot yet be<lb/>known with precision, and amuse itself with the geognostical<lb/>fables of antiquity, which are in our days reproduced under va-<lb/>rious forms.</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>