<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">South America – missions in the interior</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:00</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.43</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1824-South_America_Missions-1-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent&lt;i&gt;, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 1, S. 371–462.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">South America – missions in the interior</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1824</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The New Times&lt;/i&gt; 8101 (16. Juli 1824), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>SOUTH AMERICA&#x2014;MISSIONS IN THE<lb break="yes"/>INTERIOR.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/> (FROM HUMBOLDT&#x2019;S VOYAGE AUX REGIONS EQUINOXIALES DU<lb break="yes"/>NOUVEAU CONTINENT.)</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It was at five o&#x2019;clock in the morning on the 4th<lb break="yes"/>of September (says M. de Humboldt) that we<lb break="yes"/>commenced our journey to the Missions of the<lb break="yes"/>Chaymas Indians, and towards a group of high<lb break="yes"/>mountains which cross New Andalusia. We soon met<lb break="yes"/>with cabins inhabited by Mestizos, in the Ravine<lb break="yes" />of Los Frailes. In Europe we judge of the num-<lb break="no"/>ber of inhabitants from the extent of cultivation:<lb break="yes"/>under the Tropics, on the contrary, in the hottest<lb break="yes"/>and most humid parts of South America, the most<lb break="yes"/>populous provinces appear to be deserted; because<lb break="yes"/>men, for the sake of nourishment alone, will only<lb break="yes"/>cultivate a small proportion of land. Without<lb break="yes" />neighbours, almost without intercourse with men,<lb break="yes"/>each family of these Colonists forms an isolated<lb break="yes"/>people. It is said, that in the New World man<lb break="yes"/>appears not as an absolute master who changes the<lb break="yes"/>surface of the soil at his pleasure, but rather as a<lb break="yes"/>passing guest, who tranquilly enjoys the bounties<lb break="yes"/>of Nature. In fact, in the neighbourhood of the<lb break="yes" />most populous cities, the land retains the inherit-<lb break="no"/>ance of its forests, or is covered with a thick un-<lb break="no"/>derwood, which has never been touched with the<lb break="yes"/>axe. The natural productions of the earth so ex-<lb break="no"/>ceed in magnitude and number those introduced<lb break="yes"/>by cultivation, as to characterise the aspect of the<lb break="yes"/>country. It is to be presumed that this state of<lb break="yes" />things cannot be changed but in a long process of time.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The forests of the New World present a singular<lb break="yes"/>appearance. Every where the trunks of the trees are<lb break="yes"/>hidden under a species of verdant tapestry, and if<lb break="yes"/>due care were taken, in transplanting, to preserve the<lb break="yes"/>ligaments, a vast extent of ground might be covered.<lb break="yes"/>The same climbers which at present spread ram-<lb break="no"/>pantly over the soil, might be made to ascend the trees,<lb break="yes"/>passing from one to another to the height of 100 feet.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We travelled for some hours under the shade of<lb break="yes"/>these arbours, which hardly left an opening through<lb break="yes"/>which we could view the azure sky. It appeared to<lb break="yes"/>me of an indigo colour, and remarkably dark, as the<lb break="yes"/>green of the equinoctial plants is generally deep, and<lb break="yes"/>verging towards a brown.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Near San Fernando, the evaporation caused by<lb break="yes"/>the action of the sun was so great, that being<lb break="yes"/>slightly clothed, we felt ourselves as damp as if<lb break="yes"/>coming from a shower bath.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A path bordered by bamboos brought us to the<lb break="yes"/>small village of San Fernando. This was the first<lb break="yes"/>Mission we had seen in America. The houses or<lb break="yes"/>rather huts of the Chaymas Indians, which are sepa-<lb break="no"/>rated from all others, have no gardens round them.<lb break="yes"/>Every Indian family cultivates at some distance<lb break="yes" />from the village, besides his private garden, the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">conuco</hi> of the commune. It is in the latter of these<lb break="yes"/>that the adults of both sexes are accustomed to<lb break="yes" />labour one hour each morning and evening. In<lb break="yes"/>those Missions nearest the coast, the garden of the<lb break="yes"/>community is generally a sugar or indigo plantation<lb break="yes"/>under the superintendence of the Missionary, the<lb break="yes"/>produce of which can only be employed in the sup-<lb break="no"/>port of the Church and the purchase of sacerdotal<lb break="yes"/>ornaments. The great square of San Fernando is<lb break="yes" />situated in the middle of the village, inclosing the<lb break="yes"/>Church, the Missionary dwelling, and that unas-<lb break="no"/>piring edifice which is called the King&#x2019;s House. It<lb break="yes"/>is truly a Caravansary, appropriated to the shelter<lb break="yes"/>of travellers, and is infinitely precious in a country<lb break="yes"/>where even the word Inn is unknown.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These King&#x2019;s houses are to be met with in all<lb break="yes"/>the Spanish colonies, and one might believe that<lb break="yes"/>they are, in imitation of the Tambos of Peru,<lb break="yes"/>established by the laws of Manco-Capac.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Mission of San Fernando was founded at the<lb break="yes"/>end of the 17th century, at the junction of the<lb break="yes"/>small rivers of Manzanares and Lucalparez. The<lb break="yes"/>resident families have increased to about a hundred,<lb break="yes"/>and the Missionary here remarked that the custom<lb break="yes"/>of the young folks marrying at the ages of thirteen<lb break="yes"/>or fourteen had greatly contributed to the rapid<lb break="yes" />growth of the population. The government of<lb break="yes"/>these Indian Communes is, in other respects, most<lb break="yes"/>complicated; they have their governor, their<lb break="yes"/>alguazil major, their commandants of militia, all of<lb break="yes"/>whom carry their bows and arrows. The company<lb break="yes"/>of the archers have flags, and, habited in white,<lb break="yes"/>exercise the bow and arrow. These constitute the<lb break="yes" />National Guards of the country.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have already proved (says M. de Humboldt), in<lb break="yes"/>my work on Mexico, how very wrong it was to<lb break="yes"/>state, generally, the assumed fact of the destruc-<lb break="no"/>tion or diminution of the Indians in the Spanish<lb break="yes"/>Colonies. There still exists in the two Americas a<lb break="yes"/>colored population of above six million of souls; and<lb break="yes"/>although a great number of the tribes and languages<lb break="yes"/>has been extinguished or confounded, the number<lb break="yes" />of Indians has not greatly diminished since the dis-<lb break="no"/>covery by Columbus.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The religious orders have formed their establish-<lb break="no"/>ments between the territory of the Colonists and the<lb break="yes"/>Three Indians. The Missions should be considered<lb break="yes"/>as a species of intermediate States; they have en-<lb break="no"/>croached, no doubt, upon the liberty of the natives,<lb break="yes"/>but almost everywhere they have been subservient<lb break="yes"/>to the increase of population, which is incompatible<lb break="yes"/>with the wandering life of the independent Indians.<lb break="yes"/>In proportion as the religious orders approach the<lb break="yes"/>forests, and gain on the natives, the white colonists<lb break="yes"/>in their turn endeavour to invade on the opposite<lb break="yes"/>side the settlements of the Missionaries; after an<lb break="yes"/>unequal contest the Missionaries are gradually sup-<lb break="no"/>planted by the regular clergy. The whites and the<lb break="yes" />mulattoes, favored by the Corregidors, are esta-<lb break="no"/>blishing themselves in the midst of the Indians<choice>
                        <sic>-</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">.</corr>
                    </choice> The<lb break="yes"/>residences of the Missionaries become Spanish vil-<lb break="no"/>lages, and the natives lose even the recollection of<lb break="yes"/>their national idiom. Such has been the progress<lb break="yes" />of civilisation from the coasts to the interior.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 