<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="406" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i"><placeName>Sulphur Mountain of Ticsan</placeName>.</hi></head> <p>&#x2014;&#x201C;In following the <placeName>Cordillera of<lb/>the Andes</placeName> towards the south,&#x201D; says M. Humboldt, &#x201C;what was my<lb/>surprise, when on the other side of the equator, I found that the<lb/>celebrated <hi rendition="#i"><placeName>sulphur mountain of Ticsan</placeName></hi> (lat. 2° 10&#x2032; S.) between<lb/><placeName>Quito</placeName> and <placeName>Cuen&#x00E7;a</placeName>, was not composed either of trachyte or lime-<lb/>stone, or gypsum, but of mica slate. This mountain of sulphur,<lb/>called <hi rendition="#i"><placeName>Quello</placeName></hi> by the Indians, is, according to my barometric mea-<lb/>surement, 1250 toises above the sea. It is composed entirely of<lb/>primitive mica slate, which is not even anthracitic as are the<lb/>transition varieties of this rock. In the ravines between <placeName>Ticsan</placeName> and<lb/><placeName>Alausi</placeName>, it is seen reposing on gneiss. The sulphur is contained in a<lb/>bed of quartz more than 1200 feet thick, regularly directed N. 18°<lb/>E., and inclined like the mica slate 70° or 80° to the N.W. The<lb/>bed of quartz is worked open to-day. The side of <hi rendition="#i"><placeName>Cerro Quello</placeName></hi>,<lb/>in which the works were commenced ages ago, is opposed to the<lb/>S.S.E., and the bed appears to prolong itself towards the N.N.W.<lb/>At the same time, sulphur has not been found at the surface of the<lb/>earth in that direction, at 2000 toises from <placeName>Ticsan</placeName>. The whole is<lb/>covered by a thick vegetation.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>Towards the end of the eighteenth century, masses of sulphur<lb/>were found from two to three feet in diameter; at present, strata<lb/>much poorer are worked, the sulphur being disseminated through<lb/>them in lumps from three to four inches in thickness. It is ob-<lb/>served, that the sulphur increases in quantity with the depth of the<lb/><pb n="407" facs="#f0002" />
    works, but these are arranged so badly, that the lower strata are<lb/>almost inaccessible. As the quartz contains no fissures or cavities,<lb/>no specimens of crystallized sulphur have been found.</p><lb/><p>The sulphur does not form, as might perhaps have been sup-<lb/>posed, a mass or collection of veins, but is disseminated in small<lb/>masses, having no continuity with each other, in the quartz which<lb/>traverses the mica slate parallel to its strata. The apertures, by<lb/>which perhaps they have been united, are no longer visible; but all<lb/>the quartz has suffered a singular change. It is dull, frequently<lb/>friable, and breaks in some places with the slightest blow, which<lb/>indicates splits or cracks, which are inappreciable to the sight.<lb/>The temperature of the rock does not differ from that of the atmo-<lb/>sphere. The inhabitants are in the habit of attributing the earth-<lb/>quakes to which their country has been exposed, to the concavities<lb/>which they suppose to exist beneath the sulphur mountain. In the<lb/>great catastrophe of the 4th of February 1797, which destroyed so<lb/>many thousand Indians in the <placeName>province of Quito</placeName>, the three places<lb/>where there is most sulphur, the <placeName>Cerro Quello</placeName>, the <placeName>Azufral de Cue-<lb/>saca</placeName> near the town of <placeName>Sbarra</placeName>, and the <placeName>Machay of St. Simon</placeName>, near the<lb/>volcano of <placeName><choice><sic>Antifana</sic><corr type="editorial">Antisana</corr></choice></placeName> were only slightly agitated; but at a previous<lb/>period, an explosion resembling that of a mine occurred in the bed<lb/>of quartz itself, which contains the sulphur near <placeName>Ticsan</placeName>.&#x2014;<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Ann. de<lb/>Chim.</hi> xxvii. 131</bibl>.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>