<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="460" facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Analysis of the Water of the Rio Vinagre, in<lb/>the Andes of Popayan,</hi> by M. Mariano de Rivero; <hi rendition="#i">with<lb/>geognostic and Physical Illustrations of some Phenomena<lb/>which are exhibited by Sulphur, Sulphuretted Hydrogen,<lb/>and Water, in Volcanoes. By</hi> M. A. <hi rendition="#k">de Humboldt.</hi>
                    <lb/>[<hi rendition="#i">Phil. Mag.</hi>]<lb/>[Extract of a Letter, dated the <date>8th October 1823.]</date>
                </head>
                <lb/>
                <p>&#x201C;IN compliance with the desire of M. de Humboldt, I pro-<lb/>cured some of the water of Rio Vinagre. It was sent to me<lb/>by M. Torrés, who takes an interest in all that can contribute<lb/>to scientific researches. This water has yielded per litre: sul-<lb/>phuric acid, 1.080; muriatic acid, 0.184; alumine, 0.240;<lb/>lime, 0.160; and some indications of iron.<note place="foot" n="*">It cannot be doubted that the indications are by grammes and fractions<lb/>of grammes; a litre of the water of the Rio Vinagre includes 1.080 grammes<lb/>of sulphuric acid, and 0.184 grammes of muriatic acid. This proportion of<lb/>sulphuric acid is nevertheless very sensible to the taste, and is manifest by<lb/>an abundant precipitate with the salts of barytes.<lb/>[The litre being 2.113 pints, the contents of the water in English grains<lb/>will be as follows: sulphuric acid 16.68; muriatic acid 2.84; alumine 3.7;<lb/>lime 2.47. <hi rendition="#i">Edit.</hi>]</note> The presence<lb/>of muriatic acid confirms the observations made on the va-<lb/>pours and the stony productions of Vesuvius and of several<lb/>other volcanoes.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb/>
                <p>I had made known, at the time of my return from America,<lb/>the presence of the sulphuric and muriatic acids in the water<lb/>of the Rio Vinagre, which the aborigines call Pusambio. (See<lb/>Views of the Cordilleras, and Monuments of the People of<lb/>America, vol. <hi rendition="#k">ii.</hi> p. 166; Barometric Levelling of the Andes,<lb/>No. 126; Caldas, Samanario del Nuevo Reyno de Granada,<lb/>t. i. p. 265); but not being furnished with the salts of barytes.<lb/>I had engaged MM. Rivero and Boussingault, when they<lb/>departed from Bogota, to verify these facts. The analysis,<lb/>which we owe to one of these expert chemists, is the first<lb/>which has been attempted on the water of the Rio Vinagre.<lb/>I shall give some extracts from the journal of my travels, in<lb/>great part still unpublished, explanatory of the local circum-<lb/>stances.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The town of Popayan is situated in the beautiful valley of the<lb/>Rio Cauca, on the Bogota road to Quito, at the foot of the<lb/>two great volcanoes of Puracé and Sotarà.</p>
                <lb/>
                <pb n="461" facs="#f0002" />
                <p>These volcanoes, almost extinct, and exhibiting only the<lb/>phenomena of solfataras, form part of the central chain of the<lb/>Andes of New Granada. At 1° 55&#x2032; and 2° 20&#x2032; of north lati-<lb/>tude, the group of mountains which incloses the sources of the<lb/>Magdalena is divided into three branches, of which the east-<lb/>ern is continued towards Timana and the Nevados of Chita<lb/>and of Merida; the intermediate and central one towards the<lb/>Paramos of Guanacas and of Quimdiú; the western towards<lb/>the platiniferous district of the Choco and the isthmus of<lb/>Panama. In ascending from the town of Popayan to the sum-<lb/>mit of the volcano of Puracé, M. Bonpland and I found at<lb/>the height of 8672 feet a little plain (Llane del Corazon), in-<lb/>habited by poor Indian husbandmen. This plain is separated<lb/>from the rest of the acclivity, with which it would otherwise<lb/>be continuous, by two ravines extremely deep: it is at the<lb/>edge of these precipices that the village of Puracé is built.<lb/>Springs rise every where from the trachytic rock; each gar-<lb/>den is surrounded with a quickset hedge of narrow-leaved<lb/>euphorbium (<hi rendition="#i">lechero</hi>) of the most delicate green. This<lb/>beautiful verdure contrasts in a striking manner with the back-<lb/>ground of black and arid mountains, which surround the vol-<lb/>cano, and which are rent by the effects of the earthquakes.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The site of the village is celebrated in the country on ac-<lb/>count of three beautiful cascades [<hi rendition="#i">choreras</hi>] of the river of<lb/>Pusambio, whose water is acid, and which the people, who<lb/>know no other acid than vinegar, call <hi rendition="#i">Rio Vinagre,</hi> some-<lb/>times <hi rendition="#i">Gran Vinagre.</hi> This river takes its rise at the height<lb/>of nearly 10,871 feet, in a very inaccessible spot. Although<lb/>the temperature of the water be little different in the lower<lb/>cascades from that of the surrounding atmosphere, it is no less<lb/>certain that the sources of the Pusambio or Venagre are very<lb/>hot. This fact was attested to me by the natives and by the<lb/>missionary of the village of Puracé. In going to the summit<lb/>of the volcano I saw a column of smoke rise at the place where<lb/>the acid waters make their appearance. I have drawn the<lb/>second of the falls of the Vinagre (plate xxx of the Views of<lb/>the Cordilleras): the water which opens itself a passage across<lb/>a cavern, is precipitated more than 383 feet in depth. The<lb/>fall has a very picturesque effect; but the inhabitants of Popa-<lb/>yan would be better pleased if the river, instead of throwing<lb/>itself into the Rio Cauca, became engulfed in some other<lb/>crevice; for such is the delicacy of constitution of animals<lb/>which breath by gills, and which absorb the oxygen dissolved<lb/>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">
                        <hi rendition="#k">vol. ii. no.</hi> 5. 59</fw>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="462" facs="#f0003" /> in the water, that the Cauca, during a course of four leagues,<lb/>is destitute of fish, on account of the mixture of its waters with<lb/>those of the Rio Vinagre,<note place="foot" n="*">M. Caldas has even attributed to this mixture, doubtless with little rea-<lb/>son, the absence of goitres in the valley of Rio Cauca.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Semanario,</hi> t. l. p.<lb/>265. See my Memoir on the Goitres in the Cordilleras. (<hi rendition="#i">Magendie, Jour.<lb/>de Physiol.</hi> t. iv, p. 109)</note> which are charged both with oxide<lb/>of iron and with sulphuric and muriatic acid. After staying a<lb/>considerable time on the craggy wall of rock which borders<lb/>the cascade, a pricking sensation is felt in the eyes from the<lb/>minute spray in the atmosphere. Fish re-appear in the Rio<lb/>Cauca at the point where it becomes enlarged by the influx of<lb/>the Pindamon and of the Placé.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Journal de physique,</hi> t. lxii, p. 61.</note>
                </p>
                <lb/>
                <p>A little to the north of the sources of the Pusambio rise two<lb/>other rivulets charged in like manner with free sulphuric acid,<lb/>which the people call the Little Vinegars (<hi rendition="#i">los dos Vinagres<lb/>chicos</hi>): they throw themselves into the Rio de San Francis-<lb/>co, which is itself but a tributary of the Gran Vinagre. Dur-<lb/>ing my stay at Popayan it was an opinion generally received<lb/>that all these acid waters contained some iron dissolved by a<lb/>great quantity of carbonic acid. When it was merely remem-<lb/>bered that the sources of the Vinagre are very hot, this opin-<lb/>ion ought to have been abandoned. I boiled some water taken<lb/>from the cascade; and I found, after the ebullition, the same<lb/>acid taste and the precipitates as in the unboiled water. At<lb/>this period I had very few re-agents left.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The nitrate of silver<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">The conjoint presence of the sulphuric and muriatic acids has also been<lb/>observed by M. Vauquelin in the water which M. Leschenault had taken from<lb/>the crater-lake of Mount Idienne in Java (<hi rendition="#i">Journal de Physique,</hi> t. lxv. p. 406.)<lb/>See Phil. Mag. vol. xlii. pp. 126, 182.</note> gave a white and milky precipitate,<lb/>indicating the presence of muriates. The presence of iron<lb/>was shown by the prussiate of lime, that of lime by the oxalate<lb/>of potash. When the water was weighed with great care in<lb/>the office of the mint of Popayan, the weight of an equal<lb/>quantity of the water of the Vinagre was found to be to that of<lb/>distilled water as 2735&#x00BD; gr. to 2731 gr.; that is to say that<lb/>the specific gravity of the water of the cascade was 1.00 5.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The waters which I describe, and of which M. Rivero has<lb/>given the first analysis, must not be confounded with those of<lb/>the two subterraneous lakes which we have found near the sum-<lb/>mit of the volcano; one is 14,356 feet high, the other, above<lb/>the snows, 15.475 feet. This volcano of Puracé is a dome<lb/>
                    <pb n="463" facs="#f0004" /> of semivitreous trachyte of a bluish grey, and having a con-<lb/>choidal fracture. It does not present a great crater at its<lb/>summit, but several little mouths. It differs very much from<lb/>the neighbouring volcano, the Sotarà, which is of a conical<lb/>form, and which has thrown out an immense quantity of obsi-<lb/>dians. These masses, covering the plains of Julumito, are<lb/>balls or <hi rendition="#i">tears</hi> of obsidian, the surface of which is often tuber-<lb/>cular. They present, what I have seen no where else in the<lb/>two hemispheres, all the shades of colour, from deep black to<lb/>that of an artificial glass entirely colourless. It may appear<lb/>surprising to see that this deprivation of colour has not been<lb/>accompanied by any inflation or porosity. The obsidians of<lb/>Sotarà are mixed with fragments of enamel which resemble<lb/>the porcelain of Réaumur, and adhering to which I have<lb/>found masses of felspar which have resisted fusion.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Here, as in the Andes of Quito, as at Mexico, and at the<lb/>Canary Islands, the system of basaltic rocks lies far from the<lb/>trachytes which form the volcano of Puracé and of Sotarà.<lb/>The basalts of the Tetilla of Julumito belong only to the left<lb/>bank of the Cauca. They rise from transition porphyries free<lb/>from augite, containing some hornblende, a very little quartz<lb/>in small crystals embedded in the mass, and a felspar which<lb/>passes from the common to the vitreous variety. This por-<lb/>phyry is covered, near to Los Serillos, with a blackish-grey<lb/>limestone, traversed by veins of carbonate of lime, and so<lb/>much overcharged with carbon that in some parts it stains the<lb/>fingers like an aluminous schist, or like the lydian<note place="foot" n="*">M. Vauquelin has recently proved by a direct analysis the presence of<lb/>carboa in the purest lydian stones. I had found, in a series of experiments<lb/>made on the galvanic exciters in 1798, that the lydian stones of the transition<lb/>schists of Steeben produced jointly with zinc the same effect as graphite or<lb/>carburet of iron. I have since made some trials to prove chemically the<lb/>presence of carbon in several varieties of lydian stone. See my Experi-<lb/>ments on the Nervous and Muscular Fibre (in German), t. ii. p. 163.</note> stone of<lb/>Steeben in the Fichtelgebirge.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The trachytic dome of Puracé which gives birth to the<lb/>little river of sulphuric acid, rises out of a porphyritic syenite<lb/>(with common felspar), which in its turn is superimposed on<lb/>transition granite abounding in mica. This observation,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">See an account of the whole of these phenomena of the volcanoes of<lb/>Popayan in my <hi rendition="#i">Essai sur le Gisement des Roches,</hi> 1823, pp. 129, 139, 340.</note> very<lb/>important for the position of volcanic rocks, may be made near<lb/>to Santa Barbara in ascending from Popayan to the village of<lb/>
                    <pb n="464" facs="#f0005" /> Puracé. The volcano, like the most part of the great volcanoes<lb/>of the Andes, presents layers or mantles of melted stony matter,<lb/>not real currents of lava. Some fragments of granular limestone,<lb/>probably magnesian, which I found at more than 12,790 feet<lb/>high, seem to have been thrown up through crevices which<lb/>have since become closed. They are like those of the Fosso<lb/>Grande of Vesuvius, which owe their granular texture to vol-<lb/>canic fire. It is not possible to go on horse back further than<lb/>the cascades of the Rio Vinagre. From thence we were<lb/>eight hours in mounting on foot to the summit of the volcano<lb/>and in descending from it. The weather was dreadful; snow<lb/>and hail fell. I had a great deal of difficulty in lighting the tinder<lb/>the point of the conductor of Volta&#x2019;s electrometer; the balls<lb/>of elder pith separated from 5 to 6 lines, and the electricity<lb/>passed often from positive to negative without there being any<lb/>other symptom of storm: for thunder and lightning are (ac-<lb/>cording to my experience) generally very rare when we are<lb/>above 12,800 or 14,000 feet high. The hail was white;<note place="foot" n="*">I have already remarked elsewhere in the <hi rendition="#i">Ann. de Chimie,</hi> that at Paramo<lb/>de Guanacas, where the road from Bogota to Popayan passes to the height<lb/>of 14,700 feet, there has been seen fall, no snow, but red hail. Did it in-<lb/>close those same germs of vegetable organization which have been discover-<lb/>ed above the polar circle?</note> the<lb/>hailstones, from five to seven lines in diameter, composed of<lb/>layers varying in translucency. They were not only much<lb/>flattened towards the poles, but so much increased in their<lb/>equatorial diameter, that rings of ice separated themselves on<lb/>the least shock. I had already twice observed and described<lb/>this phenomenon, in the mountains of Bareuth, and near Cra-<lb/>cow, during a journey in Poland. Can it be admitted that<lb/>the successive layers which are added to the central nucleus<lb/>are in a state of fluidity so great that the rotary motion can<lb/>cause the flattening of the spheroids?</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>When the barometer indicated that we were come very<lb/>near the limit of perpetual snow, we found the masses of sul-<lb/>phur disseminated in imperfectly columnar trachytic rocks<lb/>augmented. This phenomenon struck me the more, as I<lb/>knew how rare sulphur is on the sides of inflamed volcanoes:<lb/>a column of yellowish smoke and a frightful noise informed<lb/>us of the neighbourhood of one of the mouths <hi rendition="#i">(bocas)</hi> of the<lb/>volcano. We had some trouble to approach its edge; the<lb/>declivity of the mountain being very steep, and the crevices<lb/>only covered by a crust of sulphur, of whose thickness we<lb/>
                    <pb n="465" facs="#f0006" /> were ignorant. We believed we might rate the extent of this<lb/>crust, which is often interrupted by rocks, at more than 12,000<lb/>square feet. These little ridges of trachytic rocks act strongly<lb/>on the magnet. I tried to keep at as much distance from<lb/>them as possible to determine the inclination of the needle.<lb/>It was at the town of Popayan (height 5,825 English feet)<lb/>23°.05, centesimal division; at the village of Puracé (height<lb/>8671 feet) 21°.81; near the summit of the volcano of Puracé<lb/>(height 14,542 feet) 20°.85. The intensity of the magnetic<lb/>force varied very little at Popayan and at the village of Puracé;<lb/>and the diminution of the inclination is certainly not the effect<lb/>of the height, as is proved by so many other observations which<lb/>I have made on the summit of the Andes, but the effect of<lb/>local attractions depending on certain centres of action in the<lb/>trachytes. The mouth of the volcano of Puracé is a perpen-<lb/>dicular cleft, the visible opening of which is only 6 feet long<lb/>and 3 broad. It is covered in form of a vault by a layer of<lb/>very pure sulphur, which is 18 inches thick, and which the<lb/>force of the elastic vapours has split on the north side. At<lb/>the distance of 12 feet from the mouth we felt an agreeable<lb/>heat. The centigrade thermometer, which had kept till then<lb/>at 6°.2 (43° F.) (a cold not at all considerable in a time of<lb/>hail, and at a height of 14,356 feet), rose to 15° (61° F).<lb/>Placed in such a manner as not to be incommoded by the<lb/>vapours, we had the pleasure of drying our clothes. The<lb/>frightful noise which is heard near this opening has almost<lb/>always the same intensity: it can only be compared to that<lb/>which would be caused by several steam-engines together,<lb/>were the dense steam suffered to escape from all at the same<lb/>moment. We threw great stones into the crevice, and we<lb/>discovered on this occasion that the opening communicated<lb/>with a basin full of boiling water. The vapours which escape<lb/>with so much violence are of the sulphurous acid, which is<lb/>indicated by their suffocating smell. We shall soon see that<lb/>the water of the subterraneous lake is charged with sulphu-<lb/>retted hydrogen; but the odour of this gas is not smelt at the<lb/>summit of the volcano, because it is disguised by the much<lb/>stronger smell of the sulphurous acid vapours. I had not any<lb/>means of determining the temperature of these vapours, which<lb/>seem to undergo a prodigiously strong pressure in the interior<lb/>of the volcano. The Indians pretend that the opening has<lb/>several compartments which are not all filled with water, and<lb/>that the noise which is heard at times in the interior of the<lb/>
                    <pb n="466" facs="#f0007" /> crevice is the forerunner of flames. I introduced by means<lb/>of a long pole, some papers coloured with the tincture of vio-<lb/>lets, under the vault, where I could be sure of not touching<lb/>the surface of the water. Drawing back the pole I found the<lb/>papers strongly reddened, but not at all inflamed, as was easy<lb/>to be foreseen.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>We succeeded after several vain attempts in obtaining some<lb/>water from the crevice: this was by tying a <hi rendition="#i">tutuma</hi> (the fruit<lb/>of the Cresentia Cujete) to a stick 8 feet long. The water<lb/>was directly poured into a bottle and hermetically stopped.<lb/>We examined it on our return to the village of Puracé; it ex-<lb/>haled a strong smell of sulphuretted hydrogen; it had no acid<lb/>taste, but some weak precipitates caused by the nitrate of sil-<lb/>ver showed the presence of muriatic acid. The crust of sul-<lb/>phur which forms above the mouth arises without doubt from<lb/>the contact of vapours of sulphurous acid with the sulphuretted<lb/>hydrogen which the subterraneous lake disengages. Even the<lb/>water of this lake is covered with a coat of sulphur which dis-<lb/>appeared in the places where we threw the stones. It re-<lb/>sults from these observations, that only the presence of the<lb/>muriatic acid, or of combinations of this acid with salifiable<lb/>bases, indicates a feeble analogy between the waters of Rio<lb/>Vinagre and those of the lakes. The first, which spring much<lb/>lower, at the declivity of the volcano of Puracé, are charged<lb/>with free sulphuric acid; the others, which are found at the<lb/>summit of the volcano, contain sulphuretted hydrogen. As the<lb/>upper mouths are found at very different heights above the<lb/>level of the sea, it may be supposed that their subterraneous<lb/>waters are owing to the melting of the snows, and that they do<lb/>not communicate. The Rio Vinagre receives its acid in the<lb/>interior of a volcano which abounds in sulphur, and the tem-<lb/>perature of which appears extremely elevated, although for<lb/>centuries no luminous phenomenon has been perceived at its<lb/>summit.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">[<hi rendition="#i">To be continued.</hi>]</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
            <pb n="513" facs="#f0008" />
            <div n="1">
                <head>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Analysis of the Water of the Rio Vinagre, in the<lb/>Andes of Popayan. By</hi> M. <hi rendition="#k">Mariano de Rivero.</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">With<lb/>Geognostic and Physical Illustrations of some Phenomena which<lb/>are exhibited by Sulphur, Sulphuretted Hydrogen, in Water,<lb/>in Volcanos. By</hi> M. A. <hi rendition="#k">de Humboldt.</hi> [<hi rendition="#i">Phil. Mag.</hi>]<lb/>(Concluded from p. 466.)</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> good curate of the village of Puracé thought to render<lb/>a great service to his parishioners, as well as to the inhabi-<lb/>tants of the town of Popayan, in causing, as he said, the <hi rendition="#i">chim-<lb/>neys of the volcano</hi> to be cleaned now and then. He ordered<lb/>the Indians to take away the crust of sulphur which rises in<lb/>form of a dome above the crevice. This crust has acquired<lb/>sometimes, as they affirm, a thickness of as much as four feet<lb/>in less than two years. It lessens without doubt the opening<lb/>by which the vapours of sulphurous acid escape; but it may<lb/>be conceived that the elastic force of these vapours is such,<lb/>that, if the opening were entirely stopped up for some mo-<lb/>ments, it would sooner break the new arch than produce<lb/>commotions by acting against the rocky sides of the volcano.<lb/>For several years the lakes, which represent in miniature the<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">crater-lakes</hi> of our extinguished volcanos, seem each to pre-<lb/>serve the same level of their line of water; which proves that<lb/>the evaporation is equal to the infiltration of the waters of<lb/>snow and rain: but this equilibrium has not always been<lb/>equally steady. About the year 1790 the <hi rendition="#i">Boca grande</hi> caus-<lb/>ed partial inundations. I dwell on this phenomenon, because<lb/>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">
                        <hi rendition="#k">vol. ii. no.</hi> 6. 65</fw>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="514" facs="#f0009" /> it seems to throw some light on a problem of the geology of<lb/>volcanos, which has not been sufficiently examined: I mean<lb/>the ejections of water and mud. At Vesuvius these ejections<lb/>are only apparent, and come neither from the interior of the<lb/>crater, nor from the lateral crevices. An immense electric<lb/>tension manifests itself in the atmosphere which surrounds the<lb/>summit of the volcano at the time of great eruptions.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Flashes of lightning cleave the air; the aqueous vapours<lb/>thrown out by the crater are cooled; thick clouds envelop<lb/>the summit during the continuance of this storm, confined to<lb/>a little space; the water descends in torrents, and is mixed<lb/>with the tufaceous substances which it drags with it.<note place="foot" n="*">M. de la Condamine (<hi rendition="#i">Mémoires de l&#x2019;Académie</hi> 1754, p. 18) had already<lb/>expressed very precise ideas on the cause of these phenomena, which are<lb/>found equally well explained in the <hi rendition="#i">Storia dell&#x2019; incendio del</hi> 1737, published<lb/>by the Academy of Naples. I saw in my last journey to Naples, (December<lb/>1822) the ravages caused by the torrents of water from the side of Ottajano,<lb/>at the foot of Vesuvius. They had transported into the plain, not only mud,<lb/>but masses of lava 48 feet in circumference and 25 feet high. See the ex-<lb/>cellent description of these phenomena by M M. Monticelli and Covelli.<lb/>(<hi rendition="#i">Storia del Vesuvio degli anni</hi> 1821-23, p. 91-98) Phil. Mag. vol. lxiii. p. 46.<lb/>By the mixture of the rain and the volcanic cinders, there is formed in the<lb/>air (l. c. p. 94) a kind of pisolites with concentric layers, which I also found<lb/>on the plain of Hambato, among the ancient ejections of the Carguairazo.<lb/>The inhabitants of the province of Quito call these pisolites <hi rendition="#i">earth hailstones.</hi>
                    </note> These<lb/>effects, purely meteorological, have given rise to the tradi-<lb/>tions about boiling waters that issued from the crater of Ve-<lb/>suvius in 1631; fabulous traditions, which are perpetuated<lb/>by an inscription at Portici.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In the volcanos of the Andes, which exceed the limit of<lb/>perpetual snow, the causes of inundations are very different<lb/>from those which we have just indicated. As the eruptions<lb/>of these colossal summits take place only after long intervals,<lb/>(every thirty or forty years, or still more rarely) banks of<lb/>snow of an enormous thickness accumulate on the sides of<lb/>the mountains. The snows do not melt at the time of the ex-<lb/>plosion only, but sometimes several days before. Thus in<lb/>February 1803, during my stay at Guayaquil, the inhabitants<lb/>of the province of Quito were frightened at the appearance of<lb/>the cone of Cotopaxi, which lost a great part of its snows in<lb/>a single night, and showed plainly the black colour of its<lb/>burnt rocks. Whatever idea may be formed of the power of<lb/>the volcanic forces, and of the intensity of the subterraneous<lb/>fires in the Andes, it cannot be admitted that the thick sides<lb/>of a cone could be uniformly warmed, and transmit the heat<lb/>with such rapidity (by the conductibility of their mass) to<lb/>
                    <pb n="515" facs="#f0010" /> the outside. The sudden melting of the snows, when, in the<lb/>Cordilleras, it precedes the eruptions, is probably owing only<lb/>to an infinity of little <hi rendition="#i">fumaroles</hi>, which disengage hot vapours<lb/>through the fissured rock of the cone. These vapours, ac-<lb/>cording to what I have had opportunity of observing in the<lb/>craters of Vesuvius, the Peak of Teneriffe, and the volcano<lb/>of Jorullo in Mexico, are more frequently pure water, which<lb/>does not act at all on the most sensible re-agents; at other<lb/>times they contain muriatic acid. It is remarkable that the<lb/>same crevice gives at very near epochs, distilled (pure) wa-<lb/>ter and very acid waters. The artificial spring which M.<lb/>Gimbernat has had the ingenious idea of forming at the sum-<lb/>mit of Vesuvius, by the condensation of the vapours in a glass<lb/>tube, has sometimes shown these variations; they prove either<lb/>the change of chemical action in the interior of the volcano,<lb/>or the accidental opening of some new communications. In<lb/>the Andes of Quito, as in Iceland, and in the eruptions of Et-<lb/>na of March 23, 1536, and March 6, 1755, the sudden melt-<lb/>ing of the banks of snow produced great devastations.<note place="foot" n="*">Ferrara, Campi Flegrei, 1810, p. 165.&#x2014;Idem, Descriz. dell&#x2019; Etna, 1818,<lb/>p. 89, 116&#x2014;120.</note>
                </p>
                <lb/>
                <p>At other times, by slow infiltrations, the snow waters are<lb/>accumulated in the lateral cavities of the volcano; shocks of<lb/>violent earthquakes, which do not always coincide with the<lb/>epoch of the fiery eruptions, open these cavities; and waters<lb/>long kept in, which support little fish of the genus <hi rendition="#i">Pimelodes</hi>,
                    <lb/>carry with them pulverized trachytes, pumice-stones, tufas,<lb/>and other incoherent matters. These liquid ejections spread<lb/>sterility over the plains for centuries. Muddy clays (<hi rendition="#i">Coda-<lb/>zales</hi>) covered a space of more than four square leagues, when,<lb/>in the night of the 19th of June 1698, the Peak of Carguai-<lb/>razo, the actual height of which exceeds 15,700 feet, sunk<lb/>down with a noise. The lakes of sulphureous water that we<lb/>found at the summit of Puracé, explain what the inhabitants<lb/>of Quito report of the fetid smell of the waters which descend<lb/>sometimes from the sides of the volcanos during great erup-<lb/>tions. Struck with the novelty of these ph&#x0153;nomena, which<lb/>we only mention here, the Spanish <hi rendition="#i">Conquistadores</hi> have, since<lb/>the sixteenth century, distinguished two sorts of volcanos,&#x2014;<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">fire volcanos</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i">water volcanos</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">volcanes de fuego y de<lb/>agua<choice><sic>.</sic><corr type="editorial">).</corr></choice></hi> This last denomination, which one might say was in-<lb/>vented to bring near to each other the <hi rendition="#i">volcanists</hi> and the nep-<lb/>tunists, and to put an end to the famous schism of dog-matical<lb/>
                    <pb n="516" facs="#f0011" /> geology, has been applied especially to the mountains of Gua-<lb/>tin ala and of the Archipelago of the Philippines. The <hi rendition="#i">Vol-<lb/>can de agua</hi>, placed between the volcano of Guatamala,<note place="foot" n="*">Juarros, <hi rendition="#i">Compendio de la Historia de Gautemala,</hi> 1809, t. i. p. 72; t. ii.<lb/>p. 351. Remesal. <hi rendition="#i">Hist. de la Provincia de San Vincente,</hi> lib. iv. cap. 6.&#x2014;<lb/>Also in the great eruption of the volcano of the province of Sinano in Japan<lb/>(July 27, 1783, boiling waters were mixed with the <hi rendition="#i">rapilli. Mémoire sur la<lb/>Dynastie regnante des Djogouns,</hi> 1820, p 182.</note> and<lb/>that of Pocaya, ruined, by torrents of water, and stones which<lb/>it sent forth the 11th of September 1541, the town of Almo-<lb/>longa, which is the ancient capital of the country. This<lb/>mountain does not attain the limit of perpetual snow, but it<lb/>remains covered with snow several months of the year.<lb/>When we call to mind the confusion of the accounts that are<lb/>found in our own days in the public papers of Europe, every<lb/>time that Etna or Vesuvius are in action, we cannot complain<lb/>of the uncertainty in which the chroniclers of Spanish Ameri-<lb/>ca and the <hi rendition="#i">Conquistadores</hi> of the sixteenth century, leave us<lb/>respecting the ph&#x0153;nomena of <hi rendition="#i">volcanic inundations</hi>, so worthy<lb/>of engaging the attention of natural philosophers. During<lb/>the eruption of Etna in 1792, there opened on the declivity<lb/>of the volcano, three miles from the crater, a gulf.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Ferrara, Descr. dell&#x2019; Etna,</hi> p. 132. As this phenomenon seems to have<lb/>some relation to that of the <hi rendition="#i">Maya de Pelileo,</hi> which contains the carburets of<lb/>hydrogen, and which I made known at my return from America, I obtained<lb/>very lately an explanatory manuscript note from the learned Sicilian geolo-<lb/>gist, M. Ferrara, on the muddy eruption of Etna, observed March 25, 1792.</note> from which<lb/>issued for several weeks water mixed with ashes, scori&#x00E6;, and<lb/>clays. These liquid ejections, which must not be confound-<lb/>ed with the ph&#x0153;nomenon of the <hi rendition="#i">Salses.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">There is only the muddy torrent (<hi rendition="#i">fiume di fango</hi>) of Santa-Maria-Nasce-<lb/>mi (March 18, 1790) in the Val di Noto, which seems to me to belong to the<lb/>actions of the Salses.</note> or air volcanos, were<lb/>very thick. It is easily conceivable that in the equinoctial<lb/>zone, even very low mountains may, by a particular disposi-<lb/>tion of their subterraneous cavities, and by the excessive<lb/>abundance of the tropical rains, be subject to cause frightful<lb/>inundations each time that they undergo shocks of earth-<lb/>quakes. Furthermore, the ph&#x0153;nomena which we have been<lb/>describing are repeated from time to time far from the volca-<lb/>nos, in secondary mountains, in the centre of Europe. Sad<lb/>examples have proved in our days that in the Alps of Swit-<lb/>zerland, where no shocks of earthquakes are felt, a simple<lb/>hydrostatic pressure lifts up and breaks with violence banks<lb/>of rocks, throwing them to a great distance, as if they were<lb/>projected by elastic forces.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The trachytes of Puracé contain sulphur like those of Mont-<lb/>
                    <pb n="517" facs="#f0012" /> Dore in Auvergne, of Budoshegy in Transylvania, of the Isle<lb/>of Montserrat in the Little Antilles, and of the Antisana in<lb/>the Andes of Quito. It is still formed daily in the clefts<lb/>around the gulfs of Puracé, either by a very slow sublima-<lb/>tion, or by the contact of the sulphurous acid vapours with<lb/>the sulphuretted hydrogen of the lake. The volcano labours<lb/>in its interior like the <hi rendition="#i">solfataras</hi>; but it presents nothing in its<lb/>form that resembles the places which are designated by that<lb/>name, and which I have visited; for example, the <hi rendition="#i">solfataras</hi> of<lb/>Puzzuoli, the Peak of Teneriffe, and the volcano of Jo-<lb/>rullo in Mexico. These last three are craters which have<lb/>vomited lava; they show that their first state was very<lb/>different to that in which we see them at present. With very<lb/>elevated temperatures, the chemical products of a volcano are<lb/>not the same as with a very low temperature. If the appel-<lb/>lation solfatara be given indefinitely to every place where<lb/>sulphur is formed or deposited, this denomination may also<lb/>be applied to a district which I shall describe here, and which<lb/>contrasts singularly with the trachytes of volcanos. In cross-<lb/>ing the Cordilleras of the Andes of Quindiu, between the ba-<lb/>sins of the Cauca and of the Magdalena (lat. 4° 50&#x2032;&#x2014;4° 45&#x2032;)<lb/>I saw an immense formation of gneiss and of micaceous schist<lb/>resting immediately on an ancient granite. The layers of<lb/>micaceous schist which alternate with strata of gneiss are free<lb/>from garnets, whilst the gneiss contains many. But in these<lb/>same primitive micaceous schists, a little to the west of the<lb/>station of the Moral, at the height of 6800 feet above the level<lb/>of the sea, in the <hi rendition="#i">Quebrada del Azufral</hi>, some <hi rendition="#i">decayed veins</hi>
                    <lb/>extremely full of crevices abound in sulphur,<note place="foot" n="*">See my Barometric and Geognstic Levelling of the Cordilleras, No. 102.</note> and exhale a<lb/>sulphureous vapour, the temperature of which rose to 47° 8&#x2032;<lb/>centessimal (118° F.), when the surrounding air was at 20° 2&#x2032;<lb/>(63° F.) Here then is repeated on a small scale, in the clifts<lb/>of a primitive rock, the ph&#x0153;nomena of the trachytic <hi rendition="#i">solfatara</hi>
                    <lb/>of Budoshegy in Transylvania, which has been recently ex-<lb/>amined by M. Bouè. The micaceous schist of Quindiu, which<lb/>surrounds the <hi rendition="#i">open veins</hi>, is decomposed, and the sulphur is<lb/>formed in masses considerable enough to become the object<lb/>of a sulphur-work which supports a family settled in the ra-<lb/>vine of the Azufral. The rock contains some decomposed<lb/>pyrites; but I much doubt whether these pyrites perform the<lb/>important part in nature which has been so long ascribed to<lb/>them in geological treatises. In the midst of the granitic<lb/>rocks of Quindiu rise the trachytes of the volcano of Tolima.<lb/>
                    <pb n="518" facs="#f0013" /> a truncated cone, which reminds us of the form of the Coto-<lb/>paxi, and which, according to a geodesic measurement made<lb/>by me at the west of Ibagué, is the highest summit of the An-<lb/>des in the northern hemisphere.<note place="foot" n="*">Height 18,321 feet; N. lat. 14° 46&#x2032;.</note> A rivulet which emits con-<lb/>siderably the smell of sulphuretted hydrogen descends from<lb/>the Peak of Tolima, and proves that the trachytes which<lb/>have penetrated the granitic rocks also contain sulphur.<lb/>Two learned travellers, M M. Rivero and Boussingault, have<lb/>recently visited this little <hi rendition="#i">solfatara in the micaceous schist</hi> of<lb/>Quindiu: they have sent some specimens to the cabinet of<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">Ecole des Mines</hi> at Paris, which contains the most com-<lb/>plete and instructive series of geognostic specimens. Follow-<lb/>ing the Cordillera of the Andes southwards, these same alter-<lb/>nations of primitive formations, and of porphyritic and tra-<lb/>chytic, are found:&#x2014;but what was my surprise, when beyond<lb/>the equator I ascertained that the celebrated <hi rendition="#i">mountain of sul-<lb/>phur of Ticsan</hi> (S. lat. 2° 10&#x2032;), between Quito and Cuenca, is<lb/>neither composed of trachyte, nor of chalk or of gypsum,<lb/>but of micaceous schist.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>This mountain of sulphur, which the Indians call <hi rendition="#i">Quello</hi>, is<lb/>situated, according to my barometric measurement, at the<lb/>height of 8000 feet above the level of the ocean. It is entire-<lb/>ly composed of primitive micaceous schist (<hi rendition="#i">glimmerschiefer</hi>),<lb/>which is not even anthracitic, as are the varieties of this<lb/>rock peculiar to transition countries. In some very deep ra-<lb/>vines between Ticsan and Alausia, the micaceous schist is seen<lb/>resting on gneiss. The sulphur is contained in a stratum of<lb/>quartz which is more than 12,00 feet thick: it lies in a toler-<lb/>ably regular direction, N. 18° E., and inclined like the mica-<lb/>ceous schist from 70° to 80° to the north-west. The bed of<lb/>quartz, which passes sometimes into the hornstone, is wrought<lb/>in an open working. The declivity of the <hi rendition="#i">Cerro Quello</hi>, on<lb/>which the works were begun some centuries since, is oppo-<lb/>site to the south-south-east; and the bed of quartz appears<lb/>to be prolonged towards the north-north-west, that is to say,<lb/>towards the coast of the Pacific Ocean. It is however as-<lb/>serted that the sulphur has not been found on the surface of<lb/>the ground in this direction to the distance of 2000 toises<lb/>from Ticsan. All is covered there with a thick vegetation.<lb/>Towards the end of the eighteenth century, masses of sulphur<lb/>were still worked, which were from 2 to 3 feet in diameter.<lb/>At present they are working some quartzose strata much less<lb/>
                    <pb n="519" facs="#f0014" /> rich, in which the sulphur is only dispersed in nodules from<lb/>3 to 4 inches thick. It is observed that the quantity of sul-<lb/>phur increases with the depth; but the working has been so<lb/>unskilfully directed that the lower strata are nearly inacces-<lb/>sible. The quartz in which the sulphur is dispersed presents<lb/>neither great fissures nor cavities, or <hi rendition="#i">druses;</hi> nor have I been<lb/>able to find any specimen of crystallized sulphur.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The mineral which is the object of the working of the <hi rendition="#i">Cerro<lb/>Quello</hi> does not form a mass of complication of veins, as<lb/>might be supposed: the sulphur is disseminated without any<lb/>continuity by little masses in the quartz which traverses the<lb/>micaceous schist in a direction parallel to its strata. The<lb/>clefts that have perhaps formerly united these masses are no<lb/>longer visible, but all the quartz seems to have undergone an<lb/>extraordinary change. It is tarnished, often brittle, and<lb/>breaks in some parts on the least shock; which indicates an<lb/>imperceptible cleavage. The temperature of the rock did<lb/>not differ from that of the exterior air. The inhabitants like<lb/>to attribute the violent earthquakes to which their country<lb/>has been sometimes exposed to concavities which they sup-<lb/>pose to exist under the mountain of sulphur. If this hypothe-<lb/>sis be well founded, it must be admitted that the cause which<lb/>it indicates acts but locally. In the great catastrophe of the<lb/>4th of February 1797, which destroyed so many thousand<lb/>Indians in the province of Quito&#x2014;the three places where<lb/>there is the most sulphur, the Cerro Quello, the Azufral of<lb/>Cuesaca near to the villa of Ibarra, and the Machay of Saint<lb/>Simon, near the volcano of Antisana, were but very feebly<lb/>agitated; but at a much earlier period there has been expe-<lb/>rienced, even on the bed of quartz which includes the sulphur<lb/>near Ticsan, an explosion similar to that of a mine.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The bed of quartz appears at the surface on the two sides<lb/>of the little river of Alausi; and facing the Cerro Quello is<lb/>found a little plain, where, in the seventeenth century, was<lb/>situated the village of Ticsan. The ruins of the church of<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Pueblo Viejo</hi> are still seen. An earthquake wholly local (for<lb/>its effects were confined to a very small space of country)<lb/>made the surrounding hills sink down: a part of the village<lb/>sunk: another part was thrown into the air, as happened at<lb/>Riobamba, where I found the bones of the unfortunate in-<lb/>habitants of the town thrown on the Cerro de la Culca, to a<lb/>height of several hundred feet. The Indians of Ticsan who<lb/>survived this catastrophe constructed their habitations more<lb/>to the north, far from the mountain of sulphur whose neigh-<lb/>
                    <pb n="520" facs="#f0015" /> bourhood they dreaded. It may be that the coincidence of<lb/>these ph&#x0153;nomena of explosion and of the position (gisement)<lb/>of a substance easy to be converted into elastic vapours has<lb/>only been accidental, but it may be also that ancient commu-<lb/>nications with the interior of the globe, those upon which is<lb/>formed by sublimation the immense deposit of sulphur, be-<lb/>came re-established from time to time, and allow the volcanic<lb/>forces to shake the surface of the soil. Near the ruins of<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Pueblo Viejo</hi> of Ticsan I found a hill of gypsum lying above<lb/>the micaceous schist: as this hill is not covered by other for-<lb/>mations, it is difficult to decide whether the gypsum, partly<lb/>fibrous and mixed with clay, is primitive, like that of Val Ca-<lb/>naria, or transition, like the gypsum of the Tarentaise.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The abundance of sulphur in primitive countries is a very<lb/>important geological fact, in relation to the study of volcanos<lb/>and of rocks, through which the subterraneous fire has open-<lb/>ed itself a passage. Before I had visited the Andes of Quito<lb/>and the mountain of Ticsan, sulphur was known only in the<lb/>transition limestone and gypsum; in the gypsums, marles and<lb/>muriatiferous clays of secondary countries, and in the rocks<lb/>exclusively called <hi rendition="#i">volcanic.</hi> These different geological situa-<lb/>tions, to which may be added the tertiary districts, very ill<lb/>explained the frequency of the sulphureous vapours exhaled<lb/>by the mouths of the volcanos, whose centre of action was<lb/>placed (and doubtless with propriety) very much below the<lb/>secondary and intermediate rocks. In proportion as we be-<lb/>come acquainted with a greater part of the globe, we not only<lb/>see positive geognosy, that is to say, the view of the forma-<lb/>tions and of the geological positions extended; but even <hi rendition="#i">geog-<lb/>ony</hi>, or systematic geognosy, the conjectural science which<lb/>investigates the causes of ph&#x0153;nomena, begins to be founded on<lb/>the analogy of more certain facts. We may have been<lb/>struck for some time past with the little masses of native sul-<lb/>phur which are disseminated in some metalliferous veins, and<lb/>which traverse granitic rocks; for example, in Schwarzwald,<lb/>near Riepoldsau. The mountain of Ticsan which I have<lb/>made known leaves no further doubt respecting the existence<lb/>of sulphur in the primitive districts. It has also been lately<lb/>found in Brazil, that the chloritic quartz formation which<lb/>covers, in the Capitania de Minas Geraes, the primitive clay-<lb/>slate contains both gold and sulphur. Lamin&#x00E6; of this rock<lb/>strongly heated burn with a blue flame. Near to Villarica,<lb/>in the district called Antonio Pereira, a schist, of the same<lb/>age as that on which is superposed the intacolumite or chlo-<lb/>
                    <pb n="521" facs="#f0016" /> itic quartz, contains a calcareous bed traversed by veins of<lb/>quartz, which the Baron d&#x2019;Eschwege (director of the gold<lb/>and diamond mines of these countries) has found filled with<lb/>little nodules of pulverulent sulphur. All these phenomena<lb/>increase in interest, when we reflect that this learned geolo-<lb/>gist, and also another German traveller (M. Pohl), incline to<lb/>the opinion that gold, micaceous iron, diamonds, euclases,<lb/>platina, and palladium, which are peculiar to the alluvial dis-<lb/>tricts of Brazil, have been derived either from the destruction<lb/>of the great formation of chloritic quartz, or from that of a<lb/>ferruginous bed (<hi rendition="#i">itabarite</hi>), which is placed above this for-<lb/>mation.</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>