<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157">
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-31" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="52" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>SCENERY OF THE UPPER OROONOKO.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>To take in at one view the grand character of these<lb break="yes"/>stupendous scenes, the spectator must be stationed on<lb break="yes"/>the little mountain of Manimi, a granitic ridge, that rises<lb break="yes"/>from the Savannah, north of the church of the mission,<lb break="yes"/>and is itself only a continuation of the steps of which<lb break="yes"/>the cataract of Manimi is composed. We often visited<lb break="yes"/>this mountain, for we were never weary of the view of<lb break="yes"/>this astonishing spectacle, concealed in one of the most<lb break="yes"/>remote corners of the earth. Arrived at the summit of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="53" facs="#f0002"/> the rock, the eye suddenly takes in a sheet of foam,<lb break="yes"/>extending a whole mile. Enormous masses of stone,<lb break="yes"/>black as iron, issue from its bosom. Some are paps<lb break="yes"/>grouped in pairs, like basaltic hills; others resemble<lb break="yes"/>towers, strong castles, and ruined buildings. Their<lb break="yes"/>gloomy tint contrasts with the silvery splendour of the<lb break="yes"/>foam. Every rock, every islet, is covered with vigo-<lb break="no"/>rous trees collected in clusters. At the foot of those<lb break="yes"/>paps, far as the eye can reach, a thick vapour is sus-<lb break="no"/>pended over the river, and through this whitish fog the<lb break="yes"/>tops of the lofty palm-trees shoot up. This majestic<lb break="yes"/>plant, the trunk of which is more than eighty feet high,<lb break="yes"/>has a leafy plume of a brilliant lustre, which rises al-<lb break="no"/>most straight toward the sky. At every hour of the<lb break="yes"/>day the sheet of foam displays different aspects. Some-<lb break="no"/>times the hilly islands and the palm-trees project their<lb break="yes"/>broad shadows; sometimes the rays of the setting sun<lb break="yes"/>are refracted in the humid cloud that shrouds the cata-<lb break="no"/>ract. Coloured arcs are formed, and vanish, and appear<lb break="yes"/>again alternately; light sport of the air, their images<lb break="yes"/>wave above the plain.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Such is the character of the landscape discovered<lb break="yes"/>from the top of the mountain of Manimi, which no tra-<lb break="no"/>veller has yet described. I do not hesitate to repeat,<lb break="yes"/>that neither time, nor the view of the Cordilleras, nor<lb break="yes"/>any abode in the temperate vallies of Mexico, have ef-<lb break="no"/>faced from my mind the powerful impression of the<lb break="yes"/>aspect of the cataracts. When I read a description of<lb break="yes"/>those places in India that are embellished by running<lb break="yes"/>waters and a vigorous vegetation, my imagination re-<lb break="no"/>traces a sea of foam and palm-trees, the tops of which<lb break="yes"/>rise above a stratum of vapour. The majestic scenes of<lb break="yes"/>nature, like the sublime works of poetry and the arts,<lb break="yes"/>leave remembrances that are incessantly awakening,<lb break="yes"/>and through the whole of life mingle with all our feel-<lb break="no"/>ings of what is grand and beautiful.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="54" facs="#f0003"/>
                <p>The calm of the atmosphere, and the tumultuous<lb break="yes"/>movement of the waters, produce a contrast peculiar to<lb break="yes"/>this zone. Here no breath of wind ever agitates the<lb break="yes"/>foliage, no cloud veils the splendour of the azure vault<lb break="yes"/>of heaven; a great mass of light is diffused in the air,<lb break="yes"/>on the earth strewn with plants with glossy leaves, and<lb break="yes"/>on the bed of the river, which extends far as the eye<lb break="yes"/>can reach. This appearance surprizes a traveller born<lb break="yes"/>in the north of Europe. The idea of wild scenery, of<lb break="yes"/>a torrent rushing from rock to rock, is linked in his<lb break="yes"/>imagination with that of a climate, where the noise of<lb break="yes"/>the tempest is mingled with the sound of the cataracts;<lb break="yes"/>and where, in a gloomy and misty day, sweeping clouds<lb break="yes"/>seem to descend into the valley, and rest upon the tops<lb break="yes"/>of the pines. The landscape of the tropics in the low<lb break="yes"/>regions of the continents has a peculiar physiognomy;<lb break="yes"/>something of greatness and repose, which it preserves<lb break="yes"/>even where one of the elements is struggling with in-<lb break="no"/>vincible obstacles. Near the equator, hurricanes and<lb break="yes"/>tempests belong to islands only, to deserts destitute of<lb break="yes"/>plants, and to those spots where parts of the atmos-<lb break="no"/>phere repose upon surfaces, from which the radiation<lb break="yes"/>of heat is very different.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#et">
                            <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 