<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div><head><hi rendition="#i">BARON HUMBOLDT</hi><lb/>AND THE MEXICAN GOVERNMENT.</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#c">(<hi rendition="#i">Translated from the Mexican Sol, of March</hi> 19, 1825.)<lb/>Letter addressed by the Minister of Relations, to Baron Alex-<lb/>ander Humboldt.</hi></p><lb/><dateline>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Mexico, July</hi> 21, 1824.</dateline></div><div><p>&#x2014;Your luminous writ-<lb/>ings relative to America, the fruit of your talents and<lb/>of your travels in this part of the globe, have been<lb/>generally received with the estimation due to the in-<lb/>teresting matter and information with which they<lb/>abound. From them can be formed a correct idea of<lb/>what Mexico will be, under a good and liberal Con-<lb/>stitution, possessing as it does, within itself, all the<lb/>elements of prosperity; and the reading of your<lb/>work, has not a little contributed to vivify the spirit of<lb/>independence, the germs of which existed amongst<lb/>many of the inhabitants, and to arouse others from<lb/>the lethargy in which they were held by foreign do-<lb/>mination. The whole nation is penetrated with gra-<lb/>titude for your labours, as they have been the means<lb/>of making known to the world its capacity of render-<lb/>ing itself happy in itself; and the supreme Govern-<lb/>ment charged with the administration of its public<lb/>concerns, heartily concur in this respect with the ge-<lb/>neral sentiment. The Government has, therefore,<lb/>been pleased to direct me, as their Minister of State<lb/>and Relations, to express to you the great satis-<lb/>faction with which they have understood it to be<lb/>your intention to return once more to this country,<lb/>and their lively hope that you will carry that idea<lb/>into effect, so that they may congratulate themselves<lb/>on counting amongst the number of the inhabitants of<lb/>this Republic, a man so illustrious and justly esteemed<lb/>throughout the civilized world. In communicating to<lb/>you these sentiments and wishes of my government, I<lb/>take the more pleasure as it affords me an opportunity<lb/>of repeating to you the expression of my high consi-<lb/>deration and respect.</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;LUCAS ALAMAN.</hi></p></div><lb/><div><p>&#x201C;Baron Alexander Humboldt.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#c">Answer to the preceding letter.</hi></p><lb/><dateline>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Paris, Nov.</hi> 6, 1824.</dateline></div><div><p>&#x2014;In an official letter of the<lb/>21st July, your Excellency has been pleased to trans-<lb/>mit to me the sentiments of affection and esteem with<lb/>which the Mexican nation and their government deign<lb/>to honour my slender literary labours. Engaged in a<lb/>career dedicated entirely to the cultivation of the<lb/>sciences, and to the support of the eternal principles<lb/>on which the progress of reason, and the amelioration<lb/>of public institutions depend, nothing could flatter<lb/>my self-love more than this solemn testimony, expressed<lb/>in so noble and interesting a manner. I therefore<lb/>beg your Excellency to present to your Government<lb/>this homage of my profound respect, and of my eter-<lb/>nal gratitude. If the works which I have published<lb/>have produced any good, it should be attributed only<lb/>to my love for the truth and the purity of my senti-<lb/>ments, and to the admiration with which I have been<lb/>inspired by a country whom nature has destined to so<lb/>exalted a fate. I am not without hope of beholding<lb/>once again (my sovereign permitting) the majestic<lb/>Corderillas of Anahuac; of studying once more the<lb/>natural productions; and of enjoying the pleasure of<lb/>witnessing the progressive happiness which must ne-<lb/>cessarily be produced in the bosom of the Republic<lb/>by free institutions and the arts of peace. In request-<lb/>ing your Excellency to be the organ of my gratitude<lb/>to the supreme Government, I seize the occasion to<lb/>reiterate to you the sentiments of high consideration<lb/>and esteem with which I have the honour to be, your<lb/>most humble and obedient servant,</p><lb/><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;ALEX. HUMBOLDT.</hi></salute></closer></div><lb/><div><p><hi rendition="#c">&#x201C;To his Excellency Lucas Alaman, Secretary of State<lb/>for the Mexican Republic.&#x201D;</hi></p><lb/><p>Letter of Baron Humboldt, to the President of the Republic.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Most Excellent Sir,</hi>&#x2014;With the most respect-<lb/>ful confidence, I address myself to the first Magistrate<lb/>of the Mexican Republic, to him whom the free<lb/>suffrages of the nation have just called to a post so<lb/>much the more eminent, as it affords the faculty of<lb/>using clemency, and of alleviating the sufferings of the<lb/>unfortunate. How satisfactory to me is the consideration<lb/>that the first time that I present myself before the<lb/>Supreme Government of a country, whose riches and<lb/>natural resources I have made known to Europe, my sup-<lb/>plications may procure @nnsolation for an unfortunate<lb/>family! I have this day learnt that Colonel Carlos<lb/>Benesky, with whom I am not personally acquainted<lb/>(although he is from the Prussian colony, and my<lb/>countryman) but who has done signal services in the<lb/>last wars of my country, has been induced by an error<lb/>of political opinion, to follow the fortunes of Augustin<lb/>Iturbide. An aged father and two sisters, of respec-<lb/>table connections, fear that he has for feited his life.<lb/>They have applied to me, hoping that my voice will<lb/>be listened to, and that my prayers may be sufficient<lb/>to obtain the liberty of a son and a brother, whose<lb/>residence in America was even unknown on the banks<lb/>of the Rhine.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;The Old World has admired the generous sentiments<lb/>displayed by the Mexican nation, in their conduct<lb/>towards the family of the Ex-Emperor. Deign, then,<lb/>your Excellency, as a distinguished favour to me, to<lb/>extend that national clemency to Colonel Benesky,<lb/>and for the sake of his unfortunate father, to commute<lb/>his punishment into merely banishment from the terri-<lb/>tory of the Republic. Emboldened by my known at-<lb/>tachment to a country for which your Excellency has<lb/>made so great and noble sacrifices, I make this sup-<lb/>plication with the most perfect confidence.&#x2014;I am,<lb/>with the most profound respect, Mr. President, your<lb/>Excellency&#x2019;s most humble and obedient servant,</p><lb/><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;ALEXANDER HUMBOLDT.</hi></salute></closer></div><lb/><div><p><hi rendition="#c">&#x201C;To his Excellency Gen. Guadalupe Victoria, President of the<lb/>Mexican Republic.&#x201D;</hi></p><lb/><p>(The wishes of Baron H. were anticipated, Colonel Benesky<lb/>having been merely sent out of the country, some time before<lb/>the above letter was received.)</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
