<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head>BARON HUMBOLDT.</head><lb/><p>Some interesting correspondence has passed between Baron<lb/>Humboldt and the Mexican Government. In a letter from<lb/>Lucas Alaman, Secretary of State for the Mexican Republic,<lb/>his Excellency states that the Baron&#x2019;s luminous writings rela-<lb/>tive to America had been received with general satisfaction,<lb/>and that the reading of the work had not a little contributed to<lb/>vivify the spirit of independence, the germs of which existed<lb/>amongst many of the inhabitants, and to arouse others from<lb/>the lethargy in which they were held by foreign domination.<lb/>The Government, heartily concurring in the general sentiment,<lb/>had directed his Excellency to express their lively hope that he<lb/>would carry his intention into effect, of once more returning<lb/>to Mexico, so that they might congratulate themselves on<lb/>counting amongst the number of the inhabitants of the Re-<lb/>public, a man so illustrious and justly esteemed throughout<lb/>the civilized world. The Baron, in reply, says, &#x201C;Engaged<lb/>in a career dedicated entirely to the cultivation of the sciences,<lb/>and to the support of the eternal principles on which the<lb/>progress of reason, and the amelioration of public institu-<lb/>tions depend, nothing could flatter my self-love more<lb/>than this solemn testimony, expressed in so noble and in-<lb/>teresting a manner. I therefore beg your Excellency to pre-<lb/>sent to your Government this homage of my profound respect,<lb/>and of my eternal gratitude. If the works which I have pub-<lb/>lished have produced any good, it should be attributed only to<lb/>my love for the truth and the purity of my sentiments, and to the<lb/>admiration with which I have been inspired by a country whom<lb/>nature has destined to so exalted a fate. I am not without hope<lb/>of beholding once again (my Sovereign permitting) the majestic<lb/>Cordilleras of Anahauc; of studying once more their natural<lb/>productions; and of enjoying the pleasure of witnessing the<lb/>happiness which must necessarily be produced in the bosom<lb/>of the Republic by free institutions and the arts of peace.&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
