<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>

<div n="1">
    <pb facs="#f0001" /> 
    <head>
        <hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#b"><hi rendition="#i">BARON HUMBOLDT.</hi></hi></hi>
    </head>
    <lb/>
<p>Some interesting correspondence has passed between Baron<lb/>
    <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi> and the Mexican Government. In a letter from<lb/>
    <hi rendition="#k">Lucas Alaman</hi>, Secretary of State for the Mexican Republic,<lb/>
    his Excellency states that the Baron&#x2019;s luminous writings rela-<lb/>
    tive to America had been received with general satisfaction,<lb/>
    and that the rending of the work had not a little contributed to<lb/>
    vivify the spirit of independence, the germs of which existed<lb/>
    amongst many of the inhabitants, and to arouse others from<lb/>
    the lethargy in which they were held by foreign domination.<lb/>
    The Government heartily concurring in the general sentiment,<lb/>
    had directed his Excellency to express their lively hope that he<lb/>
    would carry his intention into effect, of once more returning<lb/>
    to Mexico, so that they might congratulate themselves on<lb/>
    counting amongst the number of the inhabitants of the Re-<lb/>
    public, a man so illustious and justly esteemed throughout<lb/>
    the civilized world. The Baron, in reply, says, &#x201C;Engaged<lb/>
    in a career dedicated entirely to the cultivation of the sciences,<lb/>
    and to the support of the eternal principles on which the pro-<lb/>
    gress of reason, and the amelioration of public institutions de-<lb/>
    pend, nothing could flatter myself-love more than this solemn<lb/>
    testimony, expressed in so noble and in teresting a manner. I<lb/>
    therefore beg your Excellency to present to your Government<lb/>
    this homage of my profound respect, and of my eternal grati-<lb/>
    tude. If the works which I have published have produced any<lb/>
    good, it should be attributed only to my love for the truth and<lb/>
    the purity of my sentiments, and to the admiration with which<lb/>
    I have been inspired by a country whom nature has destined<lb/>
    to so exalted a fate. I am not without hope of beholding once<lb/>
    again (my Sovereign permitting) the majestic Corderillas of<lb/>
    Anahauc; and of studying once more their natural produc-<lb/>
    tions; and of enjoying the pleasure of witnessing happi-<lb/>
    ness which must necessarily be produced in the bosom of the<lb/>
    Republic, by free institutions and the arts of peace.&#x201D;
</p>
    </div>
    <lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
