<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">M. de Humboldt, and the Volcanos of Mexico</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:00</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.52</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1825-M_de_Humboldt-1-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1825-M_de_Humboldt-1-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1825-M_de_Humboldt-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">M. de Humboldt, and the Volcanos of Mexico</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1825</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in:&lt;i&gt; The Courier&lt;/i&gt; 10460 (20. Mai 1825), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
      <language ident="fra">Französisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">M. DE HUMBOLDT,<lb break="yes"/>AND THE VOLCANOS OF MEXICO.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>TO THE EDITOR OF THE COURIER.</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#et">
                            <hi rendition="#k">paris, grand hotel de richelieu,</hi>
                            <date>
                                <hi rendition="#k">may</hi> 12, 1825.</date>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#k">Sir</hi>&#x2014;Having travelled in New Spain, and knowing, from what<lb break="yes"/>I have seen and experienced, the inestimable value and correct-<lb break="no"/>ness of M. de Humboldt&#x2019;s works, I felt not a little surprised to hear<lb break="yes"/>that <hi rendition="#i">distinguished traveller</hi> constantly accused of exaggeration<lb break="yes"/>and inaccuracy. If those, who thus endeavor to detract from the<lb break="yes"/>merits of M. de Humboldt&#x2019;s work, are not so alive to the beauties<lb break="yes"/>of nature as he is, we must recollect, that there is, perhaps, no<lb break="yes"/>man now existing, who combines with the depth and details of<lb break="yes"/>almost every &#x017F;cience, so much general knowledge; and to such a<lb break="yes"/>mind, that may have the greatest value, which, by ordinary and<lb break="yes"/>superficial observers, would be slightly noticed, because they are<lb break="yes"/>unable to appreciate it. As, however, I had heard M. de Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt accused of asserting a deliberate falsehood, which no warmth<lb break="yes"/>of feeling, or liveliness of imagination, could justify; as I have in<lb break="yes" />vain endeavored to combat the interpretation often put upon the<lb break="yes"/>passage alluded to; and as an attack has been made upon him in<lb break="yes"/>a work recently published&#x2014;(Bullock&#x2019;s Mexico, vide note at the<lb break="yes"/>end of chap. vii.)&#x2014;on coming to Paris, and having had the<lb break="yes"/>honor and pleasure of making M. de Humboldt&#x2019;s acquaintance,<lb break="yes"/>I ventured to mention the subject to him, and <hi rendition="#i">then he</hi> very kindly<lb break="yes"/>addressed to me the enclosed.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>J&#x2019;ai dit dans l&#x2019;edition originale Francaise Essai Politique,<lb break="yes"/>in 4to. T. 1. p. 80, Introd. p. 17.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Pour mieux distinguer les volcans actives des volcans eteints,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">je me suis permis</hi> d&#x2019;ajouter une petite colonne de fumée aux dessins<lb break="yes"/>du Pic d&#x2019;Orizaba et du Grand Volcan de la Puebla, <hi rendition="#i">quoique je<lb break="yes" />n&#x2019;aie observé cette fumée ni à Xalapa ni à Mexico.</hi> Nous avons<lb break="yes"/>vu sortir une grande masse de cendres et des vapeurs trés denses<lb break="yes"/>de la bouche du Popocatepetl le 24 Juin 1804 dans la plaine de<lb break="yes"/>Tetimba, prés de San Nicolas de los Ranchos.&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>J&#x2019;ai dit T. 1. p. 179, chap 8.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Le Popocatepetl forme un cone enorme dont le cratére, con-<lb break="no"/>stamment enflammé, jettant de la fumée et des cendres s&#x2019;ouvre au<lb break="yes"/>milieu des neiges eternelles!&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Ce passage n&#x2019;indique certainement pas que <hi rendition="#i"
              >l&#x2019;on voit</hi> de la fumée<lb break="yes"/>de Mexico même; il dit, que le
            cratére jette encore tous les ans,<lb break="yes"/>j&#x2019;aurois pu dire tous les
            mois, de la fumée; elle se voit dans la<lb break="yes"/>plaine de Tetimba, au pic du
            volcan. Le tremblement de terre<lb break="yes"/>du 13 Janvier 1804, fut accompagné
            d&#x2019;une forte ejection de cendres<lb break="yes"/>et de fumée. Les ejections sont
            trés communes au mois de Mai<lb break="yes"/>et <choice>
              <sic>entres</sic>
              <corr type="editorial">entre</corr>
            </choice> 4 et 6 heures du soir. La direction de la fumée sert<lb break="yes"
            />m&#x00EA;me aux Indiens du voisinage de pronostic <choice>
              <sic>meteoroligique</sic>
              <corr type="editorial">météorologique</corr>
            </choice>.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>M. de Humboldt serait très reconnoissant à Monsieur Staple-<lb break="no"
            />ton, s&#x2019;il vouloit bien repandre ces éclaircissemens; car il tient<lb
              break="yes"/>beaucoup plus à la reputation d&#x2019;un voyageur <choice>
              <sic>veredique</sic>
              <corr type="editorial">verédique</corr>
            </choice> qu&#x2019;à<lb break="yes"/>celle de l&#x2019;esprit et du savoir.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Ce Mardi, Quai de l&#x2019;Ecole, 26.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>By this it will appear, that, in that faithful and beautiful de-<lb break="no"/>scription, (T. 1. p. 179, chap. viii.) of the view to be seen on a fine<lb break="yes"/>morning from the tower of the cathedral of Mexico, or from the<lb break="yes"/>hill of Chapultepetl, M. de H. does not mean to say that he has<lb break="yes"/>seen from either of those points the smoke issuing from the crater<lb break="yes"/>of Popocatepetl, but only that it is constantly inflamed, that smoke<lb break="yes"/>does issue from it, and that he himself, when near to the crater,<lb break="yes"/>was present with M. Bonpland at an eruption of smoke and<lb break="yes"/>ashes. The greatest wonders of our globe being to the inhabitants<lb break="yes"/>of New Spain an every-day scene, they are less alive to them<lb break="yes" />than the stranger, who is surprised, on enquiring after the cu-<lb break="no"/>riosities in their immediate vicinity, (to see which he has crossed<lb break="yes"/>the Atlantic), to find them often ignorant even of their existence.<lb break="yes"/>I had in vain made various and anxious enquiries at Mexico res-<lb break="no"/>pecting the activity of the volcano of Popocatepetl&#x2014;all agreed,<lb break="yes"/>that there had been no eruption within the last century. At last,<lb break="yes"/>one morning, when I was riding before breakfast from Mexico<lb break="yes"/>to the Penol de los Banos, I met an Indian, who, in reply to<lb break="yes"/>my questions, told me, that during the dry season, when the wind<lb break="yes"/>blew from the North, he had occasionally seen the smoke even<lb break="yes"/>from the city of Mexico! In Europe, we must be surprised to<lb break="yes"/>hear, that such a fact should only be known to an Indian; but<lb break="yes"/>that surprise will cease, when we consider the indolence and<lb break="yes" />indifference of the <hi rendition="#k">enlightened</hi> classes in that country, and the<lb break="yes"/>immense distance from Mexico of the summit of a mountain,<lb break="yes"/>which rises into the Heavens near 18,000 feet above the level of<lb break="yes"/>the sea, covered with eternal snows, and for ever inaccessible to<lb break="yes"/>man.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Cortez, in his letters, A.D. 1519, alludes to the smoke of<lb break="yes" />Popocatepetl.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A grand eruption, which took place in 1540 is mentioned by<lb break="yes" />Gormora.&#x2014;(Hist. Mex. published 1553.)</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The last great eruption, according to Torquemada, was in 1594.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I subjoin some extracts of M. de H.&#x2019;s Journal, which have<lb break="yes"/>not yet been published, and which he has very obligingly com-<lb break="no"/>munnicated to me:&#x2014;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The rock of Popocatepetl is obsidian-porphyry. The crater<lb break="yes"/>itself is easily to be seen with a glace; but as it inclines towards<lb break="yes"/>the East (as all the great volcanic cones in these parts do), it is<lb break="yes"/>not visible from the city of Mexico. The smell of <choice><sic>suphureous</sic><corr type="editorial">sulphureous</corr></choice><lb break="yes"/>vapours can be perceived below the limit of the snow. These<lb break="yes"/>vapours are regarded by the Indians as a presage of weather.<lb break="yes"/>When, in the evening, a black smoke arises from the crater, and<lb break="yes"/>forms itself into a cloud, inclining to the North, it is thought to<lb break="yes"/>portend rain; when it inclines to the South, it is looked upon as<lb break="yes" />the forerunner of a severe frost; when it arises perpendicularly,<lb break="yes"/>it is said to announce a storm. At times, two or three hours<lb break="yes"/>before the storm is felt in the inferior regions, clouds of<lb break="yes"/>pumice-stone and ashes arise from the crater, and they may<lb break="yes"/>be seen rolling downwards upon the snow, as particles of<lb break="yes"/>sand. There was a violent storm accompanying the earth-<lb break="no"/>quake on the 13th of January, 1804, and a considerable<lb break="yes"/>eruption of smoke and ashes from the mouth of the crater.<lb break="yes"/>The smoke is seldom to be seen in the morning; generally<lb break="yes"/>from four to six in the evening, particularly at the setting<lb break="yes"/>of the sun, and more frequently in the month of May. The<lb break="yes"/>Indians assured me, that at that period, the whole top some-<lb break="no"/>times assumes a red-yellowish color, which may be attributed<lb break="yes"/>to the sulphurcous vapours. At night, however, no <hi rendition="#i">fire</hi> has ever<lb break="yes" />been seen within the memory of man.&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Those who have visited the volcanoes of the New World, and<lb break="yes"/>of the West Indian Islands, know, that this state of constant<lb break="yes" />inflammation, and emission of smoke, is common to almost all<lb break="yes"/>of them. I descended last year, into the crater of that of Gua-<lb break="no"/>daloupe, (the elevation of which is near 6,000 feet above the<lb break="yes"/>level of the sea,) and had my hands scorched in procuring<lb break="yes"/>some of the burning sulphur, which glimmers of a bright yel-<lb break="no"/>low, through the clouds of smoke in different parts<lb break="yes"/>of the interior of the crater. In the Island of Dominica,<lb break="yes"/>I have seen several burning craters of the same descrip-<lb break="no"/>tion. Such also was precisely the state of the volcano<lb break="yes"/>of St. Vincent&#x2019;s before the remarkable eruption of 1812,<lb break="yes"/>which covered ships with ashes at two or three hundred Eng-<lb break="no"/>lish miles <hi rendition="#k">to the windward,</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="*">This has been endeavored to be explained by the counter-<lb break="maybe"/>currents of air prevalent in the Tropics, and blowing in a direction<lb break="yes"/>contrary to that of the trade-winds.</note> as well as the island of Bar-<lb break="no"/>badoes, at eighty miles distance, and the noise of which was<lb break="yes"/>heard at Antigua, (and I believe at St. Thomas&#x2019;s) where it was<lb break="yes"/>thought to be an engagement between the two fleets of France<lb break="yes"/>and Great Britain, though (wonderful to relate) not heard by<lb break="yes"/>the inhabitants of the smaller islands in the <hi rendition="#i">immediate vici-<lb break="no"/>nity of St. Vincent&#x2019;s itself.</hi> These burning mountains acquire<lb break="yes"/>the greatest interest from the consideration, that though now ap-<lb break="no"/>parently in an almost passive state, they may, by convulsion,<lb break="yes"/>become, when least expected, vast engins of the most horrible<lb break="yes"/>destruction. The giving way of a layer of earth, undermined by<lb break="yes"/>slow fire, may cause an eruption, and shake the universe.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#et">I remain, &#x0026;c. J. C. STAPLETON.</hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 