<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Interesting correspondence between baron Humboldt and the mexican government</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:00</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.48</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1825-Contestacion_a_la-05-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1825-Contestacion_a_la-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1825-Contestacion_a_la-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1825-Contestacion_a_la-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1825-Contestacion_a_la-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1825-Contestacion_a_la-05-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1825-Contestacion_a_la-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1825-Contestacion_a_la-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1825-Contestacion_a_la-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1825-Contestacion_a_la-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1825-Contestacion_a_la-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1825-Contestacion_a_la-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Interesting correspondence between baron Humboldt and the mexican government</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1825</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Courier&lt;/i&gt; 10508 (18. Juli 1825), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<pb facs="#f0002" />
<div><head><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<hi rendition="#i">INTERESTING CORRESPONDENCE BETWEEN<lb/>BARON HUMBOLDT AND THE MEXICAN GO-<lb/>VERNMENT.</hi><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/></head>
<p><hi rendition="#c">(<hi rendition="#i">Translated from the Mexican Sol, of March</hi> 19, 1825.)<lb/>Letter addressed by the Minister of Relations, to Baron Alex-<lb/>ander Humboldt.</hi></p><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#k">Mexico, july</hi> 21, 1824.</hi></dateline></div><lb/><div><p>Your luminous writings relative to America, the fruit of your<lb/>talents and of your travels in this part of the globe, have been<lb/>generally received with the estimation due to the interesting<lb/>matter and information with which they abound. From them<lb/>can be formed a correct idea of what Mexico will be, under a<lb/>good and liberal Constitution, possessing as it does, within itself,<lb/>all the elements of prosperity; and the reading of your work,<lb/>has not a little contributed to vivify the spirit of independence,<lb/>the germs of which existed amongst many of the inhabit-<lb/>ants, and to arouse others from the lethargy in which they<lb/>were held by foreign domination. The whole nation<lb/>is penetrated with gratitude for your labours, as they<lb/>have been the means of making known to the world<lb/>its capacity of rendering itself happy in itself; and<lb/>the supreme Government charged with the administration of<lb/>its public concerns, heartily concur in this respect with the ge-<lb/>neral sentiment. The Government has, therefore, been pleased<lb/>to direct me, as their Minister of State and Relations, to express<lb/>to you the great satisfaction with which they have understood it<lb/>to be your intention to return once more to this country, and<lb/>their lively hope that you will carry that idea into effect, so that<lb/>they may congratulate themselves on counting amongst the num-<lb/>ber of the inhabitants of this republic, a man so illustrious and<lb/>justly esteemed throughout the civilized world. In communi-<lb/>cating to you these sentiments and wishes of my government, I<lb/>take the more pleasure as it affords me an opportunity of repeat-<lb/>ing to you the expression of my high consideration and respect.</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#et">LUCAS ALAMAN.</hi></p><lb/><p>Baron Alexander Humboldt.</p></div><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<div><p><hi rendition="#c">Answer to the preceding Letter.</hi></p><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#k">Paris, Nov.</hi> 6, 1824.</hi></dateline></div><lb/><div><p>In an official letter of the 21st July, your Excellency has been<lb/>pleased to transmit to me the sentiments of affection and esteem<lb/>with which the Mexican nation and their government deign to<lb/>honour my slender literary labours. Engaged in a career dedi-<lb/>cated entirely to the cultivation of the sciences, and to the sup-<lb/>port of the eternal principles on which the progress of reason,<lb/>and the amelioration of public institutions depend, nothing could<lb/>flatter my self-love more than this solemn testimony, expressed in<lb/>so noble and interesting a manner. I therefore beg your Excel-<lb/>lency to present to your Government this homage of my pro-<lb/>found respect, and of my eternal gratitude. If the works which<lb/>I have published have produced any good, it should be attri-<lb/>buted only to my love for the truth and the purity of my senti-<lb/>ments, and to the admiration with which I have been inspired by<lb/>a country whom nature has destined to so exalted a fate. I am<lb/>not without hope of beholding once again (my sovereign<lb/>permitting) the majestic Corderillas of Anàhuac; of studying<lb/>once more their natural productions; and of enjoying the plea-<lb/>sure of witnessing the progressive happiness which must neces-<lb/>sarily be produced in the bosom of the Republic by free institu-<lb/>tions and the arts of peace. In requesting your Excellency to<lb/>be the organ of my gratitude to the supreme Government, I seize<lb/>the occasion to reiterate to you the sentiments of high considera-<lb/>tion and esteem with which I have the honour to be, your most<lb/>humble and obedient servant,</p><lb/><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">ALEX. HUMBOLDT.</hi></salute></closer></div><lb/><div><p><hi rendition="#c">To his Excellency Lucas Alaman, Secretary of State<lb/>for the Mexican Republic.</hi></p><lb/></div><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<div><p>Letter of Baron Humboldt, to the President of the Republic.</p><lb/><p>Most Excellent Sir&#x2014;With the most respectful confidence, I<lb/>address myself to the first Magistrate of the Mexican Republic,<lb/>to him whom the free suffrages of the nation have just called to<lb/>a post so much the more eminent, as it affords the faculty of<lb/>using clemency, and of alleviating the sufferings of the unfor-<lb/>tunate. How satisfactory to me is the consideration, that the<lb/>first time that I present myself before the Supreme Government<lb/>of a country, whose riches and natural resources I have made<lb/>known to Europe, my supplications may procure consolation for<lb/>an unfortunate family! I have this day learnt that Col. Carlos<lb/>Benesky, with whom I am not personally acquainted (although<lb/>he is from the Prussian colony, and my countryman)<lb/>but who has done signal services in the last wars of my<lb/>country, has been induced by an error of political opinion,<lb/>to follow the fortunes of Augustin Iturbide. An aged<lb/>father and two sisters, of respectable connections, fear that<lb/>he has forfeited his life. They have applied to me, hoping that<lb/>my voice will be listened to, and that my prayers may be suffi-<lb/>cient to obtain the liberty of a son and a brother, whose resi-<lb/>dence in America was even unknown on the banks of the Rhine.</p><lb/><p>The Old World has admired the generous sentiments displayed<lb/>by the Mexican nation, in their conduct towards the family of<lb/>the Ex-Emperor. Deign, then, your Excellency, as a distin-<lb/>guished favour to me, to extend that national clemency to Co-<lb/>lonel Benesky, and for the sake of his unfortunate father, to<lb/>commute his punishment into merely banishment from the terri-<lb/>tory of the Republic. Emboldened by my known attachment to<lb/>a country for which your Excellency has made so great and<lb/>noble sacrifices, I make this supplication with the most perfect<lb/>confidence.&#x2014;I am, with the most profound respect, Mr. Presi-<lb/>dent, your Excellency&#x2019;s most humble and obedient servant,</p><lb/><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">ALEXANDER HUMBOLDT.</hi></salute></closer></div><lb/><div><p><hi rendition="#c">To his Excellency Gen. Guadalupe Victoria, President of the<lb/>Mexican Republic.</hi></p><lb/><p>[The wishes of Baron H. were anticipated, Colonel Benesky<lb/>having been merely sent out of the country, some time before<lb/>the above letter was received.]</p></div><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
