<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="19" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>M. DE HUMBOLDT.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">TO THE EDITOR OF THE COURIER.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Paris, Grand H&#x00F4;tel de Richelieu, <date>May 12, 1825.</date>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Sir</hi>&#x2014;Having travelled in New Spain, and knowing, from<lb break="yes"/>what I have seen and experienced, the inestimable value and<lb break="yes"/>correctness of M. de Humboldt&#x2019;s works, I felt not a liitle sur-<lb break="no"/>prised to hear that distinguished traveller constantly aecnsod of<lb break="yes"/>exaggeration and inaccuracy. If those, who thus endenvour to<lb break="yes"/>detract from the merits of M. de Humboldt&#x2019;s work, are not so<lb break="yes"/>alive to the beauties of nature as he is, we must recollect, that there<lb break="yes"/>is, perhaps, no man now existing, who combines with the<lb break="yes"/>depth and details of almost every science, so much general know-<lb break="no"/>ledge; and to such a mind, that may have the greatest value,<lb break="yes"/>which by ordinary and superficial observers would be slightly<lb break="yes"/>noticed, because they are unble to @ it. As, however,<lb break="yes"/>I had heard M. de Humboldt accu ed of uttering @ doli@erate<lb break="yes"/>falsehood, which no warmth of feeling or liveliness of imagina-<lb break="no"/>tion could justify; as I have in vain endeavoured to combat the<lb break="yes"/>interpretation often put upon the passage alluded to; and as an<lb break="yes"/>attack has been made upon him in a work recently published &#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>(Bullock&#x2019;s Mexico, vide note at the eud of chap. vii.) &#x2014; on coming<lb break="yes"/>to Paris, and having had the honour and pleasure of making M.<lb break="yes"/>de Humboldt&#x2019;s acquaintance, I ventured to mention the subject<lb break="yes" />to him, and then he very kindly addressed to me the enclosed.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>J&#x2019;ai dit dans l&#x2019;edition originale Fran&#x00E7;aise Essai Politique, en 4to.<lb break="yes"/>T. 1. p. 80. Introd. p. 17.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Pour @eux distinguer les volcans actives des volcans eteints<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">je me suis permis</hi> d&#x2019;ajouter une petite colonne de fumée aux<lb break="yes"/>dessins du Pic d&#x2019;Orizaba et du Grand Volcan de la Puebla, <hi rendition="#i">quoi-<lb break="no"/>que je n&#x2019;aie observée cette fum&#x00EA;e ni à Zalapa, ni à Mexico.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Nous avons vu sortir une grande masse des cendres et des vapeurs<lb break="yes"/>très denses de la bouche du Popocatepetl le 24 Juin 1804, dans<lb break="yes"/>la plaine de Tetimba, près de San Nicolas de los Ranchos:&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>J&#x2019;ai dit T. 1. p. 179. chap. 8.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Le Popocatepetl forme un cone enorme dont la cratére, con-<lb break="no" />stamment enflamme, jettant de la fumée et des cendres s&#x2019;ouvre<lb break="yes"/>au milieu des neiges eternelles!&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Ce passage n&#x2019;indique certainement pas que <hi rendition="#i">l&#x2019;on voit</hi> de la &#x017F;umée<lb break="yes"/>de Mexico méme; il dit, que le cratére jette encore tous les ans@<lb break="yes"/>j&#x2019;aurois pu dire tous les mois, de la &#x017F;umée: elle se voit dans la<lb break="yes"/>plaine de Tetimba, an pic du volcan. Le tremblement de<lb break="yes"/>terre du 13 Janvier 1804, &#x017F;ut accompagné d&#x2019;une forte ejection de<lb break="yes" />cendres et de &#x017F;umée. Les ejections sont trés communes au mois<lb break="yes"/>de Mai et entre 4 et 6 heures du soir. La direction de la &#x017F;umée<lb break="yes"/>sert m&#x00EA;me aux Indiens de voisinage de pronostic meteoroligique.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. de Humboldt serait très reconnoissant à Monsicur Stapleton,<lb break="yes" />s&#x2019;il vouloit bien repandre ces éclaircissemens; car il tient beau-<lb break="no"/>coup plus à la reputation d&#x2019;un voyageur verédique qu&#x2019;a celle de<lb break="yes"/>l&#x2019;esprit et du savoir.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Ce Mardi, Quai de l&#x2019;Ecole, 26.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>By this it will appear, that in that faithful and beautiful de-<lb break="no" />scription (T. 1. p. 179, chap. viii.) of the view to be seen on a<lb break="yes"/>fine morm@g from the tower of the cathedral of Mexico, or from<lb break="yes"/>the hill. of Chapultepetl, M. de H. does nor mean to say that he<lb break="yes"/>has seen from either of those points the smoke issuing from the<lb break="yes"/>erater of Popocatepetl, but only that it is constantly inflamed,<lb break="yes"/>that smoke does issue from it, and that he himself, when near to<lb break="yes"/>the erater, was present with M. Boupland at an eruption of smoke<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> and as hes. The greatest wonders of our globe being to the in-<lb break="no"/>habita @ts of New Spain an every day scene, they are less alive to<lb break="yes"/>them than the stranger, who is surprised, on inquiring after the<lb break="yes"/>curiosi ties in their immediate vicinity (to see which he has cross-<lb break="no"/>ed the. Atlantic), to find them often ignorant even of their exist-<lb break="no"/>ence. I had in vain made various and anxious inquiries at Mex-<lb break="no"/>ico resp@ecting the activity of the volcano of Popocatepetl&#x2014;all<lb break="yes"/>agreed that there had been no eruption within the last century.<lb break="yes"/>At last, one morning, when I was riding before break&#x017F;ast from<lb break="yes"/>Mexico to the Penol de los Banos, I met an Indian, who, in re-<lb break="no"/>ply to my questions, told me, that during the dry season, when<lb break="yes"/>the wind blew from the north, he had occasionally seen the smoke<lb break="yes"/>even from the city of Mexico! In Europe, we must be surprised<lb break="yes"/>to hear, that such a fact should be only known to an Indian; but<lb break="yes"/>that surprise will cease, when we consider the indolence and<lb break="yes"/>indifference of the <hi rendition="#i">enlightened</hi> classes in that country, and the<lb break="yes"/>immense distance from Mexico of the summit of a mountain,<lb break="yes"/>which rises into the Heavens near 18,000 feet above the level of<lb break="yes"/>the sea, covered with eternal snows, and for ever inaccessible to<lb break="yes"/>man.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Cortez in his letters, A. D. 1519, alludes to the smoke of Popo-<lb break="no" />catepetl.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A grand eruption which took place in 1540 is mentioned by<lb break="yes" />Gormora.&#x2014;(Hist. Mex. pub. 1553.)</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The last great eruption, according to Torquemada, was in<lb break="yes" />15@4.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I subjoin some extracts from M. de H&#x2019;s Journal, which have<lb break="yes" />not yet been published, and which he has very obligingly com-<lb break="no" />municated to me:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The rock of Popocatepetl is obsidian porphyry. The crater<lb break="yes" />itself is easily to be seen with a glass, but as it iuclines towards<lb break="yes"/>the East as all the great volcanic cones in these parts do), it is<lb break="yes"/>not visible from the city of Mexico. The smell of sulphureous<lb break="yes"/>vapours can be perceived below the limits of the snow. These<lb break="yes"/>vapours are considered by the Indians as a presage of weather.<lb break="yes"/>When in the evening, a black smoke arises from the crater, and<lb break="yes"/>forms itself into a cloud, inclining to the north, it is thouglrt to<lb break="yes"/>portend rain; when it inclines to the south, it is looked upon as<lb break="yes"/>the forerunner of a severe frost; when it arises perpendicularly,<lb break="yes"/>it is said to announce a storm. At times, two or three hours be-<lb break="no"/>fore the storm is felt in the inferior regions, clouds of pumice<lb break="yes"/>stone and ashes arise from the crater, and they may be seen roll-<lb break="no"/>ing down wards upon the snow, as particles of sand. There was<lb break="yes"/>a violent storm accompanying the earthquake on the 13th of Ja-<lb break="no"/>nuary, 1804, and a considerable eruption of smoke and ashes from<lb break="yes"/>the mouth of the crater. The smoke is seldom to be seen in the<lb break="yes"/>morning; generally from four to s x in the evening, particularly<lb break="yes"/>at the setting of the sun, and more frequently in the month of<lb break="yes"/>May. The Indians assured me, that at that period, the whole<lb break="yes"/>tops sometimes assumed a red-yellowish colour, which may be<lb break="yes"/>attributed to the sulphureous vapours. At night, however, no<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">fire</hi> has ever been seen within the memory of man.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Those who have visited the volcanoes of the New World, and<lb break="yes"/>of the West Indian Islands, know, that this constant state of in-<lb break="no" />flammation and emission of smoke is common to almost all of<lb break="yes" />them. I descended last year, into the crater of that of Guada-<lb break="no" />loupe (tlie elevation of which is near 6000 feet above the level of<lb break="yes"/>the sea), and had my hands scorched in procuring some of the<lb break="yes"/>burning sulphur, which glimmers of a bright yellow, through<lb break="yes"/>the clouds of smoke in different parts of the interior of the crater.<lb break="yes"/>In the Island of Dominica, I have seen several burning craters<lb break="yes"/>of the some description. Such also was precisely the state of the<lb break="yes"/>volcano of St. Vincent&#x2019;s before the remarkable eruption of 1812,<lb break="yes"/>which covered ships with ashes at two or three hundred Eng-<lb break="no"/>lish miles to the <hi rendition="#i" >windward,</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">This has been endeavoured to be explained by the counter-currents<lb break="yes"/>of air prevalent in the Tropics; and blowing in a direction contrary to<lb break="yes"/>that of the trade-winds.</note> as well as the island of Barbadoes,<lb break="yes"/>at eighty miles distance, and the noise of which was heard at<lb break="yes" />Antigua, (and I believe at St. Thomas&#x2019;s,) where it was thought<lb break="yes"/>to be an engagement between the two fleets of France and Great<lb break="yes"/>Brrtain, though (wonderful to relate) not heard by the inhabi-<lb break="no"/>tants of the smaller islands in the <hi rendition="#i">immediate vicinily</hi> of St. Vin-<lb break="no" />cent&#x2019;s itself. These burning mountains acquire the greatest in-<lb break="no"/>terest from the consideration, that though now apparently in an<lb break="yes"/>almost passive state, they may, by convulsion, become, when<lb break="yes"/>least expected, vast engines of the most horrible destruction. The<lb break="yes"/>giving way of a layer of earth, undermined by slow fire, may<lb break="yes"/>cause an eruption and shake the universe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">I remain, etc.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#et">J. C. STAPLETON.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 