<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On the Volcanos of Guatemala</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:01</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.68</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1826-Ueber_den_neuesten-3</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1826-Ueber_den_neuesten-1.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1826-Ueber_den_neuesten-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1826-Ueber_den_neuesten-3.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1826-Ueber_den_neuesten-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1826-Ueber_den_neuesten-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1826-Ueber_den_neuesten-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On the Volcanos of Guatemala</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1827</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in:&lt;i&gt; The Philosophical Magazine or Annals of Chemistry, Mathematics, Astronomy, Natural History, and General Science&lt;/i&gt; 2:8 (August 1827), S. 117–122.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Fußnoten mit Asterisken; Schmuck: Initialen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="117" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">On the Volcanos of <placeName>Guatemala</placeName>. By</hi> M. <hi rendition="#k">de Humboldt.</hi> <note place="foot" n="*">The above article relating to the volcanos of <placeName>Guatemala</placeName>, or, as it is<lb/>now called, <placeName>Central America</placeName>, is extracted from a paper in a <bibl>recent num-<lb/>ber of the <hi rendition="#i">Hertha</hi></bibl>, by Alex. de Humboldt. The entire paper relates to the<lb/>present condition of this free state; but the portion we have selected alone<lb/>comes within the scope of our Journal, and is sufficiently distinct from the<lb/>rest for separate publication.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k"><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Edit.</persName></hi></note></head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#in">T</hi>HE volcanos of <placeName>Central America</placeName> are ranged successively<lb/>between the mountains of <placeName>Veragua</placeName>, and <placeName>Oaxada</placeName>, latitude<lb/>11° to 16°. The gneiss and mica slate of <placeName>Veragua</placeName> connect<lb/>them with the western chain of <placeName>New Grenada</placeName>; the granitic<lb/>gneiss of <placeName>Oaxada</placeName> unites them to the <placeName>Mexican</placeName> ridge: this con-<lb/>nection, however, is formed not by the volcanos themselves,<lb/>but by the mountainous land which surrounds them. During<lb/>my voyage from <placeName>Lima</placeName> to <placeName>Acapulco</placeName>, I collected from the Spa-<lb/>nish manuscript charts of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">John Morabda</persName> and other navigators<lb/>various particulars, which throw light on the situation of the<lb/>burning mountains of <placeName>Guatemala</placeName> with respect to the sea.<lb/>Most of these volcanos are inserted by <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Bauza</persName>, with an accuracy<lb/>peculiar to himself, in the <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Carta esferica del Mar de las An-<lb/>tillas</hi>, 1805</bibl>, and in the <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Carta esferica desde el Golfo Dulce<lb/>hasta San Blas</hi>, 1822</bibl>: yet <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Von Buch</persName> very properly remarks in<lb/>his classical work on the <placeName>Canary Isles</placeName> (<bibl>1825, p. 406&#x2014;409</bibl>),<lb/>that <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">William Furnel</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Dampier&#x2019;s</persName> mate, discovered at the early<lb/>period of his voyage almost all that we know of them at<lb/>present.</p><lb/><p>I shall pursue the series from S.E. to N.W., as they are<lb/>placed by <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Arago</persName> in the <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Annuaire du Bureau des Longitudes</hi><lb/>1824</bibl>, according to the materials which have been imparted<lb/>to me. Wherever my information does not correspond<lb/>with the charts, or these do not correspond with one an-<lb/>other, I shall state their variations with exactness, that future<lb/>voyagers may determine the geographic results arising from<lb/>them. Many of the volcanos have several names, which vary<lb/>with the variation of the Indian idioms, and are borrowed from<lb/>those of the neighbouring places. Thus in <placeName>New Spain</placeName>, <hi rendition="#i"><placeName>Po-<lb/>pocatepetl</placeName></hi> and <hi rendition="#i"><placeName>Iztaccí hunté</placeName></hi>, are called sometimes <hi rendition="#i"><placeName>Volcanes<lb/>de Puebla</placeName></hi>, sometimes <hi rendition="#i"><placeName>Volcanes de Mexico</placeName>;</hi> and from not under-<lb/>standing this, two mountains may be turned into six. An-<lb/>other source of error is, that in <placeName>America</placeName> the name of <hi rendition="#i">Vol-<lb/>cano</hi> is not only applied to the mountains whose eruptions<lb/>extend beyond the age of history, but also to masses of<lb/>trachyte, which it is certain have never burnt, and are not<lb/>connected with the interior of the earth by permanent aper-<lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">tures,</fw><lb/><pb n="118" facs="#f0002" />
        tures. Southernmost stands the <hi rendition="#i"><placeName>Volcan de Barua</placeName></hi>, lat. 8° 50&#x2032;,<lb/>in the interior of the country, seven miles N.E. of <placeName>Golfo Dulce</placeName>;<lb/>it is called in the English maps <hi rendition="#i"><placeName>Volcan de Varu</placeName></hi>, and placed,<lb/>I believe incorrectly, far more to the east (under 84° 52&#x2032; west<lb/>long., and 8° 25&#x2032; lat.) in the province of <placeName>Veragua</placeName>. Next to<lb/>the <placeName>Volcan de Barua</placeName> comes the <placeName>Volcan de Papagayo</placeName> (lat.<lb/>10° 10&#x2032;), not on the mountain of <placeName>Santa Catalina</placeName>, but five<lb/>leagues more to the north, scarcely more than 4<formula notation="TeX">\frac{3}{4}</formula> English miles<lb/>from the coast.</p><lb/><p>East of the <placeName>Volcan de Papagayo</placeName> are three old burning<lb/>mountains, near the south shore of the <placeName>lake of Nicaragua</placeName>; viz.<lb/>the <placeName>Volcan de Orosi</placeName>, between <placeName>Rio Zabales</placeName> and <placeName>Rio Terluga</placeName>;<lb/>the <placeName>Volcan de Tenorio</placeName>; and the <placeName>Volcan del Rincon de la<lb/>Vieja</placeName>,&#x2014;the last of which is in lat. 10° 57&#x2032;, and only 1° 35&#x2032; west<lb/>of the mouth of the <placeName>Rio San Juan</placeName> in the <placeName>Atlantic Ocean</placeName>. The<lb/>great <placeName>crater-lake of Nicaragua</placeName> seems to me to have been<lb/>produced by some ph&#x00E6;nomenon connected with this peculiar<lb/>eastern site of the <placeName>Volcan de la Vieja</placeName>.</p><lb/><p>North of the <placeName>city of Nicaragua</placeName>, on the isthmus between the<lb/>Lake and the sea-coast, between 10° 30&#x2032; and 12° 30&#x2032; lat. some<lb/>uncertainty still prevails in the synonomy of the volcanos.<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Juarros</persName> the historiographer of <placeName>Guatemala</placeName>, and <placeName>Antonio de la<lb/>Cerda</placeName>, <placeName>Alcalde de la Ciudad de Granada</placeName>, whose manuscript<lb/>maps I possess, adduce merely; 1. <placeName>Volcan Mombacho</placeName>, on a<lb/>mountain a few leagues south-east of the <placeName>city of Grenada</placeName>;<lb/>2. <placeName>Volcan de Sapaloca</placeName>, in the <placeName>lake of Nicaragua</placeName>, opposite<lb/><placeName>Volcan de Mombacho</placeName>; 3. <placeName>Volcan de Masaya</placeName>, between <placeName>Ciudad<lb/>de Granada</placeName> and <placeName>Ciudad de Leon</placeName>, near the little <placeName>lake Masaya</placeName><lb/>west of the <placeName>Rio Tepetapa</placeName>, which connects the <placeName>Laguna de Leon<lb/>or Managua</placeName> with the <placeName>Laguna de Nicaragua</placeName>; 4. <placeName>Volcan de<lb/>Momotombo</placeName>, at the north end of <placeName>Laguna de Leon</placeName>, rather to<lb/>the east of <placeName>Ciudad de Leon</placeName>. According to this nomenclature,<lb/>the <placeName>Volcan de Granada</placeName>, of which <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Funnel</persName> and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Dampier</persName> speak,<lb/>describing it as being in the form of a beehive, is omitted in all<lb/>the Spanish sea-charts. From a passage in <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Gomara</persName> (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Historia<lb/>de las Indias</hi>, fol. 112</bibl>), it may be concluded that <placeName>Volcan de Ma-<lb/>saya</placeName> and <placeName>Volcan de Granada</placeName>, are synonymous. The chart of<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">Deposito Hydrografico</hi> mentions: 1. <placeName>Volcan de Bombacho</placeName>,<lb/>probably the <placeName>Mombacho</placeName> of the <placeName>
        </placeName>; 2. <placeName>Volcan<lb/>de Granada</placeName>, west of <placeName>Ciudad de Granada</placeName>; 3. <placeName>Volcan de Leon</placeName>,<lb/>clearly from its situation the celebrated <placeName>Volcan de Masaya</placeName>,<lb/>20&#x2032; south of <placeName>Ciudad de Leon</placeName>. I repeat that, in my opinion,<lb/>the mountain which in the Spanish charts is called <hi rendition="#i"><placeName>Volcan<lb/>de Granada</placeName></hi>, is either <placeName>Volcan Bombacho</placeName>, or <placeName>Volcan Masaya</placeName>,&#x2014;<lb/>for both lie in the neighbourhood (south and east) of <placeName>Ciudad<lb/>de Granada</placeName>. <placeName>Volcan Masaya</placeName>, situated nearer the village of<lb/><lb/><pb n="119" facs="#f0003" />
            <placeName>Nindiri</placeName> than the <placeName>village of Masaya</placeName>, was in the first ages of the<lb/>conquest of the country the most active of all the burning<lb/>mountains of <placeName>Guatemala</placeName>. &#x201C;The Spaniards,&#x201D; says <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Juarros</persName>,<lb/>&#x201C;called it Hell, <hi rendition="#i"><placeName>el Infierno de Masaya</placeName></hi>.&#x201D; Its crater was only from<lb/>twenty to thirty paces in diameter, but the melted lava seethed<lb/>and rolled in waves as high as towers; the light from it spread<lb/>very far, as well as its frightful bellowings. At the distance<lb/>of twenty-five miles the flames of <placeName>Masaya</placeName> were visible. This<lb/>volcano peculiarly allured the monks of the 16th century, in<lb/>their thirst for gold. A Dominican, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Blas de In&#x0303;ena</persName>, as <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Go-<lb/>mara</persName> relates, descended into the crater by a chain of 140 brazas<lb/>long, armed with an iron ladle; with the ladle he intended to<lb/>have taken up the gold in fusion (the fluid lava!); the ladle<lb/>melted, and the monk escaped with difficulty. The secondary<lb/>circumstances of this story are certainly fabulous; but it is<lb/>more than probable that <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">In&#x0303;ena</persName> ventured into the crater, and<lb/>that his unsuccessful enterprise induced the <hi rendition="#i">Dechan</hi> (dean) of<lb/>the spiritual Chapter of <placeName>Leon</placeName> to obtain permission from the<lb/>king to open the <placeName>volcano of Masaya</placeName>, and to collect the gold<lb/>which was hidden in its interior. Juarros speaks of another<lb/>volcano close to that of <placeName>Masaya</placeName>, the <placeName>volcano of Nindiri or<lb/>Nidiri</placeName>, which had a great eruption in 1775, when a stream of<lb/>lava (<hi rendition="#i">rio de fuego</hi>) flowed into <placeName>Laguna de Leon</placeName>, or <placeName>Managua</placeName>,<lb/>and destroyed a great many fish. From the situation of the<lb/><placeName>village of Nindiri</placeName> it may be supposed that this ph&#x00E6;nomenon<lb/>was an eruption from the side of the <placeName>Masaya</placeName>. In <placeName>Teneriffe</placeName><lb/>also I have often heard the <placeName>Volcano de Chahorra</placeName> spoken of<lb/>as if it was a different mountain from the Peak. It is very<lb/>common in all volcanic countries for the volcanos, properly so<lb/>called, to be confounded with the sites of minor eruptions from<lb/>their own sides. In travelling from the <placeName>Volcano de Masaya</placeName><lb/>along the <placeName>Laguna of Tiscapa</placeName> across <placeName>Nagaroti</placeName> to the <placeName>city of<lb/>Leon</placeName>, east of the city you see, at the north end of <placeName>Laguna<lb/>de Leon</placeName> or de <placeName>Managua</placeName>, the lofty volcano of <placeName>Momotombo</placeName>;<lb/>further down, between lat. 12° 20&#x2032; and 13° 15&#x2032;, or between the<lb/><placeName>city of Leon</placeName> and the <placeName>Gulf of Amapala</placeName> or <placeName>Fonseca</placeName>, appear the<lb/>four <placeName>volcanos of Felica</placeName>, the <placeName>Viejo</placeName>, <placeName>Giletepe</placeName>, and <placeName>Guanacaure</placeName>.<lb/>The <placeName>volcano of Felica</placeName> is still active, like <placeName>Mombacho</placeName> and <placeName>Mo-<lb/>motombo</placeName>: persons also who visited the harbour of <placeName>Rialejo</placeName><lb/>last year, saw the <placeName>Volcano del Viejo</placeName> smoking considerably.<lb/>The <placeName>volcano of Giletepe</placeName> is named in the Spanish manuscript<lb/>charts <hi rendition="#i"><placeName>V. de Cosiguina</placeName></hi>, from the neighbouring P<placeName>unta de Cosi-<lb/>guina</placeName>, as has been correctly conjectured by M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">von Buch</persName>.</p><lb/><p>West of the <placeName>Gulf of Amapala</placeName> rise, as it were from the same<lb/>cavernous bed, the volcanos of <placeName>San Miguel Bosotlan (Usulutan?)</placeName>,<lb/><placeName>Tecapa</placeName>, <placeName>San Vincente</placeName> or <placeName>Sacatecoluca</placeName>, <placeName>San Salvador</placeName>, <placeName>Isalco</placeName>,<lb/><lb/><pb n="120" facs="#f0004" />
                <placeName>Apaneca</placeName> or <placeName>Zonzonate</placeName>, <placeName>Pacaya</placeName>, the <placeName>Volcano de Agua</placeName>, the <placeName>two<lb/>volcanos de Fuego</placeName> or <placeName>Guatemala</placeName>, <placeName>Acatenango</placeName>, <placeName>Toliman</placeName>, <placeName>Atitlan</placeName>,<lb/><placeName>Tajamulco</placeName>, <placeName>Sunil</placeName>, <placeName>Suchiltepegues</placeName>, <placeName>Sopotitlan</placeName>, the <placeName>Hamilpas</placeName><lb/>(properly two contiguous volcanos of this name), and <placeName>Soconusco</placeName>.<lb/>Of these twenty burning mountains, those of <placeName>San Miguel</placeName>, <placeName>San<lb/>Vincente</placeName>, <placeName>Isalco</placeName>, <placeName>San Salvador</placeName>, <placeName>Pacaya</placeName>, the <placeName>Volcano de Fuego</placeName><lb/>or de <placeName>Guatemala</placeName>, <placeName>Atitlan</placeName>, and the <placeName>Volcano de Sapotitlan</placeName>, have<lb/>hitherto been the most active. The <placeName>volcano of Isalc</placeName>o had<lb/>great eruptions in April 1798, and from 1805 to 1807, when<lb/>the flames often came in sight. It is particularly rich in am-<lb/>monium <note place="foot" n="*">We believe that the theory of volcanos held by M. de Humboldt, is a<lb/>modification of that proposed by Sir <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">H. Davy</persName>, in which the ph&#x00E6;nomena<lb/>they present are ascribed to the decomposition of water by the metallic<lb/>bases of the earths and alkalies existing in the earth. We presume, there-<lb/>fore, that when he states the volcano here mentioned to be rich in am-<lb/>monium, it is to be understood that it evolves a large quantity of muriate<lb/>of ammonia, from which circumstance M. de Humboldt infers that <hi rendition="#i">ammo-<lb/>nium</hi>, the supposed metallic base of <hi rendition="#i">ammonia</hi>, is abundant in its interior.<lb/><hi rendition="#et"><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">E. W. B.</persName></hi></note>.</p><lb/><p>The <placeName>volcano of Pacay</placeName>a lies three miles from the village of<lb/><placeName>Amatitlan</placeName>, and consequently east of the <placeName>Volcano de Agua</placeName>.<lb/>It is not so isolated as the latter, but is prolonged into a vast<lb/>ridge with three apparent summits. Streams of lava (which<lb/>the inhabitants here as well as in <placeName>Mexico</placeName> call desert-land<lb/>(<hi rendition="#i">mal pays</hi>)<choice><sic></sic><corr type="editorial">)</corr></choice>, pumice, scori&#x00E6; and sand, have laid waste the sur-<lb/>rounding country. At the end of the sixteenth century (ac-<lb/>cording to the <bibl><hi rendition="#i"><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Cronista Fuentes</persName></hi>, tom. i. liv. 9. cap. 9.</bibl>) the<lb/><placeName>Pacaya</placeName> emitted day and night not only smoke but flames.<lb/>The greatest and most celebrated eruptions of the volcano of<lb/><placeName>Pacaya</placeName> were those of 1565, 1651, 1664, 1668, 1671, 1677,<lb/>and of the 11th of July 1775. The last eruption was not<lb/>from the summit itself, but from one of the three lower lateral<lb/>peaks.</p><lb/><p>The <bibl>Volcan de Fuego</bibl>, or as it is also called <placeName>Volcan de<lb/>Guatemala</placeName>, is situated five miles west of the water-volcano<lb/>and two miles south-west of the city of <placeName>Antigua Guatemala</placeName>.<lb/>It still at times evolves flame and smoke. Its greatest erup-<lb/>tions since the arrival of the Spaniards were in 1581, 1586,<lb/>1623, 1705, 1710, 1717, 1732, and 1737. It is in the shape of<lb/>a beautiful cone, near its top, however, disfigured by several<lb/>hills of scori&#x00E6;, the remains of lateral eruptions.</p><lb/><p>The order of succession in which the extinguished volcanos<lb/>arise south of <placeName>Laguna de Atitlan</placeName>, between <placeName>Nueva Guatemala</placeName><lb/>and <placeName>Zapotitlan</placeName>, seems to me, as a fact in geological science, very<lb/>remarkable. They stand on two chasms east and west, and<lb/>look as if they had slidden; so that the more western row lies<lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">four</fw><lb/><pb n="121" facs="#f0005" />
                    four leagues more to the north. On the eastern chasm are<lb/>the <placeName>volcanos of Pacaya</placeName>, the <placeName>Water-volcano</placeName>, the <placeName>two volcanos<lb/>of Fuego</placeName>, and the <placeName>volcano of Acatenango</placeName>; on the western,<lb/>nearer the <placeName>lake of Atitlan</placeName>, are the <placeName>volcanos of Toliman</placeName>, <placeName>Atit-<lb/>lan</placeName>, and <placeName>Sunil</placeName>, with several isolated mountains, the names of<lb/>which are unknown to me.</p><lb/><p>The <placeName>Water-volcano</placeName> (<hi rendition="#i"><placeName>Volcan de Agua</placeName></hi>) is, in comparison with<lb/>the twenty-one partly extinguished and partly still burning<lb/>volcanos of <placeName>Central America</placeName>, one of the highest and most ce-<lb/>lebrated. It lies twenty miles east of the <placeName>great Laguna de<lb/>Atitlan</placeName>, between <placeName>Antigua Guatemala</placeName> and the populous villages<lb/>of <placeName>Mixco Amatitan</placeName> and <placeName>San Christobal</placeName>. As the altitude<lb/>of not a single mountain of the <placeName>Guatemalan Andes</placeName> has been<lb/>measured, I draw my opinion of its height merely from the<lb/>circumstance that the mountain often remains covered for<lb/>many months together with rime, with ice, and perhaps even<lb/>with snow. In so southern a latitude the height cannot be<lb/>less than 11,000, nor above 15,000 English feet. Mountains<lb/>which exceed the latter are real <hi rendition="#i">Nevados</hi>, that is, covered with<lb/>eternal snow. Capt. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Basil Hall</persName> estimates the <placeName>two volcanos of<lb/>Guatemala</placeName> at 14,331 and 14,562 feet, an admeasurement taken<lb/>at the distance of forty leagues, and which cannot therefore<lb/>be much relied on. Pater <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Remesal</persName>, (<bibl><hi rendition="#i">Hist. de la Provincia de<lb/>San Vincente,</hi> liv. iv. cap. 5.</bibl>) who plays with numbers in the<lb/>old-fashioned way, asserts, that in 1615 the Water-volcano,<lb/>as it is called, was still three leagues (<hi rendition="#i">leguas</hi>) high, although<lb/>it lost its crown (<hi rendition="#i">coronilla</hi>), which was one league high, by the<lb/>eruption of the 11th of September 1541, when <placeName>Almolonga</placeName>, or<lb/><placeName>Ciudad Vieja</placeName>, was destroyed! The geognostic relations of<lb/>this water-eruption are wholly unknown. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Juarros</persName> relates,<lb/>that neither burnt stones nor any traces of volcanic eruptions<lb/>were discoverable in the declivity of the mountain; perhaps<lb/>however ashes and lava are covered by the vegetation; per-<lb/>haps not merely subterranean caverns have been filled for<lb/>centuries by rain-water which has flowed into them, but a<lb/>crater-lake also may have existed in the summit itself.</p><lb/><p>In the <placeName>province of Quito</placeName>, I have been told, that the volcano<lb/>of Imbabaru, which has been extinguished longest, near the<lb/><placeName>Villa de Ibarra</placeName>, from time to time (probably after earthquakes)<lb/>casts forth water, slime, and fishes; thus much, however, is<lb/>certain, that the <placeName>Volcano de Agua</placeName>, which lies between the<lb/><placeName>Volcano de Pacaya</placeName> and the <placeName>Volcano de Fuego</placeName>, has the form<lb/>of a blunted cone. Two-thirds of the slopes of this great<lb/>mountain-root, which is said to be eighteen leagues in diame-<lb/>ter, are cultivated as a garden; further upwards arise majestic<lb/>woods, and on the top there still exists an elliptical cavern,<lb/><lb/><pb n="122" facs="#f0006" />
                        the diameter of which from N. to S. is 400 feet long. This<lb/>is without doubt a crater (<hi rendition="#i">caldera</hi>); and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Juarros</persName>, although he<lb/>denies that there are any traces of fire in the water-volcano,<lb/>describes (tom. ii. p. 351) it himself exactly as several intelli-<lb/>gent natives of <placeName>Guatemala</placeName> have described it to me.</p><lb/><p>North of the group of the volcanos closely ranged between<lb/><placeName>Pacaya</placeName> and <placeName>Sunil</placeName>, at the western extremity of the <placeName>lake of<lb/>Atitlan</placeName>, the heat-exhaling cavern of <placeName>Central America</placeName> seems<lb/>gradually to close. The <placeName>volcano of Soconusco</placeName>, of which<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Juarros</persName> makes no mention (in <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Bauza</persName>&#x2019;s chart, 15° 59&#x2032; lat., and<lb/>95° 41&#x2032; long.</bibl>), is the limit imposed to the series of volcanic<lb/>eruptions on the western edge of the granitic-gneiss <placeName>mountain<lb/>of Oaxada</placeName>: on the shore of the <placeName>South Sea</placeName> there is no volcano<lb/>for 220 leagues till you arrive at the <placeName>Volcan de Colonia</placeName>. After<lb/>having named, in these pages, between the parallels of 8° 50&#x2032;<lb/>and 16°, in a direction from S. E. to N. W., five-and-thirty<lb/>conical mountains, which are considered on the spot as vol-<lb/>canos, and of which fifteen have undoubtedly emitted smoke<lb/>or flames within the last half century, I may safely repeat my<lb/>assertion,&#x2014;that in no part of the globe, not even in <placeName>Chili</placeName>, or<lb/>the <placeName>Indian Archipelago</placeName> and the <placeName><choice><sic>Alentes</sic><corr type="editorial">Aleutes</corr></choice></placeName>, is there so lasting a<lb/>communication by means of caverns between the interior of<lb/>the earth and the atmosphere. Future travellers will ascer-<lb/>tain which among the thirty-five so-called <hi rendition="#i"><placeName>Volcanes de Centro-<lb/>America</placeName></hi> are cones of trachyte, and which are real open<lb/>burning mountains.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
