<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="323" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">Account of the Discovery of a Mine of Plati-<lb/>num in <placeName>Columbia</placeName>, and of Mines of Gold and of Platinum<lb/>in the <placeName>Uralian Mountains</placeName>.</hi><note place="foot" n="*">We have taken this interesting Notice from <bibl><hi rendition="#i">Le Globe,</hi> No. 90, <date>July<lb/>20, 1826</date></bibl>.</note> By Baron <hi rendition="#k">Alexander de<lb/>Humboldt.</hi></head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k"><hi rendition="#in">A</hi>t</hi> a meeting of the Academy of Sciences of <placeName>Paris</placeName>, held on<lb/>the 18th July last, Baron Humboldt communicated verbally<lb/>to the academy the following interesting information.</p><lb/><p>M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Boussingault</persName>, a celebrated French chemist, has just dis-<lb/>covered a mine of platinum at <placeName>Antioquia</placeName> in the <placeName>department of<lb/>Cundinamarca</placeName>. Hitherto this precious metal, so valuable in<lb/>the arts, had only been found in the <placeName>Uralian Mountains</placeName> in<lb/><placeName>Russia</placeName>, in <placeName>Brazil</placeName>, and in the provinces of <placeName>Choco</placeName> and <placeName>Barba-<lb/>coas</placeName>, on the coasts of the <placeName>South Sea</placeName>, but always in alluvial<lb/>lands, where it could only be met with accidentally. As this<lb/>circumstance renders the discovery of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Boussingault</persName> much<lb/>more interesting, M. Humboldt has been anxious to establish<lb/>it. He observes, that in all lands where platinum has been<lb/>discovered, there are found at a very great depth the trunks<lb/>of trees well preserved. It cannot, therefore, be supposed,<lb/>that, in this case, transplanted earth has been mistaken for<lb/>real rocks decomposed <hi rendition="#i">in situ.</hi> With regard to the platinum<lb/>found in the <placeName>province of Antioquia</placeName> by M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Boussingault</persName>, there<lb/>can be no doubt that this metal exists there in real veins in<lb/>the <placeName>valley <hi rendition="#i">de Osos</hi></placeName>, and it is sufficient to pound the materials<lb/>which these veins contain, in order to obtain from them, by<lb/>washing, the gold and the platinum which they contain.</p><lb/><p>M. Humboldt had not himself visited the country where M.<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Boussingault</persName> has discovered the platinum and gold; but ex-<lb/>perience has proved to him that almost all the auriferous<lb/>soils of <placeName>America</placeName> belong to the formation of Dyorite and Sye-<lb/>nite, and it is in this formation that M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Boussingault</persName> has dis-<lb/>covered the platinum mixed with gold. The <placeName>valley <hi rendition="#i">de Osos</hi></placeName>,<lb/>where the platinum occurs in veins, being very near the <placeName>pro-<lb/>vince of Choco</placeName>, from which it is separated only by a branch<lb/>of the <placeName>Cordillera of the Andes</placeName>, this circumstance accounts for<lb/><pb n="324" facs="#f0002" />
the presence of the same metal in the alluvial soils of the <placeName>val-<lb/>ley <hi rendition="#i">de Osos</hi></placeName>.</p><lb/><p>M. Humboldt announced at the same time, that mines of<lb/>platinum had recently been found in the <placeName>Uralian Mountains</placeName>,<lb/>in the <placeName>government of Perma</placeName>. These mines are so rich that<lb/>the price of platinum fell nearly one-third at <placeName>St Petersburg</placeName>.<lb/>Hence we may reasonably expect that this valuable metal<lb/>will cease to bear that high price at which it has hitherto been<lb/>sold. In 1824, the auriferous and platiniferous soil of the<lb/>Ural produced 286 <hi rendition="#i">puds</hi>, which gave 5700 kilogrammes of<lb/>metal, having a value of nineteen millions 500,000 francs.<lb/>The mines of all <placeName>Europe</placeName> together do not produce annually<lb/>more than 1300 kilogrammes. Those of <placeName>Chili</placeName> yield only<lb/>3000, and all <placeName>Columbia</placeName> furnishes only 5000.</p><lb/><p>The <placeName>Ural</placeName> yields at present as much gold as was ever ob-<lb/>tained from <placeName>Brazil</placeName> at the time when its mines were most pro-<lb/>ductive. The maximum, which took place in 1755, was 6000<lb/>kilogrammes of gold. At present <placeName>Brazil</placeName> yields only 1000.</p><lb/><p>It would be reasonable to suppose, that this prodigious in-<lb/>crease in the productiveness of the mines of the <placeName>Ural</placeName> might<lb/>have a very important influence, not only on the prosperity of<lb/><placeName>Russia</placeName>, but on the real value of gold. But this opinion can-<lb/>not be maintained, if we attend to the circumstance, that the<lb/>quantity of this metal actually existing on the surface of the<lb/>globe is so considerable, that a quantity eighteen millions of<lb/>francs in value, is, comparatively, almost insensible; and, be-<lb/>sides, that the diminution of the produce of almost all the<lb/>mines of the <placeName>New World</placeName> would occasion a compensation.<lb/>Relatively to the particular prosperity of <placeName>Russia</placeName>, an augmen-<lb/>tation of eighteen millions is, in reality, very little for a state<lb/>of such vast extent, particularly as nearly one-third of this<lb/>must be expended in working the mines.</p><lb/><p>Nothing, besides, is more variable than the product of<lb/>mines. Those of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, which in 1700 furnished only six<lb/>millions of piastres in gold and silver, produced twenty-five<lb/>millions in 1809; and this immense augmentation was un-<lb/>known in <placeName>Europe</placeName>, (where it had not produced any sensible re-<lb/>sult,) when M. Humboldt announced it a long time after it<lb/>had taken place. The revenue of <placeName>Mexico</placeName> has since that time<lb/><pb n="325" facs="#f0003" />
kept at nearly eighteen millions of piastres, without any effect<lb/>being produced on the price of commodities.</p><lb/><p>With regard to platinum the case is quite different. As<lb/>the quantity of this metal, which has only been worked for a<lb/>short time, is still very inconsiderable, an increase in the pro-<lb/>duce of the mines which furnish it may bring down greatly<lb/>its price,&#x2014;a result which will be extremely fortunate for the<lb/>useful arts.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
