<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="306" facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">mines of platinum.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb/>
                <p>At a meeting of the Academy of Sciences of Paris, held on<lb/>the 18th July last, Baron Humboldt communicated verbally<lb/>to the Academy the following interesting information.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>M. Boussingault, a celebrated French chemist, has just dis-<lb/>covered a mine of platinum at Antioquia in the department of<lb/>Cundinamarca. Hitherto this precious metal, so valuable in<lb/>the arts, had only been found in the Urals in Russia, in Bra-<lb/>zil, and in the provinces of Choco and Barbacoas, on the<lb/>coasts of the South Sea, but always in alluvial lands. As this<lb/>circumstance renders the discovery of M. Boussingault much<lb/>more interesting, M. Humboldt has been anxious to establish<lb/>it. He observes, that in all lands where platinum has been<lb/>discovered, there are found at a very great depth the trunks<lb/>of trees well preserved. It cannot, therefore, be supposed,<lb/>that, in this case, transplanted earth has been mistaken for<lb/>real rocks decomposed <hi rendition="#i">in situ.</hi> With regard to the platinum<lb/>found in the province of Antioquia by M. Boussingault, there<lb/>can be no doubt that this metal exists there in real veins in<lb/>the valley <hi rendition="#i">de Osos,</hi> and it is sufficient to pound the materials<lb/>which these veins contain, in order to obtain from them, by<lb/>washing, the gold and the platinum which they contain.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>M. Humboldt had not himself visited the country where<lb/>M. Boussingault has discovered the platinum and gold; but<lb/>experience has proved to him that almost all the auriferous<lb/>soils of America belong to the formation of diorite and sye-<lb/>nite, and it is in this formation that M. Boussingault has dis-<lb/>covered the platinum mixed with gold. The valley <hi rendition="#i">de Osos,</hi>
                    <lb/>where the platinum occurs in veins, being very near the pro-<lb/>vince of Choco, from which it is separated only by a branch<lb/>of the Cordillera of the Andes: this circumstance accounts for<lb/>the presence of the same metal in the alluvial soils of the val-<lb/>ley <hi rendition="#i">de Osos.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb/>
                <p>M. Humboldt announced at the same time, that mines of<lb/>platinum had recently been found in the Uralian Mountains,<lb/>in the government of Perma. These mines are so rich that<lb/>the price of platinum fell nearly one-third at St. Petersburg.<lb/>Hence we may reasonably expect that this valuable metal<lb/>will cease to bear that high price at which it has hitherto been<lb/>sold. In 1824, the auriferous and platiniferous soil of the<lb/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">Ural</fw>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="307" facs="#f0002" /> Ural produced 286 <hi rendition="#i">puds,</hi> which gave 5700 kilogrammes of<lb/>metal, having a value of nineteen millions 500,000 francs.<lb/>The mines of all Europe together do not produce annually<lb/>more than 1300 kilogrammes. Those of Chili yield only<lb/>3000, and all Columbia furnishes only 5000.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The Ural yields at present as much gold as was ever ob-<lb/>tained from Brazil at the time when its mines were most pro-<lb/>ductive. The maximum, which took place in 1755, was 6000<lb/>kilogrammes of gold. At present Brazil yields only 1000.&#x2014;<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Brewster&#x2019;s Journal.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>