<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On the Principal Causes of the Differences of Temperature on the Globe</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:01</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.81</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1827-Ueber_die_Hauptursachen-2</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1827-Ueber_die_Hauptursachen-1.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1827-Ueber_die_Hauptursachen-2.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1827-Ueber_die_Hauptursachen-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1827-Ueber_die_Hauptursachen-4.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1827-Ueber_die_Hauptursachen-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1827-Ueber_die_Hauptursachen-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1827-Ueber_die_Hauptursachen-7-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1827-Ueber_die_Hauptursachen-8-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On the Principal Causes of the Differences of Temperature on the Globe</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1828</date>
          <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal&lt;/i&gt; (Januar–März 1828), S. 329–346.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="329" facs="#f0001"/>
            <lb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#i">On the Principal Causes of the Difference of Temperature
                        on<lb/>the Globe.</hi> By Baron <hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von
                        Humboldt.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">Extract from a public Lecture delivered in the Royal
                        Academy at <placeName>Berlin</placeName>,<lb/>on the <date>3d of July 1827.</date></note></head>
                <lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#k"><hi rendition="#in">T</hi>he</hi> distribution of heat over
                    the globe, has for many years<lb/>formed one of the principal objects of my
                    researches. This sub-<lb/>ject is intimately connected with the local
                    differences of the pro-<lb/>ductions of nature, with the agriculture and the
                    commercial in-<lb/>tercourse of nations, and even, in several respects, with
                    their mo-<lb/>ral and political situation. The time is past when we were
                    satis-<lb/>fied with some undefined views on the difference of
                    geographical<lb/>and physical climates, and when all the modifications of
                    tempera-<lb/>ture were ascribed either to the shelter afforded by ridges
                    of<lb/>mountains, or to the various elevations of the surface of the<lb/>earth.
                    We have seen, that the remarkable differences of<lb/>climates which we perceive
                    in large tracts of country, under the<lb/>same latitude, and on the same level
                    above the surface of the<lb/>sea, do not arise from the trifling influence of
                    individual locali-<lb/>ties, but that they are subject to general laws,
                    determined by the<lb/>form of the continents in general, by their outlines, by
                    the state<lb/>of their surface, but particularly by their respective
                    positions,<lb/>and the proportion of their size, to the neighbouring seas.
                        The<lb/><pb n="330" facs="#f0002"/> relative position of the transparent and
                    opaque, of the fluid or<lb/>solid parts of the earth, modifies the absorption of
                    the solar rays<lb/>falling under the same angles, and at the same time the
                    produc-<lb/>tion of heat. These circumstances, the winter cover of ice
                    and<lb/>snow, which is peculiar to the continents, and to a very small<lb/>part
                    only of the seas; the slowness with which large masses of wa-<lb/>ter are heated
                    and cooled; the radiation from smooth or rough<lb/>surfaces, towards a cloudless
                    sky; the regular currents of the<lb/>ocean and of the atmosphere, by which water
                    and air from dif-<lb/>ferent latitudes and different depths and heights are
                    mixed; all<lb/>concur to produce the peculiarities of climate. It may
                    therefore<lb/>be said, that every place has a double climate, one depending
                    on<lb/>general and remote causes, on the general position and shape of<lb/>the
                    continents, and another determined by the peculiar relations<lb/>of its
                    locality.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Since the problem of the geographical distribution of heat has<lb/>been
                    considered upon general principles, meteorological ob-<lb/>servations have been
                    conducted in a more efficient manner.<lb/>A smaller number of them now lead to
                    certain results; and<lb/>the discoveries made within the last twenty years, in
                    the most<lb/>remote parts of the globe, have gradually enlarged the point<lb/>of
                    view. Physical and geological inquiries have now become<lb/>equally important
                    objects of all extensive voyages and tra-<lb/>vels. To begin with the extreme
                    north, I shall here, in the<lb/>first place, mention a man, whom the dangerous
                    and trouble-<lb/>some occupations of whale-fishing, which were the object of
                    his<lb/>voyage, have not prevented from carrying on the most
                    refined<lb/>meteorological and zoological observations. Captain
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Scoresby</persName><lb/>has, for the first time, determined the mean atmospheric
                    tem-<lb/>perature of the Polar Seas, which he has taken between the<lb/>volcanic
                    <placeName>Island of Jan Mayen</placeName>, and that part of <placeName>East Greenland</placeName><lb/>discovered by himself.
                    In endeavouring to discover a north-<lb/>west passage, the English government
                    has succeeded in affording<lb/>to geography, to climatology, and to the theory
                    of magnetism,<lb/>services which were originally promised to the commercial
                    inte-<lb/>rest of nations. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Parry</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Sabine</persName>, and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Franklin</persName> have, for
                    several<lb/>years, been employed in investigating the temperature of the
                    at-<lb/>mosphere, and of the sea, in the polar regions; they have
                    pene-<lb/>rated to <placeName>Port Bowen</placeName> and <placeName>Melville&#x2019;s Island</placeName>, consequently nearly
                        to<lb/><pb n="331" facs="#f0003"/> 75° N. Lat.; and they have, in this
                    arduous task, displayed a<lb/>perseverance, of which we find hardly a parallel
                    instance in the<lb/>history of human exertions and struggles against the
                    elements.<lb/>Captain <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Weddell</persName> has recently destroyed the ancient
                    prejudice,<lb/>sanctioned by <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Cook&#x2019;s</persName> illustrious name, that the <placeName>South Pole</placeName>
                    is, on<lb/>account of a more extended mass of ice, less accessible than
                    the<lb/><placeName>North Pole</placeName>. The discovery of a new archipelago to the SSE.<lb/>of <placeName>Terra
                        del Fuego</placeName>, has led to an expedition in which Captain<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Weddell</persName> found a sea
                    completely free from ice, under the 74°<lb/>Lat. (far beyond two solitary
                    islands discovered by the Russian<lb/>Captain <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Billinghausen</persName>.)</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In turning to the temperate zone, we find a great many points<lb/>where the
                    average temperature, which hitherto was considered to<lb/>be invariable, has
                    been measured. Various astronomers in <placeName>New<lb/>Holland</placeName>, and on the foot of the
                    <placeName>Indian Himalaya</placeName>, Catholic and<lb/>Protestant missionaries at <placeName>Macao</placeName>, in <placeName>Van
                    Diemen&#x2019;s Land</placeName>, and in<lb/>the <placeName>Sandwich Islands</placeName>, have furnished us with
                    new facts towards<lb/>comparing the northern and southern, the eastern and
                    western<lb/>hemispheres, in the torrid and temperate zones,
                    consequently<lb/>those parts of the globe which are most abundant in water,
                    as<lb/>well as those which are most abundant in land. In the same<lb/>manner,
                    the proportion of heat under the line, and in both the<lb/>tropics, has been
                    determined. These points, as ascertained in<lb/>numbers, are particularly
                    important as fixed points, because they<lb/>may, like the zone of the warmest
                    sea-water, (between 84° and<lb/>87° Fah.; 23° and 24° 5&#x2032; R.), in future
                    ages serve to determine<lb/>the much disputed variability of the temperature of
                    our planet.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>It is necessary to mention here, that we have been long in<lb/>want of
                    climatological determinations in the most southern parts<lb/>of the temperate
                    zones, between the 28° and 30° lat. This part<lb/>of the world forms as it were
                    an intermediate link between the<lb/>climate of <placeName>Palms</placeName>, and that region in which,
                    according to the<lb/>tradition of the east, mankind, along the Mediterranean,
                    in<lb/><placeName>Asia Minor</placeName>, and <placeName>Persia</placeName>, first awoke to intellectual develope-<lb/>ment,
                    to mild manners, and to taste in the cultivation of the<lb/>arts. The
                    observations of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Niebuhr</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Nouet</persName>, and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Coutel</persName> in<lb/><placeName>Egypt</placeName>, those of my unfortunate
                    friend Ritchie in the <placeName>Oasis of<lb/>Murzuk</placeName>, could, on account of local
                    circumstances, only lead to<lb/><pb n="332" facs="#f0004"/> erroneous results.
                    The large and classical work on the <placeName>Canary<lb/>Islands</placeName>, for which we are
                    indebted to Mr <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Leopold Von Buch</persName>,<lb/>has now also filled up this blank, in the
                    same way as his travels<lb/>in <placeName>Lapland</placeName> and to the most northern promontory of
                    <placeName>Europe</placeName>,<lb/>first furnished us with a clear illustration of the causes
                    which,<lb/>in the <placeName>Scandinavian peninsula</placeName>, beyond the polar circle,
                    diminish<lb/>the severity of the winter cold, and preserve to the springs
                    the<lb/>temperature which they had received from deeply seated strata,<lb/>and
                    which occasion, under the influence of a continental climate<lb/>and that of the
                    coast, an unequal elevation of the snow line, and<lb/>of the upper limit at
                    which different species of trees grow.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>If we follow the current of the sea, which traverses the<lb/>great valley of the
                    <placeName>Atlantic Ocean</placeName>, from east to west, we find<lb/>almost unexpectedly rich sources
                    of instruction in the <placeName>New<lb/>World</placeName>, from <placeName>Russian America</placeName>, and the settlements
                    of the<lb/>Canadian hunters, to the <placeName>River La Plata</placeName>, and the most
                    southern<lb/>parts of <placeName>Chili</placeName>. It is no longer foreign naturalists who
                    commu-<lb/>nicate to us the notices they have been able to collect during
                    a<lb/>short residence in plains, rich in wood and grass, and on
                    the<lb/>ice-covered ridges of the <placeName>Cordillera</placeName>; we have no longer need
                    to<lb/>judge of the mean temperature of the whole year by that of<lb/>single
                    months or weeks; here we obtain every where solid and<lb/>complete information
                    from the inhabitants themselves.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The executive power of the <placeName>United States of North America</placeName><lb/>has ordered
                    meteorological observations for five years to be made<lb/>three times a day, at
                    seventeen different points, occupied by mi-<lb/>litary garrisons, between the
                    28° and 47° lat., between the <placeName>Mis-<lb/>souri</placeName> and the <placeName>Alleghanys</placeName>, the <placeName>lake
                    Michigan</placeName>, and the <placeName>coast of Pen-<lb/>sacola</placeName>; and from these observations, the
                    average temperature of<lb/>days, months, and of the whole year, is drawn. These
                    obser-<lb/>vations calculated by Mr <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Lovell</persName>, surgeon-general of the
                    army,<lb/>have been published at the expense of the American govern-<lb/>ment,
                    and have been distributed to all scientific institutions in<lb/><placeName>Europe</placeName>. If this
                    excellent example was followed in the eastern<lb/>part of our continent, and if,
                    by the command and at the ex-<lb/>pence of a powerful monarch, similar
                    comparative theometrical<lb/>observations were carried on in well selected
                    points in the ex-<lb/>tensive district situated between the <placeName>Vistula</placeName> and the
                    <placeName>Lena</placeName>, the<lb/><pb n="333" facs="#f0005"/> whole science of climate would in a
                    few years appear in a new<lb/>and much improved form.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The zeal by which the <placeName>United States of North America</placeName> are<lb/>animated, has arisen
                    equally strong in the lately emancipated<lb/><placeName>Spanish America</placeName>. Journals, printed
                    9,000 feet above the level<lb/>of the sea, give daily the height of the
                    thermometer, barometer,<lb/>and hygrometer, taken with very exact instruments,
                    made at<lb/><placeName>Paris</placeName> and <placeName>London</placeName>, in the enormous extent from the 28° N. to<lb/>the
                    40° S. lat. Thus the political revolution of these countries<lb/>has not only
                    improved their own condition and the industry of<lb/><placeName>Europe</placeName>, but it will also,
                    when the population increases, and<lb/>scientific knowledge spreads, over so
                    many mountains and ele-<lb/>vated plains, lead to a better knowledge of the
                    higher regions of<lb/>the atmosphere. In those countries, whole provinces rise
                    like<lb/>islands in an ocean of air, to the height of <placeName>Etna</placeName>, or the <placeName>Peak<lb/>of
                    Teneriffe</placeName>: in the old continent, where the travelling natu-<lb/>ralist erects
                    his tent near the line of permanent snow, populous<lb/>towns are found in
                    <placeName>America</placeName>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In modern times <placeName>Africa</placeName>, which the ancients represented upon<lb/>coins and
                    monuments as the kingdom of palms, has been found<lb/>rather deficient in this
                    tribe of trees; and, in the same manner,<lb/>later travellers have modified in a
                    singular manner the be-<lb/>lief in the constant uniform tropical heat of the
                    <placeName>African de-<lb/>serts</placeName>. In the <placeName>Oasis of Murzuk</placeName> in <placeName>Fezzan</placeName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Ritchie</persName> and
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Lyon</persName><lb/>found, during several summer months, the thermometer in the<lb/>shade,
                    at from 5 to 6 feet above the ground, to indicate 86° to 91°<lb/>Fahr. (24° to
                    26° R.), at 5 o&#x2019;clock in the morning, and from<lb/>118° to 129° Fahr.
                    (38° to 43° R.) at noon, a temperature which<lb/>probably arose from the
                    radiation produced by the sand floating<lb/>in the air; and, in the same place,
                    Dr <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Oudney</persName> died of cold in<lb/>the end of December. This spot is situated in the
                    centre of <placeName>Af-<lb/>rica</placeName>, on the frontiers of <placeName>Bornou</placeName>, under the 13th degree of
                    lat., and,<lb/>according to barometrical measurement is not 1200 feet above
                    the<lb/>level of the sea<choice><sic>,</sic><corr type="editorial">.</corr></choice> It is said that the water in the leather
                    bottles,<lb/>which <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Oudney&#x2019;s</persName> caravan carried along with them, was frozen
                    this<lb/>same night. But Major <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Denham</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Clapperton&#x2019;s</persName> companion,<lb/>whom I
                    desired, after his return from the <placeName>lake Tchad</placeName>, to give me<lb/>some oral
                    explanation, told me, that, in the morning, some hours<lb/><pb n="334"
                        facs="#f0006"/> after Dr <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Oudney&#x2019;s</persName> death, the temperature of the air
                    was not be-<lb/>low 49° Fahr. (7<formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{2}</formula>° R.). In <placeName>South America</placeName>, at a less
                    distance<lb/>from the equator, near <placeName>Bogota</placeName> and <placeName>Quito</placeName>, I saw the water
                    free<lb/>from ice, at the height of 8500 and 9000 feet, notwithstanding<lb/>the
                    strong effect of the radiation of high plains in producing cold.<lb/>In the
                    manuscripts of young <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Beaufort</persName>, who died lately in<lb/><placeName>Upper Senegal</placeName>, a victim to
                    scientific zeal, I find that under<lb/>the 16th degree of latitude, the
                    thermometer marked in the<lb/>shade on the same day 113° Fahr. (36° R.) at noon,
                    and 59°<lb/>Fahr. (12° R.) early in the morning. The temperature of<lb/>the air
                    in the plains of <placeName>America</placeName> never sinks so low in the same<lb/>northern latitude.
                    In laying before the Academy last year,<lb/>a detailed account of the excellent
                    labours of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Ehrenberg</persName> and<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Hemperich</persName>, I have already mentioned the cold to
                    which these<lb/>learned travellers were exposed, when in the <placeName>Desert of
                    Dongola</placeName><lb/>under the 19th degree of latitude. North winds penetrated
                    into<lb/>this southern tropical country, and, in December, the thermo-<lb/>meter
                    sunk to 38° Fahr. (2° 5&#x2032; R.) above the freezing point, con-<lb/>sequently
                    12° of R. lower than it had ever been observed, under<lb/>the same latitude, in
                    the <placeName>West Indies</placeName>, according to the accounts<lb/>carefully collected by myself. It
                    is astonishing to find <placeName>Africa</placeName><lb/>in its deserts colder than <placeName>America</placeName>, with all
                    its rich vegetation,<lb/>and this not on the margin of the tropics, but at the
                    very centre<lb/>of them. The true causes of this singular cooling
                    process<lb/>have not yet been sufficiently explained. Perhaps it is the
                    ra-<lb/>diation of heat from the soil through the dry air towards a
                    cloud-<lb/>less sky, or a sudden expansion produced by the pouring of<lb/>humid
                    strata into this dry air, and the descent of the upper<lb/>parts of the
                    atmosphere.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>It is generally known that more than two-thirds of our planet<lb/>are covered by
                    a body of water, which, by its contact with the at-<lb/>mosphere, exercises the
                    most powerful influence upon the climate<lb/>of the continents. The rays from
                    the sun produce heat according<lb/>to different laws, as they fall either upon
                    the water or upon the<lb/>solid surface of the earth. The mobility of the
                    particles of<lb/>which we imagine fluid bodies to be composed, produces
                    cur-<lb/>rents and an unequal distribution of temperature; cooled and
                    con-<lb/>densed by radiation, the particles of water sink to the bottom.<lb/>By
                    ascending in balloons, climbing upon insulated peaks of<lb/><pb n="335"
                        facs="#f0007"/> mountains, by thermoscopic apparatus sunk into the sea, it
                    has<lb/>been possible to determine the velocity of the cooling process<lb/>which
                    takes place at different seasons, from below upwards, in the<lb/>atmosphere, and
                    from above downwards, in the occean, and in<lb/>fresh water lakes. The animals,
                    therefore, which dwell in both<lb/>these elements, find on each point of the
                    globe, in the aeriform<lb/>and liquid elements, the most heterogeneous climates,
                    placed in<lb/>strata one above another. In the depth of the sea, under the
                    Line,<lb/>and in <placeName>alpine lakes</placeName> of the temperate zone, there is always a
                    fixed<lb/>degree of cold, viz. that degree at which the water attains
                    the<lb/>greatest density. The experiments of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Ellis</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Forster</persName> and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Saus-<lb/>sure</persName>,
                    have been repeated under all zones and in all depths; but<lb/>what we know of
                    the lowest temperature of the air, and of sea-<lb/>water, as well as of the
                    greatest effect of the radiation of heat be-<lb/>tween the tropics, serves as an
                    infallible proof that the cold<lb/>which there exists near the bottom of the
                    sea, is produced by a<lb/>current which, in the depths of the ocean, passes from
                    the poles<lb/>towards the equator, and cools the inferior strata of water in
                    the<lb/>southern ocean, like the current of air in the upper
                    atmosphere,<lb/>which moves from the equator to the poles, to temper the
                    cold<lb/>of the winter in the northern regions.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The immortal <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Benjamin Franklin</persName> first taught us that sand-<lb/>banks are sooner
                    recognised by the thermometer than by the<lb/>sounding line. They are islands of
                    the submarine land, which<lb/>the elastic subterranean powers had not been able
                    to elevate<lb/>above the surface of the water. On the declivity of the
                    shoals,<lb/>the inferior and colder strata ascending by impulse, are
                    mixed<lb/>with the upper and warmer ones; and thus the sudden cold of<lb/>the
                    sea-water shews to the navigator that danger is near. The<lb/>shallows, by their
                    temperature, act on the air above them, in<lb/>which they produce fogs and
                    groups of clouds, which are per-<lb/>ceived at a great distance.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Before more extensive investigations had been made on the<lb/>distribution of
                    heat over the globe, it was believed that the cli-<lb/>mate of two places could
                    be determined by the extremes of the<lb/>temperature in summer and winter. This
                    view of things has<lb/>still been preserved in popular opinion, whilst
                    naturalists have<lb/>long ago renounced it as erroneous; for, although
                    undoubtedly<lb/>the extremes of single days and nights are in a certain
                        propor-<lb/><pb n="336" facs="#f0008"/> tion to the mean temperature of the
                    year, yet the distribution of<lb/>heat in the different seasons is strikingly
                    different, although<lb/>the mean annual temperature be one and the
                    same,&#x2014;a circum-<lb/>stance which has a very great influence on the growth
                    of plants<lb/>and on the health of man. I have endeavoured to determine<lb/>the
                    law of this distribution, according to different situations<lb/>and heights. But
                    comparative results in numbers ought to con-<lb/>tain the mean temperature of
                    every month, derived from the<lb/>two extremes of every day, supposing an
                    arithmetical series to<lb/>be formed. This method was first adopted by <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Reaumur</persName>
                    in<lb/>1735: he compared the produce of two harvests, not (like <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Her-<lb/>schel</persName>)
                    with the numbers and size of the spots in the sun, but<lb/>with the quantity of
                    heat which the corn received in the time of<lb/>vegetation. Many labours have of
                    late been directed towards as-<lb/>certaining the hour, the mean temperature of
                    which expresses<lb/>also that of the whole year. I here only mention the
                    observa-<lb/>tions carried on in <placeName>Scotland</placeName> at <placeName>Leith Fort</placeName>. The night watch<lb/>of
                    a military post has been employed for establishing observa-<lb/>tions of the
                    thermometer during two years, from hour to hour;<lb/>and from the mass of these
                    observations, which ought to be re-<lb/>peated in other latitudes, it has been
                    calculated, that, in the la-<lb/>titude of <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>, a single daily observation
                    at 9 o&#x2019;clock 13<lb/>minutes in the morning, and in the evening at 8
                    o&#x2019;clock 29 mi-<lb/>nutes, would be sufficient to fix the average heat of
                    the year <note place="foot" n="*">A result, which does not differ from the true
                        by one-half degree of<lb/>Reaumur&#x2019;s thermometer, is also obtained by
                        the mean of two hours of<lb/>the same denomination.&#x2014;<bibl><hi
                            rendition="#i">Results of the Thermometrical Observations made
                            at<lb/>Leith Fort every hour of the day and night during the years</hi>
                        1824 <hi rendition="#i">and</hi> 1825, p. 19.</bibl></note>.<lb/>Of the months, it
                    is April and October which give this important<lb/>result (a fact, first
                    discovered by <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Leopold von Buch</persName>, which<lb/>is connected with remarkable
                    modifications of the upper currents<lb/>of the atmosphere), except when, as in
                    the island of <placeName>Grand Ca-<lb/>nary</placeName>, local causes carry the maximum of heat to a
                    later period,<lb/>and place it in October.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>If I frequently allude to the great increase of meteorological<lb/>observations
                    within the last twenty years, I by no means wish<lb/>to express an opinion that
                    the perfection of climatology is parti-<lb/>cularly founded on such an increase.
                    Here, as in all collec-<lb/>tions of knowledge derived from experiments, which
                    are too<lb/>soon denominated sciences, every thing depends on &#x201C;an
                        accu-<lb/><pb n="337" facs="#f0009"/> rate conception of nature,&#x201D; and
                    a just view of the conse-<lb/>quences to be drawn from well-arranged facts. If
                    we attempt to<lb/>conceive the problem of the distribution of temperature in
                    its<lb/>most general sense, we may imagine the planetary heat either (as<lb/>in
                    the present oxydised, hardened surface of the earth) to be a<lb/>consequence of
                    the position in relation to a central body, which<lb/>excites heat; or (as in
                    the first state of the condensation of matter<lb/>dissolved in the form of
                    vapour) the consequence of internal<lb/>processes of oxidation, precipitation,
                    change of capacity, or elec-<lb/>tro-magnetic currents. Many geognostical
                    phenomena, which<lb/>I have mentioned in another paper, seem to indicate such a
                    de-<lb/>velopement of internal heat, produced by our planet itself.
                    More-<lb/>over, the doubts raised against the peculiar heat in mines in<lb/>both
                    parts of the world, have been entirely removed by recent<lb/>experiments of an
                    ingenious astronomer M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Arago</persName>, on water<lb/>rising up through deep borings in
                    what are called <placeName>Artesian Wells</placeName>.<lb/>The greater the depth from which the water
                    ascends, the warmer<lb/>it has been found. In this case, there can be no
                    suspicion of<lb/>strata of air sinking down and being condensed, and
                    consequent-<lb/>ly disengaging heat; nor can the neighbourhood of men, or of
                    the<lb/>lanterns of miners, exercise an influence in this case. The
                    waters<lb/>carry along with them the heat which they have acquired by a<lb/>long
                    continued contact with rocky masses at different depths.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>These important observations shew how, independently of the<lb/>obliquity of the
                    ecliptic in the earliest, and, as it were, youthful<lb/>state of our planet, the
                    tropical temperature and tropical vege-<lb/>tation could arise under every zone,
                    and continue, till, by the<lb/>radiation of heat from the hardened surface of
                    the earth, and by<lb/>the gradual filling up of the veins with heterogeneous
                    minerals<lb/>a state was formed, in which (as <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Fourier</persName> has shewn in a
                    pro-<lb/>found mathematical work) the heat of the surface, and of
                    the<lb/>atmosphere, depends merely upon the position of the planet to-<lb/>wards
                    a central body, the sun. We gladly resign to other na-<lb/>tural philosophers
                    the task to decide, how deep below the oxi-<lb/>dised and hardened surface of
                    the earth the melted fluid masses<lb/>lie, which are poured out through the
                    apertures of volcanoes,<lb/>which periodically agitate the continents and the
                    bottom of the<lb/>ocean, and force hot mineral springs upwards through clefts
                    in<lb/>granite and porphyry. The depth of our mines is too inconsi-<lb/><pb
                        n="338" facs="#f0010"/> derable to enable us, from the unequal increase of
                    temperature<lb/>which has been hitherto observed in them, to give the
                    satisfac-<lb/>tory numerical solution of a problem which occupies the
                    cu-<lb/>riosity of men who live, as it were, upon a vault of rocks.
                    Suf-<lb/>fice it here to point out how the recent views of geologists
                    have<lb/>revived the old mythus of Pyroplegeton and of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Hephastos</persName>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>When a planet is everywhere surrounded by a&#x00EB;rial strata,<lb/>and when the
                    oxidised surface of the earth, with its clefts<lb/>almost everywhere closed or
                    filled up, by a long radiation<lb/>of heat, has arrived at a state of
                    equilibrium between receiving<lb/>and losing, in such a manner that its external
                    temperature and<lb/>the difference of climates arise solely from its position
                    towards<lb/>the sun, towards a larger central body which is perpetually
                    ge-<lb/>nerating light, then the problem of the temperature of any place<lb/>in
                    its most general form, may be considered as dependent solely<lb/>upon the manner
                    in which the influence of the meridian height<lb/>of the sun manifests itself.
                    This height determines, at the same<lb/>time, the magnitude of the semidiurnal
                    circles, the density of<lb/>the a&#x00EB;rial strata, through which the rays of
                    the sun pass, before<lb/>they arrive at the horizon; it also determines the
                    quantity of the<lb/>absorbed or calorific rays (a quantity which rapidly
                    increases<lb/>with the size of the angle of incidence); and, lastly, the
                    number<lb/>of the rays of the sun, which, mathematically considered, a
                    given<lb/>horizon receives. The production of heat, as far as a greater
                    or<lb/>less is concerned, can accordingly be considered as proceeding<lb/>from
                    the illuminated surface of the earth. The absorption<lb/>which the rays of the
                    sun undergo in their passage through the<lb/>atmosphere, or (to express it in
                    another manner) the production<lb/>of heat by the diminution of light is
                    extremely small; but never-<lb/>theless is perceptible on the ocean, where, at a
                    great distance<lb/>from the coast, and even when the water was colder than
                    the<lb/>atmosphere, I observed the temperature of the latter increasing
                    at<lb/>noon with the height of the sun <note place="foot" n="*">Mr <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Arago</persName> has
                        first called my attention to this remarkable effect of the<lb/>absorption of
                        light in the atmosphere.&#x2014;<bibl>Con. des Tems pour 1828, p. 225</bibl>.</note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Recent researches <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;"><bibl>Essai Politique sur
                        l&#x2019;Isle de Cuba, 1826, t. ii. p. 79-92</bibl>. where I think<lb/>I have
                    obviated the doubts raised by Mr <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Atkinson</persName>.&#x2014;<bibl>Mem. of the
                        Astron.<lb/>Soc. vol. ii. p. 137, 137.</bibl></note> have shewn, that, in both
                        continents,<lb/><pb n="339" facs="#f0011"/> under the equator, where the
                    mean temperature rises to 82°<lb/>Fahr. (22°.2 R.) it is not much warmer than it
                    is in 10°<lb/>north and south latitude. According to the Commentary
                    of<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Geminus</persName> on the Astronomical Poem of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Aratus</persName> <note place="foot" n="*"><bibl>Esig.
                        in Aratum eays. 13. Strabo, Geogr. lib. ii. p. 97</bibl>.</note>, some
                    Greek<lb/>philosophers believed the temperature of the tropics even to
                    sur-<lb/>pass that of the equator. M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Arago</persName> has, in a very ingenious<lb/>manner,
                    demonstrated, by numerous optical experiments, that,<lb/>from the vertical
                    incidence to a zenith distance of 20°, the quan-<lb/>tity of the reflected light
                    (and the lesser heating of the illumi-<lb/>nated body depends on this quantity),
                    remains almost the<lb/>same. In comparing the mean annual temperatures with
                    one<lb/>another, I find, that, in the western part of the old continent,
                    the<lb/>temperatures diminish from the south towards the north in
                    the<lb/>following proportion <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">In the eastern
                        parts of the new continent, the diminutions of the mean<lb/>temperature are
                        as follows:<lb/><table>
                            <row>
                                <cell>From</cell>
                                <cell>20° to 30°</cell>
                                <cell>Latitude,</cell>
                                <cell>5°</cell>
                                <cell>Reaum.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <lb/>
                            <row>
                                <cell></cell>
                                <cell>30 40</cell>
                                <cell></cell>
                                <cell>5 .7</cell>
                                <cell></cell>
                            </row>
                            <lb/>
                            <row>
                                <cell></cell>
                                <cell>40 50</cell>
                                <cell></cell>
                                <cell>7 .2</cell>
                                <cell></cell>
                            </row>
                            <lb/>
                            <row>
                                <cell></cell>
                                <cell>50 60</cell>
                                <cell></cell>
                                <cell>5 .8</cell>
                                <cell></cell>
                            </row>
                        </table></note>:</p>
                <lb/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>From</cell>
                        <cell>20° to 30°</cell>
                        <cell> north Latitude.</cell>
                        <cell>3°.2</cell>
                        <cell>Reaum.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb/>
                    <row>
                        <cell></cell>
                        <cell>30 40</cell>
                        <cell></cell>
                        <cell>3 .6</cell>
                        <cell></cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb/>
                    <row>
                        <cell></cell>
                        <cell>40 50</cell>
                        <cell></cell>
                        <cell>5 .7</cell>
                        <cell></cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb/>
                    <row>
                        <cell></cell>
                        <cell>50 60</cell>
                        <cell></cell>
                        <cell>4 .4</cell>
                        <cell></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb/>
                <p>In both the continents, the region where the diminution of heat<lb/>is most
                    rapid, is to be found between 40° and 45° latitude. In<lb/>this result, the
                    observation agrees in a remarkable manner with<lb/>the theory; for the variation
                    of the square of the cosines which<lb/>expresses the law of the mean
                    temperature, is largest at 45° lati-<lb/>tude. This circumstance, as I have
                    shown in another place, has<lb/>exercised a very beneficial influence on the
                    state of civilisation<lb/>of those nations who live in the mild countries, under
                    this, the<lb/>medium parallel of latitude. There the district where the
                    vine<lb/>grows, borders upon that of the olive and orange tree. No-<lb/>where
                    else upon earth (in proceeding from the north to the<lb/>south) does the heat
                    increase more rapidly with the geographi-<lb/>cal latitude; nowhere else do the
                    various vegetable productions,<lb/>used in gardening and in agriculture, succeed
                    each other more<lb/><pb n="340" facs="#f0012"/> rapidly. This variety animates
                    industry and the commercial<lb/>intercourse of nations.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>We may here state that partial, daily, and monthly changes<lb/>of temperature
                    are, on account of the motion of the atmosphere,<lb/>produced by the
                    transportation of colder or warmer strata, by<lb/>greater or less electric
                    tension, by the formation of clouds or the<lb/>diffusion of vapours; in short,
                    by an almost infinite number of va-<lb/>riable causes, acting at a greater or
                    smaller distance. The study<lb/>of meteorology has, unfortunately, begun in a
                    zone where the<lb/>causes are most complicated, and the number and intensity of
                    the<lb/>disturbing powers greatest. If ever civilization, as may now
                    be<lb/>expected, shall establish one of its principal seats in the tropics,
                    it<lb/>is to be presumed that these phenomena, which are so simple<lb/>there,
                    will be more easily ascertained than in our climates, where<lb/>the play of many
                    conflicting causes has so long concealed them<lb/>from our view. From that which
                    is simple it is easy to proceed to<lb/>what is complicated, and we may imagine a
                    scientific meteorolo-<lb/>gy as returning from the tropics to the north. In the
                    climate<lb/>of palms, a feeble east wind always brings strata of air
                    along<lb/>with it, having generally the same temperature. The
                    barometer<lb/>shows, like the progress of the needle, the hour of the
                    day.<lb/>Earthquakes, tempests, and thunder-storms do not disturb the<lb/>small
                    but periodical tides of the atmosphere. The changed decli-<lb/>nation of the
                    sun, together with the upper currents of the air,<lb/>from the equator towards
                    the pole, modified by this declina-<lb/>tion, determine the beginning of the
                    rainy season and the elec-<lb/>tric explosions, which both begin at regular
                    periods. The tra-<lb/>veller may know his way almost as well by the direction of
                    the<lb/>clouds as by the compass; and, in the dry season, the appear-<lb/>ance
                    of a cloud on the deep blue sky would, in many districts of<lb/>the tropics,
                    astonish the natives as much as the fall of an a&#x00EB;ro-<lb/>lite or of the
                    red polar snow would do us; or as the crash of<lb/>thunder in <placeName>Peru</placeName>; or, in the
                    tropical plains, a hail storm. This<lb/>simplicity and regularity in the
                    meteorological phenomena allow<lb/>us to expect an easier and more favourable
                    insight into the re-<lb/>lation of their causes.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>As long as the observations on the magnetic inclination, de-<lb/>clination and
                    intensity of forces, remained dispersed in the re-<lb/>ports of travellers, and
                    had not been united by magnetical lines,<lb/><pb n="341" facs="#f0013"/> the
                    doctrine of the distribution of magnetism on the earth could<lb/>not be expected
                    to make any important progress. Supported by<lb/>analogy, it has been attempted
                    to simplify by a careful employ-<lb/>ment of well ascertained facts, the
                    complicated doctrine of the<lb/>distribution of heat. Places having an equal
                    mean temperature<lb/>of the year, of summer, or of winter, have been connected
                    with<lb/>one another by curves. This was the origin of the system
                    of<lb/>isothermal lines <note place="foot" n="*"><bibl>De la Distribution de la
                        Chaleur sur le Globe</bibl>.&#x2014;<bibl>Mem. de la Société<lb/>d&#x2019;Arcueil, t.
                        iii.</bibl></note>, of which I published a full account in the<lb/>year 1817. They
                    descend towards the equator, because in<lb/><placeName>Eastern Asia</placeName> and the eastern parts
                    of <placeName>North America</placeName> we find,<lb/>on an equal level above the sea, and in a more
                    southern lati-<lb/>tude, the same temperature which we meet with in the
                    <placeName>centre<lb/>of Europe</placeName>, in a more northern latitude. The remarkable
                    cir-<lb/>cumstance, that the highest civilization of the species to which<lb/>we
                    belong has developed itself, almost under the same latitudes<lb/>in the
                    temperate zone upon two opposite coasts, the eastern<lb/>coast of the new and
                    the western of the old continent, must<lb/>early call our attention to the
                    difference of heat under the same<lb/>latitudes. The question arose by how many
                    thermometrical de-<lb/>grees the old world was warmer than the new, and it is
                    not<lb/>long since it was known, that the isothermal lines from the
                    la-<lb/>titude of <placeName>Florida</placeName> to that of <placeName>Labrador</placeName>, do not run parallel, and<lb/>that
                    the eastern and western coasts of <placeName>North America</placeName> are al-<lb/>most as different
                    from one another as those of <placeName>Western Eu-<lb/>rope</placeName> and of <placeName>Eastern Asia</placeName>. The shape
                    and grouping of<lb/>the continents, and their relation to the neighbouring
                    seas,<lb/>are the principal causes which determine the inflection of
                    the<lb/>isothermal lines, or the direction of equally warm zones, into<lb/>which
                    we may conceive the whole globe to be divided. The<lb/>predominance of west
                    winds in the temperate and cold re-<lb/>gions determines the difference of
                    climates on the eastern and<lb/>western coasts of one and the same continent.
                    The western<lb/>winds, which are considered as reactions of the tropical
                    trade-<lb/>winds reach an eastern coast, after having traversed in winter<lb/>a
                    continent covered with snow and ice; to the western coasts,<lb/>on the contrary
                    (in <placeName>Europe</placeName> as well as in <placeName>New California</placeName> and<lb/><pb n="342" facs="#f0014"/>
                    <placeName>Nootka</placeName>), western winds carry strata of air, which even in<lb/>the severest
                    winter have been heated by contact with the vast<lb/>surface of the ocean. Led
                    by these ideas, I have considered it<lb/>of importance to obtain a knowledge of
                    the lowest temperature<lb/>to which the <placeName>Atlantic</placeName> sinks, out of the <placeName>Gulf Stream</placeName>,
                    between<lb/>40° and 50° north latitude (consequently in the latitudes<lb/>of
                    <placeName>Spain</placeName>, <placeName>France</placeName> and <placeName>Germany</placeName>). I have found that, in the<lb/>month of January, in
                    40° latitude, the water of the sea does not<lb/>sink below 56° Fahr. (10°.7 R.)
                    and in 45° latitude not below<lb/>54° Fahr. (9°.8 R.) The much esteemed
                    geographer of <placeName>India</placeName>.<lb/>Major <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Rennel</persName>, who for thirty years has been employed in
                    study-<lb/>ing the direction of the currents of the <placeName>Atlantic</placeName>, and who,
                    during<lb/>my last visit to <placeName>England</placeName>, communicated to me a part of his
                    ma-<lb/>nuscript materials, has, in 50° latitude, consequently in the
                    zone<lb/>of the <placeName>north of Germany</placeName>, observed in winter a temperature of<lb/>the
                    sea-water, to which the atmosphere does not reach in the<lb/>month of January,
                    even in the mild climate of <placeName>Marseilles</placeName>. If<lb/>the relative extent of <placeName>Asia</placeName> and
                    <placeName>North America</placeName>, of the <placeName>Pacific</placeName><lb/>and the <placeName>Northern Atlantic</placeName>, was different from
                    what it is, the<lb/>whole system of winds in the northern hemisphere, would,
                    by<lb/>the unequal heating of the solid, as well as of the fluid, parts<lb/>of
                    the surface of the earth, be changed in their direction as well<lb/>as in their
                    intensity.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p><placeName>Europe</placeName> is indebted for its milder climate to its position on the<lb/>globe (the
                    position in which it stands in regard to the neighbour-<lb/>ing seas) and to its
                    peculiar form. <placeName>Europe</placeName> is the western part<lb/>of the old continent; and
                    consequently the great <placeName>Atlantic Ocean</placeName>,<lb/>which already in itself has the power
                    of diminishing the cold, and<lb/>which is besides partly warmed by the <placeName>Gulf
                    Stream</placeName>, lies to the<lb/>west of it. That part of the world which of all others
                    enjoys<lb/>the greatest share of a tropical climate, the sandy <placeName>Africa</placeName>, is
                    so<lb/>situate that <placeName>Europe</placeName> is heated by the strata of air, which,
                    as-<lb/>cending from <placeName>Africa</placeName>, move from the Equator towards the <placeName>North<lb/>Pole</placeName>.
                    Had the Mediterranean not existed, the influence of <placeName>Af-<lb/>rica</placeName> on the
                    temperature and the geographical distribution of<lb/>plants and animals in
                    <placeName>Europe</placeName>, would have been still more consi-<lb/>derable. The third principal cause
                    of the milder climate of <placeName>Eu-<lb/>rope</placeName> is, that this part of the world does not
                    approach the <placeName>North<lb/><pb n="343" facs="#f0015"/> Pole</placeName> nearly as much as
                    <placeName>America</placeName> and <placeName>Asia</placeName> do; and that, on the<lb/>contrary, it lies opposite the
                    greatest extent of sea-water, free from<lb/>ice, which is known in the whole
                    polar zone. The coldest points<lb/>of the earth, which have lately been
                    improperly called Poles of<lb/>Cold, do not coincide with the magnetic poles, as
                    Dr <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Brewster</persName> has<lb/>endeavoured to prove <bibl>in the English version of my paper on
                        the<lb/>Isothermal Lines</bibl>. According to Captain <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Sabine&#x2019;s</persName>
                    researches,<lb/>the minimum of the annual mean temperature on the surface
                    of<lb/>the earth, is to the NW. of <placeName>Melville&#x2019;s Island</placeName>, in the meridian
                    of<lb/><placeName>Behring&#x2019;s Straits</placeName>, probably in 82° to 83° north Lat. The
                    sum-<lb/>mer boundary of the ice, which, between Spitzbergen and
                    <placeName>East<lb/>Greenland</placeName>, recedes to 80° and 81° north Lat., is in about 75°<lb/>N.
                    Lat., every where between <placeName>Nova Zembla</placeName>, the <placeName>Bone Islands</placeName> of<lb/><placeName>New Siberia</placeName> and
                    <placeName>Icey Cape</placeName>, the most western cape of <placeName>America</placeName>.<lb/>Even the winter boundary of
                    ice, the line on which the ice ap-<lb/>proaches the nearest to our continent,
                    scarcely surrounds <placeName>Bear<lb/>Island</placeName>. From the <placeName>North Cape</placeName>, which is heated by a
                    south-<lb/>western current of the sea, the navigation to the most
                    southern<lb/>promontory of <placeName>Spitzbergen</placeName> is never interrupted, not even in
                    the<lb/>most severe winters. The polar ice diminishes in quantity<lb/>wherever
                    it finds an opening to flow out, as in <placeName>Baffin&#x2019;s Bay</placeName>, and<lb/>between
                    <placeName>Iceland</placeName> and <placeName>Spitzbergen</placeName>. The situation of the <placeName>Atlan-<lb/>tic Ocean</placeName> exerts a most
                    beneficial influence on the existence of<lb/>that sea-water, free from ice, in
                    the meridian of <placeName>East Green-<lb/>land</placeName> and <placeName>Spitzbergen</placeName>, which has so important an
                    influence upon<lb/>the climate of the north of <placeName>Europe</placeName>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>On the other hand, the icebergs, which are driven from <placeName>Baf-<lb/>fin&#x2019;s Bay</placeName>
                    and <placeName>Barrow&#x2019;s Straits</placeName> to the south, accumulate in that<lb/>large <hi
                        rendition="#i">mediterranean</hi> sea, which geographers designate by
                    the<lb/>name of <placeName>Hudson&#x2019;s Bay</placeName>. This accumulation of ice increases
                    the<lb/>cold of the neighbouring continent so much, that, as reported<lb/>by
                    Captain <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Franklin</persName> in his latest MS., in <placeName>York Factory</placeName>, and<lb/>at the mouth of
                    <placeName>Hayes River</placeName>, which lie in the same latitudes<lb/>as the north of <placeName>Prussia</placeName> and
                    <placeName>Courland</placeName>, in digging wells, ice is<lb/>found everywhere at the depth of four
                    feet. The most northern<lb/>and most southern boundaries of the fixed polar ice,
                    that is, the<lb/>summer and winter boundaries, on the situation of which
                    the<lb/>temperature of the northern continents depends, seem to have<lb/>changed
                    but little, as far as historical records go; which fact<lb/><pb n="344"
                        facs="#f0016"/> has been recently confirmed by careful inquiries. The
                    in-<lb/>jurious influence which small isolated masses of ice,
                    driven<lb/>sometimes by currents into the neighbourhood of the
                    <placeName>Azores</placeName>,<lb/>exercise, as it is said, upon the continent of <placeName>Europe</placeName>, is one
                    of<lb/>those tales, first derived from philosophers, and received by
                    the<lb/>vulgar, after the former have long ceased to believe in them.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In the same latitudes, where, in the north of <placeName>Europe</placeName>, agri-<lb/>culture and
                    gardening are carried on, we find in <placeName>North<lb/>America</placeName> and <placeName>North Asia</placeName> only
                    marshes and tracts of land co-<lb/>vered with mosses: in the interior of <placeName>Asia</placeName>,
                    on the other hand,<lb/>the powerful radiation of heat, between the almost
                    parallel<lb/>chains of the <placeName>Himalaya</placeName>, the <hi rendition="#i">Zungling</hi> and
                    the <hi rendition="#i">Himmelsgebirge</hi>,<lb/>(a country on which
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Klaproth&#x2019;s</persName> geographical researches have<lb/>thrown great light),
                    exercises the most beneficial influence on<lb/>the Asiatic population. The line
                    of permanent snow, on the<lb/>northern declivity of the <placeName>Himalaya</placeName>, lies 4000 feet
                    higher than<lb/>on the southern; and the physical explanation which I
                    have<lb/>given of this singular phenomenon <note place="foot" n="*"><bibl>Annales de
                        Chimie et de Physique, tom. iii. p. 297</bibl>; <bibl>tom. ix. p. 310</bibl>; <bibl>tom.<lb/>xiv. p.
                            5.</bibl></note>, has, according to a report<lb/>of Mr <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Colebrooke</persName>, been confirmed
                    by recent measurements and<lb/>observations in the <placeName>East Indies</placeName>. Millions of men
                    of Thibetian<lb/>origin, of a gloomy religious cast of mind, occupy
                    populous<lb/>towns, in a country where fields and towns would, during
                    the<lb/>whole year, be buried in deep snow, if this high table-land was<lb/>less
                    extensive and less continuous.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>As the currents of the atmosphere are modified in many dif-<lb/>ferent manners,
                    by changes in the declination of the sun, and<lb/>by the direction of the chains
                    of mountains on the declivities of<lb/>which they descend, the currents, also,
                    of the liquid ocean<lb/>carry the warmer waters of the lower degrees of latitude
                    into<lb/>the temperate zone. I need not here mention how the waters<lb/>of the
                    <placeName>Atlantic</placeName>, always moved in the same direction by the<lb/>trade-winds, are carried
                    against the dike formed by the <placeName>isthmus<lb/>of Nicaragua</placeName>, then turn to the north,
                    make the round of the<lb/><placeName>Gulf of Mexico</placeName>, flow out through the <placeName>Channel of the
                    Bahamas</placeName>,<lb/>proceed as a current of warm water to the north-east
                    towards<lb/>the banks of <placeName>Newfoundland</placeName>, then to the south-east, towards
                    the<lb/>group of the <placeName>Azores</placeName>; and, when favoured by the north-west<lb/><pb
                        n="345" facs="#f0017"/> wind, carry along with them the fruits of palm trees
                    from the <placeName>An-<lb/>tilles</placeName>; casks of French wines from wrecked ships; nay, even
                    living<lb/>Esquimaux in their leather boats from <placeName>East Greenland</placeName>, which<lb/>they
                    cast on the coasts of <placeName>Ireland</placeName>, of the <placeName>Hebrides</placeName>, or of <placeName>Nor-<lb/>way</placeName>. A travelled
                    astronomer, Captain <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Sabine</persName>, who, after re-<lb/>turning from the Polar Regions,
                    performed experiments with<lb/>the pendulum in the <placeName>Gulf of Guinea</placeName>, on the
                    <placeName>African Island of<lb/>St Thomas</placeName>, informed me, how casks of palm oil, which
                    had<lb/>been lost by shipwreck at <placeName>Cape Lopez</placeName>, a little south of the<lb/><placeName>Equator</placeName>,
                    were carried onwards, first by the equatorial current,<lb/>and then by the <placeName>Gulf
                    Stream</placeName>, crossing the Atlantic twice, from<lb/>east to west, and from west to
                    east, between 3° and 50° N. Lat.,<lb/>safely arrived on the coasts of <placeName>Scotland</placeName>.
                    The well preserved<lb/>mark of the African proprietors left no doubt as to the
                    direc-<lb/>tion the casks had taken. In the same manner, as in this
                    case,<lb/>the equatorial waters in the <placeName>Atlantic</placeName> are carried north by
                    the<lb/><placeName>Gulf Stream</placeName>, I have, in the <placeName>Pacific</placeName>, in its southern
                    hemisphere,<lb/>observed a current (along the coasts of <placeName>Chili</placeName> and <placeName>Peru</placeName>),
                    which<lb/>carries colder water from higher latitudes to the Tropics. In<lb/>this
                    current I saw the thermometer, in the port of <placeName>Truxillo</placeName>, in<lb/>the month of
                    September, fall to 61° Fahr. (12°.8 R.) and in the<lb/>port of <placeName>Callao</placeName>, near
                    <placeName>Lima</placeName>, at the end of November, to 60°<lb/>Fahr. (12°.4 R.) A distinguished young
                    officer of the Danish<lb/>navy, Baron <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Dirckinck von Holmfeldt</persName>, has, at my
                    request, at<lb/>different seasons of the year 1825, observed this singular
                    phe-<lb/>nomenon, to which for so long a time no attention had been<lb/>paid.
                    Making use of thermometers, carefully compared by Mr<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Gay Lussac</persName> and myself,
                    he again found the water of the sea, in<lb/>the <placeName>port of Callao</placeName>, in August
                    60<formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{2}</formula>° Fahr. (12°.6 R.) and in March<lb/>67<formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{2}</formula>° Fahr. (15°.7 R.)
                    Whilst, out of the current, at the pro-<lb/>montory of <placeName>Parina</placeName>, the <placeName>calm sea</placeName>, as
                    usually in those latitudes,<lb/>showed the great heat of 79<formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{2}</formula>° to 81°.5
                    (21° to 22° R.) We<lb/>cannot, in this place, explain how this stream of colder
                    water,<lb/>which increases the difficulty of the southern navigation
                    from<lb/><placeName>Guayaquil</placeName> to <placeName>Peru</placeName>, and from <placeName>Peru</placeName> to <placeName>Chili</placeName>, is for some
                    months<lb/>modified in its temperature by the <placeName>Garua</placeName>, <hi rendition="#i">i.
                        e.</hi> the vapours which<lb/>constantly veil the sun; and how it renders
                    the climate of the<lb/>plains of <placeName>Peru</placeName> cooler.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>As all human attempts to arrive at a scientific view of the<lb/><pb n="346"
                        facs="#f0018"/> phenomena of nature can have for their final object only a
                    clear<lb/>conception of our own nature, thus the investigation, with
                    the<lb/>principal topics of which we have now been occupied, at last
                    leads<lb/>us to consider, how the differences of climate manifest
                    themselves<lb/>in the character, in the civilization, and, perhaps, even in
                    the<lb/>development of the language of different tribes of the human<lb/>race.
                    This is the point where the important doctrine of the dis-<lb/>tribution of heat
                    over the globe comes to be connected with the<lb/>history of mankind, and beyond
                    which it ceases to be an ob-<lb/>ject of purely physical inquiry.</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>

    </text>
</TEI>
