<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Alexander Humboldt on Negro Slavery</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:01</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.82</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1827-Voyage_aux_regions-3-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1827-Voyage_aux_regions-1-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1827-Voyage_aux_regions-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1827-Voyage_aux_regions-3-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent, during the Years 1799–1804&lt;/i&gt;, übersetzt von Williams, 7 Bände, London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, Brown / Colburn 1814–1829, Band 7, 1829, S. 260–262, S. 103–104, S. 263–267, S. 269–271, S. 280–284.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Relation historique du Voyage aux Régions équinoxiales du Nouveau Continent&lt;/i&gt;, 3 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell 1814[–1817], N. Maze 1819[–1821], J. Smith et Gide Fils 1825[–1831], Band 3, 1825[–1831], S. 446–447, S. 389, S. 447–449, S. 450–451, S. 456–458.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Alexander Humboldt on Negro Slavery</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1831</date>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Friend. A Religious and Literary Journal&lt;/i&gt; 4:19 (19. Februar 1831), S. [145]–146; 4:20 (26. Februar 1831), S. [153].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Schmuck: Trennzeichen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="145" facs="#f0001" />
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>For &#x201C;The Friend.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>ALEXANDER HUMBOLDT ON<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#b">NEGRO SLAVERY.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The seventh volume of Humboldt&#x2019;s Personal<lb break="yes"/>Narrative of his travels in Spanish America,<lb break="yes"/>which has recently appeared, is chiefly devoted<lb break="yes"/>to an examination of the statistics and geo-<lb break="no"/>graphy of Cuba and the West Indies. The<lb break="yes"/>question of negro slavery is one of the objects<lb break="yes"/>of his investigation, and the views of this cele-<lb break="no"/>brated philosopher respecting it, are in a high<lb break="yes"/>degree interesting. They are marked with the<lb break="yes"/>same accuracy and minuteness of detail, by the<lb break="yes"/>same comprehensive thought, elevated wisdom,<lb break="yes"/>and severe impartiality, which distinguish his<lb break="yes"/>other writings. I had observed, says he, &#x201C;the<lb break="yes"/>condition of the blacks in countries where the<lb break="yes"/>laws, the religion, and the national habits, tend<lb break="yes"/>to soften their fate; yet I preserved, on quitting<lb break="yes"/>America, the same horror of slavery which I<lb break="yes"/>had felt in Europe. It is in vain, that writers<lb break="yes"/>of ability, in order to veil barbarous institutions,<lb break="yes"/>by ingenious fictions of language, have invented<lb break="yes"/>the terms of <hi rendition="#i">negro peasants of the West Indies,<lb break="yes"/>black vassalage,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">patriarchal protection:</hi> it<lb break="yes"/>is to profane the noble qualities of the mind<lb break="yes"/>and the imagination, to exculpate, by illusory<lb break="yes"/>comparisons, or captious sophisms, excesses<lb break="yes"/>that afflict humanity, and for which they pre-<lb break="no"/>pare violent commotions. Do they think they<lb break="yes"/>have acquired the right of dispensing with<lb break="yes"/>commiseration, by comparing the state of the<lb break="yes"/>blacks with that of the serfs of the middle ages,<lb break="yes"/>and with that state of oppression under which<lb break="yes"/>some classes still groan in the north and east<lb break="yes"/>of Europe? Those comparisons, those artifices<lb break="yes"/>of language, that disdainful impatience, with<lb break="yes"/>which even a hope of the gradual abolition of<lb break="yes"/>slavery is repulsed as chimerical, <hi rendition="#i">are useless<lb break="yes"/>arms in the times in which we live.</hi> The great<lb break="yes"/>revolutions which the continent of America<lb break="yes"/>and the archipelago of the West Indies have<lb break="yes"/>undergone, since the commencement of the<lb break="yes"/>nineteenth century, have acted upon the ideas<lb break="yes"/>and the public reason, even in countries where<lb break="yes"/>slavery exists and begins to be modified. Many<lb break="yes"/>wise men, deeply interested in the tranquillity<lb break="yes"/>of the sugar and slave islands, feel that, by a<lb break="yes"/>liberal agreement of the proprietors, and by<lb break="yes"/>measures taken by those who know the locali-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/> ties, they might emerge from a state of crisis<lb break="yes"/>and uneasiness, of which <hi rendition="#i">indolence</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">obsti-<lb break="no"/>nacy will augment the danger.</hi>&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;If the legislation of the West Indies and<lb break="yes"/>the state of the men of colour does not shortly<lb break="yes"/>undergo a salutary change; if the legislation<lb break="yes"/>continues to discuss instead of acting, the poli-<lb break="no"/>tical preponderance will pass into the hands of<lb break="yes"/>those who have strength to labour, the will to<lb break="yes"/>be free, and the courage to endure long priva-<lb break="no"/>tions. This sanguinary catastrophe will take<lb break="yes"/>place as a necessary consequence of circum-<lb break="no"/>stances, without the intervention of the free<lb break="yes"/>blacks of Hayti, and without their abandoning<lb break="yes"/>the system of insulation, which they have<lb break="yes"/>hitherto followed. Who would venture to pre-<lb break="no"/>dict the influence which may be exerted by<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;<hi rendition="#i">an African confederation of the free states of<lb break="yes"/>the West Indies,</hi> placed between Colombia,<lb break="yes"/>North America and Guatimala, on the politics<lb break="yes"/>of the new world?&#x2019; The fear of this event may<lb break="yes"/>act more powerfully on the minds of many, than<lb break="yes"/>the principles of humanity and justice; but in<lb break="yes"/>every island, the whites believe that their power<lb break="yes"/>is not to be shaken. All simultaneous action<lb break="yes"/>on the part of the blacks appears to them im-<lb break="no"/>possible; and every change, every concession<lb break="yes"/>granted to the black population, a sign of weak-<lb break="no"/>ness. Nothing presses: the horrible catastrophe<lb break="yes"/>of Saint Domingo was only the effect of the ina-<lb break="no"/>bility of governors. Such are the illusions that<lb break="yes"/>prevail amidst the great mass of the proprietors<lb break="yes"/>and planters of the West Indies, and which are<lb break="yes"/>alike opposed to an amelioration of the state of<lb break="yes"/>the blacks in Georgia and in the Carolinas.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Slavery is no doubt the greatest of all the<lb break="yes"/>evils that afflict humanity, whether we consider<lb break="yes"/>the slave torn from his family in his native<lb break="yes"/>country, and thrown into the hold of a slave<lb break="yes"/>ship, or as making part of a flock of black men,<lb break="yes"/>parked on the soil of the West Indies; but for<lb break="yes"/>individuals there are degrees of suffering and<lb break="yes"/>privation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;What a distance between a slave who<lb break="yes"/>serves in the house of a rich man at the Havan-<lb break="no"/>na or Kingston, or who works for himself,<lb break="yes"/>giving his master but a daily retribution, and a<lb break="yes"/>slave attached to a sugar estate. The threats<lb break="yes"/>which are used to correct an obstinate negro,<lb break="yes"/>develope this scale of human privations. The<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">calessero</hi> is menaced with the <hi rendition="#i">cafetal,</hi> so the<lb break="yes"/>slave who works at the <hi rendition="#i">cafetal</hi> is menaced with<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">sugar fabric.</hi> The black who has a wife,<lb break="yes"/>who inhabits a separate hut, who, affectionate as<lb break="yes"/>are the Africans for the most part, finds, after<lb break="yes"/>his labour, that some care is taken of him<lb break="yes"/>amidst his indigent family, has a fate not to be<lb break="yes"/>compared with that of the insulated slave lost<lb break="yes"/>in the mass. This diversity of condition escapes<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> those who have not had the spectacle of the<lb break="yes"/>West Indies before their eyes. The progressive<lb break="yes"/>amelioration of the state even of the captive<lb break="yes"/>caste, explains that in the island of Cuba the<lb break="yes"/>luxury of their masters and the possibility of<lb break="yes"/>gain by their work, have drawn more than<lb break="yes"/>eighty thousand slaves towards the towns; and<lb break="yes"/>how the manumission of them, favoured by<lb break="yes"/>the wisdom of the laws, is become so active as<lb break="yes"/>to have produced, fixing on the present period,<lb break="yes"/>(1827) more than 130,000 free men of colour.<lb break="yes"/>It is in discussing the individual position of each<lb break="yes"/>class, in recompensing, by the decreasing scale<lb break="yes"/>of privations, the intelligence, the love of labour,<lb break="yes"/>and the domestic virtues, that the colonial ad-<lb break="no"/>ministration will find the means of ameliorating<lb break="yes"/>the fate of the blacks. Philanthropy does not<lb break="yes"/>consist in giving &#x2018;a little more salt fish and<lb break="yes"/>some strokes of the whip less;&#x2019; a real ame-<lb break="no"/>lioration of the captive caste, ought to extend<lb break="yes"/>over the whole moral and physical position of<lb break="yes"/>man. The impulse might have been given by<lb break="yes"/>those European governments, which have the<lb break="yes"/>sentiment of human dignity, and who know<lb break="yes"/>that <hi rendition="#i">whatever is unjust, bears with it a germ of<lb break="yes"/>destruction;</hi> but this impulse, it is afflicting to<lb break="yes"/>add, will be powerless, if the union of the pro-<lb break="no"/>prietors of the colonial assemblies or legis-<lb break="no"/>latures, fail to adopt the same views, and to act<lb break="yes"/>by a well concerted plan, of which the ultimate<lb break="yes"/>object is the cessation of slavery in the West<lb break="yes"/>Indies. Till then it will be in vain to register<lb break="yes"/>the strokes of the whip, diminish the number<lb break="yes"/>that can be inflicted at any one time; require<lb break="yes"/>the presence of witnesses, and name protectors<lb break="yes"/>of the slaves; all these regulations, dictated<lb break="yes"/>by the most benevolent intentions, are easily<lb break="yes"/>eluded; the loneliness of the plantations renders<lb break="yes"/>their execution impossible. They support a<lb break="yes"/>system of domestic inquisition incompatible<lb break="yes"/>with what is called in the colonies, <hi rendition="#i">the acquired<lb break="yes"/>rights.</hi> The state of slavery cannot be alto-<lb break="no"/>gether peaceably ameliorated, but by the simul-<lb break="no"/>taneous action of free men, (white and colour-<lb break="no"/>ed,) who inhabit the West Indies; by colonial<lb break="yes"/>assemblies and <hi rendition="#i">legislators;</hi> by the influence of<lb break="yes"/>those who, enjoying a great moral considera-<lb break="no"/>tion among their countrymen, and acquainted<lb break="yes"/>with the locality, know how to vary the means<lb break="yes"/>of amelioration according to the manners, the<lb break="yes"/>habits and the position of every island.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In preparing this task, which ought to<lb break="yes"/>comprehend at the same time, a great part of<lb break="yes"/>the archipelago of the West Indies, it is useful<lb break="yes"/>to cast a retrospective look on the events by<lb break="yes"/>which the freedom of a considerable part of<lb break="yes"/>the human race was obtained in Europe, in<lb break="yes"/>the middle ages. In order to ameliorate with-<lb break="no"/>out commotion, new institutions must be made<lb break="yes"/>to issue from those which the barbarism of cen-<lb break="no"/>turies has consecrated. It will one day be dif-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="146" facs="#f0002" />
                    <cb/> ficult to believe that till 1826, there existed no<lb break="yes"/>law in the great Antilles to prevent selling in-<lb break="no"/>fants, and separating them from their parents,<lb break="yes"/>and to prohibit the degrading custom of mark-<lb break="no"/>ing the negroes with a hot iron, merely that<lb break="yes"/>the human cattle might be more easily recog-<lb break="no"/>nised. Enact laws to take away the possibili-<lb break="no"/>ty of a barbarous outrage; fix in every sugar<lb break="yes"/>estate, the relation between the least number<lb break="yes"/>of negresses, and that of the cultivating ne-<lb break="no"/>groes; grant liberty to every slave who has<lb break="yes"/>served fifteen years, and to every negress who<lb break="yes"/>has reared four or five children, set them free<lb break="yes"/>on the condition of working a certain number<lb break="yes"/>of days for the profit of the plantation; give<lb break="yes"/>the slaves a part of the nett produce, to inte-<lb break="no"/>rest them in the increase of agricultural riches,<lb break="yes"/>fix a sum on the budget of the public expense<lb break="yes"/>destined for the ransom of slaves, and the ame-<lb break="no"/>lioration of their fate; such are the most ur-<lb break="no"/>gent objects of colonial legislation.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">(To be continued.)</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <cb/>
                <pb n="153" facs="#f0003" />
                <cb/>
            </div>
            <div n="1">
                <head>For &#x201C;The Friend.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>ALEXANDER HUMBOLDT ON<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#b">NEGRO SLAVERY.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(Concluded from page 146.)</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We can never enough praise the wisdom of<lb break="yes"/>the legislation in the new republics of Spanish<lb break="yes"/>America, which, since their birth, has been<lb break="yes"/>seriously occupied with the total extinction of<lb break="yes"/>slavery. That vast portion of the earth has,<lb break="yes"/>in this respect, an immense advantage over<lb break="yes"/>the southern part of the United States, where<lb break="yes"/>the whites, during the struggle with England,<lb break="yes"/>established liberty for their own profit, and<lb break="yes"/>where the slave population, to the number of<lb break="yes"/>one million, six hundred thousand, augments<lb break="yes"/>still more rapidly than the white. If civiliza-<lb break="no"/>tion, instead of extending itself, were to change<lb break="yes"/>its place; if, after great and deplorable con-<lb break="no"/>vulsions in Europe, America, between Cape<lb break="yes"/>Hatteras and the Missouri, become the princi-<lb break="no"/>pal seat of the light of Christianity, what a<lb break="yes"/>spectacle would that centre of civilization of-<lb break="no"/>fer, where, in the sanctuary of liberty, we<lb break="yes"/>could attend a sale of negroes after death, and<lb break="yes"/>hear the sobbings of parents, who are sepa-<lb break="no"/>rated from their children! Let us hope that<lb break="yes"/>the generous principles which have so long<lb break="yes"/>animated the legislatures in the northern parts<lb break="yes"/>of the United States, will extend, by degrees,<lb break="yes"/>towards the south, and towards those western<lb break="yes"/>regions, where, by the effect of an imprudent<lb break="yes"/>and fatal law, slavery and its iniquities have<lb break="yes"/>passed the chain of the Alleghany, and the<lb break="yes"/>banks of the Mississippi: let us hope that the<lb break="yes"/>force of public opinion, the progress of know-<lb break="no"/>ledge, the softening of manners, the legislation<lb break="yes"/>of the new continental republics, and the great<lb break="yes"/>and happy event of the recognition of Hayti<lb break="yes"/>by the French government, will exert, either<lb break="yes"/>by motives of prudence and fear, or by more<lb break="yes"/>noble and disinterested sentiments, a happy<lb break="yes"/>influence on the amelioration of the state of<lb break="yes"/>the blacks in the rest of the West Indies, in<lb break="yes"/>the Carolinas, Guyana and Brazil. *****<lb break="yes"/>On the solution of this problem, depends, in<lb break="yes"/>the West Indies only, and excluding the repub-<lb break="no"/>lic of Hayti, the security of 875,000 free men,<lb break="yes"/>(whites and men of colour,) and the softening<lb break="yes"/>the fate of 1,150,000 slaves. We have demon-<lb break="no"/>
                    <cb/> strated that this can never be obtained by<lb break="yes"/>peaceful means, without the concurrence of<lb break="yes"/>the local authorities, either colonial assemblies,<lb break="yes"/>or meetings of proprietors, designated by less<lb break="yes"/>dreaded names by the parent state. The di-<lb break="no"/>rect influence of the authorities is indispens-<lb break="no"/>able, and it is a fatal error, to believe that we<lb break="yes"/>may leave it to time to act. Yes, time will<lb break="yes"/>act simultaneously on the slaves, on the rela-<lb break="no"/>tions between the islands and the inhabitants<lb break="yes"/>on the continent, and on events which cannot<lb break="yes"/>be controverted, when they have been waited<lb break="yes"/>for in the inaction of apathy. Wherever sla-<lb break="no"/>very is long established, the increase of civili-<lb break="no"/>zation has less influence on the treatment of<lb break="yes"/>slaves, than many are disposed to admit. The<lb break="yes"/>civilization of a nation seldom extends to a<lb break="yes"/>great number of individuals; and does not<lb break="yes"/>attain those, who, in the fabrics, are in imme-<lb break="no"/>diate contact with the blacks. I have known<lb break="yes"/>very humane proprietors shrink from the diffi-<lb break="no"/>culties that arise on the great plantations; they<lb break="yes"/>hesitate to disturb the established order, to<lb break="yes"/>make innovations, which, if not simultaneous,<lb break="yes"/>not sustained by the legislature, or, which<lb break="yes"/>would be a more powerful means, by the<lb break="yes"/>general will, would fail in their end, and per-<lb break="no"/>haps aggravate the wretchedness of those,<lb break="yes"/>whose fate they were meant to soften. These<lb break="yes"/>timid considerations stop the good that might<lb break="yes"/>be done by men who have the most benevolent<lb break="yes"/>intentions, and who deplore the barbarous<lb break="yes"/>institutions, of which they have received the<lb break="yes"/>sad inheritance. Acquainted with the local<lb break="yes"/>circumstances, they know that, to produce an<lb break="yes"/>essential change in the state of the slaves, to<lb break="yes"/>lead them progressively to the enjoyment of<lb break="yes"/>liberty, requires a firm will in the local authori-<lb break="no"/>ties, the concurrence of wealthy and enlighten-<lb break="no"/>ed citizens, and a general plan, in which all the<lb break="yes"/>chances of disorder, and the means of repres-<lb break="no"/>sion, are calculated. Without this community<lb break="yes"/>of actions and efforts, slavery, with its pains<lb break="yes"/>and excesses, will maintain itself as it did in<lb break="yes"/>ancient Rome, in the midst of elegance of<lb break="yes"/>manners, the boasted progress of knowledge,<lb break="yes"/>and all the charm of civilization, which its<lb break="yes"/>presence condemns, and which it menaces to<lb break="yes"/>overwhelm, when the time of vengeance ar-<lb break="no"/>rives. Civilization, or the slow decline of na-<lb break="no"/>tions, only prepares the mind for future events;<lb break="yes"/>but, to produce great changes in the social<lb break="yes"/>state, requires a coincidence of events, of<lb break="yes"/>which the epoch cannot be calculated before<lb break="yes"/>hand. In slave countries, where long habit<lb break="yes"/>tends to legitimate institutions the most con-<lb break="no"/>trary to justice, we must count on the influence<lb break="yes"/>of knowledge, intellectual improvement, and<lb break="yes"/>the softening of manners, only inasmuch as<lb break="yes"/>they accelerate the impulse given by govern-<lb break="no"/>ments, and facilitate the execution of measures<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> once adopted. Without the directing of gov-<lb break="no"/>ernments and of legislatures, a peaceable<lb break="yes"/>change is not to be hoped for. Above all,<lb break="yes"/>the danger becomes imminent, when a general<lb break="yes"/>inquietude pervades the public mind, and<lb break="yes"/>when, in the midst of political discussions,<lb break="yes"/>which agitate neighbouring nations, the faults<lb break="yes"/>and duties of governments have been discern-<lb break="no"/>ed: the calm can then only spring from an<lb break="yes"/>authority, which, in the noble sentiments of<lb break="yes"/>its force and its right, knows how to direct<lb break="yes"/>events in opening itself the career of amelior-<lb break="no"/>ation.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>