<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1">

<div n="2"><head><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<hi rendition="#i">BARON HUMBOLDT.</hi><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/></head>
<p>Baron Alexander Humboldt, the celebrated travel-<lb/>ler, having opened a public course of physical geogra-<lb/>phy at Berlin, was said in a German paper to have<lb/>commenced subscription lectures, and to have de-<lb/>manded 3<hi rendition="#i">l.</hi> for each admission ticket. The <hi rendition="#i">Moniteur</hi><lb/>copied this statement, and thus spread it over Europe.<lb/>The Baron, who was instructing the public without<lb/>any remuneration from the purse of individuals, has<lb/>addressed the following letter to the French official<lb/>journal, contradicting the false report. As we have<lb/>mentioned the object of the correction, we may give<lb/>the letter itself in the original.&#x2014;</p></div></div><lb/><div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">a monsieur le redacteur du moniteur uni-<lb/>versel.</hi></head><lb/><p>J&#x2019;ai lu avec la plus grande surprise dans votre journal du<lb/>7 Février, Monsieur, que j&#x2019;ai ouvert des cours de géographie<lb/>physique à Berlin par souscription, &#x201C;le cachet se payant trois<lb/>louis.&#x201D; Vous donnez cette nouvelle sur la foi d&#x2019;un journal<lb/>étranger, qui m&#x2019;est resté inconnu jusqu&#x2019;ici. J&#x2019;ose croire, que<lb/>toute réfutation est superflue pour la France, ou j&#x2019;ai résidé si<lb/>longtems: mais le <hi rendition="#i">Moniteur</hi> étant répandu dans les deux mon-<lb/>des, j&#x2019;ai pensé devoir signaler la fausseté et l&#x2019;inconvenance<lb/>d&#x2019;une assertion, dont je ne veux point examiner les motifs.<lb/>J&#x2019;ai ouvert deux cours publics, et en Allemagne, comme en<lb/>France, on ne paye pas, pour obtenir le droit d&#x2019;assister à un<lb/>cours public.&#x2014;Agréez, Monsieur, etc.</p><lb/><dateline>Berlin le 23 Février, 1828.</dateline><closer><salute>A. DE HUMBOLDT.</salute></closer></div><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
