<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="134" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Account of the great congress of philosophers at Berlin<lb break="yes"/>on the</hi> 18<hi rendition="#i">th of September</hi>, 1828. From the Edinburg<lb break="yes"/>Journal of Science.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The existence of a large sociely of cultivators of the<lb break="yes"/>natural sciences ineeting annually at some great capital<lb break="yes"/>or some central town ot Europe, is a oircumstance al-<lb break="no"/>most unknown to us and deserving of our attention from<lb break="yes"/>the important advantages which may arise from it.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>About eight years ago, Dr. Okens, of Mumch, sug-<lb break="no"/>gested a plan for an annual meeting of all Germans<lb break="yes"/>who cultivated the sciences of medieme and botany. &#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>The first meeting, of about forty members, took place<lb break="yes"/>at Leipsig in 1822, and it was successively held at Halle,<lb break="yes"/>Wurtsburg, Frankfort on the Mame, Dresden Mune,<lb break="yes"/>Dresden, Munich and Berlin. All those who had print-<lb break="no"/>ed a certam number of sheets of their inquiries were<lb break="yes"/>considered as members of this academy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The great advantages which resulted to the sciences<lb break="yes"/>from the communication of observations from all quarters<lb break="yes"/>of Germany, soon induced an extension of the plan, and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> other departments of natural knowledge were admitted,<lb break="yes" />until at the last meeting the cultivators even of pure<lb break="yes" />mathematies were found in the ranks of this academy.<lb break="yes"/>Several circumstances independent of the form and con-<lb break="no"/>stitution of the academy, contributed to give un wonted<lb break="yes"/>splendor at the meeting which took place at Berlin in<lb break="yes"/>the middle of September of the last year. The capital<lb break="yes"/>selected for its temporary residence, is scarcely surpass-<lb break="no"/>ed by any in Europe in the number and celebrity of its<lb break="yes"/>savans. The taste for knowledge possessed by the reign-<lb break="no"/>ing family, has made knowledge itself fashionable; and<lb break="yes"/>the severe sufferings of the Prussians, previous to the<lb break="yes"/>war which freed both them and Europe, have impressed<lb break="yes"/>on them so strongly the lesson that &#x201C;knowledge is pow-<lb break="no"/>er,&#x201D; that its effects are visible in every department of the<lb break="yes"/>government, and in no country of Europe, do talents and<lb break="yes"/>genius so surely open for their possessors the rond to<lb break="yes"/>wealth and to distinction.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Another circumstance continued to increase the num-<lb break="no"/>bers of the meeting of the past year. The office of pre-<lb break="no"/>sident, which is annually changed, was assigned to M.<lb break="yes"/>Alexander de Humboldt, The universality of hie ac-<lb break="no"/>quirements which have left no branch within the wide<lb break="yes"/>range ot science indifferent or unexplored, has connected<lb break="yes"/>him by triendship with almost all the most celebrated<lb break="yes"/>philosophers of the age, while the polished amenity of<lb break="yes"/>his manners and his intense desire of acquiring and spread-<lb break="no"/>ing knowledge, render him accessible to strangers and<lb break="yes"/>insure them the assistanoe of his counsel in their scientific<lb break="yes"/>pursuits and the advantage being made known to all who<lb break="yes"/>are interested or occupied in similar inquiries.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Professor Lichtenstein, (director of the Museum of<lb break="yes"/>Zoology,) as secrétary of the academy, was indefatigable<lb break="yes"/>in his attentions and most ably seconded the wishes of its<lb break="yes"/>distinguished president. These two gentlemen, assisted<lb break="yes"/>by several of the residents at Berlin, undertook the nu-<lb break="no"/>merous preliminary arrangements for the accommodation<lb break="yes"/>of the meeting.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On the 18th of Sept. 1828, there were assembled at<lb break="yes"/>Berlin 377 members of the academy, whose names and<lb break="yes"/>residence, (at Berlin,) were prmted in a small phamphlet,<lb break="yes"/>and to each name was affixed anumber to indieste his seat<lb break="yes"/>in the great concert room, where the morning meetings<lb break="yes"/>took place. Each member was provided with an en-<lb break="no"/>graved eard of the hall of meeting, on which the num-<lb break="no"/>bers of the seats were printed in black ink, so that every<lb break="yes"/>person immediately found his own place and knew where<lb break="yes"/>to look for any friend whom he might wish to find.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the hour appointed, the members being assembled,<lb break="yes"/>the galleries and orchestra filled by an assemblage of a<lb break="yes"/>large part of the rank and beauty of the capital, and the<lb break="yes"/>side boxes occupied by several branches of the royal fa-<lb break="no"/>nuly, and by the foreign ambassadors, the session of the<lb break="yes"/>academy was opened by the eloquent address of the pre-<lb break="no"/>sident.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Spcech of baren Humbolt</hi>. &#x2014; &#x201C;Since through your<lb break="yes"/>choice I am permitted to open this meeting, the first<lb break="yes"/>duty I have to discharge is one of gratitude. The dis-<lb break="no"/>tinetion which has been conlerred on him who has never<lb break="yes"/>yet been able to attend your excellent society, is not the<lb break="yes"/>reward of scientifie effects, or of feeble and persevering<lb break="yes"/>attempts to discover new phenomena, or to draw the light<lb break="yes"/>of knowledge from the unexplored depths of nature. &#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>A finer feeling directs your attention to me. You have<lb break="yes"/>assured me that while during an absence of many years<lb break="yes"/>in a distant quarter of the globe, I labored in the same<lb break="yes"/>cause with yourselves, I was not a stranger in your<lb break="yes"/>thoughts.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>What can the picture of this our native land present<lb break="yes"/>more agreeable to the mind than that we perceive to-day,<lb break="yes"/>for the first time, within our walls? From the banks of<lb break="yes"/>the Neckar, the birth-place of Kepler and Sciller, to<lb break="yes"/>the remotest border of the Baltie plains;&#x2014;from hence<lb break="yes"/>to the north of the Rhine, where, under the benefieent<lb break="yes"/>influence of commerce, the treasures of exotic nature<lb break="yes"/>have for centuries been collected and investigated, the<lb break="yes"/>friends of nature, inspired by the same zeal, flock to-<lb break="no"/>gether to this assembly; from all lands where the Ger-<lb break="no"/>man language is used, and its peculiar structure effects<lb break="yes"/>the spira of the people, from the Great European Alps<lb break="yes"/>to the other side of the Weischel, where, in the country<lb break="yes"/>of Copernicus, astronomy rose in renewed splendour;<lb break="yes"/>wherever in the extensive dominions of the Germen na-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="135" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/> tion, we attempt to discover the secret operations of na-<lb break="no" />ture, whether in the heavens or in the deepest problems<lb break="yes"/>of mechanies, or in the interior of the earth, or in the<lb break="yes"/>finely woven tissues of organic structure.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Protected by noble princes, this assembly has annually<lb break="yes"/>inereased in interest and extent. Every distinetion which<lb break="yes"/>difference of religion or of government ean oceasion, is<lb break="yes"/>here annulled. Germany manifests itself in its intellec-<lb break="no"/>tual unity; and sinee knowledge of truth and performance<lb break="yes"/>of duty are the highest objects of morality, that feeling<lb break="yes"/>of unity weakens none of the bonds which the religion,<lb break="yes"/>constitution and laws of our country endear to each of us.<lb break="yes"/>This emulation in mental struggles has even called forth,<lb break="yes"/>as the glorions history of our country tells us, the fairest<lb break="yes"/>blossoms of humanity, science and art.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The assembly of German naturalists and natural phi-<lb break="no"/>losophers, since its last meeting, when it was so hospita-<lb break="no"/>bly received at Munich, has through the flattering in-<lb break="no"/>terests of neighboring states and acudemies shone with<lb break="yes"/>peenliar lustre. Allied nations have renewed the an-<lb break="no"/>eient alliance between Germany and the Scandinavian<lb break="yes"/>North. Such an interest deserves acknowledgment the<lb break="yes"/>more, because it increases the mass of facts and opinions<lb break="yes"/>here brought into one common union. It also brings<lb break="yes"/>lofty recollections to the mind of the naturalist. Scarce<lb break="yes"/>half a century has elapsed since Linne appeared, in the<lb break="yes"/>boldness of the undertakings which he has attempted<lb break="yes"/>and accomplished, as one of the greatest men of the last<lb break="yes"/>century. His glory, however bright, has not rendered<lb break="yes"/>Europe blind to the merits of Scheele and Bergman. The<lb break="yes"/>catalogue of great names is not completed; but, lest I<lb break="yes"/>should offend noble modesty, I dare not speak of the<lb break="yes"/>light still flowing in richest profusion from the north, nor<lb break="yes"/>mention the discoveries in the chemical nature of suh-<lb break="no"/>stances, in the numerical relation of their elements, or<lb break="yes"/>the eddying streams of electro-magnetic powers.<note place="foot" n="*">Berzelius and Oersted.</note> May<lb break="yes"/>those excellent persons who, deterred neither by perils<lb break="yes"/>of sea or land, have bastened to our meeting from Swe-<lb break="no"/>den, Norway, Denmark, Holland, England, and Poland,<lb break="yes"/>point out the way to other strangers in succeeding years,<lb break="yes"/>so that by turns every part of Germany may enjoy the<lb break="yes"/>benefits of scientific communication with the different<lb break="yes"/>nations of Europe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But though I restrain the expression of my personal<lb break="yes"/>feelings in presence of the assembly, let me at least name<lb break="yes"/>the patriarchs of our national glory detained from us by<lb break="yes"/>a regard for lives so dear to our country:&#x2014;Goethe, whom<lb break="yes"/>the creations of poetic fancy have not withheld from<lb break="yes"/>penetrating the secrets of nature, and who now in rural<lb break="yes"/>solitude mourns for his princely friend, as Germany for<lb break="yes"/>one of her greatest ornaments; Olbers, who has discovered<lb break="yes"/>two bodies where he predicted they would be found; the<lb break="yes"/>greatest anatomist of our age, Soemmering, who with<lb break="yes"/>equal zeal has investigated the wonders of organic struc-<lb break="no"/>ture and the spots and <hi rendition="#i">feculae</hi> of the sun, (condensations<lb break="yes"/>and openings of the photospheres,) &#x2014; Blumenbach, whose<lb break="yes"/>papd I have the honor to be, whose works and immortal<lb break="yes"/>eloquence and labors of half a century have inspired every<lb break="yes"/>where a love of comparative anatomy, physiology, and<lb break="yes"/>the general history of nature.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These observations on the literary wealth of our coun-<lb break="no"/>try, and the progressive developement of our institution,<lb break="yes"/>lead us naturally to the observations which may arise<lb break="yes"/>from the increasing number of our fellow laborers. The<lb break="yes"/>principal object of thia society is not the mutual enter-<lb break="no"/>change of treaties, or the publication of innumerable<lb break="yes"/>memoirs in some general collection, but it is to bring<lb break="yes"/>those personally together who are engaged in the same<lb break="yes"/>field of seience. It is the immediafe and, therefore, more<lb break="yes"/>obvious interchange of idens, whether presented as facts,<lb break="yes"/>opinions or doubts. It is the establishment of friendly<lb break="yes"/>connection, which throw@ light on science, adds cheer-<lb break="no"/>fulness to life, and gives grace and amenity to the man-<lb break="no"/>ners.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the most flourishing period of ancient Greece, the<lb break="yes"/>distinction between words and writing manitested itself<lb break="yes"/>most strongly among a race which bad raised itself to<lb break="yes"/>the most aplendid intellectual superiority, and to whose<lb break="yes"/>latest descendents, preserved from the shipwreck of na-<lb break="no"/>tions, we still consecrate our most anxious wishes. It<lb break="yes"/>was not the difficulty of interchanging ideas alone, nor<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> the want of German science which has spread thought<lb break="yes"/>as on wings through the world, and given it permanence,<lb break="yes"/>that lead the friends of philosophy and natural history in<lb break="yes"/>Magna Grecia and Asia Minor, to wander on long jour-<lb break="no"/>neys. That ancient race knew the inspiring inlluence<lb break="yes"/>of conversation, as it extemporaneously penetrates the<lb break="yes"/>tissue of scientific opinions and doubts. The discovery<lb break="yes"/>of truth without difference of opinion is unattainable,<lb break="yes"/>for truth in its full extent can never be recognised by all<lb break="yes"/>and at the same time. Each step that brings the student<lb break="yes"/>of nature, nearer to his object, conducts him to the thresh-<lb break="no"/>hold of new labyrinths. The mass of doubt does not<lb break="yes"/>diminish, but spreads like a moving cloud over new<lb break="yes"/>fields, and whoever calls that a golden period when the<lb break="yes"/>disputes of the learned will be finished, has as imper-<lb break="no"/>fect conception of the wants of science, as he who ex-<lb break="no"/>pects that the same opinions in geognosy, chemistry, or<lb break="yes"/>physiology will be maintained for centories.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The founders of this society, with a deep sense of the<lb break="yes"/>unity of nature, have combmed in the completest man-<lb break="no"/>ner, all the branches of physieal knowledge and of his-<lb break="no"/>torical, geometrical and experimental philosophy. The<lb break="yes"/>names of natural historian and natural philosopher are<lb break="yes"/>bere, therefore, nearly synonymous, chamed by a terres-<lb break="no"/>trial link of the type of the lower animals. Man com-<lb break="no"/>pletes the seale of higher organization. In his physiolo-<lb break="no"/>gical and pathological qualities, he scarcely presents to<lb break="yes"/>us a distinct class of beings. As to what has brought<lb break="yes"/>him to this exalted object of physical study, and raised<lb break="yes"/>him to general scientific investigation, it belongs princi-<lb break="no"/>pally to this society. Important as it is not to break<lb break="yes"/>that link which connects the investigation of organic and<lb break="yes"/>inorganic nature, the increasing ties and daily develope-<lb break="no"/>ment of this institution, render it necessary, besides the<lb break="yes"/>general meeting destined for these halls, to have specific<lb break="yes"/>meetings tor single branches of science. For it is only<lb break="yes"/>in such contracted circles, and among men whom reci-<lb break="no"/>procity of studies has brought together, that oral discus-<lb break="no"/>sions can take place. Without these, would the volun-<lb break="no"/>tary associations of men in search of truth, be deprived<lb break="yes"/>of an inspiring principle.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Among the arrangements for the advancement of the<lb break="yes"/>society, attention has been paid to the possibility of such<lb break="yes"/>a subdivision into sections. The hope that these ar-<lb break="no"/>rangements will meet with your approbation, imposes<lb break="yes"/>the duty of reminding you, that, although you had en-<lb break="no"/>trusted to two travellers equally the duty of making them,<lb break="yes"/>it is to one alone, my noble friend, M. Lichtenstem, that<lb break="yes"/>the merit of careful precaution and indefatigable activity<lb break="yes"/>is due. Out of respect to the scientific spirit which ani-<lb break="no"/>mates the Society of German Naturalists and Natural<lb break="yes"/>Philosophy, and in acknowledgment of the utility of<lb break="yes"/>their efforts, the government has readily seconed our<lb break="yes"/>wishes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the vicinity of the place of meeting thus prepared<lb break="yes"/>for our general and special labors are situated the mu-<lb break="no"/>seums of anatomy, zoology, oryctognosy and geology,<lb break="yes"/>offering to the naturalist a rich mine for observation and<lb break="yes"/>eritical discussion. The greater number of these collec-<lb break="no"/>tions have existed, like the university of Berlin, scarcely<lb break="yes"/>twenty years. The oldest of them, to which the botani-<lb break="no"/>cal garden, the richest one in Europe, belongs, have dur-<lb break="no"/>ing this period not only been increased, but entirely re-<lb break="no"/>modelled. The amusement and instruction they furaish<lb break="yes"/>recall to our grateful minds that they are the works of<lb break="yes"/>that great monarch who modestly and in simple grandeur<lb break="yes"/>adoras every year this city with new treasures of nature<lb break="yes"/>and art&#x2014;and what is of still greater vulue&#x2014;what inspires<lb break="yes"/>every Prussian with an enthusiastic love for the ancient<lb break="yes"/>reigning family, he attaches to himself every species of<lb break="yes"/>talent, and extends with confidence his royal protection<lb break="yes"/>to the free cultivation of the understanding.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Baron Humboldt&#x2019;s speech was followed by a paper on<lb break="yes" />magnetism, by professor Oersted, and several other me-<lb break="no"/>moirs were then read.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The arrival of so many persons of similar pursuit, (for<lb break="yes"/>464 members were present) rendered it convenient to<lb break="yes"/>have some ordinary at which those who choose might<lb break="yes"/>dine, and introduce their friends and families. This had<lb break="yes"/>been foreseen, and his majesty had allowed the immense<lb break="yes"/>building used for the exercise of his troops to be used for<lb break="yes"/>this purpose. One third of it was floored on the occa-<lb break="no"/>sion, and tables were arranged, at which, on one occasion,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="136" facs="#f0003"/> 850 persons sat down to dinner. On the evening of the<lb break="yes"/>first day, M. de Humboldt gave a <hi rendition="#i" >soirce</hi> in the concert<lb break="yes"/>rooms attached to the theatre. About 1,200 persons as-<lb break="no"/>sembled on this occasion, and the king of Prussia honored<lb break="yes"/>with his presence the <hi rendition="#i" >fete</hi> of his illustious chamberlain.<lb break="yes"/>The nobility of the country, foreign princes, and foreign<lb break="yes"/>am bassadors were present. It was gratifying to observe<lb break="yes"/>the princes of the blood mingled with the cultivators of<lb break="yes"/>science, and to see the heir apparent to the throne en-<lb break="no"/>gaged in conversation with those most celebrated for<lb break="yes"/>talents of his own or other countries. Nor were the<lb break="yes"/>minor arrangements of the evening beneath the consider-<lb break="no"/>ation of the president. The words of the music, select-<lb break="no"/>ed for the concert, were printed and distributed among<lb break="yes"/>the guests. The names of the most illustrious philoso-<lb break="no"/>phers which Germany had produced, were inscribed in<lb break="yes"/>letters of gold at the end of the great concert room. In<lb break="yes"/>the first rank among these, stood a name which England<lb break="yes"/>too enrols among ber brightest, and proud as she may<lb break="yes"/>well be of having fostered and brought to maturity the<lb break="yes"/>genius of the first Herschel, she has reaped an ample re-<lb break="no"/>ward in being able to claim entirely as her own the inhe-<lb break="no"/>ritor of his talents and his name.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The six succeeding days were occupied in the morning,<lb break="yes"/>by a meeting of the academy at which papers of great in-<lb break="no"/>terest were read. In the afternoon, through the arrange-<lb break="no"/>ment of M. de Humboldt and M. Lichtenstein, various<lb break="yes"/>rooms were appropriated for different sections of the aca-<lb break="no"/>demy. In one the chemical philosophers attended to<lb break="yes"/>some chemical memoir, whilst the botanists assembled<lb break="yes"/>in another room, the physiologists in a third, and the na-<lb break="no"/>tural philosophers in a fourth. Each attended to the<lb break="yes"/>reading of papers connected with their several sciences.<lb break="yes"/>Thus every member was at liberty to choose that section<lb break="yes"/>in which he felt most interest at the moment, and had at<lb break="yes"/>all times access to the others. The evenings were gene-<lb break="no"/>rally spent at the <hi rendition="#i">soirees</hi> of the <hi rendition="#i">savans</hi>, resident at Ber-<lb break="no"/>lin, whose hospitality and attentions to their learned bre-<lb break="no"/>thren of other countries were unbounded. In the morn-<lb break="no"/>ing the collections of natural history, which are rapidly<lb break="yes"/>rising into importance, were open to examination, and<lb break="yes"/>the various professors and directors assisted the stranger<lb break="yes"/>in his enquiries.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A map of Europe was printed, on which those towns<lb break="yes"/>only appeared which had sent representatives from this<lb break="yes"/>scientific congress; and the numbers sent by different<lb break="yes"/>kingdom@ appeared by the following table, which was<lb break="yes"/>attached to it:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <list>
                    <item>Russia 1</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Austria 0</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>England 1</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Holland 2</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Denmark 7</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>France 1</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Sardinia 0</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Prussia 25</item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <list>
                    <item>Bavaria 12</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Hanover 5</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Saxony 21</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Wirtemberg 12</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Sweden 13</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Naples 1</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Poland 3</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>German states <hi rendition="#u">43</hi>
                    </item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>206</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Berlin <hi rendition="#u">172</hi>
                    </item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Total 378</item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The proportion in which the cultivators of different<lb break="yes"/>sciences appeared, was not easy to ascertain, because<lb break="yes"/>there were few among the more eminent who had not<lb break="yes"/>added to more than one branch of human knowledge.<lb break="yes"/>The following table, though not professing to be very ac-<lb break="no"/>curate, will afford, perhaps, a tolerably fair view:&#x2014;Geo-<lb break="no"/>meters, 1; astronomers, 5; natural phdosophers, 23&#x2014;in<lb break="yes"/>all 39. Mines, 5; mineralogy, 14; geology, 9&#x2014;in all 30.<lb break="yes"/>Chemistry, 18; geography, 8; anatomy, 12. Zoology, 14;<lb break="yes"/>natural history, 8; and botany, 35&#x2014;in all 57. Physicians,<lb break="yes"/>175. Amateurs, 9. Various, 33. Grand total, 381.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A medal was struck in commemoration of this meet-<lb break="no"/>ing; and it was propoaed that it should form the first of<lb break="yes"/>a series, comprising all those persons most celebrated for<lb break="yes"/>their diseoveries in the past and present age.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 