<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">The supposed recent Origin of America refuted</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:02</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.90</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1828-The_supposed_recent-1-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1828-The_supposed_recent-1-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-The_supposed_recent-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Ansichten der Natur&lt;/i&gt;, Stuttgart und Tübingen: Cotta 1808, S. 94–100, Anmerkung 17.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">The supposed recent Origin of America refuted</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1828</date>
          <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal&lt;/i&gt; (Juli–September 1828), S. 309–310.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <relatedItem type="reprint">
            <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Ueber die künftigen Verhältnisse von Europa und Amerika. Politische und historographische Schriften zur Neuen Welt&lt;/i&gt;, herausgegeben von Oliver Lubrich, Hannover: Wehrhahn 2010, S. 79–81.</bibl>
          </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="309" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">The supposed recent Origin of America refuted.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">A</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">very</hi> ingenious naturalist, Mr Smith Barton, has said,<lb break="yes"/>with much justice, &#x201C;I can only consider as puerile, and in no<lb break="yes"/>way proved by natural evidence, the supposition that a great<lb break="yes"/>part of America has emerged from the bosom of the wa-<lb break="no"/>ters at a later period than the other continents <note place="foot" n="*">Fragments of the Natural History of Pennsylvania, vol. i. p. 4.</note>.&#x201D; May I be<lb break="yes"/>permitted to quote a passage from a memoir which I composed,<lb break="yes"/>on the Native Tribes of America <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Berliner Monatschrift, t. xv. p. 190.</note>. &#x201C;Justly celebrated wri-<lb break="no"/>ters have often repeated, that America is, in every sense of the<lb break="yes"/>word, a New Continent. That richness of vegetation, that mass<lb break="yes"/>of immense rivers, those great volcanoes, always in action, an-<lb break="no"/>nounce, say they, that the earth, incessantly trembling and not<lb break="yes"/>entirely dry, is less removed from the original chaotic state than<lb break="yes"/>in the old world. Long before my voyage, such ideas appeared<lb break="yes"/>to me as unphilosophical as opposed to the generally known<lb break="yes"/>laws of physics. These images of youth and disorder, as well<lb break="yes"/>as of dryness and progressive loss of vigour in the Earth, as it<lb break="yes"/>grows old, could only originate with those who amuse them-<lb break="no"/>selves with seeking out contrasts between the two hemispheres,<lb break="yes"/>and do not comprehend under a general view the constitution<lb break="yes"/>of our planet. Will it be said that the southern part of Italy<lb break="yes"/>is a newer country than Lombardy, because it is almost conti-<lb break="no"/>nually shaken by earthquakes and volcanic eruptions? Besides,<lb break="yes"/>our present volcanoes and earthquakes are slight phenomena<lb break="yes"/>compared with those revolutions of nature which the geologist<lb break="yes"/>must suppose to have taken place in the days of the melting and<lb break="yes"/>cooling of the masses which have formed the mountains, when<lb break="yes"/>the Earth was yet in a state of chaos. Different causes must<lb break="yes"/>make the effects of the energy of nature vary in different cli-<lb break="no"/>mates. In the New World, the volcanoes, to the number of<lb break="yes"/>fifty-four, may perhaps have burnt longer, because the chain of<lb break="yes"/>lofty mountains in which they are situated is nearer the sea, and<lb break="yes"/>because this circumstance, and the perpetual snow which covers<lb break="yes"/>them, appear to modify the subterranean fire, in a manner as<lb break="yes"/>yet little appreciated. Earthquakes and eruptions act there pe-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="310" facs="#f0002"/> riodically. At present physical disorder and political tranquili-<lb break="no"/>ty reign in the New Continent, while in the Old, the discords of<lb break="yes"/>the nations drive men to seek for rest in the bosom of nature.<lb break="yes"/>Perhaps a time will come when one part of the world will take<lb break="yes"/>the place of the other in this singular contrast between physical<lb break="yes"/>and moral energy. Volcanoes rest for ages, before they are<lb break="yes"/>again lighted up. The opinion that, in the older regions, there<lb break="yes"/>ought to reign a certain peace in nature, is founded merely up-<lb break="no"/>on a play of our imagination. One side of our planet can never<lb break="yes"/>be older than the other. The islands produced by volcanoes,<lb break="yes"/>such as the Azores, or gradually formed by mollusca, like many<lb break="yes"/>islands of the Pacific Ocean, are in general more recent than the<lb break="yes"/>granite masses of the central chain of Europe. A country of<lb break="yes"/>small extent, like Bohemia, and several valleys of the moon,<lb break="yes"/>circularly inclosed by mountains, may long remain covered with<lb break="yes"/>water, in consequence of partial inundations, and form a lake.<lb break="yes"/>After the waters have been entirely drained off, the name of<lb break="yes"/>newly-formed land might by metaphor be given to this, where<lb break="yes"/>vegetation would establish itself by degrees. But an aquatic<lb break="yes"/>envelope, such as the geologist figures to himself at the period<lb break="yes"/>of the formation of the secondary mountains, can only be sup-<lb break="no"/>posed, consistently with the laws of hydrostatics, as existing at<lb break="yes"/>once in all parts of the world, and in all climates. The sea<lb break="yes"/>could not remain on the vast plains of the Oronocco and Ama-<lb break="no"/>zon, without, at the same time, ravaging the countries situated<lb break="yes"/>around the Baltic. The concatenation and identity of the se-<lb break="no"/>condary strata near Carracas, in Thuringia, and in Lower<lb break="yes"/>Egypt, prove, as I have shewn in my Geological Picture of<lb break="yes"/>South America, that this great operation of nature has been per-<lb break="no"/>formed at the same period over the whole earth. &#x2014; <hi rendition="#i">Humboldt,<lb break="yes"/>Tableau de la Nature,</hi> tom. i. p. 133-139.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 