<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Congress of philosophers</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:02</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.94</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-13-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-05.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-10.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-11.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-13-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-xxx_Rede_gehalten_bei-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Congress of philosophers</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1830</date>
          <pubPlace>New York City, New York</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;Cabinet of Religion, Education, Literature, Science, and Intelligence&lt;/i&gt; 4:7 (September 1830), S. 219–223.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="219" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Account of the great Congress of Philosophers at Berlin on the</hi> 18<hi rendition="#i">th of September</hi>, 1828.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The existence of a large society of cultivators of the natural sciences meeting<lb break="yes"/>annually at some great capital or some central town of Europe, is a circumstance al-<lb break="no"/>most unknown to us and deserving of our attention from the important advantages<lb break="yes"/>which may arise from it.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>About eight years ago, Dr. Okens, of Munich, suggested a plan for an annual<lb break="yes"/>meeting of all Germans who cultivated the sciences of medicine and botany. The<lb break="yes"/>first meeting, of about forty members, took place at Leipsig in 1822, and it was suc-<lb break="no"/>cessively held at Halle, Wurtsburg, Frankfort on the Maine, Dresden Mune, Dres-<lb break="no" />den, Munich, and Berlin. All those who had printed a certain number of sheets of<lb break="yes"/>their inquiries were considered as members of this academy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The great advantages which resulted to these sciences from the communication of<lb break="yes"/>observations from all quarters of Germany, soon induced an extension of the plan<lb break="yes"/>and other departments of natural knowledge were admitted, until at the last meet-<lb break="no"/>ing the cultivators even of pure mathematics were found in the ranks of this acade-<lb break="no"/>my. Several circumstances independent of the form and constitution of the academy,<lb break="yes"/>contributed to give unwonted splendor to the meeting which took place at Berlin in<lb break="yes"/>the middle of September of the last year. The capital selected for its temporary<lb break="yes"/>residence, is scarcely surpassed by any in Europe in the number and celebrity of its<lb break="yes"/>savans. The taste for knowledge possessed by the reigning family, has made know-<lb break="no"/>ledge itself fashionable; and the severe sufferings of the Prussians, previous to the<lb break="yes"/>war, which freed both them and Europe, have impressed on them so strongly the les-<lb break="no"/>son that &#x2018;knowledge is power,&#x2019; that its effects are visible in every department of the<lb break="yes"/>government, and in no country in Europe do talents and genius so surely open for<lb break="yes"/>their possessors the road to wealth and to distinction.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Another circumstance continued to increase the number of the meeting of the<lb break="yes"/>past year. The office of President, which is annually changed, was assigned to M.<lb break="yes"/>Alexander de Humboldt. The universality of his acquirements which have left no<lb break="yes"/>branch within the wide range of science indifferent or unexplored, has connected him<lb break="yes"/>by friendship with almost all the most celebrated philosophers of the age, while the<lb break="yes"/>polished amenity of his manners and his intense desire of acquiring and spreading<lb break="yes"/>knowledge, render him accessible to strangers and insure them the assistance of his<lb break="yes"/>counsel in their scientific pursuits and the advantage being made known to all who<lb break="yes" />are interested or occupied in similar inquiries.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Professor Lichtenstein, (director of the Museum of Zoology) as secretary of the<lb break="yes"/>academy, was indefatigable in his attentions and most ably seconded the wishes of its<lb break="yes"/>distinguished President. These two gentlemen, assisted by several of the residents<lb break="yes"/>at Berlin, undertook the numerous preliminary arrangements for the accommodation<lb break="yes"/>of the meeting.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On the 18th of September, 1828, there were assembled at Berlin three hundred<lb break="yes"/>and seventy-seven members of the academy, whose names and residence (at Berlin)<lb break="yes"/>were printed in a small pamphlet, and to each name was affixed a number to indicate<lb break="yes"/>his seat in the great concert room, where the morning meetings took place. Each<lb break="yes"/>member was provided with an engraved card of the hall of meeting, on which the<lb break="yes"/>numbers of the seats were printed in black ink, so that every person immediately<lb break="yes"/>found his own place and knew where to look for any friend whom he might wish<lb break="yes"/>@o find.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="220" facs="#f0002"/>
                <p>At the hour appointed, the members being assembled, the galleries and orchestra<lb break="yes"/>filled by an assemblage of a large part of the rank and beauty of the capital, and the<lb break="yes"/>side boxes occupied by several branches of the royal family, and by the foreign am-<lb break="no" />bassadors, the session of the academy was opened by the eloquent address of the<lb break="yes"/>president.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Speech of Baron Humboldt</hi>. &#x2014; &#x2018;Since through your choice I am permitted to open<lb break="yes"/>this meeting, the first duty I have to discharge is one of gratitude. The distinction<lb break="yes"/>which has been conferred on him who has never yet been able to attend your excel-<lb break="no"/>lent society, is not the reward of scientific efforts, or of feeble and persevering<lb break="yes"/>attempts to discover new phenomena or to draw the light of knowledge from the<lb break="yes"/>unexplored depths of nature. A finer feeling directs your attention to me. You have<lb break="yes" />essured me that while during an absence of many years in a distant quarter of the<lb break="yes"/>globe, I labored in the same cause with yourselves, I was not a stranger in your<lb break="yes"/>thoughts.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x2018;What can the picture of this our native land present more agreeable to the mind<lb break="yes"/>than that we perceive to-day, for the first time, within our walls? From the banks<lb break="yes"/>of the Neckar, the birth-place of Kepler and Schiller, to the remotest border of the<lb break="yes"/>Baltic plains; &#x2014; from hence to the mouth of the Rhine, where, under the beneficent<lb break="yes"/>influence of commerce, the treasures of exotic nature have for centuries been col-<lb break="no"/>lected and investigated, the friends of nature, inspired by the same zeal, flock together<lb break="yes"/>to this assembly; from all lands where the German language is used, and its peculiar<lb break="yes"/>structure affects the spirit of the people, from the Great European Alps to the other<lb break="yes"/>side of the Weischel, where, in the country of Copernicus, astronomy rose in renewed<lb break="yes" />splendor; wherever, in the extensive dominions of the German nation, we attempt to<lb break="yes"/>discover the secret operations of nature, whether in the heavens or in the deepest<lb break="yes"/>problems of mechanics, or in the interior of the earth, or in the finely woven tissues<lb break="yes"/>of organic structure.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Protected by noble princes, this assembly has annually increased in interest and,<lb break="yes"/>extent. Every distinction which difference of religion or of government can occasion,<lb break="yes"/>is here annulled. Germany manifest itself in its intellectual unity; and since know-<lb break="no"/>ledge of truth and performance of duty are the highest objects of morality, that feeling<lb break="yes"/>of unity weakens none of the bonds which the religion, constitution and laws of our<lb break="yes"/>country endear to each of us. This emulation in mental struggles even called forth,<lb break="yes"/>as the glorious history of our country tells us, the fairest blossoms of humanity, seience<lb break="yes"/>and art.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The assembly of German naturalists and natural philosophers, since its last meeting,<lb break="yes"/>when it was so hospitably received at Munich, has, through the flattering interest of<lb break="yes"/>neighboring states and academies, shone with peculiar lustre. Allied nations have<lb break="yes" />renewed the ancient alliance between Germany and the Scandinavian North. Such<lb break="yes"/>an interest deserves acknowledgement the more, becaus it increasese the mass of facts<lb break="yes"/>and opinions here brought into one common union. It also brings lofty recollections to<lb break="yes"/>the mind of the naturalists. Scarce half a century has elapsed since Linne appeared,<lb break="yes"/>in the boldness of the undertakings which he has attempted and accomplished, as one<lb break="yes"/>of the greatest men of the last century. His glory, however bright, has not rendered<lb break="yes"/>Europe blind to the merits of Scheele and Bergman. &#x2014; The catalogue of great names<lb break="yes"/>is not completed, but, lest I should offend noble modesty I dare not speak of the<lb break="yes"/>light still flowing in richest profusion from the north, nor mention the discoveries in<lb break="yes"/>the chemical nature of substances in the numerical relation of their elements, or the<lb break="yes"/>eddying streams of electro-magnetie powers.<note place="foot" n="*">Berzelius and Oersted.</note>&#x2014;May those excellent persons who<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="221" facs="#f0003"/> deterred neither by perils of sea or land, have hastened to our meeting from Sweden,<lb break="yes"/>Norway, Denmark, Holland, England, and Poland, point out the way to other stran-<lb break="no"/>gers in succeeding years, so that by turns every part of Germany may enjoy the<lb break="yes"/>benefits of scientific communication with the different nations of Europe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But though I restrain the expression of my personal feelings in presence of the<lb break="yes"/>assembly, let me at least name the patriarchs of our national glory detained from us<lb break="yes"/>by a regard for lives so dear to our country: &#x2014; Goethe, whom the creations of poetic<lb break="yes"/>fancy have not withheld from penetrating the secrets of nature, and who now in rural<lb break="yes"/>solitude mourns for his princely friend as Germany for one of her greatest ornament;<lb break="yes"/>Olbers, who has discovered two bodies where he predicted they would be found; the<lb break="yes"/>greatest anatomists of our age, Soemmering, who with equal zeal has investigated<lb break="yes"/>the wonders of organic structure and the spots and <hi rendition="#i">feculae</hi> of the sun, (condensations<lb break="yes"/>and openings of the photospheres) &#x2014; Blumenbach, whose pupil I have the honor to be-<lb break="no"/>whose works and immortal eloquence and labors of half a century have inspired every<lb break="yes"/>where a love of comparative anatomy, physiology, and the general history of nature.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These observations on the literary wealth of our country, and the progressive de-<lb break="no"/>velopement of our institution, lead us naturally to the obstructions which may arise<lb break="yes"/>from the increasing number of our fellow laborers. The principal object of this so-<lb break="no"/>ciety is not the mutual interchange of treaties, or the publication of innumerable<lb break="yes"/>memoirs in some general collection, but it is to bring those personally together who<lb break="yes"/>are engaged in the same field of science. It is the immediate and therefore more<lb break="yes"/>obvious interchange of ideas, whether presented as facts, opinions, or doubts. It is<lb break="yes"/>the establishment of friendly connection, which throws light on science, adds, cheer-<lb break="no"/>fulness to life, and gives grace and amenity to the manners.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the most flourishing period of ancient Greece, the distinction between words and<lb break="yes"/>writing manifested itself most strongly among a race which had raised itself to the<lb break="yes"/>most splendid intellectual superiority, and to whose latest descendants preserved from<lb break="yes"/>the shipwreck of nations we still consecrate our most anxious wishes. It was not<lb break="yes"/>the difficulty of interchanging ideas alone, nor the want of German science which has<lb break="yes"/>spread thought as on wings through the world, and given it permanence, that led the<lb break="yes"/>friends of philosophy and natural history in Magna Grecia and Asia Minor to wander<lb break="yes"/>on long journeys. That ancient race knew the inspiring influence of conversation,<lb break="yes"/>as it extemporaneously penetrates the tissue of scientific opinions and doubts. The<lb break="yes"/>discovery of truth without difference of opinion is unattainable, for truth in its full<lb break="yes"/>extent can never be recognized by all and at the same time. Each step that brings<lb break="yes"/>the student of nature nearer to his object conducts him to the threshhold of new laby-<lb break="no"/>rinths. The mass of doubt does not diminish, but spreads like a moving cloud over<lb break="yes" />new fields, and whoever calls that a golden period when the disputes of the learned<lb break="yes"/>will be finished, has as imperfect a conception of the wants of science, as he who ex-<lb break="no"/>pects that the same opinions in geognosy, chemistry, or physiology will be maintained<lb break="yes"/>for centuries.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The founders of this society with a deep sense of the unity of nature have combined<lb break="yes"/>in the completest manner, all the branches of physical knowledge and of historical,<lb break="yes"/>geometrical and experimental philosophy. The names of natural historian and natural<lb break="yes"/>philosopher are here therefore nearly synonymous, chained by a terrestrial link to the<lb break="yes"/>type of the lower animals. Man completes the scale of higher organization. In his<lb break="yes"/>physiological and pathological qualities, he scarcely presents to us a distinct class of<lb break="yes"/>beings. As to what has brought him to this exalted object of physical study, and<lb break="yes"/>mised him to general scientific investigation, it belongs principally to this society.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="222" facs="#f0004"/> Important as it is not to break that link which connects the investigation of organic<lb break="yes"/>and morganic nature, the increasing ties and daily developement of this institution,<lb break="yes" />render it necessary, besides the general meeting destined for these halls, to have specific<lb break="yes"/>meetings for single branches of science. For it is only in such contracted circles and<lb break="yes"/>among men whom reciprocity of studies has brought together, that oral discussions<lb break="yes"/>can take place. Without these would the voluntary associations of men in search of<lb break="yes"/>truth, be deprived of an inspiring principle.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Among the arrangements for the advancement of the society attention has been<lb break="yes"/>paid to the possibility of such a subdivision into sections. The hope that these ar-<lb break="no"/>rangements will meet with your approbation imposes the duty of reminding you, that<lb break="yes"/>although you had entrusted to two travellers equally the duty of making them, it is<lb break="yes"/>to one alone, my noble friend M. Lichtenstein, that the merit of careful precaution<lb break="yes"/>and indefatigable activity is due. Out of respect to the scientific spirit which animates<lb break="yes"/>the Society of German Naturalists and Natural Philosophy, and in acknowledg-<lb break="no"/>of the utility of their efforts, the government has readily seconded our wishes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the vicinity of the place of meeting thus prepared for our general and special<lb break="yes"/>labors are situated the museums of Anatomy, Zoology, Oryctognosy and Geology,<lb break="yes"/>offering to the naturalist a rich mine for observation and critical discussion. The<lb break="yes"/>greater number of these collections have existed, like the University of Berlin, scarce-<lb break="no"/>ly twenty years. The oldest of them, to which the Botanical Garden, the richest<lb break="yes"/>one in Europe belongs, have during this period not only been increased, but entirely<lb break="yes"/>remodelled. The amusement and instruction they furnish recall to our grateful minds<lb break="yes"/>that they are the work of that great monarch who modestly and in simple grandeur<lb break="yes"/>adorns every year this city with new treasures of nature and art&#x2014;and what is of still<lb break="yes"/>greater value&#x2014;what inspires every Prussian with an enthusiastic love for the ancient<lb break="yes"/>reigning family, he attaches to himself every species of talent, and extends with con-<lb break="no"/>fidence his royal protection to the free cultivation of the understanding.&#x2019;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Baron Humboldt&#x2019;s speech was followed by a paper on magnetism, by Professor<lb break="yes"/>Oersted, and several other memoirs were then read.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The arrival of so many persons of similar pursuit, (for four hundred and sixty-<lb break="no"/>four members were present) rendered it convenient to have some ordinary at which<lb break="yes"/>those who chose might dine, and introduce their friends and families. This had<lb break="yes"/>been foreseen and his Majesty had allowed the immense building used for the exer-<lb break="no" />cise of his troops to be used for this purpose. One third of it was floored on the<lb break="yes"/>occasion, and tables were arranged, at which on one occasion, eight hundred and<lb break="yes"/>fifty persons sat down to dinner. On the evening of the first day, M. de Humboldt<lb break="yes"/>gave a <hi rendition="#i">soiree</hi> in the concert rooms attached to the theatre. About twelve hundred<lb break="yes"/>persons assembled on this occasion, and the King of Prussia honored with his pre-<lb break="no"/>sence the <hi rendition="#i">fete</hi> of his illustrious Chamberlain. The nobility of the country, foreign<lb break="yes"/>princes, and foreign ambassadors were present. It was gratifying to observe the<lb break="yes"/>princes of the blood mingled with the cultivators of science, and to see the heir<lb break="yes"/>apparent to the throne engaged in conversation with those most celebrated for talents<lb break="yes"/>of his own or other countries. Nor were the minor arrangements of the evening<lb break="yes"/>beneath the consideration of the President. The words of the music, selected for<lb break="yes"/>the concert, were printed and distributed among the guests, The names of the most<lb break="yes"/>illustrious philosophers which Germany had produced, were inscribed in letters of<lb break="yes"/>gold at the end of the great concert room. In the first rank among these, stood a<lb break="yes"/>name which England too enrols among her brightest, and proud as she may well be<lb break="yes"/>of having fostered and brought to maturity the genius of the first Herschel, she has<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="223" facs="#f0005"/> reaped an ample reward in being able to claim entirely as her own the inheriter of<lb break="yes"/>his talents and his name.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The six succeeding days were occupied in the morning, by a meeting of the<lb break="yes"/>academy, at which papers of great interest were read. In the afternoon, through<lb break="yes"/>the arrangements of M. de Humboldt and M. Lichtenstein, various rooms were<lb break="yes"/>appropriated for different sections of the academy. In one the chemical philosophers<lb break="yes" />attended to some chemical memoir, whilst the botanists assembled in another room,<lb break="yes"/>the physiologists in a third, and the natural philosophers in a fourth. Each attended<lb break="yes"/>to the reading of papers connected with their several sciences. Thus every member<lb break="yes"/>was at liberty to choose that section in which he felt most interest at the moment,<lb break="yes"/>and had at all times access to the others. The evenings were generally spent at the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">soirees</hi> of the <hi rendition="#i">savans</hi>, resident at Berlin, whose hospitality and attentions to their<lb break="yes"/>learned brethren of other countries were unbounded. In the morning the collections<lb break="yes"/>of natural history, which are rapidly rising into importance, were open to examina-<lb break="no"/>tions, and the various professors and directors assisted the stranger in his inquiries.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A map of Europe was printed, on which those towns only appeared which had<lb break="yes"/>sent representatives to this scientific Congress; and the numbers sent by different<lb break="yes"/>kingdoms appeared by the following table, which was attached to it:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <list>
                    <item>Russia, 1</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Austria, 0</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>England, 1</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Holland, 2</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Denmark, 7</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>France, 1</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Sardina, 0</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Prussia, 95</item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <list>
                    <item>Bavaria, 12</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Hanover, 5</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Saxony, 21</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Wirtemburg, 12</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Sweden, 13</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Naples, 1</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Poland, 3</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>German States, <hi rendition="#u">43</hi>
                    </item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>217</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Berlin, <hi rendition="#u">172</hi>
                    </item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Total, 389<note place="foot" n="*">
                            <hi rendition="#i">Not one</hi> from America!</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The proportion in which the cultivators of different sciences appeared, was not<lb break="yes"/>easy to ascertain, because there were few among the more eminent who had not<lb break="yes"/>added to more than one branch of human knowledge. The following table, though<lb break="yes"/>not professing to be very accurate, will afford, perhaps, a tolerably fair view: &#x2014;<lb break="yes" />Geometers, 1; Astronomers, 5; Natural Philosophers, 23&#x2014;in all 39. Mines, 5;<lb break="yes"/>Mineralogy, 14; Geology, 9&#x2014;in all 30. Chemistry, 18; Geography, 8; Anatomy,<lb break="yes"/>12. Zoology, 14; Natural History, 8; and Botany, 35&#x2014;in all 57. Physicians,<lb break="yes"/>175. Amateurs, 9. Various, 33. Grand total, 381.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A medal was struck in commemoration of this meeting; and it was proposed that<lb break="yes"/>it should form the first of a series, comprising all those persons most celebrated for<lb break="yes"/>discoveries in the past and present age.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The American Lyceum, when its entire organization shall have been carried into<lb break="yes"/>practical effect, will present a bolder scene of moral sublimity than even the Con-<lb break="no"/>gress of Philosophers at Berlin. The wide spread materials for scientific and literary<lb break="yes"/>organization throughout our country demand immediate consideration.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 