<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="227" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Speech</hi> made at the opening of the Society of German Natu-<lb break="no"/>ralists and Natural Philosophers at Berlin, the 18th Septem-<lb break="no"/>ber 1828. By <hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von Humboldt.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Since through your choice, which does me so much honour,<lb break="yes"/>I am permitted to open this meeting, the first duty which I<lb break="yes"/>have to discharge is one of gratitude. The distinction which<lb break="yes"/>has been conferred on him who has never yet been able to at-<lb break="no"/>tend your excellent Society, is not the reward of scientific ef-<lb break="no"/>forts, or of feeble and persevering attempts to discover new<lb break="yes"/>phenomena, or to draw the light of knowledge from the unex-<lb break="no"/>plored depths of nature. A finer feeling, however, directed<lb break="yes"/>your attention to me. You have assured me, that while, dur-<lb break="no"/>ing an absence of many years, and in a distant quarter of the<lb break="yes"/>globe, I was labouring in the same cause with yourselves, I<lb break="yes"/>was not a stranger in your thoughts. You have likewise<lb break="yes"/>greeted my return home, that, by the sacred tie of gratitude,<lb break="yes"/>you might bind me still longer and closer to our common<lb break="yes"/>country.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>What, however, can the picture of this our native land pre-<lb break="no"/>sent more agreeable to the mind than the assembly which we<lb break="yes"/>receive to day for the first time within our walls; from the<lb break="yes"/>banks of the Neckar, the birth-place of Kepler and of Schiller,<lb break="yes"/>to the remotest border of the Baltic plains; from hence to the<lb break="yes"/>mouths of the Rhine, where, under the beneficent influence<lb break="yes"/>of commerce, the treasures of exotic nature have for centuries<lb break="yes"/>been collected and investigated, the friends of nature, inspired<lb break="yes"/>with the same zeal, and, urged by the same passion, flock toge-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="228" facs="#f0002"/> ther to this assembly. Everywhere, where the German lan-<lb break="no"/>guage is used, and its peculiar structure affects the spirit and<lb break="yes"/>disposition of the people. From the Great European Alps to<lb break="yes"/>the other side of the Weichsel, where, in the country of Co-<lb break="no"/>pernicus, astronomy rose to renewed splendour; everywhere<lb break="yes"/>in the extensive dominions of the German nation we attempt<lb break="yes"/>to discover the secret operations of nature, whether in the<lb break="yes"/>heavens, or in the deepest problems of mechanics, or in the in-<lb break="no"/>terior of the earth, or in the finely woven tissues of organic<lb break="yes"/>structure.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Protected by noble princes, this assembly has annually in-<lb break="no"/>creased in interest and extent. Every distinction which diffe-<lb break="no"/>rence of religion or form of government can occasion is here<lb break="yes"/>annulled. Germany manifests itself as it were in its intellec-<lb break="no"/>tual unity; and since knowledge of truth and performance of<lb break="yes"/>duty are the highest object of morality, that feeling of unity<lb break="yes"/>weakens none of the bonds which the religion, constitution,<lb break="yes"/>and laws of our country, have rendered dear to each of us.<lb break="yes"/>Even this emulation in mental struggles has called forth (as<lb break="yes"/>the glorious history of our country tells us,) the fairest blos-<lb break="no"/>soms of humanity, science, and art.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The assembly of German naturalists and natural philoso-<lb break="no"/>phers since its last meeting, when it was so hospitably received<lb break="yes"/>at Munich, has, through the flattering interest of neighbour-<lb break="no"/>ing States and Academies, shone with peculiar lustre. Allied<lb break="yes"/>nations have renewed the ancient alliance between Germany<lb break="yes"/>and the ancient Scandinavian North.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Such an interest deserves acknowledgment the more, be-<lb break="no"/>cause it unexpectedly increases the mass of facts and opinions<lb break="yes"/>which are here brought into one common and useful union. It<lb break="yes"/>also recalls lofty recollections into the mind of the naturalist.<lb break="yes"/>Scarcely half a century has elapsed since Linné appears in the<lb break="yes"/>boldness of the undertakings which he has attempted and ac-<lb break="no"/>complished, as one of the greatest men of the last century.<lb break="yes"/>His glory, however bright, has not rendered Europe blind to<lb break="yes"/>the merits of Scheele and Bergman. The catalogue of these<lb break="yes"/>great names is not completed; but lest I shall offend noble<lb break="yes"/>modesty, I dare not speak of the light which is still flowing<lb break="yes"/>in richest profusion from the North, nor mention the disco-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="229" facs="#f0003"/> veries in the chemical nature of substances, in the numerical<lb break="yes"/>relation of their elements, or the eddying streams of electro-<lb break="no"/>magnetic powers.<note place="foot" n="*">The philosophers here referred to are Berzelius and Oersted.</note> May those excellent persons, who, deter-<lb break="no"/>red neither by perils of sea or land, have hastened to our<lb break="yes"/>meeting from Sweden, Norway, Denmark, Holland, England,<lb break="yes"/>and Poland, point out the way to other strangers in succeed-<lb break="no"/>ing years, so that by turns every part of Germany may enjoy<lb break="yes"/>the effects of scientific communication with the different na-<lb break="no"/>tions of Europe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But although I must restrain the expression of my personal<lb break="yes" />feelings in presence of this assembly, I must be permitted at<lb break="yes" />least to name the patriarchs of our national glory, who are de-<lb break="no" />tained from us by a regard for those lives so dear to their coun-<lb break="no"/>try;&#x2014;Goethe, whom the great creations of poetical fancy have<lb break="yes"/>not prevented from penetrating the <hi rendition="#i" >arcana</hi> of nature, and who<lb break="yes"/>now in rural solitude mourns for his princely friend, as Ger-<lb break="no"/>many for one of her greatest ornaments;&#x2014;Olbers, who has dis-<lb break="no"/>covered two bodies where he had already predicted they were<lb break="yes"/>to be found;&#x2014;the greatest anatomists of our age&#x2014;Soemmer-<lb break="no"/>ing, who, with equal zeal, has investigated the wonders of or-<lb break="no"/>ganic structure, and the spots and <hi rendition="#i">facul&#x0153;</hi> of the sun, (con-<lb break="no"/>densations and openings in the photosphere;) Blumenbach,<lb break="yes"/>whose pupil I have the honour to be, who, by his works and<lb break="yes"/>his immortal eloquence, has inspired everywhere a love for<lb break="yes"/>comparative anatomy, physiology, and the general history<lb break="yes"/>of nature, and who has laboured diligently for half a cen-<lb break="no"/>tury. How could I resist the temptation to adorn my dis-<lb break="no"/>course with names which posterity will repeat, as we are not<lb break="yes"/>favoured with their presence?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These observations on the literary wealth of our native coun-<lb break="no"/>try, and the progressive developement of our institution, lead<lb break="yes"/>us naturally to the obstructions which will arise from the in-<lb break="no" />creasing number of our fellow-labourers. The chief ob-<lb break="no"/>ject of this assembly does not consist, as in other societies<lb break="yes"/>whose sphere is more limited, in the mutual interchange of<lb break="yes"/>treatises, or in innumerable memoirs, destined to be printed in<lb break="yes"/>some general collection. The principal object of this Society<lb break="yes"/>is to bring those personally together who are engaged in the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="230" facs="#f0004"/> same field of science. It is the immediate, and therefore more<lb break="yes"/>obvious interchange of ideas, whether they present themselves<lb break="yes"/>as facts, opinions, or doubts. It is the foundation of friendly<lb break="yes"/>connection which throws light on science, adds cheerfulness to<lb break="yes"/>life, and gives patience and amenity to the manners.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the most flourishing period of ancient Greece, the dis-<lb break="no" />tinction between words and writing first manifested itself most<lb break="yes" />strongly amongst a race, which had raised itself to the most<lb break="yes" />splendid intellectual superiority, and to whose latest descen-<lb break="no" />dants, as preserved from the shipwreck of nations, we still con-<lb break="no" />secrate our most anxious wishes. It was not the difficulty of<lb break="yes" />interchange of ideas alone, nor the want of German science,<lb break="yes" />which has spread thought as on wings through the world, and<lb break="yes" />insured it a long continuance, that then induced the friends of<lb break="yes" />philosophy and natural history in Magna Gr&#x00E6;cia and Asia<lb break="yes" />Minor to wander on long journies. That ancient race knew<lb break="yes"/>the inspiring influence of conversation as it extemporaneous-<lb break="no"/>ly, freely, and prudently penetrates the tissue of scientific opin-<lb break="no" />ions and doubts. The discovery of the truth without differ-<lb break="no" />ence of opinion is unattainable, because the truth in its great-<lb break="no" />est extent can never be recognized by all, and at the same time.<lb break="yes"/>Each step, which seems to bring the explorer of nature nearer<lb break="yes"/>to his object, only carries him to the threshold of new laby-<lb break="no"/>rinths. The mass of doubt does not diminish, but spreads<lb break="yes"/>like a moving cloud over other and new fields; and whoever<lb break="yes"/>has called that a golden period, when difference of opinions, or,<lb break="yes"/>as some are accustomed to express it, the disputes of the learn-<lb break="no"/>ed will be finished, has as imperfect a conception of the wants<lb break="yes"/>of science, and of its continued advancement, as a person who<lb break="yes"/>expects that the same opinions in geognosy, chemistry, or phy-<lb break="no"/>siology, will be maintained for several centuries.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The founders of this society, with a deep sense of the unity<lb break="yes"/>of nature, have combined in the completest manner all the<lb break="yes"/>branches of physical knowledge, and the historical, geometri-<lb break="no"/>cal, and experimental philosophy. The names of natural his-<lb break="no"/>torian and natural philosopher are here, therefore, nearly syno-<lb break="no"/>nymous, chained by a terrestrial link to the type of the lower<lb break="yes"/>animals. Man completes the scale of higher organization. In<lb break="yes"/>his physiological and pathological qualities, he scarcely pre-<lb break="no"/>sents to us a distinct class of beings. As to what has brought<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="231" facs="#f0005"/> him to this exalted object of physical study, and has raised<lb break="yes"/>him to general scientific investigation, belongs principally to<lb break="yes"/>this society. Important as it is not to break that link which<lb break="yes"/>embraces equally the investigation of organic and inorganic<lb break="yes"/>nature, still the increasing ties and daily development of<lb break="yes"/>this institution renders it necessary, besides the general meet-<lb break="no"/>ing which is destined for these halls, to have specific meetings<lb break="yes"/>for single branches of science. For it is only in such con-<lb break="no"/>tracted circles,&#x2014;it is only among men whom reciprocity of<lb break="yes"/>studies has brought together, that verbal discussions can take<lb break="yes"/>place: Without this sort of communication, would the volun-<lb break="no"/>tary association of men in search of truth be deprived of an in-<lb break="no"/>spiring principle.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Among the preparations which are made in this city for the<lb break="yes" />advancement of the society, attention has been principally paid<lb break="yes" />to the possibility of such a subdivision into sections. The hope<lb break="yes"/>that these preparations will meet with your approbation im-<lb break="no"/>poses upon me the duty of reminding you, that, although you<lb break="yes"/>had entrusted to two travellers, equally, the duty of making<lb break="yes"/>these arrangements, yet it is to one alone, my noble friend,<lb break="yes"/>M. Lichtenstein that the merit of careful precaution and in-<lb break="no"/>defatigable activity is due. Out of respect to the scientific<lb break="yes"/>spirit which animates the Society of German Naturalists and<lb break="yes"/>Natural Philosophy, and in acknowledgment of the utility of<lb break="yes"/>their efforts, government have seconded all our wishes with<lb break="yes"/>the greatest cheerfulness.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the vicinity of the place of meeting, which has in this<lb break="yes"/>manner been prepared for our general and special labours, are<lb break="yes"/>situated the museums dedicated to anatomy, zoology, oryc-<lb break="no"/>tognosy, and geology. They exhibit to the naturalist a rich<lb break="yes"/>mine for observation and critical discussion. The greater num-<lb break="no"/>ber of these well arranged collections have existed, like the<lb break="yes" />University of Berlin, scarcely twenty years. The oldest of<lb break="yes" />them, to which the Botanical Garden (one of the richest in Eu-<lb break="no" />rope) belongs, have during this period not only been increas-<lb break="no" />ed, but entirely remodelled. The amusement and instruction<lb break="yes" />derived from such institutions call to our minds, with deep<lb break="yes" />feelings of gratitude, that they are the work of that great mo-<lb break="no" />narch, who modestly and in simple grandeur, adorns every year<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="232" facs="#f0006"/> this royal city with new treasures of nature and art; and what<lb break="yes"/>is of still greater value than the treasures themselves,&#x2014;what<lb break="yes"/>inspires every Prussian with youthful strength, and with an<lb break="yes"/>enthusiastic love for the ancient reigning family,&#x2014;that he gra-<lb break="no"/>ciously attaches to himself every species of talent, and extends<lb break="yes"/>with confidence his royal protection to the free cultivation of<lb break="yes"/>the understanding.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 