<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="213" facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#k">In</hi> presenting to my readers the account of the<lb break="yes"/>meeting of men of science at Berlin, in the autumn of<lb break="yes"/>1828, I am happy to be able to state, that its influence<lb break="yes"/>has been most beneficial, and that the annual meeting<lb break="yes"/>to be held in 1831, will take place at Vienna, the<lb break="yes" />Emperor of Austria having expressed a wish that every<lb break="yes"/>facility which his capital affords should be given to<lb break="yes"/>promote its objects.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>It is gratifying to find that a country, which has<lb break="yes"/>hitherto been considered adverse to the progress of<lb break="yes"/>knowledge, should become convinced of its value; and<lb break="yes"/>it is sincerely to be hoped, that every one of the nume-<lb break="no"/>rous members of the Society will show, by his conduct,<lb break="yes"/>that the paths of science are less likely than any others<lb break="yes"/>to interfere with those of politics.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Account of the great Congress of Philosophers at Berlin, on<lb break="yes"/>the</hi>
                    <date>18<hi rendition="#i">th of September</hi>, 1828.</date> From the Edinburgh Jour-<lb break="no"/>nal of Science, April, 1829.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> existence of a large society of cultivators of the natural<lb break="yes"/>sciences meeting annually at some great capital, or some<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="214" facs="#f0002"/> central town of Europe, is a circumstance almost unknown to<lb break="yes"/>us, and deserving of our attention, from the important ad-<lb break="no"/>vantages which may arise from it.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>About eight years ago, Dr. Okens, of Munich, suggested<lb break="yes"/>a plan for an annual meeting of all Germans who cultivated<lb break="yes"/>the sciences of medicine and botany. The first meeting, of<lb break="yes"/>about forty members, took place at Leipsic, in 1822, and it<lb break="yes"/>was successively held at Halle, Wurtzburg, Frankfort on the<lb break="yes"/>Maine, Dresden, Munich, and Berlin. All those who had<lb break="yes"/>printed a certain number of sheets of their inquiries on<lb break="yes"/>these subjects were considered members of this academy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The great advantages which resulted to these sciences<lb break="yes"/>from the communication of observations from all quarters<lb break="yes"/>of Germany, soon induced an extension of the plan, and<lb break="yes"/>other departments of natural knowledge were admitted,<lb break="yes"/>until, at the last meeting, the cultivators even of pure ma-<lb break="no"/>thematics were found amongst the ranks of this academy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Several circumstances, independent of the form and con-<lb break="no"/>stitution of the academy, contributed to give unwonted<lb break="yes"/>splendour to the last meeting, which took place at Berlin in<lb break="yes"/>the middle of September of the last year.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The capital selected for its temporary residence is scarcely<lb break="yes" />surpassed by any in Europe in the number and celebrity of<lb break="yes"/>its savans.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The taste for knowledge possessed by the reigning family,<lb break="yes"/>has made knowledge itself fashionable; and the severe<lb break="yes"/>sufferings of the Prussians previous to the war, by which<lb break="yes"/>themselves and Europe were freed, have impressed on them<lb break="yes"/>so strongly the lesson that &#x201C;knowledge is power,&#x201D; that its<lb break="yes"/>effects are visible in every department of the government;<lb break="yes"/>and there is no country in Europe in which talents and<lb break="yes"/>genius so surely open for their possessors the road to wealth<lb break="yes"/>and distinction.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Another circumstance also contributed its portion to in-<lb break="no"/>crease the numbers of the meeting of the past year. The<lb break="yes"/>office of president, which is annually changed, was assigned<lb break="yes"/>to M. Alexander de Humboldt. The universality of his<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="215" facs="#f0003"/> acquirements, which have left no branch within the wide<lb break="yes"/>range of science indifferent or unexplored, has connected<lb break="yes"/>him by friendship with almost all the most celebrated phi-<lb break="no"/>losophers of the age; whilst the polished amenity of his<lb break="yes"/>manners, and that intense desire of acquiring and of spread-<lb break="no"/>ing knowledge, which so peculiarly characterizes his mind,<lb break="yes"/>renders him accessible to all strangers, and insures for them<lb break="yes"/>the assistance of his counsel in their scientific pursuits, and<lb break="yes"/>the advantage of being made known to all those who are<lb break="yes"/>interested or occupied in similar inquiries.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Professor Lichtenstein, (Director of the Museum of Zoo-<lb break="no"/>logy,) as secretary of the academy, was indefatigable in his<lb break="yes"/>attentions, and most ably seconded the wishes of its distin-<lb break="no"/>guished president.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These two gentlemen, assisted by several of the residents<lb break="yes"/>at Berlin, undertook the numerous preliminary arrangements<lb break="yes" />necessary for the accommodation of the meeting.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On the 18th of September, 1828, there were assembled at<lb break="yes"/>Berlin 377 members of the academy, whose names and<lb break="yes"/>residences (in Berlin) were printed in a small pamphlet, and<lb break="yes"/>to each name was attached a number, to indicate his seat in<lb break="yes"/>the great concert room, in which the morning meetings took<lb break="yes"/>place. Each member was also provided with an engraved<lb break="yes"/>card of the hall of meeting, on which the numbers of the<lb break="yes"/>seats were printed in black ink, and his own peculiar seat<lb break="yes"/>marked in red ink, so that every person immediately found<lb break="yes"/>his own place, and knew where to look for any friend whom<lb break="yes"/>he might wish to find.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the hour appointed for the opening of the meeting,<lb break="yes"/>the members being assembled, and the galleries and or-<lb break="no"/>chestra being filled by an assemblage of a large part of<lb break="yes"/>the rank and beauty of the capital, and the side-boxes being<lb break="yes"/>occupied by several branches of the royal family, and by the<lb break="yes"/>foreign ambassadors, the session of the academy was opened<lb break="yes"/>by the eloquent address of the president.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="216" facs="#f0004"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Speech</hi> made at the Opening of the Society of German Natu-<lb break="no"/>ralists and Natural Philosophers at Berlin, the 18th of<lb break="yes"/>September, 1828. By <hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von Humboldt</hi>.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Since through your choice, which does me so much ho-<lb break="no"/>nour, I am permitted to open this meeting, the first duty<lb break="yes"/>which I have to discharge is one of gratitude. The dis-<lb break="no"/>tinction which has been conferred on him who has never yet<lb break="yes"/>been able to attend your excellent society, is not the reward<lb break="yes"/>of scientific efforts, or of feeble and persevering attempts to<lb break="yes"/>discover new phenomena, or to draw the light of knowledge<lb break="yes"/>from the unexplored depths of nature. A finer feeling,<lb break="yes"/>however, directed your attention to me. You have assured<lb break="yes"/>me, that while, during an absence of many years, and in a<lb break="yes"/>distant quarter of the globe, I was labouring in the same<lb break="yes"/>cause with yourselves, I was not a stranger in your thoughts.<lb break="yes"/>You have likewise greeted my return home, that, by the<lb break="yes"/>sacred tie of gratitude, you might bind me still longer and<lb break="yes"/>closer to our common country.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>What, however, can the picture of this, our native land-<lb break="no"/>present more agreeable to the mind, than the assembly which<lb break="yes"/>we receive to-day for the first time within our walls; from<lb break="yes"/>the banks of the Neckar, the birth-place of Kepler and of<lb break="yes"/>Schiller, to the remotest border of the Baltic plains; from<lb break="yes"/>hence to the mouths of the Rhine, where, under the benefi-<lb break="no"/>cent influence of commerce, the treasuries of exotic nature<lb break="yes"/>have for centuries been collected and investigated, the friends<lb break="yes"/>of nature, inspired with the same zeal, and, urged by the<lb break="yes"/>same passion, flock together to this assembly. Everywhere,<lb break="yes"/>where the German language is used, and its peculiar struc-<lb break="no"/>ture affects the spirit and disposition of the people. From<lb break="yes"/>the Great European Alps, to the other side of the Weichsel,<lb break="yes"/>where, in the country of Copernicus, astronomy rose to<lb break="yes"/>renewed splendour; everywhere in the extensive domi-<lb break="no"/>nions of the German nation we attempt to discover the secret<lb break="yes"/>operations of nature, whether in the heavens, or in the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="217" facs="#f0005"/> deepest problems of mechanics, or in the interior of the earth,<lb break="yes"/>or in the finely woven tissues of organic structure.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Protected by noble princes, this assembly has annually<lb break="yes"/>increased in interest and extent. Every distinction which<lb break="yes"/>difference of religion or form of government can occasion is<lb break="yes"/>here annulled. Germany manifests itself as it were in its<lb break="yes"/>intellectual unity; and since knowledge of truth and per-<lb break="no"/>formance of duty are the highest object of morality, that<lb break="yes"/>feeling of unity weakens none of the bonds which the religion,<lb break="yes"/>constitution, and laws of our country, have rendered dear to<lb break="yes"/>each of us. Even this emulation in mental struggles has<lb break="yes"/>called forth (as the glorious history of our country tells us,)<lb break="yes"/>the fairest blossoms of humanity, science, and art.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The assembly of German naturalists and natural philo-<lb break="no"/>sophers since its last meeting, when it was so hospitably<lb break="yes"/>received at Munich, has, through the flattering interest of<lb break="yes"/>neighbouring states and academies, shone with peculiar<lb break="yes"/>lustre. Allied nations have renewed the ancient alliance<lb break="yes"/>between Germany and the ancient Scandinavian North.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Such an interest deserves acknowledgment the more, be-<lb break="no"/>cause it unexpectedly increases the mass of facts and opi-<lb break="no"/>nions which are here brought into one common and useful<lb break="yes"/>union. It also recalls lofty recollections into the mind of the<lb break="yes"/>naturalist. Scarcely half a century has elapsed since Linné<lb break="yes"/>appears, in the boldness of the undertakings which he has<lb break="yes"/>attempted and accomplished, as one of the greatest men of<lb break="yes"/>the last century. His glory, however bright, has not ren-<lb break="no"/>dered Europe blind to the merits of Scheele and Bergman.<lb break="yes"/>The catalogue of these great names is not completed; but<lb break="yes"/>lest I shall offend noble modesty, I dare not speak of the light<lb break="yes"/>which is still flowing in richest profusion from the North,<lb break="yes"/>nor mention the discoveries in the chemical nature of sub-<lb break="no"/>stances, in the numerical relation of their elements, or the<lb break="yes"/>eddying streams of electro-magnetic powers.<note place="foot" n="*">The philosophers here referred to are Berzelius and Oersted.</note> May those<lb break="yes"/>excellent persons, who, deterred neither by perils of sea or<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="218" facs="#f0006"/> land, have hastened to our meeting from Sweden, Norway,<lb break="yes"/>Denmark, Holland, England, and Poland, point out the way<lb break="yes"/>to other strangers in succeeding years, so that by turns<lb break="yes"/>every part of Germany may enjoy the effects of scientific<lb break="yes"/>communication with the different nations of Europe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But although I must restrain the expression of my per-<lb break="no"/>sonal feelings in presence of this assembly, I must be per-<lb break="no"/>mitted at least to name the patriarchs of our national glory,<lb break="yes"/>who are detained from us by a regard for those lives so dear<lb break="yes"/>to their country; &#x2014;Goethe, whom the great creations of<lb break="yes"/>poetical fancy have not prevented from penetrating the <hi rendition="#i">arcana</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>of nature, and who now in rural solitude mourns for his<lb break="yes"/>princely friend, as Germany for one of her greatest orna-<lb break="no"/>ments; &#x2014;Olbers, who has discovered two bodies where he<lb break="yes"/>had already predicted they were to be found; &#x2014;the greatest<lb break="yes"/>anatomists of our age&#x2014;Soemmering, who, with equal zeal,<lb break="yes"/>has investigated the wonders of organic structure, and the<lb break="yes"/>spots and <hi rendition="#i">facul&#x0153;</hi> of the sun, (condensations and openings<lb break="yes"/>of the photosphere;) Blumenbach, whose pupil I have the<lb break="yes"/>honour to be, who, by his works and his immortal eloquence,<lb break="yes"/>has inspired everywhere a love of comparative anatomy,<lb break="yes"/>physiology, and the general history of nature, and who has<lb break="yes"/>laboured diligently for half a century. How could I resist<lb break="yes"/>the temptation to adorn my discourse with names which<lb break="yes"/>posterity will repeat, as we are not favoured with their<lb break="yes"/>presence?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These observations on the literary wealth of our native<lb break="yes"/>country, and the progressive developement of our institution,<lb break="yes"/>lead us naturally to the obstructions which will arise from<lb break="yes"/>the increasing number of our fellow-labourers. The chief<lb break="yes"/>object of this assembly does not consist, as in other societies<lb break="yes"/>whose sphere is more limited, in the mutual interchange of<lb break="yes"/>treatises, or in innumerable memoirs, destined to be printed<lb break="yes"/>in some general collection. The principal object of this<lb break="yes"/>Society is, to bring those personally together who are en-<lb break="no"/>gaged in the same field of science. It is the immediate, and<lb break="yes"/>therefore more obvious interchange of ideas, whether they<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="219" facs="#f0007"/> present themselves as facts, opinions, or doubts. It is the<lb break="yes"/>foundation of friendly connexion which throws light on<lb break="yes"/>science, adds cheerfulness to life, and gives patience and<lb break="yes"/>amenity to the manners.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the most flourishing period of ancient Greece, the dis-<lb break="no" />tinction between words and writing first manifested itself<lb break="yes" />most strongly amongst a race, which had raised itself to the<lb break="yes" />most splendid intellectual superiority, and to whose latest<lb break="yes" />descendants, as preserved from the shipwreck of nations, we<lb break="yes" />still consecrate our most anxious wishes. It was not the<lb break="yes" />difficulty of interchange of ideas alone, nor the want of Ger-<lb break="no" />man science, which has spread thought as on wings through<lb break="yes"/>the world, and insured it a long continuance, that then<lb break="yes"/>induced the friends of philosophy and natural history in<lb break="yes"/>Magna Gr&#x00E6;cia and Asia Minor to wander on long journeys.<lb break="yes"/>That ancient race knew the inspiring influence of conver-<lb break="no"/>sation as it extemporaneously, freely, and prudently pene-<lb break="no"/>trates the tissue of scientific opinions and doubts. The<lb break="yes"/>discovery of the truth without difference of opinion is unat-<lb break="no"/>tainable, because the truth, in its greatest extent, can never<lb break="yes"/>be recognized by all, and at the same time. Each step,<lb break="yes"/>which seems to bring the explorer of nature nearer to his<lb break="yes"/>object, only carries him to the threshold of new labyrinths.<lb break="yes"/>The mass of doubt does not diminish, but spreads like a<lb break="yes"/>moving cloud over other and new fields; and whoever has<lb break="yes"/>called that a golden period, when difference of opinions, or,<lb break="yes"/>as some are accustomed to express it, the disputes of the<lb break="yes"/>learned, will be finished, has as imperfect a conception of the<lb break="yes"/>wants of science, and of its continued advancement, as a<lb break="yes"/>person who expects that the same opinions in geognosy,<lb break="yes"/>chemistry, or physiology, will be maintained for several cen-<lb break="no"/>turies.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The founders of this society, with a deep sense of the<lb break="yes"/>unity of nature, have combined in the completest manner,<lb break="yes"/>all the branches of physical knowledge, and the historical,<lb break="yes"/>geometrical, and experimental philosophy. The names of<lb break="yes"/>natural historian and natural philosopher are here, therefore,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="220" facs="#f0008"/> nearly synonimous, chained by a terrestrial link to the type<lb break="yes"/>of the lower animals. Man completes the scale of higher<lb break="yes"/>organization. In his physiological and pathological qua-<lb break="no"/>lities, he scarcely presents to us a distinct class of beings.<lb break="yes"/>As to what has brought him to this exalted object of phy-<lb break="no"/>sical study, and has raised him to general scientific inves-<lb break="no"/>tigation, belongs principally to this society. Important as<lb break="yes"/>it is not to break that link which embraces equally the inves-<lb break="no"/>tigation of organic and inorganic nature, still the increasing<lb break="yes"/>ties and daily developement of this institution renders it<lb break="yes"/>necessary, besides the general meeting which is destined for<lb break="yes"/>these halls, to have specific meetings for single branches of<lb break="yes"/>science. For it is only in such contracted circles, &#x2014; it is only<lb break="yes"/>among men whom reciprocity of studies has brought toge-<lb break="no"/>ther, that verbal discussions can take place. Without this<lb break="yes"/>sort of communication, would the voluntary association of<lb break="yes"/>men in search of truth be deprived of an inspiring principle.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Among the preparations which are made in this city for<lb break="yes"/>the advancement of the society, attention has been prin-<lb break="no"/>cipally paid to the possibility of such a subdivision into<lb break="yes"/>sections. The hope that these preparations will meet with<lb break="yes"/>your approbation, imposes upon me the duty of reminding<lb break="yes"/>you, that, although you had entrusted to two travellers,<lb break="yes"/>equally, the duty of making these arrangements, yet it is to<lb break="yes"/>one alone, my noble friend, M. Lichtenstein, that the merit<lb break="yes"/>of careful precaution and indefatigable activity is due. Out<lb break="yes"/>of respect to the scientific spirit which animates the Society<lb break="yes"/>of German Naturalists and Natural Philosophy, and in<lb break="yes"/>acknowledgment of the utility of their efforts, government<lb break="yes"/>have seconded all our wishes with the greatest cheerfulness.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the vicinity of the place of meeting, which has in this<lb break="yes"/>manner been prepared for our general and special labours,<lb break="yes"/>are situated the museums dedicated to anatomy, zoology,<lb break="yes"/>oryctognosy, and geology. They exhibit to the naturalist a<lb break="yes"/>rich mine for observation and critical discussion. The<lb break="yes"/>greater number of these well-arranged collections have<lb break="yes"/>existed, like the University of Berlin, scarcely twenty years.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="221" facs="#f0009"/> The oldest of them, to which the Botanical Garden, (one of<lb break="yes"/>the richest in Europe) belongs, have during this period not<lb break="yes"/>only been increased, but entirely remodelled. The amuse-<lb break="no"/>ment and instruction derived from such institutions, call to<lb break="yes"/>our minds, with deep feelings of gratitude, that they are the<lb break="yes"/>work of that great monarch, who modestly and in simple<lb break="yes"/>grandeur, adorns every year this royal city with new trea-<lb break="no"/>sures of nature and art; and what is of still greater value<lb break="yes"/>than the treasures themselves, &#x2014; what inspires every Prussian<lb break="yes"/>with youthful strength, and with an enthusiastic love for<lb break="yes"/>the ancient reigning family, &#x2014;that he graciously attaches to<lb break="yes"/>himself every species of talent, and extends with confidence<lb break="yes"/>his royal protection to the free cultivation of the under-<lb break="no"/>standing.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This was followed by a paper on magnetism, by Professor<lb break="yes"/>Oersted; and several other memoirs were then read.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The arrival of so many persons of similar pursuit, (for 464<lb break="yes" />members were present,) rendered it convenient to have some<lb break="yes" />ordinary, at which those who chose might dine, and intro-<lb break="no"/>duce their friends or families. This had been foreseen, and<lb break="yes"/>his Majesty had condescended to allow the immense build-<lb break="no"/>ing used for the exercise of his troops, to be employed for<lb break="yes"/>this purpose. One-third of it was floored on the occasion,<lb break="yes"/>and tables were arranged, at which, on one occasion, 850<lb break="yes"/>persons sat down to dinner. On the evening of the first<lb break="yes"/>day, M. de Humboldt gave a large <hi rendition="#i">soirée</hi> in the concert<lb break="yes"/>rooms attached to the theatre. About 1200 persons assem-<lb break="no"/>bled on this occasion, and his Majesty the King of Prussia<lb break="yes"/>honoured with his presence the f&#x00EA;te of his illustrious cham-<lb break="no"/>berlain. The nobility of the country, foreign princes, and<lb break="yes"/>foreign ambassadors, were present. It was gratifying to<lb break="yes"/>observe the princes of the blood mingling with the culti-<lb break="no"/>vators of science, and to see the heir-apparent to the throne,<lb break="yes"/>during the course of the evening, engaged in conversation<lb break="yes"/>with those most celebrated for their talents, of his own, or<lb break="yes"/>of other countries.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="222" facs="#f0010"/>
                <p>Nor were the minor arrangements of the evening beneath<lb break="yes"/>the consideration of the President. The words of the music<lb break="yes"/>selected for the concert, were printed and distributed to the<lb break="yes"/>visitors. The names of the most illustrious philosophers<lb break="yes"/>which Germany had produced, were inscribed in letters of<lb break="yes"/>gold at the end of the great concert room.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the first rank amongst these stood a name which,<lb break="yes"/>England, too, enrolls amongst the brightest in her scientific<lb break="yes"/>annals; and proud, as well she may be, of having fostered<lb break="yes"/>and brought to maturity the genius of the first Herschel, she<lb break="yes"/>has reaped an ample reward in being able to claim as entirely<lb break="yes"/>her own, the inheritor of his talents and his name.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The six succeeding days were occupied, in the morning, by<lb break="yes"/>a meeting of the academy, at which papers of general interest<lb break="yes"/>were read. In the afternoon, through the arrangement of<lb break="yes"/>M. de Humboldt and M. Lichtenstein, various rooms were<lb break="yes"/>appropriated for different sections of the academy. In one,<lb break="yes"/>the chemical philosophers attended to some chemical me-<lb break="no"/>moir, whilst the botanists assembled in another room, the<lb break="yes"/>physiologists in a third, and the natural philosophers in a<lb break="yes"/>fourth. Each attended to the reading of papers connected<lb break="yes"/>with their several sciences. Thus every member was at<lb break="yes"/>liberty to choose that section in which he felt most interest<lb break="yes"/>at the moment, and he had at all times power of access to<lb break="yes"/>the others. The evenings were generally spent at some<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i">soirées</hi> of the savans, resident at Berlin, whose hos-<lb break="no"/>pitality and attentions to their learned brethren of other<lb break="yes"/>countries were unbounded. During the unoccupied hours<lb break="yes"/>of the morning, the collections of natural history, which are<lb break="yes"/>rapidly rising into importance, were open to examination;<lb break="yes"/>and the various professors and directors who assisted the<lb break="yes"/>stranger in his inquiries, left him equally gratified by the<lb break="yes"/>knowledge and urbanity of those who so kindly aided him.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A map of Europe was printed, on which those towns only<lb break="yes"/>appeared which had sent representatives to this scientific<lb break="yes"/>congress; and the numbers sent by different kingdoms<lb break="yes"/>appeared by the following table, which was attached to it: &#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="223" facs="#f0011"/>
                <cb/>
                <list>
                    <item>Russia ...... 1</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Austria ..... 0</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>England ..... 1</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Holland ..... 2</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Denmark ..... 7</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>France ..... 1</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Sardinia ..... 0</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Prussia ..... 95</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Bavaria ..... 12</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Hanover ..... 5</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Saxony ..... 21</item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <list>
                    <item>Wirtemburg .... 2</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Sweden ..... 13</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Naples ..... 1</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Poland ..... 3</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>German States ... <hi rendition="#u">43</hi>
                    </item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>206</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Berlin ... <hi rendition="#u">172</hi>
                    </item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>
                        <hi rendition="#u">378</hi>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The proportion in which the cultivators of different<lb break="yes"/>sciences appeared, was not easy to ascertain, because there<lb break="yes"/>were few amongst the more eminent who had not added to<lb break="yes"/>more than one branch of human knowledge. The following<lb break="yes"/>table, though not professing to be very accurate, will afford,<lb break="yes"/>perhaps, a tolerably fair view: &#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <list>
                    <item>Geometers ... 11</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Astronomers .. 5</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Natural Philosophers 23</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>&#x2014; 39</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Mines ..... 5</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Mineralogy ... 16</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Geology .... 9</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>&#x2014; 30</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Chemistry ... 18</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Geography ... 8</item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <list>
                    <item>Anatomy .... 12</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Zoology .... 14</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Natural History . 8</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Botany .... 35</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>&#x2014; 57</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Physicians .... 175</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Amateurs .... 9</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Various .... <hi rendition="#u">33</hi>
                    </item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>381</item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A medal was struck in commemoration of this meeting,<lb break="yes"/>and it was proposed that it should form the first of a series,<lb break="yes"/>which should comprise all those persons most celebrated for<lb break="yes"/>their scientific discoveries in the past and present age.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 