<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On the Luminousness of the Ocean</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:02</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.89</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1828-On_the_Luminousness-1-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1828-On_the_Luminousness-1-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-On_the_Luminousness-2.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1828-On_the_Luminousness-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Ansichten der Natur&lt;i&gt;, Stuttgart und Tübingen: Cotta 1808, S. 219–226, Anmerkung 5.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On the Luminousness of the Ocean</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1828</date>
          <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in:&lt;i&gt; The Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal&lt;/i&gt; (Juli–September 1828), S. 329–331.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="329" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Luminousness of the Ocean.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#in">T</hi>he</hi> luminousness of the ocean is one of the most beautiful<lb break="yes"/>phenomena of nature, which excites surprise, although, for<lb break="yes"/>months together, it may be seen every night. The sea is phos-<lb break="no"/>phorescent in all latitudes; but he who has not witnessed this<lb break="yes"/>phenomenon in the torrid zone, and especially in the Pacific<lb break="yes"/>Ocean, can form but an imperfect idea of the magnificence of<lb break="yes"/>such a spectacle. When a vessel of war, impelled by a fresh<lb break="yes"/>breeze, cleaves the foamy waves, and one is stationed near the<lb break="yes"/>shrouds, he cannot be satisfied with viewing the beautiful phe-<lb break="no"/>nomenon which presents itself. Every time that the side of the<lb break="yes"/>ship, as she rolls, emerges from the water, flashes of reddish<lb break="yes"/>light seem to issue from the keel, and dart toward the surface<lb break="yes"/>of the sea. Le Gentil<note place="foot" n="*">Voyage aux Indes, t. i. p. 685&#x2012;698.</note> and the elder Forster <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Observations made during a voyage round the world, 1683, p. 57. In<lb break="yes"/>German.</note>, explained the<lb break="yes" />appearance of these flashes by the electrical friction of the water<lb break="yes"/>against the body of the advancing ship. But in the present<lb break="yes"/>state of our knowledge, this explanation is no longer admissible.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There are few points of natural history respecting which there<lb break="yes" />have been so many disputes as the light emitted by the waters<lb break="yes" />of the ocean. What we know with precision on the subject, re-<lb break="no" />duces itself to the following facts. There are various shining<lb break="yes" />mollusca which, during their life, emit at pleasure a rather weak<lb break="yes"/>phosphoric light, generally of a bluish colour. This is observed<lb break="yes"/>in the <hi rendition="#i">Nereis noctiluca</hi>, the <hi rendition="#i">Medusa pelagica</hi>, var. &#x03B2;<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Forskoe, Fauna &#x00C6;gyptiaco-Arabica, p. 109.</note>, and the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Monephora noctiluca</hi>, discovered during Captain Baudin&#x2019;s expe-<lb break="no"/>dition <note place="foot" n="&#x2016;">Bory St Vincent, Voyage aux Iles d&#x2019;Afrique, t. i. p. 107, pl. 6.</note>. Of this number are also the microscopic animals,<lb break="yes"/>which have not as yet been determined, and which Forster saw<lb break="yes"/>swimming in the sea in innumerable multitudes, near the Cape<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="330" facs="#f0002"/> of Good Hope. The luminousness of sea water is sometimes<lb break="yes"/>occasioned by these living lanterns. I say sometimes; for, in<lb break="yes"/>most cases, notwithstanding the use of magnifying glasses, no<lb break="yes"/>animal is perceived in luminous water; and yet, whenever the<lb break="yes"/>wave happens to strike a hard body and breaks, producing foam,<lb break="yes"/>and whenever the water is strongly agitated, a light is produced<lb break="yes"/>resembling a flash of lightning. This phenomenon probably<lb break="yes"/>originates from the decomposed fibrils of dead mollusca which<lb break="yes"/>exist in infinite quantity in the depths of the sea. When this<lb break="yes"/>luminous water is passed through a piece of dense cloth, these<lb break="yes"/>fibrils are sometimes detached from it under the form of lumi-<lb break="no"/>nous points. When we bathed in the evening in the Gulf of<lb break="yes"/>Cariaco, near Cumana, some parts of our bodies remained lumi-<lb break="no"/>nous on coming out of the water. The luminous fibres stuck to<lb break="yes"/>the skin. From the immense quantity of mollusca dispersed<lb break="yes"/>through all the seas of the torrid zone, it need not be surprising<lb break="yes"/>that the water of the sea is luminous, even when no organic<lb break="yes"/>matter can be separated from it. The infinite division of all the<lb break="yes"/>dead bodies of dagyses<note place="foot" n="*">The genus Dagysa belongs to the Salpa tribe of Cuvier.</note> and medus&#x00E6; may render the entire sea<lb break="yes" />capable of being considered as a gelatinous fluid, and which is in<lb break="yes"/>consequence luminous, has a nauseous taste, cannot be drunk by<lb break="yes"/>man, but affords nourishment to many fishes. If a board be<lb break="yes"/>rubbed with a part of the body of the Medusa hysocella, the<lb break="yes"/>place rubbed becomes luminous whenever the finger, well dried,<lb break="yes"/>is passed over it. During my passage to South America, I<lb break="yes"/>sometimes put a medusa on a tin plate. If I struck the plate<lb break="yes"/>with another metal, the smallest vibrations of the tin were suf-<lb break="no"/>ficient to make the animal shine. How did the blow and the<lb break="yes"/>vibration act in this case? Was the temperature instantaneous-<lb break="no"/>ly raised? Were new surfaces uncovered, or did the blow<lb break="yes"/>make the phosphuretted hydrogen gas escape, so that, coming<lb break="yes"/>into contact with the oxygen of the atmosphere, or with the wa-<lb break="no"/>ter of the sea, it produced combustion? This effect of the blow<lb break="yes"/>which excites the light is particularly striking in a jumbling sea,<lb break="yes"/>when the waves dash against each other in all directions. Be-<lb break="no"/>tween the tropics, I have seen the sea luminous at all tempera-<lb break="no"/>tures; but it was more so before storms, or when the sky was<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="331" facs="#f0003"/> lowering, cloudy, and much overcast. Cold and heat seem to have<lb break="yes"/>little influence upon this phenomenon; for, on the Bank of New-<lb break="no"/>foundland, the phosphorescence is often very strong at the se-<lb break="no"/>verest time of the winter. Sometimes, all other circumstances<lb break="yes"/>appearing to be the same, the phosphorescence is very distinct<lb break="yes"/>on one night, and the following night there is scarcely any.<lb break="yes"/>Does the atmosphere favour this disengagement of light, this<lb break="yes"/>combustion of phosphuretted hydrogen? Or do not these dif-<lb break="no"/>ferences depend merely upon chance, which leads the navigator<lb break="yes"/>into a sea more or less filled with mollusca? Perhaps, also, the<lb break="yes"/>luminous animals only come to the surface of the sea when the<lb break="yes"/>atmosphere is in a certain state. M. Bory St. Vincent, asks<lb break="yes"/>with reason, why our fresh marsh-water, which is filled with po-<lb break="no"/>lypi, is not luminous? It would appear in fact, that a particu-<lb break="no"/>lar mixture of organic particles is necessary to favour this dis-<lb break="no"/>engagement of light. Willow-wood is more phosphorescent<lb break="yes"/>than oak. In England, salt-water has been rendered luminous<lb break="yes"/>by casting herring brine into it. Galvanic experiments shew<lb break="yes"/>that the luminous state of living animals depends upon an irri-<lb break="no"/>tation of the nerves. I have seen an <hi rendition="#i">Elater noctilucus</hi>, which<lb break="yes"/>died, diffuse a strong glow when I touched its anterior extremi-<lb break="no"/>ties with tin or silver. Sometimes, also, the medus&#x00E6; give out a<lb break="yes"/>stronger light at the moment when the galvanic chain is closed.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Humboldt, Tableaux de la Nature</hi>, tom. ii. p. 80&#x2012;87.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 