<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1">

<div n="2"><head><hi rendition="#i">BARON HUMBOLDT.</hi></head><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<p>Baron Alexander Humboldt, the celebrated traveller, having<lb/>opened a public course of physical geography at Berlin, was said<lb/>in a German paper to have commenced subscription lectures, and<lb/>to have demanded 3<hi rendition="#i">l.</hi> for each admission ticket. The <hi rendition="#i">Moniteur</hi><lb/>copied this statement, and thus spread it over Europe. The<lb/>Baron, who was instructing the public without any remunera-<lb/>tion from the purse of individuals, has addressed the following<lb/>letter to the French official journal, contradicting the false report.<lb/>As we have mentioned the object of the correction, we may give<lb/>the letter itself in the original.&#x2014;</p></div></div><lb/><div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">a monsieur le redacteur du moniteur universel.</hi></head><lb/><p>J&#x2019;ai lu avec la plus grande surprise dans votre Journal du 7<lb/>Février, Monsieur, que j&#x2019;ai ouvert des cours de géographie phy-<lb/>sique à Berlin par souscription, &#x201C;le cachet se payant trois louis.&#x201D;<lb/>Vous donnez cette nouvelle sur la foi d&#x2019;un journal étranger, qui<lb/>m&#x2019;est resté inconnu jusqu&#x2019;ici. J&#x2019;ose croire, que toute reintation<lb/>est superflue pour la France, ou j&#x2019;ai résidé si longtems: mais le<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Moniteur</hi> étant répandu dans les deux mondes, j&#x2019;ai pensé devoir<lb/>signaler la fausseté et l&#x2019;inconvenance d&#x2019;une assertion, dont je ne<lb/>veux point examiner les metifs. J&#x2019;ai onvert deux cours publics,<lb/>et en Allemagne, comme en France, on ne paye pas, pour<lb/>obtenir le droit d&#x2019;assister à un cours public.</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#c">A@réez, Monsieur, ect.</hi></p><lb/><dateline>Berlin le 23 Février, 1828.</dateline><closer><salute>A. DE HUMBOLDT.</salute></closer></div><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
