<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="85" facs="#f0001"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Bericht ueber die Versammlung Deutscher Natur-<lb break="no" />forscher und Aerzte in Heidelberg, in September,</hi> 1829.<lb break="yes" />Von F. <hi rendition="#k">Tiedemann</hi> und L. <hi rendition="#k" >Gmelin.</hi> [Report of the<lb break="yes"/>Proceedings at the Meeting of German Naturalists and<lb break="yes"/>Physicians at Heidelberg, in <date>September, 1829.</date> By F.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Tiedemann</hi> and L. <hi rendition="#k">Gmelin.</hi>] Heidelberg. <date>1829.</date>
                </head>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Rede, gehalten bei der Eroeffnungder Versammlung Deutscher<lb break="yes"/>Naturforscher und Aerzte in Berlin, am</hi> 18<hi rendition="#i">ten September,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>1828. Von <hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt.</hi> [Address deliv-<lb break="no"/>ered at the opening of the Meeting of German Naturalists<lb break="yes"/>and Physicians at Berlin, on the <date>18th of September, 1828.</date>
                    <lb break="yes"/>By <hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt.</hi>] Berlin. <date>1828.</date>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Among the most striking characteristics of the present age,<lb break="yes"/>are the general facility of communication existing between the<lb break="yes" />nations of the West, the Europeans and their American descen-<lb break="no" />dants, and the readiness with which each of them receives from<lb break="yes" />every other, whatever may be usefully applied to its own con-<lb break="no" />dition and circumstances. The late wars in Europe brought<lb break="yes"/>the people of different countries into closer connexion than be-<lb break="no" />fore, and thus gave birth among them to feelings of mutual<lb break="yes" />respect; while, by rendering them weary of military glory, they<lb break="yes" />tended also to awaken a more general fondness for science and<lb break="yes" />the arts of peace. Even England has cast away many of her<lb break="yes" />ancient prejudices, and has become more willing than formerly,<lb break="yes" />to receive instruction from other nations. The Frenchman no<lb break="yes" />longer regards Paris as the only city worthy of the attention of<lb break="yes"/>a traveller: the Spaniard begins to be sensible of the absurdity<lb break="yes"/>of his foolish pride; Russia herself will soon be included in<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="86" facs="#f0002"/> the circle of civilization; and many of the prevailing miscon-<lb break="no"/>ceptions and false opinions respecting the East, are beginning<lb break="yes"/>to disappear. The Chinese are no longer looked upon as mere<lb break="yes"/>barbarians: we have, in short, discovered, in the language of<lb break="yes"/>a common German proverb, that there are men beyond the<lb break="yes"/>mountains. The world is daily becoming more enlightened<lb break="yes"/>and more just. Before the people of the United States, lies<lb break="yes"/>the whole Western continent, spread out like the prospect from<lb break="yes"/>the summit of a mountain&#x2014;vast, animated, and various; and<lb break="yes"/>we are enabled, by the unexampled quickness of our commu-<lb break="no"/>nications with other countries, to adopt immediately from them<lb break="yes"/>all their valuable and useful improvements. The Latin lan-<lb break="no"/>guage, which, in the middle ages, was the only medium of<lb break="yes"/>intercourse among men of learning, is now supplanted by several<lb break="yes"/>others. Books are published at the same time, in two or three<lb break="yes"/>different dialects; and it has become indispensable for every<lb break="yes"/>well-educated man, to be familiar with some other, beside his<lb break="yes"/>vernacular tongue. We would not be understood to adopt<lb break="yes"/>the common opinion, that the progress of civilization has been<lb break="yes"/>retarded by the barriers interposed between nations, by the<lb break="yes"/>difference of their languages: nor do we consider it as at all<lb break="yes"/>unfortunate, that a single language does not universally prevail.<lb break="yes"/>On the contrary, we are convinced, that the great variety of<lb break="yes"/>the tongues and dialects spoken by her inhabitants, is one of the<lb break="yes"/>causes of the superiority which Europe, a small and insignificant<lb break="yes"/>portion of the earth, has obtained over the rest of the Eastern<lb break="yes"/>hemisphere. Polite literature is divided, not according to<lb break="yes"/>countries, but according to languages: and it passes in each<lb break="yes"/>through the same gradations, from the earliest efforts of epic<lb break="yes"/>and lyric song, to refined description and attic wit; as the<lb break="yes"/>nation, which speaks it, passes itself through the various stages<lb break="yes"/>of civilization. This remark, however, cannot with justice be<lb break="yes"/>applied to the exact sciences, to the literature of the mechanic<lb break="yes"/>arts, or to geography. Still, if one language only had been<lb break="yes"/>spoken in Europe, our admiration would hardly have been at<lb break="yes"/>the same time excited by Camoens, Ercilla, Dante, Ariosto,<lb break="yes"/>the Nibelungenlied, and Milton. If the Danes had spoken the<lb break="yes"/>same language as the Germans, Denmark could hardly have<lb break="yes"/>produced so many distinguished writers in the short interval<lb break="yes"/>between Holberg and Oehlenschlaeger. We will even go<lb break="yes"/>further, and assert, that the human intellect would not have<lb break="yes"/>attained to its present degree of developement in so many<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="87" facs="#f0003"/> departments, and with so many shades of difference in each, if<lb break="yes"/>the ideas of all men had been necessarily expressed in the same<lb break="yes"/>idiom. Language and ideas exert a constant and reciprocal<lb break="yes"/>influence; and it is one of the principal charms of the study of<lb break="yes"/>a new language, that it discloses to us new ideas.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Association, the title of whose eighth report is placed<lb break="yes"/>at the head of this article, appears to us to be one of the most<lb break="yes" />striking effects of the increased facility and desire of commu-<lb break="no" />nication between different countries. Knowledge is certainly<lb break="yes" />rapidly advancing. We do not accord in opinion with those,<lb break="yes"/>who claim for the present age a superiority in every branch of<lb break="yes" />civilization, science and art; and who forget, in their admira-<lb break="no" />tion of Fulton, that the application of the paddle-wheel, or even<lb break="yes"/>the mere wheel, to the propulsion of vessels, was an improve-<lb break="no"/>ment as great as his: but we believe, that particular ages have<lb break="yes"/>been distinguished by certain peculiar attainments; and that<lb break="yes"/>there has been very little, if any, increase of skill in modern<lb break="yes"/>times, though the diffusion of it has become more general and<lb break="yes"/>rapid. We are of the opinion just indicated, that every remark-<lb break="no"/>able age has applied its ingenuity and activity to some particular<lb break="yes"/>department, in which it has excelled preceding and subsequent<lb break="yes"/>ones. The favorite studies at the present day are natural<lb break="yes"/>philosophy, geography, statistics, and the application of science<lb break="yes"/>to the arts; and the zeal and success with which they have been<lb break="yes"/>cultivated, cannot be too highly praised.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Association of German naturalists and physicians is<lb break="yes"/>novel, we may say, unique in its character; and it well de-<lb break="no"/>serves to be imitated in other countries. It promises, as the<lb break="yes"/>reader will hereafter perceive, to be the means of effecting&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>what is most earnestly to be desired&#x2014;a scientific union of the<lb break="yes" />German and French nations: and we deem it, therefore, not<lb break="yes" />unimportant to give some account of its character and history.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In a country, in which natural philosophy is so important an<lb break="yes" />object of general pursuit as it is in Germany, and in which so<lb break="yes" />many professors of the healing art are distinguished, as their an-<lb break="no"/>nual discoveries and publications abundantly prove, for scientific<lb break="yes"/>attainments, it was desirable, that men of science should become<lb break="yes"/>personally acquainted with each other; in order that they might<lb break="yes"/>more readily exchange ideas, aid one another in their respective<lb break="yes"/>plans, and communicate more directly and with greater rapidity,<lb break="yes"/>information that could not well be conveyed through the medium<lb break="yes"/>of printed transactions; that they might, in short, enjoy the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="88" facs="#f0004"/> animating and inspiring influence of the <hi rendition="#i">living word,</hi> and con-<lb break="no"/>solidate, as far as might be practicable, the union of the great<lb break="yes"/>republic of letters. In the address, of which the title is pre-<lb break="no"/>fixed to this article, Baron Humboldt remarks, that &#x2018;the<lb break="yes"/>ancients felt the value of the <hi rendition="#i">living word,</hi> the inspiring influence<lb break="yes"/>which superior minds exert over others, and the enlightening<lb break="yes"/>effect of free and friendly intercourse on the state of opinion<lb break="yes"/>and the direction of inquiry.&#x2019; The character of this Associa-<lb break="no"/>tion may be more accurately described, by contrasting it with<lb break="yes"/>two institutions of an opposite character. It is not an academy<lb break="yes"/>of sciences, the purpose of which is, to aid profound thinkers in<lb break="yes"/>pursuing their deep and solitary researches into the recesses of<lb break="yes"/>knowledge, and to publish learned transactions. Its immediate<lb break="yes"/>object is to produce a general animation, and a rapid interchange<lb break="yes"/>of ideas. On the other hand, it bears no resemblance to the<lb break="yes"/>schools of the middle ages, with their cold and vain displays of<lb break="yes"/>controversial ingenuity. It aims at the discovery of truth by<lb break="yes"/>conversation, and not at the exhibition of dialectic skill. As the<lb break="yes"/>edifying and happy influence of public religious services is uni-<lb break="no"/>versally acknowledged, while private devotion is also an incum-<lb break="no"/>bent Christian duty, so these disciples of science expect and<lb break="yes"/>desire to edify one another by their combined, as well as by<lb break="yes"/>their separate labors. The union in an actual community of<lb break="yes"/>men, whose purposes are the same, and who labor in the same<lb break="yes"/>cause of art, science, politics, and religion, but who are scat-<lb break="no"/>tered over a vast extent of country, cannot fail to have a very<lb break="yes"/>salutary effect. It is also the object of this Association, to be-<lb break="no"/>come acquainted with the various museums, collections, and<lb break="yes"/>other treasures of science, in different parts of Germany; and<lb break="yes"/>its meetings are held in successive years, at different places,<lb break="yes" />alternately in the northern and southern parts of that country.<note place="foot" n="*">This Association will doubtless remind the reader of Klopstock&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Republic of the Learned,</hi> though there is, in fact, no real resemblance<lb break="yes"/>between them.</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Professor Ludwig Oken<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Oken was at one time a professor at the University of Jena; but in<lb break="yes"/>1820, the Duke of Saxe-Weimar was compelled by the Prussian govern-<lb break="no"/>ment to dismiss him, on account of his political opinions. He lived for<lb break="yes"/>some time at Aargau in Switzerland, and has lately been appointed<lb break="yes"/>professor at the University of Munich by King Louis of Bavaria; who<lb break="yes"/>does not seem inclined to tread in the footsteps of the Holy Alliance.<lb break="yes"/>The article &#x2018;Oken,&#x2019; in the &#x2018;<hi rendition="#i">Biographie des Contemporains,</hi>&#x2019; is not, in<lb break="yes"/>all respects, accurate.</note> may be considered as the founder<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="89" facs="#f0005"/> of this interesting and useful institution. Its origin and charac-<lb break="no"/>ter will be best explained by a view of its constitution, of which<lb break="yes"/>the following is a translation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <list>
                    <item>&#x2018;§ 1. On the 18th of September, 1822, a number of German<lb break="yes"/>naturalists and physicians formed an Association at Leipzic, which<lb break="yes"/>bears the name of the <hi rendition="#i" >Association of German Naturalists and<lb break="yes"/>Physicians.</hi>
                    </item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>&#x2018;§ 2. The principal object of the Association is to afford the<lb break="yes"/>naturalists and physicians of Germany an opportunity of becoming<lb break="yes"/>personally acquainted with one another.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>&#x2018;§ 3. Every author of a work on natural philosophy or medicine<lb break="yes"/>is considered as a member.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>&#x2018;§ 4. Inaugural dissertations are not regarded as scientific works<lb break="yes"/>for this purpose.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>&#x2018;§ 5. There is no election of members, and no diplomas are given.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>&#x2018;§ 6. Any person employed in the study of natural philosophy<lb break="yes"/>or medicine, is permitted to attend the meetings.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>&#x2018;§ 7. No absent member has a right to vote.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>&#x2018;§ 8. All questions are decided by a majority of votes.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>&#x2018;§ 9. The meetings are held annually with open doors. They<lb break="yes"/>begin regularly on the 18th of September, and continue several<lb break="yes"/>days.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>&#x2018;§ 10. The place of meeting is annually changed. At each<lb break="yes"/>meeting, the place where the succeeding one is to be held is<lb break="yes"/>determined.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>&#x2018;§ 11. A president (<hi rendition="#i">Geschaeftsfuehrer</hi>) and secretary, who<lb break="yes"/>must reside at the place of meeting, manage the affairs of the<lb break="yes"/>Association until the succeeding meeting.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>§ 12. The president fixes the time and place of meeting, and<lb break="yes"/>regulates the proceedings. He must, therefore, receive previous<lb break="yes"/>information when any paper is proposed to be read.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>§ 13. The secretary makes a record of the proceedings, keeps<lb break="yes"/>the accounts of the Association and maintains its correspondence.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>§ 14. These two officers sign in the name of the Association.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>§ 15. They notify the authorities of the place where the next<lb break="yes"/>meeting is to be held, and also give public notice of the same.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>§ 16. At each meeting, officers are chosen for the next year.<lb break="yes"/>If the persons elected decline, the officers make another choice;<lb break="yes"/>and may also, if necessary, change the place of meeting.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>§ 17. In the event of the death of one officer, the survivor<lb break="yes"/>appoints another. If both shall die, the officers of the preceding<lb break="yes"/>year resume their offices.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>§ 18. The Association makes no assessment, and holds no<lb break="yes" />property, with the exception of its records. Whatever may be<lb break="yes"/>exhibited, continues to belong to the exhibiter.</item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <fw type="sig" place="bottom">
                    <hi rendition="#k">vol. xxxi.&#x2014;no.</hi> 68. 12</fw>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="90" facs="#f0006"/>
                <list>
                    <item>§ 19. The expenses of the meetings are defrayed by the mem-<lb break="no" />bers present.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>§ 20. No change can be made in the constitution, until after<lb break="yes"/>the first five meetings.</item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This institution accords so well with the spirit of the age, or<lb break="yes" />at least with the spirit of the Germans in their ardent pursuit<lb break="yes" />of natural science, that its meetings which were held for the<lb break="yes" />four last years at Dresden, Munich, Berlin and Heidelberg,<lb break="yes" />were remarkably brilliant. The meeting at Heidelberg in 1829<lb break="yes" />was attended by two hundred and seventy-three naturalists and<lb break="yes" />physicians, among whom were individuals from all parts of<lb break="yes" />Germany, and from Switzerland, Poland, Denmark and Tus-<lb break="no"/>cany; together with seven from England, nine from France,<lb break="yes"/>and five from the Netherlands.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This meeting was rendered particularly interesting by the<lb break="yes" />presence of Baron de Ferussac, director of the &#x2018;<hi rendition="#i" >Societé du<lb break="yes"/>Bulletin universel pour la propagation des connoissances scien-<lb break="no"/>tifiques et industrielles,</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">The <hi rendition="#i">Bulletin Universel des Sciences et de l&#x2019;Industrie</hi> is a periodical<lb break="yes"/>journal published at Paris, and divided into eight sections, of each of<lb break="yes"/>which a number is issued monthly. Baron de Ferussac is the general<lb break="yes"/>director. He is assisted by eight editors, one for each section. The<lb break="yes"/>sections are arranged as follows. 1. For mathematical, physical and<lb break="yes"/>chemical science; 2. natural history and geology; 3. medical science;<lb break="yes"/>4. agriculture, horticulture, fishing, and sporting in general; 5. tech-<lb break="no" />nology; 6. geography, statistics, political economy, voyages and travels;<lb break="yes"/>7. philology, antiquities and history; 8. military science.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Encyclop&#x0153;dia<lb break="yes"/>Americana.</hi>
                    </note> who appeared as the representative of<lb break="yes"/>that Association, and for a purpose which will be best explained<lb break="yes"/>by the following letter, addressed by him to the president of<lb break="yes"/>the Society.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <div n="2" type="letter">
                            <opener>
                                <salute>
                                    <hi rendition="#k">Mr. President,</hi>
                                </salute>
                            </opener>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>The directors of the <hi rendition="#i">Universal Bulletin</hi> have imposed upon<lb break="yes"/>me the duty of presenting myself before the meeting of German<lb break="yes"/>
                                <hi rendition="#i">savans</hi> at Heidelberg, to express their wishes and their hopes.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x2018;The statutes of the Society, and the catalogue of its members,<lb break="yes"/>together with the other documents, which I have the honor to<lb break="yes"/>present to you, will enable you to form a just idea of its character,<lb break="yes"/>and of its means of influence.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x2018;It is the object of that Association, which was instituted by<lb break="yes"/>virtue of a decree of the King of France, issued on the 13th of<lb break="yes"/>March, 1828, upon the report of the ministry and the council<lb break="yes"/>of state, to establish a permanent connexion, and an active cor-<lb break="no"/>
                                <pb n="91" facs="#f0007"/> respondence between all the friends of science and the useful<lb break="yes"/>arts; to the end that the ideas and labors of each may be ren-<lb break="no"/>dered accessible and useful to all; for without this the progress<lb break="yes"/>of all must of necessity be slow, and valuable results far less<lb break="yes"/>rapidly effected.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x2018;This Association, which is peculiarly distinguished by its<lb break="yes"/>universal character, belongs exclusively to no one nation, to no<lb break="yes"/>single school, to no particular doctrine. It professes to labor<lb break="yes"/>for the <hi rendition="#i">public good.</hi> The most eminent friends of science in<lb break="yes"/>every country are invited to become its members. They must<lb break="yes"/>in every state constitute a committee for the encouragement of<lb break="yes"/>science, and for facilitating the labor and researches of scientific<lb break="yes" />men. They must form together the Senate of that general re-<lb break="no"/>public of science and industry, which is every day so rapidly<lb break="yes"/>increasing with the progress of instruction and the culture of the<lb break="yes"/>human mind.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x2018;The unquestionable importance of such an organization to<lb break="yes"/>the interest of science and men of learning, as well as to the<lb break="yes"/>progress of civilisation, has induced the association which I<lb break="yes"/>have the honor to represent, to believe, that an object so elevated<lb break="yes"/>and generous as theirs, will attract the attention of the assembly<lb break="yes" />of learned men, over which you preside.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x2018;For these reasons, the directors of the <hi rendition="#i" >Universal Bulletin</hi> be-<lb break="no"/>lieve, that it belongs to an assembly so remarkable and so solemn<lb break="yes" />as that which is now convened in Heidelberg, to manifest their<lb break="yes"/>friendly disposition towards that Institution, by some public act;<lb break="yes"/>and I have accordingly been requested, Mr. President, to beg you<lb break="yes"/>to cause this letter to be read at one of the earliest meetings of<lb break="yes" />your Association, and to ask that it may be noticed in the report<lb break="yes"/>of your proceedings; and if these requests be not disregarded,<lb break="yes"/>that it may be made the order of the day for the consideration of<lb break="yes"/>the sections.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x2018;I have also, Mr. President, the honor to enclose six copies of<lb break="yes"/>our documents, for the use of the several sections of the assembly.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <closer>
                                <salute>
                                    <hi rendition="#et">I am, with high respect, &#x0026;c.</hi>
                                </salute>
                            </closer>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <dateline>
                                <hi rendition="#i">Heidelberg, Sept.</hi> 13<hi rendition="#i" >th,</hi> 1829.</dateline>
                        </div>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The meeting at Heidelberg was organized in four depart-<lb break="no"/>ments; appropriated respectively to chemistry and natural phi-<lb break="no"/>losophy, mineralogy and geology, botany, and medicine. A<lb break="yes"/>general meeting and a separate meeting of each division were<lb break="yes"/>held every day. The session continued seven days: and we are<lb break="yes"/>astonished, on examining the report, to perceive how much sci-<lb break="no"/>entific and practical information was communicated, in so short a<lb break="yes"/>space of time. Reports of uncommon medical operations were<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="92" facs="#f0008"/> made; delicate chemical preparations were exhibited; new dis-<lb break="no"/>coveries promulgated; new instruments brought into notice; and<lb break="yes"/>a great number of scientific treatises read. Letters were receiv-<lb break="no"/>ed from learned men in many different parts of Europe, and in<lb break="yes"/>short, more activity and zeal were displayed, on this occasion,<lb break="yes"/>than upon any former one of the kind. This meeting, however,<lb break="yes"/>was inferior in brilliancy to that which was held last year at<lb break="yes"/>Berlin, and at which, as we have already mentioned, Baron<lb break="yes"/>Alexander Humboldt presided. The short introductory dis-<lb break="no"/>course, which he delivered upon that occasion, exhibited the<lb break="yes"/>refinement and elegance that belong to this distinguished philoso-<lb break="no"/>pher, so well known throughout the world for his researches<lb break="yes"/>and discoveries, in almost every department of natural science.<lb break="yes"/>Having mentioned the name of this great man, we cannot per-<lb break="no"/>mit the occasion to pass without expressing our admiration of<lb break="yes"/>his elevated character&#x2014;our deep sense of the services which<lb break="yes"/>he has rendered to the world by his indefatigable efforts in<lb break="yes"/>America, Europe, Africa and more recently in Asia, and our<lb break="yes"/>ardent wishes that his valuable life may be long continued for<lb break="yes"/>the instruction of both hemispheres.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The meeting at Berlin was rendered, by the taste of Baron<lb break="yes" />Humboldt, as pleasing as it was interesting and useful. Its<lb break="yes" />first session in the hall of the royal musical academy was<lb break="yes" />attended by more than five hundred persons, among whom<lb break="yes"/>were some of the highest officers of state. To this succeeded<lb break="yes"/>the regular meetings. In the evening, a <hi rendition="#i">conversazione</hi> was<lb break="yes"/>given by the President, in the great concert-room of the royal<lb break="yes"/>theatre. This saloon, which is one of the most elegant in<lb break="yes"/>Europe, was arranged by Mr. Schinkel, the King&#x2019;s architect,<lb break="yes"/>as a temple of German Fame. Within a semicircle of rays,<lb break="yes"/>opposite to the entrance, the names of the most distinguished<lb break="yes"/>German naturalists were inscribed in characters of gold and<lb break="yes"/>silver. On one side were placed the following lines of Goethe:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <lg>
                    <l>Es soll sich regen, schaffen, handeln,</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Erst sich gestalten, dann verwandeln,</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Nur scheinbar stehts momente still;</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Das Ew&#x2019;ge regt sich fort in Allem,</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Denn Alles muss in Nichts zerfallen,</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Wenn es im Seyn beharren will.<note place="foot" n="*">Motion, action, formation, creation, change, are the laws of existence.<lb break="yes" />Repose is a mere appearance, for the Universe is inspired in all its parts<lb break="yes"/>by a principle of constant activity; and ceasing to change is in other<lb break="yes"/>words ceasing to be.</note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="93" facs="#f0009"/>
                <p>On the other side was inscribed the following passage from<lb break="yes" />Schiller:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <lg>
                    <l>Es entbrennen im feurigen Kampf die eifernden Kraefte,</l>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <l>Grosses wirket ihr Streit, Groesseres wirket ihr Bund.<note place="foot" n="*">The power of conflicting principles is increased by the ardor of<lb break="yes"/>contention; their strife produces much good, but their union still more.</note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The King and several of the princes attended this festival:<lb break="yes"/>which was rendered still more attractive by a full orchestra and<lb break="yes"/>the first singers of the royal theatre. While the meeting con-<lb break="no" />tinued, the members were every day conveyed in carriages to<lb break="yes"/>a vast dining hall, in which were spread twenty tables, at each<lb break="yes"/>of which twenty-four persons were accommodated. Baron<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt presided at the first table. No ladies were present,<lb break="yes"/>excepting the wives or daughters of such members as did<lb break="yes"/>not reside in Berlin.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The institution has been conducted with so much success,<lb break="yes"/>that it was proposed at the last meeting that the future ones<lb break="yes"/>should occasionally be held in other countries, and it was<lb break="yes"/>particularly requested by Professor Oersted of Copenhagen,<lb break="yes"/>that the next might take place in that city; but the invitation<lb break="yes"/>was declined for the present, principally because the Association<lb break="yes"/>had not yet met in several of the German cities, which contain<lb break="yes"/>treasures of natural science well worthy of their attention.<lb break="yes"/>Hamburg has been assigned as the place of meeting for the<lb break="yes"/>next year. We should rejoice if the attendance there of some<lb break="yes"/>of our fellow citizens might produce a literary and scientific<lb break="yes"/>union between two regions, separated only by an ocean, which<lb break="yes"/>is found to oppose no obstacles of importance to our commer-<lb break="no"/>cial enterprise. Boston, New-York and Philadelphia, are not<lb break="yes"/>really more remote from Paris, than Warsaw, Stockholm,<lb break="yes"/>Lisbon, and many other European cities. The representatives<lb break="yes"/>of the United States would doubtless meet with a hospitable<lb break="yes"/>reception, and a cordial welcome from the inhabitants of a<lb break="yes"/>country, which was styled by Madame de Sta&#x00EB;l &#x2018;<hi rendition="#i">le pays des<lb break="yes"/>pensées et de la bonhommie.</hi>&#x2019;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 