<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="441" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#i">Brief Narrative of De Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels in
                        <placeName>Russia</placeName>.</hi></head>
                <lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#i">Extract from a Letter from M. de Humboldt to M.
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Arago</persName>.</hi>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i"><placeName>Oust Kaméno-<lb/>gorsk</placeName>,,
                            <placeName>Upper Irtych</placeName>, <placeName>Siberia</placeName></hi> <date><hi rendition="#i">Aug.</hi> 28. 1829</date>&#x2014;Travelling
                    for nearly the last<lb/>two months beyond the frontiers of <placeName>Europe</placeName>, to the east
                    of the <placeName>Ural</placeName>, and in the<lb/>restless life which we pass, I have lost many
                    occasions of giving you a token of my<lb/>existence and of friendship. It is
                    impossible in this hasty letter, (we arrived in<lb/>this fort, on the frontier
                    of the Step of <placeName>Kirguiz</placeName>, about 4 o&#x2019;clock this morning, and<lb/>we must
                    advance this night to the east towards <placeName>Boucktorma</placeName>, <placeName>Narim</placeName>, and the<lb/>first post
                    of <placeName>Chinese Mongolia</placeName>;) it is impossible, I say, to communicate to you<lb/>the
                    substance of the observations which we have made since our departure
                    from<lb/><placeName>St. Petersburgh</placeName> on the 8th of May. You will find no other interest in
                    the peru-<lb/>sal of these lines, than that of learning that the scientific
                    object of my journey has<lb/>been completed beyond my hopes: that, in spite of
                    the fatigues I have under-<lb/>gone, and the distance I have travelled, (we are
                    already more than 5600 versts<lb/>from <placeName>St. Petersburgh</placeName>, 320 of which we have
                    passed in this part of <placeName>Asia</placeName>,) my<lb/>health is good; that I suffer with patience
                    and courage; that I have much rea-<lb/>son to congratulate myself on my
                    companions, MM. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Rose</persName> and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Ehrenberg</persName>; and<lb/>that, laden with geological,
                    botanical, and zoological collections from the <placeName>Ural</placeName>,<lb/>the <placeName>Alta&#x00EF;</placeName>, the
                    <placeName>Obi</placeName>, the <placeName>Irtych</placeName>, and <placeName>Orenburgh</placeName>, we hope to return to <placeName>Berlin</placeName> to-<lb/>wards the
                    end of November.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Our route has been by <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <placeName>Nijne&#x00EF;-Novogorod</placeName>, and thence on the
                    <placeName>Wolga</placeName><lb/>to <placeName>Cazan</placeName>, and to the ruins of the Tatar village of <placeName>Bulgari</placeName>. From <placeName>Cazan</placeName>
                    we as-<lb/>cended the <placeName>Ural</placeName> by the picturesque vallies of <placeName>Koungour</placeName> and <placeName>Perme</placeName>.
                    Through-<lb/>out the whole journey from <placeName>Novogorod</placeName> to <placeName>Catherineburgh</placeName>, and to the
                    platinum-<lb/>washings of <placeName>Nijne&#x00EF;-Tagilsk</placeName>, we were accompanied by Count
                    <placeName>Polier</placeName>, whom you<lb/>will recollect to have seen at <placeName>Paris</placeName>. He has been
                    exercising his fine talent for<lb/>landscape-painting in these savage regions.
                    Fixed by marriage in <placeName>Russia</placeName>, he is<lb/>zealously occupied in improving the
                    working of mines.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>We spent a month in visiting the gold mines of <placeName>Borisovsk</placeName>, the malachite<lb/>mines
                    of <placeName>Goumeselevski</placeName> and of <placeName>Tagilsk</placeName>, and the washings of gold and platinum.<lb/>We
                    were astonished at the <hi rendition="#i">pepitas</hi> (water-worn masses) of
                    gold from 2 to 3 Ibs.<lb/>and even from 18 to 20 lbs, found a few inches below
                    the turf, where they had<lb/>lain unknown for ages.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The position and probable origin of these alluvia, mixed generally with
                    frag-<lb/>ments of greenstone, chlorite-slate, and serpentine, was one of the
                    principal ob-<lb/>jects of this journey. The gold annually procured from the
                    washings amounts<lb/>to 6000 kil. The discoveries beyond 59° and 60° lat. become
                    very important.<lb/>We possess the teeth of fossil elephants, enveloped in these
                    alluvia of aurife-<lb/>rous sand. Their formation, consequent on local
                    irruptions and on levellings,<lb/>is perhaps even posterior to the destruction
                    of the large animals. The amber<lb/>and the lignites which we discovered on the
                    eastern side of the Ural, are decided-<lb/>ly more ancient. With the auriferous
                    sand are found grains of cinnabar, native<lb/>copper, ceylanites, garnets,
                    little white zircons, as brilliant as diamonds, anatase,<lb/>albite, &amp;c.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>It is very remarkable, that in the middle and northern parts of the <placeName>Ural</placeName>,
                    the<lb/>platinum is found in abundance only on the western, European side. The
                    rich<lb/>gold-washings of the <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Demidov family</persName> at <placeName>Nijne&#x00EF;-Tagilsk</placeName>, are on
                    the <placeName>Asiatic side</placeName>,<lb/>on the two acclivities of the <placeName>Bartiraya</placeName>, where the
                    alluvium of <placeName>Vilkni</placeName> alone has<lb/>already produced more than 2800 lbs. of gold.
                    The platinum is found about a<lb/>league to the east of the line of the
                    separation of waters, (which must not be con-<lb/>founded with the axis of the
                    high summits,) on the <placeName>European side</placeName>, near the<lb/>course of the <placeName>Oulka</placeName>, at <placeName>Sukoi
                        Visnin</placeName>, and at <placeName>Martian</placeName>. M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Schvetsov</persName>, who had<lb/>the good fortune to study
                    under <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Berthier</persName>, and whose learning and activity have<lb/>been most useful during
                    our travels in the <placeName>Ural</placeName>, discovered chromate of iron, con-<lb/>taining grains of
                    platinum, which an able chemist at <placeName>Catherineburgh</placeName>, M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Helm</persName>,<lb/>has
                    analyzed.</p>
                <lb/>
                <pb n="442" facs="#f0002"/>
                <p>The washings of platinum at <placeName>Nijne&#x00EF;-Tagilsk</placeName> are so rich that 100 <hi
                        rendition="#i">puds</hi> (about<lb/>400 lbs. Russian) of sand afford 30
                    (sometimes 50) <hi rendition="#i">solotniks</hi> of platinum, whilst<lb/>the
                    rich alluvia of gold at <placeName>Vilkni</placeName>, and other gold-washings on the <placeName>Asiatic
                    side</placeName>,<lb/>do not give more than 1<formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{2}</formula> to 2 solotniks in the 100 puds of
                    sand.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In <placeName>South America</placeName>, a very low chain of the <placeName>Cordilleras</placeName>, that of <placeName>Cali</placeName>, also
                    sepa-<lb/>rates the auriferous and non-platiniferous sands of the eastern
                    declivity, (<placeName>Popayan</placeName>,)<lb/>from the sands of the isthmus of the <placeName>Raspadura of
                        Choco</placeName>, which are very rich in<lb/>platinum as well as gold. M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Bousingault</persName> may
                    perhaps already have thrown a<lb/>new light on this American formation, and his
                    observations will derive some ad-<lb/>ditional interest from those which we have
                    made in this place. We possess pe-<lb/>pitas of platinum of many inches in
                    length, in which M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Rose</persName> has discovered<lb/>beautiful groups of crystals of the
                    metal. As to the greenstone-porphyry of<lb/><placeName>Laya</placeName>, in which M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Engelhardt</persName> has
                    observed little grains of platinum, we have<lb/>examined it on the spot with
                    much care, but the only metallic grains which we<lb/>have been able to detect in
                    the rocks of <placeName>Laya</placeName>, and in the greenstone of <placeName>Mount<lb/>Belayr-Gora</placeName>, have appeared
                    to M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Rose</persName> to be sulphuret of iron; this phenome-<lb/>non will be a subject for
                    new research. The work of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Engelhardt</persName> on the Ural<lb/>seemed to us to be
                    worthy of much praise. Osmium and iridium have also a<lb/>particular locality,
                    not amongst the rich platiniferous alluvia of <placeName>Nijne&#x00EF;-Tagilsk</placeName>,<lb/>but
                    near <placeName>Bilembayevski</placeName> and <placeName>Kichtem</placeName>. I insist upon the geognostical charac-<lb/>ters
                    drawn from the metals which accompany the grains of platinum at
                    <placeName>Choco</placeName>,<lb/><placeName>Brazil</placeName>, and in the <placeName>Ural</placeName>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>These last lines were written on the 20th August. I have abandoned the
                    pen<lb/>for the last eight days, to occupy myself with taking lunar distances;
                    for this<lb/>southern extremity of <placeName>Siberia</placeName>, where the sources of the <placeName>Obi</placeName> and the
                    confines of<lb/><placeName>Chinese Mongolia</placeName> are found, require much attention in the
                    geographical determi-<lb/>nation of places,&#x2014;the rate of the chronometers
                    alone being liable to alteration by<lb/>the rapidity of the journey. I have been
                    since the 13th to visit the Chinese pic-<lb/>quet (outposts) in <placeName>Dzongarie</placeName>. We
                    have been obliged to leave our carriages at<lb/><placeName>Oust Kamenogorsk</placeName>, to make use,
                    in these frightful roads, of the long Siberian<lb/>carriages, in which one lies
                    down. But before speaking of the journey we have<lb/>passed in the <placeName>midst of the
                    celestial empire</placeName>, I must follow the thread of our travels.<lb/>After having
                    visited the north of the <placeName>Ural</placeName> by <placeName>Verkhoturia</placeName> and <placeName>Bogeslavsk</placeName>, taken<lb/>azimuths
                    to determine the positions of the northerly peaks, visited the mines
                    of<lb/>beryls and topazes at <placeName>Moursinsk</placeName>, we travelled from <placeName>Catherineburgh</placeName>, which
                    we left<lb/>on the 6th July, through <placeName>Tobolsk</placeName> and <placeName>Jioumère</placeName>, where the family of
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Batou-Khan</persName><lb/>formerly resided.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>We intended to go directly through <placeName>Omsk</placeName> to <placeName>Slatooust</placeName>; but the fineness of<lb/>the
                    season induced us to add the <placeName>Alta&#x00EF;</placeName> and the high <placeName>Irtych</placeName>, (3000 versts
                    round,)<lb/>to the original plan of our excursion. The governor-general of
                    <placeName>Western Siberia</placeName>,<lb/>General <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Villiaminov</persName>, gave us one of his aides-de-camp, M.
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">de Yermolov</persName>, for an<lb/>escort. General <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Litvinov</persName>, who commands on the whole line
                    of the <placeName>Kirguiz</placeName>, took<lb/>his place in coming from <placeName>Tomsk</placeName> to the mountains of
                    <placeName>Kolyvan</placeName>, and escorted us to<lb/>the Chinese post. We arrived here by
                    <placeName>Ka&#x00EF;nks</placeName> and the step of <placeName>Baraba</placeName>, where<lb/>the musquitoes rival those of
                    the <placeName>Orinoco</placeName>, and where we were smothered under<lb/>masks of horse hair. Here are
                    the romantic lake of <placeName>Kolyvan</placeName>, and the famous<lb/>mines of <placeName>Schlangenberg</placeName>, (in
                    porphyry,) of <placeName>Reiders</placeName>, and of <placeName>Siria&#x00EF;novski</placeName>, which<lb/>annually yield
                    40,000 lbs. of auriferous silver. At Oust we had the first view of<lb/>the chain
                    of the <placeName>Kirguiz</placeName>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>We took the route of <placeName>Baty</placeName>, by the fort of <placeName>Boukhtarma</placeName> and of <placeName>Krasnoyar</placeName>,
                    where,<lb/>passing the whole night of 16th to 17th August (new style) for
                    observation, I<lb/>saw the singular phenomena of the polar bands. At <placeName>Baty</placeName> there
                    are two Chinese<lb/>encampments, on the two sides of the
                    <placeName>Irtych</placeName>,&#x2014;miserable <hi rendition="#i">yourtes</hi> inhabited
                    by<lb/>Mongolian or Cambauzian soldiers. A little Chinese temple is seen on an
                    arid<lb/>eminence. The Bactrian camel with two humps pastures in the valley.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>This frontier of <placeName>Mongolia</placeName> supplied M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Ehrenberg</persName> with numerous plants and<lb/>new
                    insects. But what renders the journey in the <placeName>Alta&#x00EF;</placeName> particularly
                        important<lb/><pb n="443" facs="#f0003"/> is, that no where else in the two
                    worlds, does the granite with common large feld-<lb/>spar, deprived of albite,
                    and unaccompanied by gneiss and mica slate, exhibit<lb/>proofs of irruption and
                    effusion, as in the <placeName>Alta&#x00EF;</placeName>. We do not only see the granite<lb/>penetrating
                    in veins which are lost towards the top in the clay-slate, and making<lb/>its
                    way to the surface through this rock, but also distinctly spreading out over
                    it,<lb/>and covering a continuous space of more than 2000 toises: then conical
                    hills,<lb/>and little bells of granite, and domes of trachytic porphyry,
                    dolomites in granite,<lb/>veins of porphyry, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Rose</persName> discovered, in the north of the <placeName>Ural</placeName>, a place where the porphyry,
                    cleft<lb/>and partly rounded, had converted, by contact, lime into jasper,
                    divided by pa-<lb/>rallel bands. I have also seen these stri&#x00E6; and
                    silifications at <placeName>Pedrazio</placeName>. The<lb/><placeName>Ural</placeName> is also remarkable for the intimate
                    connection of the euphotide (serpentine)<lb/>chlorite slate, with pyroxenic
                    greenstones containing more hornblende than py-<lb/>roxene. I have endeavoured
                    to observe the temperature of the earth, (it is often<lb/>above 2° cent.) and
                    the inclination and magnetic intensity in the places which<lb/>had not been
                    visited by MM. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Hansteen</persName> and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Ehrmann</persName>. The same points prove<lb/>the motion of
                    knots from east to west, which you have noticed in your report on<lb/>the voyage
                    of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Freycinet</persName>. But the post is going, and leaves me not a moment<lb/>to
                    re-write or correct this confused letter.</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>

    </text>
</TEI>
