<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Humboldt&#x2019;s Account of the Gold and Pla-<lb/>tina District of Russia.</hi>&#x2014;The following account is<lb/>part of a letter from M. Humboldt, to M. Arago.&#x2014;&#x201C; We<lb/>spent a month in visiting the gold mines of Borisovsk, the<lb/>malachite mines of Gumeselevski, and of Tagilsk, and<lb/>the washings of gold and platinum. We were astonishe<lb/> at the <hi rendition="#i">pepilas</hi> (water-worn masses) of gold, from two to<lb/>three pounds, and even from eighteen to twenty pounds,<lb/>found a few inches below the turf, where they had lain<lb/>unknown for ages. The position and probable origin of<lb/>these alluvia, mixed generally with fragments of green<lb/>stone, chlorite slate, and serpentine, was one of the prin-<lb/>cipal objects of this journey. The gold annually pro-<lb/>cured from the washings amounts to 6,000 kil. The<lb/>discoveries beyond fifty-nine and sixty degrees latitude<lb/>become very important. We possess the teeth of fossil<lb/>elephants enveloped in these alluvia of auriferous sand.<lb/>Their formation, consequent on local irruptions and on<lb/>levelings, is, perhaps, even posterior to the destruction<lb/>of the large animals. The amber and the lignites, which<lb/>we discovered on the eastern side of the Ural, are de-<lb/>cidedly more ancient. With the auriferous sand are<lb/>found grains of cinnabar, native copper, ceylanites, gar-<lb/>nets, little white zircons, as brilliant as diamonds, ana-<lb/>tase, alvite, &amp;c. It is very remarkable, that in the<lb/>middle and northern parts of the Ural, the platinum is<lb/>found only on the western European side. The rich<lb/>gold-washings of the Demidov family, at Nijnei-tagilsk,<lb/>are on the Asiatic side, on the two acclivities of Barti-<lb/>raya, where the alluvium of Vilkni alone has already<lb/>produced more than 2,800 lbs. of gold.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;The platinum is found about a league to the east of<lb/>the separation of waters (which must not be confounded<lb/>with the axis of the high summits), on the European<lb/>side, near the course of the Oulka, at Sukoi Visnin, and at<lb/>Martian. M. Schvetsov, who had the good fortune to<lb/>study under Berthier, and whose learning and activity<lb/>have been most useful during our travels in the Ural,<lb/>discovered chromate of iron, containing grains of plati-<lb/>num, which an able chemist at Catherineburgh, M. Helm,<lb/>has analyzed. The washings of platinum at Nijnei-<lb/>tagilsk are so rich, that 100 puds (about 400 lbs. Rus-<lb/>sian) of sand afford 30 (sometimes 40) solotniks of pla-<lb/>tinum, whilst the rich alluvia of gold at Vilkni, and<lb/>other gold washings on the Asiatic side, do not give<lb/>more than 1&#x00BD; or 2 solotniks in 100 puds of sand. In<lb/>South America, a very low chain of the Cordilleras, that<lb/>of Cali, also separates the auriferous and non-platinife-<lb/>rous sand on the eastern declivity, (Popayan), from the<lb/>sands of the isthmus of the Raspadura of Choco, which<lb/>are very rich in platinum as well as gold.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>