<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157">
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Strobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-08-31" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="142" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Lofty Flight of the Condor.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Next</hi>
                    </hi> to the Condor, the Lammergeier of Switzerland and the<lb break="yes" />Falco destructor of Daudin, which is probably the same as the<lb break="yes" />Falco Harpya of Linn&#x00E6;us, are the largest flying birds.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The region which may be considered as the habitual abode of<lb break="yes"/>the Condor, begins at a height equal to that of Etna, and com-<lb break="no" />prehends strata of air at an elevation of from 9600 to 18,000<lb break="yes" />feet above the level of the sea. The largest individuals that<lb break="yes" />are met <choice><sic>with in</sic><corr type="editorial">within</corr></choice> the chain of the Andes of Quito, are about four-<lb break="no" />teen feet from the tip of one wing to that of the other, and the<lb break="yes"/>smallest only eight. From these dimensions, and from the vi-<lb break="no"/>sual angle under which this bird sometimes appears perpendi-<lb break="no"/>cularly above our heads, it may be judged to what a prodigious<lb break="yes"/>height it rises when the sky is clear. When seen, for example,<lb break="yes"/>under an angle of four minutes, it must be at a perpendicular<lb break="yes"/>distance of 6876 feet. The Cave of Antisana, situated op-<lb break="no"/>posite the mountain of Chussulongo, and from which we mea-<lb break="no"/>sured the bird soaring, is situated at a height of 12,958 feet<lb break="yes"/>above the level of the Pacific Ocean. Thus, the absolute height<lb break="yes"/>which the Condor attained, was 20,834 feet, an elevation at<lb break="yes"/>which the barometer scarcely rises to 12 inches. It is a some-<lb break="no"/>what remarkable physiological phenomenon, that this bird, which<lb break="yes"/>for hours continues to fly about in regions where the air is so<lb break="yes"/>rarefied, all at once descends to the edge of the sea, as along the<lb break="yes"/>western slope of the volcano of Pichincha, and thus in a few<lb break="yes"/>minutes passes as it were through all the varieties of climate.<lb break="yes"/>At a height of 20,000 feet, the air-cells of the Condor which<lb break="yes"/>are filled in the lowest regions, must be inflated in an extraor-<lb break="no"/>dinary manner. Sixty years ago, Ulloa expressed his astonish-<lb break="no"/>ment at the circumstance that the vulture of the Andes could fly<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="143" facs="#f0002"/> at a height where the mean pressure of the air is only 14 inches.<note place="foot" n="*">Astronomical observations made by order of the King of Spain, p. 109.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>It was then imagined, from the analogy of experiments made<lb break="yes"/>with the pneumatic machine, that no animal could live in so rare<lb break="yes"/>a medium. I have seen the barometer fall on <choice><sic>Chiniborazo</sic><corr type="editorial">Chimborazo</corr></choice> to<lb break="yes"/>13 inches 11<formula notation="TeX" >\frac{2}{10}</formula> lines. My friend, M. Gay Lussac, respired for a<lb break="yes"/>quarter of an hour in an atmosphere whose pressure was only<lb break="yes"/>0<hi rendition="#sup">m.</hi>.3288. At heights like these, man in general finds himself<lb break="yes"/>reduced to a most painful state of debility. In the Condor, on<lb break="yes"/>the contrary, the act of respiration appears to be performed with<lb break="yes"/>equal ease, in mediums where the pressure differs from 12 to 30<lb break="yes"/>inches. Of all living beings, it is without doubt the one that<lb break="yes"/>can rise at will to the greatest distance from the earth&#x2019;s surface.<lb break="yes"/>I say, at will, because small insects are carried still higher by<lb break="yes"/>ascending currents. Probably the height which the Condor at-<lb break="no"/>tains is greater than that which we have found by the calcula-<lb break="no"/>tion mentioned above. I remember that on Cotopaxi, in the<lb break="yes"/>Plain of Suniguaicu, covered with pumice, and elevated 13,578<lb break="yes"/>feet above the level of the sea, I perceived that bird at such<lb break="yes"/>a height, that it appeared like a black dot. What is the smallest<lb break="yes"/>angle under which objects weakly lighted are distinguished?<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">It is probably one minute. In 1806, a balloon, which was four fathoms<lb break="yes"/>in diameter, was seen with the naked eye at Berlin to fall at a distance of<lb break="yes"/>40,200 feet. It was then under a visual angle of 2&#x2032;4&#x2033;. But it could have<lb break="yes" />been distinguished at a much greater distance, notwithstanding the consti-<lb break="no"/>tution of our northern atmosphere.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>The diminution which the rays of light undergo by passing<lb break="yes"/>through the strata of the atmosphere, has a great influence upon<lb break="yes"/>the minimum of the angle. The transparency of the air of<lb break="yes"/>mountains is so great under the equator, that, in the province of<lb break="yes"/>Quito, as I have elsewhere shewn<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">In my memoir on the diminution of heat, and on the lower limit of per-<lb break="no"/>petual snow.</note>, the poncho or white mantle<lb break="yes"/>of a person on horseback is distinguishable at a horizontal dis-<lb break="no"/>tance of 84,032 feet, and consequently under an angle of 13<lb break="yes"/>seconds.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#et">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Humboldt, Tableaux de la Nature,</hi> t. ii. pp. 72&#x2014;78.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 