<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="300" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#i">On the Systems of Numerical Signs used by different
                        Nations,<lb/>and on the Origin of the Expression of Value by Position<lb/>in
                        the Indian Numbers. By</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt.</hi><lb/>[Read in a Class-Session of
                    the Royal Academy of Sciences, in <placeName>Berlin</placeName>,<lb/>the <date>2d of March,
                        1829</date>.]<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Translated from the German, and
                            communicated by</hi> <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">J. W.</persName></head>
                <lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#k"><hi rendition="#in">I</hi>n</hi> our researches upon numerical
                    figures (the only hiero-<lb/>glyphics which, among the nations of the old
                    continent, have<lb/>been preserved, besides the alphabetical figures used to
                    express<lb/>the different sounds of spoken language,) our attention
                    has,<lb/>hitherto, rather been directed to the characteristic physiognomy<lb/>of
                    the figures and their peculiar formation, than to the spirit<lb/>of the methods
                    by which human sagacity has succeeded in<lb/>expressing quantities with a
                    greater or less degree of simplicity.<lb/>These researches have been entered
                    into with views as narrow<lb/>and as contracted as those made on languages. The
                    latter<lb/>have, for a length of time, been compared rather according to<lb/>the
                    frequency of certain sounds and terminations, or to the<lb/>form of their roots,
                    than to the organic formation of their<lb/>grammars. For many years I have been
                    occupied constantly,<lb/>and with particular predilection, in endeavouring to
                    bring<lb/>under a general view the different systems of numerical
                    figures<lb/>used by the different nations of ancient and modern times, and
                    in<lb/>this way I have succeeded in throwing some light on the origin<lb/>of
                    what is called the <hi rendition="#i">Arabic numerical system.</hi> Many
                    circum-<lb/>stances concurred to enable me to effect it. I myself
                    have<lb/>acquired, on my travels, a knowledge of the numerical systems<lb/>of
                    the Aztekes (Mexicans), and of the Muyscas <note place="foot" n="*">On the
                        opinion that the numerical figures of the Muyscas (which at the<lb/>same
                        time are the hieroglyphics of the moon-days of the increasing age of
                        the<lb/>moon) have some connexion with the face of the moon, increasing by
                        degrees<lb/>according to its different phases, <bibl>see Humboldt, Vues des Cord.
                        et Monumens<lb/>des Peuples indigènes de l&#x2019;Amérique, t. ii., p.
                        237&#x2014;243. Pl. XLIV.</bibl></note> (the inha-<lb/>bitants of the elevated
                    plain of <placeName>Cundinamarca</placeName>); <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Thomas<lb/>Young</persName> made the discovery of the Egyptian
                    numerical figures,<lb/>which (as is now known) do not, all of them, express
                        the<lb/><hi rendition="#i">multipla</hi> of the groups by juxtaposition; the
                    Arabic Gobar,<lb/>or Dust-figures, were discovered by <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Silvestre de Sacy</persName>, in
                        a<lb/><pb n="301" facs="#f0002"/> Parisian manuscript; the peculiar nature
                    of this system in-<lb/>duced me to compare it with the numerical figures of
                    the<lb/>Mexicans and Chinese; by the publication of a great number<lb/>of Indian
                    grammars we have lately obtained the certainty,<lb/>that in <placeName>India</placeName> within the
                    <placeName>Ganges</placeName>, as well as without that river,<lb/>not only different figures and
                    alphabetical signs are used in<lb/>expressing numbers, but also that the systems
                    themselves of<lb/>computation differ from one another,&#x2014;in some of them
                    value<lb/>being expressed by position, in others not; lastly, a
                    peculiar<lb/>Indian method, till now quite unknown, has been preserved<lb/>and
                    discovered in a scholion of the Greek monk <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Neophytus</persName>.<lb/>In an Essay composed
                    by me, and read in the Session of the<lb/>Académie des Inscriptions et Belles
                    Lettres, in 1819, I have<lb/>already tried to shew, that some nations shorten
                    the unartificial<lb/>method of juxtaposition by writing exponents, or
                    indicators<lb/>over the figures, (as it is used by the Mexicans, in the
                    ligatures<lb/>of four times 13, or 52 years, by the Chinese, the
                    Japanese,<lb/>and the Hindoos, speaking the Tamul language,) and also
                    the<lb/>manner in which, by means of these indicators, and the sup-<lb/>pression
                    of the group-signs written horizontally or vertically,<lb/>the excellent Indian
                    system, expressing value by position,<lb/>might have been arrived at. The
                    spreading of this system<lb/>must considerably have been favoured by the very
                    ancient use<lb/>of a particular contrivance, <hi rendition="#i">the strings of
                        reminiscence and cal-<lb/>culation.</hi> These are either loose cords, as
                    the quippos of the<lb/>Tartars, Chinese, Egyptians, Peruvians <note place="foot"
                        n="*">On the quippos used for counting the sins in the confessional, <bibl>see
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Acosta</persName>,<lb/>Hist. Natural de las Indias, lib. vi., cap. 8</bibl>. <bibl>El Inca
                                Garcilaso, lib. vi., cap. 9.</bibl><lb/><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Freret</persName>, Mem. de l&#x2019;Acad. t. vi., p.
                        109.</bibl></note>, and Mexicans,<lb/>which have been transformed into Christian
                    beads, or ritual<lb/>calculation-machines <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;"
                        ><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Klaproth&#x2019;s</persName> Asiat. Magaz., t. ii., p. 78.</bibl></note>; or they are
                    extended and fixed in a<lb/>frame. In the last form they are found in the <hi
                        rendition="#i">Suanpan</hi>, used<lb/>in all the internal countries of <placeName>Asia</placeName>,
                    in the <hi rendition="#i">abacus</hi> of the<lb/>Romans and ancient Tuscans
                    <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Otfried Müller&#x2019;s</persName> Etrusker, t. ii., p.
                        318.</bibl></note>, and in the instruments of<lb/>the palpable arithmetic used by
                    the Slavonian tribes <note place="foot" n="§">In the Russian language <hi
                            rendition="#i">chotki</hi> signifies the beads, and <hi rendition="#i"
                            >choty</hi> the calculation-<lb/>board, with its fixed
                    cords.</note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The files of cords or wires in the very simple Asiatic<lb/><pb n="302"
                        facs="#f0003"/> Suanpan represent the higher or lower groups of a
                    numeral<lb/>system, whether tenths, hundredths, and thousandths, or, in
                    the<lb/>sexagesimal division, degrees, minutes, and seconds. The<lb/>manner of
                    calculating is always the same. The pearls or<lb/>beads again are the indicators
                    of the groups, and an empty<lb/>file indicates a cypher, consequently the empty
                        <hi rendition="#i">sunya</hi> (sansu),<lb/><hi rendition="#i">sifr,</hi> or
                    properly <hi rendition="#i">sifron, sihron</hi> (Arabic, according to <hi
                        rendition="#i"><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Meninski</persName><lb/>prorsus vacuum</hi>).</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>I am not able to prove in a strict historical manner, that the<lb/>Indian system
                    of nine figures, indicating different values by<lb/>the places they occupy, has
                    been invented in the way I have<lb/>indicated, but I believe I have discovered
                    the way in which<lb/>this invention may have been gradually brought about.
                    That,<lb/>perhaps, is as much as can be done: for the history of the<lb/>first
                    steps in the development of the mental faculties, and of<lb/>the scale of
                    civilization, is involved in darkness; and com-<lb/>monly imparts to us nothing
                    more than the knowledge of<lb/>possibilities. But it is for that very reason
                    that this part of<lb/>history is so interesting.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Only a short extract of the Essay read by me in the Aca-<lb/>démie des
                    Inscriptions has been published, and that in a place<lb/>where it hardly will be
                    sought for <note place="foot" n="*"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Gay Lussac</persName> et <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Arago</persName>, Annales de Chimie et de
                        Physique, t. xii., p. 93</bibl>,<lb/>among the Monthly Notices of the Transactions
                        of the Institute. <bibl>Humboldt,<lb/>Essais Pol. sur la Nouvelle Espagne (2d.
                        edit.), t. iii., p. 122&#x2014;124</bibl>.</note>. The manuscript itself is<lb/>in
                    the hands of M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Champollion</persName>, who intended to publish it,<lb/>with some new and
                    important facts respecting the different<lb/>methods of the Egyptian figures
                    discovered by him in <placeName>Turin</placeName>.<lb/>Since that time I have continued, from time to
                    time, to render<lb/>my first work more complete; but as I have no hope left
                    to<lb/>find the necessary leisure for publishing it in its whole extent,<lb/>I
                    intend to put together in this essay the most important re-<lb/>sults. Perhaps
                    this is also a favourable time for doing it; for,<lb/>now that the researches
                    respecting languages and monuments<lb/>have taken a different and more useful
                    direction, and that<lb/>our intercourse with the nations inhabiting the southern
                    and<lb/>eastern countries of <placeName>Asia</placeName> is on the increase, it may be of
                    some<lb/>utility to bring into discussion problems, which are in
                    close<lb/>connexion with the intellectual march of the human mind, and<lb/><pb
                        n="303" facs="#f0004"/> (by the latest comparisons of numerical
                    hieroglyphics, and the<lb/>simple graphic method,) with our glorious progress in
                    the<lb/>mathematical sciences. One of the greatest mathematicians<lb/>of our
                    times and of all times, the author of the &#x201C;<bibl>Mécanique<lb/>Céleste</bibl> <note
                        place="foot" n="*"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Laplace</persName>, Exposé du système du Monde (5th edit.), p. 325</bibl>.
                        The assertion of<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Delambre</persName>, (<bibl>Histoire de l&#x2019;Astron. Ancienne, t.
                        i., p. 543,</bibl>) in his contest respecting<lb/>the merit of the ancient Indian
                        arithmetic, as it is explained in <hi rendition="#i"><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Bhascara
                            Acharya&#x2019;s</persName><lb/><bibl>Lilawati</bibl>,</hi> is in very strange opposition to the
                        opinion of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Laplace</persName>. But language<lb/>alone can hardly prompt me to suppress
                        the figures of the groups.</note>,&#x201D; says, &#x201C;The idea of
                    expressing all quantities by<lb/>nine figures, whereby is imparted to them both
                    an absolute<lb/>value, and one by position, is so simple, that this very
                    sim-<lb/>plicity is the reason for our not being sufficiently aware,
                    how<lb/>much admiration it deserves. But it is this simplicity, and<lb/>the
                    facility which calculations acquire by it, that raises the<lb/>arithmetical
                    system of the Indians to the rank of the most<lb/>useful inventions. How
                    difficult it was to discover such a<lb/>method may be inferred from the
                    circumstance, that it has<lb/>escaped the talents of <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Archimedes</persName> and of
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Apollonius</persName> of <placeName>Perga</placeName>,<lb/>two of the most profound geniuses of antiquity.&#x201D;
                    The fol-<lb/>lowing observations, I hope, will shew, that the Indian
                    method<lb/>of calculation may very possibly have arisen by degrees out
                    of<lb/>others, which were used earlier, and even now continue to be<lb/>used, in
                    the eastern countries of <placeName>Asia</placeName>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>As language, in general, affects the manner of writing, and<lb/>writing again
                    reacts on language, but only under certain con-<lb/>ditions which have been
                    inquired into by <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Silvestre de Sacy</persName>, and<lb/>my brother, so also the different
                    modes of computation used<lb/>by different nations, and their numerical
                    hieroglyphics, recipro-<lb/>cally act upon one another. Yet no very great
                    consequence<lb/>is to be attached to this alternate action. Numerical
                    figures<lb/>do not always follow the same groups of unities like
                    languages;<lb/>and moreover in languages we do not always discover the
                    same<lb/>resting-points (the same quinary intermediate stops) as
                    in<lb/>numerical signs. But if we bring together under one view,<lb/>the
                    language (names of numbers) and the numerical figures used<lb/>in the remotest
                    parts of the earth, as the common product of<lb/>human intelligence applied to
                    quantitative relations, we discover<lb/>in the written numbers of one race, the
                    isolated seeming pecu-<lb/>liarities of language of another race; we may even
                    add, that<lb/><pb n="304" facs="#f0005"/> a certain awkwardness in the numerical
                    command of language<lb/>and writing is a very false standard of what is called
                    the state<lb/>of cultivation of mankind. Here the same complicated
                    and<lb/>contrasted relations to each other take place, as with nations,<lb/>of
                    which some possess an alphabet, or mere ideographical signs,<lb/>some have the
                    most luxuriant abundance of grammatical forms<lb/>and flexions, rising out of
                    the root in systematical progression,<lb/>whilst others use languages destitute
                    of forms and flexions, as<lb/>if benumbed in their very birth; and all this in
                    the most dif-<lb/>ferent gradations of intellectual culture and political
                    institu-<lb/>tions. So the one race of mankind finds itself driven in
                    the<lb/>most opposite directions by the alternate action of the internal<lb/>and
                    external world, (an alternate action whose first decisive<lb/>efforts are
                    wrapped up in the mythological darkness of the<lb/>remotest antiquity); keeping
                    most stedfastly to its old nature,<lb/>even when great revolutions of the world
                    bring geographi-<lb/>cally near to each other races the most heterogeneous
                    in<lb/>language: whilst the similarity of the sounds which re-echo<lb/>from the
                    remotest zones, in grammatical forms of language, and<lb/>graphic attempts to
                    express large numbers, proves the unity of<lb/>the old stock&#x2014;the
                    ascendancy of that which springs out of<lb/>the internal intelligence, out of
                    the common organization of<lb/>mankind.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Travellers observing that some nations formed heaps of five<lb/>or twenty pebbles
                    or grains of seed, when they were about to<lb/>make a computation, asserted that
                    these nations were not<lb/>capable to count farther than till five or twenty
                    <note place="foot" n="*"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Pauw</persName>, Recherches Philos. sur les Américains, t.
                        ii., p. 162.</bibl> <bibl>(Humboldt,<lb/>Monumens Américains, t. ii., p.
                        232&#x2014;237.)</bibl></note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>As well may it be asserted that the Europeans are not<lb/>capable of counting
                    farther than ten, because seventeen is com-<lb/>pounded of seven and ten. In the
                    language of the most cul-<lb/>tivated nations of the west, for instance in those
                    of the Greeks<lb/>and Romans, some expressions are yet preserved, which
                    refer<lb/>evidently to such heaps or groups,
                    &#x03C8;&#x03B5;&#x03C6;&#x03AF;&#x03B6;&#x03B5;&#x03B9;&#x03BD;, <hi
                        rendition="#i">ponere calculum,<lb/>calculum detrahere.</hi> Groups of
                    unities procure resting-places<lb/>in counting; and as in the different nations
                    the members of<lb/>the body are similarly formed (the four extremities are
                    divided<lb/>fivefoldly) they stop either after having counted the fingers
                        of<lb/><pb n="305" facs="#f0006"/> one hand, or those of both, or they add
                    also the two feet to the<lb/>hands. This difference in proceeding produces
                    different rest-<lb/>ing-places, and thus are formed groups of 5, 10, or 20. It
                    is,<lb/>however, worth observing, that among the nations of the
                    new<lb/>continent, as among the Mandingas in <placeName>Africa</placeName>, the Biscayans,<lb/>and the
                    Gaelic tribes of the old continent, groups of twenty<lb/>are in prevailing use
                        <note place="foot" n="*">Instances of such numeral groups of twenty unities
                        are found in <placeName>America</placeName><lb/>among the <hi rendition="#i">Muyscas</hi>, the
                        Otomites, the Aztekes, the Cora Indians, &amp;c.</note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In the Chibcha language of the Muyscas, (who, like the<lb/>inhabitants of <placeName>Japan</placeName>
                    and of <placeName>Thibet</placeName> had an ecclesiastical and a<lb/>laical chief; and whose method of
                    intercalating the 37th month<lb/>like the inhabitants of <placeName>North India</placeName>, has been
                    published and<lb/>explained by me <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;"><bibl>Monum.
                        Américains, t. ii., p. 250&#x2014;253</bibl>. The Muyscas had some
                        stones<lb/>covered with arithmetical hieroglyphs, which, by being placed in
                        a certain order,<lb/>facilitated to the priests (xeques) the intercalation
                        of the ritual year. The figure<lb/>of a stone which served for that purpose
                        may be seen in my <bibl>work, Tab. XLIV.</bibl></note>), 11, 12, 13, are called foot one
                    (quihieha<lb/>ata), foot two (quihieha bosa), foot three (quihieha
                    mica),<lb/>from quihieha or quhieha (foot), and the first three unities,<lb/><hi
                        rendition="#i">ata, bozha</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">bosa</hi>, and <hi
                        rendition="#i">mica</hi>. The arithmetical signification<lb/>of <hi
                        rendition="#i">foot</hi> is ten, because the foot begins to be taken into
                    account,<lb/>when both hands are passed through. To express twenty,
                    the<lb/>Muyscas use in their arithmetical language the expression <hi
                        rendition="#i">foot<lb/>ten</hi>, or <hi rendition="#i">the small house</hi>
                    (gueta), perhaps because they used, in<lb/>counting, grains of maize, and such a
                    heap of maize reminded<lb/>them of the barn, where maize was laid up. By means
                    of the<lb/>expression <hi rendition="#i">small house</hi> (or barn), and twenty
                    (both feet and<lb/>hands) they formed the expressions for 30, 40, 80, by
                    joining<lb/>them together, as, twenty plus ten; twice twenty; four
                    times<lb/>twenty. Quite similar are the Celtic expressions which have<lb/>passed
                    into the languages of Roman origin, as, quatre vingt,<lb/>and quinze vingt, or
                    those more rarely met with, as six vingt,<lb/>sept vingt, huit vingt. Deux
                    vingt, and trois vingt are not<lb/>used in French; but in the Gaelic or Celtic
                    dialect of <placeName>West<lb/>Britany</placeName>, through which I passed a few years ago, twenty
                    is<lb/>called <hi rendition="#i">ugent</hi>, forty <hi rendition="#i"
                        >daou-ugent</hi>, or two twenty; sixty <hi rendition="#i"
                    >tri-ugent</hi>,<lb/>or three twenty. It is even said <hi rendition="#i">deh ha
                        nao ugent,</hi> or ten over<lb/>nine twenty = 190 <note
                            place="foot" n="&#x2021;" xml:id="fn1-1" next="#fn1-2"><bibl><hi rendition="#i"><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Davies&#x2019;s</persName> Celtic
                                Researches,</hi> 1804. p. 321</bibl>. <bibl>Legodinec Grammaire
                            Celto-bretonne</bibl>,</note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <pb n="306" facs="#f0007"/>
                <p>It is by no means a difficult task for me to give a still greater<lb/>number of
                    remarkable instances of the analogy existing between<lb/>language and numerical
                    hieroglyphics in juxtaposition, in the<lb/>subtraction of unities by prefixing
                    them, in writing, before<lb/>the group, and in the intermediate landing-places
                    of 5 and 15<lb/>in those nations who have adopted groups of 10 or 20. In<lb/>the
                    languages of some very rude American tribes, for instance<lb/>in those of the
                        <hi rendition="#i">Guarinis</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Lulos, six,
                        seven</hi>, and <hi rendition="#i">eight</hi> are<lb/>expressed by <hi
                        rendition="#i">four with two, four with three, five with three</hi>.<lb/>The
                    more civilized <hi rendition="#i">Muyscas</hi> say <hi rendition="#i"
                        >twenty</hi> (or house) <hi rendition="#i">with ten,</hi><lb/>instead of
                    thirty. The Cymri, in <placeName>Wales</placeName>, use in such a case<lb/><hi rendition="#i">deg</hi>
                    (ten), or <hi rendition="#i">ugain</hi> (with twenty); as the French use <hi
                        rendition="#i">soixante<lb/>et dix</hi>, for seventy. We find addition
                    effected by juxta-<lb/>position, chiefly among the old Tuscans, Romans,
                    Mexicans,<lb/>and Egyptians; subtractive or diminishing expressions
                    among<lb/>the Indians in the Sanscrit <note place="foot" n="*">M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Bopp</persName> quotes
                        even 95 (or hundred &#x2014;5) in the words pantschonam
                        satam<lb/>&#x2014;contracted from <hi rendition="#i"><choice><sic>pantcsha</sic><corr type="editorial">pantscha</corr></choice></hi> (five)
                        and <hi rendition="#i">una</hi> (less).</note>, where 19 is called <hi
                        rendition="#i">unavinsati,</hi><lb/>99 <hi rendition="#i">unasata;</hi>
                    among the Romans in <hi rendition="#i">undeviginti</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">unus
                        de<lb/>viginti</hi>), for 19; <hi rendition="#i">undeoctoginta</hi>, for 79;
                        <hi rendition="#i">duodequadraginta</hi>,<lb/>for 38: among the Greeks in
                    &#x03B5;&#x1F34;&#x03BA;&#x03BF;&#x03C3;&#x03B9;
                    &#x03B4;&#x03B5;&#x03CC;&#x03BD;&#x03C4;&#x03B1;
                    &#x1F15;&#x03BD;&#x03BF;&#x03C2;, 19;
                    and<lb/>&#x03C0;&#x03B5;&#x03BD;&#x03C4;&#x03B5;&#x03BA;&#x03CC;&#x03BD;&#x03C4;&#x03B1;
                    &#x03B4;&#x03C5;&#x03BF;&#x1FD6;&#x03BD;
                    &#x03B4;&#x03B5;&#x03BF;&#x03BD;&#x03C4;&#x03BF;&#x1FD6;&#x03BD;, 48; that is,
                        <hi rendition="#i">wanting two to make up<lb/>fifty</hi>. Such subtractive
                    expressions have passed into the<lb/>writing of numbers, and in such a case the
                    figures expressing<lb/>unities to be subtracted are prefixed to the signs of the
                    groups<lb/>of five and ten, and even to their multiplicates, for
                    instance,<lb/>to 50 or 100 (IV, and XI, and XL, and XT, for four-and-<lb/>forty
                    among the Romans and ancient Tuscans <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Otfried
                        Müller</persName>, Etrusker, ii., p. 317&#x2014;320</bibl>.</note>; though in<lb/>the last
                    nation the numerical figures probably were entirely<lb/>derived from the
                    alphabet, according to the researches lately<lb/>made by <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Otfried Müller</persName>). In
                    some rare Roman inscriptions<lb/>
                    <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1"
                            ><bibl>1807, p. 55</bibl>. In the Celtic or Kymrich dialect of Wales, 5 is called <hi
                                rendition="#i">pump;</hi><lb/>10 <hi rendition="#i">deg;</hi> 20 <hi
                                rendition="#i">ugain;</hi> 30 <hi rendition="#i">deg ar ugain;</hi>
                            40 <hi rendition="#i">deugain;</hi> 60 <hi rendition="#i">trigain.</hi>
                        <bibl>(<persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">William<lb/>Owen&#x2019;s</persName> Dictionary of the Welsh Language, vol. i., p.
                            137.</bibl>) The same system<lb/>of twenty unities is used in the language of
                            the Biscayans: <hi rendition="#i">bi</hi> is 2; <hi rendition="#i"
                                >lau,</hi> 4;<lb/><hi rendition="#i">amar,</hi> 10; <hi
                                rendition="#i">oguai,</hi> 20; <hi rendition="#i">birroguai,</hi>
                            40; <hi rendition="#i">lauroguai,</hi> 80; <hi rendition="#i"
                                >berrgouai-tamar,</hi> 50, namely<lb/>forty and ten (amar). <bibl><hi
                                    rendition="#i"><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Larramendi</persName>,</hi> urte della Lengua Bascongada, 1729,
                            p. 38.</bibl><lb/>(The numeral figures of the Biscayan and Gaelic languages are
                            not mixed toge-<lb/>ther in <bibl>my Monum. vol. ii., p. 237</bibl>, but they are
                            placed near one another to facili-<lb/>tate the comparison; by an error
                            of print, however, <hi rendition="#i">les premiers</hi> is said instead
                                of<lb/><hi rendition="#i">les deux</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">les
                                uns et les autres.</hi>)</note><lb/><pb n="307" facs="#f0008"
                                /> collected by <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Marini</persName> <note place="foot" n="*"><bibl>Iscrizioni della Villa di
                        Albano, p. 193.</bibl> <bibl>Hervas Aritmetica delle Nazioni,<lb/>1786, p. 11,
                    16.</bibl></note>, even four unities are found before ten,<lb/>for instance, IIIIX=6.
                    We shall soon see, that among some<lb/>tribes inhabiting the East Indies,
                    methods are found in which<lb/>the joining of figures, which among the Romans
                    and ancient<lb/>Tuscans indicated only addition or subtraction,
                    expresses<lb/>addition or multiplication, according to the place or the
                    direc-<lb/>tion of the signs. In these Indian systems, (to use
                    Roman<lb/>figures,) IIX is twenty, and XII is twelve.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In many languages the groups of 5, 10, and 20, are called<lb/>a hand, two hands,
                    and hand and foot (in the language of<lb/>the Guaranis <hi rendition="#i"
                        >mbombiade</hi>). When the fingers of both ex-<lb/>tremities, viz., fingers
                    and toes, are gone through in counting,<lb/>then it is considered that the
                    number comprehends the whole<lb/>body, thus: the word <hi rendition="#i"
                        >man</hi> becomes the symbol for twenty.<lb/>Therefore, in the language of
                    the Yaruros (of which tribe I<lb/>found populous villages, erected by the
                    missionaries on the river<lb/><placeName>Apure</placeName>, which falls into the <placeName>Orinoco</placeName>) forty are
                    called two men,<lb/><hi rendition="#i">noeni pume</hi>, from <hi rendition="#i"
                        >no eni</hi> two, and <hi rendition="#i">pume</hi> man. It is
                    known,<lb/>that in the Persian language the word <hi rendition="#i">pencha</hi>
                    signifies <hi rendition="#i">fist</hi>,<lb/>and <hi rendition="#i">pendj</hi>
                    five, derived from the Sanscrit word <hi rendition="#i">pancha</hi>.
                    &#x201C;The<lb/>last is (according to the ingenious observation of M.
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Bopp</persName>)<lb/>to be considered as the original of the Roman <hi rendition="#i"
                        >quinque</hi>, as the<lb/>Indian <hi rendition="#i">chatur</hi> of quatuor.
                    The plural of <hi rendition="#i">chatur</hi> is chatvaras,<lb/>and approaches
                    very near the Doric-&#x00C6;olian
                    &#x03C4;&#x03AD;&#x03C4;&#x03C4;&#x03B1;&#x03C1;&#x03B5;&#x03C2;. The<lb/>Indian
                        <hi rendition="#i">ch</hi> is pronounced as the English in words of
                    Saxon<lb/>origin, but in Greek it becomes a <hi rendition="#i">t;</hi> therefore
                        <hi rendition="#i">chatvaras</hi> is<lb/>changed into <hi rendition="#i"
                        >tatvaras,</hi> as <hi rendition="#i">pancha</hi> into <hi rendition="#i"
                        >panta</hi> (the Greek
                    &#x03C0;&#x03AD;&#x03BD;&#x03C4;&#x03B5;,<lb/>&#x00C6;olice
                    &#x03C0;&#x03AD;&#x03BC;&#x03C0;&#x03B5;, whence
                    &#x03C0;&#x03B5;&#x03BC;&#x03C0;&#x03AC;&#x03B6;&#x03B5;&#x03B9;&#x03BD; to
                    count by fingers, or up<lb/>to five). But in the Latin language, the Indian <hi
                        rendition="#i">ch</hi> is ex-<lb/>pressed by <hi rendition="#i">qu</hi> and
                    thus <hi rendition="#i">chatur</hi> is changed into <hi rendition="#i"
                        >quatuor,</hi> and<lb/><hi rendition="#i">pancha</hi> into <hi
                        rendition="#i">quinque. Pancha</hi> itself never signifies in India<lb/><hi
                        rendition="#i">hand</hi>, but only the number five. But panchasakha is
                    a<lb/>descriptive expression for hand, as a limb with five branches <note
                        place="foot" n="&#x2020;">On the numerals in Sanscrit, compared with those
                        of the Greek, Latin and<lb/>Gothic languages, a very interesting essay, in
                        manuscript, was communicated to<lb/>me by M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Bopp</persName>, in <placeName>Paris</placeName>, in 1820; and it
                        was composed by him for the purpose<lb/>of being inserted in <bibl>my work, <hi
                            rendition="#i">On the Numerical Signs of
                    Nations.</hi></bibl></note>.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>As in languages, and with peculiar na&#x00EF;veté in those of<lb/><pb n="308"
                        facs="#f0009"/> <placeName>South America</placeName>, the groups of five, ten, and twenty,
                    are<lb/>distinguished by peculiar expressions, so, in the same manner,<lb/>these
                    groups are easily to be recognized in numeral hiero-<lb/>glyphics. The Romans
                    and Tuscans <note place="foot" n="*">Respecting the Tuscan figure for 500, see
                        <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Otfried Müller</persName>, Etrusker, sec. iv.,<lb/>fig. 2</bibl>.</note> had single figures
                    to<lb/>express 5, 50, and 500. In the language of the Aztekes<lb/>(natives of
                    <placeName>Mexico</placeName>), we find not only the group-signs of a<lb/>flag for 20, <hi
                        rendition="#i">a quill filled with grains of gold</hi> (which in
                    some<lb/>districts of <placeName>Mexico</placeName> were used as money) for the quadrate of<lb/>20 or
                    400, and a bag (xiquipilli) with 8000 cocoa nuts (which<lb/>likewise served as a
                    medium of barter) for the cube of 20 or<lb/>8000, but even (in the instances
                    where the flag is divided into<lb/>four equal parts, and the half or three
                    quarters of it are<lb/>coloured) numerical signs for <hi rendition="#i"
                        >half-twenty</hi> or 10, and for<lb/><formula notation="TeX">\frac{3}{4}</formula> twenty or 15, two hands and a
                    foot, as it were <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;"><bibl>Humboldt, Monum. Améric., tom.
                        i., p. 309.</bibl></note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>But the most remarkable of all proofs of the alternate effect<lb/>between
                    numerical language and numerical figures, is to be<lb/>met with in <placeName>India</placeName>. Here
                    the value of the unities expressed<lb/>by their position has, in Sanscrit, been
                    even transplanted into<lb/>the language. Thus the Indians have a figurative
                    method<lb/>of expressing numbers by the names of objects, of which a<lb/>certain
                    number is known. For instance, <hi rendition="#i">surya</hi> (the sun)
                    ex-<lb/>presses 12, because, according to the mythology of the
                    Hindoos,<lb/>there were twelve suns in the order of the twelve months.
                    The<lb/>two <hi rendition="#i">Aswinas</hi> (Castor and Pollux), who also are
                    met with in<lb/>the Nakchatras, are used to express the number two. <hi
                        rendition="#i">Manu</hi><lb/>signifies fourteen, taken from the <hi
                        rendition="#i">menus</hi> of their mythology.<lb/>Now it will become
                    intelligible, how the word <hi rendition="#i">surymanu,</hi> in which<lb/>the
                    symbols of twelve and fourteen are combined, signifies the<lb/>year 1214. These
                    facts I owe to the kind communication of<lb/>the learned <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Colebrooke</persName>. Probably,
                    according to these prin-<lb/>ciples, 1412 will be expressed by <hi
                        rendition="#i">Manusurya,</hi> and 314 by<lb/><hi rendition="#i"
                        >Aswinimanu.</hi> We find besides so complete a numeration in<lb/>Sanscrit,
                    that a single word, <hi rendition="#i">koti</hi>, is used to express 10
                    millions.<lb/>In the <hi rendition="#i">qquichau</hi> language of <placeName>Peru</placeName>, which
                    does not count by<lb/>groups of twenty, a single word stands for a million
                    (hunu).</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>If it be true that we count by decimals, <hi rendition="#i">quia tot digiti,
                        per</hi><lb/><pb n="309" facs="#f0010"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">quos numerare solemus,</hi> as <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Ovid</persName> says, we probably should
                    have<lb/>adopted a duodenary scale <note place="foot" n="*"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Debrosses</persName>, vol. ii.,
                        p. 158</bibl>.</note>, if our extremities had been<lb/>divided sixfoldly. Such a
                    scale has the great advantage, that<lb/>its groups can be divided by 2, 3, 4 and
                    6 without leaving<lb/>a fraction, and for that reason it has been adopted by
                    the<lb/>Chinese for their measures and weights, from the earliest<lb/>times.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The preceding observations regard the relation between<lb/>language and writing,
                    between the numerals and their figures.<lb/>I shall proceed to consider the
                    latter by themselves. I remind<lb/>the reader that this essay is only an extract
                    from my larger<lb/>and unfinished work, and that I shall not speak of the
                    hete-<lb/>rogeneous forms of the simple elements (numerical) figures,<lb/>but of
                    the spirit of the different methods of expressing<lb/>numeral quantities, which
                    are adopted by different nations.<lb/>I, therefore, shall only take notice of
                    the figure or form of the<lb/>numerical signs, whenever it affects my
                    conclusions respecting<lb/>the identity or heterogeneousness of the methods
                    themselves.<lb/>The mode of proceeding adopted for the purpose of
                    expressing<lb/>the pure or mixed <hi rendition="#i">multipla</hi> of the denary
                    fundamental groups<lb/><hi rendition="#i">n</hi> (for instance 4<hi
                        rendition="#i">n,</hi> 4<hi rendition="#i">n</hi><hi rendition="#sup"
                    >2</hi>, or 4<hi rendition="#i">n</hi> + 7, 4<hi rendition="#i">n</hi><hi
                        rendition="#sup">2</hi> + 6<hi rendition="#i">n,</hi> 4<hi rendition="#i"
                        >n</hi><hi rendition="#sup">2</hi> + 6<hi rendition="#i">n</hi> + 5)
                    is<lb/>very different in different nations. Sometimes it is effected
                    by<lb/>forming a row (that is by giving different value to the
                    figures<lb/>according to their position), after the manner of some
                    nations<lb/>of the Hindoos; sometimes by mere juxtaposition, as among<lb/>the
                    ancient Tuscans, the Romans, Mexicans, and Egyptians.<lb/>Some nations use for
                    that purpose coefficients, as that tribe<lb/>of the Hindoos, inhabiting India
                    within the <placeName>Ganges</placeName>, which uses<lb/>the Tamul language; others use exponents or
                    indicators,<lb/>placed over the figures of the groups, as the Chinese,
                    Japanese,<lb/>and also the Greek in employing myriads; others again, use<lb/>an
                    inverted method. These place over the nine numerical<lb/>figures a number of
                    cyphers or points, to indicate the relative<lb/>value of them, and in this
                    system, the cyphers or points are<lb/>the signs of the groups placed over the
                    unities. The last<lb/>method is found in the Arabic Gobar writings, and in
                    an<lb/>Indian numerical system, preserved and explained in a scho-<lb/><pb
                        n="310" facs="#f0011"/> lion of the Greek monk <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Neophytus</persName>. These five
                    different<lb/>methods are in no way dependent on the forms of the
                    nu-<lb/>merical figures, and to prove this fact more evidently, I shall,<lb/>in
                    this treatise, employ no other signs than the arithmetical<lb/>and algebraical,
                    which are in common use. In this way the<lb/>attention is more directed to the
                    essential point, the spirit<lb/>of the method. I already have used such a mode
                    of pasi-<lb/>graphic notations in another work, treating of a very
                    hete-<lb/>rogeneous subject, the regular stratification and often
                    peri-<lb/>odical filation of the minerals (<bibl>in the appendix to the
                    Essai<lb/>Geognostique sur le Gisement des Roches</bibl>) <note place="foot" n="*"><bibl>Ed.
                        1823, p. 364&#x2014;375.</bibl></note>, and there I<lb/>have tried to shew, how by
                    this method our abstract views<lb/>on an object can be rendered more general.
                    Proceeding in<lb/>this way, all observations respecting the form and
                    composition<lb/>of individuals, which in themselves may be very useful
                    and<lb/>true, but would turn off the attention, are suppressed, in<lb/>order to
                    place in a purer and clearer light a phenomenon,<lb/>which we wish to
                    investigate in preference to others. This<lb/>is an advantage which in some way
                    may be justified by the<lb/>chilly insipidity of such abstractions.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>As regards the manner of writing numbers adopted by dif-<lb/>ferent nations, it
                    is usual to distinguish the <hi rendition="#i">figures not de-<lb/>pending on
                        alphabetical</hi> letters, from the alphabetical letters<lb/>which indicate
                    numerical value, either by forming a certain<lb/>row, or by short lines or
                    points added to them; or lastly, by<lb/>the initials of the numerals (in
                    reference to language) <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">The Arabic figures called
                            <hi rendition="#i">Diwani,</hi> are compounded of mere monograms
                        or<lb/>abbreviations of the initial letters of the numerals, and are the
                        most complicated<lb/>instance of such initials. Whether the C and M, used by
                        the ancient Tuscans and<lb/>Romans, are, in fact, initials taken from the
                        Tuscan and Roman languages, is much<lb/>more subject to doubt than is
                        commonly believed. (<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Leslie</persName>, Philos. of Arith., p. 7<lb/>&#x2014;9, 211</bibl>.
                        <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Debrosses</persName>, t. i., p. 436</bibl>. <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Hervas</persName>, p. 32&#x2014;35</bibl>. <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Otfried Müller</persName>,
                        Etrusker,<lb/>p. 304&#x2014;318.</bibl>) The cross at right angles, used by the
                        Greek, and quite similar to<lb/>the Chinese figure of ten, signifies in the
                        most ancient inscriptions <hi rendition="#i">a thousand</hi><lb/>(<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Boeckh</persName>,
                        Corpus Inscript. Graec., vol. i., p. 23</bibl>), and is only the oldest form of <hi
                            rendition="#i">ch.</hi><lb/>(<bibl>Nouveau Traité de Diplom. par deux
                        Religieux de St. Maur, vol. i., p. 678.</bibl>)</note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>It is beyond all doubt, that the nations of Hellenic, Semitic,<lb/>and Aramaic
                    origin (among the last even the Arabs, before<lb/>they received the numerical
                    figures from the Persians, in the<lb/>fifth century of the Hegira <note
                        place="foot" n="&#x2021;"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Silvestre de Sacy</persName>, Gramm. Arabe, 1810, t. i., p.
                        74, Note 6</bibl>.</note>), used the same signs to express<lb/><pb n="311"
                        facs="#f0012"/> letters and numerals, even in the period of their ripe
                    civiliza-<lb/>tion. On the other hand we find, in the new continent,
                    at<lb/>least two nations, the Aztekes and the Muyscas, who used<lb/>numerical
                    figures without having letters. Among the Egyp-<lb/>tians, the numerical
                    hieroglyphics commonly used to express<lb/>units, tenths, hundreds, and
                    thousands, seem likewise to have<lb/>had no relation to the phonetic
                    hieroglyphics. Quite different<lb/>from the alphabet are likewise the ancient
                    Persian figures of<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">Pehlwi</hi>, for the first nine
                    unities, as those of the ancient<lb/>Tuscans, the Romans, and even the Greeks in
                    the most ancient<lb/>times. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Anquetil</persName> has already observed <note place="foot"
                        n="*"><bibl>Mém. de l&#x2019;Acad. des Belles Lettres, t. xxxi., p. 357</bibl>.</note>,
                    that the alphabet of<lb/>the Zend language, which, being composed of 48
                    elements,<lb/>could have facilitated the expressing of numbers, by
                    alphabet-<lb/>ical letters, never uses them as numerical figures, and that
                    in<lb/>the books written in the Zend language, numbers are always<lb/>expressed
                    by the figures of the Pehlwi, and at the same time<lb/>with the numerals of the
                    Zend language. Should, by further<lb/>researches, this want of numerical figures
                    in the Zend language<lb/>be confirmed, it must induce us to suppose that the
                    Zend<lb/>nation, which, in its language, discovers a very intimate
                    affinity<lb/>to the Sanscrit, must have been separated from the
                    Hindoos,<lb/>before the last had arrived at expressing value by
                    position.<lb/>But, the nine unities excepted, the figures of the groups
                    of<lb/>ten, hundred, and thousand are derived from letters in the<lb/>Pehlwi
                    language. <hi rendition="#i">Dal</hi> is 10; <hi rendition="#i">re</hi> and <hi
                        rendition="#i">za,</hi> connected together,<lb/>100; <hi rendition="#i"
                        >re</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">ghain</hi>, connected together, 1000. When
                    we<lb/>take together, in one view, all that is known to us of the<lb/>numerical
                    figures used by the different nations, little as it<lb/>is, it seems sufficient
                    to oblige us to confess, that the<lb/>distinction of alphabetical numerals and
                    of numerical figures,<lb/>independent of the alphabet, is as uncertain and
                    useless<lb/>as that of the languages in such as are composed of
                    mono-<lb/>syllables, and in those using polysyllabic words, a
                    distinction<lb/>long ago abandoned by truly philosophical investigators
                    of<lb/>languages. The numerical figures used by the inhabitants of<lb/>some
                    southern districts of India within the Ganges, who speak<lb/>the Tamul language,
                    do not express value by position, and<lb/><pb n="312" facs="#f0013"/> are quite
                    different from those used in Sanscrit manuscripts, if<lb/>the figure of 2 is
                    excepted. Who can say whether these<lb/>figures are not to be derived from the
                    Tamul letters? It is<lb/>true the figure for the group of a hundred is not to be
                    found<lb/>among these letters, but the sign of the group of ten is to
                    be<lb/>recognized in the letter <hi rendition="#i">ya,</hi> and the <hi
                        rendition="#i">two</hi> in the letter <hi rendition="#i">u</hi>.
                    The<lb/>numerical figures in the <hi rendition="#i">Teloogoa</hi> language,
                    likewise spoken in<lb/>the southern districts of <placeName>India</placeName> within the <placeName>Ganges</placeName><note
                        place="foot" n="*"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Campbell&#x2019;s</persName> Grammar of the Teloogoa language,
                        (Madras,) 1816. p. 4. 208.</bibl><lb/>This is what formerly, but falsely, was
                        called the Gentoo language. By the natives<lb/>it is named <hi
                            rendition="#i">Trilinga,</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">Telenga.</hi> With
                        the table of the numerical figures in<lb/><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Campbell&#x2019;s</persName> grammar</bibl>, other
                        varieties of Indian numerical characters to be found<lb/>in <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Wahl&#x2019;s</persName>
                        General History of the Oriental Languages, 1784, Tab. I</bibl>. may be
                        <choice><sic>com</sic><corr type="editorial">com-</corr></choice><lb/>pared.</note>, which indi-<lb/>cate value by position, are in a
                    strange manner different from<lb/>all other Indian figures, as far as they are
                    known, in the signs<lb/>for 1, 8, and 9, whilst they agree with them in the
                    figures of<lb/>2, 3, 4, and 6. The necessity of expressing quantities
                    by<lb/>writing has probably been felt sooner than that of writing<lb/>words, and
                    therefore we may consider numerical figures as the<lb/>most ancient written
                    characters.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The instruments of <hi rendition="#i">palpable arithmetic</hi>, as they are
                    called<lb/>in an ingenious work, <bibl>the Philosophy of Arithmetic, by
                        Mr.<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Leslie</persName>, (1817,)</bibl> in opposition to the <hi rendition="#i">figurative</hi>
                    or <hi rendition="#i">graphic</hi>, are<lb/>both hands, heaps of pebbles
                    (calculi, &#x03C8;&#x03B7;&#x03C6;&#x03BF;&#x03B9;), grains of seed,<lb/>loose
                    strings with knots (arithmetical strings, the quippos of<lb/>the Tartars and
                    Peruvians), the suanpan put in a frame, the<lb/>table of the abacus, and the
                    calculating machine of the Slavo-<lb/>nian nations with balls or grains of seed
                    in files. All these in-<lb/>struments furnish to the eye the first graphic
                    notations of<lb/>groups of a different degree. One hand, or a string
                    with<lb/>knots or moveable balls, indicates the unities up to 5, or 10,<lb/>or
                    20. How often, by shutting of the single fingers, one hand<lb/>is gone through
                    (&#x03C0;&#x03B5;&#x03BC;&#x03C0;&#x03AC;&#x03B6;&#x03B5;&#x03C3;&#x03B8;&#x03B1;&#x03B9;),
                    is indicated by the other hand,<lb/>of which every finger, that is, every unit,
                    expresses a group of<lb/>five. Two loose strings with knots stand in the same
                    relation<lb/>to one another. The calculation-strings, with moveable
                    balls,<lb/>extended and fixed in a frame, or the ancient Asiatic
                    suanpan,<lb/>which, in very ancient times, (perhaps by the Egyptians<lb/>at the
                    time of the Pythagorean league,) was brought to the<lb/><pb n="313"
                        facs="#f0014"/> nations of the west as abax or tabula logistica, are used in
                    the<lb/>same manner, only that the strings indicate groups of second,<lb/>third,
                    and fourth order upwards and downwards. The <hi rendition="#i"
                    >kouas</hi>,<lb/>which are more ancient than the characters used at present
                    by<lb/>the Chinese, and even the magic drawings (ralm) of central<lb/><placeName>Asia</placeName> and
                    <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, which exhibit knotty parallels, often broken<lb/>off, almost in the
                    manner of musical notes, seem only to be<lb/>graphic projections of these
                    calculation and reflection-strings <note place="foot" n="*">In the East, <hi
                            rendition="#i">ralm</hi> is called the <hi rendition="#i">negromantic
                            art of the sand.</hi> Uninterrupted<lb/>lines, and others broken off,
                        present the elements of it, and direct the negromant.<lb/>(<bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Richardson</persName> and
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Wilkins</persName>, Diction. Persian and Arabic. 1806. t. i., p. 482.</bibl>) In<lb/>Dresden a
                        remarkable manuscript is preserved. It was brought from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>,
                        and<lb/>exhibits nothing but figures like musical notes. I have published it
                        in my<lb/><bibl>Monumens Améric. Pl. xliv</bibl>. When at <placeName>Paris</placeName>, I was visited by a
                        learned Persian,<lb/>who, at the first view, recognized in it an oriental
                            <hi rendition="#i">ralm.</hi> Quite similar, and truly<lb/>American
                        kouas and linear drawings, I discovered after that time in some<lb/>Aztetic
                        hieroglyphic manuscripts, and on the sculptures of <placeName>Palenque</placeName>, in the
                        repub-<lb/>lic of <placeName>Guatimala</placeName>. In the ancient Chinese numerical figures, the
                        sign of the<lb/>group of ten is a pearl on a string, and evidently an
                        imitative drawing of the<lb/>quippu.</note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In the Asiatic suanpan, and in the abacus, which was much<lb/>more used by the
                    Romans, on account of the inconvenient<lb/>figures adopted by them, than by the
                    Greeks, who had been<lb/>much more successful in their mode of writing numbers
                    <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Nicomachus</persName>, in Ast. Theologumena Arith.
                        1817, p. 96.</bibl> In the financial<lb/>system of the middle age, the account
                        table (abax) became the exchequer.</note>, the<lb/>quinary rows are
                    preserved together with the denary ones,<lb/>forming geometrical progressions
                    upwards and downwards.<lb/>Outside of every calculation-string, indicating a
                    group or<lb/>order, (<hi rendition="#i">n, n</hi><hi rendition="#sup">2</hi>,
                        <hi rendition="#i">n</hi><hi rendition="#sup">3</hi>,) a shorter string was
                    placed, on which every<lb/>ball expressed the amount of five balls of the longer
                    string.<lb/>By this contrivance the number of the unities was diminished<lb/>to
                    such a degree, that the principal string needed only to con-<lb/>tain four
                    balls, and the accessary only one <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">So the Roman
                        abacus was contrived. In <placeName>China</placeName> five balls were placed on the<lb/>first, and
                        two balls on the last. The balls, which were not employed in a
                        calcula-<lb/>tion, were pushed aside.</note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>It seems that among the Chinese, from the most ancient<lb/>times, the custom had
                    prevailed to consider arbitrarily any<lb/>one of the parallel strings as
                    containing the units, and that<lb/>thus they obtained, upwards and downwards,
                    decimal frac-<lb/>tions, entire numbers, and powers of ten <note place="foot"
                        n="§">On the first attempts to establish the decimal system, made by
                        <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Michael<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Stifelius</hi></persName> of <placeName>Eslingen</placeName>, <hi
                            rendition="#i"><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Stevenus</persName></hi> of <placeName>Brugge</placeName>, and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Bombelli</persName> of <placeName>Bologna</placeName>, see
                        <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Leslie</persName>,<lb/>Philos. of Arithmetic, p. 134.</bibl></note>. How late (in the<lb/><pb
                        n="314" facs="#f0015"/> beginning of the sixteenth century?) has the
                    knowledge of the<lb/>decimal fractions been introduced into the countries of
                    the<lb/>West, which the nations of the East had been taught long<lb/>ago by
                    their palpable arithmetic! The descending scale from<lb/>the unit downwards, was
                    known to the Greeks only in the<lb/>sexagesimal system for degrees, minutes, and
                    seconds; but as<lb/>they had not <hi rendition="#i">n</hi>&#x2014;1, that is, 59
                    numerical figures, the value by<lb/>position could only be expressed by layers
                    of two figures.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>If we direct our attention to the origin of numbers, we find<lb/>that they could
                    be written and read with great exactness, when<lb/>they were indicated by heaps
                    of pebbles, or by the balls on the<lb/>strings of the calculation-machines. The
                    impression which<lb/>these proceedings left behind on the mind, has
                    everywhere<lb/>affected the manner of writing numbers. In the
                    historical,<lb/>ritual, and negromantic hieroglyphics of the Mexicans,
                    pub-<lb/>lished by me, the units up to nineteen (the first simple figure<lb/>for
                    a group is twenty) are exhibited as great round coloured<lb/>grains, and, what
                    deserves to be mentioned, they are counted<lb/>from the right to the left hand,
                    like the Semitic writings.<lb/>This is evident in 12, 15, 17, where the first
                    row contains ten,<lb/>and the second is not quite filled up. In the most
                    ancient<lb/>Greek monuments, and in the Tuscan sepulchral inscriptions,<lb/>the
                    units are expressed by vertical lines; the same custom<lb/>prevailed among the
                    Romans and Egyptians (which, respect-<lb/>ing the last, has been proved by
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Thomas Young</persName>, <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Jomard</persName>,<lb/>and <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Champollion</persName>). The Chinese use horizontal lines up
                    to<lb/>the number four; and such lines are likewise found in
                    some<lb/>Ph&#x0153;nician coins described by <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Eckhel</persName> (<bibl>t. iii., p. 410</bibl>).
                    The<lb/>Romans sometimes omitted the quinary figure in inscriptions,<lb/>and,
                    therefore, we find even eight lines as unities placed<lb/>together. Many
                    instances of this kind are collected by <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Marini</persName>,<lb/>in his <hi rendition="#i"
                        ><bibl>Monumenti dei Fratelli Arvali</bibl></hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*"><bibl>T. i., p. 31.; t. ix., 675</bibl>&#x2014;for instance in
                        Octumvir.</note>, a work which deserves<lb/>attention. The heads of the
                    nails, which anciently were em-<lb/>ployed by the Romans to indicate the years
                    (annales antea in<lb/>clavis fuerunt, quos ex lege vetusta figebat pr&#x00E6;tor
                    maximus,<lb/>says the <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">elder Pliny</persName>, <bibl>vii. 40.</bibl>) could have led them to
                    the<lb/>unity-points of the Mexicans, and, in fact, we find such points<lb/><pb
                        n="315" facs="#f0016"/> used in the subdivision of ounces and feet, together
                    with the<lb/>horizontal lines (used by the Chinese and Ph&#x0153;nicians) <note
                        place="foot" n="*"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Marini</persName>, t. i., p. 228</bibl>.</note>.<lb/>These points and
                    lines, nine or nineteen in number, in the<lb/>denary or vicesimal scale of the
                    old and new continent, are<lb/>the most simple of all notations in the system of
                    juxtaposition.<lb/>Here the unities are properly more counted than read.
                    The<lb/>separate existence, the individuality, if I may say so, of
                    the<lb/>numerical figures as signs of numbers, is first to be recognized<lb/>in
                    the numerical letters of the Semitic and Hellenic tribes, and<lb/>among the
                    inhabitants of <placeName>Thibet</placeName>, and the Indian tribes, who<lb/>express 1, 2, 3, 4, by
                    ideographic, distinct figures. In the<lb/>ancient Persian Pehlwi a remarkable
                    transition is to be ob-<lb/>served from the inartificial method of expressing
                    numbers by<lb/>the repetition of the figure of the unity, to that of using
                    com-<lb/>pound ideographic hieroglyphics, in numbers greater than the<lb/>unity.
                    There the first nine figures are evidently formed by as<lb/>many notches or
                    teeth as they contain unities; five and nine<lb/>are even merely the numbers 2,
                    3, and 4 twisted together,<lb/>without the repetition of the figure of <hi
                        rendition="#i">one</hi>. In the system of<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Devanagari</hi>, which is truly of Indian origin, in the Per-<lb/>sian and
                    Arabic-European figures, we are only able to discover<lb/>a contraction of 2 and
                    3 units, in the figures of 2 and 3 <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Abel Remusat
                        </persName>Langues Tartares, p. 30.</bibl> On the strange numerical figures<lb/>used in <placeName>Java</placeName>,
                        see <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Crawfurd</persName>, vol. ii., p. 263.</bibl></note>,<lb/>certainly not in the higher
                    figures, which in <placeName>India</placeName> within the<lb/><placeName>Ganges</placeName> are written very differently from
                    one another.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>As I mention here the <hi rendition="#i">Indian</hi> numerical figures, and
                    shall<lb/>be obliged to do it frequently in this essay, I feel myself<lb/>bound
                    to make some observations on this expression. At the<lb/>same time I shall take
                    the opportunity of declaring myself<lb/>against the old prejudices, that in
                    India only one set of nu-<lb/>merical figures are employed in expressing
                    numbers, and never<lb/>alphabetical letters in their place, and that in every
                    district of<lb/>that extensive country, a knowledge of a system, a
                    different<lb/>value to the different position of the figures is met
                    with,<lb/>likewise that there never are peculiar figures used to
                    indicate<lb/>the groups. As, according to what has been repeatedly said<lb/>by
                    my brother William von Humboldt, the Sanscrit is not<lb/><pb n="316"
                        facs="#f0017"/> well distinguished by the name of &#x201C;Indian and
                    ancient-Indian<lb/>language,&#x201D; because in that country many more very
                    ancient lan-<lb/>guages are found which do not derive their origin from the
                    San-<lb/>scrit; so likewise the expression, &#x201C;Indian and
                    ancient-Indian<lb/>figures,&#x201D; is too indefinite, not only as far as it
                    regards the form<lb/>of the figures, but also respecting the spirit of the
                    methods.<lb/>For in India the principal groups of <hi rendition="#i">n,
                        n</hi><hi rendition="#sup">2</hi>, <hi rendition="#i">n</hi><hi
                        rendition="#sup">3</hi>, and their <hi rendition="#i">mul-<lb/>tipla,</hi>
                        2<hi rendition="#i">n,</hi> 3 <hi rendition="#i">n</hi> ..... are sometimes
                    expressed by juxtaposition,<lb/>sometimes by coefficients, and sometimes merely
                    by the place<lb/>of the figures. Even the existence of a distinct figure for
                    the<lb/>cypher, is, in the Indian system, no necessary condition of
                    the<lb/>method of expressing value by position, as it is proved by
                    the<lb/>scholion of the monk <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Neophytus</persName>. In <placeName>India</placeName> within the <placeName>Ganges</placeName><lb/>the most
                    extended languages are the Tamul and the Teloogou.<lb/>The tribes who speak the
                    first use figures different from their<lb/>alphabet, of which only two, the two
                    and the eight, exhibit a<lb/>slight similarity with the Indian (Devanagari)
                    figures of two<lb/>and five <note place="foot" n="*"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Robert Anderson</persName>, Rudiments
                        of Tamul Grammar, 1821, p. 135</bibl>.</note>. Much more different from the Indian
                    figures<lb/>are those of the Cingalese <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">James
                        Chater</persName>, Grammar of the Cingalese Language. Colombo, 1815, p. 135.</bibl></note>. In
                    both the Tamul and the<lb/>Cingalese languages the different value of the
                    figures is not<lb/>indicated by position, they have also no distinct figure for
                    the<lb/>cypher, but distinct hieroglyphics for the groups <hi rendition="#i">n,
                        n</hi><hi rendition="#sup">2</hi>, <hi rendition="#i">n</hi><hi
                        rendition="#sup">3</hi> ....<lb/>The Cingalese make use of juxtaposition,
                    the Tamuls of co-<lb/>efficients. In <placeName>India</placeName> without the <placeName>Ganges</placeName>, in the <placeName>empire of
                    the<lb/>Burmese</placeName>, we find the value expressed by position, and a dis-<lb/>tinct
                    figure for the cypher, but the figures used by them do<lb/>not resemble the
                    Arabic, Persian, and Devanagari Indian<lb/>figures <note place="foot"
                        n="&#x2021;"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Carey</persName>, Grammar of the Burman Language, 1814, p. 196</bibl>. Only the
                        Bur-<lb/>mese figures of 3, 4, and 7, resemble in some manner those of 2, 5,
                        and 7.</note>. The Persian figures, used also by the Arabs, are all<lb/>of
                    them quite different from the Devanagari figures <note place="foot" n="§"
                        >Compare <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">John Shakespear</persName>, Grammar of the Hindustani Language, 1813,<lb/>p.
                            95</bibl>, and <bibl>Pl. I. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">William Jones</persName>, Grammar of the Persian Language, 1809, p.
                                93.</bibl><lb/><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Silvestre de Sacy</persName>, Grammaire Arabe. Pl. VIII.</bibl></note>; 7 is<lb/>like
                    a Roman 5; 8 like a Tuscan 5. Among the figures<lb/>which we call Arabic, only
                    1, 2, 3, resemble the figures of the<lb/>Devanagari of the same value; the 4 of
                    the Devanagari is our<lb/>8; our 9 is the 7 of the Devanagari. Our 7 is the
                    Persian 6.<lb/><pb n="317" facs="#f0018"/> In Bengali the 5 is expressed by the
                    figure of a crescent, and<lb/>2, 5, 6, 8, and 9 are quite different from the
                    Devanagari<lb/>figures <note place="foot" n="*"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Graves Chamney Houghton</persName>, Rud. of
                        Bengali Grammar, 1821, p. 133.</bibl></note>. The numerical figures of Guzerath are
                    only dis-<lb/>torted Indian Devanagari figures <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;"
                        ><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Robert Drummond</persName>, Illustrations of the Grammatical Parts of the
                        Guzerath<lb/>and Mahratt Language, 1818, p. 25</bibl>.</note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>I shall make no observation on the influence of the earliest<lb/>numerical
                    figures on the form of the alphabetical letters, nor<lb/>of the distortion of
                    the letters purposely introduced in order<lb/>to distingush them from the
                    numerical signs, nor even on the<lb/>difference of the place which a figure used
                    in both respects<lb/>occupies sometimes (as in the aboudjet of the Semitic
                    tribes<lb/>in <placeName>Asia</placeName> and <placeName><choice><sic>Arica</sic><corr type="editorial">Africa</corr></choice></placeName>) <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Silvestre de Sacy</persName>,
                        t. i., p. 10.</bibl></note>. Such observations do not belong to the<lb/>subject of
                    this essay, and have been the origin of many<lb/>groundless hypotheses in
                    comparing the alphabetical letters<lb/>with the numerical hieroglyphics. I
                    myself was once of the<lb/>opinion that the Indian figures, notwithstanding the
                    form of<lb/>two and three, were the letters of an obsolete alphabet,
                    of<lb/>which yet some traces are found among the Ph&#x0153;nician,
                    Sama-<lb/>ritan, Palmyrian, and Egyptian characters, (the last on
                    the<lb/>mummies). Even the old Persian monuments of <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Nakshi<lb/>Rustan</hi> seem to exhibit them <note place="foot" n="§"
                            ><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Silvestre de Sacy</persName>, Antiquités de la Perse, Pl. I., n. 1</bibl>. Compare the
                        nume-<lb/>rical inscriptions on <placeName>Mount Sinai</placeName>, in <bibl>Description de
                        l&#x2019;Egypte, vol. v. Pl. LVII.</bibl></note>. How many characters in<lb/>these
                    inscriptions resemble in a striking manner the nume-<lb/>rical figures known
                    under the name of Indian! Many other<lb/>scholars have likewise asserted, that
                    the numerical figures<lb/>called the Indian, are derived from the
                    Ph&#x0153;nician alphabet <note place="foot" n="&#x007C;&#x007C;"><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Guyot de la
                        Marne</persName> in Mem. de Trevoux, 1736, p. 160</bibl>; <bibl>1740. Mars, p. 269.<lb/>John, Bibl.
                            Archeol. b. i., p. 479</bibl>. <bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Büttner</persName>, vergl. Tafeln, 1769, St. i., p.
                                13.</bibl><lb/><bibl><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Eichhorn</persName>, Einleitung in der alte Testam. b. i., p. 197</bibl>. Wahl,
                        Geschichte der Mor-<lb/>genl. Litteratur, p. 601, 630. <bibl>Fundgruben des
                            Orients, b. iii., p. 87</bibl>.</note>,<lb/>and the sagacious <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Eckhel</persName> has already
                    observed that the simi-<lb/>larity between the letters of the Ph&#x0153;nicians
                    and the numerical<lb/>figures was so great, that the word <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Abdera</hi> is expressed by<lb/>19990, and by 15550 <note place="foot"
                        n="&#x00B6;"><bibl>Doctrina Numerorum veterum, 1794, t. iii. p. 396&#x2014;404,
                        421, 494.</bibl></note>. But the origin of the numerical<lb/>figures, as well as
                    that of the alphabetical letters, is enveloped<lb/>in an obscurity, to dissipate
                    which, by a philological investi-<lb/>gation, founded on historical facts, is
                    rendered impossible by<lb/><pb n="318" facs="#f0019"/> the scarcity of the
                    materials, if we do not wish to content our-<lb/>selves with a few negative
                    results.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>We have seen that some nations, in expressing numbers by<lb/>writing, mix
                    together alphabetical letters and ideographic<lb/>figures arbitrarily chosen.
                    Likewise we find, that respecting<lb/>the mode of expressing the <hi
                        rendition="#i">multipla</hi> of the fundamental groups<lb/>the most
                    heterogeneous methods are used. We discover even<lb/>that one system completely
                    developes what, in another, is only<lb/>slightly indicated. The same incongruity
                    obtains in lan-<lb/>guages. In one language, some grammatical forms do
                    appear<lb/>only in a few instances, and are slightly expressed,
                    whilst<lb/>another has developed them with a peculiar predilection, and<lb/>with
                    every effort of mental power. Should I, therefore, ex-<lb/>plain the numerical
                    systems singly, as they are used by dif-<lb/>ferent nations, the similarity of
                    their methods would be ren-<lb/>dered obscure, and we should lose the track on
                    which the<lb/>human mind proceeding, at last arrived to discover the
                    master-<lb/>piece of the Indian arithmetic, in which every figure has
                    a<lb/>double value, an absolute and a relative, of which the last
                    is<lb/>increasing, in a geometrical progression, from the right to the<lb/>left.
                    In my following observations I shall therefore abandon<lb/>the ethnographical
                    order, and only consider the different means<lb/>employed by nations to express
                    in writing the groups of the<lb/>units.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">First method.</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Juxtaposition</hi> is effected by simple addi-<lb/>tion in
                    numerical figures as well as in alphabetical signs. It<lb/>was in use among the
                    ancient Tuscans, the Romans, among the<lb/>Greeks only up to a myriad, among the
                    Semitic tribes, the<lb/>Mexicans, and also in the greatest part of the Pehlwi
                    calculations.<lb/>This method renders the computation extremely difficult,
                    when<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">multipla</hi> of the groups (2<hi rendition="#i"
                        >n,</hi> 3<hi rendition="#i">n,</hi> 2<hi rendition="#i">n</hi><hi
                        rendition="#sup">2</hi> ....) are not expressed<lb/>by distinct signs. The
                    Tuscans and the Romans repeated the<lb/>figure of ten as far as fifty; the
                    Mexicans, whose first figure<lb/>of a group was 20 (a flag), repeated this
                    hieroglyphic up<lb/>to 400. The Greeks, however, have in the rows of the
                    tenths<lb/>and hundreds, which begin with <hi rendition="#i">iota</hi> and <hi
                        rendition="#i">rho</hi>, distinct figures<lb/>for 20, 30, 400 and 600. The
                    three <hi rendition="#i">episemes</hi> (letters of an<lb/>obsolete alphabet),
                        <hi rendition="#i">bau, koppa,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">sanpi</hi>, serve
                    to express 6,<lb/>90, and 900. The two last terminate the rows of the
                        tenths<lb/><pb n="319" facs="#f0020"/> and the hundreds, and in this manner
                    the numerical value of<lb/>the Greek alphabetical figures approaches a little
                    nearer to the<lb/>semitic <hi rendition="#i">aboudjed</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">Hervas, Aritmetica delle Nazioni, p. 78. On the ancient
                        order of the letters<lb/>in the Semitic alphabet see Description de
                        l&#x2019;Egypte moderne, t. ii. P. ii. p. 208.</note>. M. Böckh, in his
                    learned observations on<lb/>the digamma, has shewn that <hi rendition="#i"
                        >bau</hi> is the <hi rendition="#i">wau</hi> of the Semites,<lb/>(the F of
                    the Latins,) <hi rendition="#i">koppa</hi>, the Semitic <hi rendition="#i"
                        >koph</hi> (9), and <hi rendition="#i">sanpi</hi><lb/>the Semitic <hi
                        rendition="#i">shin</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Staatshaushaltung der Athener. B. II. p.
                        385.</note>. The row of the unities beginning with<lb/><hi rendition="#i"
                        >alpha</hi>, and ending with <hi rendition="#i">theta</hi>, forms in the
                    Greek system the<lb/>oeot-numbers
                    (&#x03D6;&#x03C5;&#x03B8;&#x03BC;&#x03AD;&#x03BD;&#x03B5;&#x03C2;), and
                    Apollonius had invented a con-<lb/>trivance <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;"
                        >Delambre, Hist. de l&#x2019;Astronomie Ancienne, t. ii. p. 10.</note>, by
                    the help of which they were reduced, in the last<lb/>results, to the
                    corresponding members of the second and third<lb/>row (the analogues).</p>
                <lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Second Method.</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Multiplication or diminution of the<lb/>value by signs placed
                        over or under the figures.</hi> In the fourth<lb/>row of the Greek
                    notations, the <hi rendition="#i">pythmenes</hi> return by analogy,<lb/>but
                    increased a thousand times by a line placed under the<lb/>figures. In this way
                    the Greeks arrived, in their numerical<lb/>system, at a myriad,&#x2014;they
                    wrote every number up to 9999.<lb/>Had they adopted this notation with a line
                    for all the groups,<lb/>and suppressed all the figures after <hi rendition="#i"
                        >theta</hi> (9), the letter &#x03B2; with<lb/>one, two or three lines would
                    have expressed 20, 200, and 2000,<lb/>and thus the Greek system would have
                    approached, as we shall<lb/>see afterwards, the system of the Arabic <hi
                        rendition="#i">Gobar</hi> figures, which<lb/>is very little known, and at
                    the same time the system expressing<lb/>value by position. But, unhappily, the
                    Greeks did not adopt<lb/>this notation for the tenths and hundreds, applied it
                    only for<lb/>the thousands, and did not try to employ it in higher groups.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>As a line added under the figures increases their value a<lb/>thousand times,
                    thus a vertical line, in the Greek system, added<lb/>over the figure, indicates
                    a fraction, whose numerator is the<lb/>unit, and whose denominator is expressed
                    by the figure itself.<lb/>Thus in Diophantus, &#x03B3;&#x1FFD; = <formula notation="TeX">frac{1}{3}</formula>,
                    &#x03B4; = &#x03BC;; but if the numerator is<lb/>greater than the unity, it is
                    expressed by the principal figure,<lb/>and the denominator is written like an
                    exponent &#x03B3;<hi rendition="#sup">&#x1D5F;</hi> = &#xBE; <note
                            place="foot" n="§" xml:id="fn2-1" next="#fn2-2">Delambre, t. ii. p. 11. The line added over the
                            alphabetical letters to indicate<lb/>that they are used as numerical
                            figures, ought not to be confounded with the sign<lb/>of fractions. The
                            first is also never vertical in the oldest manuscripts of
                        mathe-</note>. In<lb/><pb n="320" facs="#f0021"/> the Roman
                    inscriptions, a horizontal line added over them,<lb/>increases their value a
                    thousand times, and here it may be con-<lb/>sidered only as a means of
                    abbreviating and of saving space.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The method of <hi rendition="#i">Eutocius</hi> for expressing myriads is more
                    im-<lb/>portant. In it we find among the Greeks the first trace of
                    the<lb/>system of exponents, or rather indicators, which rose to such<lb/>a
                    degree of importance in the East. M<hi rendition="#sup">&#x03B1;</hi>, M<hi
                        rendition="#sup">&#x03B2;</hi>, M<hi rendition="#sup">&#x03B3;</hi>,
                    indicate<lb/>10,000, 20,000, 30,000. Here we find these indicators used<lb/>only
                    with the myriads. But the Chinese and the Japonese,<lb/>which last received
                    their civilization from the first about 200<lb/>years before our &#x00E6;ra,
                    both use them for the <hi rendition="#i">multipla</hi> of all<lb/>groups. Three
                    horizontal lines under the figure of ten, signify<lb/>thirteen, but if they are
                    placed over it they express thirty.<lb/>According to this method, 3456 is
                    written, (I use the Roman<lb/>figures as signs of groups, and the Indian as
                    exponents)</p>
                <lb/>
                <list>
                    <item>M<hi rendition="#sup">3</hi></item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>C<hi rendition="#sup">4</hi></item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>X<hi rendition="#sup">5</hi></item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>I<hi rendition="#sup">6</hi></item>
                </list>
                <lb/>
                <p>Among the Egyptians the same kind of indicators are found.<lb/>Two or four
                    unities placed over a curved line, which denotes<lb/>a thousand, are used to
                    express 2000 or 4000 <note place="foot" n="*">Kosegarten, de hierogl. Aegypt. p.
                        54. The assertion of Gatterer adopted<lb/>by him from Bianchini (Dec. 1,
                        cap. iii., p. 3), from Goquet (vol. i. p. 226), and<lb/>from Debrosses (vol.
                        i. p. 432), that among the Egyptians the figures received<lb/>value by their
                        position in a perpendicular row, has not been confirmed by
                        modern<lb/>researches. Gatterer, Weltgeschichte bis Cyrus, p. 555,
                        586.</note>. Among the<lb/>Aztekes, or Mexicans, I found for 312 years the
                    sign of the<lb/><hi rendition="#i">vinculum,</hi> with six unities as exponent
                    (6&#x00D7;52=312), and I<lb/>have published it in my work of the American
                    Monuments.<lb/>Among the Chinese, Aztekes, and Egyptians, the signs
                    of<lb/>groups are always under the exponent, as if <formula notation="TeX"
                        >\overset{@}{\text{X}}</formula> were written<lb/>instead of 50; but in the
                    Arabic <hi rendition="#i">Gobar</hi> figures the signs of the<lb/>groups are
                    placed over the indicators. For in the Gobar sys-<lb/>tem the signs of the
                    groups are points, consequently cyphers;<lb/>for in India, in Thibet, and in
                    Persia, cyphers and points are<lb/>identical. These Gobar signs, which, since
                    1818, have attracted<lb/><note place="foot" n="§" xml:id="fn2-2" prev="#fn2-1">matical works,
                            but horizontal, and thus the mistaking of it for the sign of
                            fraction<lb/>is obviated. Bast. de Usu Litterarum ad Numeros indicandos,
                            in Gregorii<lb/>Corinthii Liber de Dialectis Lingu&#x00E6;
                            Gr&#x00E6;c&#x00E6;. 1811. p. 850.</note><lb/><pb n="321"
                        facs="#f0022"/> my peculiar attention, were discovered in a manuscript in
                    the<lb/>library of the old Abbey of St. Germain du Près, by my friend<lb/>and
                    instructor, M. Silvestre de Sacy. This great orientalist<lb/>says, &#x201C;Le
                        <hi rendition="#i">Gobar</hi> a un rapport avec le chiffre indien, mais il
                    n&#x2019;a<lb/>pas de zero <note place="foot" n="*">See Gramm. Arabe, p. 76, and
                        the observations added to pl. viii.</note>.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>To me, however, it seems, that the figure of the cypher there<lb/>is found; it
                    is, however, not placed aside the figures, but over<lb/>them, as in the scholion
                    of Neophytus. It is, indeed, the signs<lb/>of the cypher or the points, which
                    have caused to be given to<lb/>these characters, the strange name of <hi
                        rendition="#i">gobar</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">dust</hi> characters.<lb/>He
                    who sees them for the first time is doubtful whether they<lb/>represent a
                    transition from figures to letters, or not. It is only<lb/>with pain, that the
                    Indian 3, 4, 5 and 9 can be distinguished.<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Dal</hi> and
                        <hi rendition="#i">ha</hi> are, perhaps, the Indian figures of 6 and 2
                    distorted.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The indication by means of points is thus effected:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb/>
                <list>
                    <item>3 instead of 30,</item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>4&#x2025; instead of 400,</item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>6&#x2234; instead of 6000.</item>
                </list>
                <lb/>
                <p>These points recall to our memory a mode of notation used<lb/>by the Greeks <note
                        place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Ducange, Paleogra, p. xii.</note>, but not
                    frequently met with, and be-<lb/>ginning only with the myriad. Here, &#x03B1;
                        <hi rendition="#sup">&#x2025;</hi> is used for 10,000,<lb/>and &#x03B2; ::
                    for 200 millions. One point, which, however, is never<lb/>employed, serves to
                    express 100 in this system of geometrical<lb/>progressions. In Diophantus and
                    Pappus, a point is found be-<lb/>tween the alphabetical figures, instead of the
                    initial &#x39C;&#x03C5; (My-<lb/>riad). In this method, therefore, a point multiplies
                    to figures<lb/>to the left 10,000 times. It would seem that some
                    obscure<lb/>ideas of notation, by points and cypher, had been brought
                    from<lb/>the East into Europe by the Alexandrines. The figure of the<lb/>cypher
                    is, indeed, used by Ptolom&#x00E6;us, and even as an indi-<lb/>cation of
                    something that is wanting. He employs it in the<lb/>descending sexagesimal scale
                    to indicate the wanting degrees,<lb/>minutes, and seconds. Delambre even
                    pretends to have found<lb/>the figure of the cypher in the manuscripts of <hi
                        rendition="#i">Theon</hi>, in his<lb/>commentary on the Syntaxis of
                        Ptolom&#x00E6;us<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;" xml:id="fn3-1" next="#fn3-2">Histoire de
                            l&#x2019;Astronomie Ancienne, t. i., p. 547; t. ii., p. 10. The passage
                            of<lb/>Theon is not to be found in his printed works. Delambre is
                            inclined to attribute<lb/>the origin of the Greek figure of the cypher
                            sometimes to an abbreviation of
                            &#x03BF;&#x03CD;&#x03B4;&#x03AD;&#x03BD;</note>. The
                        cypher,<lb/><pb n="322" facs="#f0023"/> consequently, was known in the west
                    long before the invasion<lb/>of the Arabs <note place="foot" n="*">Planudes,
                        Treatise on the <hi rendition="#i">Arithmoi Indikoi, third method,
                            Multiplication of the<lb/>Value by Coefficients.</hi></note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>We have seen, that the Chinese, by placing indicators per-<lb/>pendicularly over
                    or under the groups, indicate the difference<lb/>between <formula notation="TeX"
                        >\underset{2}{\text{X}} = 12</formula>, and <formula notation="TeX"
                        >\overset{2}{\text{X}} = 20</formula>. The same effect is produced<lb/>among
                    the Greeks, Armenians, and those tribes of the Hin-<lb/>doos, who speak the
                    Tamul language, by adding figures in<lb/>horizontal direction. Diophantus and
                    Pappus wrote &#x03B2; &#x39C; &#x03C5;<lb/>for twice ten thousands, whilst &#x03B1; &#x39C;
                    &#x03C5;&#x03B2; (where &#x03B2; is placed to the<lb/>right of the initials of
                    the myriad) signifies ten thousands, plus<lb/>two or 10,002. In the same manner,
                    the Tamul figures are<lb/>used, as, for instance: 4X = 40, and X4 = 14. In the
                    ancient<lb/>Persian Pehlwi, according to Anquetil, and among the
                    Arme-<lb/>nians, according to Cerbied <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Grammaire
                        Arménienne, 1825, p. 25.</note>, multiplicators employed to ex-<lb/>press
                    the <hi rendition="#i">multipla</hi> of the hundred, are found placed to
                    the<lb/>left. To these examples may yet be added, the above-men-<lb/>tioned
                    point of Diophantus, which is used instead of &#x39C;&#x03C5;, and<lb/>multiplies the
                    figures to the left a thousand times. For, as far<lb/>as regards the method, it
                    belongs to this class <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">This mode of separating
                        numbers by points, though it is otherwise used in a<lb/>very inconsistent
                        manner, expresses properly the value by position. It is also<lb/>used in
                        three passages of the elder Pliny (vi., 24, 33; xxx., 3), which have
                        given<lb/>rise to many controversies.</note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Fourth Method.</hi> &#x2014; <hi rendition="#i">Multiplication
                        and diminution, in<lb/>ascending and descending direction, brought about by
                        dividing<lb/>the figures in layers, of which the value decreases in
                        geome-<lb/>trical proportion.</hi></p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Both Archimedes in the Octades, and Apollonius in the<lb/>Tetrades, make use of
                    this notation, but only in numbers above<lb/>(10,000)<hi rendition="#sup"
                    >2</hi>, and in a hundred of millions, or a myriad of my-<lb/>riads @<note
                        place="foot" n="§">Delambre, Hist. de l&#x2019;Astron. Ancienne, t. i., p
                        105; t. ii., p. 9.</note>. Here, as well as in the descending sexagesimal
                        seale<lb/><note place="foot" n="&#x2021;" xml:id="fn3-2" prev="#fn3-1">sometimes to a
                            peculiar relation in which the letter <hi rendition="#i">omicron</hi>
                            stands to the sexage-<lb/>simal system, l. c., t. ii., p. 14, and
                            Journal des Savans, 1817, p. 539. It is strange,<lb/>that in the old
                            Indian arithmetic of the Lilawati, the figure of the cypher,
                            placed<lb/>aside a number, indicates, that such a number is to be
                            subtracted. Delambre, vol. i.,<lb/>p. 540. What does the Ling (the true
                            cypher) signify, which in Chinese figures is<lb/>written under 12, 13,
                            22, 132? In Greek inscriptions the signs of cyphers indi-<lb/>cate
                            oboles. (Bockh, Staatshaushaltung der Athener, b. ii., p.
                        379.)</note><lb/><pb n="323" facs="#f0024"/> of the astronomer of
                    Alexandria, where degrees, minutes, and<lb/>seconds are indicated, the value is
                    evidently expressed by the<lb/>position of the figures. They follow one another
                    in different<lb/>layers, and thus, they express an absolute and a relative
                    value.<lb/>But, as in the last mentioned scale, every layer is composed
                    of<lb/>two figures (for want of <hi rendition="#i">n</hi> &#x2014; 1 or 59
                    figures); the value expressed<lb/>by position does here not procure the
                    advantages accruing from<lb/>the Indian figures. When the three hundred and
                    sixty parts<lb/>of a circle are considered as so many entires, the minutes
                    are<lb/>sixtieths of them, the seconds are sixtieths of the minutes,
                    &amp;c.<lb/>Considering them as fractions, Ptolom&#x00E6;us distinguished
                    them<lb/>by the sign of fraction, a line placed above, and, in order to
                    ex-<lb/>press their descending progression, by which every layer of
                    two<lb/>figures has sixty times less value than the preceding, the
                    frac-<lb/>tion-signs were increased in number from layer to layer.<lb/>According
                    to these principles, the minutes are indicated by one<lb/>line, the common
                    designation of fractions (the numerator of<lb/>which is the unit), the seconds
                    by two such lines, the terces by<lb/>three; but, the degrees themselves, as
                    being entires, were not<lb/>distinguished by a line, but, perhaps, by nought
                    (&#x03BF;&#x1F50;&#x03B4;&#x03AD;&#x03BD;), or a<lb/>cypher <note place="foot"
                        n="*">On the use of the cypher, <hi rendition="#i">see</hi> Leslie, p. 12,
                        135; Germanen und Griechen<lb/>Hist., v. ii., p. 2&#x2014;33; Ducange,
                        Glossar. Medi&#x00E6; Gr&#x00E6;citatis, t. ii., p. 572. Mannert<lb/>de
                        Nummorum quos Arabicos vocant Origine Pythagor. p 17. In the
                        Greek<lb/>arithmetic M<hi rendition="#sub">&#x03BF;</hi> signifies the
                        unity; &#x03BC;&#x03CC;&#x03BD;&#x03B1;&#x03C2;, as a delta (&#x0394;), when
                        a cypher (properly<lb/>omicron) is placed over it, signifies <hi
                            rendition="#i">tetartos</hi>. Bast, Gregor., Corinth. p. 851.
                        Thus,<lb/>we find in Diophantus, M<hi rendition="#sup"
                        >&#x03BF;</hi>&#x03BA;&#x03B1; = 21. The Indian grammatical sign, <hi
                            rendition="#i">anuswara,</hi> has<lb/>indeed the figure of the Indian
                        cypher. It indicates, however, nothing but a modi-<lb/>fication in the
                        accentuation of the vowel placed nearest to it, and is in no
                        way<lb/>connected with the <hi rendition="#i">sunya.</hi></note> &#x2014; I
                    say, perhaps, for in the writings of Ptolom&#x00E6;us<lb/>and Theon, the figure
                    of the cypher is not yet used to indicate<lb/>degrees.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The simple enumeration of the methods used by those<lb/>nations who did not know
                    the Indian system of position, in ex-<lb/>pressing the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >multipla</hi> of the fundamental groups, shews, in my<lb/>opinion at least,
                    the way in which the Indian system probably<lb/>has been invented by degrees.
                    When the number 3568 is<lb/>written either in a perpendicular or in a horizontal
                    direction, by<lb/>means of indicators: <formula notation="TeX"
                        >\overset{3}{\text{M}}\overset{5}{\text{C}}\overset{6}{\text{X}}\overset{8}{\text{I}}</formula>, it is
                    evident that the figures of<lb/>the groups M C, &amp;c., may be omitted. For our
                    Indian figures<lb/>are only the multiplicators of the different groups. This
                        mode<lb/><pb n="324" facs="#f0025"/> of expressing every number only by
                    unities (multiplicators) is<lb/>moreover suggested by the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >suanpan</hi>, of which the strings indi-<lb/>cated the thousands, hundreds,
                    tenths and unities in fixed<lb/>order. To express the above-mentioned number the
                    strings<lb/>contained 3, 5, 6 and 8 balls. No sign of groups is here to
                    be<lb/>observed. The places themselves supply the signs of groups,<lb/>and these
                    places (the strings) are filled up with the unities<lb/>(multiplicators). Thus
                    the Indian system may have been in-<lb/>vented in either way, by the <hi
                        rendition="#i">figurative</hi> as well as by the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >pal-<lb/>pable</hi> arithmetic. If a string was empty, or in writing a
                    layer<lb/>was not occupied by a figure, if consequently a group (a mem-<lb/>ber
                    of the progression) was wanting, the empty place in writing<lb/>was filled up by
                    the hieroglyphic of emptiness, a circle open in<lb/>the middle, sunya, sifron,
                    cyphra <note place="foot" n="*">In English, the expression cypher for nullity
                        has been preserved; whilst, in<lb/>the other languages of the west, this
                        word is used to indicate the numerical figures<lb/>in general; in them the
                        cypher is called zéro (sifron, siron). According to Wilson<lb/>any numerical
                        quantity is called in Sanscrit <hi rendition="#i">sambhara</hi>.</note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>That the notation of numerical quantities has been improved<lb/>and brought to
                    perfection in India only by degrees, is proved<lb/>by the numerical figures of
                    the Tamul language, in which<lb/>every numerical quantity is expressed by the
                    nine figures of<lb/>the unities, by distinct figures for the groups of 10, 100,
                    and<lb/>1000, and by multiplicators added to the left hand. The same<lb/>is also
                    proved by the remarkable <hi rendition="#i">arithmoi indikoi</hi>, in
                    the<lb/>scholion of the monk, Neophytus, which is preserved in the<lb/>library
                    of Paris (Cod. Reg. fol. 15), and was communicated<lb/>to me by the kindness of
                    Professor Brandes. The nine figures<lb/>of Neophytus are, the four excepted, all
                    of them like those of<lb/>the Persians. The figures of 1, 2, 3, and 9 are even
                    found in<lb/>some Egyptian inscriptions containing numbers <note place="foot"
                        n="&#x2020;">Kosegarten, p. 54.</note>. The unities<lb/>are multiplicated, a
                    ten, a hundred, and a thousand times,<lb/>by writing over them one, two, or
                    three cyphers, as <formula notation="TeX"
                        >\overset{\circ}{2}=20</formula>,<lb/><formula notation="TeX"
                        >\overset{\circ}{24}=240</formula>, <formula notation="TeX"
                        >\overset{\circ\circ}{5}=500</formula>, <formula notation="TeX"
                        >\overset{\overset{\circ}{\circ\circ}}{6}=6000</formula>. If, instead of
                    cyphers, <hi rendition="#i">points</hi> are<lb/>used, the Arabic <hi
                        rendition="#i">Gobar</hi> figures are obtained. I shall give<lb/>here a
                    literal translation in Latin of the scholion itself, and<lb/>observe only, that
                    the monk erroneously calls the expression<lb/>tzüphron an Indian word.</p>
                <lb/>
                <pb n="325" facs="#f0026"/>
                <p>Tzyphra est et vocatur id, quod cuivis litter&#x00E6; inde a decade<lb/>et
                    insequentibus numeris quasi
                    &#x03BF;&#x0304;&#x03BC;&#x03B9;&#x03BA;&#x03C1;&#x1F78;&#x03BD; inscribitur.
                    Significat<lb/>autem hac Indica voce tale analogiam numerorum. Ubi
                    igitur<lb/>scriptum est simile prim&#x00E6; litter&#x00E6;
                    &#x1F04;&#x03BB;&#x03C6;&#x03B1;, pro unitate script&#x00E6;,<lb/>atque
                    superimpositum habet vel punctum, vel quasi
                    &#x03BF;&#x0304;&#x03BC;&#x03B9;&#x03BA;&#x03C1;&#x1F78;&#x03BD;,<lb/>addita
                    altera figura litter&#x00E6; Indic&#x00E6;, differentiam et
                    augmentum<lb/>numerorum declarat. E. g. pro primo Gr&#x00E6;co numero, &#x1FB1;
                    scripto,<lb/>apud Indos | sive linea recta perpendicularis, quando non<lb/>habet
                    superimpositum punctum vel
                    &#x03BF;&#x0304;&#x03BC;&#x03B9;&#x03BA;&#x03C1;&#x1F78;&#x03BD;, ipsum hoc
                    denotat<lb/>unitatem, ubi vero superimpositum sit punctum atque
                    altera<lb/>littera adscripta sit, figura quidem similis priori, significat
                    XI,<lb/>propter additamentum similis litter&#x00E6; atque
                    superimpositum<lb/>unum punctum. Similiter etiam in reliquis litteris,
                    quemad-<lb/>modum adspectus docet. Si vero plura habet puncta,
                    plura<lb/>denotat. Quod intelligas, lector, et supputes unumquidque.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In this system we do not find that value is expressed by position<lb/>any more
                    than in the system of the <hi rendition="#i">Gobar</hi> figures. The
                    number<lb/>3006 was written <formula notation="TeX"
                        >\overset{\overset{\circ}{\circ\circ}}{36}</formula>. But in using it, it
                    must soon have been<lb/>observed, that the same figures often expressed
                    different value,<lb/>and that (when all the groups were filled up) in <formula
                        notation="TeX">\overset{\overset{\circ}{\circ\circ}}{3}</formula>
                    <formula notation="TeX">\overset{\circ\circ}{4}</formula>
                    <formula notation="TeX">\overset{\circ}{6}</formula> 7, the<lb/>points or
                    cyphers, by decreasing regularly in number, became<lb/>superfluous. The cyphers,
                    as it were, served only to facilitate<lb/>the pronouncing of the number. If we
                    now suppose that the<lb/>custom of writing the cyphers <hi rendition="#i"
                        >aside</hi> the figures instead of<lb/>placing them <hi rendition="#i"
                        >above</hi>, became prevalent, the Indian notation as<lb/>used at present,
                    was introduced for the unmixed groups, as<lb/><formula notation="TeX"
                        >\overset{\overset{\circ}{\circ\circ}}{3}=3000</formula>. If further, to
                        <formula notation="TeX"
                        >\overset{\overset{\circ}{\circ\circ}}{3}=3000</formula> were to be added
                        <formula notation="TeX">\overset{\circ}{4}=40</formula>, that<lb/>place of
                    the cypher was filled up which was assigned to 40 by<lb/>the exponent indicating
                    the group. Thus 3040 was obtained,<lb/>and two of the three cyphers, which were
                    required to express<lb/>the thousands, and which had previously been placed on
                        <hi rendition="#i">one</hi><lb/>line with the unities, remained there to
                    indicate the empty<lb/>places. According to the scholion of Neophytus,
                    therefore,<lb/>the figures of the cypher are (like the points over the <hi
                        rendition="#i">Gobar</hi><lb/>figures) indicators for the notation of the
                    ascending groups.<lb/>From the observations made on this system it is easy to
                        per-<lb/><pb n="326" facs="#f0027"/> ceive, how the cyphers have been placed
                    in the row of the<lb/>figures, and have preserved that place, when the value
                    by<lb/>position was adopted.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In reviewing once more the different methods used by the<lb/>different nations of
                    both continents in computing numbers,<lb/>which till now have been in part so
                    little known, we find,<lb/><hi rendition="#i">firstly</hi>, in some only a small
                    number of figures indicating<lb/>groups, and those almost only for <hi
                        rendition="#i">n</hi><hi rendition="#sup">2</hi>, <hi rendition="#i"
                        >n</hi><hi rendition="#sup">3</hi>, <hi rendition="#i">n</hi><hi
                        rendition="#sup">4</hi> .... not for 2<hi rendition="#i">n,</hi><lb/>3<hi
                        rendition="#i">n,</hi> and 2<hi rendition="#i">n</hi><hi rendition="#sup"
                        >2</hi>, 2<hi rendition="#i">n</hi><hi rendition="#sup">3</hi> .... as among
                    the Romans and ancient Tus-<lb/>cans <note place="foot" n="*">For
                        brevity&#x2019;s sake I here take no notice of the figures of the groups of
                            the<lb/><hi rendition="#i">quinary</hi> system (V, L, D...) which form
                        intermediate sections.</note>, X, C, M, and, therefore all the intermediate
                    groups,<lb/>for instance, 2<hi rendition="#i">n</hi> or 2<hi rendition="#i"
                        >n</hi><hi rendition="#sup">2</hi>, are to be expressed by
                    juxtaposition,<lb/>as in XX or CCCC; we find further, in others, a
                    great<lb/>number of figures of groups, not only to express <hi rendition="#i">n,
                        n</hi><hi rendition="#sup">2</hi>, (<hi rendition="#i">iota</hi><lb/>and <hi
                        rendition="#i">rho</hi> among the Greek alphabetic figures) but also to
                    ex-<lb/>press 3<hi rendition="#i">n</hi> or 4<hi rendition="#i">n</hi><hi
                        rendition="#sup">2</hi> (in &#x03BB; and &#x03C5;), by whose application a
                    great<lb/>heterogeneity of the elements is produced in expressing 2+2<hi
                        rendition="#i">n</hi><lb/>+ 2<hi rendition="#i">n</hi><hi rendition="#sup"
                        >2</hi> (for instance, &#x03C3;&#x03BA;&#x03B2; for 222); we find lastly,
                    that the<lb/>multipla of the fundamental groups and their powers (2<hi
                        rendition="#i">n,</hi><lb/>3<hi rendition="#i">n,</hi> 4<hi rendition="#i"
                        >n</hi><hi rendition="#sup">2</hi>, 5<hi rendition="#i">n</hi><hi
                        rendition="#sup">2</hi>,) are, by others, expressed either by the
                    addition<lb/>of indicators over or under the figures of the groups (by
                    the<lb/>Chinese <formula notation="TeX">\overset{2}{\text{X}}</formula>,
                        <formula notation="TeX">\overset{3}{\text{X}}</formula>, <formula
                        notation="TeX">\overset{4}{\text{C}}</formula>, <formula notation="TeX"
                        >\overset{5}{\text{O}}</formula>, by the Hindoos speaking the
                    Tamul<lb/>language 2X, 3X, 4C, 5C,) or by placing over the figures of<lb/>the
                    first nine unities a progressive number of points, that<lb/>is &#x03B1;&#x0307;
                    = 10, &#x03B2;&#x0307; = 20, &#x03B1;&#x0308; = 100, &#x03B1;@ = 1000, &#x03B4;@
                    = 40,000, as in the <hi rendition="#i">Gobar-</hi><lb/>figures, in the scholion
                    of Neophytus, and in the descending<lb/>sexagesimal scale of the astronomers of
                    Alexandria, for<lb/><formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{60}</formula>,
                    <formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{60^2}</formula>, <formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{60^@}</formula>, in 1°
                    37&#x2032; 37&#x2033; 37&#x2034; .... We have seen in what<lb/>manner the
                    indicators (multiplicators) used by the nations of<lb/>Eastern Asia, and by the
                    inhabitants of the southern districts<lb/>of India within the Ganges, or, where
                    originally figures of<lb/>groups did not exist, in what manner the placing of
                    points<lb/>over the <hi rendition="#i">pythmenes</hi> in the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Gobar-</hi>system and in the scholion<lb/>of Neophytus; and lastly, in what
                    manner even the strings of<lb/>the suanpan, in which different value is
                    expressed by the<lb/><pb n="327" facs="#f0028"/> relative position of the
                    strings, could lead men to invent that<lb/>system, in which value is expressed
                    by position.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Whether the simple Indian system, expressing value by<lb/>position, was brought
                    into the west by the learned astronomer,<lb/>Rihan Muhammed eben Ahmet Albiruni
                        <note place="foot" n="*">According to an observation of the orientalist
                        Sedillot, not less acquainted<lb/>with the Greek, than with the Arabian
                        astronomy.</note>, who remained a<lb/>long time in India, or by Moorish
                    custom-house officers in<lb/>the ports of North Africa, and their intercourse
                    with the<lb/>Italian merchants, I do not presume to decide. Further,<lb/>though
                    mental culture was doubtless very early disseminated<lb/>in India, it remains
                    doubtful whether the numerical system<lb/>expressing value by position, which
                    has so powerfully affected<lb/>the progress of the mathematical sciences, had
                    already been<lb/>invented and adopted by that nation, when the
                    Macedonian<lb/>conqueror invaded their country. In how different a
                    con-<lb/>dition, in how much more perfect a state would the mathe-<lb/>matical
                    sciences have been transmitted to the learned epoch<lb/>of the Hashimides by
                    Archimedes, Apollonius of Perga and<lb/>Diophantus, if the western countries of
                    the old continent had<lb/>received the Indian numerical system twelve or
                    thirteen cen-<lb/>turies sooner, at the time of Alexander&#x2019;s expedition.
                    But<lb/>that part of upper India, which was then overrun by the<lb/>Greeks, the
                    Penjab, as far as Palibothra, was, according to the<lb/>learned researches of M.
                    Lassen, inhabited by nations very<lb/>little advanced in civilization. Those who
                    lived farther to<lb/>the east, called them even barbarians. Seleucus Nicator
                    was<lb/>the first who passed the river Sarasvatis, and by doing so,<lb/>the
                    limits that separated the civilized and uncivilized tribes;<lb/>and then he
                    advanced towards the Ganges <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Lassen, Comment.
                        Geog. de Pentap., p. 58.</note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The old Indian numerical figures of the Tamul language,<lb/>which express the
                    quantities 2<hi rendition="#i">n,</hi> 3<hi rendition="#i">n</hi><hi
                        rendition="#sup">2</hi> .... by the addition of<lb/>multiplicators, and
                    consequently besides the figures for the first<lb/>nine unities, have distinct
                    ones for <hi rendition="#i">n, n</hi><hi rendition="#sup">2</hi>, <hi
                        rendition="#i">n</hi><hi rendition="#sup">3</hi>, .... prove
                    evidently<lb/>that, in India, besides that system which exclusively has
                    ob-<lb/>tained the name of Indian (or Arabic) figures, and in which<lb/>value is
                    expressed by position, there yet, at the same time,<lb/><pb n="328"
                        facs="#f0029"/> existed others, which did not express value by the same
                    method.<lb/>Now it may be the case, that Alexander and his successors
                    in<lb/>Bactria, in their temporary incursions, did not have intercourse<lb/>with
                    any tribes, among whom the knowledge of the system ex-<lb/>pressing value by
                    position had then become prevalent.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>I could wish that the traces of what is still to be discovered<lb/>(and that is
                    yet very much), might soon be pursued with in-<lb/>creasing zeal, by
                    philologists, who have opportunity of examin-<lb/>ing either Greek, Persian, or
                    Arabian manuscripts <note place="foot" n="*">Among the Arabian manuscripts,
                        those especially are to be recommended to<lb/>peculiar attention, which
                        treat of custom-house or financial affairs, or of arithmetic<lb/>in general;
                        as, for instance, Abu Jose Alchindus <hi rendition="#i">de Arithmetica
                            Indica;</hi> Abdel-<lb/>hamid Ben Vasee Abulphadl <hi rendition="#i">de
                            Numerorum Proprietatibus;</hi> Amad Ben Omar<lb/>Alkarabisi <hi
                            rendition="#i">Liber de Indica Numerondi Ratione;</hi> the Indian
                        Algebra by Katka;<lb/>Mohammed Ben Lara <hi rendition="#i">de Numerorum
                            Disciplina</hi> (Casari Biblioth. Arabico-His-<lb/>pana, t. i. p. 353,
                        405, 410, 426, 433.)</note>. The<lb/>manner in which old manuscripts of the
                    Sanscrit literature<lb/>are paged, can sometimes bring us to important
                    observa-<lb/>tions and discoveries. To give an instance, hardly any<lb/>person
                    would have expected to find in India, besides the<lb/>decimal system with
                    position, a sedecimal system without<lb/>position. It seems, however, that some
                    Indian tribes had<lb/>adopted in their calculations groups of sixteen, as the
                    natives<lb/>of America, and the Gauls and Biscayans, those of twenty.<lb/>For
                    such a remarkable numeration has been discovered, more<lb/>than ten years ago,
                    by M. Bopp, in a manuscript of the old<lb/>Indian poem, Mahabharata (Cod. Reg.,
                    Paris, p. 178). He<lb/>had the kindness to communicate it to me for publication,
                    when<lb/>I laid before the <hi rendition="#i">Académie des Inscriptions et
                        Belles Lettres</hi><lb/>my first essay on the numerical signs of the
                    different nations.<lb/>The first sixty-five pages are paged with Indian
                    alphabetic let-<lb/>ters, but only the consonants of the Sanscrit alphabet are
                        used<lb/>(<hi rendition="#i">k</hi> for 1, <hi rendition="#i">kh</hi> for 2
                    ....). This refutes the opinion till now ge-<lb/>nerally prevailing, that the
                    Hindoos always used ideographic<lb/>figures to express numbers, and never
                    alphabetical letters, as<lb/>the Semitic tribes and the Greeks <note
                        place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Si l&#x2019;arithmétique de position n&#x2019;est
                        pas originaire de l&#x2019;Inde, elle doit au moins y<lb/>avoir existé de
                        temps immémorial; car on ne trouve chez les Indiens aucune
                        trace<lb/>d&#x2019;une notation alphabétique telle que la notation des
                        Hebreux, des Grecs et des<lb/>Arabes.&#x2014;(Delambre, Histoire de
                        l&#x2019;Astronomie Ancienne, t. i., p. 543.)</note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>On the sixtieth page begins the extraordinary sedecimal<lb/><pb n="329"
                        facs="#f0030"/> notation. Of the <hi rendition="#i">pythmenes</hi>, fifteen
                    in number, hardly two<lb/>figures are found among those we know. (The aspirated
                        <hi rendition="#i">t</hi><lb/>of the Sanscrit alphabetical letters is used
                    for 3 and <hi rendition="#i">d</hi> for<lb/>12.) They are likewise quite
                    different from the Indian (Ara-<lb/>bic) figures. It deserves to be noticed,
                    that the figure of 1,<lb/>with a cypher added to it, signifies four, as that
                    figure doubled<lb/>(two vertical lines), with a cypher added to them,
                    signifies<lb/>eight. They form, as it were, resting-places,
                    intermediate<lb/>landings, of the sedecimal system for <formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{4}</formula> and <formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{2}</formula><hi rendition="#sup">n</hi>.
                    But, <formula notation="TeX">\frac{3}{4}</formula> of <hi rendition="#i">n</hi><lb/>(12), is not indicated by a
                    cypher, but by a peculiar hieroglyph,<lb/>similar to the Arabic four. To express
                    the principal funda-<lb/>mental group itself (16), and the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >multipla</hi> of it (2 <hi rendition="#i">n,</hi> 3 <hi rendition="#i"
                        >n</hi> ....),<lb/>the known Bengali figures are used; so that the Bengali
                    1, pre-<lb/>ceded by a curved line, signifies 16; the Bengali 2 is used
                    for<lb/>32; the 3 for 48. The multipla of <hi rendition="#i">n</hi> are
                    consequently indicated<lb/>only as groups of first, second, third, .... order.
                    The numbers<lb/>2 <hi rendition="#i">n</hi> + 4, or 3 <hi rendition="#i">n</hi>
                    + 6, (that is 36 and 54 in the sedecimal sys-<lb/>tem,) are expressed by the
                    Bengali figure of 2, and the added<lb/>Mahabharatan figure of 4, or by the
                    Bengali figure of 3, and<lb/>the added Mahabharatan figure of 6 <note
                        place="foot" n="*">I use here the expression Mahabharatan figure only for
                        the purpose of indi-<lb/>cating, with a proper word, the numerical system
                        discovered in the manuscript of<lb/>that poem.</note>.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>It is, indeed, a very regular, but at the same time a very in-<lb/>convenient and
                    complicated mode of counting, the origin of<lb/>which is the more difficult to
                    guess, as it presupposes the<lb/>knowledge of the Bengali figures.</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>

    </text>
</TEI>
