<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validit채tspr체fung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="418" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Humboldt&#x2019;s Account of the Gold and Platina District<lb/>of <placeName>Russia</placeName>.</hi></head><lb/><p>The following account is part of a letter from M. Humboldt to M.<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Arago</persName>:&#x2014;&#x2018;We spent a month in visiting the gold mines of <placeName>Borisovsk</placeName>,<lb/>the malachite mines of <placeName>Goumeselevski</placeName> and of <placeName>Tagilsk</placeName>, and the wash-<lb/>ings of gold and platinum. We were astonished at the <hi rendition="#i">pepitas</hi><lb/>(waterworn masses) of gold, from 2 to 3lbs., and even from 18 to<lb/>20lbs., found a few inches below the turf, where they had lain un-<lb/>known for ages. The position and probable origin of these alluvia,<lb/>mixed generally with fragments of greenstone, chlorite slate, and<lb/>serpentine, was one of the principal objects of this journey. The<lb/>gold annually procured from the washings amounts to 6000 kil.<lb/>The discoveries beyond 59째 and 60째 latitude become very important.<lb/>We possess the teeth of fossil elephants enveloped in these alluvia<lb/>of auriferous sand. Their formation, consequent on local irruptions<lb/>and on levellings, is, perhaps, even posterior to the destruction of the<lb/>large animals. The amber and the lignites, which we discovered on<lb/>the eastern side of the Ural, are decidedly more ancient. With the<lb/>auriferous sand are found grains of cinnabar, native copper, ceyla-<lb/>nites, garnets, little white zircons as brilliant as diamonds, anatase,<lb/>alvite, &amp;c. It is very remarkable, that in the middle and northern<lb/>parts of the <placeName>Ural</placeName>, the platinum is found in abundance only on the<lb/><placeName>western European side</placeName>. The rich gold-washings of the Demidov<lb/>family, at <placeName>Nijne&#x00EF;-tagilsk</placeName>, are on the <placeName>Asiatic side</placeName>, on the two acclivi-<lb/>ties of the <placeName>Bartiraya</placeName>, where the alluvium of <placeName>Vilkni</placeName> alone has already<lb/>produced more than 2800lbs. of gold.</p><lb/><p>The platinum is found about a league to the east of the line of the<lb/>separation of waters (which must not be confounded with the axis of<lb/>the high summits), on the European side, near the course of the<lb/><placeName>Oulka</placeName>, at <placeName>Sukoi Visnin</placeName>, and at <placeName>Martian</placeName>. M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Schvetsov</persName>, who had<lb/>the good fortune to study under <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Berthier</persName>, and whose learning and<lb/>activity have been most useful during our travels in the <placeName>Ural</placeName>, disco-<lb/>vered chromate of iron, containing grains of platinum, which an able<lb/>chemist at <placeName>Catherineburgh</placeName>, M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Helm</persName>, has analyzed. The washings<lb/>of platinum at <placeName>Nijne&#x00EF;-Tagilsk</placeName> are so rich, that 100 <hi rendition="#i">puds</hi> (about 400<lb/>lbs. Russian) of sand afford 30 (sometimes 50) <hi rendition="#i">solotniks</hi> of platinum,<lb/>whilst the rich alluvia of gold at <placeName>Vilkni</placeName>, and other gold washings on<lb/>the Asiatic side, do not give more than 1<formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{2}</formula> to 2 solotniks in 100 puds<lb/>of sand. In <placeName>South America</placeName>, a very low chain of the <placeName>Cordilleras</placeName>,<lb/>that of <placeName>Cali</placeName>, also separates the auriferous and non-platiniferous sands<lb/>of the eastern declivity (<placeName>Popayan</placeName>), from the sands of the isthmus of<lb/>the <placeName>Raspadura of Choco</placeName>, which are very rich in platinum as well as<lb/>gold. M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Bousingault</persName> may, perhaps, already have thrown a new<lb/><pb n="419" facs="#f0002" />
        light on this American formation, and his observations will derive<lb/>some additional interest from those which we have made in this place.<lb/>We possess pepitas of platinum, of many inches in length, in which<lb/>M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Rose</persName> has discovered beautiful groups of crystals of the metal.</p><lb/><p>&#x2018;As to the greenstone porphyry of <placeName>Laya</placeName>, in which M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Engelhardt</persName><lb/>has observed little grains of platinum, we have examined it on the<lb/>spot with much care, but the only metallic grains which we have been<lb/>able to detect in the rocks of <placeName>Laya</placeName>, and in the greenstone of <placeName>Mount<lb/>Belayr-Gora</placeName>, have appeared to M. <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Rose</persName> to be sulphuret of iron; this<lb/>phenomenon will be a subject for new research. The work of M.<lb/><persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">Engelhardt</persName> on the <placeName>Ural</placeName> seemed to us to be worthy of much praise.<lb/>Osmium and iridium have also a particular locality, not amongst the<lb/>rich platiniferous alluvia of <placeName>Nijne&#x00EF;-Tagilsk</placeName>, but near <placeName>Belemboyevski</placeName><lb/>and <placeName>Kichtem</placeName>. I insist upon the geognostical characters drawn from<lb/>the metals which accompany the grains of platinum at <placeName>Choco</placeName>,<lb/><placeName>Brazil</placeName>, and in the <placeName>Ural</placeName>.&#x2019;<note place="foot" n="*"><bibl>Edin. Geog. Journ. ii. 441</bibl>.</note></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
