<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="97" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Discourse delivered by Baron <hi rendition="#k">Alexander Humboldt</hi> at the<lb break="yes"/>Extraordinary Meeting of the Imperial Academy of Sciences<lb break="yes"/>of St Petersburg, held on the</hi> 28<hi rendition="#i">th November</hi> 1829.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#et">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Gentlemen,</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#in">
                        <hi rendition="#k">If,</hi>
                    </hi> on this occasion, when there is manifested a noble ardour<lb break="yes" />for honouring the labours of human intellect, I venture to crave<lb break="yes"/>your indulgence, I do so only in discharging a duty which you<lb break="yes"/>have imposed upon me. On returning to my native country,<lb break="yes"/>after traversing the icy ridges of the Cordilleras, and the great<lb break="yes"/>forests of the equinoctial regions, and on being restered to Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope, then agitated by wars, after long enjoying the peaceful-<lb break="no"/>ness of nature, and the imposing aspect of wild luxuriance, I re-<lb break="no"/>ceived from this illustrious Academy, as a public mark of its<lb break="yes"/>good will, the honour of being associated with it. I still love<lb break="yes"/>to turn my thoughts toward the period of my life when the<lb break="yes"/>same eloquent voice which you have heard at the opening of<lb break="yes"/>this meeting, called me into the midst of you, and, by ingenious<lb break="yes"/>fictions, almost persuaded me that I had merited the palm which<lb break="yes"/>you conferred upon me. How far was I then from thinking<lb break="yes"/>that I should not sit at a meeting over which you, Sir <note place="foot" n="*">M. Ouvaroff, Preaident of the Imperial Russian Academy of Sciences.</note>, pre-<lb break="no"/>side, until I had returned from the banks of the Irtisch, the<lb break="yes"/>confines of Chinese Songarie, and the shores of the Caspian Sea!<lb break="yes"/>By the fortunate concatenation of events in the course of a rest-<lb break="no"/>le@s and sometimes laborious life, I have been enabled to com-<lb break="no"/>pare the auriferous deposits of the Uralian Mountains and New<lb break="yes" />Grenada&#x2014;the porphyry and trachyte formations of Mexico and<lb break="yes"/>Altai&#x2014;the savannas of the Orinoco, and the steppes of South-<lb break="no"/>ern Siberia, which offer a vast field to the peaceful conquests of<lb break="yes"/>agriculture, and to those arts which, while they add to the<lb break="yes"/>riches of nations, soften their manners, and progressively im-<lb break="no"/>prove the condition of society.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have been enabled to carry, in part, the same instruments,<lb break="yes"/>or those of similar but improved construction, to the shores of<lb break="yes"/>the Obi and the River of Amazons. In the long interval be-<lb break="no"/>tween my two journeys, the physical sciences, and especially<lb break="yes"/>geognosy, chemistry, and the electro-magnetic theory, have<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="98" facs="#f0002"/> undergone considerable changes. New instruments, I might al-<lb break="no"/>most say new organs, have been invented to bring man into<lb break="yes"/>more immediate contact with the mysterious powers which ani-<lb break="no"/>mate the works of creation, and of which the apparent disturb-<lb break="no"/>ances and irregularities are subject to eternal laws. If modern<lb break="yes"/>travellers can submit to their observations, in a brief period of<lb break="yes"/>time, a larger portion of the earth&#x2019;s surface, it is to the improve-<lb break="no"/>ments effected in the mathematical and physical sciences, to the<lb break="yes"/>precision of our instruments, the perfection of our methods, and<lb break="yes"/>the art of grouping facts and rising to general considerations,<lb break="yes"/>that they owe the advantages which they possess. The traveller<lb break="yes"/>applies to use what, through the beneficial influenoe of societie@,<lb break="yes"/>and the studies of sedentary life, has been prepared in the silence<lb break="yes"/>of the cabinet. To judge with equity and justice the merit of<lb break="yes"/>travellers of different times, we must be acquainted with the<lb break="yes"/>degree of development which practical astronomy, geognosy,<lb break="yes"/>meteorology, and descriptive natural history, had simultaneously<lb break="yes"/>acquired. It is thus that the degree of culture of the great do-<lb break="no"/>main of the sciences must be reflected in the traveller who would<lb break="yes"/>raise himself to the level of his times; and, in this manner,<lb break="yes"/>travels undertaken for the extension of the physical knowledge<lb break="yes"/>of the globe, must at different ages present an individual cha-<lb break="no" />racter&#x2014;the physiognomy of a given epoch. They exhibit a<lb break="yes" />pieture of the state of cultivation through which the sciences<lb break="yes" />have pregressively passed.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In thus tracing the duties of these who have gone through<lb break="yes"/>the same eareer as myself, and whose example has often re-<lb break="no"/>kindled my ardour in moments of difficulty, I have pointed out<lb break="yes"/>the source of the feeble success of a devotion, which your gene-<lb break="no"/>rous indulgence has condescended to magnify by public testi-<lb break="no"/>monials of your approbation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Finishing under happy auspices a long journey, undertaken<lb break="yes"/>by the order of a magnanimous monarch, powerfully aided by<lb break="yes"/>the knowledge of two philosphers, whose labours Europe has ap-<lb break="no" />preciated, MM. Ehrenberg and Rose, I might here confine my-<lb break="no" />self to laying before you the homage of my lively and respectful<lb break="yes"/>gratitude;&#x2014;I might solicit him who, young as he still is, has<lb break="yes"/>ventured to penetrate into those ancient <hi rendition="#i">mysteries,</hi> the memo-<lb break="no"/>rable sources of the religious and political civilization of Greece,<lb break="yes"/>to lend the aid of his eloquence to enable me to express more<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="99" facs="#f0003"/> worthily the sentiments by which I am animated. But I am<lb break="yes"/>sware, Gendemen, that the charm of eloquence, were it even in<lb break="yes"/>aecordance with the vivacity of feeling, is not sufficient in this<lb break="yes"/>@bly. You have been charged in this vast empire with the<lb break="yes"/>gr@d and neble mission of giving a general impulse to the cul-<lb break="no"/>tivation of science and literature&#x2014;of encouraging the labours<lb break="yes"/>which are in harmony with the present state of human know-<lb break="no"/>ledge&#x2014;of vivifying and enlarging the mind in the domain of<lb break="yes"/>the higher mathematics, the physical history of the globe, and<lb break="yes"/>the history of the nations as illustrated by the menuments of<lb break="yes"/>different ages. Your view is directed forwards to the career<lb break="yes"/>which remains to be run, and the tribute of gratitude which<lb break="yes"/>I offer you&#x2014;the only tribute worthy of your Institution&#x2014;is<lb break="yes"/>the solemn engagement by which I now bind myself to remain<lb break="yes"/>@ to the cultivation of the scienoes to the last moment of<lb break="yes"/>an already advanced career, to explore nature unceasingly, and<lb break="yes"/>to @ a course which has been traced by you and your il-<lb break="no"/>@trious predecessors.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This community of aetion in the higher studies, the aid which<lb break="yes"/>the different branches of human acquirement lend to each other,<lb break="yes"/>and the efforts that have been made at the same time in the two<lb break="yes" />continents, and in the wide expanse of the seas, have impressed a<lb break="yes"/>rapid movement upon the physical sciences, as, after ages of<lb break="yes"/>@, the simultaneousness of efforts similarly affected the<lb break="yes"/>progress of reason. Happy the country whose gover@ent ac-<lb break="no"/>cerds an august protection to literature and the arts, which do not<lb break="yes"/>merely delight the imagination of man, but also inerease his in-<lb break="no"/>tellectual power and enlarge his conceptions;&#x2014;to the physical<lb break="yes"/>sciences and the mathematics, which have so beneficial an influ-<lb break="no"/>@ upon the development of industry and public prosperity;<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;to the zeal of travellers, who force their way into unknown re-<lb break="no"/>gion@, or explore the riches of their native soil, and determine<lb break="yes"/>by @ measurements the nature of its configuration! In<lb break="yes"/>here recalling to mind a small part of what has been done in<lb break="yes"/>the year now about to close, I am rendering to the Prince a<lb break="yes"/>@ge which, by its very simplicity, cannot be displeasing to<lb break="yes"/>him.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>While MM. Rose and Ehrenberg and myself have, between<lb break="yes"/>the Ur@, the Altai, and the Caspian Sea, examined the geogno-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="100" facs="#f0004"/> stical constitution of the ground&#x2014;the relations of its heights and<lb break="yes"/>depressions, indicated by barometrical measurements&#x2014;the varia-<lb break="no"/>tions of the earth&#x2019;s magnetism in different latitudes (especially<lb break="yes"/>the augmentations of the inclination and intensity of the mag-<lb break="no"/>netic forces)&#x2014;the temperature of the interior of the globe&#x2014;the<lb break="yes"/>state of humidity of the atmosphere, by means of a psychrome-<lb break="no"/>tric instrument, which had not previously been employed on a<lb break="yes"/>long journey&#x2014;and, lastly, the astronomical position of some<lb break="yes"/>places, the geographical distribution of vegetables, and of seve-<lb break="no"/>ral groups of the animal kingdom hitherto little known; philo-<lb break="no"/>sophers and intrepid travellers have confronted the dangers pre-<lb break="no"/>sented by the snow-clad summits of Elborouz and Ararat.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I feel happy in seeing safely restored to the bosom of the<lb break="yes" />Academy him whose valuable ideas respecting the hororary va-<lb break="no" />riations of the magnetic needle we have just received, and<lb break="yes"/>to whom the sciences are indebted (along with ingenious and<lb break="yes" />delicate researches in crystallography) for the discovery of the<lb break="yes"/>influence of temperature upon the intensity of the electro-mag-<lb break="no"/>netic powers. M. Kupfer has recently returned from the Cau-<lb break="no"/>casian Alps, among which, after long migrations of the human<lb break="yes"/>race, in the great shipwreck of nations and tongues, so many<lb break="yes"/>different tribes have found refuge. To the name of this travel-<lb break="no"/>ler, our learned associate, is joined, by similarity of labours, the<lb break="yes"/>name of the philosopher who, with a noble perseverance, has<lb break="yes"/>struggled on the ridges of Ararat, regarded as the classic soil of<lb break="yes"/>the earliest and most venerable recollections of history, with the<lb break="yes"/>obstacles which the depth and softness of the eternal snows pre-<lb break="no"/>sented to him. I am almost afraid of wounding the modesty of<lb break="yes"/>the father, by adding, that M. Parrot, the traveller of Ararat,<lb break="yes"/>worthily sustains in the sciences the lustre of a hereditary cele-<lb break="no"/>brity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the more eastern regions of the empire, which have re-<lb break="no"/>ceived illustration from the immortal labours of my country-<lb break="no"/>man Pallas, (pardon me, Gentlemen, if I claim for Prussia part<lb break="yes"/>of the glory of which two nations at once may be proud), in the<lb break="yes"/>Uralian and Kolyvan mountains, we have followed the still re-<lb break="no"/>cent traces of the scientific expeditions of MM. Ledebour,<lb break="yes"/>Meyer and Bunge, and of MM. Hoffmann and Helmersen. The<lb break="yes"/>beautiful Flora of the Altai has already enriched the botanical<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="101" facs="#f0005"/> @ with which this capital is honoured, and which<lb break="yes"/>has risen, as by enchantment, thanks to the indefatigable and en-<lb break="no"/>lightened zeal of its director, to the rank of the first botanical<lb break="yes"/>gardens of Europe. The scientific world waits with impatience<lb break="yes"/>the publication of the Flora of the Altai, of which Dr Bunge<lb break="yes"/>himself, in the neighbourhood of Zmeinogorsk, shewed my friend<lb break="yes"/>M. Ehrenberg some interesting productions. It was unques-<lb break="no"/>tionably the first time that a traveller from Abyssinia, Dongola,<lb break="yes"/>Sin@i and Palestine, ascended the mountains of Riddersky, co-<lb break="no"/>vered with perpetual snows.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The geognestical description of the southern part of the Ural<lb break="yes"/>has been confided to two young naturalists, MM. Hoffmann and<lb break="yes" />Helmerssen, one of whom was the first who gave an accurate<lb break="yes" />account of the volcanoes of the South Sea. This choice is due<lb break="yes" />to an enlightened minister, a friend of science and its cultivators,<lb break="yes"/>the Count Cancrin, whose kind attention, activity and foresight,<lb break="yes"/>have impressed my fellow-labourers and myself with a gratitude<lb break="yes"/>not to be effaced. MM. Helmerssen and Hoffmann, pupils of<lb break="yes"/>the celebrated school of Dorpat, have studied for two years<lb break="yes"/>with success the different ramifications of the Ural Mountains,<lb break="yes"/>from the great Taganai, and the granites of Iremel, to beyond<lb break="yes"/>the plain of Gouberlinsk, which is connected, more to the south,<lb break="yes"/>with the Mougodjares Monntains, and to the east between Lake<lb break="yes"/>Aral and the b@sin of the Caspian Sea. It was there that M.<lb break="yes"/>Lemm, in spite of the severity of the winter, made the first ac-<lb break="no"/>curate astronomical observations that have been obtained of this<lb break="yes"/>arid yet inhabited country. We had the great satisfaction of<lb break="yes"/>being accompanied for a month by MM. Hoffmann and Hel-<lb break="no"/>merssen, and it was by them that we were first shewn a forma-<lb break="no"/>tion of volcanic amygdaloids, near Grasnuschinskaia, the only<lb break="yes"/>ones that have as yet been discovered in the long chain of the<lb break="yes"/>Ural which separates Europe and Asia, which presents the most<lb break="yes"/>@ eruptions of metals on its eastern slope, and which<lb break="yes"/>@, in veins or in alluvium, gold, platina, o@miuret of iri-<lb break="no"/>dium, @, discovered by Count Polier in alluvia to the<lb break="yes"/>west of the lofty mountain of Catschcaner, @on, sapphire,<lb break="yes"/>@ethyst, ruby, topaz, beryl, garnet, anatase, found by M. Rose,<lb break="yes"/>the celylanite, and other valuable productions of India and<lb break="yes"/>Brasil.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I might extend the list of important labours performed in the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="102" facs="#f0006"/> present year of his Majesty&#x2019;s reign, by speaking of the trigone-<lb break="no"/>metrical observations of the west, which, by the union of the la-<lb break="no"/>bours of Generals Schubert and Tenner, and of M. Struve, the<lb break="yes"/>great astronomer of Dorpat, will clucidate the figure of the<lb break="yes"/>Earth on a great scale;&#x2014;of the geological constitution of Lake<lb break="yes"/>Raikal, which has been examined by M. Hess;&#x2014;of the magne-<lb break="no"/>tic expedition of MM. Hansteen, Erman and Dowe, justly cele-<lb break="no"/>brated over all Europe, the most extensive and adventurous<lb break="yes"/>that has ever been undertaken by land (from Berlin and Chris-<lb break="no"/>tiania to Kamtchatka, where it connects itself with the great le-<lb break="no"/>bours of Captains Wrangell and Anjou);&#x2014;lastly, of the cir-<lb break="no"/>cumnavigation of the globe, which, by the command of the So-<lb break="no"/>vereign, Captain Luethe has performed, and which, through<lb break="yes"/>the co-operation of three excellent naturalists, Dr Mertens, Ba-<lb break="no"/>ron Kittliz, and M. Postels, has been productive of important<lb break="yes"/>results in Astronomy, Physica, Botany and Anatomy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have undertaken to poiat out this co@unity of efforts by<lb break="yes"/>which several portions of the empire have been explored, by the<lb break="yes"/>aid of modern science, by that of new instrumenta, and new<lb break="yes"/>me@, founded upon the analogy of facts formerly unknown.<lb break="yes"/>It is also by a community of interests that, having once more<lb break="yes"/>ventured upon a new journey, I have found pleasure in adorn-<lb break="no"/>ing my discourse with names which have become dear to science.<lb break="yes"/>After having admired the richness of the mineral productiona,<lb break="yes"/>the wonders of physical nature, one loves to point out (and it is<lb break="yes"/>a pleasant duty to perform in a strange land, in the midst of<lb break="yes"/>the assembly which listens to me) the intellectual richness of a<lb break="yes"/>nation, the labours of those useful men, disinterested in their<lb break="yes"/>devotion to science, who traverse their country, or, in solitude,<lb break="yes"/>prepare by study, by calculation and experiment, the discoveries<lb break="yes"/>of future generations.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If, as we have proved by recent examples, the vast extent of<lb break="yes"/>the Russian Empire, which surpasses that of the visible part of<lb break="yes"/>the moon, requires the concurrence of numerous observers, this<lb break="yes"/>very extent also presents advantages of another kind, which<lb break="yes"/>have long been known to you, Gentlemen, but which, in their<lb break="yes"/>relation to the present state of our knowledge of the physical<lb break="yes"/>history of the earth, do not appear to me to have been suffi-<lb break="no"/>ciently appreciated; I would not speak of that immense scale,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="103" facs="#f0007"/> from Li@ and Finland to the South Sea, which @ the<lb break="yes"/>chores of eastern A@ia and Ru@ America, on which the po-<lb break="no"/>@ and formation of rocks of all ages may be studied, within<lb break="yes"/>the @ of the same empire; the remains of those @<lb break="yes"/>@ which the @cient revolutions of our planet have buried<lb break="yes"/>im the b@wels of the earth; the gigantic bones of land quadr@-<lb break="no"/>peds now lost, or whose kindred species live only in the tropical<lb break="yes"/>regions;&#x2014;I would not draw the attention of this assembly to<lb break="yes"/>the aids which the geography of plants and animals (a science<lb break="yes"/>only commencing its existence) will one day derive from a more<lb break="yes"/>profound specific knowledge of the climatic distribution of or-<lb break="no"/>ganized beings, from the happy regions of the Chersonesus and<lb break="yes"/>Mingrelia, from the frontiers of Persia and Asia Minor, to the<lb break="yes"/>melancholy shores of the Frozen Ocean;&#x2014;I prefer confining<lb break="yes"/>myself to those variable phenomena whose regular periodicity,<lb break="yes"/>determined with the rigorous precision of astronomical observa-<lb break="no"/>tions, would le@d directly to the discovery of the great lawa of<lb break="yes"/>@ure.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If, in the school of Alexandri@, and at the splendid @poch of<lb break="yes"/>the Arabi@s (the first m@sters in the art of ob@ving and in-<lb break="no" />terrogating nature by means of experiment), the ins@<lb break="yes"/>which we owe to the great age of Galileo, Huygens and @<lb break="yes"/>@, had been known, we should now know, by comparative<lb break="yes"/>@vations, if the height of the atmosphene, the qua@tity of<lb break="yes"/>water which it contains and precipitates, and the mean temp@<lb break="yes"/>rature of places, have diminished in the course of age@<lb break="yes"/>should know the secular changes of the electro-magnetic charge<lb break="yes"/>of our planet, and the modifications which the temperature of<lb break="yes"/>the different strata of the globe, incre@ in the ratie of the<lb break="yes"/>depth, may have undergone, whether through an aug@<lb break="yes"/>of radiation, or from internal volcanic motions; la@tly we<lb break="yes"/>should know the variations of the level of the ocean, the p@tial<lb break="yes"/>disturbances c@ed by the barometrical preasure in the equ@<lb break="yes"/>brium of the @, and the relative frequency of certain winda,<lb break="yes"/>depending upon the form and surfaces of the continenta. M.<lb break="yes"/>O@ky would submit to his profound calculati@ these<lb break="yes"/>deta, that had accumulated through ages, @ he has recently<lb break="yes"/>solved with success one of the most diffi@ problems of the<lb break="yes"/>propagation of vibrations.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="104" facs="#f0008"/>
                <p>Unfortunately, in the physical sciences, the civilisation of<lb break="yes" />Europe did not commence at so early a period. We are, as the<lb break="yes" />priests of Sais said of the Hellenes, a new people. The almost<lb break="yes" />simultaneous invention of those organs by which we are brought<lb break="yes" />into contact with the external world,&#x2014;the telescope, the thermo-<lb break="no"/>meter, the barometer, the pendulum, and that other instrument,<lb break="yes"/>the most general and the most powerful of all, the infinitesimal<lb break="yes"/>calculus,&#x2014;hardly dates thirty lustrums back. In this conflict of<lb break="yes"/>the powers of nature, which yet does not destroy her stability,<lb break="yes"/>the periodical variations do not seem to surpass oertain limits;<lb break="yes"/>they make the entire system oscillate round a mean state of equi-<lb break="no"/>librium,&#x2014;at least such is the case in the present state of things,<lb break="yes"/>since the great cataclysms which swallowed up so many genera-<lb break="no"/>tions of animals and plants. Now the value of the periodical<lb break="yes"/>change is determined with so much the more precision, the<lb break="yes"/>greater the interval between the extreme observations.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is the duty of the scientific bodies which are continually<lb break="yes" />forming and renovating themselves,&#x2014;the academies, the univer-<lb break="no"/>sities, the many learned societies scattered over Europe, in the<lb break="yes"/>two Americas, at the southern extremity of Africa, in India, and<lb break="yes"/>even in New Holland, which, although but of late so wild, al-<lb break="no"/>ready possesses an observatory,&#x2014;to observe, to measure, and, as<lb break="yes"/>it were, to watch over, what is variable in the economy of na-<lb break="no"/>ture. The illustrious author of the Mecanique Celeste, has of-<lb break="no"/>ten verbally expressed the same thought in the midst of the In-<lb break="no"/>stitute, where I have had the honour of sitting with him for<lb break="yes"/>eighteen years.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The western nations have earried into the different parts of<lb break="yes"/>the world those forms of civilization, that development of the<lb break="yes"/>human intelleet, whose origin ascends to the epoch of the intel-<lb break="no" />lectual greatness of the Greeks, and to the gentle influence of<lb break="yes" />Christianity. Divided in languages and manners, and in politi-<lb break="no" />cal and religious institutions, the enlightened nations form in<lb break="yes" />our days but a single family (and this is one of the most beauti-<lb break="no"/>ful results of modern civilization), when the object in view is<lb break="yes"/>the great interests of science, literature, and art, all that, spring-<lb break="no"/>ing from an internal source, the depths of thought and feeling,<lb break="yes"/>elevates man above the vulgar cares of society.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In this noble community of interests and action, most of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="105" facs="#f0009"/> impertant problems which have reference to the physics of the<lb break="yes"/>globe, and which I have pointed out above, may, without doubt,<lb break="yes"/>become the object of simultaneous researches; but the @<lb break="yes"/>extent of the Russian Empire in Europe, Asia, and America,<lb break="yes"/>pre@ts peculiar and local advantages, well wo@thy of occupy-<lb break="no"/>ing, for one day, the thoughts of this illustrious society. An<lb break="yes"/>imp@lse given from so high a source would produce a happy ac-<lb break="no"/>tivity among the observers with which your country is honour-<lb break="no"/>ed. I would venture to point out here, and to recommend to<lb break="yes"/>your notice, three objects which are not (as was once said under<lb break="yes"/>a misapprehension of the concatenation of human acquirements)<lb break="yes"/>merely speculative and theoretical, but which have intimate re-<lb break="no"/>ference to the ordinary wants of life.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The nautical art, the teaching of which, encouraged by the<lb break="yes" />highest patronage, has, under the direction of a great navigat@r <note place="foot" n="*">Admiral Krusenstern.</note>,<lb break="yes"/>assumed so happy a development in this country, has, for cen-<lb break="no"/>turies back, required a precise knowledge of the variation@ of<lb break="yes"/>the earth&#x2019;s magnetism in declination, inclination, and intensity<lb break="yes"/>of forces, for the declination of the needle in different seas, the<lb break="yes"/>appreciation of which is more exclusively required by mariners,<lb break="yes"/>is intimately connected in theory with two other elements, the<lb break="yes"/>inclination and the intensity measured by oscillations. At no<lb break="yes"/>former peried did the knowledge of the variations of the terres-<lb break="no"/>trial magnetism make so rapid advances as within the last thirty<lb break="yes"/>years. The angles which the needle forms with the vertical and<lb break="yes"/>the meridian of the place,&#x2014;the intensity of forces, of which I have<lb break="yes"/>had the good fortune to ascertain the increase from the equator<lb break="yes"/>to the magnetic pole,&#x2014;the horary variations of inclination, decli-<lb break="no" />nation, and intensity, often modified by the aurora borealis,<lb break="yes" />earthquakes, and mysterious motions in the interior of the earth,<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;the irregular disturbances of the needle, which I have designat-<lb break="no"/>ed, in a long course of observations, by the name of magnetie tem-<lb break="no"/>pests,&#x2014;have, in their turn, become objects of the most labo@<lb break="yes"/>researches. The great discoveries of Oerstedt, Arago, Ampere,<lb break="yes"/>Seeb@ck, Morichini, and Mrs Somerville, have revealed to @s<lb break="yes"/>the mutual relations of magneti@m with electricity, heat and solar<lb break="yes"/>light. There are only three metals, Iron, Nickel, and Cobalt,<lb break="yes"/>that become magnetic. The surprising phenomenon of rotstory<lb break="yes"/>magnetism, which my illustrious friend M. Arago first made<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="106" facs="#f0010"/> known, shews us that nearly all the bodies in nature are transi-<lb break="no"/>torily susceptible of electro-magnetic actions. The Russian<lb break="yes"/>empire is the only country on earth traversed by two lines with-<lb break="no"/>out declination, or along which the needle is directed towards<lb break="yes"/>the poles of the earth. One of these two lines, whose position<lb break="yes"/>and periodical motion of translation from east to west, are the<lb break="yes"/>principal elements of a future theory of the terrestrial magnetism,<lb break="yes"/>passes, according to the last researches of MM. Hansteen and<lb break="yes"/>Erman, between Mourom and Nijni-Novogorod; the second,<lb break="yes"/>some degrees to the east of Irkoutsk between Parchnikaia and<lb break="yes"/>Jarbinsk. Their prolongation northwards, and the rapidity of<lb break="yes"/>their motion westward, are not yet known. The physics of the<lb break="yes"/>globe require the complete tracing of the two lines without de-<lb break="no"/>clination, at equi-distant periods, for example, every ten years,&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>the precise determination of the absolute variations of inelination<lb break="yes"/>and intensity at all the points where MM. Hansteen, Erman,<lb break="yes"/>and myself, have observed in Europe, between St Petersburg,<lb break="yes"/>Cazan and Astracan, in Northern Asia between Jekaterinburg,<lb break="yes"/>Miask, Oust-Kamenogorsk, Obdorsk, and Jakoutsk. These re-<lb break="no"/>sults cannot be obtained by strangers who traverse the country<lb break="yes"/>in a single direction, and at a single period. There is required<lb break="yes"/>a system of combined observations, carried on during a long pe-<lb break="no"/>riod of time, and confided to observere established in the differ-<lb break="no"/>ent countries. St Petersburg, Moscow, and Cazan, are fortu-<lb break="no"/>nately situated very near the first line of no deelination, which<lb break="yes"/>traverses European Russia. Kiachta and Verkhné-Oudinsk pre-<lb break="no"/>sent advantages for the second or Siberian line. When we re-<lb break="no"/>flect on the comparative precision of observations made at sea<lb break="yes"/>and on land, with the aid of the instruments of Borda, Bessel,<lb break="yes"/>and Gambey, we may easily be persuaded that Russia, by its<lb break="yes"/>position, is capable of forwarding the theory of magnetism in a<lb break="yes"/>very great degree, in the space of twenty years. In speaking<lb break="yes"/>of these matters, I am only, gentlemen, in a manner, the inter-<lb break="no"/>preter of your desires. The manner in which you received the<lb break="yes"/>request which I addressed to you, seven months ago, relative to<lb break="yes"/>the correspondent observations of horary variations made at<lb break="yes"/>Paris, at Berlin, in a mine at Freyberg, and at Cazan, by the<lb break="yes"/>le@ned and laborioua astronomer M. Simonoff, has proved that<lb break="yes"/>the Imperial Academy will worthily second the other academies<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="107" facs="#f0011"/> of Europe in the thoray, but useful, research into the periodi-<lb break="no"/>city of all the magnetic phenomena.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If the resolution of the problem which I have just pointed<lb break="yes"/>@ equally important for the physical history of our planet<lb break="yes"/>@ the improvement of the art of navigation, the second object<lb break="yes"/>@ I have to lay before you, and for which the extent of the<lb break="yes"/>@ presents immense advantages, is more imm@ly con-<lb break="no"/>@cted with general wants,&#x2014;the cultivation of the soil, the exa-<lb break="no"/>@tion of the configuration of the ground, the exact know-<lb break="no"/>@ge of the humidity of the air, which visibly decreases with<lb break="yes"/>the destruction of the forests and the diminution of the water of<lb break="yes"/>@kes and rivers. The first and noblest object of seience re-<lb break="no"/>@ides undoubtedly in themselves, in the enlargement of the<lb break="yes"/>sphere of ideas, and of the intellectual power of @an. It is not<lb break="yes"/>in the @om of an @cademy like yours, under the monarch who<lb break="yes"/>regulates the destinie@ of the empire, that the res@rch of great<lb break="yes"/>physical truth@ requi@ the aupport of a material and @ternal<lb break="yes"/>interest, of an immediate application to the wants of social<lb break="yes"/>@: but when the sciences, without deviating from their noble<lb break="yes"/>@ object, are capable of exercising a direct influence upon<lb break="yes"/>@ and the arts (which are too exclusively called use-<lb break="no"/>ful), it is the duty of the philosopher to point out these rela-<lb break="no"/>@ between the scientific inve@tigation of countries, and the<lb break="yes"/>increase of territorial riches.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A country which e@tends over more than 135 degrees of<lb break="yes"/>longitude, from the happy zone of the olive to the climates in<lb break="yes"/>which the ground is only covered with lichena, is more than any<lb break="yes"/>other capable of advancing the study of the atmosphere, the<lb break="yes"/>knowledge of the mean temperatures of the year, and, what is<lb break="yes"/>@ch more important for the cycle of vegetation, that of the<lb break="yes"/>distrihution of the annual heat among the different seasons.<lb break="yes"/>Add to these data for obtaining a group of facts intimately<lb break="yes"/>connected with each other, the variable pre@ure of the air, and<lb break="yes"/>the @elation of this pressure to the predominant winds and the<lb break="yes"/>temperature, the extent of the horary variations of the barome-<lb break="no"/>ter (which under the tropics, transform a tube filled with mer-<lb break="no"/>cury into a kind of time-piece of most imperturbable regularity<lb break="yes"/>in its progress), the hygrometric state of the air, and the annual<lb break="yes"/>quantity of rain, which it is of so much importance to the<lb break="yes"/>agriculturist to know. When the varied inflections of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="108" facs="#f0012"/> isothermal lines, or lines of equal heat, shall be traced by accu-<lb break="no"/>rate observations, and continued at least five years, in European<lb break="yes"/>Russia and Siberia; when they shall have been prolonged to<lb break="yes"/>the western coasts of America, where an excellent navigator<lb break="yes"/>Captain Wrangel, is soon to reside,&#x2014;the science of the distribu-<lb break="no"/>tion of heat at the surface of the globe, and in the strata acces-<lb break="no"/>sible to our researches, will be established upon solid founda-<lb break="no"/>tions.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The government of the United States of North America,<lb break="yes"/>keenly interested in the progress of population, and of an exten-<lb break="no"/>sive cultivation of useful plants, has long been sensible of the<lb break="yes" />advantages afforded by the great extent of its possessions from<lb break="yes" />the Atlantic to the Rocky Mountains, from Louisiana and Flo-<lb break="no" />rida, where the sugar-cane is cultivated, to the Canadian lakes.<lb break="yes"/>Meteorological instruments, after being compared with each<lb break="yes"/>other, have been distributed over a great number of places, the<lb break="yes"/>selection of which has been submitted to minute discussion,<lb break="yes"/>and the annual results, reduoed to a small number of figures, are<lb break="yes"/>published by a central committee, which watches over the uni-<lb break="no"/>formity of the observations and calculations. I have already<lb break="yes"/>pointed out in a memoir, in which I have discussed the general<lb break="yes"/>causes upon which the differences of climate in the same lati-<lb break="no"/>tude depend, on how great a scale this beautiful example of the<lb break="yes"/>United States might be followed in the Russian Empire<note place="foot" n="*">This beautiful memoir was published in vol. iv. of the New Series of this<lb break="yes"/>Journal.</note>.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We are happily far removed from the period when philoso-<lb break="no"/>phers thought they knew the olimate of a place, when they<lb break="yes"/>knew the extremes of temperature attained by the thermome-<lb break="no"/>ter in winter and summer. A uniform method, founded upon<lb break="yes"/>the choice of hours, and up to the level of our recently acquir-<lb break="no"/>ed knowledge of the true means of the days, months, and whole<lb break="yes"/>year, will replace the old and defective methods. By this in-<lb break="no"/>vestigation, various prejudices respecting the selection of objects<lb break="yes"/>of cultivation, the possibility of planting the vine, the mulberry,<lb break="yes"/>the chesnut, or the oak, will disappear in certain provinces of<lb break="yes"/>the empire. To extend it to the most remote parts, we may<lb break="yes"/>reckon upon the enlightened co-operation of many well-educated<lb break="yes"/>young officers, with whom the Corps des Mines is honoured,<lb break="yes"/>that of physicians animated by zeal for the physical sciences,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="109" facs="#f0013"/> and upon the pupils of that excellent institution, the School of<lb break="yes"/>Canals, Bridges, and Roads, in which mathematical studies of a<lb break="yes"/>high order give rise to a kind of instinetive taste for order and<lb break="yes"/>precision.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Along with the two objects of research which we have just<lb break="yes"/>ex@ined in their relation to the extent of the empire (the earth&#x2019;s<lb break="yes" />magnetism and the study of the atmosphere, which leads at the<lb break="yes" />same time, by the aid of the mean heights of the barometer, to<lb break="yes" />the improved knowledge of the configuration of the ground), I<lb break="yes" />would mention, in concluding, a third kind of inquiry of a more<lb break="yes" />lecal interest, although connected with the great questions of<lb break="yes" />physical geography. A considerable part of the earth&#x2019;s surface<lb break="yes"/>around the Caspian Sea, is inferior to the level of the Black Sea<lb break="yes"/>and the Baltic. This depression, which had been supposed for<lb break="yes"/>more than a century, and which has been measured by the<lb break="yes"/>laborious efforts of MM. Parrot and Engelhardt, may be<lb break="yes"/>ranked among the most surprising geognostical phenomena.<lb break="yes"/>The exact determination of the mean annual barometric height<lb break="yes"/>of the city of Orenburg, which we owe to MM. Hoffmann and<lb break="yes"/>Helmerssen; a levelling <hi rendition="#i" >(nivellement par station?)</hi> made by<lb break="yes"/>the aid of the barometer, by the same observers, from Orenburg<lb break="yes"/>to Gourief, the eastern port of the Caspian Sea; corresponding<lb break="yes"/>measures taken during several months in these two places; and,<lb break="yes"/>lastly, observations recently made by us at Astracan and at the<lb break="yes"/>mouth of the Volga, corresponding at once to Sarepta, Orenburg,<lb break="yes"/>Cazan, and Moscow, will serve, when all the data are brought<lb break="yes"/>together and rigorously calculated, to verify the absolute height<lb break="yes"/>of this internal basin.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On the northern side of the Caspian Sea, every thing appears<lb break="yes"/>to indicate at the present day a progressive diminution of the<lb break="yes" />level of the waters; but without giving too much credit to the<lb break="yes" />report of Hanway (an old English traveller, of otherwise re-<lb break="no" />spectable character), about the periodical risings and fallings, we<lb break="yes"/>cannot deny the encroachments of the Caspian Sea near the an-<lb break="no"/>cient city of Terek <hi rendition="#i">(perhaps the old town of Terek or Old Terek)</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and to the south of the mouth of the Cyrus, where scattered<lb break="yes"/>trunks of trees, the remains of a forest, are seen always inun-<lb break="no"/>dated. The islet of Pogorelaia Plita, on the contrary, seems to<lb break="yes"/>be progressively extending and rising above the waves, which,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="110" facs="#f0014"/> not many years ago covered it, previous to the flames which<lb break="yes"/>were perceived by navigators at a distance.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>To solve in a satisfactory manner the great problems relative<lb break="yes"/>to the depression, which is perhaps variable, of the level of the<lb break="yes" />waters, and of that of the continental basin of the Caspian Sea,<lb break="yes"/>it were desirable that there should be traced a <hi rendition="#i">soundings line</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>around this basin, in the plains of Sarepta, Ouralsk, and Oren-<lb break="no"/>burg, by uniting the points which are precisely at the level of<lb break="yes"/>the Baltic and Black Seas; that it should be determined by<lb break="yes"/>marks placed on the coasts all round the Caspian Sea (like the<lb break="yes"/>marks placed nearly a century ago on the coasts of Sweden, by<lb break="yes"/>the directions of the Stockholm Academy), whether there be a<lb break="yes"/>general or partial, a continuous or periodical, fall of the waters,<lb break="yes"/>or whether (as the great geologist M. Leopold de Buch sup-<lb break="no"/>poses in respect to Scandinavia) a part of the neighbouring land<lb break="yes"/>is elevated or depressed by volcanic causes acting at immense<lb break="yes"/>depths in the interior of the globe. The mountainous isthmus<lb break="yes"/>of Caucasus, partly composed of trachyte and other rocks,<lb break="yes"/>which undoubtedly owe their origin to volcanic fires, margins<lb break="yes"/>the Caspian Sea to the west, while it is surrounded to the east<lb break="yes"/>by tertiary and secondary formations, which extend towards<lb break="yes"/>those countries of ancient celebrity, for the knowledge of which<lb break="yes"/>Europe is indebted to the important work of Baron Meyen-<lb break="no"/>dorf.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In these general views, which I submit to your enlightened<lb break="yes" />consideration, I have attempted to point out some of the advan-<lb break="no" />tages which the physical history of the globe might derive from<lb break="yes" />the position and extent of this empire. I have exposed the<lb break="yes" />views which vividly presented themselves to me, in sight of the<lb break="yes" />regions from which I have just returned. It has appeared to<lb break="yes"/>me more suitable to render a public testimony of approbation to<lb break="yes" />those who, under the auspices of the government, have pursued<lb break="yes" />the same career as myself, and to direct the attention to what<lb break="yes" />remains to be done for the advancement of science, and for the<lb break="yes" />glory of your country, than to speak of my own efforts, and<lb break="yes" />compress within a narrow compass the results of observations<lb break="yes" />which have still to be compared with the great mass of partial<lb break="yes" />data which you have collected.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have alluded in this discourse to the extent of country<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="111" facs="#f0015"/> which separates the line of no magnetic variation, to the east of<lb break="yes"/>Lake Baikal from the basin of the Caspian Sea, the valleys of<lb break="yes"/>the Cyrus, and the frocen summits of Caneasus. At these<lb break="yes"/>@es the mind involuntarily reverts to that recent struggle, in<lb break="yes"/>which the moderation of the conqueror has increased the glory<lb break="yes"/>of his arms, which has opened up new paths to commerce, and<lb break="yes"/>has en@red the deliverance of Greece, the long abandoned<lb break="yes"/>cradle of the civilization of our ancestors. But it is not in this<lb break="yes"/>peaceful assembly that I ought to celebrate the glory of arms.<lb break="yes"/>The august monarch, who has deigned to call me to this coun-<lb break="no"/>try, and to smile upon my labours, presents himself to my ima-<lb break="no"/>gination as a peace-making genius. Vivifying by his example<lb break="yes"/>all that is true, great, and generous, he has delighted, since the<lb break="yes"/>dawn of his reign, in protecting the study of the sciences which<lb break="yes"/>nourish and strengthen the understanding, and that of litera-<lb break="no"/>ture and the arts, which embellish life, and add to the comfort<lb break="yes"/>of society.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 