<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Letter from Baron Humboldt</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:02</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">IV.98</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1829-Lettre_de_M-04-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-01.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-04-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-08.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-13.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-14.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-17.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-18.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-19.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-20.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-21-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-22-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-23-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1829-Lettre_de_M-24-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Letter from Baron Humboldt</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1829</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;Morning Advertiser&lt;/i&gt; 12007 (19. Oktober 1829), [o. S.]; 12008 (20. Oktober 1829), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#b">LETTER FROM BARON HUMBOLDT.</hi></head>
                <p><hi rendition="#c">(From the <hi rendition="#i">Journal du Commerce</hi>.)</hi></p>
                <p>In a late account of the Sitting of the Academy of<lb/>
                Sciences we alluded to a letter from Baron Humboldt,<lb/>
                    which was read to that learned Society. It was addressed<lb/>
                    to M. Arago, who wishes us to make it public. Com-<lb/>
                    merce is essentially connected with the progress of geo-<lb/>
                    graphic science, consequently our readers will read with<lb/>
                interest the correspondence of that celebrated traveller.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#right">&#x201C;Uat Kamenogorak, upon the Upper Irtisch, in<lb/>
                Siberia, August 13, 1829.</hi></p>
                <p>&#x201C;I have been during the last two months, beyond the<lb/>
                    frontiers of Europe Eastward of Ural, and in the agitated<lb/>
                    life we lead, I have lost many opportunities of sending<lb/>
                    you signs of my existence and friendship. It is impossible<lb/>
                    in this letter, written in haste&#x2014;(we are upon the frontier<lb/>
                    of the Steppe of the Kirgises, about four in the morning,<lb/>
                    and we proceed this night up to the eastward, towards<lb/>
                    Buckt@rmu, Narim, and the first post of Chinese Mongolia)<lb/>
                    it is impossible, I say, to communicate the precise observa-<lb/>
                    tions we have made since our departure from Petersburgh<lb/>
                on the 20th of May.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;You will find no other satisfaction in reading these lines<lb/>
                    than that of knowing, that the scientific object of my<lb/>
                    journey has been successful beyond my hopes; that not-<lb/>
                    withstanding the fatigues and the space we have travelled<lb/>
                    over (we have since our departure gone over 5,600<lb/>
                    wersts, of which 1,320 were in this part of Asia,) my<lb/>
                    health is good; that I suffer with patience and courage;<lb/>
                    that I have to bestow much praise on my companions, M.<lb/>
                    Rose and M. Ehremberg; and that, laden with collections<lb/>
                    geological, botanical, and zoological, obtained from the<lb/>
                    Oural, the Altai, the Obi, the Irtisch, and the Oremburg,<lb/>
                    we hope to return to Berlin about the end of November.<lb/>
                    I cannot descrive all the amiable cares taken by the Rus-<lb/>
                sian Government to facilitate the object of this excursion.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;We travelled with three carriages, conducted by a su-<lb/>
                    perior officer of Mines, and preceded by a courier of the<lb/>
                    crown. We were occasionally provided with 30 or 40<lb/>
                    horses at a station, and during the night and day relays<lb/>
                    were placed with the greatest order. I regard this as a<lb/>
                    mark of beneficence and personal attention; @is public<lb/>
                    homage offered to science; a noble munificence expanding<lb/>
                in favour of modern civilization.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;Our rout has been by Moscow, Nischmi Nowgorod,<lb/>
                    then upon the Wolga to Casan, and to the ruins of the<lb/>
                    Tartar City of Bulgaria, where the family of Tamerlain<lb/>
                    resided. This part of Russia, inhabited by Musulmans,<lb/>
                    covered with Greek churches and mosques, is very re-<lb/>
                    markable, giving, like the Ural, Baschkire, and the<lb/>
                    Altai, a lively interest to the fine researches of<lb/>
                    the &#x201C;Asia Poliglotta&#x201D; of M. Klaproth. From<lb/>
                    Casan we remounted the Oural by the picturesque<lb/>
                    valleys of Kungur and Perm. During the whole<lb/>
                    of the journey from Nischmi Nowgorod, to Catherine-<lb/>
                    bourgh, and the Palatinate of Nischne-Tagilsk, we were<lb/>
                    accompanied by Count Pohir, whom you may remember<lb/>
                    you saw at Paris, at the residence of the Duchess de<lb/>
                    Duras. He is exercising in these wild regions his ad-<lb/>
                    mirable talent for landscape painting. Fixed by his mar-<lb/>
                    riage in Russia, he is also actively occupied in working<lb/>
                    mines. I reached, amidst a train of romantic circumstances,<lb/>
                    the Asiatic declivity of the Ural, in the same caleche which<lb/>
                    conveyed me from Paris to Verona, to Naples, and to<lb/>
                    Berlin. It was in the best state, and did honour to its<lb/>
                Parisian construction.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;We have employed a month in visiting the gold<lb/>
                    mines of Borosowsk, the mines of Malachite, of Ta-<lb/>
                    gilsk, the iron and copper mines; the working for<lb/>
                    beryl and topazes; the washings for gold and platina.<lb/>
                    We were astonished at the gold pips (pepites) from two<lb/>
                    to three, and form eighteen to twenty livres in value,<lb/>
                    found a few inches below the grassy turf, where it had re-<lb/>
                    mained unknown during ages. It is the position and<lb/>
                    origin probably of those alluvions, generally mixed with<lb/>
                    fragments of grunstein, schiste chloriteux, and serpentine,<lb/>
                which has been one of the principal objects of this journey.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;The new discoveries beyond 59 and 60 degrees of latitude<lb/>
                    become very important. We find, with the teeth of ele-<lb/>
                    phants, fossils enveloped in alluvials of auriferous sand&#x2014;<lb/>
                    Their formation succeeds the local destruction of those<lb/>
                    great animals. The amber and lignites discovered upon<lb/>
                    the eastern declivity of the Oural, are decidedly the most<lb/>
                    ancient. The auriferous sand found among grains of<lb/>
                    cinabar, copper, and other ores, have a brilliancy beyond<lb/>
                    the sparkling of the diamond. It is very remarkable, that<lb/>
                    in the middle and northern part of the Oural the platina is<lb/>
                    not found so abundant as on the western and European<lb/>
                    side. The richest lavages of gold, are upon the Asiatic<lb/>
                    declivity of the side of the Bartiraya. M. Rose discovered<lb/>
                    a beautiful group of christalized platina.&#x201D;</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#c">(<hi rendition="#i">To be continued</hi>.)</hi></p>
                
                <pb facs="#f0002"/>
                <p><hi rendition="#b">LETTERS FROM BARON HUMBOLDT.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#c">(<hi rendition="#i">Concluded</hi>.)</hi></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#right">August, from the 8th to the 20th.</hi></p>
                <p>The last lines of this are written on the 20th of August.<lb/>
                    I quitted the pen eight days since to take @@ distances;<lb/>
                    for this southern extremity of Siberia, where we find the<lb/>
                    sources of the Obim and the confines of the Chinese Mon-<lb/>
                    golia, requires much attention, with respect to geogra-<lb/>
                    phical position. The regularity of chronometers is altered<lb/>
                    by the rapidity of travelling. I have been since the 13th<lb/>
                    on a visit to the Chinese piquet (advanced post) in Son-<lb/>
                    garia. We were compelled to leave our carriages at<lb/>
                    Ust-Kamenogotsk, and to take for the dreadful roads of<lb/>
                    this country the long sledges of Siberia, in which we lie<lb/>
                    down. But before I speak of the journey we made to the<lb/>
                    celestial empire, I must resume the thread of our travels.<lb/>
                    After having visited the north of the Oural, by Wercho-<lb/>
                    @rna and Bagerlawsk, we took azimuths to determine the<lb/>
                    positions of its nothern feet, then inspected the mines of<lb/>
                    beryl and topaz of Mursinsk. We left Sicatherinburg<lb/>
                    between the 6th and 18th of July for Tobolsk, by Jiumere,<lb/>
                    where the family of Balu Chan formerly resided. We<lb/>
                    were desirous of pursuing a direct course by Om@k upon<lb/>
                    Stratoust, but the beauty of the season induced us to add<lb/>
                    the Altai and the Upper Irtisch, (a deviation of 3,000<lb/>
                    werstes) to our primitve plan of operation. The Gover-<lb/>
                    nor General of Western Siberia, General Villiaminof, met<lb/>
                    us, accompanied by one of his Aides de Camp, M. de Yer-<lb/>
                    molof. General Litvinof, who commanded all the line of<lb/>
                    the Kirguises, put himself to the inconvenience of coming<lb/>
                    from Tomsk to the mountains of Kolivan to rejoin us, and<lb/>
                    co@@ us to the Chinese post. We arrived here by the<lb/>
                    Steppe of Bora@, where the mosquitos rival those of the<lb/>
                    Oronoque, and where they are stifled under a mask of<lb/>
                    horse hair. We have seen the romantic lake of Ke@wan,<lb/>
                    the famous mines of Schlangenberg (producing porphyry),<lb/>
                    those of Reiders and Sinianefski, which produce annually<lb/>
                    40,000 pounds of auriferous silver. At Ust we had the<lb/>
                    first sight of the @hain of the Kirguises.</p>
                <p>They sent to the advance post of the Chinese at Mongo-<lb/>
                    lia, (Sougario,) to know whether they would receive us<lb/>
                    with General Litvinof. Permission was granted, but<lb/>
                    subject to Chinese etiquette. The Chinese commandant<lb/>
                    expected, notwithstanding the difference in rank, that they<lb/>
                    should pay him the first visit in his tent, and he informed<lb/>
                    them that he should do the same if he ever touched the<lb/>
                    Russian territory. We took the road for Batty by the<lb/>
                    little Fort of Buctorma, and by Kraswoyar, where we<lb/>
                    passed the night of the 16th and 17th of August, (new style,)<lb/>
                    observing the singular phenomena of Polar bandes.&#x2014;<lb/>
                    (Pray examine at that time your magnetic registre) At<lb/>
                    Batty we found two Chinese encampments upon both sides<lb/>
                    of the Irtisch. They made a miserable appearance. The<lb/>
                    tents were occupied by the Mongols, or Cambanzes. A<lb/>
                    small Chinese temple stood upon a barren hill. Camels<lb/>
                    and two oxen were grazing in the valley. The two com-<lb/>
                    manders, one of whom had only left Pekin a week before,<lb/>
                    were of pure Chinese origin;&#x2014;they are changed every<lb/>
                    three years. Dressed in silk, and each wearing a fine<lb/>
                    peacock&#x2019;s feather in his cap, they received us with a<lb/>
                gravity rather pleasing. Iin exchange for a few yards of<lb/>
                    cloth and red velvet, they gave me a Chinese book in five<lb/>
                    volumes; the subject is historical, and however common it<lb/>
                    may be, it will be a precious gift, because it is connected<lb/>
                    with this little excursion. Fortunately, this frontier of<lb/>
                    Mongolia has been a fruitful mine for rare plants and new<lb/>
                    insects. M. Ehrenberg has made ample collections; but<lb/>
                    that which renders the journey from the Altai very im-<lb/>
                    portant, is the circumstance, that in no other part of the<lb/>
                    two worlds has granite gneiss, and other primitive ores,<lb/>
                    given to much proof of eruption and expansion as at the<lb/>
                    Altai. We not only see granite penetrate in veins which<lb/>
                    run upwards, but it opens holes, and extends in a con-<lb/>
                    tinued manner more than 2,000 fathoms in length. The<lb/>
                    hills contain cones, and bells of granite, with porphyry in<lb/>
                    the form of fomes. The granite is intermixed with white<lb/>
                    stone, and veins of porphyry are seen running in every<lb/>
                direction.</p>
                <p>M. Rose discovered in the north of the Ural a spot<lb/>
                    where the porphyry, forming round hodies, is divided<lb/>
                    into parallel rings, by coming in contact with calcarious<lb/>
                jasper.</p>
                <p>I have seen such divisions and <hi rendition="#i">silicifications</hi> at Pe-<lb/>
                    drazio&#x2014;I have remarked the temperature of the earth<lb/>
                    (it is often above 2 deg), the intensity and magnetic inclina-<lb/>
                    tion in places which Messrs. Hausteen and Ermann have<lb/>
                    not visited. Our observations confirm the motion of the<lb/>
                    clouds from East to West, which you alluded to in your<lb/>
                report of the journey of M. Frecinet.</p>
                <p>The post is going off. I have not time to read over, nor<lb/>
                    correct this confused letter. I hope to be with you next<lb/>
                summer.</p>
                <p>A thousand expressions of friendship to Gay Lussac.</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>

    </text>
</TEI>
