<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="149" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>ON THE CHAINS OF MOUNTAINS AND VOLCANOS OF<lb break="yes"/>CENTRAL ASIA.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#k">by baron a. von humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">In</hi> the journey I made, during the summer of 1829, in Northern Asia, be-<lb break="no"/>yond the Ob, I passed nearly seven weeks on the frontiers of Chinese Zunga-<lb break="no"/>ria, between the forts of Oust-Kamenogorsk and Bouktaminsk, and the Chi-<lb break="no"/>nese advanced station named Khoni-ma&#x00EF;lakhou, to the north of lake Za&#x00EF;sang;<lb break="yes"/>on the line of the Cossacks of the steppe of the Kirghiz, and on the coasts<lb break="yes"/>of the Caspian Sea. At the important emporia of Semipolatinsk, Petropaulov-<lb break="no"/>ski, Tro&#x00EF;tzka&#x00EF;a, Orenburg, and Astrakan, I endeavoured to obtain from the<lb break="yes"/>Tatars, who travel about so much, &#x2014; and by Tatars I understand, as the Rus-<lb break="no" />sians do, not Mongols, but men of Turk family, Bokhars, and Tashkandis, &#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>information respecting the tracts of Inner Asia adjoining their country.<lb break="yes"/>Travels to Toorfan, Aksu, Khoten, Yarkand, and Cashmer are very rare; but<lb break="yes"/>Cashgar, the country between the Alta&#x00EF; and the northern slope of the Celestial<lb break="yes" />Mountains (<hi rendition="#i">T&#x00EB;en-shan</hi>), where Choogulchak,<note place="foot" n="*">A frontier station established by the Chinese in 1767. This town has ramparts of earth; the magis-<lb break="no"/>trates and inspectors of the frontier reside here. The garrison consists of 1,000 Chinese soldiers and<lb break="yes"/>1,800 Manchoos or Mongols. The Chinese are permanently placed there; they constitute a military<lb break="yes" />colony, and are obliged to cultivate the earth for their subsistence. The Manchoos and Mongols are<lb break="yes"/>sent from Ele, and are relleved every year.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Klaproth.</hi>
                    </note> Korgos, and Gulja, or Kura,<lb break="yes"/>are situated, the Khanat of Kokand, Bokhara, Tashkand, and Shersaves, to<lb break="yes"/>the south of Samarkand, are frequently visited. At Orenburg, where cara-<lb break="no"/>vans of some thousand camels arrive annually, and where the exchange is<lb break="yes"/>crowded with different nations, M. de Gens, a well-informed man, has been<lb break="yes"/>collecting, with care, for the last twenty years, a mass of very important materials<lb break="yes"/>relating to the geography of Inner Asia. Amongst the numerous itineraries,<lb break="yes"/>which M. de Gens communicated to me, I found the following remark: &#x201C;in<lb break="yes" />proceeding from Semipolatinsk to Yarkand, when we reached lake Ala-kul, or<lb break="yes"/>Ala-dinghis, a little to the north-east of the great lake Balkashi (the Palcati-<lb break="no"/>nor of D&#x2019;Anville), which receives the waters of the Ele, we saw a very lofty<lb break="yes"/>mountain, which formerly emitted fire. Even at the present day, this moun-<lb break="no"/>tain, which raises itself in the lake like a little island, occasions violent tem-<lb break="no"/>pests, which annoy the caravans; wherefore a few sheep are sacrificed, in<lb break="yes"/>passing, to this ancient volcano.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This fact, taken from the mouth of a Tatar traveller, at the beginning of the<lb break="yes"/>present century, excited in me the more interest, since it recalled to my mind<lb break="yes"/>the burning mountains of Central Asia, which we have become acquainted<lb break="yes"/>with from the learned researches of M. M. Rémusat and Klaproth in Chinese<lb break="yes"/>works, and the position of which, at so great a distance from the sea, has<lb break="yes"/>caused so much astonishment. Shortly before my departure from St. Peters-<lb break="no"/>burgh, I received, by the great politeness of M. de Klosterman, the following<lb break="yes"/>information, which he had procured from Bokhars and Tashkandis:&#x2014;&#x201C; the<lb break="yes"/>distance from Semipolatinsk to Gulja is twenty-five days: the route is by<lb break="yes"/>mounts Alashan and Kondegatay (in the steppe of the Kirghiz of the middle<lb break="yes"/>horde), the borders of lake Savande-kul, the Tarbagatay mountains in Zunga-<lb break="no"/>ria and the river Emyl: when it is traversed, the road unites to that which<lb break="yes"/>leads from Choogulchak to the province of Ele. From the banks of the Emyl<lb break="yes"/>to lake Ala-kul, the distance is sixty versts. The Tatars estimate the distance<lb break="yes"/>of this lake from Semipolatinsk at 455 versts. It is on the right, and its ex-<lb break="no"/>tent is 100 versts from east to west. In the midst of this lake rises a very<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="150" facs="#f0002"/> high mountain, called Aral-toobeh. From thence to the Chinese station be-<lb break="no"/>tween the small lake Yanalashe-kul and the river Baratara,<note place="foot" n="*">The name of this river is Boro-tala-gol; it flows, not from east to west, but from west to east; and<lb break="yes"/>it empties itself not into the Alak-tugul-noor, but into the Khaltar-usike-noor.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Klaproth.</hi>
                    </note> on the banks of<lb break="yes"/>which Kalmuks dwell, it is reckoned fifty-five versts.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Comparing the itinerary of Orenburg with that of Semipolatinsk, there re-<lb break="no"/>mained no doubt that the mountain which, according to the tradition of the<lb break="yes"/>natives, consequently in historical times, emitted fire, was the conical isle of<lb break="yes"/>Araltoobeh. As the most important point in these statements concerned the<lb break="yes"/>geographical position of the isle, and its relative situation in respect to the<lb break="yes"/>volcanos discovered by Messrs. Rémusat and Klaproth, in very ancient<lb break="yes"/>Chinese books, as then existing in the interior of Asia, to the north and south<lb break="yes"/>of mount T&#x00EB;en-shan, it will not be out of place to insert here some details<lb break="yes"/>respecting the geography of this region.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The central and interior portion of Asia, which forms neither an immense<lb break="yes"/>cluster of mountains nor a continued table-land, is crossed from east to west<lb break="yes"/>by four grand systems of mountains, which have manifestly influenced the<lb break="yes"/>movements of the population; these are, the Alta&#x00EF;, which is terminated to<lb break="yes"/>the west by the mountains of the Kirghiz; the T&#x00EB;en-shan, the Kwan-lun, and<lb break="yes" />the Himalaya chain. Between the Alta&#x00EF; and the T&#x00EB;en-shan, are placed Zunga-<lb break="no"/>ria and the basin of the Ele; between the T&#x00EB;en-shan and the Kwan-lun, Little<lb break="yes"/>or rather Upper Bucharia, or Cashgar, Yarkand, Khoten, the great desert of<lb break="yes"/>Gobi (or Cha-mo), Toorfan, Khamil (Hami), and Tangout, that is, the<lb break="yes" />northern Tangout of the Chinese, which must not be confounded with Tibet,<lb break="yes"/>or Se-fan; lastly, between the Kwan-lun and the Himalaya, Eastern and<lb break="yes"/>Western Tibet, where H&#x2019;lassa and Ladak are situated.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>1. <hi rendition="#i">The system of the Alta&#x00EF;</hi> encompasses the sources of the Irtish, and of<lb break="yes"/>the Yenisse&#x00EF; or Kem; to the east, it takes the name of Tangnu; that of the<lb break="yes"/>Sayanian mountains between lakes Kossogol and Baikal; farther on, that of<lb break="yes"/>the lofty Kenta&#x00EF; and the mountains of Dauria; lastly, to the north-east, it<lb break="yes"/>joins the Yablonnoy-khrebet, the Khingkhan and the Aldan mountains, which<lb break="yes"/>stretch along the sea of Okhotsk. The mean latitude of its course from east to west<lb break="yes"/>is between 50° and 51° 30&#x2032;. We shall soon have satisfactory notions respect-<lb break="no"/>ing the geography of the north-eastern part of this system, between the Baikal,<lb break="yes"/>Yakutsk, and Okotsk, for which the world will be indebted to Dr. Erdman,<lb break="yes"/>who has recently traversed those parts. The Alta&#x00EF;, properly so called, scarcely<lb break="yes"/>occupies seven degrees of longitude; but we give to the northernmost portion<lb break="yes"/>of the mountains encompassing the vast mass of high land of Inner Asia, and<lb break="yes"/>occupying the space comprised between the 48th and 51st parallels, the<lb break="yes"/>name of the <hi rendition="#i">System of the Alta&#x00EF;,</hi> because simple names are more easily impressed<lb break="yes"/>upon the memory, and because that of Alta&#x00EF; is best known to Europeans from<lb break="yes"/>the great metallic wealth of these mountains, which now annually yield 70,000<lb break="yes"/>marks of silver and 1,900 marks of gold. The Alta&#x00EF;, in Turkish, in Mongol,<lb break="yes" />Alta&#x00EF;-in-oola, &#x201C;gold mountain,&#x201D; is not a chain of mountains, forming the<lb break="yes"/>limit of a country, like the Himalaya, which bounds the table-land of Tibet,<lb break="yes"/>and which consequently lowers itself abruptly only on the side of India, which<lb break="yes"/>is lower than the other country. The plains adjoining lake Za&#x00EF;sang, and espe-<lb break="no"/>cially the steppes near lake Balkashi, are certainly not more than 300 toises<lb break="yes"/>(1968 English feet) above the level of the sea.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I avoid intentionally, in this paper, conformably to the statements I collected<lb break="yes"/>on the spot, employing the term Lesser Alta&#x00EF;, if this term is applied to the<lb break="yes"/>vast mass of mountains situated between the course of the Narym, lake Telet-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="151" facs="#f0003"/> sky, the Bia, Serpent Mountain, and the Irtish above Oustkamenogorsk,<lb break="yes"/>consequently the territory of Russian Siberia, between the 79th and 86th me-<lb break="no"/>ridians east of Paris, and between the parallels of 49° 30&#x2032; and 52° 30&#x2032;. This<lb break="yes" />Little Alta&#x00EF; is probably, owing to its extent and elevation, much more consi-<lb break="no"/>derable than the Great Alta&#x00EF;, whose position and existence, as a chain of<lb break="yes"/>snowy mountains, are, perhaps, equally problematical. Arrowsmith, and se-<lb break="no"/>veral modern geographers, who have followed the model he has arbitrarily<lb break="yes" />adopted, give the name of Great Alta&#x00EF; to an imaginary continuation of the<lb break="yes"/>T&#x00EB;en-shan which is carried to the eastward of Khamil (Hami) and Barkoul<lb break="yes"/>(Chin-se-foo), a Manchoo town, and runs to the north-east, towards the<lb break="yes"/>eastern sources of the Yenisse&#x00EF; and Mount Tangnu. The direction of the line<lb break="yes"/>of separation of the waters, between the affluents of the Orkhon and those of<lb break="yes"/>the Aral-noor, lake of the steppe, and the unfortunate practice of marking by<lb break="yes"/>high chains of mountains where systems of streams separate, have occasioned<lb break="yes"/>this error. If it be desired to retain on our maps the name of Great Alta&#x00EF;, it<lb break="yes"/>should be given to the succession of lofty mountains ranged in a course directly<lb break="yes" />opposite (parallel to the chain of the Khangai),<note place="foot" n="*">Mount Khanggay-ula is to the north of the source of the Orkhon. Its summits are lofty and con-<lb break="no"/>siderable. This chain is a branching off of the Altai, which comes from the north-west: it extends to the<lb break="yes" />eastward to the rivers Orkhon and Tula with their affluents, and becomes the Kenteh of the Khinggan.<lb break="yes"/>A branch of this chain separates to the west and runs to the north under the name of the Kuku-daban;<lb break="yes"/>it encompasses the Upper Selengga and all its affluents, which take their origin in it, and then runs a<lb break="yes"/>distance of 1,000 <hi rendition="#i">le</hi> into the Russian territory. The Orkhon, the Tamir, and their affluents have like-<lb break="no"/>wise their sources in this chain, which is probably the same which the Chinese distinguish by the name<lb break="yes"/>of Yang-jin-shan.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k" >Klaproth.</hi>
                    </note> or from the north-west to<lb break="yes"/>the south-east, between the right bank of the Upper Irtish, and the Yeke-<lb break="no"/>Aral-noor, or Lake of the Great Isle, near Gobdo-Khoto.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There, consequently, to the south of the Narym and of the Bukhtorma,<lb break="yes"/>which bounds what is called the Little-Russian Alta&#x00EF;, was the primitive abode<lb break="yes"/>of the Turk tribes; the place where Dizabul, their grand khan, towards the<lb break="yes"/>close of the sixth century, received an ambassador from the emperor of Con-<lb break="no" />stantinople. This <hi rendition="#i">gold-mountain</hi> of the Turks, the <hi rendition="#i">Kin-shan</hi> of the Chinese,<lb break="yes"/>a name with the same signification, bore heretofore also those of <hi rendition="#i" >Ek-tag,</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Ektel,</hi> both of which probably have an analogous meaning. It is said that<lb break="yes"/>more to the south, under the 46th parallel, and almost in the meridian of Pi-<lb break="no"/>jan and Toorfan, a lofty peak is still called in Mongol <hi rendition="#i">Alta&#x00EF;nniro,</hi> &#x201C;summit of<lb break="yes"/>the Alta&#x00EF;.&#x201D; If some degrees farther to the south, this Great Alta&#x00EF; unites itself<lb break="yes"/>to the Naiman-ula mountains, we there find a transverse ridge which, running<lb break="yes"/>from the north-west to the south-east, joins the Russian Alta&#x00EF; to the T&#x00EB;en-<lb break="no"/>shan, northward of Barkoul and Hami.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">The Chinese (in their <hi rendition="#i">imperial geography of China</hi>), in tracing the direction of the Great Altai from<lb break="yes"/>the north-west to the south-east, makes it almost re-unite itself to the T&#x00EB;en-shan, which corresponds<lb break="yes" />exactly with what M. de Humboldt states.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k" >Klaproth.</hi>
                    </note> This is not the place to develope<lb break="yes"/>how the system of north-western direction so general in our hemisphere is<lb break="yes"/>traced in the beds of the rocks, in the line of the Alps of Alghin, of the<lb break="yes"/>lofty steppe of the Chuya, of the chain of the Jyiktu, which is the culminating<lb break="yes"/>point of the Russian Alta&#x00EF;, and in the hollows of the narrow valleys, where<lb break="yes"/>flow the Chulyshman, the Chuya, the Katunia, and the Upper Charysh;<lb break="yes"/>lastly, in the whole course of the Irtish from Krasnoyarskoi to Tobolsk.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Between the meridians of Oust-Kamenogorsk and of Semipolatinsk, the sys-<lb break="no"/>tem of the Alta&#x00EF; mountains extends from east to west, beneath the parallels<lb break="yes"/>of 59 and 50, by a chain of hills and low mountains, for 160 geographical<lb break="yes"/>leagues, as far as the steppe of the Kirghiz. This range, though of very small<lb break="yes"/>importance in respect to size and elevation, is highly interesting to geognosy.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="152" facs="#f0004"/> There does not exist a continued chain of Kirghiz mountains, which, as the<lb break="yes"/>maps represent, under the names of Alghidin-tsano or Alghidin-chamo, unites<lb break="yes"/>the Ural and the Alta&#x00EF;. Some isolated hills of 500 or 600 feet high, groups<lb break="yes" />of small mountains which, like the Semi-tau near Semipolatinsk, rise abruptly<lb break="yes"/>to the height of 1,000 or 1,200 feet above the plains, deceive the traveller who<lb break="yes"/>is not accustomed to measure the inequality of the soil; but it is not less re-<lb break="no"/>markable that these clusters of hills and small mountains have been raised<lb break="yes" />across a furrow which forms this line of division of the waters between the<lb break="yes"/>affluents of the Saras, or to the south in the steppe, and those of the Irtish<lb break="yes"/>to the north: a fissure which follows uniformly, as far as the meridian of Sve-<lb break="no"/>rinagolovskoy, the same direction for sixteen degrees of longitude.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the line of division of the waters between the Alta&#x00EF; and the Ural, between<lb break="yes"/>the 49th and 50th parallels, is observable an effort of nature, a kind of attempt<lb break="yes"/>of subterranean energy, to force up a chain of mountains; and this fact recalls<lb break="yes"/>powerfully the similar appearances I remarked in the new continent.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But the non-continued range of low mountains and hills of crystallized rocks,<lb break="yes"/>by which the system of the Alta&#x00EF; is prolonged to the west, does not reach the<lb break="yes"/>southern extremity of the Ural, a chain which, like that of the Andes, presents<lb break="yes"/>a long wall running from north to south, with metallic mines on its eastern side:<lb break="yes"/>it terminates abruptly under the meridian of Sverinogovloskoy, where geo-<lb break="no"/>graphers are accustomed to place the Alghinic mountains, the name of which is<lb break="yes"/>entirely unknown by the Kirghiz of Troitsk and of Orenburg.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>II. <hi rendition="#i">System of the T&#x00EB;en-shan.</hi>&#x2014;Their mean latitude is 42°. Their culminating<lb break="yes"/>point is perhaps the mass of mountain remarkable by its three peaks, covered<lb break="yes"/>with eternal snows, and celebrated under the name of Bokhda-ula, or &#x201C;Holy<lb break="yes"/>Mountain,&#x201D; in the Mongol-Calmuc tongue; which has caused Pallas to give to<lb break="yes"/>the whole chain the denomination of Bogdo. From the Bokhda-ula, the<lb break="yes"/>T&#x00EB;en-shan runs easterly towards Barkoul, where, to the north of Hami, it<lb break="yes"/>sinks abruptly, and spreads itself to the level of the high desert called the<lb break="yes"/>Great Gobi, or Shamo, which extends south-west and north-east, from<lb break="yes" />Kwa-chow, a town of China, to the sources of the Argun. Mount Nomkhun,<lb break="yes"/>to the north-west of the Sogok and the Sobo, little lakes of the steppe, de-<lb break="no"/>notes, perhaps, by its position, a slight swell, an angle in the desert; for<lb break="yes"/>after an interruption of at least ten degrees of longitude, there appears, a little<lb break="yes"/>more to the south than the T&#x00EB;en-shan, in my opinion, as a continuation of<lb break="yes"/>this system, at the great bend of the Hwang-ho, or Yellow River, the snowy<lb break="yes"/>chain of the Gajar, or Yn-shan, which runs likewise from west to east, under<lb break="yes"/>the parallels of 41 and 42, consequently to the north of the country of Ordos.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Let us now return to the neighbourhood of Toorfan and the Bokhda-ula, and<lb break="yes"/>follow the western prolongation of the second system of mountains; we shall<lb break="yes"/>perceive that it extends between Gulja (Ele), the place whither the Chinese<lb break="yes"/>government exiles criminals, and Kucha; then between Temoortu, a large<lb break="yes"/>lake, the name of which signifies &#x201C;ferruginous water,&#x201D; and Aksu, to the<lb break="yes"/>north of Cashgar, and runs towards Samarkand. The country comprised be-<lb break="no"/>tween the first and second systems of mountains, or between the Alta&#x00EF; and the<lb break="yes"/>T&#x00EB;en-shan, is closed on the east, beyond the meridian of Peking, by the<lb break="yes"/>Khingkhan-ula, a mountainous crest which runs S.S.W. and N.N.E.; but to<lb break="yes"/>the west, it is entirely open on the side of the Chwei, the Sarasu and the<lb break="yes" />Lower Sihoon. In this part there is no transverse ridge, provided, at least,<lb break="yes"/>we do not regard as such the series of elevations which extend, north and<lb break="yes"/>south, to the west of lake Zaisang, across the Targabatay, as far as the north-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="153" facs="#f0005"/> eastern extremity of the Ala-tau,<note place="foot" n="*">This is a name which has occasioned much confusion. The Kirghis, particularly those of the grand<lb break="yes"/>horde, give the title of Ala-tagh (<hi rendition="#i">Alatau,</hi> &#x201C;speckled <choice><sic>monntains</sic><corr type="editorial">mountains</corr></choice>&#x201D;) to a series of elevations extending<lb break="yes"/>from west to east, under the parallels of 43° 30&#x2032; to 45°, from the Upper Sihoon (Syr-daria or Jaxartes),<lb break="yes"/>near Tonkat, towards lakes Balkashi and Temoortu. The eastern portion of the Ala-tau rises consider-<lb break="no"/>ably at the great sinuosity made by the Sihoon to the north-west, and connects with the Kara-tau<lb break="yes"/>(&#x201C;Black Mountain&#x201D;) at Taras or Turkestan. The natives likewise give the name of Ala-tau to the<lb break="yes"/>mountains to the south of the Tarbagatay between lakes Ala-kul, Balkashi, and Temoortu. Is it from<lb break="yes" />these denominations that geographers have been in the habit of calling the whole second system of<lb break="yes"/>mountains that of T&#x00EB;en-shan, Alak or Ala-tau? The Oolug-tagh, or &#x201C;Great Mountain,&#x201D; named on<lb break="yes"/>some maps Oulug-tag Oolu-tau, and Ooluk-tagh, must not be confounded with the Ala-tau or Ala-taghi.</note> between lakes Balkash and Alak-tugul-<lb break="no"/>noor, and then beyond the course of the Ele, to the eastward of the Temoor-<lb break="no"/>tu-nor (between lat. 44° and 49°), and which present the appearance of a<lb break="yes"/>wall occasionally interrupted on the side of the Kirghiz steppe.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is quite otherwise with the portion of Central Asia, which is bounded by<lb break="yes"/>the second and third systems of mountains, the Himalaya and Kwan-lun. In<lb break="yes"/>fact, it is closed to the west in a very evident manner by a transverse ridge,<lb break="yes"/>which is prolonged from south to north, under the name of Bolor or Beloor-<lb break="no"/>tagh.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">According to M. Klaproth, this transversal ridge is named in Ouigoor <hi rendition="#i">Boolyt-tagh,</hi> &#x201C;Cloudy<lb break="yes" />Mountain,&#x201D; on account of the extraordinary rains which fall uninterruptedly in this latitude, during<lb break="yes"/>three months. West of this transverse ridge of Beloor, is the station of Pamir, nearly under the pa-<lb break="no"/>rallel of Cashgar. Marco Polo has named, after this station, a table-land of which modern geographers<lb break="yes"/>have made sometimes a chain of mountains, sometimes a province situated farther to the south. This<lb break="yes"/>district is still interesting to the naturalist, on account of the celebrated Venetian traveller having first<lb break="yes" />observed there a fact, which has so often occurred in my experience, at considerable elevations, in the<lb break="yes"/>New World, namely, that it is extremely difficult to light and to keep fire in there.</note> This chain separates Little from Great Bucharia, and from Cashgar,<lb break="yes" />Badakshan, and the Upper Jihoon or Amoodaria. Its southern portion, which<lb break="yes"/>connects with the system of the Kwan-lun mountains, forms, according to the<lb break="yes"/>denomination used by the Chinese, a part of the Tsung-ling. To the north, it<lb break="yes"/>joins the chain which passes to the north-west of Cashgar, and bears the name<lb break="yes"/>of the defile of Cashgar (<hi rendition="#i">Cashgar-divan,</hi> or <hi rendition="#i" >davan</hi>), according to the narrative<lb break="yes"/>of Nasaroff, who, in 1813, travelled as far as Kokand. Between Kokand,<lb break="yes"/>Dervazeh, and Hissa, consequently between the still unknown sources of the<lb break="yes" />Sihoon and Amoo-daria, the T&#x00EB;en-shan rises previous to sinking again in the<lb break="yes"/>Khanat of Bokhara, and presents a group of lofty mountains, several summits<lb break="yes"/>of which, such as the Takt-i-Suleyman, the crest called Terek and others, are<lb break="yes"/>covered with snow even in summer. Farther to the east, on the road which<lb break="yes" />runs from the western bank of lake Temoortu to Cashgar, the T&#x00EB;en-shan does<lb break="yes"/>not appear to me to attain so great an elevation; at least no mention is made<lb break="yes"/>of snow in the itinerary from Semipolatinsk to Cashgar. The road passes to<lb break="yes"/>the eastward of lake Balkashi, and to the westward of lake Yssi-kul or Temoor-<lb break="no" />tu, and traverses the Narun or Narym, an affluent of the Sihoon. At 105<lb break="yes"/>versts to the south of the Narun, it goes over Mount Rovatt, which is pretty<lb break="yes"/>high, and about fifteen versts wide; it has a large cavern, and is situated be-<lb break="no"/>tween the At-bash, a small river, and the little lake of Chater-kul. This is the<lb break="yes" />culminating point previous to arriving at the Chinese post placed to the south of<lb break="yes"/>the Aksu, a small river of the steppe, the village of Artush and Cashgar.<lb break="yes"/>This city, built on the banks of the Aratumen, contains 15,000 houses and<lb break="yes"/>80,000 inhabitants, but is yet smaller than Samarkand. The Cashgar-<lb break="no"/>davan <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">The terms <hi rendition="#i">davan,</hi> in Oriental-Turki, <hi rendition="#i">dabahn,</hi> in Mongol, and <hi rendition="#i" >dabagan,</hi> in Manchoo, denote not a<lb break="yes"/>mountain, but a pass in a mountain; <hi rendition="#i">Cashgar-davan,</hi> therefore, signifies only the pass across the moun-<lb break="no"/>tains to Cashgar.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Klaproth.</hi>
                    </note> does not appear to form a continuous wall, but to offer an open pas-<lb break="no"/>sage at several points. M. Gens expressed to me his surprise that none of the<lb break="yes"/>numerous itineraries of Bokharians which he has collected, make mention of<lb break="yes"/>a lofty chain of mountains between Kokand and Cashgar. The great snowy<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="154" facs="#f0006"/>
                    
                    <lb break="yes"/>mountains seem not to re-appear till east of the meridian of Aksu, for<lb break="yes"/>these same itineraries mention Jeparleh,<note place="foot" n="*">This is the Moosar-tag, or glacier between Ele and Kucha. The ice with which it is sheeted gives<lb break="yes"/>it the appearance of a mass of silver. A road, called <hi rendition="#i">Mussar-dabahn,</hi> cut through these glaciers, leads<lb break="yes"/>from the S. W. to the N. or, to, speak more accurately, from Little Bucharia to Ele. The following is<lb break="yes"/>a description of this mountain by a modern Chinese geographer: &#x201C;to the north is the post-station of<lb break="yes" />Gakhtsa-karkai, and to the south that of Tamga-tash, or Terma Khada; they are distant from each<lb break="yes"/>other 120 <hi rendition="#i">le.</hi> On proceeding to the south, after quitting the former, the view extends over a vast space<lb break="yes"/>covered with snow, which, in winter, is very deep. In summer, on the top of the ice, snow and<lb break="yes"/>marshy places are found. Men and cattle follow the winding paths at the side of the mountain. Who-<lb break="no"/>ever is so imprudent as to venture upon this sea of snow is irrecoverably lost. After traversing upwards of<lb break="yes"/>twenty <hi rendition="#i">le,</hi> you reach the glacier, where neither sand, trees, nor grass can be seen: the most terrifying<lb break="yes"/>objects are the gigantic rocks formed into one by masses heaped upon one another. When the eye<lb break="yes"/>dwells upon the intervals which separate these masses of ice, a gloomy chasm appears, into which the<lb break="yes"/>light never penetrates. The sound of the water rushing beneath the ice resembles the report of thunder.<lb break="yes" />Carcasses of camels and horses are scattered here and there. In order to facilitate the passage, steps<lb break="yes"/>have been cut in the ice, to ascend and descend, but they are so slippery that they are extremely danger-<lb break="no"/>ous. Too frequently travellers find their grave in these precipices. Men and cattle walk in file, trem-<lb break="no"/>bling with alarm, in these inhospitable tracts. If night surprises the traveller, he must seek shelter<lb break="yes"/>under a large stone; if the night happen to be calm, very pleasing sounds are heard, like those of seve-<lb break="no"/>ral instruments combined: it is the echo which repeats the cracking noise produced by the breaking ice.<lb break="yes"/>The road, which is pursued the day before, is not always that which it is convenient to follow the next<lb break="yes"/>day. At a distance, to the west, a mountain, which has been hitherto inaccessible, displays its scarped<lb break="yes" />and icy summits. The halting-place of Tamga-tash is eighty <hi rendition="#i">le</hi> from this place. A river, called Moos-<lb break="no"/>sur Gol, rushes with frightful impetuosity from the edges of the ice, flows to the south-east, and joins<lb break="yes"/>the Erghew, which falls into lake Lob. Four days&#x2019; journey to the south of Tamga-tash, is an arid<lb break="yes"/>plain, which does not produce the smallest plant. At eighty or ninety <hi rendition="#i">le</hi> further off, gigantic rocks<lb break="yes"/>still recur. The commandant of Ushi sends every year one of his officers with oblations to this glacier.<lb break="yes"/>The formula of the prayer recited on this occasion is transmitted from Peking by the Tribunal of Rites.<lb break="yes"/>Ice is found along the whole crest of the T&#x00EB;en-shan, if it is traversed lengthwise; but, on the contrary,<lb break="yes"/>if it is crossed from north to south, that is in its width, ice is found only in a space of a few <hi rendition="#i">le.</hi> Every<lb break="yes"/>morning, ten men are employed, in the pass of Mussar-tag, in cutting steps for ascending and descend-<lb break="no"/>ing; in the afternoon, the sun has either melted them or rendered them extremely slippery. Sometimes<lb break="yes"/>the ice gives way under the feet of the travellers, and they are ingulphed, without a hope of ever seeing<lb break="yes"/>day-light again. The Mohamedans of Little Bucharia sacrifice a ram previous to traversing these moun-<lb break="no"/>tains. Snow falls there throughout the year: it never rains.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Klaproth.</hi>
                    </note> a glacier covered with perpetual snow,<lb break="yes"/>on the Kura road, on the banks of the Ele at Aksu, nearly half-way, between<lb break="yes"/>the warm springs of Arashan to the north of Kanjeilao, a Chinese station, and<lb break="yes"/>the advanced post of Tamga-tash.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The western prolongation of the T&#x00EB;en-shan or Mooz-tag, as the editors of<lb break="yes"/>the Memoirs of Sultan Baber call it by pre-eminence, deserves a particular<lb break="yes"/>notice. At the point where the Beloor-tag joins the right angle of the Mooz-tag,<lb break="yes"/>or traverses as a lode or vein this great system, the latter continues its course<lb break="yes"/>without interruption from east to west, under the denomination of Asferah-tag,<lb break="yes"/>to the south of the Sihon, towards Khojand and Urateppeh, in Ferghana. This<lb break="yes"/>chain of Asferah, which is covered with perpetual snow, and is improperly<lb break="yes"/>called the chain of Pamer, separates the sources of the Sihon (Jaxartes) from<lb break="yes"/>those of the Amoo (Oxus); it turns to the south-west, nearly in the meridian<lb break="yes"/>of Khojand, and in this direction is called, as far as near Samarkand, Ak-tag<lb break="yes" />(&#x201C;White or Snowy Mountain&#x201D;), or Al-botom. Farther to the west, on the<lb break="yes"/>smiling and fertile banks of the Kohik, commences the great dip or depression<lb break="yes"/>of land, comprehending Great Bucharia, the country of Maveralnahar, which is<lb break="yes"/>so low, and where the highly-cultivated soil and the wealth of the towns attract<lb break="yes" />periodically the invasions of the people of Iran, Candahar, and Upper Mon-<lb break="no"/>golia; but beyond the Caspian Sea, nearly in the same latitude, and in the<lb break="yes"/>same direction as the T&#x00EB;en-shan, appears the Caucasus, with its porphyritic and<lb break="yes"/>trachytic rocks. One is inclined, therefore, to regard it as a continuation of<lb break="yes"/>the furrow, in the form of a lode, on which the T&#x00EB;en-shan rises in the east,<lb break="yes"/>just as, to the west of the great cluster of the mountains of Azerbaijan and<lb break="yes"/>Armenia, is observable, in Taurus, a continuation of the action of the fissure<lb break="yes"/>of the Himalaya and the Hindu Coosh. It is thus that, in a geognostic sense,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="155" facs="#f0007"/> the disjointed members of the mountains of Western Asia, as Mr. Ritter calls<lb break="yes"/>them, connect themselves with the forms of the land in the east.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>III. <hi rendition="#i">The System of the Kwan-lun,</hi> or Koolkun, or Tartash-davan, enters<lb break="yes"/>Khoten (Elechi),<note place="foot" n="*" >The position of Khoten is very incorrectly laid down in all the maps. Its latitude, according to the<lb break="yes"/>astronomical observations of the Missionaries Felix d&#x2019;Arocha, Espinha, and Hallerstein, is 37° 0<choice><sic>&#x2035;</sic><corr type="editorial">&#x2032;</corr></choice>; the<lb break="yes"/>longitude 35° 52&#x2032; W. of Peking. This longitude determines the mean direction of the Kwan-lun.</note> where Hindu civilization and the worship of Buddha pene-<lb break="no"/>trated 500 years before it reached Tibet and Ladak, between the cluster of<lb break="yes" />mountains of Kookoo-noor and Eastern Tibet, and the country called Kachi.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This system of mountains commences westward of the Tsung-ling (&#x201C;Onion or<lb break="yes"/>Blue Mountains&#x201D;), upon which M. Abel Rémusat has diffused so much light in<lb break="yes"/>his learned <hi rendition="#i">History of Khoten.</hi> This system connects itself, as already ob-<lb break="no" />served, with the transverse chain of Bolor; and, according to the Chinese<lb break="yes"/>books, forms the southern portion of it. This quarter of the globe, between<lb break="yes"/>Little Tibet and Badakshan, abounding in rubies, lazulite, and turquoise, <choice><sic>i</sic><corr type="editorial">is</corr></choice><lb break="yes"/>very little known; and, according to recent accounts, the table-land of Kho-<lb break="no"/>rasan, which runs towards Herat, and bounds the Hindu-Kho or Hindu-<lb break="no"/>Coosh, to the north, appears to be a continuation of the system of the Kwan-<lb break="no"/>lun to the west, rather than a prolongation of the Himalaya, as commonly<lb break="yes" />supposed. From the Tsung-ling, the Kwan-lun or Koolkun runs from west<lb break="yes"/>to east, towards the sources of the Hwang-ho (Yellow River), and penetrates,<lb break="yes"/>with its snowy peaks, into the Chinese province of Shen-se. Nearly in the<lb break="yes"/>meridian of these sources, rises the great cluster of mountains of lake Koo-<lb break="no"/>koo-noor, a cluster which supports itself, on the north, against the snowy<lb break="yes"/>chain of the Nan-shan, or Ki-lian-shan, extending also from west to east. Be-<lb break="no" />tween the Nan-shan and the T&#x00EB;en-shan, on the side of Hami, the mountains of<lb break="yes"/>Tangout bound the edge of the high desert of Gobi or Shamo, which stretches<lb break="yes"/>from south-west to north-east. The latitude of the middle portion of the<lb break="yes"/>Kwan-lun is about 35° 30&#x2032;.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>IV. <hi rendition="#i">System of the Himalaya.</hi>&#x2014;This separates the valleys of Cashmer (Seri-<lb break="no"/>nagur) and Nepal from Butan and Tibet; to the west, it stretches, by Jevahir,<lb break="yes"/>to 4,026 toises (26,420 feet); to the east, by Dhavalaghiri, to 4,390 (28,809<lb break="yes"/>feet) of actual height above the level of the sea; it runs generally in a direction<lb break="yes"/>from N.W. to S.E., and consequently is not parallel with the Kwan-lun; it<lb break="yes"/>approaches it so nearly, in the meridian of Attock and Jellalabad, that between<lb break="yes"/>Cabul, Cashmer, Ladak, and Badakshan, the Himalaya seems to form only a<lb break="yes"/>single mass of mountains with the Hindu-Kho and the Tsung-ling. In like<lb break="yes"/>manner, the space between the Himalaya and the Kwan-lun is more shut up<lb break="yes" />with secondary chains and isolated masses of mountains, than the table-lands<lb break="yes"/>between the first, second, and third systems of mountains. Consequently, Tibet<lb break="yes"/>and Kachi cannot properly be compared, in respect to their geognostic con-<lb break="no"/>struction, with the elevated longitudinal valleys,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">In the Andes, I found that the mean height of the longitudinal valley between the Eastern and<lb break="yes"/>Western Cordilleras, from the cluster of mountains of Los Robles, near Popayan, to that of Pasco,<lb break="yes"/>as well as those in 2° 20&#x2032; N. lat. to 10° 30<choice><sic>&#x2035;</sic><corr type="editorial">&#x2032;</corr></choice> S. lat., was about 1,500 toises (9,843 feet). The table-land, or<lb break="yes"/>rather longitudinal valley, of Tiahuanaco, along the Lake of Titicaca, the primitive seat of Peruvian<lb break="yes"/>civilization, is more elevated than the Peak of Teneriffe. However, according to my experience, it<lb break="yes"/>cannot be asserted generally that the absolute height to which the soil of the longitudinal valleys appears<lb break="yes"/>to have been raised by subterranean force, augments with the absolute height of the neighbouring<lb break="yes"/>chains. In like manner, the elevation of isolated chains above the vallies is very various, showing that<lb break="yes"/>at the foot of the chain the raised plain is elevated at the same time, or has preserved its ancient level.</note> situated between the chain<lb break="yes"/>of the eastern and western Andes, for example, with the table-land which en-<lb break="no"/>closes the lake of Titicaca, a correct observer of which (Mr. Pentland) found<lb break="yes"/>that its elevation above the sea was 1,986 toises (13,033 feet). Nevertheless,<lb break="yes"/>it must not be represented that the height of the table-land between the Kwan-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="156" facs="#f0008"/> lun and the Himalaya, as well as in all the rest of Central Asia, is equal<lb break="yes"/>throughout. The mildness of the winters, and the cultivation of the vine,<note place="foot" n="*">The cultivation of plants, whose vegetable life is almost limited to the duration of summer, and<lb break="yes"/>which, despoiled of leaves, remain buried during winter, may be accounted for by the influence which<lb break="yes"/>vast table-lands exert upon the radiation of heat; but it is not the same with the slightest rigour of<lb break="yes"/>winters, when we refer to elevations of 1,800 to 2,000 toises (11,812 to 13,125 feet) at six degrees to the<lb break="yes"/>north of the equinoctial zone.</note> in<lb break="yes" />the gardens of H&#x2019;lassa, in the parallel of 29° 40&#x2032;,&#x2014;facts ascertained by the ac-<lb break="no"/>counts published by M. Klaproth and the Archimandrite Hyacinth,&#x2014;proclaim<lb break="yes"/>the existence of deep valleys and circular hollows. Two considerable rivers,<lb break="yes"/>the Indus and the Zzambo (Sampoo),<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">The researches of M. Klaproth have proved that this river, which is entirely separated from the<lb break="yes"/>system of the Brahmaputra, is identical with the Irrawaddy of the Burmese empire.</note> denote a depression in the table-land<lb break="yes"/>of Tibet, to the north-west and south-east, the axis of which is found nearly<lb break="yes"/>in the meridian of the gigantic Javahir, the two sacred lakes of Manassora-<lb break="no"/>vara and Ravana Hrada, and Mount Ca&#x00EF;lasa, or Ca&#x00EF;las, in Chinese O-new-ta,<lb break="yes"/>and in Tibetan Gang-dis-ri. From this nucleus springs the chain of Kara-ko-<lb break="no"/>rum-padisha, which runs to the north-west, consequently to the north of La-<lb break="no"/>dak, towards the Tsung-ling; and the snowy chains of Hor (Khor) and Zzang,<lb break="yes"/>which run to the east. That of Hor, at its north-western extremity, connects<lb break="yes"/>itself with the Kwan-lun; its course, from the eastern side, is towards the<lb break="yes"/>Tangri-noor (&#x201C;Lake of Heaven&#x201D;). The Zzang, farther to the south than the<lb break="yes"/>chain of Hor, bounds the long valley of the Zzangbo, and runs from west<lb break="yes"/>to east, towards the N&#x00EB;en-tsin-tangla-gangri, a very lofty summit which,<lb break="yes"/>between H&#x2019;lassa and lake Tangri-noor (improperly called Terkiri), terminates<lb break="yes"/>at Mount Nom-shun-ubashi. Between the meridians of Ghorka, Katmandu,<lb break="yes"/>and H&#x2019;lassa, the Himalaya sends out to the north, towards the right bank, or<lb break="yes"/>the southern border of the valley, of the Zzang-bo, several branches covered<lb break="yes"/>with perpetual snow. The highest is Yarla-shamboy-gangri, the name of which,<lb break="yes"/>in Tibetan, signifies &#x201C;the snowy mountain in the country of the self-existing<lb break="yes" />deity.&#x201D; This peak is to the westward of lake Yamruk-yumdzo, which our<lb break="yes"/>maps call Palteh,<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">There can be no doubt that <hi rendition="#i">Palteh</hi> is derived from <hi rendition="#i">Bhaldi,</hi> the Tibetan name of a town a little to<lb break="yes"/>the north, which has been corrupted by the Chinese into <hi rendition="#i">Pe&#x00EF;ti</hi> or <hi rendition="#i" >Peti.</hi>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Klaproth.</hi>
                    </note> and which resembles a ring, being almost filled by an island.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If, availing ourselves of the Chinese writings which M. Klaproth has collect-<lb break="no"/>ed, we follow the system of the Himalaya towards the east, beyond the Eng-<lb break="no"/>lish territories in Hindustan, we perceive that it bounds Assam to the north,<lb break="yes"/>contains the sources of the Brahmaputra, passes through the northern part of<lb break="yes"/>Ava, and penetrates into the Chinese province of Yun-nan, where, to the<lb break="yes" />westward of Yung-chang, it exhibits sharp and snowy peaks; it turns abruptly<lb break="yes"/>to the north-east on the confines of Ho-kwang, of Keang-si, and of Fuh-kien,<lb break="yes"/>and extends, with its snowy summits near to the ocean, where we find, as if it<lb break="yes"/>was a prolongation of this chain, an island (Formosa), the mountains of which<lb break="yes"/>are covered with snow during the greatest part of the summer, which shows<lb break="yes"/>an elevation of at least 1,900 toises (12,469 feet). Thus we may follow the<lb break="yes"/>system of the Himalaya, as a continuous chain, from the Eastern Ocean, and<lb break="yes"/>track it by the Hindu-Coosh, across Candahar and Khorasan; and lastly as far<lb break="yes"/>as the Caspian Sea in Azerbaijan, through an extent of seventy-three degrees<lb break="yes"/>of longitude, half that of the Andes. The western extremity, which is vol-<lb break="no"/>canic, but covered likewise with snow to Demavend, loses the peculiar charac-<lb break="no"/>ter of a chain in the cluster of the mountains of Armenia, connected with the<lb break="yes"/>Sangalu, the Bingheul, and Cashmer-dag, lofty summits in the pashalic of Er-<lb break="no"/>zeroum. The mean direction of the system of the Himalaya is N. 55° W.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">(<hi rendition="#i">To be concluded next Month.</hi>)</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <pb n="232" facs="#f0009"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>ON THE CHAINS OF MOUNTAINS AND VOLCANOS OF<lb break="yes"/>CENTRAL ASIA.<note place="foot" n="*">Concluded from p. 156.</note>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#k">by baron a. von humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> aforegoing are the principal features of a geognostic description of<lb break="yes"/>Central Asia, which I have drawn up with the aid of numerous materials ac-<lb break="no"/>cumulated by me during a long series of years. Of these materials, the por-<lb break="no"/>tion for which we are indebted to modern European travellers is of small impor-<lb break="no" />tance, in comparison with the prodigious space which is occupied by the chain<lb break="yes"/>of the Alta&#x00EF;, the Himalaya mountains, the transverse ridges of the Bolor and<lb break="yes"/>the Kingkan. Those who, at the present day, have published the most im-<lb break="no"/>portant and complete details on these subjects are the learned persons who<lb break="yes"/>are conversant with Chinese, Manchoo, and Mongol literature. The more<lb break="yes" />general the cultivation of the Asiatic dialects shall become, the better shall we<lb break="yes"/>appreciate the utility of these so-long-neglected sources, for the study of the<lb break="yes"/>geognostic constitution of Middle Asia. Until M. Klaproth diffuses a new<lb break="yes"/>light upon this study by a special work of his own, the picture which I have<lb break="yes"/>here exhibited of the four systems of mountains which run from east to west,<lb break="yes"/>the materials for which were, in a great part, furnished by the learned person<lb break="yes"/>whom I have just named, will not be without its use. In order to ascertain<lb break="yes"/>the characteristic properties which are to be found in the inequalities of the<lb break="yes"/>globe&#x2019;s surface, and to discover the laws which regulate the local disposition<lb break="yes"/>of the masses of mountains, and the dips or depressions, we may have recourse<lb break="yes"/>to the analogy which other continents may offer. If once the grand forms and<lb break="yes"/>predominating courses of the chains are well determined, we shall see con-<lb break="no"/>nected with this fundamental principle, as with a common type, whatever ap-<lb break="no"/>peared at first isolated in these phenomena, and at variance with rules, pro-<lb break="no"/>claiming another date of formation. This method, which I followed in my<lb break="yes"/>geognostic description of South America, I have endeavoured to apply here<lb break="yes"/>to the limits of the grand masses of Middle Asia.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In bestowing a parting glance upon the four systems of mountains which<lb break="yes"/>divide the continent of Asia from east to west, we observe that the southern<lb break="yes"/>has the greatest extent, and the fullest developement in respect of length.<lb break="yes"/>The Alta&#x00EF; hardly attains, with its elevated summits, the 78th degree; the<lb break="yes" />T&#x00EB;en-shan, the chain at whose foot are situated Hami, Aksu, and Cashgar,<lb break="yes"/>reaches at least to the meridian of 69° 45&#x2032;; provided we place Cashgar, ac-<lb break="no"/>cording to the authority of the missionaries, in 71° 37&#x2032; east of Paris.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;" >The astronomical geography of Inner Asia is still very confused, because the elements of the obser-<lb break="no"/>vations are not known, merely the results.</note> The<lb break="yes"/>third and fourth systems are, as it were, blended in the grand clusters of Ba-<lb break="no"/>dakshan, Little Tibet, and Cashgar. Beyond the 69th and 70th meridians<lb break="yes"/>there is but one chain, that of the Hindu-Kho, which is depressed towards<lb break="yes"/>Herat, but which afterwards, to the southward of Asterabad, rises to a con-<lb break="no"/>siderable height towards the volcanic and snowy mountain of Demavend.<lb break="yes"/>The table-land of Iran, which, in its greatest extension, from Tehran to Shi-<lb break="no"/>raz, appears to attain the average height of 650 toises (4,265 feet), throws off,<lb break="yes"/>towards India and Tibet, two branches, the Himalaya and the Kwan-lun<lb break="yes"/>chain, and forms a bifurcation of the furrow from which the mountainous<lb break="yes" />masses rise. Thus the Kwan-lun may be considered as a saliant fracture of<lb break="yes"/>the Himalaya. The intermediate space, comprising Tibet and Kachi, is inter-<lb break="no"/>sected by numerous rents in all directions. This analogy with the most com-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="233" facs="#f0010"/> mon phenomena of the formation of lodes or veins is manifested in a very<lb break="yes"/>striking manner, as I have elsewhere shewn, in the long and narrow line of<lb break="yes"/>the Cordilleras of the New World.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We may trace beyond the Caspian Sea, to the 45th meridian (of Paris), the<lb break="yes"/>systems of the Himalaya and the Kwan-lun, which are prolonged till they join<lb break="yes"/>in the cluster situated between Cashmer and Fyzabad. Thus the chain of the<lb break="yes"/>Himalaya remains to the south of the Bolor, the Ak-tag, the Mingboolak, and<lb break="yes"/>the Ala-tau, between Badakshan, Samerkand, and Turkestan; to the east of<lb break="yes"/>the Caucasus it joins the table-land of Azerbaijan, and bounds to the south the<lb break="yes"/>great dip or valley, of which the Caspian Sea and lake Aral<note place="foot" n="*">A series of barometrical levels continued throughout a very severe winter, during the expedition of<lb break="yes" />Colonel Berg, from the Caspian Sea to the western shore of Lake Aral, at the Bay of Mertvoy Kultuk,<lb break="yes"/>by Captains Duhamel and Anjou, has demonstrated that the level of Lake Aral is 117 English feet<lb break="yes"/>above that of the Caspian Sea.</note> occupies the lowest<lb break="yes"/>basin, and in which a considerable portion of land whose surface is probably<lb break="yes"/>18,000 square leagues, and which lies between the Kooma, the Don, the Vol-<lb break="no"/>ga, the Yak, the Obsheysyrt, lake Aksakal, the Lower Sihon, and the Khanat<lb break="yes"/>of Khiva, upon the shores of the Amoo-daria, is situated below the level of<lb break="yes"/>the ocean. The existence of this singular depression has been the object of<lb break="yes"/>laborious barometrical observations of levels between the Caspian Sea and the<lb break="yes"/>Black Sea, by MM. Parrot and Engelhardt; between Orenburg and Gouriev<lb break="yes"/>at the mouth of the Yayk, by MM. Helmersen and Hoffmann. A country so<lb break="yes"/>low is abundant in tertiary formations, whence proceed garnets, and <hi rendition="#i">debris</hi> of<lb break="yes"/>scorified rocks, and it offers to the geognostic inquirer, from the constitution<lb break="yes"/>of its soil, a phenomenon hitherto unique in our planet. To the south of<lb break="yes"/>Baku, and in the gulf of Balkan, this aspect is materially modified by volcanic<lb break="yes"/>influence. The Academy of Sciences of St. Petersburgh has recently com-<lb break="no"/>plied with my solicitations to get determined by a series of stations of baro-<lb break="no"/>metric levels upon the north-eastern edge of this basin, upon the Volga between<lb break="yes"/>Kamyshin and Saratov, upon the Yayk between the Obsheysyrt, Orenburg,<lb break="yes"/>and the Uralsk, upon the Yemba and beyond the hills of Mougojar, by which<lb break="yes"/>the Ural extends itself towards the south, on the side of lake Aksakal and to-<lb break="no"/>wards Sarasu, the position of a geod&#x0153;sic line, uniting all the points at the<lb break="yes"/>level of the surface of the ocean.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have referred already to the hypothesis, according to which this great dip<lb break="yes"/>of the land of Western Asia was formerly continued as far as the mouth of<lb break="yes"/>the Ob and the Frozen Sea, by a valley traversing the desert of Kara-koum<lb break="yes"/>and the numerous groupes of oases in the steppes of the Kirghiz and Baraba.<lb break="yes"/>Its origin appears to me to be more ancient than that of the Ural mountains,<lb break="yes"/>the southern prolongation of which may be traced in an uninterrupted course<lb break="yes" />from the table-land of Gaberlinsk to Oostoort, between lake Aral and the<lb break="yes"/>Caspian Sea. Would not a chain, whose height is so inconsiderable, have en-<lb break="no"/>tirely disappeared if the great furrow of the Ural had not been formed subse-<lb break="no"/>quently to this depression? Consequently, the period of the sinking of<lb break="yes"/>Western Asia coincides rather with that of the swell of the table-land of Iran,<lb break="yes"/>that of Central Asia, the Himalaya, the Kwan-lun, the T&#x00EB;en-shan, and all the<lb break="yes"/>old systems of mountains running from east to west; perhaps also with the<lb break="yes"/>period of the exaltation of the Caucasus and the cluster of mountains of Ar-<lb break="no" />menia and Erzeroum. No part of the earth, not even excepting South Africa,<lb break="yes"/>presents a mass of land so extensive, and elevated to so great a height, as in<lb break="yes"/>Inner Asia. The principal axis of this exaltation, which probably preceded<lb break="yes"/>the eruption of the chains from the clefts running from east to west, as in the<lb break="yes"/>direction of S. W. and N.E., from the cluster of mountains between Cashmer,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="234" facs="#f0011"/> Badakshan, and the Tsung-ling in Tibet, where are situated the Ca&#x00EF;lasa, and<lb break="yes"/>the sacred lakes,<note place="foot" n="*">The lakes Manasa and Ravan Hrad. <hi rendition="#i" >Manasa,</hi> in Sanscrit, signifies &#x201C;spirit.&#x201D; Manasa-vara is<lb break="yes"/>the easternmost of these two lakes: its name means literally &#x201C;the most perfect of honourable lakes.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>The westernmost lake is named <hi rendition="#i">Ravanah Hrad,</hi> or &#x201C;Lake of Ravana,&#x201D; after the celebrated hero of the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Ramdyana.</hi>
                        <hi rendition="#k">Bopp.</hi>
                    </note> as far as the snowy summits of the Inshan and Khingkan.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">This direction of the axis of exaltation from the S.W. to the N.E. is again found beyond the 55th<lb break="yes"/>degree of latitude, in the space comprized between Western Siberia, a low country, and Eastern Si-<lb break="no"/>beria, a country full of chains of mountains: this space is bounded by the meridian of Irkutsk, the<lb break="yes"/>Frozen Sea, and the Sea of Okotsk. Dr. Erdman has discovered among the Aldan mountains, at<lb break="yes"/>Allakh-yuma, a peak 5,000 feet high. To the north of the Kwan-lun, the chain of Northern Tibet,<lb break="yes"/>and to the west of the meridian of Peking, the portions of elevated land most important in respect to<lb break="yes"/>the extent and height, are the following:&#x2014;1. To the east of the cluster of the Khokhonoor, the space<lb break="yes"/>between Toorfan, Tangout, the great sinuosity of the Hwang-ho, Garjan, and the chain of the Khing-<lb break="no"/>khan, a space which comprehends the great desert of Gobi. 2. The table-land between the snowy<lb break="yes"/>mountains of Khanghay and Tangnu, and between the sources of the Yenise&#x00EF;, the Selengga and the<lb break="yes"/>Amoor. 3. To the west of the district watered by the upper course of the Oxus (Amu), and of the<lb break="yes"/>Jaxartes (Sihoon); between Fyzabad, Balkh, Samarkend and the Ala-tau near Turkestan, to the<lb break="yes"/>westward of the Bolor (Beloot-tag). The elevation of this transverse ridge has produced in the soil of<lb break="yes"/>the great longitudinal valley of the T&#x00EB;en-shan-nar-lu, between the second and third systems of moun-<lb break="no"/>tains from east to west, or between the T&#x00EB;en-shan and the Kwanlun, a counter-slope from west to<lb break="yes"/>east, whilst in the longitudinal valley of the T&#x00EB;enshan-pe-lu in Zungaria, between the T&#x00EB;en-shan and<lb break="yes"/>the Alta&#x00EF;, a general declivity is observable from east to west.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>The elevation of so enormous a mass would suffice to produce a hollow which,<lb break="yes"/>even at the present day, is perhaps not half filled with water, and which, since<lb break="yes"/>it was formed, has been so modified by the action of subterranean forces, that,<lb break="yes"/>according to the traditions of Tatars, collected by Professor Eichwald, the<lb break="yes" />promontory of Absheron was formerly united by an isthmus with the opposite<lb break="yes"/>coast of the Caspian Sea in Turcomania. The great lakes, which have been<lb break="yes"/>formed in Europe at the foot of the Alps, are a phenomenon analogous to the<lb break="yes"/>cavity in which the Caspian Sea is situated, and owe in the same manner their<lb break="yes"/>origin to a sinking of the soil. We shall soon see that it is principally in the<lb break="yes" />compass of this hollow, consequently in the space where the resistance was<lb break="yes"/>least, that recent traces of volcanic action are apparent.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The position of mount Aral-toobeh, which formerly emitted fire, of the<lb break="yes"/>existence of which I became aware from the itineraries of Colonel Gens, be-<lb break="no"/>comes more interesting when we compare it with that of the volcanos of P&#x00EF;h-<lb break="no"/>shan and Ho-chow, on the northern and southern sides of the T&#x00EB;en-shan,<lb break="yes"/>with that of the <hi rendition="#i">solfatara</hi> of Urumtsi, and with that of the adjoining chasm of<lb break="yes"/>lake Darlay, which exhales ammoniacal vapours. The researches of MM.<lb break="yes"/>Klaproth and Rémusat acquainted us with this last fact upwards of six years<lb break="yes"/>ago.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The volcano situated in about the latitude of 42° 25&#x2032; or 42° 35&#x2032;, between<lb break="yes"/>Korgos, on the banks of the Ele, and Kucha, in Little Bucharia, belongs to<lb break="yes"/>the chain of the T&#x00EB;en-shan: perhaps it may be on the northern face, three<lb break="yes"/>degrees to the eastward of lake Yssi-kul or Tremoortu. Chinese authors call<lb break="yes"/>it P&#x00EF;h-shan (&#x201C;White Mountain&#x201D;), Ho-shan, and Aghi (&#x201C;Fiery Mountain.&#x201D;)<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">The details given M. Klaproth (<hi rendition="#i">Tabl. Hist. de l&#x2019; Asie</hi>, p. 110; <hi rendition="#i">Mém</hi>. relatifs à l&#x2019;Asie, t. ii. p. 358)<lb break="yes"/>are the most complete, and derived principally from the history of the Ming dynasty. M. Abel-Ré-<lb break="no"/>musat (<hi rendition="#i">Journ. Asiat</hi>. t. v. p. 45; <hi rendition="#i" >Descrip. de Khotan,</hi> t. ii. p. 9), has added more in the Japanese<lb break="yes"/>translation of the grand Chinese Encyclop&#x00E6;dia. The root <hi rendition="#i">ag,</hi> which is found in the word <hi rendition="#i">Aghi</hi>, accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to M. Klaproth, signifies &#x201C;fire&#x201D; in Hindustani. To the south of P&#x00EF;h-shan, in the neighbourhood<lb break="yes"/>of Khoten, belonging to the Teen-shan-nar-lu, there can be no doubt that, prior to our era, Sanscrit<lb break="yes"/>was spoken, or a language possessing a strong analogy with it: but in Sanscrit a flaming mountain is<lb break="yes"/>called Agni-ghiri. According to M. Bopp, <hi rendition="#i">Aghi</hi> is not a Sanscrit word. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>The root <hi rendition="#i">ag</hi>, which is found in the word <hi rendition="#i">Aghi</hi>, signifies &#x201C;fire&#x201D; in all the dialects of Hindustan;<lb break="yes"/>this element is <hi rendition="#i" >ag</hi> in Hindustani, <hi rendition="#i">agh</hi> in Mahratta, and the form of <hi rendition="#i">agi</hi> is still preserved in the dialect<lb break="yes"/>of the Punjab. The word <hi rendition="#i">agni,</hi> by which &#x201C;fire&#x201D; is commonly designated in Sanscrit, belongs to the<lb break="yes"/>same root, as well as <hi rendition="#i">agun</hi> in Bengalee, <hi rendition="#i">ogun</hi> in Russian, and the <hi rendition="#i">ignis</hi> of the Latins. <hi rendition="#k" >Klaproth.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>It is not known with certainty whether the name of <hi rendition="#i">P&#x00EF;h-shan</hi> implies that its<lb break="yes"/>summit reaches the line of perpetual snow, which the height of this mountain<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="235" facs="#f0012"/> would determine, at least the minimum; or whether it merely denotes the<lb break="yes"/>glittering hue of a peak covered with saline substances, pumice stone, and vol-<lb break="no"/>canic ashes in decomposition. A Chinese author of the seventh century says:<lb break="yes"/>at 200 <hi rendition="#i">le</hi>, or fifteen leagues, to the north of the city of Kwei-chow (now<lb break="yes"/>Kucha), in about the latitude of 41° 37&#x2032; and longitude 80° 35&#x2032; E., accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to the astronomical determination of the missionaries made in the<lb break="yes"/>country of the Eleuths, rises the P&#x00EF;h-shan, which emits fire and smoke with-<lb break="no"/>out interruption. It is from thence sal ammoniac is brought; upon one of the<lb break="yes"/>declivities of the Fiery Mountain (Ho-shan), all the stones burn, melt, and<lb break="yes"/>flow to a distance of some tens of <hi rendition="#i">le</hi>. The fused mass <note place="foot" n="*">The history of the Chinese dynasty of Tang, speaking of the lava from the P&#x00EF;h-shan, states that<lb break="yes"/>it ran like liquid fat. <hi rendition="#k" >Klaproth.</hi>
                    </note> hardens as it becomes<lb break="yes"/>cold. The natives use it in disorders <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">This is not lava, but the saline particles which appear in the form of an efflorescence on its<lb break="yes" />surface.</note> as a medicine: sulphur is also found<lb break="yes" />there.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. Klaproth observes that this mountain is now called Khalar,<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">The P&#x00EF;h-shan of the ancient Chinese, at present has the Turk name of Eshik-bash: <hi rendition="#i">Eshik</hi> is a<lb break="yes" />species of goat, and <hi rendition="#i">bash</hi> signifies &#x201C;head.&#x201D; Sulphur is produced there in abundance. The Eshik-bash<lb break="yes"/>belongs to the elevated mountains which in the time of the Wei dynasty (the third century) bounded,<lb break="yes"/>to the north-west, the kingdom of Kwei-tsu (Ku-cha); it is the Aghi-shan under the Suy dynasty (in<lb break="yes"/>the early moiety of the seventh century). The history of this dynasty relates that this mountain<lb break="yes"/>always shewed fire and smoke, and that sal-ammoniac was obtained there. In the description of the<lb break="yes"/>Western country, which forms a part of the history of the Tang dynasty, we find that the mountain in<lb break="yes"/>question was then called Aghi-teen-shan (which may be translated &#x201C;mountain of fields of fire&#x201D;), or<lb break="yes"/>P&#x00EF;h-shan (&#x201C;white mountain&#x201D;), that it was to the north of the city of Ilolo, and that it emitted<lb break="yes" />perpetual fire. Ilolo (or perhaps Irolo, Ilor, or Irol) was then the residence of the King of Kwei-tsu.<lb break="yes"/>The Eshik-bash is to the north of Ku-cha, and 200 <hi rendition="#i">le</hi> to the west of the Khan-tengri, which forms<lb break="yes"/>part of the chain of the Teen-shan. The Eshik-bash is very large, and much sulphur and sal-ammo-<lb break="no" />niac is even now collected there. It gives birth to the river Eshik-bash-gol, which flows to the south<lb break="yes"/>of the city of Kucha, and falls, after a course of 200 <hi rendition="#i">le</hi>, into the Erghew.</note> and that,<lb break="yes"/>conformably to the account given by the Bokhars who bring to Siberia sal<lb break="yes"/>ammoniac (called <hi rendition="#i">nao-ska</hi> in Chinese, and <hi rendition="#i" >no&#x0304;sha&#x0304;der</hi> in Persian), the mountain<lb break="yes"/>to the south of Korgos is so abundant in this species of salt that the natives<lb break="yes"/>frequently employ it as a means of paying their tribute to the emperor of<lb break="yes"/>China. In a recent <hi rendition="#i">Description of Central Asia</hi>, published at Peking in 1777,<lb break="yes"/>we find the following statement:&#x2014;&#x201C;the province of Ku-cha produces copper,<lb break="yes"/>saltpetre, sulphur, and sal ammoniac. The latter article comes from an ammo-<lb break="no"/>niac mountain to the north of the city of Ku-cha, which is full of chasms and<lb break="yes"/>caverns. These apertures, in spring, summer, and autumn, are filled with<lb break="yes"/>fire, to such a degree that, during the night the mountain appears illuminated<lb break="yes"/>by thousands of lamps. No one is then able to approach it. In winter alone,<lb break="yes" />when the vast quantity of snow has extinguished the fire, the natives are able<lb break="yes"/>to labour in collecting the sal ammoniac, for which purpose they strip them-<lb break="no"/>selves quite naked. The salt is found in caverns, in the form of stalactites,<lb break="yes"/>which renders it difficult to be detached.&#x201D; The name of Tartarian salt, for-<lb break="no"/>merly given in commerce to this salt, ought to have long ago directed attention<lb break="yes"/>to the volcanic phenomena of Central Asia.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. Cordier, in his letter to M. Abel Rémusat, &#x201C;on the existence of two<lb break="yes"/>burning volcanos in Central Asia,&#x201D; calls P&#x00EF;h-shan a <hi rendition="#i">solfatara</hi> like that of Puz-<lb break="no"/>zuoli. In the state in which it is described in the work cited further back, the<lb break="yes"/>P&#x00EF;h-shan might well deserve only the name of an extinct volcano, although<lb break="yes"/>the igneous phenomena are wanting in the solfataras I have seen: such as those<lb break="yes"/>of Puzzuoli, the crater of the peak of Teneriffe, the Rucu-pishinsha, and the<lb break="yes"/>volcano of Jorullo; but passages in more ancient Chinese historians, who re-<lb break="no" />late the march of the army of the Heung-nus, in the first century of our era,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="236" facs="#f0013"/> speak of masses of rocks in fusion flowing to the distance of some miles: so<lb break="yes"/>that it is impossible, in these expressions, not to understand eruptions of lava.<lb break="yes"/>The ammoniac mountain between Kucha and Korgos has also been a volcano,<lb break="yes"/>in activity, in the strictest sense of the word: a volcano which emitted torrents<lb break="yes"/>of lava in the centre of Asia, 400 geographical leagues from the Caspian Sea<lb break="yes"/>to the west, 433 from the Frozen Sea to the north, 504 from the Great Ocean<lb break="yes"/>to the east, and 440 from the Indian-Ocean to the south. This is not the<lb break="yes"/>place to discuss the question relative to the influence of the proximity of the<lb break="yes"/>sea on the action of volcanos; I merely solicit attention to the geographical<lb break="yes"/>position of the volcanos of Inner Asia, and their reciprocal relations. The<lb break="yes"/>P&#x00EF;h-shan is distant from 300 to 400 leagues from all the seas. When I returned<lb break="yes"/>from Mexico, some celebrated mineralogists expressed their astonishment<lb break="yes"/>when they heard me speak of the volcanic eruption of the plain of Jorullo,<lb break="yes" />and of the volcano of Popocatepetl, as still in activity; although the former<lb break="yes"/>is only thirty leagues from the sea, and the latter forty-three leagues. Gebel<lb break="yes"/>Koldaghi, a conical and smoking mountain of Kordofan, of which Mr. Rüp-<lb break="no"/>pell was told at Dongola, is 150 leagues from the Red Sea, and this distance<lb break="yes"/>is but a third of that at which the P&#x00EF;h-shan, which for 1,700 years has emitted<lb break="yes"/>torrents of lava, is situated from the Indian Ocean. The hypothesis, con-<lb break="no"/>formably to which the Andes present no volcano in activity in those parts<lb break="yes"/>where the chain recedes from the sea, is without foundation. The system of<lb break="yes"/>mountains of the Caraccas, which run from east to west, or the chain of the<lb break="yes"/>coast of Venezuela, is shaken by violent earthquakes, but has no more aper-<lb break="no" />tures which are in permanent communication with the interior of the earth,<lb break="yes"/>and which discharge lava, than the chain of the Himalaya, which is little more<lb break="yes"/>than 100 leagues from the gulf of Bengal, or the Ghauts, which may almost be<lb break="yes"/>termed a coast-chain. Where trachyte has been unable to penetrate across<lb break="yes"/>the chains when they have been elevated, they discover no chasms; no chan-<lb break="no"/>nels are opened whereby the subterranean forces can act in a permanent man-<lb break="no"/>ner at the surface. The remarkable fact of the proximity of the sea wherever<lb break="yes"/>volcanos are still in activity,&#x2014;a fact which, in general, is not to be denied,&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>seems to be accounted for less by the chemical agency of the water, than by<lb break="yes"/>the configuration of the crust of the globe, and the deficiency of resistance<lb break="yes"/>which, in the vicinity of maritime basins, the elevated masses of the continent<lb break="yes"/>oppose to elastic fluids, and to the efflux of bodies in fusion in the interior of<lb break="yes"/>our planet. Real volcanic phenomena may occur, as in the old country of the<lb break="yes"/>Eleuths, and at Toorfan, to the south of the T&#x00EB;en-shan, wherever, owing to<lb break="yes"/>ancient resolutions, a fissure is opened in the crust of the globe at a distance<lb break="yes"/>from the sea. The reason why volcanos in activity are not more rarely remote<lb break="yes"/>from the sea, is merely because, wherever an eruption has been unable to force<lb break="yes"/>itself through the declivity of continental masses towards a maritime basin, a<lb break="yes"/>very unusual concurrence of circumstances is requisite to permit a permanent<lb break="yes"/>communication between the interior of the globe and the atmosphere, and to<lb break="yes"/>form apertures which, like intermittent warm springs, effuse, instead of water,<lb break="yes"/>gases and oxidised earths in fusion, in other words, lava.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>To the eastward of the P&#x00EF;h-shan, the &#x201C;White Mountain&#x201D; of the Eleuths,<lb break="yes"/>the whole northern slope of the T&#x00EB;en-shan presents volcanic phenomena:<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;lava and pumice-stone are seen there, and even considerable solfataras,<lb break="yes"/>which are called &#x2018;fiery places.&#x2019; The solfatara of Uroomtsi is five leagues in<lb break="yes"/>circumference; in winter it is not covered with snow; it would be supposed<lb break="yes"/>to be full of ashes. If a stone be thrown into this basin, flames issue forth, as<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="237" facs="#f0014"/> well as a black smoke, which continues some time. Birds dare not fly over<lb break="yes"/>these fiery places.&#x201D; Eastward, sixty leagues from P&#x00EF;h-shan, is a lake of very<lb break="yes"/>considerable extent, the different names of which in the Chinese, Kirghis, and<lb break="yes" />Calmuc languages, signify &#x201C;warm salt and ferruginous water.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If we cross the volcanic chain of the T&#x00EB;en-shan, we find E.S.E. of lake Yssi-<lb break="no"/>kul (so often mentioned in the itineraries which I have collected), and of the<lb break="yes"/>volcano of the P&#x00EF;h-shan, the volcano of Toorfan, which may also be called the<lb break="yes"/>volcano of Ho-chow (&#x201C;City of Fire&#x201D;), for it is very near that city.<note place="foot" n="*">Ho-chow, a city, now destroyed, was a league and a half to the east of Toorfan.</note> M.<lb break="yes"/>Abel Rémusat has made particular mention of this volcano in his <hi rendition="#i">Histoire de<lb break="yes" />Khoten,</hi> and in his letter to M. Cordier.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">M. Rémusat calls the volcano of P&#x00EF;h-shan, to the north of Kucha, the volcano of Bishbalik. From<lb break="yes"/>the time of the Mongols in China, all the country between the northern slope of the T&#x00EB;en-shan and the<lb break="yes"/>little chain of the Tarbagatay has been called Bishbalik.</note> No reference is made to stony<lb break="yes" />masses in fusion (torrents of lava), there, as at P&#x00EF;h-shan; but &#x201C;a column of<lb break="yes"/>smoke is seen continually to issue; this smoke gives place at night to a flame<lb break="yes"/>like that of torch. Birds and other animals, upon which the light falls, appear<lb break="yes"/>of a red colour. The natives, when they go thither to collect the <hi rendition="#i">nao-sha,</hi> or<lb break="yes"/>sal ammoniac, put on wooden shoes, for leather soles would be very soon<lb break="yes"/>burned.&#x201D; Sal ammoniac is procured at the volcano of Ho-chow not only in the<lb break="yes"/>form of a crust or sediment, according as it is deposited by the vapours which<lb break="yes" />exhale it; but Chinese books likewise make mention of &#x201C;a greenish liquor<lb break="yes"/>collected in cavities, which is boiled and evaporated, and from it sal ammoniac<lb break="yes"/>is obtained in the form of small lumps like sugar, of extreme whiteness and<lb break="yes"/>perfect purity.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>P&#x00EF;h-shan and the volcano of Ho-chow or Toorfan are 140 leagues apart, in<lb break="yes"/>the direction of east and west. About forty leagues westward of the meridian<lb break="yes"/>of Ho-chow, at the foot of the gigantic Bokhda-ula, is the great solfatara of<lb break="yes"/>Uroomtsi. At 140 leagues north-west of this, in a plain adjoining the banks<lb break="yes"/>of the Khobok, which flows into the small lake of Darlay, rises a hill, &#x201C;the<lb break="yes"/>clefts of which are very warm, though they do not exhale smoke (visible va-<lb break="no"/>pours): the sal ammoniac in these crevices is sublimed into so solid a coating,<lb break="yes"/>that the stone is obliged to be broken in order to get it.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These four places hitherto known, namely, P&#x00EF;h-shan, Ho-chow, Uroomtsi,<lb break="yes"/>and Khobok, which exhibit evident volcanic phenomena, in the interior of<lb break="yes"/>Asia, are 130 or 140 leagues to the south of the point of Chinese Zungaria,<lb break="yes"/>where I was at the beginning of 1829. Aral-tubeh, the conical and insular<lb break="yes"/>mountain of lake Ala-kul, which has been in a state of ignition in historical<lb break="yes"/>times, and which is mentioned in the itineraries collected at Semipolatinsk, is<lb break="yes"/>in the volcanic territory of Bishbalik. This insular mountain is situated to<lb break="yes"/>the west of the ammoniac-cavern of Khobok, and to the north of P&#x00EF;h-shan,<lb break="yes"/>which still emits light, and which formerly discharged lava, and at a distance<lb break="yes"/>of sixty leagues from each of these two points. From Lake Ala-kul to Lake<lb break="yes" />Zaisang, where the Russian Cossacks of the line of the Irtish exercise the<lb break="yes"/>right of fishing, by connivance of the Mandarins, the distance is reckoned at<lb break="yes"/>fifty-one leagues. The Tarbagatay, at the foot of which is situated Choogon-<lb break="no"/>chak, a town of Chinese Mongolia, and where Dr. Meyer, the learned and<lb break="yes"/>enterprizing companion of M. Ledebour, fruitlessly essayed, in 1825, to pro-<lb break="no"/>secute his researches in natural history, extends to the south-west of Lake<lb break="yes" />Zaisang towards the Ala-kul. <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;" xml:id="fn1-1" next="#fn1-2">I do not wish to express any doubt respecting the existence of the Ala-kul and the Alaktugul-noor,<lb break="yes"/>lakes in the vicinity of each other; but it appears singular to me, that the Tatars and Mongols, who</note> We are thus acquainted, in the interior of<lb break="yes"/>Asia, with a volcanic territory, the surface of which is upwards of 2,500<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">traverse</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="238" facs="#f0015"/> square leagues, and which is distant 300 or 400 leagues from the sea: it occu-<lb break="no"/>pies a moiety of the longitudinal valley situated between the first and second<lb break="yes"/>systems of mountains. The chief seat of volcanic action seems to be in the<lb break="yes" />T&#x00EB;en-shan. Perhaps the colossal Bokhda-ula is a trachytic mountain like<lb break="yes"/>Chimborazo. On the side north of the Tarbagatay and of Lake Darlay the<lb break="yes"/>action becomes weaker; yet Mr. Rose and I found white trachyte along the<lb break="yes"/>south-western declivity of the Alta&#x00EF;, upon a bell-shaped hill at Ridderski, near<lb break="yes"/>the village of Butachikha.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On both sides of the T&#x00EB;en-shan, north and south, violent earthquakes are<lb break="yes"/>felt. The town of Aksu was entirely destroyed by a convulsion of this kind<lb break="yes"/>at the beginning of the eighteenth century. Professor Eversman, of Casan,<lb break="yes"/>whose repeated travels have made us acquainted with Bokhara, was told by a<lb break="yes"/>Tatar, who was a servant of his, well acquainted with the country between<lb break="yes" />Lakes Balkashi and Ala-kul, that earthquakes were very common there.<lb break="yes"/>In eastern Siberia, to the north of the fiftieth parallel, the centre of the circle<lb break="yes"/>of shocks appears to be at Irkutsk, and in the deep basin of Lake Baikal,<lb break="yes"/>where, on the Kiachta road, especially on the banks of the Jeda and the<lb break="yes"/>Chekoy, basalt is found with olivine, cellular amygdaloid, shabassie, and<lb break="yes" />apophyllite.<note place="foot" n="*">Dr. Hess, associate of the Academy of Sciences of St. Petersburgh, who resided on the borders of<lb break="yes" />the Baikal and to the south of the lake, from 1826 to 1828, gives us reason to expect a geological descrip-<lb break="no"/>tion of a portion of the remarkable country which he traversed. He frequently observed at Verkhnei-<lb break="no"/>Oudinsk granite alternating several times with conglomerates.</note> In the month of February 1829, Irkutsk suffered greatly from<lb break="yes"/>violent earthquakes; and in the month of April following, convulsions were<lb break="yes"/>also felt at Ridderski, which were perceived at the bottom of the mines, where<lb break="yes"/>they were very severe. But this part of the Alta&#x00EF; is the extreme limit of the<lb break="yes"/>circle of shocks; further to the west, in the plains of Siberia, between the<lb break="yes"/>Alta&#x00EF; and the Ural, as well as along the entire chain of the latter, no motion<lb break="yes"/>has hitherto been observed. The volcano of P&#x00EF;h-shan, the Aral-tubeh, to the<lb break="yes" />westward of the caverns of sal ammoniac of Khobok, Ridderski, and the por-<lb break="no"/>tion of the Alta&#x00EF; which abounds in metals, are situated for the most part in a<lb break="yes"/>direction which but slightly deviates from that of the meridian. Perhaps the<lb break="yes"/>Alta&#x00EF; may be comprehended within the circle of the convulsions of the T&#x00EB;en-<lb break="no"/>shan, and the shocks of the Alta&#x00EF;, instead of coming only from the east, or<lb break="yes"/>from the basin of the Baikal, may also come from the volcanic country of<lb break="yes"/>Bishbalik. In many parts of the new continent it is clear that the circles of<lb break="yes"/>shocks intersect each other, that is, the same country receives terrestrial con-<lb break="no" />vulsion periodically on two different quarters.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1">traverse these parts so often, and who have been questioned at Semipolatinsk, should only know the<lb break="yes"/>Ala-kul, and assert that the Alaktugul-noor owes its existence to a confusion of names. M. Pansner,<lb break="yes"/>in his Russian map of Inner Asia, which may be implicitly relied on with regard to the country north of<lb break="yes"/>the course of the Ele, makes the Ala-kul (properly Ala-ghul, or &#x201C;party-coloured lake&#x201D;) communicate<lb break="yes"/>with the Alaktugul by five channels. Possibly the isthmus which separates these lakes may be marshy,<lb break="yes"/>which causes them to be considered as one. Casim Bek, a professor at Casan, and who is a Persian by<lb break="yes"/>birth, insists that <hi rendition="#i">tugul</hi> is a Tataro-Turkish negation, and that, therefore, <hi rendition="#i">Alaktugul</hi> signifies &#x201C;the<lb break="yes"/>lake not variegated,&#x201D; as Ala-tau-ghul implies &#x201C;the lake of the variegated mountain.&#x201D; Perhaps the<lb break="yes"/>names of Ala-kul and Ala-tugul mean merely &#x201C;lake near the Ala-tau mountain,&#x201D; which stretches from<lb break="yes" />Turkestan to Zungaria. The small map published by the English missionaries of the Caucasus, does<lb break="yes"/>not contain the Ala-kul; there appears only a group of three lakes, the Balkashi, the Alak-tugul, and<lb break="yes"/>the Koorgeh. The hypothesis, however, according to which the vicinity of large lakes produces, in the<lb break="yes"/>interior of Asia, the same effect upon volcanos remote from the sea, as the ocean, is without founda-<lb break="no"/>tion. The volcano of Toorfan is surrounded only by insignificant lakes; and, as it has been already<lb break="yes" />remarked, Lake Temoortu or Yssi-kul, which is less than double the extent of the Lake of Geneva, is<lb break="yes"/>thirty-three leagues from the volcano of P&#x00EF;h-shan.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>The Chinese maps represent the two lakes as one, having a mountain in the midst. This lake is called<lb break="yes"/>Ala-kul, its eastern portion bears the name of Alak-tugul-nor, and its western gulf that of She-bartu-<lb break="no"/>kholay.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k" >Klaproth.</hi>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="239" facs="#f0016"/>
                <p>The volcanic territory of Bishbalik is to the eastward of the great dip of the<lb break="yes"/>old world. Travellers who have journeyed from Orenburg to Bokhara, relate<lb break="yes"/>that at Sussak in the Kara-tau, which forms with the Ala-tau a promontory to<lb break="yes"/>the north of the town of Taraz in Turkestan, on the edge of the dip, warm<lb break="yes"/>springs spout up. On the south and on the west of the inner basin we find<lb break="yes"/>two volcanos still in activity; Demavend, which is visible from Tehran, and<lb break="yes" />the Seyban of Ararat,<note place="foot" n="*">The height of Ararat, according to Parrot, is 2,700 toises (17,718 feet); that of Elbourz, according<lb break="yes"/>to Kuppfer, 2,560 (16,800 feet) above the level of the ocean.</note> which is covered with vitrified lava. The trachytes,<lb break="yes"/>porphyries, and thermal springs of the Caucasus are well known. On both<lb break="yes"/>sides of the isthmus between the Caspian and Black Seas, naphtha springs and<lb break="yes"/>volcanos of mud are numerous. The muddy volcano of Taman, of which<lb break="yes"/>Pallas and Messrs. Engelhard and Parrot have described the last fiery eruption,<lb break="yes"/>in 1794, from the reports of Tatars, is, according to the very sensible remark<lb break="yes"/>of Mr. Eichwald, &#x201C;a dependency of Baku, and of the whole peninsula of<lb break="yes"/>Absheron.&#x201D; Eruptions take place where the volcanic forces encounter least<lb break="yes"/>opposition. On the 27th November 1827, crackings and tremblings of the<lb break="yes"/>earth, of a violent character, were succeeded, at the village of Gokmali, in<lb break="yes"/>the province of Baku, three leagues from the western shore of the Caspian<lb break="yes"/>Sea, by an eruption of flames and stones. A space of ground, 200 toises long<lb break="yes"/>and 150 wide, burned for twenty-seven hours without intermission, and rose<lb break="yes"/>above the level of the neighbouring soil. After the flame became extinct,<lb break="yes"/>columns of water were ejected, which continue to flow till the present hour.<lb break="yes"/>I am gratified at being enabled to state here, that Mr. Eichwald&#x2019;s periplus of<lb break="yes"/>the Caspian Sea, which will soon appear, will contain some very important<lb break="yes"/>physical and geological observations, more particularly upon the connexion of<lb break="yes"/>fiery eruptions with the appearance of naphtha-springs and strata of sal gem,<lb break="yes"/>on masses of calcareous rock hurled to considerable distances, on the elevation<lb break="yes"/>and sinking of the bed of the Caspian Sea, which still continue; on the pass-<lb break="no"/>ing of black porphyry, partly vitrified and containing garnets (<hi rendition="#i">melapyres</hi>),<lb break="yes" />through granite, red quartzose porphyry, very dark syenite, and calcareous<lb break="yes"/>spar, in the Krasnovodsk mountains washed by the bay of the Balkan, to the<lb break="yes"/>northward of the ancient mouth of the Oxus (Amoo-doria). We shall learn<lb break="yes"/>from the geognostic description of the eastern shore of the Caspian Sea, where<lb break="yes"/>the island of Chabekan discovers naphtha-springs the same as Baku and the<lb break="yes" />isles between this town and Salian, what species of crystallized rocks are hidden<lb break="yes"/>beneath the rocks in horizontal strata in the peninsula of Absheron, where the<lb break="yes"/>action of subterranean fire is always felt, and where it has not yet been able<lb break="yes"/>to reach the open air. The porphyries of the Caucasus, which run from<lb break="yes"/>W.N.W. to E.S.E., a position and a direction which I have already mentioned<lb break="yes"/>as the reason of the presumed connexion of this chain with the cleft of the<lb break="yes"/>T&#x00EB;en-shan, discover themselves again, traversing all the rocks nearly to the<lb break="yes"/>centre of the great dip of the old world, to the east of the Caspian Sea, in the<lb break="yes" />mountains of Krasnovodsk and Kurreh. Recent researches and the traditions<lb break="yes"/>of the Tatars inform us, that the existence of naphtha-springs has always been<lb break="yes"/>preceded by fiery eruptions. Several salt lakes on the two opposite shores of<lb break="yes"/>the Caspian Sea have a very elevated temperature; and blocks of sal gem, tra-<lb break="no"/>versed by asphaltum, are formed, as Mr. Eichwald remarks with much shrewd-<lb break="no" />ness, &#x201C;by the effect of a sudden volcanic action, as at Vesuvius,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">In an eruption of this volcano in 1805, M. Guy Lussac and I found small fragments of sal-gem in<lb break="yes"/>the lava as it cooled. My Tatar itineraries likewise speak of sal-gem in the neighbourhood of a vol-<lb break="no"/>canic mountain of the T&#x00EB;en-shan, north of Aksu, between the station of Turpa-gad and Mount Arbab.</note> in the<lb break="yes"/>Cordilleras of South America and in Azarbaijan, or even under our own obser-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="240" facs="#f0017"/> vation by the slow but continued action of heat.&#x201D; M. L. de Buch has long<lb break="yes"/>directed his attention to the connexion of the volcanic forces with the masses<lb break="yes"/>of enhedral sal-gem, which traverse so often and so many formations of hori-<lb break="no" />zontal strata.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We have already seen that the circles of the terrestrial convulsions, of<lb break="yes"/>which Lake Baikal or the volcanos of T&#x00EB;en-shan are the centre, do not extend<lb break="yes"/>in western Siberia beyond the western declivity of the Alta&#x00EF;, and do not pass<lb break="yes"/>the Irtish or the meridian of Semipolatinsk. In the chain of the Ural, earth-<lb break="no" />quakes are not felt, nor, notwithstanding the rocks abound in metals, neither<lb break="yes"/>basalt or olivine is found, nor trachytes, properly so called, nor mineral springs.<lb break="yes"/>The circle of the phenomena of Azarbaijan, which includes the peninsula of<lb break="yes"/>Absheron, or the Caucasus, often extends as far as Kizlar and Astrakhan.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is the same on the border of the great hollow in the west. If we direct<lb break="yes"/>our observation from the Caucasian isthmus to the north and north-west, we<lb break="yes"/>come to the country of grand formations in horizontal and tertiary strata,<lb break="yes"/>which occupy southern Russia and Poland. In this region, the rocks of<lb break="yes"/>pyroxene pierce the red free-stone of Yekaterinoslav, whilst asphaltum and<lb break="yes"/>springs impregnated with sulphurous gas denote other masses concreted in the<lb break="yes"/>form of sediment. It may also be mentioned as an important fact, that in<lb break="yes"/>the chain of the Ural, which abounds so much in serpentine and amphibole,<lb break="yes"/>and which serves as a boundary between Europe and Asia, a true amygdaloidal<lb break="yes"/>formation appears at Griasnushinskaia, towards its southern extremity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We shall content ourselves here with observing, with reference to the inge-<lb break="no"/>nious opinions recently promulgated by M. Elie de Beaumont, respecting the<lb break="yes"/>relative age and the parallelism of systems of contemporary mountains, that<lb break="yes"/>in the interior of Asia likewise, the four grand chains which run from east to<lb break="yes"/>west are of a totally different origin from the chains which lie in a direction<lb break="yes" />north and south, or N. 30° W., and S. 30° E. The chain of the Ural, the<lb break="yes"/>Belor, or Beloor-tag, the Ghauts of Malabar, and the Kingkhan, are probably<lb break="yes"/>more modern than the chains of the Himalaya and the T&#x00EB;en-shan. The<lb break="yes"/>systems of different epochs are not always separated from each other by any<lb break="yes"/>considerable space, as in Germany, and in the greater part of the new conti-<lb break="no"/>nent. Frequently, chains of mountains, or axes of exaltation, of dissimilar<lb break="yes"/>directions, and belonging to epochs totally different, are nearly approximated<lb break="yes"/>by nature; resembling so far the characters on a monument which, crossing<lb break="yes"/>different ways, were engraved at different periods, and carry intrinsic marks of<lb break="yes"/>their own date. Thus, in the south of France, are seen chains and undu-<lb break="no"/>lated swellings, some of which are parallel to the Pyrenees and others to the<lb break="yes"/>western Alps. The same diversity of geological phenomena is apparent in the<lb break="yes"/>high land of Central Asia, where isolated portions appear as it were sur-<lb break="no"/>rounded and enclosed by subdivisions, in parallel lines, of the systems of<lb break="yes"/>mountain.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 