<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Notes from a Notice (of some time past) of the Journey of M. de Humboldt in Siberia, and Researches of Mr. Ehrenberg on the Organisation, and the Geographical Distribution of the Infusoria and Northern Asia</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:03</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">V.1</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1830-Notice_sur_le-4-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Notice_sur_le-1.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Notice_sur_le-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Notice_sur_le-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Notice_sur_le-4-neu.xml" type="self"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Notes from a Notice (of some time past) of the Journey of M. de Humboldt in Siberia, and Researches of Mr. Ehrenberg on the Organisation, and the Geographical Distribution of the Infusoria and Northern Asia</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1837</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Literary Gazette; and Journal of Belles Lettres, Arts, Sciences, &amp;amp;c.&lt;/i&gt; 1072 (5. August 1837), S. 499.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Schmuck: Kapitälchen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="499" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Notes from a Notice (of some time past) of the<lb break="yes" />Journey of M. de Humboldt in Siberia, and<lb break="yes"/>Researches of Mr. Ehrenberg on the Organ-<lb break="no"/>isation, and the Geographical Distribution of<lb break="yes"/>the Infusoria and Northern Asia.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">The</hi> journey,&#x201D; says M. de Humboldt&#x2019;s re-<lb break="no"/>port, &#x201C;which Mr. Ehrenberg, Gustave Rose,<lb break="yes"/>and myself accomplished, under the auspices of<lb break="yes" />the Emperor of Russia, to the mines of the<lb break="yes"/>Ural and of the Altai, to the frontiers of Chi-<lb break="no"/>nese Dzengaria, and to the Caspian Sea, has<lb break="yes"/>had in view a sufficient variety of objects to<lb break="yes"/>entitle the results to be given in memoirs and<lb break="yes"/>in particular works. We possess geological<lb break="yes" />collections, made by ourselves, much more com-<lb break="no"/>plete than any that had hitherto been brought<lb break="yes"/>from that part of European Asia. Mr. Rose<lb break="yes"/>has arranged them, in the museum of Berlin,<lb break="yes"/>by the side of the geognostic collections from<lb break="yes" />Mexico, Quito, Southern Brazil, the Canary<lb break="yes"/>Islands, and different parts of Europe. I am<lb break="yes"/>occupied in concentrating the principal results<lb break="yes"/>of our labours, in a physical table of the coun-<lb break="no"/>tries we have traversed, a work which is about<lb break="yes"/>to appear, under the title of &#x2018;Geognostical,<lb break="yes"/>Mathematical, and Astronomical Observations.&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Ehrenberg, whose former travels in Nubia,<lb break="yes" />Dongola, and Abyssinia, had offered some very<lb break="yes"/>fertile means of comparisons and new views,<lb break="yes"/>will treat, in a separate volume, of the geo-<lb break="no"/>graphical relations of the vegetable kingdom<lb break="yes"/>between the Wolga, the Irtyche, and the Obi,<lb break="yes"/>between the north of the Ural and the steppe<lb break="yes"/>of the Kirghese.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;We will combine zoological descriptions,<lb break="yes"/>more especially those of fresh-water shells of<lb break="yes"/>insects and fish which abound in the great<lb break="yes"/>rivers, and in the Caspian Sea. I shall have<lb break="yes"/>the honour to communicate to the Academy the<lb break="yes" />extract of a memoir, which is not yet printed,<lb break="yes"/>and in which Mr. Ehrenberg, after having cha-<lb break="no"/>racterised the variety of the great royal tiger of<lb break="yes"/>India, which shews itself to the north of the<lb break="yes"/>great Cordillera of the Celestial mountains<lb break="yes"/>(Tcheanchan), even to the north of Tarbagatai,<lb break="yes" />and of the region of Dioptases, exposes the dif-<lb break="no"/>ference of the <hi rendition="#i">Felis pardus</hi> of Cuvier, of the<lb break="yes"/>
                  <hi rendition="#i">Felis chalybeata</hi> of <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/116738928">Hermann</persName>, which is the <hi rendition="#i">Felis<lb break="yes"/>pardus</hi> of Tamminch, and of the <hi rendition="#i">Felis irbis</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(long-haired panther), which Pallas has con-<lb break="no" />founded with the <hi rendition="#i">Felis pardus</hi> of Africa, and<lb break="yes"/>of which we obtained a fine skin at Semipola-<lb break="no" />tinsk, on the borders of the Irtyche. Mr. Rose<lb break="yes"/>has been successful in discovering sulphuretted<lb break="yes"/>tin in the Southern Ural, or Bachteyre, and a<lb break="yes"/>combination of silver and of tellurium in a mi-<lb break="no"/>neral of Sawodinski, near the Altai. The<lb break="yes" />existence of tin, and of tellurium, in Asiatic<lb break="yes"/>Russia, was, before our journey, as unknown<lb break="yes"/>as the existence of diamonds in European<lb break="yes"/>Russia.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Mr. Rose, whose exactness in chemical ana-<lb break="no"/>lysis is well known, is occupied at this moment<lb break="yes"/>in a very extended work on the gold obtained<lb break="yes"/>from washing, and on the gold obtained from<lb break="yes"/>veins which are not yet destroyed, as well as<lb break="yes" />on the proportions in which gold is mingled<lb break="yes"/>with silver in Siberia, the produce of which<lb break="yes"/>metal, at this moment, exceeds 6000 kilo-<lb break="no"/>grammes. There scarcely exists a country in<lb break="yes"/>the world in which the rocks and veins present<lb break="yes" />a greater variety of minerals, equally remark-<lb break="no"/>able for their beauty and for their chemical<lb break="yes"/>composition.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>&#x201C;The number of species of <hi rendition="#i">infusoria</hi> observed<lb break="yes"/>between the Caspian Sea, the Ural, and the<lb break="yes" />Altai, has been 113, amongst which eight con-<lb break="no"/>stitute new genera. Mr. Ehrenberg has suc-<lb break="no"/>ceeded, by feeding these transparent and gela-<lb break="no"/>tinous beings, in discovering the extreme com-<lb break="no"/>plication of their organs, in colouring their<lb break="yes"/>mouths, their stomachs, the extremity of their<lb break="yes" />alimentary canals, to paint them, if we may so<lb break="yes"/>express ourselves, interiorly in blue and red.<lb break="yes"/>In glancing over the eight plates drawn by<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Ehrenberg, we see at once the surprising<lb break="yes"/>complication of these beings, of which several<lb break="yes"/>are not more than 1-9000th part of a line<lb break="yes" />(1-12th of an inch) in length. The author<lb break="yes"/>made use of a microscope by Chevallier, and<lb break="yes"/>generally of a power of 800 times the size.<lb break="yes"/>He gives the results of ten years of observa-<lb break="no"/>tions, which are so much the more sure, as the<lb break="yes" />anatomy of the <hi rendition="#i">mollusc&#x00E6;</hi> of the Red Sea had<lb break="yes"/>accustomed him to the use of microscopes and<lb break="yes" />micrometers.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The smallest <hi rendition="#i">infusoria</hi> which have been<lb break="yes"/>considered as the most simple, have all a mouth<lb break="yes" />and organs of nutrition, and sometimes from<lb break="yes"/>thirty to forty stomachs. They all seize their<lb break="yes"/>prey, and live upon solid substances. In the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Monas termo</hi>, which is only 1-1500th of a line<lb break="yes"/>in length, four stomachs, a mouth, and hairs<lb break="yes" />surrounding that mouth, are visible. The <hi rendition="#i">Verti-<lb break="no"/>cell&#x00E6; leucophrys</hi> (<hi rendition="#i" >Paramacium</hi>) have a more<lb break="yes"/>complex organisation. The number of eyes<lb break="yes"/>varies in the <hi rendition="#i" >Rotifer&#x00E6;</hi>, in the genera <hi rendition="#i">Englena</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>and <hi rendition="#i">Eosphora;</hi> but what will most attract the<lb break="yes"/>attention of naturalists who are interested in<lb break="yes"/>microscopical anatomy, is the complication of<lb break="yes" />the muscular and nervous system, the mouth,<lb break="yes"/>provided with cartilaginous teeth, the organs<lb break="yes"/>of nutrition and of generation of the <hi rendition="#i">Hydatina<lb break="yes"/>senta</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">Verticella senta</hi>).</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Mr. Ehrenberg discusses the genera which<lb break="yes"/>had been established on other principles; and<lb break="yes"/>he finds that the animals of the same species<lb break="yes"/>have been in the different stages of growth,<lb break="yes"/>and, according as they had had food or not,<lb break="yes"/>had been classed under different genera. Mr.<lb break="yes" />Ehrenberg has frequently seen <hi rendition="#i">infusoria</hi> issue<lb break="yes"/>from eggs, and no direct observation led him to<lb break="yes" />admit a spontaneous generation, nor an agglo-<lb break="no"/>meration of <hi rendition="#i">infusoria</hi> to form the rudiments of<lb break="yes" />vegetables and of animals. He thinks that all<lb break="yes"/>infusory animals change their situation, and<lb break="yes"/>seek their food solitarily. Out of the 113<lb break="yes"/>species observed and described during the course<lb break="yes"/>of the journey, thirty-one species belong to<lb break="yes" />Europe, and eighty-two to Asia; two-thirds<lb break="yes"/>are also observed in central Europe. The<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Kalpoda cucullus</hi> appears to be the species the<lb break="yes"/>most generally spread. Mr. Ehrenberg found<lb break="yes"/>it from Mount Sinai to Dongola, near Berlin,<lb break="yes"/>at St. Petersburg, on the north of the Ural,<lb break="yes"/>and at the foot of the Altai. In the mines of<lb break="yes"/>Siberia, three species of monades are met with;<lb break="yes"/>and the <hi rendition="#i">Kalpoda cucullus</hi>, at fifty-six fathoms<lb break="yes"/>in depth, in places entirely deprived of light.<lb break="yes"/>The <hi rendition="#i">infusoria,</hi> according to their structure,<lb break="yes"/>form the natural class of animals which inhabit<lb break="yes"/>the sea and the continent. Some species are<lb break="yes"/>met with which, like cryptogamic plants, are<lb break="yes" />identical under the most various zones. They<lb break="yes"/>appear to vary more from climate,&#x2014;from Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope to Dongola, than from east to west, &#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>from Berlin to Altai.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The saline waters of the Asiatic steppes do<lb break="yes"/>not present any very particular forms. Dew,<lb break="yes"/>examined with the greatest care in the midst<lb break="yes"/>of the African deserts, offered no infusory<lb break="yes"/>animals, whilst eight different species were<lb break="yes" />met with in the wells of the oasis of Jupiter<lb break="yes"/>Ammon.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>&#x201C;The researches on infusory animals made<lb break="yes"/>during the last journey of De Humboldt, ex-<lb break="no"/>tended for more than 50° of longitude, and 14°<lb break="yes"/>of latitude.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 