<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On the Mountain-chains and Volcanoes of Central Asia, with a Map of Chains of Mountains and Volcanoes of Central Asia</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:03</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">V.2</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1830-Ueber_die_Bergketten-10</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Ueber_die_Bergketten-01.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Ueber_die_Bergketten-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Ueber_die_Bergketten-03.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Ueber_die_Bergketten-04.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Ueber_die_Bergketten-05.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Ueber_die_Bergketten-06.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Ueber_die_Bergketten-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Ueber_die_Bergketten-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Ueber_die_Bergketten-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Ueber_die_Bergketten-10.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Ueber_die_Bergketten-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Ueber_die_Bergketten-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1830-Ueber_die_Bergketten-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt,&lt;i&gt; Fragmente einer Geologie und Klimatologie Asiens. Aus dem Französischen mit Anmerkungen, einer Karte und einer Tabelle vermehrt von Julius Löwenberg&lt;/i&gt;, Berlin 1832, S. 1–70.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On the Mountain-chains and Volcanoes of Central Asia, with a Map of Chains of Mountains and Volcanoes of Central Asia</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1831</date>
          <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal&lt;/i&gt; 11 (Juli–September 1831), S. 227–240; 12 (Oktober–Dezember 1831), S. 145–159, Karte.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung, Kapitälchen; Fußnoten mit Asterisken und Kreuzen; Schmuck: Initialen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="227" facs="#f0001" /><lb/><div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">On the Mountain-chains and Volcanoes of Central Asia, with a<lb/>Map of Chains of Mountains and Volcanoes of Central Asia.</hi><lb/>By M. <hi rendition="#k">de Humboldt</hi><note place="foot" n="*">This memoir we consider of high importance, as illustrating not only<lb/>the geography, but also the geognosy, of several interesting parts of Central<lb/>Asia.</note>. (With a Map.)</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k"><hi rendition="#in">V</hi>olcanoes,</hi> which demonstrate a perpetual communication be-<lb/>tween the earth which is fluid, or in a state of fusion, and the<lb/>atmosphere surrounding its hardened and oxidated surface, are,<lb/>by their connexion with the formation of beds of rock-salt, with<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Salses</hi> (small conical hills, which in their eruptions emit mud,<lb/>naphtha, gases unfit for supporting life, and sometimes also, but<lb/>only for a short period, flames, vapours, and blocks), with hot<lb/>springs, earthquakes, and the upraising of mountains, an object<lb/>of so great importance for every thing which appertains to the<lb/>observation of nature, that they interest not only geologists, but<lb/>likewise natural philosophers, in the general acceptation of this<lb/>term. Leopold von Buch has already, in his great work on the<lb/><pb n="228" facs="#f0002" />
Canary Isles <note place="foot" n="*">This splendid and very valuable work we trust to see translated into Eng-<lb/>lish. If published in octavo, it would be accessible to every geological reader,<lb/>and find a place in every library of Natural History in Britain.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Edit.</hi></note>, explained, with much talent, luminous ideas<lb/>upon the distribution of volcanoes, which are sometimes in isola-<lb/>ted groups around a central volcano, at other times arranged<lb/>longitudinally in a series. The memoir which I now present<lb/>on these volcanic phenomena, situated at a great distance from<lb/>the sea, is certainly much less important; it treats of the local<lb/>phenomena of Central Asia, and of the interior of South Ame-<lb/>rica, concerning which I have had opportunities of collecting<lb/>information little known hitherto. We know still so little of<lb/>the kind of mysterious connexion of volcanoes in activity with<lb/>the vicinity of the sea, that every thing which relates to a vol-<lb/>cano of which we learn the existence very unexpectedly in the<lb/>interior of a continent, gives a very high interest even to a local<lb/>phenomenon.</p><lb/><p>The central and interior portion of Asia, which forms<lb/>neither an immense cluster of mountains nor a continued table-<lb/>land, is crossed from east to west by four grand systems of<lb/>mountains, which have manifestly influenced the movements of<lb/>the population; these are, the Alta&#x00EF;, which is terminated to the<lb/>west by the mountains of the Kirghiz; the T&#x00EB;en-shan, the<lb/>Kwan-lun, and the Himalaya chain. Between the Alta&#x00EF; and<lb/>the T&#x00EB;en-shan, are placed Zungaria and the basin of the Ele;<lb/>between the T&#x00EB;en-shan and the Kwan-lun, Little or rather<lb/>Upper Bucharia, or Cashgar, Yarkand, Khoten, the great<lb/>desert of Gobi (or Cha-mo), Toorfan, Khamil (Hami), and<lb/>Tangout, that is, the northern Tangout of the Chinese, which<lb/>must not be confounded with Tibet or Se-fan; lastly, between<lb/>the Kwan-lun and the Himalaya, Eastern and Western Tibet,<lb/>where H&#x2019;lassa and Ladak are situated.</p><lb/><p>1. <hi rendition="#i">The system of the Alta&#x00EF;</hi> encompasses the sources of the<lb/>Irtish, and of the Yenisse&#x00EF; or Kem; to the east, it takes the<lb/>name of Tangnu; that of the Sayanian mountains between<lb/>lakes Kossogol and Baikal; farther on, that of the lofty Kenta&#x00EF;<lb/>and the mountains of Dauria; lastly, to the north-east, it joins<lb/>the Yablonnoy-khrebet, the Khingkhan and the Aldan moun-<lb/>tains, which stretch along the sea of Okhotsk. The mean lati-<lb/><pb n="229" facs="#f0003" />
tude of its course from east to west is between 50° and 51° 30&#x2032;.<lb/>We shall soon have satisfactory notions respecting the geogra-<lb/>phy of the north-eastern part of this system, between the Baikal,<lb/>Yakutsk, and Okotsk, for which the world will be indebted to<lb/>Dr Erdmann, who has recently traversed those parts. The<lb/>Alta&#x00EF;, properly so called, scarcely occupies seven degrees of<lb/>longitude; but we give to the northernmost portion of the<lb/>mountains encompassing the vast mass of high land of Inner<lb/>Asia, and occupying the space comprised between the 48th and<lb/>51st parallels, the name of the <hi rendition="#i">System of the Alta&#x00EF;,</hi> because simple<lb/>names are more easily impressed upon the memory, and because<lb/>that of Alta&#x00EF; is best known to Europeans, from the great metal-<lb/>lic wealth of these mountains, which now annually yield 70,000<lb/>marks of silver and 1900 marks of gold <note place="foot" n="*">A mark is equal to 4608 grains.</note>. The Alta&#x00EF;, in Turkish,<lb/>in Mongol, Alta&#x00EF;-in-oola, &#x2018;gold mountain,&#x2019; is not a chain of<lb/>mountains, forming the limit of a country, like the Himalaya,<lb/>which bounds the table-land of Tibet, and which consequently<lb/>lowers itself abruptly only on the side of India, which is lower<lb/>than the other country. The plains adjoining lake Za&#x00EF;sang, and<lb/>especially the steppes near lake Balkashi, are certainly not more<lb/>than 300 toises (1968 English feet) above the level of the sea.</p><lb/><p>I avoid, intentionally, in this paper, conformably to the<lb/>statements I collected on the spot, employing the term Lesser<lb/>Alta&#x00EF;, if this term is applied to the vast mass of mountains si-<lb/>tuated between the course of the Narym, lake Teletsky, the<lb/>Bia, Serpent Mountain, and the Irtish above Oustkamenogorsk,<lb/>consequently the territory of Russian Siberia, between the 79th<lb/>and 86th meridians east of Paris, and between the parallels of<lb/>49° 30&#x2032; and 52° 30&#x2032;. This Little Alta&#x00EF; is probably, owing to<lb/>its extent and elevation, much more considerable than the<lb/>Great Alta&#x00EF;, whose position and existence as a chain of snowy<lb/>mountains are, perhaps, equally problematical. Arrowsmith,<lb/>and several modern geographers, who have followed the model<lb/>he has arbitrarily adopted, give the name of Great Alta&#x00EF; to an<lb/>imaginary continuation of the T&#x00EB;en-shan, which is carried to<lb/>the eastward of Khamil (Hami) and Barkoul (Chin-se-foo), a<lb/>Manchoo town, and runs to the north-east, towards the eastern<lb/><pb n="230" facs="#f0004" />
sources of the Yeniss&#x00EB;i and Mount Tangnu. The direction of<lb/>the line of separation of the waters, between the affluents of the<lb/>Orkhon and those of the Aral-noor, lake of the steppe, and the<lb/>unfortunate practice of marking by high chains of mountains<lb/>where systems of streams separate, have occasioned this error.<lb/>If it be desired to retain on our maps the name of Great Alta&#x00EF;,<lb/>it should be given to the succession of lofty mountains ranged<lb/>in a course directly opposite (parallel to the chain of the<lb/>Khangai <note place="foot" n="*">&#x201C;Mount Khanggay-ula is to the north of the source of the Orkhon. Its<lb/>summits are lofty and considerable. This chain is a branching of the Alta&#x00EF;,<lb/>which comes from the north-west: it extends to the eastward to the rivers<lb/>Orkhon and Tula with their affluents, and becomes the Kenteh of the<lb/>Khinggan. A branch of this chain separates to the west, and runs to the<lb/>north under the name of the Kuku-daban; it encompasses the Upper Selengga<lb/>and all its affluents, which take their origin in it, and then runs a distance of<lb/>1000 <hi rendition="#i">le</hi> into the Russian territory. The Orkhon, the Tamir, and their af-<lb/>fluents, have likewise their sources in this chain, which is probably the same<lb/>which the Chinese distinguish by the name of Yang-jin-shan.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Klaproth.</hi></note>), or from the north-west to the south-east, between<lb/>the right bank of the Upper Irtish, and the Yeke-Aral-noor,<lb/>or Lake of the Great Isle, near Gobdo-Khoto.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;There, consequently, to the south of the Narym and of the<lb/>Bukhtorma, which bounds what is called the Little Russian<lb/>Alta&#x00EF;, was the primitive abode of the Turk tribes; the place<lb/>where Dizabul, their grand khan, towards the close of the sixth<lb/>century, received an ambassador from the Emperor of Con-<lb/>stantinople. This <hi rendition="#i">gold-mountain</hi> of the Turks, the <hi rendition="#i">Kin-shan</hi><lb/>of the Chinese, a name with the same signification, bore hereto-<lb/>fore also those of <hi rendition="#i">Ek-tag</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Ektel,</hi> both of which probably<lb/>have an analogous meaning. It is said that more to the south,<lb/>under the 46th parallel, and almost in the meridian of Pijan<lb/>and Toorfan, a lofty peak is still called in Mongol <hi rendition="#i">Alta&#x00EF;nniro,</hi><lb/>&#x2018;summit of the Alta&#x00EF;.&#x2019; If some degrees farther to the south,<lb/>this Great Alta&#x00EF; unites itself to the Naiman-ula mountains, we<lb/>there find a transverse ridge which, running from the north-<lb/>west to the south-east, joins the Russian Alta&#x00EF; to the T&#x00EB;en-shan,<lb/>northward of Barkoul and Hami <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">&#x201C;The Chinese (in their <hi rendition="#i">imperial geography of China</hi>), in tracing the direc-<lb/>tion of the Great Alta&#x00EF; from the north-west to the south-east, make it almost<lb/>re-unite itself to the T&#x00EB;en-shan, which corresponds exactly with what M.<lb/>de Humboldt states.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Klaproth.</hi></note>. This is not the place to<lb/><pb n="231" facs="#f0005" />
develope how the system of north-western direction, so general<lb/>in our hemisphere, is traced in the beds of the rocks, in the line<lb/>of the Alps of Alghin, of the lofty steppe of the Chuya, of the<lb/>chain of the Jyiktu, which is the culminating point of the Rus-<lb/>sian Alta&#x00EF;, and in the hollows of the narrow valleys, where flow<lb/>the Chulyshman, the Chuya, the Katunia, and the Upper<lb/>Charysh; lastly, in the whole course of the Irtish from Kras-<lb/>noyarskoi to Tobolsk.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Between the meridians of Oust-Kamenogorsk and of Semi-<lb/>polatinsk, the system of the Alta&#x00EF; mountains extends from east<lb/>to west, beneath the parallels of 59° and 50°, by a chain of hills<lb/>and low mountains, for 160 geographical leagues, as far as the<lb/>steppe of the Kirghiz. This range, though of very small im-<lb/>portance in respect to size and elevation, is highly interesting to<lb/>geognosy. There does not exist a continuous chain of Kirghiz<lb/>mountains, which, as the maps represent under the names of<lb/>Alghidin-tsano or Alghidin-chamo, unites the Ural and the<lb/>Alta&#x00EF;. Some isolated hills of 500 or 600 feet high, groups of<lb/>small mountains, which, like the Semi-tau near Semipolatinsk,<lb/>rise abruptly to the height of 1000 or 1200 feet above the<lb/>plains, deceive the traveller who is not accustomed to measure<lb/>the inequality of the soil; but it is not less remarkable that<lb/>these clusters of hills and small mountains have been raised<lb/>across a furrow which forms this line of division of the waters<lb/>between the affluents of the Saras, or to the south in the steppe,<lb/>and those of the Irtish to the north: a fissure which follows<lb/>uniformly, as far as the meridian of Sverinagolovskoy, the same<lb/>direction for sixteen degrees of longitude.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;In the line of division of the waters between the Alta&#x00EF; and<lb/>the Ural, between the 49th and 50th parallels, is observable an<lb/>effort of nature, a kind of attempt of subterranean energy, to<lb/>force up a chain of mountains; and this fact recalls powerfully<lb/>the similar appearances I remarked in the new continent.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;But the non-continued range of low mountains and hills of<lb/>crystallized rocks, by which the system of the Alta&#x00EF; is prolonged<lb/>to the west, does not reach the southern extremity of the Ural,<lb/>a chain which, like that of the Andes, presents a long wall run-<lb/>ning from north to south, with metallic mines on its eastern<lb/>side: it terminates abruptly under the meridian of Sverinogov-<lb/><pb n="232" facs="#f0006" />
loskoy, where geographers are accustomed to place the Alghinic<lb/>mountains, the name of which is entirely unknown by the<lb/>Kirghiz of Troitsk and of Orenburg.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;II. <hi rendition="#i">System of the T&#x00EB;en-Shan.</hi>&#x2014;Their mean latitude is 42°.<lb/>Their culminating point is perhaps the mass of mountain re-<lb/>markable by its three peaks, covered with eternal snows, and<lb/>celebrated under the name of Bokhda-ula, or &#x2018;Holy Mountain,&#x2019;<lb/>in the Mongol-Calmuc tongue; which has caused Pallas to give<lb/>to the whole chain the denomination of Bogdo. From the<lb/>Bokhda-ula, the T&#x00EB;en-shan runs easterly towards Barkoul,<lb/>where, to the north of Hami, it sinks abruptly, and spreads it-<lb/>self to the level of the high desert called the Great Gobi, or<lb/>Shamo, which extends south-west and north-east, from Kwa-<lb/>chow, a town of China, to the sources of the Argun. Mount<lb/>Nomkhun, to the north-west of the Sogok and the Sobo, little<lb/>lakes of the steppe, denotes perhaps by its position, a slight<lb/>swell, an angle in the desert; for after an interruption of at<lb/>least ten degrees of longitude, there appears, a little more to the<lb/>south than the T&#x00EB;en-shan, in my opinion, as a continuation of<lb/>this system, at the great bend of the Hwang-ho, or Yellow<lb/>River, the snowy chain of the Gajar, or Yn-shan, which runs<lb/>likewise from west to east, under the parallels of 41° and 42°,<lb/>consequently to the north of the country of Ordos.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Let us now return to the neighbourhood of Toorfan and<lb/>the Bokhda-ula, and follow the western prolongation of the<lb/>second system of mountains; we shall perceive that it extends<lb/>between Gulja (Ele), the place whither the Chinese government<lb/>exiles criminals, and Kucha; then between Temoortu, a large<lb/>lake, the name of which signifies &#x2018;ferruginous water,&#x2019; and Aksu,<lb/>to the north of Cashgar, and runs towards Smarkand. The<lb/>country comprised between the first and second systems of moun-<lb/>tains, or between the Alta&#x00EF; and the T&#x00EB;en-shan, is closed on the<lb/>east, beyond the meridian of Peking, by the Khingkhan-ula, a<lb/>mountainous crest which runs SSW. and NNE.; but to the<lb/>west it is entirely open on the side of the Chwei, the Sarasu and<lb/>the lower Sihoon. In this part there is no transverse ridge,<lb/>provided, at least, we do not regard as such the series of eleva-<lb/>tions which extend north and south, to the west of lake Zaisang,<lb/>across the Targabatay, as far as the north-eastern extremity of<lb/><pb n="233" facs="#f0007" />
  the Ala-tau <note place="foot" n="*">This is a name which has occasioned much confusion. The Kirghiz,<lb/>particularly those of the grand horde, give the title of Ala-tagh (<hi rendition="#i">Alatau,</hi><lb/>&#x2018;speckled mountains&#x2019;) to a series of elevations extending from west to east,<lb/>under the parallels of 43° 30&#x2032; to 45°, from the Upper Sihoon (Syr-daria or<lb/>Jaxartes), near Tonkat, towards lakes Balkashi and Temoortu. The eastern<lb/>portion of the Ala-tau rises considerably at the great sinuosity made by the<lb/>Sihoon to the north-west, and connects with the Kara-tau (&#x2018;Black Moun-<lb/>tain&#x2019;) at Taras or Turkestan. The natives likewise give the name of Ala-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>tau to the mountains to the south of the Tarbagatay between lakes Ala-kul,<lb/>Balkashi, and Temoortu. Is it from these denominations that geographers<lb/>have been in the habit of calling the whole second system of mountains that<lb/>of T&#x00EB;en-shan, Alak or Ala-tau? The Oolug-tagh, or &#x2018;Great Mountain,&#x2019;<lb/>named on some maps Oulug-tag Oolu-tau, and Ooluk-tagh, must not be con-<lb/>founded with the Ala-tau or Ala-taghi.</note>, between lakes Balkash and Alak-tugulnoor, and<lb/>then beyond the course of the Ele, to the eastward of the Te-<lb/>moortu-nor (between lat. 44° and 49°), and which present the<lb/>appearance of a wall occasionally interrupted on the side of the<lb/>Kirghiz steppe.</p><lb/><p>It is quite otherwise with the portion of Central Asia, which<lb/>is bounded by the second and third systems of mountains, the<lb/>Himalaya and Kwan-lun. In fact, it is closed to the west in a<lb/>very evident manner by a transverse ridge, which is prolonged<lb/>from south to north, under the name of Bolor or Beloortagh <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">According to M. Klaproth, this transversal ridge is named in Ouigoor<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Boolyt-tagh,</hi> &#x2018;Cloudy Mountain&#x2019;, on account of the extraordinary rains which<lb/>fall uninterruptedly in this latitude during three months. West of this<lb/>transverse ridge of Beloor, is the station of Pamir, nearly under the parallel<lb/>of Cashgar. Marco Polo has named after this station a table-land, of which<lb/>modern geographers have made sometimes a chain of mountains, sometimes<lb/>a province situated farther to the south. This district is still interesting to<lb/>the naturalist, on account of the celebrated Venetian Traveller having first<lb/>observed there a fact, which has so often occurred in my experience, at con-<lb/>siderable elevations, in the New World, namely, that it is extremely difficult<lb/>to light and to keep fire in there.</note><lb/>This chain separates Little from Great Bucharia, and from<lb/>Cashgar, Badakshan and the Upper Jihoon or Amoodaria. Its<lb/>southern portion, which connects with the system of Kwan-lun<lb/>mountains, forms, according to the denomination used by the<lb/>Chinese, a part of the Tsung-ling. To the north it joins the<lb/>chain which passes to the north-west of Cashgar, and bears the<lb/>name of the defile of Cashgar (<hi rendition="#i">Cashgar-divan</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">davan</hi>), ac-<lb/>cording to the narrative of Nasaroff, who, in 1813, travelled as<lb/><pb n="234" facs="#f0008" />
    far as Kokand. Between Kokand, Dervazeh and Hissa, conse-<lb/>quently between the still unknown sources of the Sihoon and<lb/>Amoo-daria, the T&#x00EB;en-shan rises previous to sinking again in<lb/>the Khanat of Bokhara, and presents a group of lofty moun-<lb/>tains, several summits of which, such as the Takt-i-Suleyman,<lb/>the crest called Terek and others, are covered with snow even<lb/>in summer. Farther to the east, on the road which runs from<lb/>the western bank of lake Temoortu to Cashgar, the T&#x00EB;en-shan<lb/>does not appear to me to attain so great an elevation; at least<lb/>no mention is made of snow in the itinerary from Semipolatinsk<lb/>to Cashgar. The road passes to the east ward of lake Balkashi,<lb/>and to the westward of lake Yssi-kul or Temoortu, and traverses<lb/>the Narun or Narym, an affluent of the Sihoon. At 105 versts to<lb/>the south of the Narun, it goes over Mount Rovatt, which is<lb/>pretty high, and about fifteen versts wide; it has a large cavern,<lb/>and is situated between the At-bash, a small river, and the little<lb/>lake of Chater-kul. This is the culminating point previous to<lb/>arriving at the Chinese post placed to the south of the Aksu, a<lb/>small river of the steppe, the village of Artush, and Cashgar. This<lb/>city, built on the banks of the Aratumen, contains 15,000 houses<lb/>and 80,000 inhabitants, but is yet smaller than Samarkand.<lb/>The Cashgar-davan <note place="foot" n="*">The terms <hi rendition="#i">davan</hi> in Oriental-Turki, <hi rendition="#i">dabahn</hi> in Mongol, and <hi rendition="#i">dabagan</hi><lb/>in Manchoo, denote not a mountain, but a pass in a mountain; <hi rendition="#i">Cashgar da-<lb/>van,</hi> therefore, signifies only the pass across the mountains to Cashgar.&#x2014;<lb/><hi rendition="#k">Klaproth.</hi></note> does not appear to form a continuous wall,<lb/>but to offer an open passage at several points. M. Gens ex-<lb/>pressed to me his surprise that none of the numerous itineraries<lb/>of Bokharians which he has collected, make mention of a lofty<lb/>chain of mountains between Kokand and Cashgar. The great<lb/>snowy mountains seem not to reappear till east of the meridian<lb/>of Aksu, for these same itineraries mention Jeparleh <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;" xml:id="fn1-1" next="#fn1-2">This is the Moosar-tag, or <hi rendition="#i">glacier</hi> between Ele and Kucha. The ice<lb/>with which it is sheeted gives it the appearance of a mass of silver. A road,<lb/>called <hi rendition="#i">Mussar-dabahn,</hi> cut through these glaciers, leads from the SW. to the N.,<lb/>or, to speak more accurately, from Little Bucharia to Ele. The following is a<lb/>description of this mountain by a modern Chinese geographer: &#x2018;To the north<lb/>is the post station of Gakhtsa-karkai, and to the south that of Tamga-tash,<lb/>or Terma-Khada; they are distant from each other 120 <hi rendition="#i">le.</hi> On proceeding</note>, a <hi rendition="#i">glacier</hi><lb/><pb n="235" facs="#f0009" />
    covered with perpetual snow, on the Kura road, on the banks<lb/>of the Ele at Aksu, nearly half-way between the warm springs<lb/>of Arashan to the north of Kanjeilao, a Chinese station, and<lb/>the advanced post of Tamga-tash.</p><lb/><p>The western prolongation of the T&#x00EB;en-shan or Mooz-tag, as<lb/>the editors of the Memoirs of Sultan Baber called it by pre-<lb/><note place="foot" n="" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1">to the south, after quitting the former, the view extends over a vast space<lb/>covered with snow, which in winter is very deep. In summer, on the top of<lb/>the ice, snow and marshy places are found. Men and cattle follow the wind-<lb/>ing paths at the side of the mountain. Whoever is so imprudent as to ven-<lb/>ture upon this sea of snow is irrecoverably lost. After traversing upwards of<lb/>twenty <hi rendition="#i">le,</hi> you reach the glacier, where neither sand, trees, nor grass can be<lb/>seen: the most terrifying objects are the gigantic rocks formed of masses<lb/>of ice heaped upon one another. When the eye dwells upon the intervals<lb/>which separate these masses of ice, a gloomy chasm appears, into which the<lb/>light never penetrates. The sound of the water rushing beneath the ice re-<lb/>sembles the report of thunder. Carcasses of camels and horses are scattered<lb/>here and there. In order to facilitate the passage, steps have been cut in<lb/>the ice, to ascend and descend, but they are so slippery that they are ex-<lb/>tremely dangerous. Too frequently travellers find their graves in these pre-<lb/>cipices. Men and cattle walk in file, trembling with alarm, in these inhos-<lb/>pitable tracts. If night surprise the traveller, he must seek shelter under a<lb/>large stone; if the night happen to be calm, <hi rendition="#i">very pleasing sounds are heard,<lb/>like those of several instruments combined;</hi> it is the echo which repeats the<lb/>cracking noise produced by the breaking ice. The road, which is pursued<lb/>the day before, is not always that which it is convenient to follow the next<lb/>day. At a distance, to the west, a mountain, which has been hitherto inac-<lb/>cessible, displays its steep and icy summits. The halting-place of Tamga-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>tash is eighty <hi rendition="#i">le</hi> from this place. A river, called Moossur Gol, rushes with<lb/>frightful impetuosity from the edges of the ice, flows to the south-east, and<lb/>joins the Erghew, which falls into lake Lob. Four days&#x2019; journey to the<lb/>south of Tamga-tash, is an arid plain, which does not produce the smallest<lb/>plant. At eighty or ninety <hi rendition="#i">le</hi> further off, gigantic rocks still recur. The<lb/>commandant of Ushi sends every year one of his officers with oblations to<lb/>this glacier. The formula of the prayer recited on this occasion is trans-<lb/>mitted from Peking by the Tribunal of Rites. Ice is found along the whole<lb/>crest of the T&#x00EB;en-shan, if it is traversed lengthwise; but, on the contrary,<lb/>if it is crossed from north to south, that is in its width, ice is found only in<lb/>a space of a few <hi rendition="#i">le.</hi> Every morning ten men are employed in the pass of<lb/>Mussar-tag, in cutting steps for ascending and descending; in the afternoon<lb/>the sun has either melted them or rendered them extremely slippery. Some-<lb/>times the ice gives way under the feet of the travellers, and they are in-<lb/>gulfed, without a hope of ever seeing day-light again. The Mohamedans<lb/>of Little Bucharia sacrifice a ram previous to traversing these mountains.<lb/>Snow falls there throughout the year: it never rains.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Klaproth.</hi></note><lb/><pb n="236" facs="#f0010" />
eminence, deserves a particular notice. At the point where<lb/>the Beloor-tag joins the right angle of the Mooz-tag, or tra-<lb/>verses as a vein this great system, the latter continues its<lb/>course without interruption from east to west, under the deno-<lb/>mination of Asferah-tag, to the south of the Sihon, towards Kho-<lb/>jand and Urateppeth, in Ferghana. This chain of Asferah,<lb/>which is covered with perpetual snow, and is improperly called<lb/>the chain of Pamer, separates the sources of the Sihon (Jaxartes)<lb/>from those of the Amoo (Oxus); it turns to the south-west,<lb/>nearly in the meridian of Khojand, and in this direction is<lb/>called, as far as near Samarkand, Ak-tag (&#x201C;White or Snowy<lb/>Mountain&#x201D;), or Al-botom. Farther to the west, on the smiling<lb/>and fertile banks of the Kohik, commences the great dip or<lb/>depression of land, comprehending Great Bucharia, the coun-<lb/>try of Maveralnahar, which is so low, and where the highly-cul-<lb/>tivated soil and the wealth of the towns attract periodically the<lb/>invasions of the people of Iran, Candahar, and Upper Mon-<lb/>golia; but beyond the Caspian Sea, nearly in the same latitude,<lb/>and in the same direction as the T&#x00EB;en-shan, appears the<lb/>Caucasus, with its porphyritic and trachytic rocks. One is in-<lb/>clined, therefore, to regard it as a continuation of the rent,<lb/>in the form of a vein, on which the T&#x00EB;en-shan rises in the east,<lb/>just as, to the west of the great group of the mountains of<lb/>Azerbaijan and Armenia, is observable, in Taurus, a continua-<lb/>tion of the action of the fissure of the Himalaya and the Hindu<lb/>Coosh. It is thus that, in a geognostic sense, the disjointed<lb/>members of the mountains of Western Asia, as Mr Ritter, in<lb/>his excellent View of Asia, calls them, connect themselves with<lb/>the forms of the land in the east.</p><lb/><p>III. <hi rendition="#i">The System of the Kwan-lun,</hi> or Koolkun, or Tartash-<lb/>davan, enters Khoten (Elechi <note place="foot" n="*">The position of Knoten is very incorrectly laid down in all the maps.<lb/>Its latitude, according to the astronomical observations of the Missionaries<lb/>Felix d&#x2019;Arocha, Espinha, and Hallerstein, is 37° 0&#x2032;; the longitude 35° 52&#x2032; W.<lb/>of Peking. This longitude determines the mean direction of the Kwan-<lb/>lun</note>), where Hindu civilization and<lb/>the worship of Buddha penetrated 500 years before it reached<lb/><pb n="237" facs="#f0011" />
  Tibet and Ladak, between the group of mountains of Kookoo-<lb/>noor and Eastern Tibet, and the country called Kachi.</p><lb/><p>This system of mountains commence westward of the Tsung-<lb/>ling (&#x201C;Onion or Blue Mountains&#x201D;), upon which M. Abel<lb/>Rémusat has diffused so much light in his learned <hi rendition="#i">History of<lb/>Khoten.</hi> This system connects itself, as already observed, with<lb/>the transverse chain of Bolor; and according to the Chinese<lb/>books, forms the southern portion of it. This quarter of the globe,<lb/>between Little Tibet and Badakshan, abounding in rubies,<lb/>lazulite, and turquoise, is very little known; and, according to<lb/>recent accounts, the table-land of Khorasan, which runs to-<lb/>wards Herat, and bounds the Hindu-Kho or Hindu-Coosh to<lb/>the north, appears to be a continuation of the system of the<lb/>Kwan-lun to the west, rather than a prolongation of the Hima-<lb/>laya, as commonly supposed. From the Tsung-ling, the Kwan-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>lun or Koolkun runs from west to east, towards the sources of<lb/>the Hwang-ho (Yellow River), and penetrates, with its snowy<lb/>peaks into the Chinese province of Shen-se. Nearly in the<lb/>meridian of these sources, rises the great cluster of mountains of<lb/>lake Kookoo-noor, a cluster which supports itself, on the north,<lb/>against the snowy chain of the Nan-shan, or Ki-lian-shan, ex-<lb/>tending also from west to east. Between the Nan-shan and the<lb/>T&#x00EB;en-shan, on the side of Hami, the mountains of Tangout<lb/>bound the edge of the high desert of Gohi or Shamo, which<lb/>stretches from south-west to north-east. The latitude of the<lb/>middle portion of the Kwan-lun is about 35° 30&#x2032;.</p><lb/><p>IV. <hi rendition="#i">System of the Himalaya,</hi>&#x2014;This separates the valleys of<lb/>Cashmer (Serinagur) and Nepal from Butan and Tibet; to the<lb/>west, it stretches by Jevahir, to 4026 toises (26,420 feet); to<lb/>the east, by Dhavalaghiri, to 4390 (28,809 feet) of actual<lb/>height above the level of the sea: it runs generally in a direc-<lb/>tion from NW. to SE., and consequently is not parallel with<lb/>the Kwan-lun; it approaches it so nearly, in the meridian of<lb/>Attock and Jellalabad, that between Cabul, Cashmer, Ladak,<lb/>and Badakshan, the Himalaya seems to form only a single mass<lb/>of mountains with the Hindu-Kho and the Tsung-ling. In<lb/>like manner, the space between the Himalaya and the Kwan-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>lun is more shut up with secondary chains and isolated masses<lb/><pb n="238" facs="#f0012" />
    of mountains, than the table-lands between the first, second, and<lb/>third systems of mountains. Consequently, Tibet and Kachi<lb/>cannot properly be compared, in respect to their geognostic<lb/>construction, with the elevated longitudinal valleys <note place="foot" n="*">In the Andes, I found that the mean height of the longitudinal val-<lb/>ley between the Eastern and Western Cordilleras, from the cluster of moun-<lb/>tains of Los Robles, near Popayan, to that of Pasco, as well as those in 2°<lb/>20&#x2032; N. Lat. to 10° 30&#x2032; S. Lat., was about 1500 toises (9843 feet). The table-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>land, or rather longitudinal valley of Tiahuanaco, along the Lake of Titicaca,<lb/>the primitive seat of Peruvian civilization, is more elevated than the Peak<lb/>of Teneriffe. However, according to my experience, it cannot be asserted<lb/>generally that the absolute height to which the bottom of the longitudinal val-<lb/>leys appears to have been raised by subterranean force, augments with the<lb/>absolute height of the neighbouring chains. In like manner, the elevation<lb/>of isolated chains above the valleys is very various, showing that at the<lb/>foot of the chain the raised plain is elevated at the same time, or has pre-<lb/>served its ancient level.</note>, situated<lb/>between the chain of the eastern and western Andes, for ex-<lb/>ample, with the table-land which encloses the lake of Titicaca,<lb/>a correct observer of which (Mr Pentland) found that its ele-<lb/>vation above the sea was 1986 toises (13,033 feet). Neverthe-<lb/>less, it must not be represented that the height of the table-land<lb/>between the Kwan-lun and the Himalaya, as well as in all the<lb/>rest of Central Asia, is equal throughout. The mildness of the<lb/>winters, and the cultivation of the vine <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">The cultivation of plants, whose vegetable life is almost limited to<lb/>the duration of summer, and which, despoiled of leaves, remain benumbed du-<lb/>ring winter, may be accounted for by the influence which vast table-lands<lb/>exert upon the radiation of heat; but it is not the same with the less<lb/>rigour of winters, when we refer to elevations of 1800 to 2000 toises<lb/>(11,812 to 13,125 feet) at six degrees to the north of the equinoctial zone.</note>, in the gardens of<lb/>H&#x2019;lassa, in the parallel of 29° 40&#x2032;,&#x2014;facts ascertained by the ac-<lb/>counts published by M. Klaproth and the Archimandrite<lb/><persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118898388">Hyacinth</persName>,&#x2014;proclaim the existence of deep valleys and circular<lb/>hollows. Two considerable rivers, the Indus and the Zzambo<lb/>(Sampoo <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">The researches of M. Klaproth have proved that this river, which is<lb/>entirely separated from the system of the Brahmaputra, is identical with<lb/>the Irrawaddy of the Burmese empire.</note>), denote a depression in the table-land of Tibet, to<lb/>the north-west and south-east, the axis of which is found nearly<lb/>in the meridian of the gigantic Javahir, the two sacred lakes of<lb/>Manassoravara and Ravana Hrada, and Mount Ca&#x012B;lasa, or<lb/><pb n="239" facs="#f0013" />
    Cailas, in Chinese O-new-ta, and in Tibetan Gang-dis-ri. From<lb/>this nucleus springs the chain of Kara-korum-padisha, which<lb/>runs to the north-west, consequently to the north of Ladak, to-<lb/>wards the Tsung-ling; and the snowy chains of Hor (Khor)<lb/>and Zzang, which runs to the east. That of Hor, at its north-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>western extremity, connects itself with the Kwan-lun; its course,<lb/>from the eastern side, is towards the Tangri-noor (&#x201C;Lake of<lb/>Heaven&#x201D;). The Zzang, farther to the south than the chain of<lb/>Hor, bounds the long valley of the Zzangbo, and runs from<lb/>west to east, towards the N&#x00EB;en-tsin-tangla-gangri, a very lofty<lb/>summit which, between H&#x2019;lassa and lake Tangri-noor (impro-<lb/>perly called Terkiri), terminates at Mount Nom-shun-ubashi.<lb/>Between the meridians of Ghorka, Katmandu, and H&#x2019;lassa, the<lb/>Himalaya sends out to the north, towards the right bank, or<lb/>the southern border of the valley of the Zzang-bo, several<lb/>branches covered with perpetual snow. The highest is Yaria-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>shamboy-gangri, the name of which, in Tibetan, signifies &#x201C;the<lb/>snowy mountains in the country of the self-existing deity.&#x201D;<lb/>This peak is to the westward of lake Yamruk-yumdzo, which<lb/>our maps call Palteh <note place="foot" n="*">There can be no doubt that <hi rendition="#i">Palteh</hi> is derived from <hi rendition="#i">Bhaldi,</hi> the Tibetan<lb/>name of a town a little to the north, which has been corrupted by the Chinese<lb/>into <hi rendition="#i">Peiti</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">Peti</hi>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Klaproth.</hi></note>, and which resembles a ring, being al-<lb/>most filled by an island.</p><lb/><p>If, availing ourselves of the Chinese writings which M.<lb/>Klaproth has collected, we follow the system of the Himalaya<lb/>towards the east, beyond the English territories in Hindustan,<lb/>we perceive that it bounds Assam to the north, contains the<lb/>sources of the Brahmaputra, passes through the northern part<lb/>of Ava, and penetrates into the Chinese province of Yun-nan,<lb/>where, to the westward of Yung-chang, it exhibits sharp and<lb/>snowy peaks; it turns abruptly to the north-east on the confines<lb/>of Ho-kwang, of Keang-si, and of Fuh-kien, and extends with<lb/>its snowy summits near to the ocean, where we find, as if it was<lb/>a prolongation of this chain, an island (Formosa), the moun-<lb/>tains of which are covered with snow during the greatest part of<lb/>the summer, which shows an elevation of at least 1900 toises<lb/>(12,469 feet). Thus we may follow the system of the Hima-<lb/>laya, as a continuous chain, from the Eastern Ocean, and track<lb/><pb n="240" facs="#f0014" />
it by the Hindu-Coosh, across Candahar and Khorasan; and<lb/>lastly as far as the Caspian Sea in Azerbaijan, through an ex-<lb/>tent of seventy-three degrees of longitude, half that of the<lb/>Andes. The western extremity, which is volcanic, but covered<lb/>likewise with snow to Demavend, loses the peculiar character<lb/>of a chain in the cluster of the mountains of Armenia, con-<lb/>nected with the Sangalu, the Bingheul, and Cashmer-dag, lofty<lb/>summits in the pashalic of Erzeroum. The mean direction of<lb/>the system of the Himalaya is N. 55° W.</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">(To be continued.)</hi></hi></p><lb/><pb n="145" facs="#f0015" />
<div n="2"><head><hi rendition="#i">On the Chains of Mountains and Volcanoes of Central Asia.</hi><lb/>By <hi rendition="#k">Baron A. Von Humboldt.</hi> (Concluded from preced-<lb/>ing Volume, p. 240.)</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k"><hi rendition="#in">S</hi>uch</hi> are the principal features of a geognostical description of<lb/>Central Asia, which I have drawn up with the aid of numerous<lb/>materials accumulated by me during a long series of years.<lb/>Of these materials, the portion for which we are indebted to<lb/>modern European travellers is of small importance, in com-<lb/>parison with the prodigious space which is occupied by the<lb/>chain of the Alta&#x00EF;, the Himalaya mountains, the transverse<lb/>ridges of the Bolor and the Kingkan. Those who, at the pre-<lb/>sent day, have published the most important and complete de-<lb/>tails on these subjects are the learned persons who are conver-<lb/>sant with Chinese, Manchoo, and Mongol literature. The more<lb/>general the cultivation of the Asiatic dialects shall become, the<lb/>better shall we appreciate the utility of these so-long-neglected<lb/>sources, for the study of the geognostic constitution of Central<lb/>Asia. Until M. Klaproth diffuses a new light upon this study<lb/>by a special work of his own, the picture which I have here ex-<lb/>hibited of the four systems of mountains which run from east to<lb/>west, the materials for which were, in a great part furnished by<lb/>the learned person whom I have just named, will not be with-<lb/>out its use. In order to ascertain the characteristic properties<lb/>which are to be found in the inequalities of the globe&#x2019;s surface,<lb/>and to discover the laws which regulate the local disposition of<lb/>the masses of mountains, and the depressions, we may have<lb/>recourse to the analogy which other continents may offer. If<lb/>once the grand forms and predominating courses of the chains<lb/>are well determined, we shall see connected with this fundamen-<lb/>tal principle, as with a common type, whatever appeared at first<lb/>isolated in these phenomena, and at variance with rules, pro-<lb/>claiming another date of formation. This method, which I fol-<lb/>lowed in my geognostic description of South America, I have<lb/>endeavoured to apply here to the limits of the grand masses of<lb/>Central Asia.</p><lb/><p>In taking a last view of the four systems of mountains which<lb/>divide the continent of Asia from east to west, we observe<lb/><pb n="146" facs="#f0016" />
that the southern has the greatest extent, and the fullest de-<lb/>velopment in respect of length. The Alta&#x00EF; hardly attains,<lb/>with its elevated summits, the 78th degree; the T&#x00EB;en-shan, the<lb/>chain at whose foot are situated Hami, Aksu, and Cashgar,<lb/>reaches at least to the meridian of 69° 45&#x2032;; provided we place<lb/>Cashgar, according to the authority of the missionaries, in 71°<lb/>37&#x2032; east of Paris <note place="foot" n="*">The astronomical geography of Inner Asia is still very confused, because<lb/>the elements of the observations are not known, merely the results.</note>. The third and fourth systems are, as it were,<lb/>blended in the grand clusters of Badakshan, Little Tibet, and<lb/>Cashgar. Beyond the 69th and 70th meridians there is but one<lb/>chain, that of the Hindu-Kho, which is depressed towards He-<lb/>rat, but which afterwards, to the southward of Asterabad, rises<lb/>to a considerable height towards the volcanic and snowy moun-<lb/>tain of Demavend. The table-land of Iran, which, in its great-<lb/>est extension, from Tehran to Shiraz, appears to attain the ave-<lb/>rage height of 650 toises (4265 feet), throws off, towards India<lb/>and Tibet, two branches, the Himalaya and the Kwan-lun chain,<lb/>and forms a bifurcation of the rent from which the mountain-<lb/>ous masses arose. Thus the Kwan-lun may be considered as a<lb/>saliant branch of the Himalaya. The intermediate space, com-<lb/>prising Tibet and Katchi, is intersected by numerous rents in all<lb/>directions. This analogy with the most common phenomena of<lb/>the formation of veins is manifested in a very striking manner,<lb/>as I have elsewhere shewn, in the long and narrow line of the<lb/>Cordilleras of the New World.</p><lb/><p>We may trace beyond the Caspian Sea, to the 45th meridian<lb/>(of Paris) the systems of the Himalaya and the Kwan-lun, which<lb/>are prolonged till they join in the group situated between Cash-<lb/>mer and Fyzabad. Thus the chain of the Himalaya remains<lb/>to the south of the Bolor, the Ak-tag, the Mingboolak, and the<lb/>Ala-tau, between Badakshan, Samerkand, and Turkestan; to the<lb/>east of the Caucasus it joins the table-land of Azerbidjan, and<lb/>bounds to the south the <hi rendition="#i">great depression,</hi> of which the Caspian<lb/>Sea and lake Aral <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">A series of barometrical levels continued throughout a very severe win-<lb/>ter, during the expedition of Colonel Berg, from the Caspian Sea to the west-<lb/>ern shore of Lake Aral, at the Bay Mertvoy Kultuk, by Captains Duhamel<lb/>and Anjou, has demonstrated that the level of Lake Aral is 117 English feet<lb/>above that of the Caspian Sea.</note> occupies the lowest basin, and in which a con-<lb/>siderable portion of the land whose surface is probably 18,000<lb/><pb n="147" facs="#f0017" />
square leagues, and which lies between the Kooma, the Don, the<lb/>Volga, the Yak, the Obsheysyrt, lake Aksakal, the Lower Sihon,<lb/>and the Khanat of Khiva, upon the shores of the Amoo-daria,<lb/>is situated below the level of the ocean. The existence of this<lb/>singular depression has been the object of laborious barometrical<lb/>observations of levels between the Caspian Sea and the Black<lb/>Sea, by MM. Parrot and Engelhardt; between Orenburg and<lb/>Gouriev at the mouth of the Yaik, by MM. Helmersen and<lb/>Hoffmann. This very low country is abundant in tertiary forma-<lb/>tions, whence proceeds melaphyre, and <hi rendition="#i">debris</hi> of scorified rocks,<lb/>and offers to the geognostic inquirer, from the constitution of its<lb/>soil, a phenomena hitherto unique in our planet. To the south<lb/>of Baku, and in the Gulf of Balkan, this aspect is materially<lb/>modified by volcanic forces. The Academy of Sciences of St<lb/>Petersburgh has recently complied with my solicitations to get<lb/>determined by a series of stations of barometric levels upon<lb/>north-eastern edge of this basin, upon the Volga between Kamy-<lb/>shin and Saratov, upon the Yaik between the Obsheysyrt, Oren-<lb/>burg, and the Uralsk, upon the Yemba and beyond the hills of<lb/>Mougojar, by which the Ural extends itself towards the south<lb/>on the side of lake Aksakal and towards Sarasu, the position of<lb/>a geod&#x0153;sic line, uniting all the points at the level of the surface<lb/>of the ocean.</p><lb/><p>I have referred already to the hypothesis, according to which<lb/>this great depression of the land of Western Asia was formerly<lb/>continued as far as the mouth of the Ob and the Frozen Sea, by<lb/>a valley traversing the desert of Kara-koum and the numerous<lb/>groups of oases in the steppes of the Kirghiz and Baraba. Its<lb/>origin appears to me to be more ancient than that of the Ural<lb/>mountains, the southern prolongation of which may be traced in<lb/>an uninterrupted course from the table-land of Gaberlinsk to<lb/>Oustoort, between lake Aral and the Caspian Sea. Would not<lb/>a chain, whose height is so inconsiderable, have entirely dis-<lb/>appeared if the great rent of the Ural had not been formed<lb/>subsequently to this depression? Consequently, the period of<lb/>the sinking of Western Asia coincides rather with that of the<lb/>rising of the table-land of Iran, that of Central Asia, the Hima-<lb/>laya, the Kwan-lun, the T&#x00EB;en-shan, and all the old systems of<lb/>mountains running from east to west; perhaps also with the<lb/><pb n="148" facs="#f0018" />
period of the upraising of the Caucasus and the cluster of moun-<lb/>tains of Armenia and Erzeroum. No part of the earth, not<lb/>even excepting South Africa, presents a mass of land so extensive,<lb/>and elevated to so great a height, as that in Central Asia. The<lb/>principal axis of this upraising, which probably preceded the<lb/>eruption of the chains from the rents running from east to west,<lb/>as in the direction of S. W. and N. E., from the group of moun-<lb/>tains between Cashmer, Badakshan, and the Tsung-ling in Tibet,<lb/>where are situated the Ca&#x00EF;lasa, and the sacred lakes<note place="foot" n="*">The lakes Manasa and Ravan Hrad. <hi rendition="#i">Manasa,</hi> in Sanscrit, signifies<lb/>&#x201C;spirit.&#x201D; Manasa-vara is the easternmost of these two lakes: its name means<lb/>literally &#x201C;the most perfect of honourable lakes.&#x201D; The westernmost lake is<lb/>named <hi rendition="#i">Ravanah Hrad,</hi> or &#x201C;Lake of Ravana,&#x201D; after the celebrated hero of the<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Ramayana.</hi>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Bopp.</hi></note>, as far as<lb/>the snowy summits of the Inshan and Khingkan<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">This direction of the axis of elevation from the S. W. to the N. E. is<lb/>again found beyond the 55th degree of latitude, in the space comprised be-<lb/>tween Western Siberia, a low country, and Eastern Siberia, a country full of<lb/>chains of mountains: this space is bounded by the meridian of Irkutsk, the<lb/>Frozen Sea, and the Sea of Okotsk. Dr Erdman has discovered among the<lb/>Aldan mountains, at Allakh-yuma, a peak 5000 feet high. To the north of<lb/>the Kwan-lun, the chain of Northern Tibet, and to the west of the meridian<lb/>of Peking, the portions of elevated land most important in respect to the ex-<lb/>tent and height, are the following:&#x2014;1. To the east of the cluster of the Kook-<lb/>oonoor, the space between Toorfan, Tangut, the great sinuosity of the<lb/>Hoang-ho, Garjan, and the chain of the Khing-khan, a space which compre-<lb/>hends the great desert of Gobi. 2. The table-land between the snowy moun-<lb/>tains of Khangai and Tangnu, and between the sources of the Yenise&#x00EF;, the<lb/>Selengga and the Amoor. 3. To the west of the district watered by the upper<lb/>course of the Oxus (Amou), and of the Jaxartes (Sihoon); between Fyzabad,<lb/>Balkh, Samarkand and the Ala-tau near Turkestan, to the westward of the<lb/>Bolor (Beloot-tag). The upraising of this transverse ridge has produced in<lb/>the soil of the great longitudinal valley of the T&#x00EB;en-shan-nar-lu, between the<lb/>second and third systems of mountains from east to west, or between the<lb/>T&#x00EB;en-shan and the Kwanlun, a counter-slope from west to east, whilst in the<lb/>longitudinal valley of the T&#x00EB;enshan-pe-lu in Zungaria, between the T&#x00EB;en-shan<lb/>and the Alta&#x00EF;, a general declivity is observable from east to west.</note>. The eleva-<lb/>tion from below of so enormous a mass would suffice to produce<lb/>a sinking or hollow which, even at the present day, is perhaps<lb/>not half filled with water, and which, since it was formed, has<lb/>been so modified by the action of subterranean forces, that, ac-<lb/>cording to the traditions of Tartars, collected by Professor Eich-<lb/>wald, the promontory of Absheron was formerly united by an<lb/>isthmus with the opposite coast of the Caspian Sea in Turco-<lb/>mania. The great lakes, which have been formed in Europe<lb/><pb n="149" facs="#f0019" />
  at the foot of the Alps, are a phenomenon analogous to the ca-<lb/>vity in which the Caspian Sea is situated, and owe in the same<lb/>manner their origin to a sinking of the land. We shall soon<lb/>see that it is principally in the compass of this hollow, conse-<lb/>quently in the space where the resistance was least, that recent<lb/>traces of volcanic action are apparent.</p><lb/><p>The position of mount Aral-toube, which formerly emitted<lb/>fire, of the existence of which I became aware from the itine-<lb/>raries of Colonel Gens, becomes more interesting when we com-<lb/>pare it with that of the volcanoes of Pechan and Ho-tcheou, on<lb/>the northern and southern sides of the T&#x00EB;en-shan, with that of<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">solfatara</hi> of Ouroumtsi, and with that of the adjoining chasm<lb/>of lake Darlai, which exhales ammoniacal vapours. The re-<lb/>searches of MM. Klaproth and Rémusat acquainted us with<lb/>this last fact upwards of six years ago.</p><lb/><p>The volcano situated in about the latitude of 42° 25&#x2032; or 42° 35&#x2032;,<lb/>between Korgos, on the banks of the Ele, and Kouche, in Little<lb/>Bucharia, belongs to the chain of the T&#x00EB;en-shan: perhaps it<lb/>may be on the northern face, three degrees to the eastward of<lb/>lake Yssi-kul or Tremoortu. Chinese authors call it P&#x00EF;h-shan<lb/>(&#x201C;White Mountain&#x201D;), Ho-shan, and Aghi (&#x201C;Fiery Moun-<lb/>tain&#x201D;)<note place="foot" n="*">The details given M. Klaproth (<hi rendition="#i">Tabl. Hist. de l&#x2019;Asie,</hi> p. 110; <hi rendition="#i">Mem.</hi> re-<lb/>latifs á l&#x2019;Asie, t. ii. p. 358) are the most complete, and derived principally<lb/>from the history of the Ming dynasty. M. Abel-Rémusat (<hi rendition="#i">Journ. Asiat.</hi> t. v.<lb/>p. 45; <hi rendition="#i">Descrip. de Khotan,</hi> t. ii. p. 9), has added more in the Japanese trans-<lb/>lation of the grand Chinese Encyclopedia. The root <hi rendition="#i">ag,</hi> which is found in<lb/>the word <hi rendition="#i">Aghi,</hi> according to M. Klaproth, signifies &#x201C;fire&#x201D; in Hindustani.<lb/>To the south of Pih-shan, in the neighbourhood of Khoten, belonging to the<lb/>T&#x00EB;en-shan-nar-lu, there can be no doubt that, prior to our era, Sanscrit was<lb/>spoken, or a language possessing a strong analogy with it: but in Sanscrit a<lb/>flaming mountain is called Agni-ghri. According to M. Bopp, <hi rendition="#i">Aghi</hi> is not a<lb/>Sancrit word.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi><lb/>The root <hi rendition="#i">ag,</hi> which is found in the word <hi rendition="#i">Aghi,</hi> signifies &#x201C;fire&#x201D; in all the<lb/>dialects of Hindustan; this element is <hi rendition="#i">ag</hi> in Hindustani, <hi rendition="#i">agh</hi> in Mahratta,<lb/>and the form of <hi rendition="#i">agi</hi> is still preserved in the dialect of the Punjab. The word<lb/><hi rendition="#i">agni,</hi> by which &#x201C;fire&#x201D; is commonly designated in Sanscrit, belongs to the same<lb/>root, as well as <hi rendition="#i">agun</hi> in Bengalee, <hi rendition="#i">ogun</hi> in Russian, and the <hi rendition="#i">ignis</hi> of the<lb/>Latins.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Klaproth.</hi></note>. It is not known with certainty whether the name of <hi rendition="#i">P&#x012D;h-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>shan</hi> implies that its summit reaches the line of perpetual snow,<lb/>which the height of this mountain would determine, at least the<lb/>minimum; or whether it merely denotes the glittering hue of a<lb/><pb n="150" facs="#f0020" />
    peak covered with saline substances, pumice-stone, and volcanic<lb/>ashes in decomposition. A Chinese author of the seventh cen-<lb/>tury says: At 200 <hi rendition="#i">le,</hi> or fifteen leagues, to the north of the city<lb/>of Kwei-chow (now Koutche), in about the latitude of 41° 37 and<lb/>longitude 80° 35&#x2032; E., according to the astronomical determina-<lb/>tion of the missionaries made in the country of the Eleuths, rises<lb/>the Pechan, which emits fire and smoke without interruption.<lb/>It is from thence sal ammoniac is brought; upon one of the de-<lb/>clivities of the Fiery Mountain (Ho-tcheou), all the stones burn,<lb/>melt, and flow to a distance of some tens of <hi rendition="#i">le.</hi> The fused mass <note place="foot" n="*">The history of the Chinese dynasty Tang, speaking of the lava from the<lb/>Pih-shan, states that it ran like liquid fat.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Klaproth.</hi></note><lb/>hardens as it becomes cold. The natives use it in disorders <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">This is not lava, but the saline particles which appear in the form of an<lb/>efflorescence on its surface.</note><lb/>as a medicine: sulphur is also found there.</p><lb/><p>M. Klaproth observes, that this mountain is now called Kha-<lb/>lar <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">The Pih-shan of the ancient Chinese, at present has the Turk name of<lb/>Eshik-bosh; <hi rendition="#i">Eshik</hi> is a species of goat, and <hi rendition="#i">bash</hi> signifies &#x201C;head.&#x201D; Sulphur<lb/>is produced there in abundance. The Eshik-bash belongs to the elevated<lb/>mountains, which, in the time of the Wei dynasty (the third century) bound-<lb/>ed, to the north-west, the kingdom of Kwei-tsu (Ku-cha); it is the Aghi-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>shan under the Suy dynasty (in the early moiety of the seventh century).<lb/>The history of this dynasty relates that this mountain always shewed fire<lb/>and smoke, and that sal-ammoniac was obtained there. In the description of<lb/>the western country, which forms a part of the history of the Tang dynas-<lb/>ty, we find that the mountain in question was then called Aghi-teen-shan<lb/>(which may be translated &#x201C;mountain of fields of fire&#x201D;), or Pih-shan (&#x201C;white<lb/>mountain&#x201D;), that it was to the north of the city of Ilolo, and that it emitted<lb/>perpetual fire. Ilolo (or perhaps Irolo, Ilor, or Irol) was then the residence<lb/>of the King of Kwei-tsu.<lb/>The Eshik-bash is to the north of Ku-cha, and 200 leagues to the west of<lb/>the Kan-tengri, which forms part of the chain of the Teen-chan. The Eshik-<lb/>bash is very large, and much sulphur and sal-ammoniac is even now col-<lb/>lected there. It gives birth to the river Eshik-bash-gol, which flows to the<lb/>south of the city of Kucha, and falls, after a course of 200 <hi rendition="#i">le,</hi> into the<lb/>Erghew.</note>, and that, conformably to the account given by the Bok-<lb/>hars, who bring to Siberia sal-ammoniac (called <hi rendition="#i">nao-sha</hi> in<lb/>Chinese, and <hi rendition="#i">n&#x014D;sh&#x0101;der</hi> in Persian), the mountains to the south of<lb/>Korgos is so abundant in this species of salt, that the natives<lb/>frequently employ it as a means of paying their tribute to the<lb/>Emperor of China. In a recent <hi rendition="#i">Description of Central Asia,</hi><lb/><pb n="151" facs="#f0021" />
published at Peking in 1777, we find the following statement:<lb/>&#x2014;&#x201C; The province of Ku-cha produces copper, saltpetre, sul-<lb/>phur, and sal-ammoniac. The latter article comes from an am-<lb/>moniac mountain to the north of the city of Koutche, which is<lb/>full of chasms and caverns. These apertures in spring, sum-<lb/>mer, and autumn, are filled to such a degree, that, during the<lb/>night, the mountain appears illuminated by thousands of lamps.<lb/>No one is then able to approach it. In winter alone, when the<lb/>vast quantity of snow has extinguished the fire, the natives are<lb/>able to labour in collecting the sal-ammoniac, for which purpose<lb/>they strip themselves quite naked. The salt is found in ca-<lb/>verns, in the form of stalactites, which renders it difficult to be<lb/>detached.&#x201D; The name of Tartarian salt, formerly given in<lb/>commerce to this salt, ought to have long ago directed attention<lb/>to the volcanic phenomena of Central Asia.</p><lb/><p>M. Cordier, in his letter to M. Abel Rémusat, &#x201C;on the ex-<lb/>istence of two burning volcanoes in Central Asia,&#x201D; calls Pechan<lb/>a <hi rendition="#i">solfatara</hi> like that of Puzzuoli. In the state in which it is<lb/>described in the work cited farther back, the Pechan might<lb/>well deserve only the name of an extinct volcano, although the<lb/>igneous phenomena are wanting in the solfataras I have seen:<lb/>such as those of Puzzuoli, the crater of the Peak of Teneriffe,<lb/>the Rucu-pichincha, and the volcano of Jorullo; but passages in<lb/>more ancient Chinese historians, who relate the march of the ar-<lb/>my of the Heung-nus, in the first century of our era, speak of<lb/>masses of rocks in fusion flowing to the distance of some miles:<lb/>so that it is impossible, in these expressions, not to understand<lb/>eruptions of lava. The ammoniac mountain between Koutche<lb/>and Korgos has also been a volcano, in activity, in the strictest<lb/>sense of the word: a volcano which emitted torrents of lava in<lb/>the centre of Asia, 400 geographical leagues from the Caspian<lb/>Sea to the west, 433 from the Frozen Sea to the north, 504<lb/>from the Great Ocean to the east, and 440 from the Indian Ocean<lb/>to the south. This is not the place to discuss the question rela-<lb/>tive to the influence of the proximity of the sea on the action of<lb/>volcanoes; I merely solicit attention to the geographical posi-<lb/>tion of the volcanoes of Inner Asia, and their reciprocal rela-<lb/>tions. The Pechan is distant from 300 to 400 leagues from<lb/>all the seas. When I returned from Mexico, some celebrated<lb/><pb n="152" facs="#f0022" />
mineralogists expressed their astonishment when they heard me<lb/>speak of the volcanic eruption of the plain of Jorullo, and of the<lb/>volcano of Popocatepetl, as still in activity: although the former<lb/>is only thirty leagues from the sea, and the latter forty-three<lb/>leagues. Gebel Koldaghi, a conical and smoking mountain of<lb/>Kordofan, of which Mr Rüppel was told at Dongola, is 150<lb/>leagues from the Red Sea, and this distance is but a third of<lb/>that at which the Pechan, which for 1700 years has emitted<lb/>torrents of lava, is situated from the Indian Ocean. The hy-<lb/>pothesis, conformably to which the Andes present no volcano in<lb/>activity in those parts where the chain recedes from the sea, is<lb/>without foundation. The system of mountains of the Caraccas,<lb/>which run from east to west, or the chain of the coast of Vene-<lb/>zuela, is shaken by violent earthquakes, but has no longer<lb/>apertures which are in permanent communication with the in-<lb/>terior of the earth, and which discharge lava, than the chain of<lb/>the Himalaya, which is little more than 100 leagues from the<lb/>Gulf of Bengal, or the Ghauts, which may almost be termed a<lb/>coast-chain. Where trachyte has been unable to penetrate<lb/>across the chains when they have been elevated, they discover<lb/>no rents; no channels are opened, whereby the subterranean<lb/>forces can act in a permanent manner at the surface. The re-<lb/>markable fact of the proximity of the sea wherever volcanoes<lb/>are still in activity,&#x2014;a fact which, in general, is not to be de-<lb/>nied,&#x2014;seems to be accounted for less by the chemical agency<lb/>of the water, than by the configuration of the crust of the globe,<lb/>and the deficiency of resistance, which, in the vicinity of mari-<lb/>time basins, the upraised masses of the Continent oppose to<lb/>elastic fluids, and to the efflux of matters in fusion in the interior<lb/>of our planet. Real volcanic phenomena may occur, as in the<lb/>old country of the Eleuths, and at Toorfan, to the south of the<lb/>T&#x00EB;en-shan, wherever, owing to ancient resolutions, a fissure is<lb/>opened in the crust of the globe at a distance from the sea. The<lb/>reason why volcanoes in activity are not more rarely remote<lb/>from the sea, is merely because, wherever an eruption has been<lb/>unable to force itself through the declivity of continental masses<lb/>towards a maritime basin, a very unusual concurrence of cir-<lb/>cumstances is requisite to permit a permanent communication<lb/>between the interior of the globe and the atmosphere, and to<lb/><pb n="153" facs="#f0023" />
form apertures, which, like intermittent warm springs, effuse,<lb/>instead of water, gases and oxidized earths in fusion, in other<lb/>words, lava.</p><lb/><p>To the eastward of Pechan, the &#x201C;White Mountain&#x201D; of the<lb/>Eleuths, the whole northern slope of the T&#x00EB;en-shan presents<lb/>volcanic phenomena: &#x201C;lava and pumice-stone are seen there,<lb/>and even considerable solfataras, which are called &#x2018;fiery places.&#x2019;<lb/>The solfatara of Ouroumtsi is five leagues in circumference;<lb/>in winter it is not covered with snow; it is supposed to be<lb/>full of ashes. If a stone be thrown into this basin, flames issue<lb/>forth, as well as a black smoke, which continues some time. Birds<lb/>dare not fly over these fiery places.&#x201D; Eastward, sixty leagues<lb/>from Pechan, is a lake of very considerable extent, the diffe-<lb/>rent names of which in the Chinese, Kirghiz, and Calmuc lan-<lb/>guages, signify, &#x201C;warm salt and ferruginous water.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>If we cross the volcanic chain of the T&#x00EB;en-shan, we find<lb/>E. S. E. of lake Issikoul (so often mentioned in the itineraries<lb/>which I have collected), and of the volcano of the Pechan, the<lb/>volcano of Toorfan, which may also be called the volcano of<lb/>Ho-chow (&#x201C;City of Fire&#x201D;), for it is very near that city <note place="foot" n="*">Ho-chow, a city, now destroyed, was a league and a half to the east of<lb/>Toorfan.</note>. M.<lb/>Abel Rémusat has made particular mention of this volcano in<lb/>his <hi rendition="#i">Histoire de Khoten,</hi> and in his letter to M. Cordier <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">M. Rémusat calls the volcano of Pechan, to the north of Koutche, the<lb/>volcano of Bishbalik. From the time of the Mongols in China, all the coun-<lb/>try between the northern slope of the Téen-shan and the little chain of the<lb/>Tarbagatay has been called Bishbalik.</note>. No<lb/>reference is made to stony masses in fusion (torrents of lava),<lb/>there, as at Pechan; but &#x201C;a column of smoke is seen continu-<lb/>ally to issue; this smoke gives place at night to a flame like that<lb/>of a torch. Birds and other animals upon which the light falls,<lb/>appear of a red colour. The natives, when they go thither to<lb/>collect the <hi rendition="#i">nao-sha,</hi> or sal-ammoniac, put on wooden shoes, for<lb/>leather soles would be very soon burned.&#x201D; Sal-ammoniac is pro-<lb/>cured at the volcano of Ho-tcheou, not only in the form of a crust<lb/>or sediment, according as it is deposited by the vapours which<lb/>exhale it; but Chinese books likewise make mention &#x201C;of a<lb/>greenish liquor collected in cavities, which is boiled and evapo-<lb/><pb n="154" facs="#f0024" />
  rated, and from it sal-ammoniac is obtained in the form of small<lb/>lumps like sugar, of extreme whiteness, and perfect purity.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>Pechan and the volcano of Ho-tcheou or Tufan are 140<lb/>leagues apart, in the direction of east and west. About forty<lb/>leagues westward of the meridian of Ho-tcheou, at the foot of the<lb/>gigantic Bokhda-ula, is the great solfatara of Ouroumtsi. At<lb/>140 leagues north-west of this, in a plain adjoining the banks of<lb/>the Kobok, which flows into the small lake of Darlai, rises a<lb/>hill, &#x201C;the clefts of which are very warm, though they do not<lb/>exhale smoke (visible vapours): the sal-ammoniac, in these cre-<lb/>vices is sublimed into so solid a coating, that the stone is obliged<lb/>to be broken in order to get it.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>These four places hitherto known, namely, Pechan, Ho-<lb/>tcheou, Ouroumtsi, and Kobok, which exhibit evident volcanic<lb/>phenomena, in the interior of Asia, are 130 or 140 leagues to<lb/>the south of the point of Chinese Zungaria, where I was at the<lb/>beginning of 1829. Aral-toube, the conical and insular moun-<lb/>tain of Lake Ala-kul, which has been in a state of ignition in<lb/>historical times, and which is mentioned in the itineraries col-<lb/>lected at Semipolatinsk, is in the volcanic territory of Bishbalik.<lb/>This insular mountain is situated to the west of the ammoniac-<lb/>cavern of Kobok, and to the north of Pechan, which still<lb/>emits light, and which formerly discharged lava, and at a dis-<lb/>tance of sixty leagues from each of these two points. From<lb/>Lake Ala-kul to Lake Zaisang, where the Russian Cossacks of<lb/>the line of the Irtish, exercise the right of fishing, by conni-<lb/>vance of the Mandarins, the distance is reckoned at fifty-one<lb/>leagues. The Tarbagatai, at the foot of which is situated<lb/>Choogonchak, a town of Chinese Mongolia, and where Dr<lb/>Meyer, the learned and enterprising companion of M. Lede-<lb/>bour, fruitlessly essayed, in 1825, to prosecute his researches in<lb/>natural history, extends to the south-west of Lake Zaisang to-<lb/>wards the Ala-kul <note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn2-1" next="#fn2-2">I do not wish to express any doubt respecting the existence of the Ala-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>kul and the Alaktugul-noor lakes, in the vicinity of each other; but it ap-<lb/>pears singular to me, that the Tartars and Mongols, who traverse these parts<lb/>so often, and who have been questioned at Semipolatinsk, should only know<lb/>the Ala-kul, and assert that the Alaktugul-noor owes its existence to a con-<lb/>fusion of names. M. Pansner, in his Russian map of Inner Asia, which may<lb/>be implicitly relied on with regard to the country north of the course of the</note>. We are thus acquainted, in the interior<lb/><pb n="155" facs="#f0025" />
        of Asia, with a volcanic territory, the surface of which is upwards<lb/>of 2500 square leagues, and which is distant 300 or 400 leagues<lb/>from the sea: it occupies a moiety of the longitudinal valley situ-<lb/>ated between the first and second systems of mountains. The chief<lb/>seat of volcanic action seems to be in the T&#x00EB;en-shan. Perhaps<lb/>the colossal Bokhda-ula is a trachytic mountain like Chimbora-<lb/>zo. On the side north of the Tarbagatai and of Lake Darlai,<lb/>the action becomes weaker; yet Mr Rose and I found white<lb/>trachyte along the south-western declivity of the Alta&#x00EF;, upon a<lb/>bell-shaped hill at Ridderski, near the village of Butach-<lb/>chikha.</p><lb/><p>On both sides of the T&#x00EB;en-shan, north and south, violent<lb/>earthquakes are felt. The town of Aksou was entirely destroyed<lb/>by a convulsion of this kind at the beginning of the eighteenth<lb/>century. Professor Eversman, of Casan, whose repeated tra-<lb/>vels have made us acquainted with Bokhara, was told by a Tar-<lb/>tar, who was a servant of his, well acquainted with the country<lb/>between Lakes Balkashi and Ala-kul, that earthquakes were<lb/>very common there. In eastern Siberia, to the north of the fif-<lb/>tieth parallel, the centre of the circle of shocks appears to be at<lb/>Irktusk, and in the deep basin of Lake Baikal, where, on the<lb/>Kiachta road, especially on the banks of the Jeda, and the<lb/><note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn2-2" prev="#fn2-1">Ele, makes the Ala-kul (properly Ala-ghul, or &#x201C;party-coloured lake&#x201D;) com-<lb/>municate with the Alaktugul by five channels. Possibly the isthmus which<lb/>separates these lakes, may be marshy, which causes them to be considered as<lb/>one. Casim Bek, a professor at Casan, and who is a Persian by birth, insists<lb/>that <hi rendition="#i">tugul</hi> is a Tartaro-Turkish negation, and that therefore, <hi rendition="#i">Altatugul</hi> signi-<lb/>fies &#x201C;the lake not variegated,&#x201D; as Ala-tau-ghul implies &#x201C;the lake of the va-<lb/>riegated mountain.&#x201D; Perhaps the names of Ala-kul and Ala-tugul mean<lb/>merely &#x201C;lake near the Ala-tau mountain,&#x201D; which stretches from Turkestan<lb/>to Zungaria. The small map published by the English missionaries of the<lb/>Caucasus, does not contain the Ala-kul; there appears only a group of three<lb/>lakes, the Balkashi, the Alak-tugul, and the Koorgeh. The hypothesis,<lb/>however, according to which the vicinity of large lakes produces, in the in-<lb/>terior of Asia, the same effect upon volcanoes remote from the sea, as the<lb/>ocean, is without foundation. The volcano of Toorfan is surrounded only by<lb/>insignificant lakes; and, as it has been already remarked, Lake Temoortu or<lb/>Ysal-kul, which is less than double the extent of the Lake of Geneva, is<lb/>thirty-three leagues from the volcano of Pih-shan.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi><lb/>The Chinese maps represent the two lakes as one, having a mountain in<lb/>the midst. This lake is called Ala-kul, its eastern portion bears the name of<lb/>Alak-tugul nor, and its western gulf that of She-bartu-kholay.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Klaproth.</hi></note><lb/><pb n="156" facs="#f0026" />
          Chekoy, basalt is found with olivine, cellular amygdaloid,<lb/>chabasie, and apophyllite <note place="foot" n="*">Dr Hess, associate of the Academy of Sciences of St Petersburgh, who<lb/>resided on the borders of the Balkal, and to the south of the lake, from 1826<lb/>to 1828, gives us reason to expect a geological description of a portion of the<lb/>remarkable country which he traversed. He frequently observed at Verkh-<lb/>nei-Oudinsk granite alternating several times with conglomerate.</note>. In the month of February<lb/>1829, Irktusk suffered greatly from violent earthquakes;<lb/>and in the month of April following, convulsions were also<lb/>felt at Ridderski, which were perceived at the bottom of the<lb/>mines, where they were very severe. But this part of the<lb/>Alta&#x00EF; is the extreme limit of the circle of shocks; farther to the<lb/>west, in the plains of Siberia, between the Alta&#x00EF; and the Ural,<lb/>as well as along the entire chain of the latter, no motion has hi-<lb/>therto been observed. The volcano of Pechan, the Aral-tou-<lb/>be, to the westward of the caverns of sal-ammoniac of Kobok,<lb/>Ridderski, and the portion of the Alta&#x00EF; which abounds in me-<lb/>tals, are situated for the most part in a direction which but<lb/>slightly deviates from that of the meridian. Perhaps the Alta&#x00EF;<lb/>may be comprehended within the circle of the convulsions of the<lb/>T&#x00EB;en-shan, and the shocks of the Alta&#x00EF;, instead of coming only<lb/>from the east, or from the basin of the Baikal, may also come<lb/>from the volcanic country of Bishbalik. In many parts of the<lb/>new continent, it is clear, that the circles of shocks intersect each<lb/>other, that is, the same country receives terrestrial convulsions<lb/>periodically on two different quarters.</p><lb/><p>The volcanic territory of Bishbalik is to the eastward of the<lb/>great depression of the old world. Travellers who have journeyed<lb/>from Orenburg to Bokhara, relate that at Sussak in the Kara-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>tau, which forms with the Ala-tau a promontory to the north of<lb/>the town of Taraz in Turkestan, on the edge of the depression,<lb/>warm springs spout up. On the south and on the west of the inner<lb/>basin we find two volcanoes still in activity; Demavend, which<lb/>is visible from Tehran, and the Seyban of Ararat, <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">The height of Ararat, according to Parrot, is 2700 toises (17,718 feet);<lb/>that of Elbourz, according to Kuppfer, 2560 (16,800 feet) above the level of<lb/>the ocean.</note> which is<lb/>covered with vitrified lava. The trachytes, porphyries, and ther-<lb/>mal springs of the Caucasus are well known. On both sides of<lb/>the isthmus between the Caspian and Black Seas, naphtha springs<lb/>and volcanoes of mud are numerous. The mud volcano of Ta-<lb/>man, of which Pallas and Messrs Engelhard and Parrot have<lb/><pb n="157" facs="#f0027" />
described the last fiery eruption, in 1794, from the reports of<lb/>Tartars, is, according to the very sensible remark of Mr Eich-<lb/>wald, &#x201C;a dependency of Baku, and of the whole peninsula of<lb/>Absheron.&#x201D; Eruptions take place where the volcanic forces<lb/>encounter least opposition. On the 27th November 1827, crack-<lb/>ings and tremblings of the earth, of a violent character, were<lb/>succeeded, at the village of Gokmali, in the province of Baku,<lb/>three leagues from the western shore of the Caspian Sea, by an<lb/>eruption of flames and stones. A space of ground, 200 toises<lb/>long and 150 wide, burned for twenty-seven hours without in-<lb/>termission, and rose above the level of the neighbouring soil.<lb/>After the flame became extinct, columns of water were ejected,<lb/>which continue to flow till the present hour. I am gratified at<lb/>being enabled to state here, that Mr Eichwald&#x2019;s periplus of the<lb/>Caspian Sea, which will soon appear, will contain some very im-<lb/>portant physical and geological observations, more particularly<lb/>upon the connexion of fiery eruptions with the appearance of<lb/>naphtha-springs and strata of rock-salt, on the blocks of calcare-<lb/>ous rock hurled to considerable distances, on the elevation and<lb/>depression of the bed of the Caspian Sea, which still continue;<lb/>on the passing of black porphyry, partly vitrified and contain-<lb/>ing garnets <hi rendition="#i">(melapyres),</hi> through granite, red quartzose por-<lb/>phyry, very dark calcareous syenite, in the Krasnovodsk moun-<lb/>tains washed by the bay of the Balkan, to the northward of the<lb/>ancient mouth of the Oxus (Amoo-doria). We shall learn from<lb/>the geognostic description of the eastern shore of the Caspian<lb/>Sea, where the island of Chabekan discovers naphtha-springs<lb/>the same as Baku and the isles between this town and Salian,<lb/>what species of crystallized rocks are hidden beneath the rocks<lb/>in horizontal strata in the peninsula of Absheron, where the ac-<lb/>tion of subterranean fire is always felt, and where it has not yet<lb/>been able to reach the open air. The porphyries of the Cauca-<lb/>sus, which run from W. N. W. to E. S. E., a position and a di-<lb/>rection which I have already mentioned as the reason of the<lb/>presumed connexion of this chain with the rent of the T&#x00EB;en-shan,<lb/>discover themselves again, traversing all the rocks nearly to the<lb/>centre of the great depression of the old world, to the east of the<lb/>Caspian Sea, in the mountains of Krasnovodsk and Kurreh.<lb/>Recent researches and the traditions of the Tartars inform us,<lb/>that the existence of naphtha springs has always been preceded<lb/><pb n="158" facs="#f0028" />
by fiery eruptions. Several salt lakes on the two opposite shores<lb/>of the Caspian Sea have a very elevated temperature; and blocks<lb/>of rock-salt, traversed by asphaltum, are formed, as Mr Eich-<lb/>wald remarks with much shrewdness, &#x201C;by the effect of a sudden<lb/>volcanic action, as at Vesuvius,<note place="foot" n="*">In an eruption of this volcano in 1805, M. Guy Lussac and I found<lb/>small fragments of rock-salt in the lava as it cooled. My Tartar itineraries<lb/>likewise speak of rock-salt in the neighbourhood of a volcanic mountain of the<lb/>T&#x00EB;en-shan, north of Aksou, between the station of Turpa-gad and Mount<lb/>Arbab.</note> in the Cordilleras of South<lb/>America and in Azirbidjan, or even under our own observation<lb/>by the slow but continued action of heat.&#x201D; M. L. de Buch has<lb/>long directed his attention to the connexion of the volcanic for-<lb/>ces with the masses of anhydrous rock-salt, which traverse so<lb/>often and so many formations of horizontal strata.</p><lb/><p>We have already seen that the circles of the terrestrial con-<lb/>vulsions, of which Lake Baikal or the volcanoes of T&#x00EB;en-shan are<lb/>the centre, do not extend in western Siberia beyond the western<lb/>declivity of the Alta&#x00EF;, and do not pass the Irtish or the meridian<lb/>of Semipolantinsk. In the chain of the Ural, earthquakes are<lb/>not felt, nor, notwithstanding the rocks abound in metals, do we<lb/>find there basalt or olivine, nor trachytes, properly so called, nor<lb/>mineral springs. The circle of the phenomena of Azerbidajan,<lb/>which includes the peninsula of Absheron, or the Caucasus, of-<lb/>ten extends as far as Kizlar and Astrakhan.</p><lb/><p>It is the same on the border of the great depression in the west.<lb/>If we direct our observation from the Caucasian isthmus to the<lb/>north and north-west, we come to the country of grand forma-<lb/>tions in horizontal and tertiary strata, which occupy southern<lb/>Russia and Poland. In this region, the rocks of pyroxene pierce<lb/>the red free-stone of Yekaterinoslav, whilst asphaltum and<lb/>springs impregnated with sulphurous gas denote other masses<lb/>hid under the sedimentary deposits. It may also be mention-<lb/>ed as an important fact, that in the chain of the Ural, which<lb/>abounds so much in serpentine and hornblende, and which serves<lb/>as a boundary between Europe and Asia, a true amygdaloidal<lb/>formation appear at Griasnushinskaia, towards its southern ex-<lb/>tremity.</p><lb/><p>We shall content ourselves here with observing, with refer-<lb/>ence to the ingenious opinions recently promulgated by M. Elie<lb/>de Beaumont, respecting the relative age and the parallelism of<lb/><pb n="159" facs="#f0029" />
systems of contemporary mountains, that, in the interior of Asia<lb/>likewise, the four grand chains which run from east to west are<lb/>of a totally different origin from the chains which lie in a direc-<lb/>tion north and south, or N. 30° W., and S. 30° E. The chain<lb/>of the Ural, the Bolor, or Beloor-tag, the Ghauts of Malabar,<lb/>and the Kingkhan, are probably more modern than the chains<lb/>of the Himalaya and the T&#x00EB;en-shan. The systems of different<lb/>epochs are not always separated from each other by consider-<lb/>able spaces, as in Germany, and in the greater part of the new<lb/>continent. Frequently, chains of mountains, or axes of uprais-<lb/>ing, of dissimilar directions, and belonging to epochs totally<lb/>different, are nearly approximated by nature; resembling so far<lb/>the characters on a monument which, crossing different ways,<lb/>were engraved at different periods, and carry intrinsic marks of<lb/>their own date. Thus, in the south of France, are seen chains<lb/>and undulated swellings, some of which are parallel to the Pyre-<lb/>nees and others to the western Alps. The same diversity of<lb/>geological phenomena is apparent in the high land of Central<lb/>Asia, where isolated portions appear as it were surrounded and<lb/>enclosed by subdivisions, in parallel lines, of the systems of<lb/>mountain.</p></div></div><lb/></body>
  <back>
    <div type="editorial">
      <head>Abbildungen</head>
      <figure facs="1830-Ueber_die_Bergketten-10.jpg"/>
    </div>
  </back>
</text>
</TEI>
