<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="112" facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#i">Ehrenberg&#x2019;s Researches on the Infusoria.</hi> &#x2014; At a meeting of the Academy<lb break="yes"/>of Sciences of Paris, in October last, Baron Humboldt gave a brief notice<lb break="yes"/>of a work just published in German by his fellow traveller, M. Ehrenberg,<lb break="yes"/>entitled &#x201C;The Organization, Classification, and Geographical Distribution<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i">Infusoria</hi> in Africa and the north of Asia.&#x201D; &#x201C;The number of<lb break="yes"/>species,&#x201D; M. de Humboldt remarked, &#x201C;which were observed during the<lb break="yes"/>course of our travels between the Caspian Sea, the Ural, and the Alta&#x00EF;,<lb break="yes"/>amount to 113, of which eight belong to new genera. By feeding these<lb break="yes"/>gelatinous and translucid beings with indigo and carmine, M. Ehrenberg has<lb break="yes"/>been able to colour their mouth, stomachs, and the extremity of their<lb break="yes" />alimentary canal, and by thus painting them, as it were, internally, in red and<lb break="yes"/>blue, to detect the extreme complication of their organs. In examining<lb break="yes"/>the eight plates in Ehrenberg&#x2019;s work, a single glance will show the astonish-<lb break="no"/>ing complexity of these beings, many of which, however, do not exceed<lb break="yes"/>1-2000th of a line in length. The author employed a Chevallier micro-<lb break="no"/>scope, and generally a magnifying power of 80 diameters. He now<lb break="yes"/>publishes the results of ten years&#x2019; observations, the accuracy of which is<lb break="yes"/>increased by his long use of the microscope and micrometer in examining<lb break="yes"/>the structure of the <hi rendition="#i">mollusca</hi> of the Red Sea. The smallest, and what<lb break="yes"/>have been considered the most simple <hi rendition="#i" >Infusoria,</hi> are all provided with a<lb break="yes"/>mouth and organs of nutrition, and sometimes from thirty to forty stomachs.<lb break="yes"/>They all seize their prey, and feed on solid substances. In the <hi rendition="#i" >monas-termo,</hi>
                <lb break="yes"/>which is only 1-1500th of a line long, we may distinguish four stomachs,<lb break="yes"/>a mouth, and cili&#x00E6; surrounding the mouth. The <hi rendition="#i">Vorticell&#x0153;, Leucophr&#x0153;,</hi>
                <lb break="yes"/>and the <hi rendition="#i">Param&#x0153;cia,</hi> have a more complicated structure. The number of<lb break="yes"/>eyes varies in the <hi rendition="#i">Rotifer&#x0153;,</hi> in the genera <hi rendition="#i" >Euglena</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Eosphora.</hi> But<lb break="yes"/>what most attracts the attention of those who occupy themselves with<lb break="yes" />microscopic anatomy, is the complication of the muscular and nervous<lb break="yes"/>systems, of the mouth furnished with cartilaginous teeth, and of the organs<lb break="yes"/>of nutrition and generation in the <hi rendition="#i" >Hydatina senta,</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">Vorticella senta,</hi> Müller,)<lb break="yes"/>as presented in the eighth plate of this work. The Academy will doubtless<lb break="yes"/>condescend to examine the anatomical portion of this memoir, and the<lb break="yes"/>classification of the <hi rendition="#i" >Infusoria,</hi> according to their internal organization,<lb break="yes" />especially the parallelism of the <hi rendition="#i">nuda</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">loricata,</hi> (naked, and covered with<lb break="yes"/>shields,) which characterizes the whole of this class. M. Ehrenberg<lb break="yes"/>discusses the genera which have been established upon other principles, and<lb break="yes" />finds, that individuals of the same species, in different degrees of distension,<lb break="yes"/>according to the absence or presence of food in their interior, have been<lb break="yes"/>described as distinct genera. He has often observed the <hi rendition="#i">Infusoria</hi> pass out<lb break="yes"/>from the ova, and no direct observation has led him to admit either a<lb break="yes" />spontaneous generation, or an agglomeration of <hi rendition="#i">Infusoria,</hi> to form the rudi-<lb break="no"/>ments of vegetables and animals. He thinks that all the <hi rendition="#i">Infusoria</hi> move<lb break="yes"/>about during life, and separately seek their food. Of the 113 species<lb break="yes"/>observed and described during the course of our travels, 31 species belong<lb break="yes"/>to Europe, and 82 to Asia; but of the species collected in Asia, two-thirds<lb break="yes"/>are also observed in central Europe. The <hi rendition="#i">Kolpoda cucullus</hi> seems to be the<lb break="yes"/>most generally distributed: M. Ehrenberg found it from Mount Sina&#x00EF; to<lb break="yes"/>Dongola, near Berlin, at St Petersburg, in the north of the Ural, and at the<lb break="yes"/>foot of the Alta&#x00EF;. In the mines of Siberia, (Soimonofskoi and Schlangen-<lb break="no" />berg), three species of <hi rendition="#i">monad</hi> were found, and again the <hi rendition="#i">Kolpoda cucullus,</hi>
                <lb break="yes"/>at a depth of 56 fathoms, in places entirely deprived of light. The <hi rendition="#i">Infusoria,</hi>
                <lb break="yes"/>in their structure, form two natural classes of animals, inhabiting the sea<lb break="yes"/>and the land. Some species are found, which (like <hi rendition="#i">cryptogami&#x0153;</hi>) are<lb break="yes"/>identical under the most opposite latitudes; they appear to vary, according<lb break="yes"/>to the climates, more from Europe to Dongola, than from east to west,<lb break="yes"/>from Berlin to the Alta&#x00EF;. The salt waters of the Asiatic steps present no<lb break="yes"/>very peculiar forms. The dew, examined with the greatest care, in the<lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="113" facs="#f0002"/> midst of the deserts of Africa, afforded no <hi rendition="#i">Infusoria,</hi> whilst eight species<lb break="yes"/>swarm in the pits of the oasis of Jupiter Ammon.&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>The investigations made on the <hi rendition="#i">Infusoria,</hi> during M. de Humboldt&#x2019;s last<lb break="yes"/>journey, extend over more than 50° of longitude and 14° of latitude. &#x2014; <hi rendition="#i">Ann.<lb break="yes"/>des Sciences Nat.</hi> Oct. 1830.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 