<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/103788910X">
                        <surname>Metz</surname>
                        <forename>Bernhard</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-10-04" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="719" facs="#f0001"/>
            <p/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>M. de Humboldt stated that he had established at Berlin, at the<lb break="yes" />bottom of the mines of Freyberg in Saxony, at St. Petersburgh,<lb break="yes"/>at Casan, at Archangel, at Irkutsk, on the borders of Lake Baikal<lb break="yes"/>in Siberia, and at Pekin, magnetic houses in imitation of the mag-<lb break="no"/>netic observatory established at Paris in one of the apartments of<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">Observatoire Royal</hi>. Ever since the reign of Peter the Great,<lb break="yes"/>the Russian Government has maintained a mission at Pekin,<lb break="yes"/>which is renewed every ten years; but there had never been any<lb break="yes"/>men of science attached to this mission until M. Fuss, the bro-<lb break="no"/>ther of the Secretary of the Academy of Sciences of St. Peters-<lb break="no"/>burgh, made a voyage to China last year, and commenced a series<lb break="yes"/>of meteorological, magnetic, and astronomical observations,<lb break="yes"/>which will be continued by M. Kowanko, a young officer of the<lb break="yes"/>mines, who is to pass ten years at Pekin. M. Fuss, on the 22d<lb break="yes"/>April last, wrote a letter from that city, which has been commu-<lb break="no"/>nicated by M. Kuppfer to M. Arago and M. de Humboldt, and<lb break="yes"/>of which the following is the substance: &#x2014; M. Fuss made magnetic<lb break="yes"/>observations in 17 stations during his progress through the celes-<lb break="no"/>tial empire to Pekin; but he was afraid to take any astronomical<lb break="yes"/>measures, on account of the jealousy of the Chinese. A tower in<lb break="yes"/>masonry has been constructed at Pekin, surmounted by a tent,<lb break="yes"/>as a protection against the inclemency of the atmosphere. This<lb break="yes"/>observatory is surrounded by houses; but, happily for magnetic<lb break="yes"/>experiments, no iron is used in the Chinese buildings. The cross<lb break="yes"/>on the top of the edifice, belonging to the Russian Mission, which<lb break="yes"/>is only a short distance off, serves as a <hi rendition="#i">point de m&#x00EF;re</hi> for the azi-<lb break="no"/>muthal directions. On the 30th December, 1830, the magnetic<lb break="yes"/>inclination was found to be 54° 32&#x2032;; and the declination observed<lb break="yes"/>on the 10th January, 1831, at three o&#x2019;clock in the afternoon, was<lb break="yes"/>1° 42&#x2032; 57&#x2033; West. The longitude of the observatory is about 114°<lb break="yes"/>East of Paris; the latitude has been ascertained with precision<lb break="yes"/>to be 39° 54&#x2032; 9&#x2033;. 5. This observation differs only by 5&#x2032; from that<lb break="yes"/>made by Father Hyacinth. The magnetic observations are made<lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="720" facs="#f0002"/> at the same hour as in the European observatories above-men-<lb break="no"/>tioned. Barometrical and thermometrical notes are taken four<lb break="yes"/>times every day. From the winter solstice to the date of the<lb break="yes"/>letter, the maximum height of the barometer was 345.7 lines of<lb break="yes"/>Paris; this was at midnight, on the 10th of March, at which<lb break="yes"/>time a slight shock of an earthquake was felt towards the North;<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;the minimum was 330.9 lines, difference 14.8 lines. The<lb break="yes"/>highest temperature during the same period was 25° centigrade,<lb break="yes"/>at four o&#x2019;clock in the afternoon of the 20th April; and the lowest,<lb break="yes"/>13°.5 below zero, at six in the morning of the 5th February: the<lb break="yes"/>mean temperature was 12°.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>M. Kuppfer, in forwarding the above letter, announced that he<lb break="yes"/>had also recently received a letter from the celebrated Norwegian<lb break="yes" />natural philosopher M. Hansteen, in which he abandons his hypo-<lb break="no" />thesis of two linear magnets, by which he had imagined he could<lb break="yes" />account for the magnetic phenomena of the globe. M. Kuppfer<lb break="yes" />announces that he is employed in examining the various observa-<lb break="no" />tions which have been made on the magnetic needle. It has ge-<lb break="no" />nerally been supposed that the magnetic power could only be<lb break="yes"/>lost by heat; but M. Kuppfer has ascertained that it may be<lb break="yes"/>equally affected by cold. Thence, in order to compare needles<lb break="yes"/>properly, they should be exposed to the two extremes of tempe-<lb break="no"/>rature, by plunging them first into boiling water, and then into a<lb break="yes"/>frigorific liquid, at 20° below zero. It has, however, been al-<lb break="no"/>ready observed, that magnets sustaining a great weight have let<lb break="yes"/>it fall when the temperature has suddenly fallen.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>M. de Humboldt then presented a Chinese Almanack for 1832,<lb break="yes"/>calculated by the Astronomical Tribunal of Pekin, in which the<lb break="yes"/>different days are placed under the protection of 34 genii. Parti-<lb break="no"/>cular days are designated for giving entertainments; others are<lb break="yes"/>pointed out as propitious for feeding on dogs; others for mar-<lb break="no"/>rying, for building, for pulling down, etc. M. de Humboldt<lb break="yes"/>added, that when the Chinese authorities were asked whether<lb break="yes"/>they should take any precautions against the cholera, they re-<lb break="no"/>plied, that fear alone was the cause of people being attacked by<lb break="yes"/>it, and that therefore no preventive measure ought to be adopted.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 