<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>PARIS ACADEMY OF ARTS AND SCI-<lb break="no"/>ENCES.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">Meeting held on the 17th instant.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A letter addressed to the president of the Academy by<lb break="yes"/>Baron de Humboldt, at Berlin, was read at this sitting;<lb break="yes"/>it relates to the Baron&#x2019;s friend and travelling companion,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Bompland</hi>, who lately contrived to obtain his release from<lb break="yes"/>years of captivity in Paraguay. &#x201C;Above a twelvemonth<lb break="yes"/>had elapsed,&#x201D; says the Baron, &#x201C;since we received the<lb break="yes"/>first intelligence of the arrival of M. Bompland in the<lb break="yes"/>province of the Missions; but no letter from him had<lb break="yes"/>ever reached Europe, and his relatives at La Rochelle<lb break="yes"/>felt the same anxiety on his account which I did. At<lb break="yes"/>length I have had the happiness of receiving direct news<lb break="yes"/>from him through the care of Baron Dehessert. A let-<lb break="no"/>ter from Bompland, dated Buenos Ayres, the 7th of May<lb break="yes"/>1832, advises, that he had received a few lines, which I<lb break="yes"/>had forwarded to him at the close of July last year,<lb break="yes"/>whilst residing at Corrientes, near the confluence of the<lb break="yes"/>Parana and Paraguay, in 1832. &#x2018;I have been crossed,&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>says he, &#x2018;in every labor I have projected since I quitted<lb break="yes"/>the soil of France. My ill stars have persecuted me for<lb break="yes"/>the last fifteen years; but I am fain to believe that my<lb break="yes"/>fate will prove more auspicious, now that I am out of<lb break="yes"/>Paraguay. Being once more restored to my friends, and<lb break="yes"/>having renewed my connexion with civilized Europe,<lb break="yes"/>I have resumed all my former labors in natural his-<lb break="no"/>tory, with the greatest activity, in order that I may<lb break="yes"/>be enabled to return to my native country as quickly as<lb break="yes"/>possible. The collections I formed in Paraguay and the<lb break="yes"/>Portuguese Missions ought to have reached Buenos<lb break="yes" />Ayres ever since the month of March. I look for them<lb break="yes"/>with the greatest uneasiness, and shall forward them<lb break="yes"/>immediately upon their arrival, (which cannot be long de-<lb break="no"/>layed) to the care of the Minister of Foreign Affairs at<lb break="yes"/>Paris, praying him to deliver over the cases to the Mu-<lb break="no"/>seum of Natural History. The <hi rendition="#i">Jardin des Plantes</hi> will<lb break="yes"/>receive, not only what I have recently collected, but such<lb break="yes"/>herbaria as I have put together at Corrientes and Buenos<lb break="yes"/>Ayres, and particularly my general herbarium, and the<lb break="yes"/>geological series of the route we pursued. To this col-<lb break="no"/>lection I shall add the specimens of rocks which I have<lb break="yes"/>just collected, as well as such as I may succeed in pro-<lb break="no"/>curing during my excursions to Monte Video, Maldona-<lb break="no"/>do, and Cabo-Santa-Maria. *** Such are the fertili-<lb break="no"/>ty of the soil and the richness of the vegetation in the<lb break="yes"/>Portuguese Missions, that I think it my duty to return to<lb break="yes"/>that quarter, and I am willing to believe, that those who<lb break="yes"/>kindly take an interest in my early return to Europe, will<lb break="yes"/>not disapprove this trip. It would be cruel to leave this<lb break="yes"/>clime without adding such a host of remarkable produc-<lb break="no"/>tions to our botanical stores. My collections will com-<lb break="no"/>prise two new species of <hi rendition="#i">Convolvuli</hi>, the roots of which<lb break="yes"/>possess all the healing qualities of the jalap. I am in<lb break="yes"/>hopes that the School of Medieine will likewise set some<lb break="yes"/>essays on foot as to the uses to which three extremely<lb break="yes"/>bitter barks, derived from three new species of a class<lb break="yes"/>belonging to the family of the <hi rendition="#i" >Simaroub&#x0153;&#x0153;</hi>, may be put.<lb break="yes"/>These barks are of the flavor of the sulphate of quinine,<lb break="yes"/>and are used with the most salutary effect in cases of<lb break="yes"/>dysentery and other gastric derangements. If, whilst<lb break="yes"/>here, I could but receive proper information on the effi-<lb break="no"/>cacy of these barks, as it might appear from trials in Pa-<lb break="no"/>ris, I would endeavor to secure a supply of them for our<lb break="yes"/>hospitals before my departure. ** I avail myself of this<lb break="yes"/>opportunity,&#x201D; adds de Humboldt, &#x201C;to communicate a<lb break="yes"/>geological fact to the Academy, which has been known<lb break="yes"/>here only within the last few days, and is connected with<lb break="yes"/>other facts, which have been observed elsewhere in Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope, and even in the heart of Asia. M. Von Secken-<lb break="no"/>dorf has discovered fragments of Grauwakke, accompa-<lb break="no"/>nied with petrifactions incrusted in granite, in the valley<lb break="yes"/>of Badan, (of the Hartz) in a quarry near the high road<lb break="yes"/>which leads to Hartzburg. M. Hartmann, the translator<lb break="yes"/>of Lyell&#x2019;s Geology, has just confirmed this observation. &#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>P. S. At the very moment of closing this letter, I receive<lb break="yes"/>the very important information that Encke&#x2019;s Comet, of<lb break="yes"/>three years and three tenths, was observed at Buenos<lb break="yes"/>Ayres in the beginning of June 1832. M. Encke has<lb break="yes"/>heard from M. Olbers, of Bremen, that M. Massotti<lb break="yes"/>(probably the same gentleman who was formerly at the<lb break="yes"/>Milan Observatory, and has published some works on<lb break="yes"/>planetary orbits) observed the Comet at Buenos Ayres<lb break="yes"/>on the 2nd of June last, at 5h 30 mean time, with 56° 37<lb break="yes"/>5 of right ascension, and 11° 20 1 of southern declension.<lb break="yes"/>This observation appears to differ not more than some 2&#x2032;<lb break="yes"/>from the short period comet, which M. Encke has calcu-<lb break="no"/>lated by anticipation.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>At this meeting of the Academy also, it wasre@<lb break="yes"/>that Messrs. Caperon and M. Albert have announced<lb break="yes"/>the discovery of an expeditious method of preserving the<lb break="yes"/>humen body, without any external preparation, or alter-<lb break="no"/>ation of the features of the countenance, as well as<lb break="yes"/>without producing diminution in any part of the body.<lb break="yes"/>The operation is performed in eight days; and the inven-<lb break="no"/>tors have requested permission to submit a specimen for<lb break="yes"/>the inspection of the Academy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. Geoffrey presented the first fasciculus of his &#x2018;Zoo-<lb break="no" />logical Studies,&#x2019; in which, amongst other recently discov-<lb break="no"/>ered animals, he describes three birds, natives of Pata-<lb break="no"/>gonia, which were killed in that country by W. M. Des-<lb break="no"/>salines d&#x2019;Orbigny. The latter has collected some ex-<lb break="no"/>tremely interesting details of their habits, of which the<lb break="yes"/>following is an instance: &#x2014;&#x201C;On the 20th of March,<lb break="yes"/>1819, being then in the midst of the <hi rendition="#i">Salina de Andres<lb break="yes"/>Paz</hi>, I observed a small superstructure, which looked<lb break="yes"/>like a little island of earthenware, and rose apparently<lb break="yes"/>about a foot above the surface of the Salina. Upon ask-<lb break="no"/>ing my peon what this might be, he replied, that it was a<lb break="yes"/>groupe of flamingos&#x2019; nests. Being anxious to examine<lb break="yes"/>them, I walked across the salty expanse, and, as I ad-<lb break="no"/>vanced, could not refrain from admiring its immense ex-<lb break="no"/>tent, which covered a space of more than five miles<lb break="yes"/>square; the whole of this lake of salt presented a sur-<lb break="no"/>face of dense crystalized crust, six inches in thickness.<lb break="yes"/>at length I came to a halt; and here I found three thou-<lb break="no"/>sand nests, so disposed as to form a small island in the<lb break="yes"/>centre of the lake. Each of them is a cone, about a foot<lb break="yes"/>and a half high, truncated and concave at the upper end,<lb break="yes"/>like a common nest, but without any plants in its struc-<lb break="no"/>ture. Every nest stands at twelve inches distance from<lb break="yes"/>those around it; nor can a more singular sight exist than<lb break="yes"/>this myriad of cones, all of similar form and height. I<lb break="yes"/>found several eggs still in the nests. My peon told me,<lb break="yes"/>that a large flight of flamingos alights on the spot every<lb break="yes"/>year for the purpose of building their nests; that the fe-<lb break="no"/>male sits across the nest to lay and hatch her eggs; and<lb break="yes"/>that those who dig the salt collect and eat a great many<lb break="yes"/>of the eggs, as well as take away the young birds, the<lb break="yes"/>flesh of which, he said, was of exquisite flavor. The<lb break="yes"/>eggs are of a greenish hue, spotted with brown. and they<lb break="yes"/>are somewhat more than four inches in diameter.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 