<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="635" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#c">Meeting held on the 17th instant.</hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <list>
                <item>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Letter from Bonpland: his Botanical Discoveries<lb break="yes"/>and Collections &#x2014; Geological Fact &#x2014; Encke&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>Comet &#x2014; New method of Embalming &#x2014; Habits of<lb break="yes"/>the Flamingo in Patagonia.</hi>
                </item>
            </list>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>A letter, addressed to the president of the<lb break="yes"/>Academy by Baron de Humboldt, at Berlin, was<lb break="yes"/>read at this sitting; it relates to the Baron&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>friend and travelling companion, <hi rendition="#i">Bonpland</hi>, who<lb break="yes"/>lately contrived to obtain his release from years<lb break="yes"/>of captivity in Paraguay. &#x201C;Above a twelve-<lb break="no"/>month had elapsed,&#x201D; says the Baron, &#x201C;since we<lb break="yes"/>received the first intelligence of the arrival of<lb break="yes"/>M. Bonpland in the province of the Missions;<lb break="yes"/>but no letter from him had ever reached Europe,<lb break="yes"/>and his relatives at La Rochelle felt the same<lb break="yes"/>anxiety on his account which I did. At length<lb break="yes"/>I have had the happiness of receiving direct<lb break="yes"/>news from him through the care of Baron De-<lb break="no"/>lessert. A letter from Bonpland, dated Buenos<lb break="yes"/>Ayres, the 7th May 1832, advises, that he had<lb break="yes"/>received a few lines, which I had forwarded to<lb break="yes"/>him at the close of July last year, whilst resi-<lb break="no"/>dent at Corrientes, near the confluence of the<lb break="yes" />Parana and Paraguay, in January 1832. &#x2018;I<lb break="yes"/>have been crossed,&#x2019; says he, &#x2018;in every labour<lb break="yes"/>I have projected since I quitted the soil of<lb break="yes"/>France. My ill stars have persecuted me for<lb break="yes"/>the last fifteen years; but I am fain to believe<lb break="yes"/>that my fate will prove more auspicious, now<lb break="yes"/>that I am out of Paraguay. Being once more<lb break="yes"/>restored to my friends, and having renewed my<lb break="yes"/>connexion with civilized Europe, I have re-<lb break="no"/>sumed my former labours in natural history<lb break="yes"/>with the greatest activity, in order that I may<lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/> be enabled to return to my native country as<lb break="yes"/>quickly as possible. The collections I formed<lb break="yes"/>in Paraguay and the Portuguese Missions ought<lb break="yes"/>to have reached Buenos Ayres ever since the<lb break="yes"/>month of March. I look for them with the<lb break="yes"/>greatest uneasiness, and shall forward them im-<lb break="no"/>mediately upon their arrival, (which cannot be<lb break="yes"/>long delayed,) to the care of the Minister of<lb break="yes"/>Foreign Affairs at Paris, praying him to deliver<lb break="yes" />over the cases to the Museum of Natural His-<lb break="no"/>tory. The <hi rendition="#i">Jardin des Plantes</hi> will receive, not<lb break="yes"/>only what I have recently collected, but such<lb break="yes"/>herbaria as I have put together at Corrientes<lb break="yes"/>and Buenos Ayres, and particularly my general<lb break="yes"/>herbarium, and the geological series of the route<lb break="yes"/>we pursued. To this collection I shall add the<lb break="yes" />specimens of rocks which I have just collected,<lb break="yes"/>as well as such as I may succeed in procuring<lb break="yes"/>during my excursions to Monte Video, Maldo-<lb break="no"/>nado, and Cabo-Santa-Maria. *** Such are<lb break="yes" />the fertility of the soil and the richness of the<lb break="yes"/>vegetation in the Portuguese Missions, that I<lb break="yes"/>think it my duty to return to that quarter, and<lb break="yes"/>I am willing to believe, that those who kindly<lb break="yes"/>take an interest in my early return to Europe,<lb break="yes"/>will not disapprove this trip. It would be cruel<lb break="yes"/>to leave this clime without adding such a host<lb break="yes"/>of remarkable productions to our botanical<lb break="yes"/>stores. My collections will comprise two new<lb break="yes"/>species of <hi rendition="#i">Convolvuli</hi>, the roots of which possess<lb break="yes"/>all the healing qualities of the jalap. I am in<lb break="yes"/>hopes that the School of Medicine will likewise<lb break="yes"/>set some essays on foot as to the uses to which<lb break="yes"/>three extremely bitter barks, derived from three<lb break="yes"/>new species of a class belonging to the family<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i">Simaroub&#x0153;&#x0153;</hi>, may be put. These barks<lb break="yes"/>are of the flavour of the sulphate of quinine, and<lb break="yes"/>are used with the most salutary effect in cases of<lb break="yes"/>dysentery and other gastric derangements. If,<lb break="yes" />whilst here, I could but receive proper infor-<lb break="no"/>mation on the efficacy of these barks, as it might<lb break="yes"/>appear from trials in Paris, I would endeavour<lb break="yes"/>to secure a supply of them for our hospitals be-<lb break="no"/>fore my departure.&#x2019; *** I avail myself of this<lb break="yes" />opportunity,&#x201D; adds De Humboldt, &#x201C;to commu-<lb break="no"/>nicate a geological fact to the Academy, which<lb break="yes"/>has been known here only within the last few<lb break="yes"/>days, and is connected with other facts, which<lb break="yes"/>have been observed elsewhere in Europe, and<lb break="yes" />even in the heart of Asia. M. Von Seckendorf<lb break="yes"/>has discovered fragments of <hi rendition="#i">Grauwakke</hi>, accom-<lb break="no"/>panied with petrifactions incrusted in granite, in<lb break="yes"/>the valley of Badan (of the Hartz), in a quarry<lb break="yes"/>near the high road which leads to Hartzburg.<lb break="yes"/>M. Hartmann, the translator of Lyell&#x2019;s Geology,<lb break="yes"/>has just confirmed this observation. &#x2014; P.S. At<lb break="yes"/>the very moment of closing this letter, I receive<lb break="yes" />the very important information that Encke&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>Comet, of three years and three tenths, was<lb break="yes"/>observed at Buenos Ayres in the beginning of<lb break="yes"/>June 1832. M. Encke has heard from M. Ol-<lb break="no" />bers (of Bremen), that M. Massotti (probably<lb break="yes"/>the same gentleman who was formerly at the<lb break="yes"/>Milan Observatory, and has published some<lb break="yes"/>works on planetary orbits), observed the comet<lb break="yes"/>at B. A. on the 2nd of June last, at 5<hi rendition="#sup">h</hi> 30&#x2032; mean<lb break="yes"/>time, with 56° 37&#x2032; 5&#x2033; of right ascension, and<lb break="yes"/>11° 20&#x2032; 1&#x2033; of southern declension. &#x2014; This obser-<lb break="no"/>vation appears to differ not more than some 2&#x2032;<lb break="yes"/>from the short-period comet, which M. Encke<lb break="yes"/>has calculated by anticipation.&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 