<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>Baron Humboldt has addressed a letter from Berlin to<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">Academie des Sciences</hi> of Paris. The following is<lb break="yes"/>a copy:&#x2014;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>Monsieur le President &#x2014; The generous interest<lb break="yes"/>which the Institute has taken, in its sittings,<lb break="yes"/>whenever the name of my friend and travelling<lb break="yes"/>companion, M. Boupland, has been mentioned&#x2014;the<lb break="yes"/>kind feeling with which the Academy has deigned to<lb break="yes"/>associate itself to the frui@less attempts which ought to<lb break="yes"/>have accelerated the release of this learned man, imposes<lb break="yes"/>on me the duty of addressing these lines to you. More<lb break="yes"/>than twelve months had elapsed since the first news of the<lb break="yes"/>arrival of M. Boupland in the <hi rendition="#i">Provincia de las Mis-<lb break="no"/>siones:</hi> no letter from him had come to Europe, and my<lb break="yes"/>uneasiness was shared with his relations, who reside at Ro-<lb break="no"/>chelle; at last I was fortunate enough to receive news direct,<lb break="yes"/>by means of M. le Baron Delessert. A letter from M. Bou-<lb break="no"/>pland, dated Buenos Ayres, May 7, 1832, informs me that<lb break="yes"/>he had in January received a letter which I had written to<lb break="yes"/>him from Paris about the end of July last year, during<lb break="yes"/>his stay at Corrientes, near the conflux of the rivers Parara<lb break="yes"/>and Paraguay.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;I have been thwarted, he says, in all the projects I<lb break="yes"/>had formed on quitting France. An evil star has followed<lb break="yes"/>me for fifteen years. I hope that my lot will be more<lb break="yes"/>fortunate now that I have quitted Paraguay. Restored to<lb break="yes"/>my friends, and in communication again with civilization<lb break="yes"/>and with Europe, I have resumed my researches in natural<lb break="yes"/>history with the greatest activity, in order to return as<lb break="yes"/>soon as possible to my native land. My collections at<lb break="yes"/>Paraguay and the Portuguese mission ought to have<lb break="yes" />arrived at Buenos Ayres in the month of March. I ex-<lb break="no"/>pect them with great uneasiness, and I shall expedite<lb break="yes"/>them as soon as they arrive, which cannot be long, under<lb break="yes"/>address to the Minister for Foreign Affairs at Paris, with a<lb break="yes"/>request to the Minister to cause the chests to be forwarded<lb break="yes"/>to the Museum of Natural History.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;The <hi rendition="#i">Jardin des Plantes</hi> will not only receive what I<lb break="yes"/>have gathered recently, but also such herbs as I have<lb break="yes"/>saved at Corrientes and at Buenos Ayres, particularly my<lb break="yes"/>
                <hi rendition="#i">herbier general</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i">suite geoligique</hi> of the course<lb break="yes"/>of our travels.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;I will add to the collection some geological specimens<lb break="yes"/>which I have already gathered, and also such as I may<lb break="yes"/>procure in a few days in my excursions to Monte Video,<lb break="yes"/>Maldonado, and Cabo-San@a-Maria.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;Here I live in the house of M. le Chev. de Angelis, a<lb break="yes" />Neapolitan, who has received me with the greatest hospi-<lb break="no"/>tality, and whom you have seen at Paris in the society of<lb break="yes"/>Madame the Comtesse Orloff. I find every facility in<lb break="yes"/>expediting my collections to France.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;The fertility of the soil, and the richness of vegeta-<lb break="no"/>tion in the Portuguese settlements are such, that I think of<lb break="yes"/>returning there: I think that those who wish to interest<lb break="yes"/>themselves in my speedy return to Europe, will not dis-<lb break="no"/>approve of this journey. It would be cruel to leave<lb break="yes"/>without enriching Botany with so many remarkable pro-<lb break="no"/>ductions. My collections contain two new kinds of <hi rendition="#i">con-<lb break="no"/>volvulus,</hi> the roots of which have all the fine qualities of<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">salep.</hi> I hope also that the Medical School will<lb break="yes"/>make some experiments upon three new sorts of Bark,<lb break="yes"/>very bitter, belonging to the <hi rendition="#i" >genus simaroubus.</hi> These<lb break="yes"/>barks have the taste of <hi rendition="#i">sulphate of quinine,</hi> and act<lb break="yes"/>with great effect in complaints of the stomach<lb break="yes"/>and dysenteries. If I could still obtain information<lb break="yes"/>respecting the efficacy of these barks, after a trial at Paris,<lb break="yes"/>I should try, before my departure, to make arrangements<lb break="yes"/>for the supply of our hospitals.&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>Such is the information which I have considered it my<lb break="yes"/>duty to extract from the letter of M. Boupland, and I<lb break="yes"/>have to regret other letters previously written and proba-<lb break="no"/>bly lost. I take this opportunity to communicate to the<lb break="yes"/>academy a geological fact, with which we have only<lb break="yes"/>been acquainted for a few days, and which forms a link<lb break="yes"/>to other facts ob@erved in Europe, and even in the in-<lb break="no"/>terior of Asia. M. de Seckendorf has found in Hartz<lb break="yes" />(valley of Radan), in a quarry near the highway leading<lb break="yes"/>to Hartzbourg, fragments of <hi rendition="#i">grawakke,</hi> with petrifica-<lb break="no"/>tion <hi rendition="#i">empatee dans le granit.</hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>The translator of <hi rendition="#i">Geologie de Lyel,</hi> M. Hartman, has<lb break="yes"/>con@irmed the accuracy of this information, and an-<lb break="no" />nounces that he will shortly send me specimens, carefully<lb break="yes"/>detached by regular work of art, <hi rendition="#i">a la paintrole.</hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <closer>
                <dateline>
                    <hi rendition="#et">Berlin, Aug. 26, 1832.</hi>
                </dateline>
                <hi rendition="#et">I have, &#x0026;c &#x0026;c.</hi>
            </closer>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 