<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="618" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Letter to the President of the Academy of Sci-<lb break="no" />ences, from Baron Alex. von Humboldt.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <dateline>
                    <hi rendition="#et">Paris, Sept. 20.</hi>
                </dateline>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <salute>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Sir,</hi>
                </salute>
                <p>&#x2014;The generous interest which the Insti-<lb break="no"/>tute has always manifested whenever the name<lb break="yes"/>of my friend and fellow-traveller, M. Bonpland,<lb break="yes"/>has been mentioned in its sittings, and the active<lb break="yes"/>kindness with which the Academy of Sciences<lb break="yes"/>has taken part in the fruitless attempts that<lb break="yes" />have been made to obtain his deliverance, make<lb break="yes"/>it my duty to address these lines to you. More<lb break="yes"/>than a year had elapsed since the receipt of the<lb break="yes"/>first news of the arrival of M. Bonpland in the<lb break="yes"/>Provincia de las Missiones. None of his letters<lb break="yes"/>had reached Europe; and my uneasiness was<lb break="yes" />shared by the relations of M. Bonpland, who<lb break="yes"/>reside at La Rochelle. At length I have been<lb break="yes"/>so happy as to receive direct intelligence,<lb break="yes"/>through the kindness of Baron Delessert. A<lb break="yes"/>letter from M. Bonpland, dated Buenos Ayres,<lb break="yes" />May 7th, 1832, informs me that some lines<lb break="yes"/>which I wrote to him in July, last year, reached<lb break="yes"/>him in January, 1832, during his stay at Cor-<lb break="no"/>rientes, situated near the conflux of the rivers<lb break="yes"/>Parana and Paraguay. &#x201C;I have been hin-<lb break="no" />dered,&#x201D; he says, &#x201C;in all the plans which I<lb break="yes" />formed when I left France. An evil star has<lb break="yes"/>attended me for fifteen years: I flatter myself<lb break="yes"/>that I shall be more fortunate now that I have<lb break="yes"/>quitted Paraguay. Restored to my friends, again<lb break="yes"/>able to communicate with civilisation and Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope, I have resumed my ancient studies in<lb break="yes" />natural history with the greatest activity, that<lb break="yes"/>I may be able to return as soon as possible to<lb break="yes"/>my country. My collections of Paraguay and<lb break="yes"/>the Portuguese ought to have arrived at Buenos<lb break="yes"/>Ayres in the month of March: I expect their<lb break="yes" />arrival with impatience (which cannot be long<lb break="yes"/>delayed), and will immediately send them to<lb break="yes"/>Europe, addressed to the Minister for Foreign<lb break="yes"/>Affairs at Paris, with a request to have the<lb break="yes"/>cases delivered to the Museum of Natural His-<lb break="no" />tory. The Jardin des Plantes will receive not<lb break="yes"/>only what I have recently collected, but what<lb break="yes"/>herbaria I have saved at Corrientes and Buenos<lb break="yes"/>Ayres, and, in particular, my general her-<lb break="no"/>barium, and the geological series of the course<lb break="yes" />of our journey. I shall add to this collection<lb break="yes"/>the rocks which I have lately obtained, as well<lb break="yes"/>as those which, in a few days, I may procure<lb break="yes"/>in the excursions which I shall make on Monte<lb break="yes"/>Video, Maldonado, and Cabo Santa Maria. I<lb break="yes"/>am here in the house of the Chevalier de An-<lb break="no"/>gelis, a Neapolitan, who has received me with<lb break="yes"/>the greatest hospitality, and whom you formerly<lb break="yes"/>saw at Paris, in the circle of Countess Orloff.<lb break="yes"/>I find every facility for forwarding my collec-<lb break="no" />tions to France. The fertility of the soil, and<lb break="yes"/>the luxuriance of the vegetation in the Portu-<lb break="no"/>guese missions are such, that I feel myself<lb break="yes"/>bound to return to them. I think that even<lb break="yes"/>those who desire my speedy return to Europe<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="619" facs="#f0002"/> will not disapprove my undertaking this jour-<lb break="no"/>ney. It would be cruel to come away without<lb break="yes" />enriching botany with so many remarkable<lb break="yes"/>productions. My collections will contain two<lb break="yes"/>new species of convolvulus, the roots of which<lb break="yes"/>have all the good qualities of the orchis morio.<lb break="yes"/>I hope also that the School of Medicine will<lb break="yes"/>make some trials of the use of those very bitter<lb break="yes" />barks belonging to three new species of a genus<lb break="yes"/>which belongs to the family of the quassia<lb break="yes"/>simarouba. These barks have a taste of sul-<lb break="no"/>phate of quinine, and act in the most beneficial<lb break="yes"/>manner in dysenteries and other similar com-<lb break="no" />plaints. If I could receive, while I am here,<lb break="yes"/>some information respecting the efficacy of these<lb break="yes"/>barks, as observed at Paris, I would endeavour,<lb break="yes"/>before my departure, to make arrangements to<lb break="yes"/>supply our hospitals.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Such are the particulars which I have thought<lb break="yes"/>it my duty to extract from M. Bonpland&#x2019;s let-<lb break="no"/>ter, which make me regret other letters, writ-<lb break="no"/>ten before, and which are probably lost. I take<lb break="yes"/>this opportunity of communicating to the Aca-<lb break="no"/>demy a geological fact, which has been known<lb break="yes"/>to us here only a few days, and which is con-<lb break="no"/>nected with other facts observed in Europe and<lb break="yes"/>in the interior of Asia. M. de Seckendorf has<lb break="yes"/>found in the Harz (Valley of Radau), in a<lb break="yes"/>quarry near the road leading to Harzburg,<lb break="yes" />fragments of grauwacke (with petrification)<lb break="yes"/>embedded in granite. M. Hartmann, trans-<lb break="no"/>lator of Lyell&#x2019;s Geology, has just confirmed the<lb break="yes"/>truth of this observation, and announces that<lb break="yes"/>he will soon send specimens.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Berlin, Aug. 26th,</hi> 1832.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>P.S. Just as I am closing my letter, I receive<lb break="yes"/>the important news that Encke&#x2019;s comet (of the<lb break="yes"/>short period of three years three-tenths), was<lb break="yes"/>observed at Buenos Ayres at the beginning of<lb break="yes"/>June, 1832. M. Encke has been informed by<lb break="yes" />M. Olbers, that a member of the Typographic<lb break="yes"/>Bureau of Buenos Ayres, M. Massoti (perhaps<lb break="yes"/>the same who was formerly at the observatory<lb break="yes"/>at Milan, and also had published observations<lb break="yes"/>on the planetary orbits) observed the comet on<lb break="yes" />the 2d of June, 1832, at Buenos Ayres, 5° 30&#x2032;<lb break="yes"/>civil time, in 56° 37&#x2032; 5&#x2033; right ascension, in<lb break="yes"/>11° 20&#x2032; 1&#x2033; south declination; which appears<lb break="yes"/>not to differ more than about two minutes<lb break="yes"/>from M. Encke&#x2019;s calculations for the comet<lb break="yes"/>with the short period observed by him.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 