<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="182" facs="#f0001"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>PULQUE.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>(Abridged from Black&#x2019;s Translation of Humboldt&#x2019;s New Spain.)</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>There hardly exists a race of savages upon the<lb break="yes"/>face of the earth, who cannot prepare some kind of<lb break="yes"/>beverage from the vegetable kingdom; yet there are<lb break="yes"/>few nations who cultivate certain plants, merely<lb break="yes"/>with a view to prepare beverages from them. The<lb break="yes"/>most part of civilized nations, draw their drinks from<lb break="yes"/>the same plants which constitute the basis of their<lb break="yes"/>nourishment; and the old continent affords us no<lb break="yes"/>instance of vine plantations but west of the Indus.<lb break="yes"/>But in the new continent, we have the example of<lb break="yes"/>a people, who not only extract liquors from the amy-<lb break="no"/>laceous and sugary substance of the maize, the ma-<lb break="no"/>niock, and bananas, or from the pulp of several species<lb break="yes"/>of mimosa, but who cultivate expressly a plant of<lb break="yes"/>the family of the ananas, to convert its juice into a<lb break="yes"/>spirituous liquor, which is called pulque. On the<lb break="yes"/>interiour table-land, and in the intendency of Puebla,<lb break="yes"/>and in that of Mexico, through a vast extent of<lb break="yes"/>country, the eye reposes only on fields planted with<lb break="yes"/>pittes or maguey. This plant, of a coriaccous and<lb break="yes"/>prickly leaf, which, whith the <hi rendition="#i">cactus opuntia,</hi> has be-<lb break="no"/>come wild, since the sixteenth century, throughout<lb break="yes"/>all the south of Europe, the Canary islands, and the<lb break="yes"/>coast of Africa, gives a peculiar character to the<lb break="yes"/>Mexican landscape.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The agaves are planted in rows, at a distance of<lb break="yes"/>fifty-eight inches from each other. The plants only<lb break="yes"/>begin to yield the juice, which goes by the name of<lb break="yes"/>honey, on account of the sugary principle with<lb break="yes"/>which it abounds, when the hampe is on the point<lb break="yes"/>of its development. And as the plant is destroyed<lb break="yes"/>if the incision be made long before the flowers would<lb break="yes"/>naturally have developed themselves, it is of great<lb break="yes"/>importance for the cultivator to know exactly the<lb break="yes"/>period of efflorescence. Its proximity is announced<lb break="yes"/>by appearances, which the experienced cultivator<lb break="yes"/>readily understands. He goes daily through his<lb break="yes"/>plantations to mark the plants that approach afflo-<lb break="no"/>rescence; and if he has any doubt, he applies to the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">experts</hi> of the village&#x2014;old Indians, who, from longer<lb break="yes"/>experience, have a judgment, or rather tact, more<lb break="yes"/>securely to be relied on.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>About the age of eight years in general, but in<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> good soils so early as five, and in bad not till eigh-<lb break="no" />teen, a maguey begins to give signs of the develop-<lb break="no"/>ment of its hampe. They th@ prepare to collect<lb break="yes"/>the juice of which the pulque is made. They cut<lb break="yes"/>the bundle of central leaves, and enlarge, insensibly,<lb break="yes"/>the wound, covering it with lateral leaves, which<lb break="yes"/>they raise by drawing them close and tying them at<lb break="yes"/>the extremities. In this wound the vessels appear<lb break="yes"/>to deposite all the juice which would have formed the<lb break="yes"/>colossal hampe, loaded with flowers. This is a true<lb break="yes"/>vegetable spring, that keeps running for two or three<lb break="yes"/>months, and from which the Indian draws three or<lb break="yes"/>four times a day. We may judge of the quickness<lb break="yes"/>or slowness of the motion of the juice, by the quan-<lb break="no"/>tity of honey extracted from the maguey at different<lb break="yes"/>times of the day: a plant commonly yields, in<lb break="yes"/>twenty-four hours, 242 cubick inches, nea@ equal to<lb break="yes"/>eight pints, of which three are obtained @,<lb break="yes" />two at mid-day, and three at six in th@ evening.<lb break="yes"/>A very vigorous plant sometimes yields about seven<lb break="yes"/>quarts, or 454 cubick inches, per day, for from four<lb break="yes"/>to five months, which amounts to the enormous<lb break="yes"/>quantity of 67,130 cubick inches, supplied by a plant<lb break="yes"/>scarcely five feet in height.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The honey, or juice of the agave, is of a very<lb break="yes"/>agreeable sour taste. It easily ferments on account<lb break="yes"/>of the sugar and mucilage which it contains. To<lb break="yes"/>accelerate this fermentation, they add, however, a<lb break="yes"/>little old and acid pulque. This operation is termi-<lb break="no"/>nated in three or four days. The vinous beverage,<lb break="yes"/>which resembles cider, has an odour of putrid meat,<lb break="yes"/>extremely disagreeable; but Europeans who have<lb break="yes"/>been able to get over the aversion which this fetid<lb break="yes"/>odour inspires, prefer the pulque to any other liquor.<lb break="yes"/>They consider it as stomachick, strengthening, and<lb break="yes"/>especially as very nutritive; and it is recommended<lb break="yes"/>to lean persons.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A very intoxicating brandy is formed from the<lb break="yes"/>pulque, which is called <hi rendition="#i">mexical</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">aguardiente de<lb break="yes"/>maguey,</hi> and though the Spanish colonial government<lb break="yes"/>prohibited its use, as prejudicial to the Spanish<lb break="yes"/>brandy trade, such quantities of it were manufactured,<lb break="yes"/>that the whole importation of brandy into Mexico<lb break="yes"/>alone amounted to 32,000 barrels.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>But the maguey is not only the wine of the Aztecks,<lb break="yes"/>it can also supply the place of the hemp of Asia,<lb break="yes"/>and the papyrus of the Egyptians. The paper on<lb break="yes"/>which the ancient Mexicans painted their hiero-<lb break="no"/>glyphical figures, was made of the fibres of agave<lb break="yes"/>leaves, macerated in water, and disposed in layers<lb break="yes"/>like the Egyptian papyrus, and the mulberry of the<lb break="yes"/>South Sea islands. M. Humboldt brought home<lb break="yes"/>with him several fragments of Azteck manuscripts,<lb break="yes"/>written on maguey papers of a thickness, so different,<lb break="yes"/>that some of them resembled pasteboard, while<lb break="yes"/>others resembled Chinese paper. The thread which<lb break="yes"/>is obtained from the maguey, is known in Europe<lb break="yes"/>by the name of pite thread, and is preferred by<lb break="yes"/>naturalists to every other, because it is less subject<lb break="yes"/>to twist. The juice which the agave yields, when<lb break="yes"/>it is still far from the period of efflorescence, is very<lb break="yes"/>acid, and is successfully employed as a caustick in<lb break="yes"/>the cleansing of wounds. The prickles, which ter-<lb break="no"/>minate the leaves, served, formerly, like those of<lb break="yes"/>the cactus, for pins and nails to the Indian@</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 