<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/103788910X">
                        <surname>Metz</surname>
                        <forename>Bernhard</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-24" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="440" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>PULQUE.<lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">Abridged from Black&#x2019;s Translation of &#x2018;Humboldt&#x2019;s New Spain.&#x2019;</hi>)</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">There</hi> hardly exists a race of savages upon the face of<lb break="yes"/>the earth who cannot prepare some kind of beverage<lb break="yes"/>from the vegetable kingdom: yet there are few nations<lb break="yes"/>who cultivate certain plants merely with a view to pre-<lb break="no"/>pare beverages from them. The most part of civilized<lb break="yes"/>nations draw their drinks from the same plants which<lb break="yes"/>constitute the basis of their nourishment; and the old<lb break="yes"/>continent affords us no instance of vine plantations but<lb break="yes"/>to the west of the Indus. But in the new continent we<lb break="yes"/>have the example of a people who not only extract liquors<lb break="yes"/>from the amylaceous and sugary substance of the maize,<lb break="yes"/>the manioc, and bananas, or from the pulp of several<lb break="yes"/>species of mimosa, but who cultivate expressly a plant of<lb break="yes"/>the family of the ananas, to convert its juice into a spi-<lb break="no"/>rituous liquor, which is called Pulque. On the interior<lb break="yes"/>table land, and in the intendency of Puebla, and in that<lb break="yes"/>of Mexico, through a vast extent of country, the eye<lb break="yes"/>reposes only on fields planted with pittes or maguey.<lb break="yes"/>This plant, of a coriaceous and prickly leaf, which, with<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">cactus opuntia,</hi> has become wild since the sixteenth<lb break="yes"/>century throughout all the south of Europe, the Canary<lb break="yes"/>Islands, and the Coast of Africa, gives a peculiar cha-<lb break="no"/>racter to the Mexican landscape.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The agaves are planted in rows at a distance of fifty-<lb break="no"/>eight inches from each other. The plants only begin<lb break="yes"/>to yield the juice which goes by the name of honey, on<lb break="yes"/>account of the sugary principle with which it abounds<lb break="yes"/>when the hampe is on the point of its development.<lb break="yes"/>And as the plant is destroyed if the incision be made<lb break="yes"/>long before the flowers would naturally have developed<lb break="yes"/>themselves, it is of great importance for the cultivator to<lb break="yes"/>know exactly the period of efflorescence. Its proximity<lb break="yes"/>is announced by appearances which the experienced<lb break="yes"/>cultivator readily understands. He goes daily through<lb break="yes"/>his plantations to mark the plants that approach efflo-<lb break="no"/>rescence; and if he has any doubt he applies to the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">experts</hi> of the village&#x2014;old Indians, who, from longer<lb break="yes"/>experience, have a judgment or rather tact more securely<lb break="yes"/>to be relied on.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>About the age of eight years in general, but in good<lb break="yes"/>soils so early as five, and in bad not till eighteen, a<lb break="yes"/>maguey begins to give signs of the development of its<lb break="yes"/>hampe. They then prepare to collect the juice of which<lb break="yes"/>the pulque is made. They cut the bundle of central<lb break="yes"/>leaves and enlarge, insensibly, the wound, covering it<lb break="yes"/>with lateral leaves, which they raise by drawing them<lb break="yes"/>close and tying them at the extremities. In this wound<lb break="yes"/>the vessels appear to deposit all the juice which would<lb break="yes"/>have formed the colossal hampe loaded with flowers.<lb break="yes"/>This is a true vegetable spring that keeps running for<lb break="yes"/>two or three months, and from which the Indian draws<lb break="yes"/>three or four times a-day. We may judge of the quick-<lb break="no"/>ness or slowness of the motion of the juice by the quan-<lb break="no"/>tity of honey extracted from the maguey at different<lb break="yes"/>times of the day: a plant commonly yields, in twenty-<lb break="maybe"/>four hours, 242 cubic inches, nearly equal to eight pints,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> of which three are obtained at sun-rise, two at mid-day,<lb break="yes" />and three at six in the evening. A very vigorous plant<lb break="yes" />sometimes yields about seven quarts, or 454 cubic inches,<lb break="yes"/>per day for from four to five months, which amounts to<lb break="yes"/>the enormous quantity of 67,130 cubic inches, supplied<lb break="yes"/>by a plant scarcely five feet in height.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The honey, or juice of the agave, is of a very agreeable<lb break="yes"/>sour taste. It easily ferments on account of the sugar<lb break="yes"/>and mucilage which it contains. To accelerate this<lb break="yes"/>fermentation they add, however, a little old and acid<lb break="yes"/>pulque. This operation is terminated in three or four<lb break="yes"/>days. The vinous beverage, which resembles cider<lb break="yes"/>has an odour of putrid meat, extremely disagreeable;<lb break="yes"/>but Europeans who have been able to get over the<lb break="yes"/>aversion which this fetid odour inspires, prefer the<lb break="yes"/>pulque to any other liquor. They consider it as stoma-<lb break="no"/>chic, strengthening, and especially as very nutritive;<lb break="yes"/>and it is recommended to lean persons.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A very intoxicating brandy is formed from the pulque,<lb break="yes"/>which is called <hi rendition="#i">mexical</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">aguardiente de maguey,</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>though the Spanish colonial government prohibited its<lb break="yes"/>use, as prejudicial to the Spanish brandy trade, such<lb break="yes"/>quantities of it were manufactured, that the whole<lb break="yes"/>importation of brandy into Mexico alone amounted to<lb break="yes"/>32,000 barrels.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But the maguey is not only the wine of the Aztecs, it<lb break="yes"/>can also supply the place of the hemp of Asia, and the<lb break="yes"/>papyrus of the Egyptians. The paper on which the<lb break="yes"/>ancient Mexicans painted their hieroglyphical figures<lb break="yes"/>was made of the fibres of agave leaves, macerated in<lb break="yes"/>water, and disposed in layers like the Egyptian papyrus,<lb break="yes"/>and the mulberry of the South Sea Islands. M. Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt brought home with him several fragments of<lb break="yes"/>Aztec manuscripts written on maguey papers of a<lb break="yes" />thickness so different that some of them resembled<lb break="yes"/>pasteboard, while others resembled Chinese paper. The<lb break="yes"/>thread which is obtained from the maguey is known in<lb break="yes"/>Europe by the name of pite thread, and is preferred by<lb break="yes"/>naturalists to every other, because it is less subject to<lb break="yes"/>twist. The juice which the agave yields, when it is still<lb break="yes"/>far from the period of efflorescence, is very acid, and is<lb break="yes"/>successfully employed as a caustic in the cleansing of<lb break="yes"/>wounds. The prickles which terminate the leaves served<lb break="yes"/>formerly, like those of the cactus, for pins and nails to<lb break="yes"/>the Indians.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 