<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Pulque</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:04</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">V.24</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1833-Pulque-2-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1833-Pulque-1-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1833-Pulque-2-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1833-Pulque-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1833-Pulque-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>&lt;i&gt;Essai politique sur le royaume de la Nouvelle-Espagne. Avec un atlas physique et géographique, fondé sur des observations astronomiques, des mesures trigonométriques et des nivellemens barométriques&lt;/i&gt;, 2 Bände, Paris: F. Schoell [1808–] 1811, Band 2, S. 417–422 [Quart-Ausgabe] [stark gekürzt und kompiliert]</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>&lt;i&gt;Political Essay on the Kingdom of New Spain&lt;/i&gt;, übersetzt von John Black, 4 Bände, London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, Brown / H. Colburn 1811, Band 2, S. 470–481 [stark gekürzt und kompiliert]</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Pulque</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1836</date>
          <pubPlace>Cincinnati, Ohio</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Family Magazine; or, Monthly Abstract of General Knowledge&lt;/i&gt; 1:4 (April 1836), S. 182, Tafel.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="182" facs="#f0001"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>PULQUE.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>(Abridged from Black&#x2019;s Translation of Humboldt&#x2019;s New Spain.)</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>There hardly exists a race of savages upon the<lb break="yes"/>face of the
            earth, who cannot prepare some kind of<lb break="yes"/>beverage from the vegetable
            kingdom; yet there are<lb break="yes"/>few nations who cultivate certain plants,
              merely<lb break="yes"/>with a view to prepare beverages from them. The<lb break="yes"
            />most part of civilized nations, draw their drinks from<lb break="yes"/>the same plants
            which constitute the basis of their<lb break="yes"/>nourishment; and the old continent
            affords us no<lb break="yes"/>instance of vine plantations but west of the Indus.<lb
              break="yes"/>But in the new continent, we have the example of<lb break="yes"/>a
            people, who not only extract liquors from the amy-<lb break="no"/>laceous and sugary
            substance of the maize, the ma-<lb break="no"/>niock, and bananas, or from the pulp of
            several species<lb break="yes"/>of mimosa, but who cultivate expressly a plant of<lb
              break="yes"/>the family of the ananas, to convert its juice into a<lb break="yes"
            />spirituous liquor, which is called pulque. On the<lb break="yes"/>interiour
            table-land, and in the intendency of Puebla,<lb break="yes"/>and in that of Mexico,
            through a vast extent of<lb break="yes"/>country, the eye reposes only on fields planted
              with<lb break="yes"/>pittes or maguey. This plant, of a coriaceous and<lb break="yes"
            />prickly leaf, which, whith the <hi rendition="#i">cactus opuntia,</hi> has be-<lb
              break="no"/>come wild, since the sixteenth century, throughout<lb break="yes"/>all the
            south of Europe, the Canary islands, and the<lb break="yes"/>coast of Africa, gives a
            peculiar character to the<lb break="yes"/>Mexican landscape.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The agaves are planted in rows, at a distance of<lb break="yes"/>fifty-eight inches from each other. The plants only<lb break="yes"/>begin to yield the juice, which goes by the name of<lb break="yes"/>honey, on account of the sugary principle with<lb break="yes"/>which it abounds, when the hampe is on the point<lb break="yes"/>of its development. And as the plant is destroyed<lb break="yes"/>if the incision be made long before the flowers would<lb break="yes"/>naturally have developed themselves, it is of great<lb break="yes"/>importance for the cultivator to know exactly the<lb break="yes"/>period of efflorescence. Its proximity is announced<lb break="yes"/>by appearances, which the experienced cultivator<lb break="yes"/>readily understands. He goes daily through his<lb break="yes"/>plantations to mark the plants that approach afflo-<lb break="no"/>rescence; and if he has any doubt, he applies to the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">experts</hi> of the village&#x2014;old Indians, who, from longer<lb break="yes"/>experience, have a judgment, or rather tact, more<lb break="yes"/>securely to be relied on.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>About the age of eight years in general, but in<lb break="yes"/>
            <cb/> good soils so early as five, and in bad not till eigh-<lb break="no"/>teen, a
            maguey begins to give signs of the develop-<lb break="no"/>ment of its hampe. They then
            prepare to collect<lb break="yes"/>the juice of which the pulque is made. They cut<lb
              break="yes"/>the bundle of central leaves, and enlarge, insensibly,<lb break="yes"
            />the wound, covering it with lateral leaves, which<lb break="yes"/>they raise by
            drawing them close and tying them at<lb break="yes"/>the extremities. In this wound the
            vessels appear<lb break="yes"/>to deposite all the juice which would have formed the<lb
              break="yes"/>colossal hampe, loaded with flowers. This is a true<lb break="yes"
            />vegetable spring, that keeps running for two or three<lb break="yes"/>months, and from
            which the Indian draws three or<lb break="yes"/>four times a day. We may judge of the
              quickness<lb break="yes"/>or slowness of the motion of the juice, by the quan-<lb
              break="no"/>tity of honey extracted from the maguey at different<lb break="yes"/>times
            of the day: a plant commonly yields, in<lb break="yes"/>twenty-four hours, 242 cubick
            inches, nearly equal to<lb break="yes"/>eight pints, of which three are obtained at
              sunrise,<lb break="yes"/>two at mid-day, and three at six in the evening.<lb
              break="yes"/>A very vigorous plant sometimes yields about seven<lb break="yes"
            />quarts, or 454 cubick inches, per day, for from four<lb break="yes"/>to five months,
            which amounts to the enormous<lb break="yes"/>quantity of 67,130 cubick inches, supplied
            by a plant<lb break="yes"/>scarcely five feet in height.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The honey, or juice of the agave, is of a very<lb break="yes"/>agreeable sour taste. It easily ferments on account<lb break="yes"/>of the sugar and mucilage which it contains. To<lb break="yes"/>accelerate this fermentation, they add, however, a<lb break="yes"/>little old and acid pulque. This operation is termi-<lb break="no"/>nated in three or four days. The vinous beverage,<lb break="yes"/>which resembles cider, has an odour of putrid meat,<lb break="yes"/>extremely disagreeable; but Europeans who have<lb break="yes"/>been able to get over the aversion which this fetid<lb break="yes"/>odour inspires, prefer the pulque to any other liquor.<lb break="yes"/>They consider it as stomachick, strengthening, and<lb break="yes"/>especially as very nutritive; and it is recommended<lb break="yes"/>to lean persons.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A very intoxicating brandy is formed from the<lb break="yes"/>pulque, which is called <hi rendition="#i">mexical</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">aguardiente de<lb break="yes"/>maguey,</hi> and though the Spanish colonial government<lb break="yes"/>prohibited its use, as prejudicial to the Spanish<lb break="yes"/>brandy trade, such quantities of it were manufactured,<lb break="yes"/>that the whole importation of brandy into Mexico<lb break="yes"/>alone amounted to 32,000 barrels.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>But the maguey is not only the wine of the Aztecks,<lb break="yes"/>it can
            also supply the place of the hemp of Asia,<lb break="yes"/>and the papyrus of the
            Egyptians. The paper on<lb break="yes"/>which the ancient Mexicans painted their
              hiero-<lb break="no"/>glyphical figures, was made of the fibres of agave<lb
              break="yes"/>leaves, macerated in water, and disposed in layers<lb break="yes"/>like
            the Egyptian papyrus, and the mulberry of the<lb break="yes"/>South Sea islands. M.
            Humboldt brought home<lb break="yes"/>with him several fragments of Azteck
              manuscripts,<lb break="yes"/>written on maguey papers of a thickness, so different,<lb
              break="yes"/>that some of them resembled pasteboard, while<lb break="yes"/>others
            resembled Chinese paper. The thread which<lb break="yes"/>is obtained from the maguey,
            is known in Europe<lb break="yes"/>by the name of pite thread, and is preferred by<lb
              break="yes"/>naturalists to every other, because it is less subject<lb break="yes"/>to
            twist. The juice which the agave yields, when<lb break="yes"/>it is still far from the
            period of efflorescence, is very<lb break="yes"/>acid, and is successfully employed as a
            caustick in<lb break="yes"/>the cleansing of wounds. The prickles, which ter-<lb
              break="no"/>minate the leaves, served, formerly, like those of<lb break="yes"/>the
            cactus, for pins and nails to the Indians.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 