<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-14" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="130" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Baron de Humboldt.</hi>&#x2014;In the expectation that we<lb/>
                    should receive letters from Germany on the subject, we at<lb/>
                    first deferred, and subsequently forgot to record the<lb/>
                    death of this celebrated man. It is, however, not yet too<lb/>
                    late, and we shallm therefore, translate the following ex-<lb/>
                    tract from a letter, written by the celebrated traveller,<lb/>
                    Baron Alexander de Humboldt, to M. Arago. &#x201C;While<lb/>
                    labouring under heavy affliction, we always think of those<lb/>
                    dearest to us, and I feel soothed by writing to you. We<lb/>
                    watched his dying bed for ten days; his weakness had<lb/>
                    been much increased for several weeks previous, and in-<lb/>
                    cessant trembling was manifested in every limb; still his<lb/>
                    mind preserved all its energy, and he never ceased his<lb/>
                    labours. He leaves two works nearly finished, the one on<lb/>
                    those languages of the Indian Archipelago which proceed<lb/>
                    from the Sanscrit, and the other on the origin and phi-<lb/>
                    losophy of languages in general, both of which will be pub-<lb/>
                    lished. My brother has left all the MSS of these works,<lb/>
                    and his precious collection of books, to the public library.<lb/>
                    He died of an inflammation on the lungs, and, from the<lb/>
                    beginning, traced the progress of the malady with an afflict-<lb/>
                    ing certainty. His was a mind of the highest order, and he<lb/>
                    had a noble and elevated soul; I remain sadly isolated,<lb/>
                    but I hope to have the pleasure of embracing you this<lb/>
                    year.&#x201D; We have only a few words to add from our per-<lb/>
                    sonal knowledge of our brother here so justly lamented.<lb/>
                    Besides the high character borne in private life, as a hus-<lb/>
                    band, a father, a brother, and a friend, the Baron William<lb/>
                    de Humboldt was distinguished as a satesman and a<lb/>
                    savant: his career of ambassador and minister secured him<lb/>
                    the friendship of his sovereign, and his learning the consi-<lb/>
                    deration of civilized Europe. His vigorous mind was prin-<lb/>
                    cipally directed, not only to a colloquial knowledge of lan-<lb/>
                    guages, but to the philosophy of all tongues of which he<lb/>
                    could obtain certain information. Not only were Euro-<lb/>
                    pean and Oriental languages familir to him, but he<lb/>
                    comprehended those of North and South America, and<lb/>
                    he was incessantly seeking for data concerning those of<lb/>
                    which there are but obscure traces. We once saw him<lb/>
                    question a young and enlightened traveller, just returned<lb/>
                    from barbarous climes, and his usually mild manner<lb/>
                    assumed the most keend and searching form, and we never<lb/>
                    shall forget the expression of his prominent eyes, as he<lb/>
                    fixed them on his informer, evidently wishing to know<lb/>
                    more than even the language itseld could afford.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Athe-<lb/>
                    neum.</hi>
                    
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 