<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">TRACES OF MAMMALIA IN THE NEW RED SAND-<lb/>STONE</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">grès bigarré</hi>) <hi rendition="#k">OF HILDBURGHAUSEN<lb/>IN GERMANY, COMMUNICATED TO THE ACA-<lb/>DEMY OF SCIENCES OF FRANCE, BY M. DE<lb/>HUMBOLDT, AUGUST 19</hi>.</head>
        <p>About a year since, a distinguished savant, M. Seigler,<lb/>observed the impressions of the feet of some animals on<lb/>the surface of the sandstone, in a quarry near Hildburg-<lb/>hausen. Living animals had evidently made these impres-<lb/>sions on the sandstone while it was in a soft state, and they<lb/>appeared to have walked over the sand in various directions.<lb/>There are impressions of the feet of several small animals,<lb/>but the most important are those of some large mammalia.<lb/>From a careful examination of the impressions last men-<lb/>tioned, it is inferred that they have been made by the feet<lb/>of an animal of the <hi rendition="#i">marsupial</hi> order (that is, of animals<lb/>bearing their young in a pouch like the kangaroo), but the<lb/>form and direction of the fingers and toes are unlike those<lb/>of any known recent animals. In a large slab of the sand-<lb/>stone deposited in the museum at Berlin, the impressions<lb/>are shewn in relief; those of the hind feet indicate a very<lb/>fleshy foot. The animal appears to have trod with all its<lb/>weight; its step resembles that of the bear, a sort of am-<lb/>ble, the anterior right extremity being placed very regularly<lb/>near the hind right foot. Even in the forefeet the thumb is<lb/>separated from the other fingers, almost as in the quadri-<lb/>mana. Some of the impressions of the hind feet are<lb/>twelve or thirteen inches long. Independently of the<lb/>nature of the animal which has occasioned these im-<lb/>pressions, the phenomenon in question is of vast import-<lb/>ance to geologists, because it adds another to the few<lb/>authenticated instances hitherto known, of the existence of<lb/>mammalia at a very remote perios of the earth&#x2014;a period<lb/>immediately subsequent to the deposition of the coal<lb/>measures. At that epoch we know there were vast islands<lb/>or continents clothed with vegetation, and these may have<lb/>been inhabited by mammiferous animals. This discovery<lb/>will in nowise affect the well established fact of the vast<lb/>preponderance of enormous reptiles at that period of the<lb/>secondary formations so emphatically called the <hi rendition="#i">age of rep-<lb/>tiles</hi>, and which a late writer in a Bridgwater Essay has so<lb/>strangely attempted to refute! But what vagaries will not<lb/>an author indulge in, who imagines that the Iguanodon and<lb/>other enormous fossil saurians may still exist in some<lb/>&#x201C;subterranean metropolis of the reptile world&#x201D; (vide<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Kirby&#x2019;s Essay</hi>), and explains the absence of the fossil<lb/>remains of man by assuming that the Almighty willed that<lb/>the bones of the antediluvians should be concealed for ever<lb/>from our view!</p></div><lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
