<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="42" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#i">Letter from</hi> Baron von Humboldt <hi rendition="#i">to
                        His Royal Highness<lb/>the Duke of</hi> Sussex, K.G., <hi rendition="#i"
                        >President of the Royal Society of<lb/>London, on the Advancement of the
                        Knowledge of Terrestrial<lb/>Magnetism, by the Establishment of Magnetic
                        Stations and<lb/>corresponding Observations.</hi><note place="foot"
                        n="&#x2020;">We translate this letter from Schumacher&#x2019;s <hi
                            rendition="#i">Astronomische Nachrichten</hi>,<lb/>No. 306, which has
                        been kindly communicated to us for the purpose.</note></head>
                <lb/>
                <opener><salute><hi rendition="#k">Sir,</hi></salute></opener>
                <lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#in">T</hi>HE generous interest taken by Your Royal Highness
                    in<lb/>the advancement of human knowledge, encourages me to<lb/>hope for the
                    favourable reception of the request which with re-<lb/>spectful confidence, I
                    now venture to address to you. I take<lb/>the liberty of soliciting your
                    attention to the labours requisite<lb/>for the investigation, by precise means,
                    almost constantly em-<lb/>ployed, of the variations of <hi rendition="#i"
                        >terrestrial magnetism.</hi> By obtaining<lb/>the cooperation of a great
                    number of zealous observers, pro-<lb/>vided with instruments of similar
                    construction, M. Arago,<lb/><pb n="43" facs="#f0002"/> Mr. Kupffer, and myself
                    have succeeded in the last eight years<lb/>in extending these researches over a
                    very considerable part<lb/>of the northern hemisphere. Permanent <hi
                        rendition="#i">magnetic stations</hi> be-<lb/>ing now established from Paris
                    to China, following towards<lb/>the east the parallels from 40° to 60°, I feel
                    myself justified<lb/>in soliciting, through the intervention of Your Royal
                    Highness,<lb/>the powerful cooperation of the Royal Society of London,
                    to<lb/>sanction this enterprise, and also to promote its success by
                    the<lb/>establishment of new stations, as well in the vicinity of
                    the<lb/>magnetic equator as in the temperate part of the
                    southern<lb/>hemisphere.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>An object which is equally important whether it be consi-<lb/>dered in connexion
                    with the physics of the earth or the im-<lb/>provement of nautical science, has
                    a double claim upon the<lb/>attention of a Society, which has from its
                    commencement, with<lb/>constantly increasing success, cultivated the vast field
                    of the<lb/>exact sciences. Our information respecting the
                    progressive<lb/>development of the knowledge which we possess of <hi
                        rendition="#i">terrestrial<lb/>magnetism</hi> must be indeed imperfect, if
                    we are ignorant of the<lb/>numerous valuable observations which have been made
                    at dif-<lb/>ferent epochs, and are still being made, in the British
                    isles,<lb/>and in various parts of the equinoctial zone subject to the<lb/>same
                    empire. Our present object is to render these observa-<lb/>tions more useful,
                    that is, better adapted to manifest great<lb/>physical laws, by coordinating
                    them according to a uniform<lb/>plan, and connecting them with the observations
                    now in pro-<lb/>gress upon the continent of Europe and Northern Asia.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Having been much occupied during my travels in the equi-<lb/>noctial regions of
                    America, during the years 1799&#x2014;1804, with<lb/>the ph&#x00E6;nomena of the
                    intensity of the magnetic forces, and the<lb/>inclination and declination of the
                    magnetic needle, on my re-<lb/>turn to my own country I conceived the design of
                    examining<lb/>the progress of the <hi rendition="#i">horary variations of the
                        declination,</hi> and<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">perturbations</hi> to which
                    it is liable, by employing a method<lb/>which, I believe, has never yet been
                    followed upon an exten-<lb/>sive scale. In a large garden at Berlin, during the
                    years<lb/>1806 and 1807, particularly at the period of the equinoxes<lb/>and
                    solstices, I measured the angular alterations of the mag-<lb/>netic meridian, at
                    intervals of an hour, often of half an hour,<lb/>without interruption during
                    four, five, and six days, and as<lb/>many nights. Mr. Oltmanns, whose numerous
                    calculations of<lb/>geographical positions have recommended him to the
                    notice<lb/>of astronomers, kindly shared with me the fatigues of
                    these<lb/>labours. The instrument which we employed was a magnetic<lb/>telescope
                        (<hi rendition="#i">lunette aimantée</hi>) of Prony, capable of being
                    reversed<lb/>upon its axis, suspended according to the method of
                        Coulomb,<lb/><pb n="44" facs="#f0003"/> placed in a glass frame, and
                    directed towards a very distant<lb/>meridian mark, the divisions of which,
                    illuminated during the<lb/>night, indicated even six or seven seconds of horary
                    variation.<lb/>In verifying the habitual regularity of a <hi rendition="#i"
                        >nocturnal period,</hi><lb/>I was struck with the frequency of the
                    perturbations, espe-<lb/>cially of oscillations the amplitude of which extended
                    beyond<lb/>all the divisions of the scale, and which occurred repeatedly<lb/>at
                    the same hours before sunrise, and the violent and ac-<lb/>celerated movements
                    of which could not be attributed to any<lb/>accidental mechanical cause. These
                    vagaries of the needle, the<lb/>almost periodical return of which has recently
                    been confirmed<lb/>by Mr. Kupffer in the narration of his Travels in the
                    Caucasus,<lb/>appeared to me the effect of a reaction of the interior of
                    the<lb/>earth towards the surface; I should venture to say, of <hi
                        rendition="#i">magnetic<lb/>storms,</hi> which indicate a rapid change of
                    tension. From that<lb/>time it has been my desire to establish on the east and
                    west<lb/>of the meridian of Berlin apparatus similar to my own, in<lb/>order to
                    obtain corresponding observations made at great di-<lb/>stances and at the same
                    hours; but the political tempest of<lb/>Germany, and my hasty departure for
                    France, whither I was<lb/>sent by the Government, delayed for a length of time
                    the ex-<lb/>ecution of this project. Fortunately my illustrious friend<lb/>M.
                    Arago, after his return from the coasts of Africa and the<lb/>prisons of Spain,
                    undertook, I think about the year 1818, a<lb/>series of observations upon
                    magnetic declinations at the Ob-<lb/>servatory of Paris, which, made daily at
                    intervals uniformly<lb/>fixed, and continued upon the same plan to the present
                    day,<lb/>are considered, with regard to their number and mutual con-<lb/>nexion,
                    superior to everything that has been attempted in<lb/>this kind of physical
                    investigations. Gambey&#x2019;s apparatus,<lb/>which is employed, is of perfect
                    execution. Provided with<lb/>micrometers and microscopes, it may be employed
                    with more<lb/>certainty and convenience than Prony&#x2019;s instrument, which
                    is<lb/>attached to a strong magnetized bar of 20<formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{4}</formula> inches in length.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>During the progress of these observations M. Arago has<lb/>discovered, and proved
                    by numerous examples, a ph&#x00E6;nomenon<lb/>which differs essentially from the
                    observation made by Prof.<lb/>Hiorter at Upsal in 1741. He has discovered not
                    only that<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">Auror&#x00E6; boreales</hi> disturb the
                    regular progress of the horary<lb/>declinations there when they are not visible,
                    but also that<lb/>early in the morning, often ten or twelve hours before the
                    lu-<lb/>minous ph&#x00E6;nomenon is developed in a very distant place,
                    its<lb/>appearance is announced by the particular form presented by<lb/>the
                    curve of the diurnal variations, that is, by the value of the<lb/><hi
                        rendition="#i">maxima</hi> of elongation of the morning and night. Another
                    new<lb/>fact was manifested in the perturbations. Mr. Kupffer having<lb/><pb
                        n="45" facs="#f0004"/> established at Cazan, nearly the eastern limit of
                    Europe, one<lb/>of Gambey&#x2019;s compasses, exactly similar to that employed
                    by<lb/>M. Arago at Paris, the two observers were convinced by a<lb/>certain
                    number of corresponding measures of horary declina-<lb/>tion, that,
                    notwithstanding a difference of longitude of more<lb/>than 47°, the
                    perturbations were isochronous. They were like<lb/>signals which from the
                    interior of the earth simultaneously<lb/>arrived at its surface on the borders
                    of the Seine and the<lb/>Wolga.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>When in 1827 I again fixed my residence at Berlin, my<lb/>first care was to renew
                    the series of observations which I had<lb/>made at short intervals during the
                    days and nights of the<lb/>years 1806 and 1807. I endeavoured at the same time
                    to<lb/>generalize the means of simultaneous observations, the acci-<lb/>dental
                    employment of which had just produced results so im-<lb/>portant. One of
                    Gambey&#x2019;s compasses was placed in the <hi rendition="#i">mag-<lb/>netic
                        pavilion,</hi> in which no portion of iron was introduced,<lb/>which had
                    been erected in the middle of a garden. Regular<lb/>observations could not
                    commence till the autumn of 1828.<lb/>Being called, in the spring of 1829, by
                    His Majesty the Em-<lb/>peror of Russia, to undertake a mineralogical tour in
                    the<lb/>North of Asia and on the Caspian Sea, I had an opportunity<lb/>rapidly
                    to extend the line of stations towards the east. At<lb/>my request the Imperial
                    Academy and the Curator of the<lb/>University of Cazan erected <hi
                        rendition="#i">magnetic houses</hi> at St. Petersburgh<lb/>and Cazan. In a
                    committee of the Imperial Academy, at<lb/>which I had the honour of presiding, a
                    discussion took place<lb/>on the immense advantages, with regard to our
                    knowledge of<lb/>the laws of terrestrial magnetism, presented by the vast
                    extent<lb/>of country limited on one side by the curve without declina-<lb/>tion
                    of Doskino, (between Moscow and Cazan, or with more<lb/>precision, according to
                    M. Adolphe Erman, between Osabli-<lb/>kowo and Doskino, in lat. 56° 0&#x2032;,
                    and long. 40° 36&#x2032; east<lb/>of Paris,) and on the other, by the curve
                    without declina-<lb/>tion of Arsentchewa near Lake Baikal, which is believed
                    to<lb/>be identical with that of Doskino, with a difference of meri-<lb/>dians
                    of 63° 21&#x2032;. The Imperial department for Mines having<lb/>generously
                    concurred in the same object, <hi rendition="#i">magnetic stations</hi><lb/>have
                    been successively established at Moscow, Barnaoul, the<lb/>astronomical position
                    of which I find to be at the foot of<lb/>Altai, in lat. 53° 19&#x2032;
                    21&#x2033;, long. 5<hi rendition="#sup">h</hi> 27&#x2032; 20&#x2033; east of
                    Paris, and<lb/>at Nertschinsk. The Academy of St. Petersburgh has done<lb/>still
                    more, and has sent a courageous and clever astronomer,<lb/>M. George Fuss, the
                    brother of its perpetual secretary, to<lb/>Pekin, and has procured the erection
                    there of a <hi rendition="#i">magnetic<lb/>pavilion,</hi> in the convent garden
                    of the monks of the Greek<lb/><pb n="46" facs="#f0005"/> church. This
                    undertaking cannot be mentioned without re-<lb/>calling the fact, that,
                    according to the <hi rendition="#i">Penthsaoyani,</hi> a me-<lb/>dical natural
                    history composed under the Soung dynasty,<lb/>nearly four hundred years before
                    Christopher Columbus and<lb/>the natives of Europe had the least idea of
                    magnetic declina-<lb/>tion, the Chinese suspended the needle by means of a
                    thread,<lb/>to allow it perfect freedom of motion; and that they knew
                    that<lb/>when thus suspended, according to the method of Coulomb,<lb/>(as in the
                    Jesuit Lana&#x2019;s apparatus in the seventeenth century,)<lb/>the needle
                    declined to the south-east, and never rested at the<lb/>true south point. Since
                    the return of M. Fuss, M. Kowanko,<lb/>a young officer of mines, whom I had the
                    pleasure to meet<lb/>in the Oural, continues the observations of horary
                    declination,<lb/>corresponding to those of Germany, St. Petersburgh,
                    Cazan,<lb/>and Nicolajeff in the Crimea, where Admiral Greigh has
                    esta-<lb/>blished one of Gambey&#x2019;s compasses, the care of which is
                    con-<lb/>fided to the director of the Observatory, Mr. Knorre. I have<lb/>also
                    obtained the establishment of a magnetic apparatus at the<lb/>depth of
                    thirty-five fathoms in an adit in the mines of Freiberg<lb/>in Saxony, where Mr.
                    Reich to whom we are indebted for his<lb/>valuable labours upon the mean
                    temperature of the earth at dif-<lb/>ferent depths, is assiduously engaged in
                    making observations at<lb/>regulated intervals. M. Boussingault, who neglects
                    nothing<lb/>which is calculated to advance the progress of the physics of
                    the<lb/>earth, has sent us from South America observations of
                    horary<lb/>declination made at Marmato, in the province of Antioquia,
                    in<lb/>north lat. 5° 27&#x2032;, in a place where the declination is
                    eastern,<lb/>as at Cazan and Barnaoul in Asia; while on the
                    north-western<lb/>coasts of the new continent, at Sitka in the Russian
                    settle-<lb/>ments, Baron von Wrangel, also provided with one of
                    Gam-<lb/>bey&#x2019;s compasses, has taken part in the simultaneous
                    observa-<lb/>tions made at the time of the solstices and equinoxes. A
                    Spanish<lb/>admiral, M. de Laborde, having been informed of a request<lb/>that I
                    had made to the Patriotic Society of the Havannah, had<lb/>the kindness,
                    unsolicited, to desire me to send him instruments<lb/>proper for determining
                    with precision the inclination, the ab-<lb/>solute declination, and the horary
                    variation of declination and<lb/>intensity of the magnetic forces. The valuable
                    instruments<lb/>desired, exactly similar to those in the possession of the
                    Obser-<lb/>vatory of Paris, arrived in safety in the island of Cuba; but
                    the<lb/>alteration in the maritime command at the Havannah, and other<lb/>local
                    circumstances, have hitherto prevented the employment<lb/>of them, and the
                    establishment of a magnetic station under<lb/>the tropic of Cancer. The same has
                    also occurred up to the<lb/>present time with regard to one of Gambey&#x2019;s
                    compasses which<lb/>M. Arago had caused to be erected, at his own expense,
                        to<lb/><pb n="47" facs="#f0006"/> obtain observations in the interior of
                    Mexico, where the soil<lb/>is elevated six thousand feet above the level of the
                    sea. Lastly,<lb/>during my last residence in Paris, I had the honour of
                    pro-<lb/>posing to Admiral Duperré, Minister for marine affairs,
                    the<lb/>establishment of a magnetic station in Iceland. The pro-<lb/>posal was
                    received with the utmost eagerness, and the instru-<lb/>ment, which is already
                    ordered, will be deposited during the<lb/>present summer at the port of
                    Reikiawig, when the expedi-<lb/>tion which has been sent to the north in search
                    of M. de Blosse-<lb/>ville and his companions in misfortune returns to Iceland
                    to<lb/>continue its scientific labours. There cannot be any doubt<lb/>that the
                    Danish Government, which protects with generous<lb/>ardour astronomy and the
                    advancement of nautical science,<lb/>will favour the establishment of a magnetic
                    station in one of<lb/>its provinces bordering on the polar circle. At Chili
                    also<lb/>M. Gay has made a great number of corresponding
                    horary<lb/>observations, according to the instructions of M. Arago.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>I have entered upon this long and minute historical detail,<lb/>to show how far I
                    have hitherto succeeded, in conjunction with<lb/>my friends, in extending the
                    number of simultaneous observa-<lb/>tions. After my return from Siberia, Mr.
                    Dove and I pub-<lb/>lished, in 1830, a graphic delineation of the curves of
                    horary<lb/>declination of Berlin, Freiberg, Petersburgh, and Nicolajeff<lb/>in
                    the Crimea, to show the parallelism of these lines, notwith-<lb/>standing the
                    distance of the stations and the influence of ex-<lb/>traordinary perturbations.
                    In the comparison of the observa-<lb/>tions of St. Petersburgh and Nicolajeff,
                    use has been made<lb/>of observations taken at the very small intervals of
                    twenty mi-<lb/>nutes. It must not, however, be imagined that this
                    parallelism<lb/>of inflections always exists in the horary curves. We
                    have<lb/>found that even in places very near to each other,&#x2014;for
                    instance,<lb/>at Berlin and in the mines of Freiberg,&#x2014;the magnetic
                    reac-<lb/>tions from the interior to the surface of the earth are not
                    al-<lb/>ways simultaneous; that one of the needles presents consider-<lb/>able
                    perturbations, while the other preserves that regularity,<lb/>which under each
                    meridian is the function of the true time of<lb/>the place. In the memoir
                    published in 1830, I proposed the fol-<lb/>lowing periods for simultaneous
                    observations at all the stations.</p>
                <lb/>
                <list>
                    <item><list rendition="#rightBraced"><item>March 20th and 21st.</item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>May 4th and 5th.</item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>June 21st and 22nd.</item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>Aug. 6th and 7th.</item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>Sept. 23rd and 24th.</item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>Nov. 5th and 6th.</item>
                    <lb/>
                        <item>Dec. 21st and 22nd.</item></list> From four o&#x2019;clock in the morning of<lb/>the
                        first day, to midnight of the se-<lb/>cond day. The observations to
                        be<lb/>continued at each <hi rendition="#i">magnetic station</hi><lb/>during
                        the day and night, at inter-<lb/>vals not exceeding one hour.</item>
                </list>
                <lb/>
                <p>As several observers situated upon the line of the stations<lb/><pb n="48"
                        facs="#f0007"/> have found these periods too near to each other, it has
                    been<lb/>thought advisable to insist in preference upon the time of
                    the<lb/>solstices and equinoxes.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>England, from the time of William Gilbert, Graham, and<lb/>Halley to that of the
                    more recent exertions of Messrs. Gilpin,<lb/>Beaufoy (at Bushy), Barlow, and
                    Christie, has produced a<lb/>rich collection of materials applicable to the
                    discovery of the<lb/>physical laws which regulate the variation of the magnetic
                    de-<lb/>clination, either in one place according to the different hours<lb/>and
                    seasons, or at various distances from the magnetic equator<lb/>and the lines
                    without declination. Mr. Gilpin made observations<lb/>during twelve hours every
                    day for more than seven months.<lb/>The numerous observations of Colonel Beaufoy
                    were regularly<lb/>published in Thomson&#x2019;s Annals. The memorable
                    expedi-<lb/>tions to the most inhospitable regions of the North have
                    fur-<lb/>nished Messrs. Sabine, Franklin, Hood, Parry, Henry
                    Foster,<lb/>Beechey, and James Clarke Ross with a rich harvest of
                    im-<lb/>portant observations. Physical geography is indebted for
                    a<lb/>considerable increase of knowledge respecting terrestrial mag-<lb/>netism
                    and meteorology to the attempts which have recently<lb/>been made to determine
                    the form of the north-west passage<lb/>or strait; and to the perilous
                    explorations of the frozen coasts<lb/>of Asia by Captains Wrangel, Lütke, and
                    Anjou. During the<lb/>progress of these noble efforts, an unexpected impulse
                    has<lb/>been given to the physical sciences by the light thrown upon<lb/>them by
                    a branch of natural philosophy the theoretical pro-<lb/>gress of which for two
                    centuries had been extremely slow.<lb/>Such has been the effect of the grand
                    discoveries of Oersted,<lb/>Arago, Ampère, Seebeck, and Faraday upon the nature
                    of<lb/>electro-magnetic forces. Excited by the talents and
                    ingenious<lb/>exertions of learned travellers cooperating for the
                    promotion<lb/>of one object, Messrs. Hansteen, Due, and Adolphus Erman,<lb/>by
                    the fortunate union of very precise astronomical and phy-<lb/>sical means, have
                    explored, throughout the immense extent<lb/>of Northern Asia, the isoclinal,
                    isogonal, and isodynamic<lb/>curves for very nearly the same epoch. When
                    speaking of<lb/>this great project, long since conceived and proposed by
                    Mr.<lb/>Hansteen, I ought, perhaps, to pass over in silence the
                    obser-<lb/>vations upon magnetic inclination which I made upon
                    the<lb/>rarely-visited frontier of Chinese Dzoungarie and on the<lb/>coasts of
                    the Caspian Sea, published in the second vo-<lb/>lume of my <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Fragmens Asiatiques.</hi> My learned countryman<lb/>Mr. Adolphus Erman, who
                    embarked at Kamtschatka and re-<lb/>turned to Europe by Cape Horn, had the rare
                    advantage of<lb/>continuing throughout a long voyage the measure of the
                    three<lb/>manifestations of terrestrial magnetism at the surface of the<lb/><pb
                        n="49" facs="#f0008"/> globe. He employed the same instruments and the same
                    me-<lb/>thods which he had made use of from Berlin to the mouth of<lb/>the Oby,
                    and thence to the Sea of Okhotsk.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>That which characterizes our epoch, at a time distinguished<lb/>by grand
                    discoveries in optics, electricity, and magnetism, is<lb/>the possibility of
                    connecting ph&#x00E6;nomena by the generalization<lb/>of empirical laws, and the
                    mutual aid afforded by sciences<lb/>which had long remained isolated. At the
                    present day simple<lb/>observations upon horary declination or magnetic
                    intensity,<lb/>made simultaneously in situations very distant from each
                    other,<lb/>reveal, so to speak, what passes at profound depths in
                    the<lb/>interior of our planet, and in the superior regions of the
                    at-<lb/>mosphere. The luminous emanations, the polar explosions<lb/>which
                    accompany the magnetic storm, appear to follow great<lb/>changes in the habitual
                    or mean tension of terrestrial mag-<lb/>netism.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>It would tend greatly to promote the advancement of the<lb/>mathematical and
                    physical sciences if, under the Presidency<lb/>and auspices of Your Royal
                    Highness, the Royal Society<lb/>of London, to which I make it my boast to have
                    belonged for<lb/>twenty years, would exert its powerful influence to extend
                        the<lb/><hi rendition="#i">line of simultaneous observations,</hi> and to
                    establish <hi rendition="#i">permanent<lb/>magnetic stations,</hi> either in the
                    region of the tropics, on each<lb/>side of the magnetic equator, the proximity
                    of which neces-<lb/>sarily diminishes the amplitude of the horary declinations,
                    or<lb/>in the high latitudes of the southern hemisphere and in Ca-<lb/>nada. I
                    venture to propose this latter point, because obser-<lb/>vations upon horary
                    declination made in the vast extent of the<lb/>United States are still very
                    rare. Those, however, of Salem,<lb/>in 1810, calculated by Mr. Bowditch, and
                    compared by Arago<lb/>with the observations of Cassini, Gilpin, and Beaufoy,
                    merit<lb/>great praise, and might serve as a guide to observers in Ca-<lb/>nada
                    in investigating whether the declination there does not<lb/>diminish between the
                    vernal equinox and the summer solstice,<lb/>contrary to what occurs in Western
                    Europe. In a memoir<lb/>that I published five years ago, I suggested as magnetic
                    sta-<lb/>tions extremely favourable to the progress of our knowledge,<lb/>New
                    Holland, Ceylon, the Mauritius, the Cape of Good<lb/>Hope (rendered illustrious
                    by the labours of Sir John Her-<lb/>schel), St. Helena, and some point on the
                    eastern coast of<lb/>America to the south of Quebec. In the last century, in
                    the<lb/>years 1794 and 1796, an English traveller, Mr. Macdonald,<lb/>made some
                    new and important observations upon the diurnal<lb/>motion of the needle at
                    Sumatra and St. Helena, which have<lb/>since been confirmed and extended upon a
                    large scale in the<lb/>scientific expeditions of Captains Freycinet and
                        Duperrey;<lb/><pb n="50" facs="#f0009"/> the former having the command of
                    the sloop Uranie from<lb/>1817 to 1820, and the latter, who has six times
                    crossed the<lb/>magnetic equator, commanding the sloop Coquille from 1822<lb/>to
                    1825. To promote the rapid advancement of the theory<lb/>of terrestrial
                    magnetism, or at least to establish with more<lb/>precision empirical laws, it
                    is necessary at the same time to<lb/>prolong and to vary the lines of <hi
                        rendition="#i">corresponding observations</hi>;<lb/>also to distinguish in
                    observations of horary variations, what<lb/>arises from the influence of the
                    seasons, of serene and cloudy<lb/>weather and of abundant rains, of the hours of
                    day and night,<lb/>and of the true time at each place, that is, from the
                    influence<lb/>of the sun, and of all isochronous influences at the
                    different<lb/>meridians. To these observations of horary declination must<lb/>be
                    united those of the annual movement of the <hi rendition="#i">absolute
                        declina-<lb/>tion</hi>, of the <hi rendition="#i">inclination of the
                        needle</hi>, and of the <hi rendition="#i">intensity of<lb/>the magnetic
                        forces</hi>, the increase of which from the magnetic<lb/>equator to the
                    poles is unequal in the Western American and<lb/>the Eastern Asiatic
                    hemispheres. All these <hi rendition="#i">data,</hi> indispensa-<lb/>ble bases
                    for the future theory, can only acquire certainty and<lb/>importance by the
                    means of establishments which shall remain<lb/>permanent for a great number of
                    years, of Physical Obser-<lb/>vatories in which the investigation of numerical
                    elements may<lb/>be repeated at settled intervals of time, and with similar
                    in-<lb/>struments. Travellers who cross a country in but one direc-<lb/>tion and
                    at one epoch merely prepare the way for an under-<lb/>taking which should
                    embrace the complete delineation of the<lb/>lines without declination at
                    intervals equally distant; the pro-<lb/>gressive removal of the points of
                    intersection of the terrestrial<lb/>and magnetic equators; the changes of form
                    in the isogonal<lb/>and isodynamic lines; and the influence upon the slow or
                    ac-<lb/>celerated movement of the curves, which indubitably arises<lb/>from the
                    configuration and articulation of the continents. It<lb/>must be considered
                    fortunate if the isolated labours of tra-<lb/>vellers, whose cause it is my
                    office to plead, have contributed<lb/>to give animation to a species of
                    investigation which is the<lb/>work of centuries, and which requiries the
                    concurrence of<lb/>numerous observers, distributed according to a plan
                    arranged<lb/>after mature consideration, under the direction of several
                    of<lb/>the great scientific centres of Europe. The directors should<lb/>not
                    always confine themselves to the narrow limits of the<lb/>same instructions, but
                    they should vary them freely in adapta-<lb/>tion to the progressive state of
                    physical science, and the im-<lb/>provement of instruments and methods of
                    observation.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>When soliciting Your Royal Highness to condescend to<lb/>communicate this letter
                    to the illustrious Society over which<lb/>you preside, it is not in any degree
                    my office to inquire, which<lb/><pb n="51" facs="#f0010"/> are the magnetic
                    stations that merit preference at the present<lb/>time, or that local
                    circumstances may admit of establishing.<lb/>To have solicited the concurrence
                    of the Royal Society of<lb/>London will be sufficient to give new life to a
                    useful enter-<lb/>prise in which I have been engaged for very many years.
                    I<lb/>venture simply to express the wish that, should my proposi-<lb/>tion be
                    received with indulgence, the Royal Society would<lb/>enter into direct
                    communication with the Royal Society of<lb/>Göttingen, the Royal Institute of
                    France, and the Imperial<lb/>Academy of Russia, in order to adopt measures the
                    best<lb/>adapted for the combination of what it may be proposed to<lb/>establish
                    with what already exists upon a very considerable<lb/>extent of surface. Perhaps
                    also measures might be previously<lb/>concerted for the publication of <hi
                        rendition="#i">partial observations</hi>, and also<lb/>(if the calculation
                    would not require too much time, and too<lb/>much retard the communications,) of
                    the <hi rendition="#i">mean results.</hi> One of<lb/>the happy effects of
                    civilization and the progress of reason is,<lb/>that when addressing learned
                    societies, their willing concur-<lb/>rence may be relied upon if the object for
                    which it is solicited<lb/>tends to promote the advancement of the sciences or
                    the intel-<lb/>lectual development of humanity.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Labours of astonishing precision have been performed,<lb/>within the last few
                    years, with instruments of extraordinary<lb/>power, in a magnetic pavilion of
                    the Observatory of Göttin-<lb/>gen, which are well worthy of the attention of
                    philosophers,<lb/>as they offer a more precise method of measuring the
                    horary<lb/>variations. The magnetized bar is of much larger dimensions<lb/>than
                    even the bar of Prony&#x2019;s magnetic telescope; and the ex-<lb/>tremity is
                    furnished with a mirror, in which are reflected the<lb/>divisions of a scale
                    which is more or less distant, according to<lb/>the angular value desired to be
                    given to these divisions. By<lb/>the employment of this improved method the
                    necessity for the<lb/>observer&#x2019;s approaching the magnetized bar is
                    obviated, and<lb/>by preventing the currents of air produced by the
                    proximity<lb/>of the human body, or during the night, of a lamp,
                    observa-<lb/>tions may be made in the smallest intervals of time. The<lb/>great
                    geometrician Mr. Gauss,&#x2014;to whom we owe this mode of<lb/>making
                    observations, as well as the means of reducing the in-<lb/>tensity of the
                    magnetic force in any part of the earth to an<lb/>absolute proportion, and the
                    ingenious invention of a <hi rendition="#i">magneto-<lb/>meter</hi> put into
                    motion by a <hi rendition="#i">multiplier of
                    induction</hi>,&#x2014;pub-<lb/>lished in the years 1834 and 1835 several series
                    of simulta-<lb/>neous observations made with similar apparatus, and at
                    inter-<lb/>vals of five or ten minutes, at Göttingen, Copenhagen,
                    Altona,<lb/>Brunswick, Leipzig, Berlin (where Mr. Encke has
                    already<lb/>established a very spacious magnetic house, near the New<lb/>Royal
                    Observatory), Milan, and Rome. Mr. Schumacher&#x2019;s<lb/><pb n="52"
                        facs="#f0011"/> German Ephemeris (<hi rendition="#i">Jahrbuch für</hi> 1836)
                    proves graphically,<lb/>and by the parallelism of the smallest inflections of
                    the horary<lb/>curves, the simultaneity of the perturbations at Milan
                    and<lb/>Copenhagen, two cities having a difference of latitude of 10°
                    13&#x2032;.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Mr. Gauss first made observations at the times which I pro-<lb/>posed in 1830,
                    but with the intention of referring the angular<lb/>dimensions of magnetic
                    declination to the smallest intervals of<lb/>time. (On the 7th of February 1834,
                    alterations of six minutes<lb/>of the arc corresponded to a single minute of
                    time.) Mr. Gauss<lb/>reduced the forty-four hours of simultaneous
                    observations<lb/>to twenty-four hours; and appointed six [seven?] periods
                    of<lb/>the year, viz. the last Saturday of each month consisting of<lb/>an
                    uneven number of days, for the stations which are provided<lb/>with his new
                    apparatus. The small magnetized bars which<lb/>he employs as magnetometers are
                    of four pounds weight, and<lb/>the large ones of twenty-five pounds. The curious
                        <hi rendition="#i">apparatus<lb/>of induction</hi> proper to render sensible
                    and measurable the<lb/>oscillatory movements predicted by a theory founded
                    upon<lb/>Mr. Faraday&#x2019;s admirable discovery, consists of two bars
                    fast-<lb/>ened together, each of twenty-five pounds weight. I thought<lb/>it
                    proper to mention the valuable labours of Mr. Gauss, in<lb/>order that those
                    members of the Royal Society of London<lb/>who have rendered most service to the
                    study of terrestrial<lb/>magnetism, and who know the localities of the colonial
                    esta-<lb/>blishments, may take into consideration whether bars of
                    great<lb/>weight, provided with a mirror, and suspended in a
                    pavilion<lb/>carefully closed, should be employed in the new stations to
                    be<lb/>established; or whether Gambey&#x2019;s compass, hitherto
                    uniformly<lb/>used in our present stations in Europe and Asia, should
                    still<lb/>be employed. In discussing this question the advantages
                    will<lb/>undoubtedly be estimated which, in the apparatus of Mr.<lb/>Gauss,
                    arise from the smaller mobility of the bars by currents of<lb/>air, as well as
                    from the facility and rapidity with which the<lb/>angular divisions may be read
                    in very short intervals of time.<lb/>My desire is only to see the line of
                    magnetic stations extended,<lb/>whatever be the means by which the precision of
                    the corre-<lb/>sponding observations may be attained. I ought also to
                    men-<lb/>tion that two accomplished travellers, Messrs. Sartorius
                    and<lb/>Listing, provided with very portable instruments of small
                    di-<lb/>mensions, have very successfully employed the method of the<lb/>great
                    geometrician of Göttingen in their excursions to Na-<lb/>ples and in
                        Sicily.<note place="foot" n="*">An abstract of a memoir by Prof. Gauss in
                        which his apparatus and me-<lb/>thod of observation are fully described will
                        be found in Lond. &amp; Edinb. Phil.<lb/>Mag., vol. ii. p. 291, <hi
                            rendition="#i">et seq.</hi>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k"
                    >Edit.</hi></note></p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Your Royal Highness will, I hope, excuse the length of this<lb/><pb n="53"
                        facs="#f0012"/> communication; but I thought that it would be useful to
                    unite<lb/>under one point of view what has been done or proposed
                    in<lb/>different countries towards the attainment of extensive
                    simul-<lb/>taneous observations upon the laws of terrestrial magnetism.</p>
                <lb/>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Accept, Sir, the acknowledgement of the profound respect<lb/>with
                        which I have the honour of being,<lb/><hi rendition="#et">Your Royal
                            Highness&#x2019;s, &amp;c. &amp;c.,</hi><lb/></salute>
                    <lb/>
                    <dateline>Berlin, April, 1836.</dateline>
                    <signed><hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt.</hi></hi></signed></closer>
                <lb/>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>

    </text>
</TEI>
