<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-20" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. Validation.<note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="691" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>AN ACCOUNT OF TWO ATTEMPTS TO ASCEND<lb break="yes"/>CHIMBORAZO.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">by alexander von humboldt.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <list>
                    <item>The following interesting narrative is abridged from an excerpt<lb break="yes"/>from the unpublished Journal of this distinguished traveller, com-<lb break="no"/>munieated to the Edinburgh Philosophical Journal.</item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> highest mountain-summits of both continents&#x2014;in the<lb break="yes"/>old continent, Dliawalagiri (White Mountain) and the Jawa-<lb break="no"/>hir; in the new, the Sorata and the Illimani&#x2014;remain un-<lb break="no"/>searched by man. The highest point of the earth&#x2019;s surface<lb break="yes"/>a@ained lies in South America, on the south east side of<lb break="yes"/>Chimborazo. There travellers have reached the height of<lb break="yes"/>nearly 19,700 Engli@h feet&#x2014;viz: in Juno 1802, 3,016 toises,<note place="foot" n="*">A tol@ is 1.91901 metres, or 6.39450 English feet</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>in December 1831, 3,080 toises above the level of the sea.<lb break="yes"/>Barometrical mensurements have thus been made in the chain<lb break="yes"/>of the Andes 4.000 feet above the level of the summit of<lb break="yes"/>Mont Blanc. The height of Mont Blanc is, in relation to<lb break="yes"/>that of the Cordilleras, so inconsiderable, that in the latter<lb break="yes"/>there are much-frequented passes that are higher; indeed,<lb break="yes"/>the upper part of the grest city of Potosi has an elevation<lb break="yes"/>only 323 toises inferior to that of the summit of Mont Blanc.<lb break="yes"/>I have thought it needful to premise these numerical state-<lb break="no"/>ment@, in order to present to the imagin@tion definite points<lb break="yes"/>of compatison for the hypsometric&#x2014;@ it were plastic, con-<lb break="no"/>templation of the surface of the earth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On the 22d of June 1790, I was in the crater of the Peak<lb break="yes"/>of Teneriffe. Three years afterward, almost on the same<lb break="yes"/>day, (the 23d June 1802,) I reached a point 6,700 feet<lb break="yes"/>higher, near the summit of Chimborazo. After a long delay<lb break="yes"/>in the table-land of Quito, one of the most wonderful and pic-<lb break="no"/>ture@que regions of the earth, we undertook the journey<lb break="yes"/>toward the forc@ts of the Peruvi@ bark trees of Lox@, the<lb break="yes"/>upper course of the river Amazon, westward of the celebra-<lb break="no"/>ted strait l&#x2019;ongo de Manseriche, and through the sandy desert<lb break="yes"/>slong the l&#x2019;eruvian coast of the South Sea toward Lima,<lb break="yes"/>where wo were to observe the transit of Mercury on the 9th<lb break="yes"/>November 1802. On a plain covered with pumice-stone&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>where, after the fearful earthqu@ke of 4th February 1797, the<lb break="yes"/>building of the new city Riobamba was begun&#x2014;we enjoyed<lb break="yes"/>for several days a splendid view of the bell or dome-shaped<lb break="yes"/>sammit of Chimborazo. We had the clearest weather, fa-<lb break="no"/>voring trigonometrical observation. By means of @ large<lb break="yes"/>telescope, we had thoroughly examined the snow-mantle of<lb break="yes"/>the mountain, @till 1,570 toises distant, and discovered several<lb break="yes"/>ridges, which, projecting like sterile black streak@, converged<lb break="yes"/>toward the summit, and gave hope that upon them a firm<lb break="yes"/>footing might be obtained in the region of eternal snow.<lb break="yes"/>Riobamba Nuevo lies within sight of the enormous and now<lb break="yes"/>indented mountain Capuc-urcu, called by the Spaniards El<lb break="yes"/>Altar, which, says a tradition of the natives, was once higher<lb break="yes"/>than Chimborazo, and after having been many years in a<lb break="yes"/>state of eruption, suddenly fell in. Riobamba Nuevo mu@<lb break="yes"/>not be confounded with the old Riobamba of the great map<lb break="yes"/>of La Cond@mine and Don l&#x2019;edro Maldonado. The latter<lb break="yes"/>city was entirely destroyed by the great catastrophe of the<lb break="yes"/>4th February 1797, which in a few minutes destroyed 45,000<lb break="yes"/>human being@. We were in the plain of Tapi@, from which,<lb break="yes"/>on the 22d June, we began our expedition toward Chimbe-<lb break="no"/>razo, being already nearly 10,000 English feet above the<lb break="yes"/>level of the South Sea. We gently ascended as far as the<lb break="yes"/>foot of the mountain, where, in the Indian village Calpi, we<lb break="yes"/>were to pass the night. This plain is sparingly covered with<lb break="yes"/>Cactus stems and Schinus moll@, which resembles a weeping<lb break="yes"/>willow. Herds of variegated @, in thousands, seek here<lb break="yes"/>a scanty subsistence. At so great a height, the nightly ter-<lb break="no"/>restrial radiation of heat, when the sky is cloudless, proves<lb break="yes"/>injurious to agriculture, thro@gh cold and frost.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Very near to Calpi, north-westward of Lican, there is in<lb break="yes"/>the barren table-land a little isolated hill&#x2014;the <hi rendition="#i">black mountain,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Yana-Urcu, the name of which has not been given by the<lb break="yes"/>French academicians, but which, in a geognostical point of<lb break="yes"/>view, deserves much attention. The hill lies S. S. E. of Chim-<lb break="no"/>borazo, at a distance of less than three miles, and separated<lb break="yes"/>from the same by the high plain of Lusi@ only. If in it we<lb break="yes"/>do not recognize a lateral eruption of Chimborazo, the origin<lb break="yes"/>of the cone must certainly be ascribed to the subterra@eous<lb break="yes"/>forces which, under that mountain, have for thousands of<lb break="yes"/>years vainly sought au opening. It is of later origin than<lb break="yes"/>the elevation of the great dome-shaped mountain. The<lb break="yes"/>Yana-Urcu forms, with the northern hill Naguangachi, a con-<lb break="no"/>nected eminence in the form of a horse-shoe; the bow, more<lb break="yes"/>than a semi-circle, is open toward the east. There probably<lb break="yes"/>lies in the centre of the horse-shoe the point out of which the<lb break="yes"/>black slags have been thrown, that now lie spread far around.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We found there a funnel-shaped depression of about 120<lb break="yes"/>feet in depth, in the interior of which there is a small hill,<lb break="yes"/>whose height does not equal that of the sur@ounding margin.<lb break="yes"/>Yana-Urcu probably signifies the southern culminating point<lb break="yes"/>of the old crater margin, which, at the most, is elevated 400<lb break="yes"/>feet above the level of Calpi. Naguangachi signifies the<lb break="yes"/>northern lower end. According to the tradition of the na-<lb break="no"/>tives, and according to old MSS. which the Cacike or Apu<lb break="yes"/>of Lican possessed, the volcanic eruption of the Yana-Urcu<lb break="yes"/>occurred immediately after the death of the Inca Tupa-Yu-<lb break="no"/>panqui; thus probably in the middle of the fifteenth century.<lb break="yes"/>Tradition anys that a fire-ball, or indeed a star, fell from<lb break="yes"/>heaven and set on fire the mountain. Such fables, connect-<lb break="no"/>ing the fall of aerolites with eruptions, are also spread among<lb break="yes"/>the tribes of Mexico. On the eastern side of the Yana-Urcu,<lb break="yes"/>or rather at tue foot of the hill toward Lican, the natives con<lb break="yes"/>ducted us to a projecting rock, an opening in which resem-<lb break="no"/>bled the mouth of a forsaken gallery. Here, as well as at<lb break="yes"/>the distance of ten feet, there is heard a violent subterranean<lb break="yes"/>noise, which is accompanied by a current of air, or subterra-<lb break="no"/>nean wind. The current of air is much too weak to admit<lb break="yes"/>of the noise being attributed to it. The noise certainly arises<lb break="yes"/>from a subterranean brook, which is precipitated downward<lb break="yes"/>into a deep hollow, and through its fall occasions a motion<lb break="yes"/>in the air. A monk, the priest at Calpi, had, with the same<lb break="yes"/>idea, some time before, continued on the gallery at @n open<lb break="yes"/>fissure to procure water for his village. The hardness of<lb break="yes"/>the black augite rock probably interrupted the work. Chim-<lb break="no"/>borazo, notwithstanding its enormous mass of snow, send@<lb break="yes"/>down into the table-land such insignificant brooks of water,<lb break="yes"/>that it may be presumed the greater part of its water flows<lb break="yes"/>through clefts to the interior. In the village of Calpi itself,<lb break="yes"/>also, there was formerly heard a great noise in a house that<lb break="yes"/>had no cellar. Before the celebrated carthquake of the 4th<lb break="yes"/>February 1797, there sprang forth a brook in the south-west<lb break="yes"/>of the village at a deeper point. Many Indians considered<lb break="yes"/>this brook as a part of the water that flows under the Yana-<lb break="no"/>Urcu. But since the great earthquake, this brook has again<lb break="yes"/>di@ppcared.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After we had passed the night at Calpi, which, according<lb break="yes"/>to a barometrical measurement, lies 10,500 English feet above<lb break="yes"/>the see, we began, on the morning of the 23d, our proper ex-<lb break="no"/>pedition up Chimborazo. We attempted to ascend the moun-<lb break="no"/>tain on the S.S.E. side, and the Indians who were to attend<lb break="yes"/>us as guides, but of whom but a few had ever reached the<lb break="yes"/>limit of perpetual snow, gave this course the preference. We<lb break="yes"/>found Chimborazo surrounded with great plains, which rise,<lb break="yes"/>step-like, one above the other. Proceeding first through the<lb break="yes"/>Llanos de Lusia, then, after rather a gradual ascent of scarcely<lb break="yes"/>5,600 feet in length, we re@ched the table-land (Llano) of<lb break="yes"/>S@gun. The first step (@tufe) is at a height of 11,000 feet,<lb break="yes"/>the second 12,500. These grass-grown plains thus equal in<lb break="yes"/>elevation, respectively, the highest summit of the Pyrenees<lb break="yes"/>(Peak Nethou) and the summit of the Peak of Teneriffe.<lb break="yes"/>The perfect horizontality of these table-lands allows us to in-<lb break="no"/>fer the long continuance of stagnant water. The traveller<lb break="yes"/>imagines he sees before him the bottom of a lake. On the<lb break="yes"/>acclivity of the Swias Alp@. there is sometimes observed this<lb break="yes"/>phenomenon of small step-like plains, lying one above the<lb break="yes"/>othe@, which, like the emptied basins of Alpine lakes, are<lb break="yes"/>un@ted by narrow open passes. The wid@ly extended grass<lb break="yes"/>lands are on Chimborazo, as every where around the high<lb break="yes"/>summits of the Andes, so monotonous that the family of the<lb break="yes"/>grasses are seldom interrupted by dicotyledonous plants.<lb break="yes"/>There prevails almost the heathy scenery which I have seen<lb break="yes"/>in the barren part of northern Asia. The Flora of Chimbora-<lb break="no"/>zo, in general, appeared to us less rich than that of the other<lb break="yes"/>snow mountains which surround the city of Quito. But a<lb break="yes"/>few Calceolati&#x00E6;, Composit&#x00E6;, and Gentian&#x00E6;&#x2014;among which<lb break="yes"/>the beautiful Gentian&#x00E6; cernua, shining forth with purple<lb break="yes"/>flowers&#x2014;rear themselves on the high plain of Si@gun, be-<lb break="no"/>tween the associated grasses. These belong, for the most<lb break="yes"/>part, to the genera of Northern Europe. The temperature<lb break="yes"/>of the air generally provailing in these regions of Alpine<lb break="yes"/>grasses, elevated respectively 10,000 and 13,000 feet, fluctu-<lb break="no"/>ates by day between 39° 2&#x2032; and 60° 8&#x2032; Fahrenheit, by night<lb break="yes"/>between 32° and 50° Fahrenheit.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>My plan was to perform a trigonometrical operation in the<lb break="yes" />beautiful and perfectly level grass-land of Si@gun. I had<lb break="yes"/>made arrangements for measuring a base line here. The an-<lb break="no"/>gles of altitude would have proved very considerable in s@ch<lb break="yes"/>proximity to the summit of Chimborazo. There rema@ed<lb break="yes"/>yet a perpendicular height of less than 9,000 feet (the height<lb break="yes"/>of the Canigou in the Pyrenees) to determine. Yet with the<lb break="yes"/>enormous masses of single mountains in the chain of the An-<lb break="no"/>des, every determination of the height above the sea is com-<lb break="no"/>pounded of a barometricul and trigonometrical observation.<lb break="yes"/>I had taken with me the sextant and other instruments of<lb break="yes"/>measurement in vain. The summit of Chimborazo remained<lb break="yes"/>densely veiled in mist. From the high plain of Si@gun the<lb break="yes"/>ascent is tolerably steep as far as the little Alpine lake of<lb break="yes"/>Yana-Coche. Thus far I had remained on the mule, having<lb break="yes"/>from time to time alighted with my travelling companion, M.<lb break="yes"/>Bonpland, merely to collect plants. Yana-Coche does not<lb break="yes"/>deserve the name of a lake. It is a circular basin of scarcely<lb break="yes"/>130 feet in diameter. The sky became more and more ob-<lb break="no"/>scured; but between and over the mist-strata there still lay<lb break="yes"/>scattered single groups of clouds. The summit of Chimbo-<lb break="no"/>razo was visible for a few moments at a time. Much snow<lb break="yes"/>having fallen during the preceding night, I left the mule<lb break="yes"/>where we found the lower border of this newly-fallen snow,<lb break="yes"/>a border which must not be confounded with the limit of per-<lb break="no"/>petual snow. The barometer showed that we had only now<lb break="yes"/>attained the height of 15,000 feet. On other mountains,<lb break="yes"/>likewise near to the equator, I have seen snow fall at the<lb break="yes"/>height of 12,000 feet, but not lower. My companion rode as<lb break="yes"/>far as the line of perpetual snow, i. e. to the height of Mont<lb break="yes"/>Blanc; which mountain, as is known, would not in this lati-<lb break="no"/>tude (1° 27&#x2032; south) be covered with snow. The horses and<lb break="yes"/>mules remained there to await our return.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A hundred and fifty toises above the little basin of Yana-<lb break="no"/>Coche, we saw at length naked rock. Hitherto the grass-<lb break="no"/>land had withdrawn the ground from any geognostical exam-<lb break="no"/>ination. Great walls of rock, extending from the N. E.<lb break="yes"/>toward the S. W. in part clef@into misshapen columns, reared<lb break="yes"/>themselves out of the eternal snow&#x2014;a brownish-black augite<lb break="yes"/>rock, shining like pitch-stone porphyry. The columus were<lb break="yes"/>very thin, perhaps from fifty to sixty feet in height, almost<lb break="yes"/>like the trachyte columns of Tabla-Uinca on the volcano Pi-<lb break="no"/>chincha. One group stood alone, and reminded one of masts<lb break="yes"/>and stems of trees. The steep walls led us through the snow<lb break="yes"/>region to a narrow ridge of rock extending toward the sum-<lb break="no"/>mit, by which alone it was possibla for us to advance any<lb break="yes"/>further, for the snow was then so soft that one scarcely dared<lb break="yes"/>to tread upon it@ surface. The ridge consisted of very weath-<lb break="no"/>ered crumbling rock. It was often vesicular like a basaltic<lb break="yes"/>amygdaloid.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The path became more and more narrow and steep. The<lb break="yes"/>natives forsook us all but one at the height of 16,600 feet.<lb break="yes"/>All entreaties and threats were unavailing. The Indians<lb break="yes"/>maintained that they suffered more than we did from breath-<lb break="no"/>lessness. We remained alone, Bonpland, our amiable friend<lb break="yes"/>the younger son of the Marquis of Selvalegro, Carlos Montu-<lb break="no"/>far, who in the subsequent struggle for freedom was shot (at<lb break="yes"/>the command of General Morillo,) a Mestize from the neigh-<lb break="no"/>boring village of Sun Juan, and myself. We attained, with<lb break="yes"/>great exe@tion and endurance, a greater height than we had<lb break="yes"/>dared hope to reach, as we were almost entirely wrapped in<lb break="yes"/>mist. The ridge, (very significantly called, in Spanish, Cu-<lb break="no"/>chilla, as it were the knife-back,) was in many places only<lb break="yes"/>eight or ten inches broad: On the left the precipice was con-<lb break="no"/>cealed by snow, the surface of the latter seemed glazed with<lb break="yes"/>frost. The thin, icy mirror-like surface had an inclination of<lb break="yes"/>about 30°. On the right our view sank shuddering 800 or<lb break="yes"/>1,000 feet into an abyss out of which projected, perpendicu-<lb break="no"/>larly, snowless masses of rock. We held the body continu-<lb break="no"/>ally inclined towards this side, for the precipice upon the left<lb break="yes"/>seemed still more threatening, because there no chance pre-<lb break="no"/>sented itself of grasping the toothed rock, and because, fur-<lb break="no"/>ther, the thin ic@-crust offered no security against sinking in<lb break="yes"/>the loose snow. Only extremely light porous bits of dolerite<lb break="yes"/>could we roll down this crust of ice; and the inclined plane<lb break="yes"/>of snow was so extended that we lost sight of the stones<lb break="yes"/>thus rolled down before they came to rest. The absence of<lb break="yes"/>snow, as well upon the ridge along which we ascended, as<lb break="yes"/>upon the rocks on our right hand towards the east, cannot be<lb break="yes"/>ascribed so much to the steepness of the masses, and to the<lb break="yes"/>gales of wind, as to open clefts, which breathe out warm air<lb break="yes"/>from deeper situated beds. We soon found our further as-<lb break="no"/>cent more difficul@, from the increase of the crumbling nature<lb break="yes"/>of the rock. At single and very @teep <hi rendition="#i">eckelons</hi> it @ ne-<lb break="no"/>cessary to apply at the same time the hands and feet, as is so<lb break="yes"/>u@ual in all alpine journeys. As the rock was very keenly an-<lb break="no"/>gular, we were painfully hurt, especially in the hands. @<lb break="yes"/>pold Von Buch and I suffered very much in this man@<lb break="yes"/>the crater of the Peak of Teneriffe, which aboun@ in obsi-<lb break="no"/>dian. The little adhesion of the rocks of the @ now ren-<lb break="no"/>dered greater caution necessary, as m@ny @ which we<lb break="yes"/>supposed firm, lay loose and covered with @and. We pro-<lb break="no"/>ceeded one after the other, and so muth the more slowly, us<lb break="yes"/>it was needful to try the places which @med uncertain.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Happily the attempt to reach the summit of Chimborazo @<lb break="yes"/>the last of our mountain journeya in South America; hence<lb break="yes"/>previous experience guided us, and gave us more confidence<lb break="yes"/>in our powers. It is a peculiar character of all excur@<lb break="yes"/>in the Andes, that above the snow line white people find them@<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="692" facs="#f0002"/> selves, in the most perilous situations, always without guides,<lb break="yes"/>indeed without any knowledge of localities.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We could see the summit no longer, even for a moment<lb break="yes"/>only at a time, and were hence doubly cur@ous to know, how<lb break="yes"/>much higher it remained for us to ascend. We examined<lb break="yes"/>@ barometer at a point where the brendth of the ridge per-<lb break="no"/>@ted of two persons standing conveniently together. We<lb break="yes"/>were now at an elevation of 18,500 feet; thus scarcely two<lb break="yes"/>hundred feet higher than we had been two months before<lb break="yes"/>when climbing a similar ridge of the Antisa@. It is with<lb break="yes"/>the determining of heights in climbing mountains, as with<lb break="yes"/>the determining of temperature in the heat of summer. One<lb break="yes"/>finds with vexation the thermometer not so high, the barome-<lb break="no"/>ter not so low, as one expected. As the air, notwithstanding<lb break="yes"/>the height, was quite saturated with moisture, we now found<lb break="yes"/>the loose rock and the sand that filled its interstices extreme-<lb break="no"/>ly wet. The air was still 37° 04&#x2032; Fab. Shortly before, we<lb break="yes"/>had, in a dry place, been able to bury the thermometer @<lb break="yes"/>inches deep in the sand. It indicated 42° 44&#x2032; Fahr. The<lb break="yes"/>result of this observation is very remarkable, for lower down,<lb break="yes"/>at the limit of perpetual snow, the mean heat of the atmos-<lb break="no"/>phere is according to many observations, collected by Bous-<lb break="no"/>singault and myself, only 34° 88&#x2032; Fahr. The temperature of<lb break="yes"/>earth (sand) at 42° 44&#x2032; Fahr. must therefore be ascribed to<lb break="yes"/>the subterranean heat of the dolerito mountain; I do not<lb break="yes"/>say to the whole mass but to the current of air ascending<lb break="yes"/>from the interior.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After an hour of cautious climbing the ridge of rock be-<lb break="no"/>came less steep; but ulas! the mist remained as thick as ev-<lb break="no"/>er. We now began gradually to suffer from great nausea.<lb break="yes"/>The tendency to vomiting was combined with some giddi-<lb break="no"/>ness; and much more troublesome than the difficulty of<lb break="yes"/>breathing. A colored man (a Mestize of San Juan) not from<lb break="yes"/>selfish motives, but merely out of good nature, had been un-<lb break="no"/>willing to forsake us. He was a poor vigorous peasant and<lb break="yes"/>suffered more than we did. We had h&#x00E6;morrhage from the<lb break="yes"/>gums and lips. The conjunctiva of the eyes likewise, was,<lb break="yes"/>in all, gorged in blood. These symptoms of extravasation in<lb break="yes"/>the eyes, and of oozing from the lips and gums, did not in<lb break="yes"/>the least disquiet us, as we had repeatedly experienced them<lb break="yes"/>before. In Europe, M. Zumstein began to experience h&#x00E6;-<lb break="no"/>morrhage at a much lower elevation on Monte Rosa. The<lb break="yes"/>Spanish warriors during the conquest of the equinoctial re-<lb break="no"/>gion of America (during the Conquista) did not ascend<lb break="yes"/>above the snow line, thus but little above the elevation of<lb break="yes"/>Mont Blanc, and yet Acosta, in his &#x2018;Historia Natural de las<lb break="yes"/>Indias&#x2019;&#x2014;a kind of physical geography, which may be called a<lb break="yes"/>masterpiece of the sixteenth century&#x2014;speaks circumstantial-<lb break="no"/>ly of &#x201C;nausea and spasm of the stomach,&#x201D; as painful symp-<lb break="no"/>toms of the <hi rendition="#i">mountain sickness,</hi> which in these respects is<lb break="yes"/>analagous to <hi rendition="#i">sea-sickness.</hi> On the volcano of Pichincha I<lb break="yes"/>once felt, without experiencing h&#x00E6;morrhage. so violent an af-<lb break="no"/>fection of the stomach, accompanied by giddiness, that I was<lb break="yes"/>f@ad senseless on the ground, just as I left my companions<lb break="yes"/>on a wall of rock above the defile of Verde-Cucha, in order<lb break="yes"/>to perform some electrical experiments on a perfectly open<lb break="yes"/>space. The height was inconsiderable, below 4,800 feet.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>But on the Antisana, at the considerable elevation of 8,500<lb break="yes"/>feet, our young travelling companton. D@ Carlos Montufar,<lb break="yes"/>bled freely from the lips. All of these phenemena vary ac-<lb break="no"/>cording to age, constitution, the tenderness of the skin, and<lb break="yes"/>the preceding exertions of the muscular powers; yet for sin-<lb break="no"/>gle individuals they are a kind of measure of the atmosphe-<lb break="no"/>ric tenuity, and of the absolute elevation reached. Accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to my observations in the Cordilleras, these symptoms<lb break="yes"/>manifest themselves in white people, with a mercurial colum@<lb break="yes"/>berween 14 inches and 15 inches 10 lin@.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The layers of mist that prevented our seeing distant objects,<lb break="yes" />appeared suddenly, notwithstanding the total stillness of the<lb break="yes" />air, perhaps th@ough electrical processes, to be broken up.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>We recognized once more, and indeed immediately before us,<lb break="yes"/>the dome-shaped summit of Chimborazo. It was an earned<lb break="yes"/>monotonous gaze. The hope to reach this summit animate@<lb break="yes"/>@r powers anew. The ridge of rock, only here and there<lb break="yes"/>covered with thin flakes of snow, became somewhat broader.<lb break="yes"/>We hastened onwards, with certain steps, when all at once<lb break="yes"/>a ravjne of 400 feet in depth, and 50 broad, set an insur-<lb break="no"/>mountable barrier to our undertaking. We saw distinctly be-<lb break="no"/>yond the abyss, our ridge of rock continned forward in the<lb break="yes"/>same direction; yet I doubt this leading to the summit itself.<lb break="yes"/>The chasm was not to be gon@ round. On the Anti@, M.<lb break="yes"/>Bonpland indeed had found it possible, after a very cold night<lb break="yes"/>to proceed for a considerable length through the snow. We<lb break="yes"/>durst not venture the attempt, berause of the looseness of the<lb break="yes"/>mass, and the form of the precipice rendered climbing down<lb break="yes"/>impossible. It was one o&#x2019;clock in the afternoon: We set up<lb break="yes"/>with much care the barometer. It indicated 13 inches 11<lb break="yes"/>lines. The temperature of the air was now 29° 12&#x2032; Fahr.;<lb break="yes"/>but after several years&#x2019; stay in the hottest regions of the tro-<lb break="no"/>pies, this small degree of cold benumbed us. Besides, ou@<lb break="yes"/>boots were thoroughly soaked with snow-water, for the sand<lb break="yes"/>that covered here and there the ridge, was mixed with old<lb break="yes"/>snow, According to La Place&#x2019;s barumetrical formula, we<lb break="yes"/>bad reached a height of 19,200 English feet. If La Conda-<lb break="no"/>mine&#x2019;s estimate of the height of Chimborazo, as noted on the<lb break="yes"/>stone table of the Jesuit&#x2019;s College at Quito, be correct, there<lb break="yes"/>@iled us yet to the summit of the mountain 1,300 feet, or<lb break="yes"/>@ the height of St. Peter&#x2019;s Church at Rome.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We remained a short time in this mournful solitude, being<lb break="yes"/>soon again entirely veiled in mist. The humid air was not<lb break="yes"/>thereby set in motion. No fixed direction was to be observed<lb break="yes"/>in single groups of the denser particles of vapor; I therefore<lb break="yes"/>cannot say whether at this elevation the west wind blows,<lb break="yes"/>opposing the tropical mo@soon. We saw no longer the @<lb break="yes"/>mit of Chimbor@, none of the neighboring snow-mountains,<lb break="yes"/>still less the table lands of Quito. We were as though isolated<lb break="yes"/>in a ball of air. Some stone lichens only had followed us<lb break="yes"/>above the line of perpetual snow. The last cryptogami@<lb break="yes"/>plants which I collected were Lecidea atrovirens (Lichen<lb break="yes"/>geographicus, <hi rendition="#i" >@&#x2019;eb.</hi>), and a Gyrophora of <hi rendition="#i">Acharius,</hi> a new<lb break="yes"/>species (Gyrophora r@gosa), at about the height of 18,000<lb break="yes"/>@eet. The last moss, Grimmia longirostris, grew 2500 feet<lb break="yes"/>lower down. A butterfly (sphinx) was caught by M. Bonp-<lb break="no"/>land at the height of 16,000 feet; we saw a fly 1700 feet<lb break="yes"/>higher. I must remark, that we met with no condor on Chim-<lb break="no"/>bo@axo, that powerful vulture, which is so frequent on Anti-<lb break="no"/>sana and Pich@cha, and which shows great confidence from<lb break="yes"/>its ignorance of man. The condor loves pure air, in order<lb break="yes"/>the easier from on high to recognize its prey or its food, for<lb break="yes"/>it gives dead animals the preference.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As the weather became more and more cloudy, we hasten-<lb break="no"/>ed down upon the same ledge of rock, that had favored our<lb break="yes"/>ascent. Caution, however, on account of the uncertainty of<lb break="yes"/>the steps, was more necessary than @ climbing up. We<lb break="yes"/>foresaw that in Europe &#x2018;a little bit of Chimborazo&#x2019; would be<lb break="yes"/>asked for. At that time no mountain rock in any part of South<lb break="yes"/>America had been named: the rocks of all the high summits<lb break="yes"/>of the Andes were called granite. As we were at the height<lb break="yes"/>of about 18,400 feet, it began to hail violently. The hailstones<lb break="yes"/>were opaque, and milk-white, with concentric layers; some<lb break="yes"/>appeared considerably flattened by rotation; twenty minutes<lb break="yes"/>before we reached the lower limit of perpetual snow, the hail<lb break="yes"/>was r@placed by snow. The flakes were so dense, that the<lb break="yes"/>snow soon cavered the ridge of rock many inches deep; we<lb break="yes"/>should have been brought into great danger, had the snow<lb break="yes"/>surprised as at the height of 17,000 feet. At a few minutes<lb break="yes"/>after two o&#x2019;clock, we reached the point where our mules were<lb break="yes"/>standing. The natives that remained behind, had been very<lb break="yes"/>apprehensive for our safety.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>That part of our expedition which lay above the snow-line,<lb break="yes"/>had lasted only three and a half hours, during which, not-<lb break="no" />withstanding the tenuity of the air, we had not found it need-<lb break="no" />ful to take rest by sitting down. On account of the snow newly<lb break="yes" />fallen, we found in our descent from Chimborazo, the lower<lb break="yes" />limit of perpetual snow, in accidental and temporary @onjunc-<lb break="no" />tion with the deeper spor@dial spots of snow on the naked<lb break="yes" />lichen covered rocks, and on the grass plain (Pajonal); yet it<lb break="yes" />was always easy to @ecognizo the proper limit of perpetual<lb break="yes" />snow, (then at the height of 15,700 feet) by the thickness of<lb break="yes" />the bed and by its peeatiar @te.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We took a somewhat more northern way buck to the vil-<lb break="no"/>lage of Calpi than the Llanos de Si@gun, through the Paramo<lb break="yes"/>de Pungupala, a district rich in plant@. By five o&#x2019;clock in the<lb break="yes"/>evening we were @gain with the friendly clergyman of Calpi.<lb break="yes"/>As usual, the misty day of the expedition was succeeded by<lb break="yes"/>the clearest weather. On the 25th of June, at Riobamba<lb break="yes"/>Nuevo, Chimborazo presented itself in @ its splendor,&#x2014;I<lb break="yes"/>may say, in the calm greatness and supremacy which is the<lb break="yes"/>natural character of the tropical landscape. A second attempt<lb break="yes"/>upon a ridge interrupted by a cha@, would certainly have<lb break="yes"/>turned out as fruitless as the first, and I was already engaged<lb break="yes"/>with the @rigonometrical measurement of the volcano of Tun-<lb break="no"/>gurahu.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Boussingault, on the 16th of December 1831, with his En-<lb break="no"/>glish friend Colonel Hall,&#x2014;who was soon afterwards @-<lb break="no"/>sinated in Quito,&#x2014;made a new attempt to reach the summit<lb break="yes"/>of Chimborazo, first from Moeha and Chillapulla, then from<lb break="yes"/>Arenal, thus by a different way from that @rodden by Bonp-<lb break="no"/>land, Don Carlos Montufar, and myself. He was obliged to<lb break="yes"/>give up the ascent, when his barometer indicated thirteen<lb break="yes"/>@ches eight and a half lines, with an atmospheric tempera-<lb break="no"/>turc of 8° .8 (46° .04 F.) He thus saw the uncorrected<lb break="yes"/>@ of mercury almost three lines lower, and reached a<lb break="yes"/>point 400 feet higher than I did, viz. 3080 toises. Let us have<lb break="yes"/>the words of this well-known traveller of the Andes, who was<lb break="yes"/>the first to carry a chemical apparatus to, and into, the cra-<lb break="no"/>ters of volcanoes. &#x2018;The way, says Boussingault, which we<lb break="yes"/>@pened for ourselves through the snow, in the latter part of<lb break="yes"/>our expedition, permitted of our advancing but very slowly.<lb break="yes"/>On the right we were enabled to grasp hold of a rock, on the<lb break="yes"/>left, the abyss was fearful. We were already sensible of the<lb break="yes"/>effect of the attenuated air, and were obliged, every two or<lb break="yes"/>three steps to sit down. As soon, however, as we were @cated,<lb break="yes"/>we again stood up, for our sufferings lasted only while we<lb break="yes"/>moved. The snow we were obliged to tread was soft, and<lb break="yes"/>lay three or four inches deep, on a very smooth and hard co-<lb break="no"/>vering of ice. We were obliged to hew our steps. A negro<lb break="yes"/>wert before, to perform this work, by which his powers were<lb break="yes"/>soon exhausted. As I was endeavoring to pass him, for the<lb break="yes"/>purpose of relieving him, I slipped, and happily was held<lb break="yes"/>back by Colonel Hall and my negro. We were (add@ M.<lb break="yes"/>Boussingault) for a moment all three in the greatest danger.<lb break="yes"/>Further on, the snow became more favorable, and at three<lb break="yes"/>o&#x2019;clock we stood upon the long-lonked-for ridge of rock, which<lb break="yes"/>was only a few feet broad, and surrounded by imm@urabl@<lb break="yes"/>depth. Here we became convinced that to advance farth@<lb break="yes"/>was impossible. We found ourselves at the foot of a prism<lb break="yes"/>of rock, whose upper surface covered with a cap of snow,<lb break="yes"/>forms the p@er summit of Chimborazo. To have a @ue<lb break="yes"/>figure of the topography of the whole mou@ain, @e must<lb break="yes"/>@gine an @ snow-covered moss of rock, which @<lb break="yes" />all sides appears as if supported by butt@es. The latter<lb break="yes"/>are the ridges, which, adherent, project throngh the e@al<lb break="yes" />snow.&#x2019;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 