<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-20" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. Validation.<note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="832" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>AN ACCOUNT OF TWO ATTEMPTS TO ASCEND<lb break="yes"/>CHIMBORAZO.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">By Alexander von Humboldt.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>[The following interesting narrative is abridged from an<lb break="yes" />excerpt from the unpublished Journal of this distinguished<lb break="yes" />traveller, communicated to the <hi rendition="#i">Edinburgh Philosophical<lb break="yes"/>Journal.</hi>]</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> highest mountain-summits of both continents,<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;in the old continent, Dhawalagiri (White Moun-<lb break="no"/>tain) and the Jawahir; in the new, the Sorata and<lb break="yes"/>the Illimani,&#x2014;remain unreached by man. The<lb break="yes"/>highest point of the earth&#x2019;s surface attained, lies in<lb break="yes"/>South America on the south-east side of Chimborazo.<lb break="yes"/>There travellers have reached the height of nearly<lb break="yes"/>18,500 Paris feet<note place="foot" n="*">One French foot is = 1.07892, or about 1 <formula notation="MathML">
                                <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline">
                                    <mfrac>
                                        <mi>1</mi>
                                        <mi>10</mi>
                                    </mfrac>
                                </math>
                            </formula> Eng-<lb break="no"/>lish.&#x2014;Tr.</note>&#x2014;viz. in June 1802, 3016 toises,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">A toise is = 1.94904 metres, or 6.39459 English feet.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Tr.</note>
                        <lb break="yes"/>in December 1831, 3080 toises, above the level of<lb break="yes"/>the sea. Barometrical measurements have thus been<lb break="yes"/>made, in the chain of the Andes 3720 (Paris) feet<lb break="yes"/>above the level of the summit of Mont Blanc. The<lb break="yes"/>height of Mont Blanc is in relation to that of the<lb break="yes"/>Cordilleras so inconsiderable, that in the latter, there<lb break="yes"/>are much-frequented passes that are higher; indeed,<lb break="yes"/>the upper part of the great city of Potosi has an<lb break="yes"/>elevation only 323 toises inferior to that of the<lb break="yes"/>summit of Mont Blanc. I have thought it needful<lb break="yes"/>to premise these numerical statements, in order to<lb break="yes"/>present to the imagination definite points of com-<lb break="no"/>parison for the hypsometric, as it were plastic, con-<lb break="no"/>templation of the surface of the earth.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>On the 22nd of June 1799, I was in the crater of<lb break="yes"/>the Peak of Teneriffe. Three years afterwards,<lb break="yes"/>almost on the same day (the 23rd June 1802), I<lb break="yes"/>reached a point 6700 feet higher, near the summit<lb break="yes"/>of Chimborazo. After a long delay in the table-land<lb break="yes"/>of Quito, one of the most wonderful and picturesque<lb break="yes"/>regions of the earth, we undertook the journey to-<lb break="no"/>wards the forests of the Peruvian bark trees of Loxa,<lb break="yes"/>the upper course of the river Amazons, westward of<lb break="yes"/>the celebrated strait (Pongo de Manseriche), and<lb break="yes"/>through the sandy desert along the Peruvian coast<lb break="yes"/>of the South Sea towards Lima, where we were to<lb break="yes"/>observe the transit of Mercury on the 9th November<lb break="yes"/>1802. On a plain covered with pumice-stone,&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>where (after the fearful earthquake of 4th February<lb break="yes"/>1797) the building of the new city Riobamba was<lb break="yes"/>begun,&#x2014;we enjoyed for several days a splendid view<lb break="yes"/>of the bell or dome-shaped summit of Chimborazo.<lb break="yes"/>We had the clearest weather, favouring trigonometri-<lb break="no"/>cal observation. By means of a large telescope, we<lb break="yes"/>had thoroughly examined the snow-mantle of the<lb break="yes"/>mountain, still 1570 toises distant, and discovered<lb break="yes"/>several ridges, which, projecting like sterile black<lb break="yes"/>streaks, converged towards the summit, and gave<lb break="yes"/>some hope that, upon them, a firm footing might be<lb break="yes"/>obtained in the region of eternal snow. Riobamba<lb break="yes"/>Nuevo lies within sight of the enormous and now<lb break="yes"/>indented mountain Capac-urcu, called by the Spani-<lb break="no"/>ards El Altar, which (says a tradition of the natives)<lb break="yes"/>was once higher than Chimborazo, and after having<lb break="yes"/>been many years in a state of eruption, suddenly fell<lb break="yes"/>in.&#x2014;Riobamba Nuevo must not be confounded with<lb break="yes"/>the old Riobamba of the great map of La Condamine<lb break="yes"/>and Don Pedro Maldonado. The latter city was<lb break="yes" />entirely destroyed by the great catastrophe of the<lb break="yes"/>4th February 1797, which in a few minutes destroyed<lb break="yes"/>45,000 human beings.&#x2014;We were in the plain of<lb break="yes"/>Tapia, from which, on the 22nd June, we began our<lb break="yes"/>expedition towards Chimborazo, being already 8898<lb break="yes"/>Paris feet (1483 toises) above the level of the South<lb break="yes"/>Sea.&#x2014;We gently ascended as far as the foot of the<lb break="yes"/>mountain, where, in the Indian village Calpi, we<lb break="yes"/>were to pass the night. This plain is sparingly<lb break="yes"/>covered with Cactus stems and Schinus molle, which<lb break="yes"/>resembles a weeping willow. Herds of variegated<lb break="yes"/>llamas, in thousands, seek here a scanty subsistence.<lb break="yes"/>At so great a height, the nightly terrestrial radiation<lb break="yes"/>of heat, when the sky is cloudless, proves injurious<lb break="yes"/>to agriculture, through cold and frost.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Very near to Calpi, northwestward of Lican, there<lb break="yes"/>is in the barren table-land a little isolated hill, the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">black mountain,</hi> Yana-Ureu, the name of which<lb break="yes"/>has not been given by the French academicians,<lb break="yes"/>but which, in a geognostical point of view, de-<lb break="no"/>serves much attention. The hill lies S.S.E. of<lb break="yes"/>Chimborazo, at a distance of less than three miles<lb break="yes"/>(15 to 1°), and separated from the same by the high<lb break="yes"/>plain of Lusia only. If in it we do not recognize a<lb break="yes"/>lateral eruption of Chimborazo, the origin of the cone<lb break="yes"/>must certainly be aseribed to the subterranean forces<lb break="yes"/>which, under that mountain, have for thousands of<lb break="yes"/>years vainly sought an opening. It is of later origin<lb break="yes"/>than the elevation of the great dome-shaped moun-<lb break="no"/>tain. The Yana-Urcu forms, with the northern hill<lb break="yes"/>Naguangachi, a connected eminence in the form of<lb break="yes"/>a horse-shoe; the bow, more than a semicircle, is<lb break="yes"/>open towards the east. There probably lies in the<lb break="yes"/>centre of the horse-shoe the point out of which the<lb break="yes"/>black slags have been thrown, that now lie spread<lb break="yes"/>far around. We found there a funnel-shaped depres-<lb break="no"/>sion of about 120 feet in depth, in the interior of<lb break="yes"/>which there is a small hill, whose height does not<lb break="yes"/>equal that of the surrounding margin. Yana-Ureu<lb break="yes"/>probably signifies the southern culminating point of<lb break="yes"/>the old crater-margin, which, at the most, is elevated<lb break="yes"/>400 feet above the level of Calpi. Naguangachi<lb break="yes"/>signifies the northern lower end.&#x2014;According to the<lb break="yes"/>tradition of the natives, and according to old MSS.<lb break="yes"/>which the Cacike or Apu of Lican (the Conchocandi)<lb break="yes"/>possessed, the volcanic eruption of the Yana-Urcu<lb break="yes"/>occurred immediately after the death of the Inca<lb break="yes"/>Tupa-Yupanqui:&#x2014;thus probably in the middle of<lb break="yes"/>the fifteenth century. Tradition says that a fire-ball,<lb break="yes"/>or indeed a star, fell from heaven and set on fire the<lb break="yes"/>mountain. Such fables, connecting the fall of a&#x00EB;ro-<lb break="no"/>lites with eruptions, are also spread among the tribes<lb break="yes"/>of Mexico.&#x2014;On the eastern side of the Yana-Urcu,<lb break="yes"/>or rather at the foot of the hill towards Lican, the<lb break="yes"/>natives conducted us to a projecting rock, an opening<lb break="yes"/>in which resembled the mouth of a forsaken gallery.<lb break="yes"/>Here, as well as at the distance of ten feet, there is<lb break="yes"/>heard a violent subterranean noise, which is accom-<lb break="no"/>panied by a current of air, or subterranean wind.<lb break="yes"/>The current of air is much too weak to admit of the<lb break="yes"/>noise being attributed to it. The noise certainly<lb break="yes"/>arises from a subterranean brook, which is pre-<lb break="no"/>cipitated downwards into a deep hollow, and through<lb break="yes"/>its fall occasions a motion in the air. A monk, the<lb break="yes"/>priest at Calpi, had, with the same idea, some time be-<lb break="no"/>fore, continued on the gallery at an open fissure to pro-<lb break="no"/>cure water for his village. The hardness of the black<lb break="yes"/>augite rock probably interrupted the work. Chim-<lb break="no"/>borazo, notwithstanding its enormous mass of snow,<lb break="yes"/>sends down into the table-land such insignificant<lb break="yes"/>brooks of water, that it may be presumed the greater<lb break="yes"/>part of its water flows through clefts to the interior.<lb break="yes"/>In the village of Calpi itself also, there was formerly<lb break="yes"/>heard a great noise in a house that had no cellar.<lb break="yes"/>Before the celebrated earthquake of the 4th February<lb break="yes"/>1797, there sprang forth a brook in the south-west of<lb break="yes"/>the village at a deeper point. Many Indians con-<lb break="no"/>sidered this brook as a part of the water that flows<lb break="yes"/>under the Yana-Ureu. But since the great carth-<lb break="no"/>quake, this brook has again disappeared.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>After we had passed the night at Calpi, which,<lb break="yes"/>according to my barometrical measurement, lies<lb break="yes"/>9720 feet (1620 toises) above the sea, we began, on<lb break="yes"/>the morning of the 23rd, our proper expedition up<lb break="yes"/>Chimborazo. We attempted to ascend the moun-<lb break="no"/>tain on the S.S.E. side, and the Indians who were<lb break="yes"/>to attend us as guides, but of whom but a few had<lb break="yes"/>ever reached the limit of perpetual snow, gave this<lb break="yes"/>course the preference. We found Chimborazo sur-<lb break="no"/>rounded with great plains, which rise, step-like, one<lb break="yes"/>above the other. Proceeding first through the Llanos<lb break="yes"/>de Lusia, then after rather a gradual ascent of scarcely<lb break="yes"/>5000 feet in length, we reached the table-land (Llano)<lb break="yes"/>of Sisgun. The first step (stufe) is at a height of<lb break="yes"/>10,200 feet, the second 11,700. These grass-grown<lb break="yes"/>plains thus equal in elevation, respectively, the high-<lb break="no"/>est summit of the Pyrenees (Peak Nethou) and the<lb break="yes"/>summit of the Peak of Teneriffe. The perfect<lb break="yes" />horizontality of these table-lands allows us to infer<lb break="yes"/>the long continuance of stagnant water. The tra-<lb break="no"/>veller imagines he sees before him the bottom of a<lb break="yes"/>lake. On the acclivity of the Swiss Alps, there is<lb break="yes"/>sometimes observed this phenomenon of small step-<lb break="no"/>like plains, lying one above the other, which, like<lb break="yes"/>the emptied basins of alpine lakes, are united by<lb break="yes"/>narrow open passes. The widely extended grass<lb break="yes"/>lands are on Chimborazo, as every where around the<lb break="yes"/>high summits of the Andes, so monotonous that the<lb break="yes"/>family of the grasses are seldom interrupted by<lb break="yes"/>dicoty ledonous plants. There prevails almost the<lb break="yes"/>heathy scenery which I have seen in the barren part<lb break="yes"/>of northern Asia. The Flora of Chimborazo, in gene-<lb break="no"/>ral, appeared to us less rich than that of the other<lb break="yes"/>snow mountains which surround the city of Quito.<lb break="yes"/>But a few Calceolari&#x00E6;, Composit&#x00E6;, and Gentian&#x00E6;,<lb break="yes"/>among which the beautiful Gentiana cernua shining<lb break="yes"/>forth with purple flowers,&#x2014;rear themselves on the<lb break="yes"/>high plain of Sisgun, between the associated grasses.<lb break="yes"/>These belong, for the most part, to the genera of<lb break="yes"/>Northern Europe. The temperature of the air<lb break="yes"/>generally prevailing in these regions of alpine grasses,<lb break="yes"/>elevated respectively 1600 and 2000 toises, fluctuates<lb break="yes"/>by day between 4° and 16° C. (39°.2 and 60°.8 F.)<lb break="yes"/>by night between 0° and 10° (32° and 50° F.)</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>My plan was to perform a trigonometrical opera-<lb break="no"/>tion in the beautiful perfectly level grass land of<lb break="yes"/>Sisgun. I had made arrangements for measuring a<lb break="yes"/>base line here. The angles of altitude would have<lb break="yes"/>proved very considerable in such proximity to the<lb break="yes"/>summit of Chimborazo. There remained yet a per-<lb break="no"/>pendicular height of less than 8400 feet (the height<lb break="yes"/>of the Canigou in the Pyrenees) to determine. Yet<lb break="yes"/>with the enormous masses of single mountains in the<lb break="yes"/>chain of the Andes, every determination of the height<lb break="yes"/>above the sea is compounded of a barometrical and<lb break="yes"/>trigonometrical observation. I had taken with me<lb break="yes"/>the sextant and other instruments of measurement<lb break="yes"/>in vain. The summit of Chimborazo remained<lb break="yes" />densely veiled in mist. From the high plain of Sis-<lb break="no"/>gun the ascent is tolerably steep as far as the little<lb break="yes"/>alpine lake of Yana-Coche. Thus far I had remained<lb break="yes"/>on the mule, having from time to time alighted with<lb break="yes"/>my travelling companion M. Bonpland merely to<lb break="yes"/>collect plants. Yana-Coche does not deserve the<lb break="yes"/>name of a lake. It is a circular basin of scarcely<lb break="yes"/>130 feet in diameter. The sky became more and<lb break="yes"/>more obscured; but between and over the mist-strata<lb break="yes"/>there still lay scattered single groups of clouds. The<lb break="yes"/>summit of Chimborazo was visible for a few moments<lb break="yes"/>only at a time. Much snow having fallen during<lb break="yes"/>the preceding night, I left the mule where we found<lb break="yes"/>the lower border of this newly-fallen snow, a border<lb break="yes"/>which must not be confounded with the limit of per-<lb break="no"/>petual snow. The barometer showed that we had<lb break="yes"/>only now attained the height of 13,500 feet. On<lb break="yes"/>other mountains, likewise near to the equator, I have<lb break="yes"/>seen snow fall at the height of 11,200 feet, but not<lb break="yes"/>lower. My companion rode as far as the line of<lb break="yes"/>perpetual snow, <hi rendition="#i">i. e.</hi> to the height of Mont Blanc;<lb break="yes"/>which mountain, as is known, would not in this lati-<lb break="no"/>tude (1° 27&#x2032; south) always be covered with snow.<lb break="yes"/>The horses and mules remained there to await our<lb break="yes"/>return.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A hundred and fifty toises above the little basin of<lb break="yes" />Yana-Coche, we saw at length naked rock. Hitherto<lb break="yes"/>the grass-land had withdrawn the ground from any<lb break="yes"/>geognostical examination. Great walls of rock, ex-<lb break="no"/>tending from the N.E. towards the S.W., in part<lb break="yes"/>cleft into misshapen columns, reared themselves out<lb break="yes"/>of the eternal snow,&#x2014;a brownish-black augite rock<lb break="yes"/>shining like pitch-stone porphyry. The columns<lb break="yes"/>were very thin, perhaps from fifty to sixty feet in<lb break="yes"/>height, almost like the trachyte columns of Tabla-<lb break="no"/>Umca on the volcano Pichincha. One group stood<lb break="yes"/>alone, and reminded one of masts and stems of trees.<lb break="yes"/>The steep walls led us through the snow region to a<lb break="yes"/>narrow ridge of rock extending towards the summit,<lb break="yes"/>by which alone it was possible for us to advance any<lb break="yes"/>farther; for the snow was then so soft that one<lb break="yes"/>scarcely dared to tread upon its surface. The ridge<lb break="yes"/>consisted of very weathered crumbling rock. It was<lb break="yes"/>often vesicular like a basaltic-amygdaloid.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The path became more and more narrow and<lb break="yes"/>steep. The natives forsook us all but one at the<lb break="yes"/>height of 15,600 feet. All entreaties and threats<lb break="yes"/>were unavailing. The Indians maintained that they<lb break="yes"/>suffered more than we did from breathlessness. We<lb break="yes"/>remained alone, Bonpland,&#x2014;our amiable friend the<lb break="yes"/>younger son of the Marquis of Selvalegre, Carlos<lb break="yes"/>Montufar, who in the subsequent struggle for free-<lb break="no"/>dom, was shot (at the command of General Morillo),<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;a Mestize from the neighbouring village of San<lb break="yes"/>Juan,&#x2014;and myself. We attained, with great exer-<lb break="no"/>tion and endurance, a greater height than we had<lb break="yes"/>dared hope to reach, as we were almost entirely<lb break="yes"/>wrapped in mist. The ridge (very significantly called,<lb break="yes"/>in Spanish, Cuchilla, as it were the knife-back) was<lb break="yes"/>in many places only eight to ten inches broad. On<lb break="yes"/>the left the precipice was concealed by snow, the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="833" facs="#f0002"/> surface of the latter seemed glazed with frost. The<lb break="yes"/>thin icy mirror-like surface had an inclination of<lb break="yes"/>about 30°. On the right our view sank shuddering<lb break="yes"/>800 or 1000 feet into an abyss out of which pro-<lb break="no"/>jected, perpendicularly, snowless masses of rock. We<lb break="yes"/>held the body continually inclined towards this side,<lb break="yes"/>for the precipice upon the left seemed still more<lb break="yes"/>threatening, because there no chance presented itself<lb break="yes"/>of grasping the toothed rock, and because, further,<lb break="yes"/>the thin ice-crust offered no security against sinking<lb break="yes"/>in the loose snow. Only extremely light porous bits<lb break="yes"/>of dolerite could we roll down this crust of ice; and<lb break="yes"/>the inclined plane of snow was so extended that we<lb break="yes"/>lost sight of the stones thus rolled down before they<lb break="yes"/>came to rest. The absence of snow, as well upon<lb break="yes"/>the ridge along which we ascended, as upon the rocks<lb break="yes"/>on our right hand towards the east, cannot be as-<lb break="no"/>cribed so much to the steepness of the masses, and to<lb break="yes"/>the gales of wind, as to open clefts, which breathe<lb break="yes"/>out warm air from deeper situated beds. We soon<lb break="yes"/>found our further ascent more difficult, from the in-<lb break="no"/>crease of the crumbling nature of the rock. At single<lb break="yes"/>and very steep <hi rendition="#i">échélons</hi> it was necessary to apply at<lb break="yes"/>the same time the hands and feet, as is so usual in<lb break="yes"/>all alpine journeys. As the rock was very keenly<lb break="yes"/>angular, we were painfully hurt, especially in the<lb break="yes"/>hands. Leopold Von Buch and I suffered very much<lb break="yes"/>in this manner near the crater of the Peak of Tene-<lb break="no"/>riffe, which abounds in obsidian.&#x2014;The little adhesion<lb break="yes"/>of the rocks upon the ridge now rendered greater<lb break="yes"/>caution necessary, as many masses which we sup-<lb break="no"/>posed firm lay loose and covered with sand. We<lb break="yes"/>proceeded one after the other, and so much the more<lb break="yes"/>slowly, as it was needful to try the places which<lb break="yes"/>seemed uncertain. Happily the attempt to reach<lb break="yes"/>the summit of Chimborazo was the last of our moun-<lb break="no"/>tain journeys in South America; hence previous<lb break="yes"/>experience guided us, and gave us more confidence<lb break="yes"/>in our powers. It is a peculiar character of all ex-<lb break="no"/>cursions in the Andes, that above the snow line white<lb break="yes"/>people find themselves, in the most perilous situations,<lb break="yes"/>always without guides, indeed without any knowledge<lb break="yes"/>of localities.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We could see the summit no longer, even for a<lb break="yes"/>moment only at a time, and were hence doubly<lb break="yes"/>curious to know, how much higher it remained for<lb break="yes"/>us to ascend. We examined the barometer at a<lb break="yes"/>point where the breadth of the ridge permitted of<lb break="yes"/>two persons standing conveniently together. We<lb break="yes"/>were now at an elevation of 17,300 feet; thus scarcely<lb break="yes"/>two hundred feet higher than we had been two months<lb break="yes"/>before, when climbing a similar ridge on the Antisana.<lb break="yes"/>It is with the determining of heights in climbing<lb break="yes"/>mountains, as with the determining of temperature<lb break="yes"/>in the heat of summer. One finds with vexation<lb break="yes"/>the thermometer not so high, the barometer not so<lb break="yes"/>low, as one expected. As the air, notwithstanding<lb break="yes"/>the height, was quite saturated with moisture, we<lb break="yes"/>now found the loose rock and the sand that filled its<lb break="yes"/>interstices extremely wet. The air was still 2° 8&#x2032;<lb break="yes"/>(37° 04&#x2032; Fahr.) Shortly before, we had in a dry<lb break="yes"/>place been able to bury the thermometer three inches<lb break="yes"/>deep in the sand. It indicated +5° 8&#x2032; (+42° 44&#x2032;<lb break="yes"/>Fahr.) The result of this observation, which was<lb break="yes"/>made at the height of about 2860 toises, is very<lb break="yes"/>remarkable, for 400 toises lower down, at the limit<lb break="yes"/>of perpetual snow, the mean heat of the atmosphere<lb break="yes"/>is according to many observations, carefully collected<lb break="yes"/>by Boussingault and myself, only +1° 6&#x2032; (34° 88&#x2032;<lb break="yes"/>Fahr.) The temperature of earth (sand) at +5° 8&#x2032;<lb break="yes"/>(42° 44&#x2032; Fahr.) must therefore be ascribed to the<lb break="yes"/>subterranean heat of the dolerite mountain; I do<lb break="yes"/>not say to the whole mass, but to the current of air<lb break="yes"/>ascending from the interior.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>After an hour of cautious climbing, the ridge of<lb break="yes"/>rock became less steep; but alas! the mist remained<lb break="yes"/>as thick as ever. We now began gradually to suffer<lb break="yes"/>from great nausea. The tendency to vomiting was<lb break="yes"/>combined with some giddiness; and much more trou-<lb break="no"/>blesome than the difficulty of breathing. A coloured<lb break="yes"/>man (a Mestize of San Juan), not from selfish motives,<lb break="yes"/>but merely out of good-nature, had been unwilling to<lb break="yes"/>forsake us. He was a poor vigorous peasant, and suf-<lb break="no"/>fered more than we did. We had h&#x00E6;morrhage from<lb break="yes"/>the gums and lips. The conjunctiva of the eyes<lb break="yes"/>likewise, was, in all, gorged with blood. These symp-<lb break="no"/>toms of extravasation in the eyes, and of oozing from<lb break="yes"/>the lips and gums, did not in the least disquiet us,<lb break="yes"/>as we had repeatedly experienced them before. In<lb break="yes"/>Europe, M. Zumstein began to experience h&#x00E6;mor-<lb break="no"/>rhage at a much lower elevation on Monte Rosa. The<lb break="yes"/>Spanish warriors during the conquest of the equi-<lb break="no"/>noctial region of America (during the Conquista),<lb break="yes"/>did not ascend above the snow line, thus but little<lb break="yes"/>above the elevation of Mont Blanc, and yet Acosta,<lb break="yes"/>in his &#x2018;Historia Natural de las Indias,&#x2019;&#x2014;a kind of<lb break="yes"/>physical geography, which may be called a master-<lb break="no"/>piece of the sixteenth century,&#x2014;speaks circumstan-<lb break="no"/>tially of &#x201C;nausea and spasm of the stomach,&#x201D; as<lb break="yes"/>painful symptoms of the <hi rendition="#i">mountain-sickness,</hi> which in<lb break="yes" />these respects is analogous to <hi rendition="#i">sea-sickness.</hi> On the<lb break="yes"/>volcano of Pichincha I once felt, without experienc-<lb break="no"/>ing h&#x00E6;morrhage, so violent an affection of the stomach,<lb break="yes"/>accompanied by giddiness, that I was found senseless<lb break="yes"/>on the ground, just as I left my companions on a<lb break="yes"/>wall of rock above the defile of Verde-Cucha, in<lb break="yes"/>order to perform some electrical experiments on a<lb break="yes"/>perfectly open space. The height was inconsiderable,<lb break="yes"/>below 13,800 feet. But on the Antisana, at the<lb break="yes"/>considerable elevation of 17,220 feet, our young<lb break="yes"/>travelling companion, Don Carlos Montufar, bled<lb break="yes"/>freely from the lips. All of these phenomena vary<lb break="yes"/>according to age, constitution, the tenderness of the<lb break="yes"/>skin, the preceding exertions of the muscular powers;<lb break="yes"/>yet for single individuals they are a kind of measure<lb break="yes"/>of the atmospheric tenuity, and of the absolute eleva-<lb break="no"/>tion reached. According to my observations in the<lb break="yes"/>Cordilleras, these symptoms manifest themselves in<lb break="yes"/>white people, with a mercurial column between 14<lb break="yes"/>inches,&#x2014;and 15 inches 10 lines.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The layers of mist that prevented our seeing dis-<lb break="no"/>tant objects, appeared suddenly, notwithstanding the<lb break="yes"/>total stillness of the air, perhaps through electrical<lb break="yes"/>processes, to be broken up. We recognized once<lb break="yes"/>more, and indeed immediately before us, the dome-<lb break="no"/>shaped summit of Chimborazo. It was an earnest,<lb break="yes"/>momentous gaze. The hope to reach this summit<lb break="yes"/>animated our powers anew. The ridge of rock, only<lb break="yes"/>here and there covered with thin flakes of snow, be-<lb break="no"/>came somewhat broader. We hastened onwards,<lb break="yes"/>with certain steps, when all at once a ravine of some<lb break="yes"/>400 feet in depth, and 50 broad, set an insurmount-<lb break="no"/>able barrier to our undertaking. We saw distinctly<lb break="yes"/>beyond the abyss, our ridge of rock continued for-<lb break="no"/>ward in the same direction; yet I doubt its leading<lb break="yes"/>to the summit itself. The chasm was not to be gone<lb break="yes"/>round. On the Antisana, M. Bonpland indeed had<lb break="yes"/>found it possible, after a very cold night, to proceed<lb break="yes"/>for a considerable length through the snow. We<lb break="yes"/>durst not venture the attempt, because of the loose-<lb break="no"/>ness of the mass, and the form of the precipice ren-<lb break="no"/>dered climbing down impossible. It was one o&#x2019;clock<lb break="yes"/>in the afternoon. We set up with much care the<lb break="yes"/>barometer. It indicated 13 inches 11<formula notation="MathML">
                            <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline">
                                <mfrac>
                                    <mi>2</mi>
                                    <mi>10</mi>
                                </mfrac>
                            </math>
                        </formula> lines. The<lb break="yes"/>temperature of the air was now &#x2014;1° 6&#x2032; (+29° 12&#x2032;<lb break="yes"/>Fahr.), but after several years&#x2019; stay in the hottest<lb break="yes"/>regions of the Tropics, this small degree of cold<lb break="yes"/>benumbed us. Besides, our boots were thoroughly<lb break="yes"/>soaked with snow-water, for the sand that covered<lb break="yes"/>here and there the ridge was mixed with old snow.<lb break="yes"/>According to La Place&#x2019;s barometrical formula, we<lb break="yes"/>had reached a height of 3016 toises, or more pre-<lb break="no"/>cisely 18,097 Paris feet. If La Condamine&#x2019;s estimate<lb break="yes"/>of the height of Chimborazo, as noted on the stone-<lb break="no"/>table of the Jesuit&#x2019;s College in Quito, be correct,<lb break="yes"/>there failed us yet of the summit of the mountain<lb break="yes"/>1224 feet, or thrice the height of St. Peter&#x2019;s church<lb break="yes"/>at Rome.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We remained but a short time in this mournful<lb break="yes"/>solitude, being soon again entirely veiled in mist.<lb break="yes"/>The humid air was not thereby set in motion. No<lb break="yes"/>fixed direction was to be observed in single groups of<lb break="yes"/>the denser particles of vapour; I therefore cannot<lb break="yes"/>say whether at this elevation the west wind blows,<lb break="yes"/>opposing the Tropical monsoon. We saw no longer<lb break="yes"/>the summit of Chimborazo, none of the neighbouring<lb break="yes"/>snow-mountains, still less the table lands of Quito.<lb break="yes"/>We were as though isolated in a ball of air. Some<lb break="yes"/>stone lichens only had followed us above the line of<lb break="yes"/>perpetual snow. The last cryptogamic plants which<lb break="yes"/>I collected were Leeidea atrovirens (Lichen geogra-<lb break="no"/>phicus, <hi rendition="#i">Web.</hi>), and a Gyrophora of <hi rendition="#i">Acharius,</hi> a new<lb break="yes"/>species (Gyrophora rugosa), at about the height of<lb break="yes"/>2820 toises. The last moss, Grimmia longirostris,<lb break="yes"/>grew 400 toises lower down. A butterfly (sphinx)<lb break="yes"/>was caught by M. Bonpland at the height of 15,000<lb break="yes"/>feet; we saw a fly 1600 feet higher. I must remark,<lb break="yes"/>that we met with no condor on Chimborazo, that<lb break="yes"/>powerful vulture, which is so frequent on Antisana<lb break="yes"/>and Pichincha, and which shows great confidence<lb break="yes"/>from its ignorance of man. The condor loves pure<lb break="yes"/>air, in order the easier from on high to recognize its<lb break="yes"/>prey or its food, for it gives dead animals the pre-<lb break="no"/>ference.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>As the weather became more and more cloudy, we<lb break="yes"/>hastened down upon the same ledge of rock, that had<lb break="yes"/>favoured our ascent. Caution, however, on account<lb break="yes"/>of the uncertainty of the steps, was more necessary<lb break="yes"/>than in climbing up. We tarried only just to col-<lb break="no"/>lect fragments of rock. We foresaw that in Europe<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;a little bit of Chimborazo&#x201D; would be asked for. At<lb break="yes"/>that time, no mountain rock in any part of South<lb break="yes"/>America had been named; the rocks of all the high<lb break="yes"/>summits of the Andes were called granite. As we<lb break="yes"/>were at the height of about 17,400 feet, it began to<lb break="yes"/>hail violently. The hailstones were opaque, and<lb break="yes"/>milk-white, with concentric layers; some appeared<lb break="yes"/>considerably flattened by rotation; twenty minutes<lb break="yes"/>before we reached the lower limit of perpetual snow,<lb break="yes"/>the hail was replaced by snow. The flakes were so<lb break="yes"/>dense, that the snow soon covered the ridge of rock<lb break="yes"/>many inches deep; we should have been brought<lb break="yes"/>into great danger, had the snow surprised us at the<lb break="yes"/>height of 18,000 feet. At a few minutes after two<lb break="yes"/>o&#x2019;clock, we reached the point where our mules were<lb break="yes"/>standing. The natives that remained behind, had<lb break="yes"/>been very apprehensive for our safety.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>That part of our expedition which lay above the<lb break="yes"/>snow-line, had lasted only 3&#x00BD; hours, during which,<lb break="yes" />notwithstanding the tenuity of the air, we had not<lb break="yes"/>found it needful to take rest by sitting down. On<lb break="yes"/>account of the snow newly fallen, we found in our<lb break="yes"/>descent from Chimborazo, the lower limit of per-<lb break="no"/>petual snow, in accidental and temporary conjunction<lb break="yes"/>with the deeper sporadial spots of snow on the naked<lb break="yes"/>lichen-covered rocks, and on the grass plain (Pajo-<lb break="no"/>nal); yet it was always easy to recognize the proper<lb break="yes"/>limit of perpetual snow (then at the height of 2470<lb break="yes"/>toises) by the thickness of the bed and by its peculiar<lb break="yes"/>state.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We took a somewhat more northern way back<lb break="yes"/>to the village of Calpi than the Llanos de Sisgun,<lb break="yes"/>through the Paramo de Pungupala, a district rich in<lb break="yes"/>plants. By five o&#x2019;clock in the evening we were again<lb break="yes"/>with the friendly clergyman of Calpi. As usual, the<lb break="yes"/>misty day of the expedition was succeeded by the<lb break="yes"/>clearest weather. On the 25th of June, at Rio-<lb break="no"/>bamba Nuevo, Chimborazo presented itself in all its<lb break="yes"/>splendour,&#x2014;I may say, in the calm greatness and<lb break="yes"/>supremacy which is the natural character of the<lb break="yes"/>tropical landscape. A second attempt upon a ridge<lb break="yes"/>interrupted by a chasm, would certainly have turned<lb break="yes"/>out as fruitless as the first, and I was already engaged<lb break="yes"/>with the trigonometrical measurement of the volcano<lb break="yes"/>of Tungurahua.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Boussingault, on the 16th of December 1831, with<lb break="yes"/>his English friend Colonel Hall,&#x2014;who was soon<lb break="yes"/>afterwards assassinated in Quito,&#x2014;made a new at-<lb break="no"/>tempt to reach the summit of Chimborazo, first from<lb break="yes"/>Mocha and Chillapullu, then from Arenal, thus by a<lb break="yes"/>different way from that trodden by Bonpland, Don<lb break="yes"/>Carlos Montufar, and myself. He was obliged to<lb break="yes"/>give up the ascent, when his barometer indicated 13<lb break="yes"/>inches 8&#x00BD; lines, with an atmospheric temperature of<lb break="yes"/>+7°.8 (+46°.04 F.). He thus saw the uncorrected<lb break="yes"/>column of mercury almost three lines lower, and<lb break="yes"/>reached a point 64 toises higher than I did, viz.<lb break="yes"/>3080 toises. Let us have the words of this well-<lb break="no"/>known traveller of the Andes, who was the first to<lb break="yes"/>carry a chemical apparatus to, and into, the craters<lb break="yes"/>of volcanoes. &#x201C;The way,&#x201D; says Boussingault, &#x201C;which<lb break="yes"/>we opened for ourselves through the snow, in the<lb break="yes"/>latter part of our expedition, permitted of our ad-<lb break="no"/>vancing but very slowly. On the right we were<lb break="yes"/>enabled to grasp hold of a rock, on the left, the<lb break="yes"/>abyss was fearful. We were already sensible of the<lb break="yes"/>effect of the attenuated air, and were obliged, every<lb break="yes"/>two or three steps to sit down. As soon, however,<lb break="yes"/>as we were seated, we again stood up, for our suffer-<lb break="no"/>ings lasted only while we moved. The snow we<lb break="yes" />were obliged to tread was soft, and lay three or four<lb break="yes" />inches deep, on a very smooth and hard covering of<lb break="yes"/>ice. We were obliged to hew our steps. A Negro<lb break="yes"/>went before, to perform this work, by which his<lb break="yes"/>powers were soon exhausted. As I was endeavour-<lb break="no"/>ing to pass him, for the purpose of relieving him, I<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="834" facs="#f0003"/> slipped, and happily was held back by Colonel Hall<lb break="yes"/>and my Negro. We were (adds M. Boussingault)<lb break="yes"/>for a moment all three in the greatest danger. Fur-<lb break="no"/>ther on, the snow became more favourable, and at<lb break="yes"/>three quarters past three o&#x2019;clock we stood upon the<lb break="yes"/>long-looked-for ridge of rock, which was only a few<lb break="yes"/>feet broad, and surrounded by immeasurable depths.<lb break="yes"/>Here we became convinced that to advance farther<lb break="yes"/>was impossible. We found ourselves at the foot of<lb break="yes"/>a prism of rock, whose upper surface covered with a<lb break="yes"/>cap of snow, forms the proper summit of Chimborazo.<lb break="yes"/>To have a true figure of the topography of the whole<lb break="yes"/>mountain, one must imagine an enormous snow-<lb break="no" />covered mass of rock, which from all sides appears<lb break="yes"/>as if supported by buttresses. The latter are the<lb break="yes"/>ridges, which, adherent, project through the eternal<lb break="yes"/>snow.&#x201D;</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 