<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-20" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="89" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#k">two attempts to ascend chimborazo.<lb break="yes"/>by alexander von humboldt.</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">Translated from the German by Dr. Martin Barry;<lb break="yes"/>in Jameson&#x2019;s Journal.</hi>)</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> highest mountain-summits of both<lb break="yes" />continents,&#x2014;in the old continent, Dhawala-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="90" facs="#f0002"/> giri (White Mountain) and the Jawahir; in<lb break="yes"/>the new, the Sorata and the Illimani,&#x2014;re-<lb break="no"/>main unreached by man. The highest point<lb break="yes"/>of the earth&#x2019;s surface attained, lies in South<lb break="yes"/>America on the south-east side of Chimbo-<lb break="no"/>razo. There travellers have reached the<lb break="yes"/>height of nearly 18,500 Paris feet<note place="foot" n="*">One French foot is =1.07892, or about 1,1.15th<lb break="yes"/>English.&#x2014;Tr.</note>&#x2014;viz., in<lb break="yes"/>June 1802, 3,016 toises,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">A toise is =1.94904 metres, or 6.39459 English<lb break="yes" />feet.&#x2014;Tr.</note> in December, 1831,<lb break="yes"/>3,080 toises, above the level of the sea. Ba-<lb break="no"/>rometrical measurements have thus been<lb break="yes"/>made, in the chain of the Andes 3,720<lb break="yes"/>(Paris) feet above the level of the summit of<lb break="yes"/>Mont Blanc. The height of Mont Blanc is<lb break="yes"/>in relation to that of the Cordilleras so incon-<lb break="no"/>siderable, that in the latter, there are much<lb break="yes"/>frequented passes that are higher; indeed,<lb break="yes"/>the upper part of the great city of Potosi has<lb break="yes"/>an elevation only 323 toises inferior to that of<lb break="yes"/>the summit of Mont Blanc. I have thought<lb break="yes"/>it needful to premise these numerical state-<lb break="no"/>ments, in order to present to the imagination<lb break="yes"/>definite points of comparison for the hypso-<lb break="no"/>metric, as it were plastic, contemplation of<lb break="yes"/>the surface of the earth.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The attainment of great heights is of less<lb break="yes"/>scientific interest, when the same lie far<lb break="yes"/>above the snow-line, and can be visited for a<lb break="yes"/>few hours only. Immediate barometrical<lb break="yes"/>measurements of heights afford indeed this<lb break="yes" />advantage, that the results are quickly ob-<lb break="no"/>tained, yet the summits are, for the most part,<lb break="yes"/>surrounded by high plains, adapted for trigo-<lb break="no"/>nometrical operations, by which all the ele-<lb break="no"/>ments of the measurements can be repeatedly<lb break="yes"/>proved; whilst a single determination by<lb break="yes" />means of the barometer, is liahle to consider-<lb break="no"/>able errors, because of the ascending and<lb break="yes"/>descending currents of air on the mountain<lb break="yes"/>slopes, and the variation in the decrease of<lb break="yes"/>temperature thus occasioned. The nature of<lb break="yes" />the rocks, from the permanent covering of<lb break="yes"/>snow, is almost entirely withdrawn from<lb break="yes"/>geognostic observation, since there are pre-<lb break="no"/>sented only single ridges composed of much<lb break="yes"/>weathered strata. Organic life ceases in<lb break="yes" />these lofty solitudes. Scarcely do the condor<lb break="yes"/>and winged insects stray into these attenu-<lb break="no"/>ated strata of the atmosphere, the latter being<lb break="yes"/>carried up by the currents of air. If the<lb break="yes"/>endeavours of travelling natural philosophers<lb break="yes"/>who strive to climb the higher summits of<lb break="yes" />the earth, is scarcely rewarded by a serious<lb break="yes"/>scientific interest, there is, on the other hand,<lb break="yes"/>an active popular participation in such endea-<lb break="no"/>vours. That which seems unattainable has<lb break="yes"/>a mysterious attractive power; we wish that<lb break="yes"/>all should be explored,&#x2014;at least attempted,<lb break="yes"/>though not to be obt@ined. Chimborazo has<lb break="yes"/>been the wearisome object of all inquiries<lb break="yes" />addressed to me since my first return to<lb break="yes"/>Europe. The thoroughly exploring of the<lb break="yes"/>most important laws of nature, the most vivid<lb break="yes"/>delineations of stratified zones of plants and<lb break="yes"/>differences in climates, determining, as the<lb break="yes"/>latter do, the object of agriculture, were sel-<lb break="no"/>dom capable of diverting attention from the<lb break="yes" />snow clad summit which at that time (before<lb break="yes" />Peutland&#x2019;s journey to Bolivia) was supposed<lb break="yes"/>to be the culminating point of the dike-like<lb break="yes"/>Andes.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I shall here extract from the still unprinted<lb break="yes"/>portion of my journals, the simple narration of<lb break="yes"/>a mountain journey. The entire detail of the<lb break="yes"/>trigonometrical measurement, which I made<lb break="yes"/>at New Riobaraba in the plain of Tapia, was<lb break="yes"/>made known in the introduction to the first<lb break="yes" />volume of my <hi rendition="#i">Astronomical Observations,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>soon after my return. The geographical dis-<lb break="no" />tribution of the plants on the acclivity of<lb break="yes"/>Chimborazo and the neighbouring moun-<lb break="no"/>tains (from the sea-coast up to a height of<lb break="yes"/>14,800 feet), I have attempted to represent<lb break="yes"/>by a figure in a table of my <hi rendition="#i" >Geographical<lb break="yes"/>and Physical Atlas of South America,</hi> ac-<lb break="no"/>cording to the excellent determination by<lb break="yes"/>Kunth of the alpine vegetation of the Cordil-<lb break="no"/>leras, collected by Bonpland and myself.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The history of the ascent itself, which can<lb break="yes"/>present but little dramatic interest, was re-<lb break="no"/>served for the fourth and last volume of my<lb break="yes"/>journey towards the equatorial regions. But<lb break="yes"/>since my friend M. Boussingault, now Pro-<lb break="no"/>fessor of Chemistry at Lyons, one of the most<lb break="yes" />talented and learned travellers of modern<lb break="yes"/>times, has recently, at my request, described<lb break="yes"/>in the Annals de Chimie et de Physiques,<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">See Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal, vol.<lb break="yes"/>xix, for 1835, where there is a translation of Boussin-<lb break="no"/>gault&#x2019;s memoir.</note>
                        <lb break="yes"/>this enterprise, which very closely resembles<lb break="yes"/>my own,&#x2014;and since our observations are<lb break="yes"/>mutually confirmative of each other,&#x2014;this<lb break="yes"/>small fragment of a journey, which I here<lb break="yes" />lay before the public, will no doubt be fa-<lb break="no"/>voured with an indulgent reception. I shall<lb break="yes"/>provisionally refrain from all circumstantial<lb break="yes"/>geognostic and physical discussions.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>On the 22nd of June, 1799, I was in the<lb break="yes"/>crater of the Peak of Tenneriffe. Three<lb break="yes"/>years afterwards, almost on the same day<lb break="yes"/>(the 23rd of June, 1802), I reached a point<lb break="yes"/>6,700 feet higher, near the summit of Chim-<lb break="no" />borazo. After a long delay in the table-<lb break="no"/>land of Quito, one of the most wonderful and<lb break="yes"/>picturesque regions of the earth, we under-<lb break="no"/>took the journey towards the forests of the<lb break="yes"/>Peruvian bark trees of Loxa, the upper course<lb break="yes"/>of the river Amazons, westward of the cele-<lb break="no" />brated strait (Pongo de Manseriche), and<lb break="yes"/>through the sady desert along the Peruvian<lb break="yes"/>coast of the South Sea towards Lima, where<lb break="yes"/>we were to observe the transit of Mercury on<lb break="yes"/>the 9th of November, 1802. On a plain covered<lb break="yes"/>with pumice-stone,&#x2014;where (after the fearful<lb break="yes"/>earthquake of February 4, 1797) the build-<lb break="no" />ding of the new city Riobamba was begun,&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="91" facs="#f0003"/> we enjoyed for several days a splendid view<lb break="yes"/>of the bell or dome-shaped summit of Chim-<lb break="no" />borazo. We had the clearest weather, fa-<lb break="no"/>vouring trigonometrical observation. By<lb break="yes"/>means of a large telescope, we had thoroughly<lb break="yes"/>examined the snow-mantle of the mountain,<lb break="yes"/>still 15,700 toises distant, and discovered<lb break="yes"/>several ridges, which, projecting like sterile<lb break="yes"/>black streaks, converged towards the summit<lb break="yes" />and gave some hope that, upon them, a firm<lb break="yes"/>footing might be obtained in the region of<lb break="yes"/>eternal snow. Riobamba Nuevo lies within<lb break="yes"/>sight of the enormous and now indented<lb break="yes"/>mountain Capac-urcu, called by the Span-<lb break="no" />iards @Altar, which (says a tradition of the<lb break="yes"/>natives) was once higher than Chimborazo,<lb break="yes"/>and after having been many years in a state<lb break="yes"/>of eruption suddenly fell in. This terror-<lb break="no"/>spreading event is said to have taken place<lb break="yes"/>shortly before the conquest of Quito by the<lb break="yes" />Inca Tupac-Yupanqui. Riobamba Nuevo<lb break="yes"/>must not be confounded with the old Rio-<lb break="no"/>bamba of the great map of La Condamine<lb break="yes"/>and Don Pedro Maldonado. The latter city<lb break="yes" />was entirely destroyed by the great catas-<lb break="no"/>trophe of the 4th of February, 1797, which in a<lb break="yes"/>few minutes destroyed 45,000 human beings.<lb break="yes"/>The new Riobamba lies, according to my<lb break="yes"/>chronometrical observations, 42 seconds more<lb break="yes"/>to the eastward than the old Riobamba, but<lb break="yes" />almost in the same latitude (1° 41&#x2032; 46&#x2033;<lb break="yes" />south). We were in the plain of Tapia, from<lb break="yes"/>which, on the 22nd of June, we began our ex-<lb break="no"/>pedition towards Chimborazo, being already<lb break="yes"/>8,898 Paris feet<note place="foot" n="*">Thus 2.890 metres. Boussingault calculated<lb break="yes"/>this elevation to be 2,870 metres, and estimated the<lb break="yes"/>mean temperature of the high plain of Tabia at<lb break="yes"/>16°,4 C. (61°52 F.)</note> (1,483 toises) above the<lb break="yes"/>level of the South Sea. This table-land is a<lb break="yes"/>part of the valley-land between the Eastern<lb break="yes"/>and Western Andes, <hi rendition="#i">i. e.</hi> between the chain<lb break="yes"/>of the active volcanoes Cotopaxi and Tungu-<lb break="no"/>rahua on the one hand, and the chain of the<lb break="yes"/>Iliniza and Chimborazo on the other. We<lb break="yes" />gently ascended as far as the foot of the last<lb break="yes"/>mentioned mountain, where, in the Indian<lb break="yes"/>village Calpi, we were to pass the night.<lb break="yes"/>This plain is sparingly covered with Cactus<lb break="yes"/>stems and Schinus molle, which resembles a<lb break="yes"/>weeping willow. Herds of variegated llamas,<lb break="yes" />in thousands, seek here a scanty subsistence.<lb break="yes"/>At so great a height, the nightly terrestrial<lb break="yes"/>radiation of heat, when the sky is cloudless,<lb break="yes"/>proves injurious to agriculture, through cold<lb break="yes"/>and frost. Before reaching Calpi, we visited<lb break="yes"/>Lican, now likewise a small village, but<lb break="yes" />before the conquest of the country by the<lb break="yes"/>eleventh Inca,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">The same Tupac-Yupanqui, whose well preserved<lb break="yes"/>remains, Garcillasso de la Vega, so lately as in 1559,<lb break="yes"/>had seen in the family-vault at Cuzco.</note> a considerable city, and the<lb break="yes"/>place of residence of the Conchocando, or<lb break="yes"/>Prince of Puruay. The natives believe that<lb break="yes"/>the few wild llamas found on the western<lb break="yes"/>side of Chimborazo, are derived from dis-<lb break="no"/>persed and fugitive herds, which, after the<lb break="yes" />destruction of the old Lican, became wild.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Very near to Calpi, north-westward of<lb break="yes"/>Lican, there is in the barren table-land a<lb break="yes"/>little isolated hill, the <hi rendition="#i">black mountain,</hi> Yana-<lb break="no"/>Urcu, the name of which has not been given<lb break="yes"/>by the French academicians, but which, in a<lb break="yes"/>geognostical point of view, deserves much<lb break="yes"/>attention. The hill lies SS.E. of Chimbo-<lb break="no" />razo, at a distance of less than three miles<lb break="yes"/>(15 to 1°), and separated from the same by<lb break="yes"/>the high plain of Luisa only. If in it we do<lb break="yes"/>not recognise a lateral eruption of Chimbo-<lb break="no"/>razo, the origin of the cone must certainly be<lb break="yes"/>ascribed to the subterranean forces which,<lb break="yes" />under that mountain, have for thousands of<lb break="yes"/>years vainly sought an opening. It is of<lb break="yes"/>later origin than the elevation of the great<lb break="yes"/>dome-shaped mountain. The Yana-Urcu<lb break="yes"/>forms, with the northern hill Naguangachi,<lb break="yes" />a connected eminence in the form of a horse-<lb break="no"/>shoe; the bow, more than a semicircle, is<lb break="yes"/>open towards the east. There probably lies<lb break="yes"/>in the centre of the horse-shoe, the point out<lb break="yes"/>of which the black slags have been thrown,<lb break="yes"/>that now lie spread far around. We found<lb break="yes" />there a funnel-shaped depression of about<lb break="yes"/>120 feet in depth, in the interior of which<lb break="yes"/>there is a small hill, whose height does not<lb break="yes"/>equal that of the surrounding margin.<lb break="yes"/>Yana-Urcu probably signifies the southern<lb break="yes" />culminating point of the old crater-margin,<lb break="yes"/>which, at the most, is elevated 400 feet above<lb break="yes"/>the level of Calpi. Naguangachi signifies<lb break="yes"/>the northern lower end. The whole emi-<lb break="no"/>nence reminds one,&#x2014;through its horse-shoe<lb break="yes"/>form, not in regard to its rock,&#x2014;of the some-<lb break="no"/>what higher hill Javirac (el Panecillo de<lb break="yes" />Quito), which rises isolated at the foot of the<lb break="yes"/>volcano Pichincha, in the plain of Turu-<lb break="no"/>bamba, and which, in La Condamine&#x2019;s, or<lb break="yes"/>rather Morainville&#x2019;s map, is drawn errone-<lb break="no"/>ously as a perfect cone. According to the<lb break="yes"/>tradition of the natives, and according to old<lb break="yes"/>MSS. which the Cacike or Apu of Lican (the<lb break="yes" />Conchocandi) possessed, the volcanic erup-<lb break="no"/>tion of the Yana-Urcu occurred immediately<lb break="yes"/>after the death of the Inca Tupa-Yupanqui:<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;thus probably in the middle of the 15th<lb break="yes"/>century. Tradition says that a fire-ball, or<lb break="yes"/>indeed a star, fell from heaven and set on fire<lb break="yes"/>the mountain. Such fables, connecting the<lb break="yes" />fall of a&#x00EB;rolites with eruptions are also spread<lb break="yes" />among the tribes of Mexico. The rock of<lb break="yes"/>the Yana-Urcu is a porous, dark clove-co-<lb break="no"/>loured, often entirely black slaggy mass,<lb break="yes"/>which may be easily confounded with porous<lb break="yes"/>basalt. Olivin is entirely wanting in it, the<lb break="yes"/>white, sparingly distributed crystals it con-<lb break="no" />tains, are throughout small and probably<lb break="yes"/>Labrador. Here and there, I saw a sprink-<lb break="no"/>ling of iron-pyrites. The whole belongs pro-<lb break="no"/>bably to the black augite-porphyry, as well<lb break="yes"/>as the whole formation of Chimborazo, to<lb break="yes" />which I am not disposed to give the name<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="92" facs="#f0004"/> trachyte, since it contains ro felspar, (with<lb break="yes"/>some albite), such as is contained in our<lb break="yes" />trachyte of the Siebengebirge near Bonn.<lb break="yes"/>The slaggy masses of the Yana-Urcu altered<lb break="yes"/>by a very active fire, are indeed extremely<lb break="yes"/>light, but proper pumice-stone has not been<lb break="yes"/>thrown out there. The eruption has taken<lb break="yes" />place through a grey, irregularly stratified<lb break="yes"/>mass of dolerite, which here forms the table-<lb break="no"/>land, and resembles the rock of Penipe (at<lb break="yes"/>the foot of the volcano of Tungurahua) where<lb break="yes"/>syenite and mica-slate containing garnets,<lb break="yes"/>have been broken through. On the eastern<lb break="yes" />side of the Yana-Urcu, or rather at the foot<lb break="yes"/>of the hill towards Lican, the natives con-<lb break="no"/>ducted us to a projecting rock, an opening in<lb break="yes"/>which resembled the mouth of a forsaken<lb break="yes"/>gallery. Here, as well as at the distance of<lb break="yes"/>ten feet, there is heard a violent subterranean<lb break="yes"/>noise, which is accompanied by a current of<lb break="yes" />air, or subterranean wind. The current of<lb break="yes"/>air is much too weak to admit of the noise<lb break="yes"/>being attributed to it. The noise certainly<lb break="yes"/>arises from a subterranean brook, which is<lb break="yes"/>precipitated downwards into a deep hollow,<lb break="yes" />and through its fall occasions a motion in<lb break="yes"/>the air. A monk, the priest at Calpi, had,<lb break="yes"/>with the same idea, some time before, conti-<lb break="no"/>nued on the gallery at an open fissure to pro-<lb break="no"/>cure water for his village. The hardness of<lb break="yes"/>the black augite rock probably interrupted<lb break="yes" />the work. Chimborazo, notwithstanding its<lb break="yes"/>enormous mass of snow, sends down into the<lb break="yes"/>table-land such insignificant brooks of water,<lb break="yes"/>that it may be presumed the greater part of<lb break="yes"/>its water flows through clefts to the interior.<lb break="yes"/>In the village of Calpi itself also, there was<lb break="yes"/>formerly heard a great noise in a house that had<lb break="yes"/>no cellar. Before the celebrated earthquake<lb break="yes" />of the 4th of February, 1797, there sprang<lb break="yes"/>forth a brook in the south-west of the village,<lb break="yes"/>at a deeper point. Many Indians considered<lb break="yes"/>this brook as a part of the water that flows<lb break="yes"/>under the Yana-Urcu. But since the great<lb break="yes"/>earthquake, this brook has again disappeared.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#c">(<hi rendition="#i">To be continued.</hi>)</hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="134" facs="#f0005"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#k">humboldt&#x2019;s two attempts to ascend<lb break="yes" />chimborazo.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <div n="3">
                        <head>(<hi rendition="#i">Continued from. page</hi> 92.)</head>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rendition="#k">After</hi> we had passed the night at Calpi,<lb break="yes"/>which, according to my barometrical mea-<lb break="no" />surement, lies 9,720 feet (1,620 toises) above<lb break="yes"/>the sea, we began, on the morning of the<lb break="yes"/>23rd, our proper expedition up Chimborazo.<lb break="yes"/>We attempted to ascend the mountain on the<lb break="yes"/>SS.E. side, and the Indians who were to<lb break="yes"/>attend us as guides, but of whom but a few<lb break="yes"/>had ever reached the limit of perpetual snow,<lb break="yes"/>gave this course the preference. We found<lb break="yes"/>Chimborazo surrounded with great plains,<lb break="yes" />which rise, step-like, one above the other.<lb break="yes"/>Proceeding first through the Llanos de Luisa,<lb break="yes"/>then after rather a gradual ascent of scarcely<lb break="yes"/>5,000 feet in length, we reached the table<lb break="yes"/>land (Llano) of Sisgun. The first step<lb break="yes"/>(stufe) is at a height of 10,200 feet, the<lb break="yes"/>second 11,700. These grass grown plains<lb break="yes" />thus equal in elevation, respectively, the<lb break="yes"/>highest summit of the Pyrenees (Peak Ne-<lb break="no"/>thou) and the summit of the peak of Tene-<lb break="no"/>riffe. The perfect horizontality of these<lb break="yes"/>tahle-lands allows us to infer the long conti-<lb break="no"/>nuance of stagnant water. The traveller<lb break="yes"/>imagines he sees before him the bottom of a<lb break="yes"/>lake. On the acclivity of the Swiss Alps,<lb break="yes"/>there is sometimes observed this phenomenon<lb break="yes"/>of small step-like plains, lying one above the<lb break="yes"/>other, which, like the emptied basins of<lb break="yes" />alpine lakes, are united by narrow open<lb break="yes"/>passes. The widely extended grass lands<lb break="yes"/>(los Pajonales) are on Chimborazo, as every<lb break="yes"/>
                            <pb n="135" facs="#f0006"/> @here around the high summits of the<lb break="yes"/>@ndes, so monotonous that the family of the<lb break="yes"/>@asses (species of Paspalum, Andropogon,<lb break="yes" />@romus, Dejeuxia, Stipa) are seldom inter-<lb break="no"/>@upted by dicotyledonous plants. There pre-<lb break="no"/>@ails almost the heathy scenery which I have<lb break="yes"/>@een in the barren part of Northern Asia.<lb break="yes"/>The flora of Chimborazo, in general, appeared<lb break="yes"/>to us less rich than that of the other snow<lb break="yes"/>mountains which surround the city of Quito.<lb break="yes"/>But a few Calceolari&#x00E6;, Composit&#x00E6;, (Bidens,<lb break="yes"/>Eupatorium, Dumerilia paniculata, Werne-<lb break="no"/>ria nubigena) and Gentian&#x00E6;, among which<lb break="yes"/>the beautiful Gentiana cernua shining forth<lb break="yes"/>with purple flowers,&#x2014;rear themselves on the<lb break="yes"/>high plain of Sisgun, between the associated<lb break="yes"/>grasses. These belong, for the most part, to<lb break="yes"/>the ge@era of Northern Europe. The tem-<lb break="no" />@ture of the air generally prevailing in<lb break="yes"/>these regions of alpine grasses, elevated res-<lb break="no"/>pectively 1,600 and 2,000 toises, fluctuates<lb break="yes"/>by day between 4° and 16° C. (39°.2 and<lb break="yes"/>60°.8 F.) by night between 0° and 10° (32°<lb break="yes"/>and 50° F.). The mean temperature of the<lb break="yes" />whole year, according to my collective obser-<lb break="no"/>vations in the neighbourhood of the Equator,<lb break="yes"/>appears to be about 9°<note place="foot" n="*">All temperatures mentioned in this paper are<lb break="yes"/>expressed in degrees of the centigrade thermometer.<lb break="yes"/>(The equivalent degree of Fahrenheit has been since<lb break="yes"/>added.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Tr.</hi>)</note> (48°.2 F.). In the<lb break="yes"/>flat lands of the Temperate Zone, this is the<lb break="yes"/>mean temperature of the north of Germany,<lb break="yes"/>for example, of Luneburg (Lat. 53° 15&#x2032;); but<lb break="yes"/>here the distribution of heat among the dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent months (the most important element<lb break="yes" />in determining the character of the vegeta-<lb break="no"/>tion of a country) is so unequal, that in<lb break="yes"/>February, the mean heat is&#x2014;1°.8 (+28°.76<lb break="yes"/>F.), in July + 18° (+64°.4 F.)</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>My plan was to perform a trigonometrical<lb break="yes"/>operation in the beautiful perfectly level grass<lb break="yes"/>land of Sisgun. I had made arrangements<lb break="yes"/>for measuring a base line here. The angles<lb break="yes"/>of altitude would have proved very conside-<lb break="no"/>rable in such proximity to the summit of<lb break="yes"/>Chimborazo. There remained yet a perpen-<lb break="no" />dicular height of less than 8,400 feet (the<lb break="yes"/>height of the Canigou in the Pyrenees) to<lb break="yes"/>determine. Yet with the enormous masses<lb break="yes"/>of single mountains in the chain of the<lb break="yes"/>Andes, every determination of the height<lb break="yes"/>above the sea is compounded of a barometrical<lb break="yes"/>and trigonometrical observation. I had taken<lb break="yes"/>with me the sextant and other instruments of<lb break="yes"/>measurement in vain. The summit of Chim.<lb break="yes" />borazo remained densely veiled in mist.<lb break="yes"/>From the high plain of Sisgun the ascent is<lb break="yes"/>tolerably steep as far as the little alpine lake<lb break="yes"/>of Yana-Coche. Thus far I had remained<lb break="yes"/>on the mule, having from time to time<lb break="yes"/>alighted with my travelling companion, M.<lb break="yes"/>Bonpland, merely to collect plants. Yana-<lb break="no" />Coche does not deserve the name of a lake.<lb break="yes"/>It is a circular basin of scarcely 130 feet in<lb break="yes"/>diameter. The sky became more and more<lb break="yes"/>obscured; but between and over the mist-<lb break="no"/>strata there still lay scattered single groups<lb break="yes"/>of clouds. The summit of Chimborazo was<lb break="yes"/>visible for a few moments only at a time.<lb break="yes"/>Much snow having fallen during the prece-<lb break="no" />ding night, I left the mule where we found<lb break="yes"/>the lower border of this newly-fallen snow, a<lb break="yes"/>border which must not be confounded with<lb break="yes"/>the limit of perpetual snow. The barometer<lb break="yes"/>showed that we had only now attained the<lb break="yes"/>height of 13,500 feet. On other mountains,<lb break="yes"/>likewise near to the equator, I have seen snow<lb break="yes"/>fall at the height of 11,200 feet, but not<lb break="yes"/>lower. My companion rode as far as the<lb break="yes" />line of perpetual snow, <hi rendition="#i">i.e.</hi> to the height of<lb break="yes"/>Mont Blanc; which mountain, as is known,<lb break="yes"/>would not in this latitude (1° 27&#x2032; south)<lb break="yes"/>always be covered with snow. The horses<lb break="yes" />and mules remained there to await our<lb break="yes"/>return.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>A hundred and fifty toises above the little<lb break="yes"/>basin of Yana-Coche, we saw at length<lb break="yes"/>naked rock. Hitherto the grass-land had<lb break="yes"/>withdrawn the ground from any geognostical<lb break="yes"/>examination. Great walls of rocks, extend-<lb break="no"/>ing from the N.E. towards the S.W., in part<lb break="yes"/>cleft into misshapen columns, reared them-<lb break="no"/>selves out of the eternal snow,&#x2014;a brownish-<lb break="no"/>black augite rock shining like pitch-stone<lb break="yes"/>porphyry. The columns were very thin,<lb break="yes" />perhaps fifty to sixty feet in height, almost<lb break="yes"/>like the trachyte columns of Table-Umca on<lb break="yes"/>the volcano Pichincha. One group stood<lb break="yes"/>alone, and reminded one of masts and stems<lb break="yes"/>of trees. The steep walls led us through the<lb break="yes"/>snow region to a narrow ridge of rock ex-<lb break="no"/>tending towards the summit by which alone<lb break="yes" />it was possible for us to advance any farther;<lb break="yes"/>for the snow was then so soft that one<lb break="yes"/>scarcely dared to tread upon its surface. The<lb break="yes"/>ridge consisted of very weathered crumbling<lb break="yes"/>rock. It was often vesicular like a basaltic-<lb break="no"/>amygdaloid.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>The path became more and more narrow<lb break="yes"/>and steep. The natives forsook us all but<lb break="yes"/>one at the height of 15,600 feet. All entrea-<lb break="no"/>ties and threats were unavailing. The In-<lb break="no"/>dians maintained that they suffered more<lb break="yes"/>than we did from breathlessness. We re-<lb break="no" />mained alone, Bonpland,&#x2014;our amiable friend<lb break="yes"/>the younger son of the Marquis of Selvalegre,<lb break="yes"/>Carlos Montufar, who, in the subsequent<lb break="yes"/>struggle for freedom, was shot, (at the com-<lb break="no"/>mand of General Morillo),&#x2014;a Mestize from<lb break="yes"/>the neighbouring village of San Juan,&#x2014;and<lb break="yes"/>myself. We attained with great exertion<lb break="yes"/>and endurance, a greater height than we had<lb break="yes"/>dared hope to reach, as we were almost en-<lb break="no"/>tirely wrapped in mist. The ridge (very sig-<lb break="no"/>nificantly called, in Spanish, Cuchilla, as it<lb break="yes"/>were the knife-back) was in many places<lb break="yes" />only eight to ten inches broad. On the left<lb break="yes"/>the precipice was concealed by snow, the sur-<lb break="no"/>face of the latter seeming glazed with frost.<lb break="yes"/>
                            <pb n="136" facs="#f0007"/> The thin icy mirror-like surface had an incli-<lb break="no"/>nation of about 30°. On the right our view<lb break="yes"/>sank shuddering 800 or 1,000 feet into an<lb break="yes"/>abyss out of which projected, perpendicularly,<lb break="yes"/>snowless masses of rock. We held the body<lb break="yes"/>continually inclined towards this side, for the<lb break="yes"/>precipice upon the left seemed still more<lb break="yes"/>threatening, because there no chance pre-<lb break="no" />sented itself of grasping the toothed rock,<lb break="yes"/>and because, further, the thin ice-crust offered<lb break="yes"/>no security against sinking in the loose snow.<lb break="yes"/>Only extremely light porous bits of dolerite<lb break="yes"/>could we roll down this crust of ice; and the<lb break="yes"/>inclined plane of snow was so extended that<lb break="yes"/>we lost sight of the stones thus rolled down<lb break="yes"/>before they came to rest. The absence of<lb break="yes" />snow, as well upon the ridge along which we<lb break="yes"/>ascended, as upon the rocks on our right<lb break="yes"/>hand towards the east, cannot be ascribed so<lb break="yes"/>much to the steepness of the masses, and to<lb break="yes"/>the gales of wind, as to open clefts, which<lb break="yes"/>breathe out warm air from deeper situated<lb break="yes"/>beds. We soon found our further ascent<lb break="yes" />more difficult from the increase of the crum-<lb break="no"/>bling nature of the rock. At single and very<lb break="yes"/>steep <hi rendition="#i">échélons</hi> it was necessary to apply at<lb break="yes"/>the same time the hands and feet, as is so<lb break="yes"/>usual in all alpine journeys. As the rock<lb break="yes"/>was very keenly angular, we were painfully<lb break="yes"/>hurt, especially in the hands. Leopold Von<lb break="yes"/>Buch and I suffered very much in this man-<lb break="no"/>ner near the crater of the Peak of Teneriffe,<lb break="yes"/>which abounds in obsidian. I had had<lb break="yes" />besides (if it be permitted a traveller to men-<lb break="no"/>tion such unimportant particulars) for several<lb break="yes"/>weeks a sore in the foot, occasioned by the<lb break="yes"/>accumulations of Niguas<note place="foot" n="*">The Sand-flea, the Chique of the French colo-<lb break="no"/>nists of the West Indies, au insect that introduces<lb break="yes"/>itself under the human skin, and, as the ovary of the<lb break="yes"/>impregnated female considerably enlarges, inflam-<lb break="no"/>mation is excited.</note> (<hi rendition="#i">Pulex pene-<lb break="no"/>trans</hi>), and much increased by fine dust of<lb break="yes"/>pumice-stone during measurements in Llano<lb break="yes"/>de Tapia. The little adhesion of the rocks<lb break="yes"/>upon the ridge now rendered greater caution<lb break="yes"/>necessary, as many masses which we sup-<lb break="no" />posed firm lay loose and covered with sand,<lb break="yes"/>We proceeded one after the other, and so<lb break="yes"/>much the more slowly, as it was needful to<lb break="yes"/>try the places which seemed uncertain.<lb break="yes"/>Happily the attempt to reach the summit of<lb break="yes"/>Chimborazo was the last of our mountain<lb break="yes"/>journeys in South America; hence previous<lb break="yes"/>experience guided us, and gave us more con-<lb break="no"/>fidence in our powers. It is a peculiar cha-<lb break="no"/>racter of all excursions in the Andes, that<lb break="yes"/>above the snow-line white people find them-<lb break="no"/>selves in the most perilous situations, always<lb break="yes"/>without guides, indeed without any know-<lb break="no" />ledge of localities.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>We could see the summit no longer, even<lb break="yes"/>for a moment only at a time, and were hence<lb break="yes"/>doubly curious to know, how much higher it<lb break="yes"/>remained for us to ascend. We examined<lb break="yes"/>the barometer at a point where the breadth<lb break="yes"/>of the ridge permitted of two persons stand-<lb break="no"/>ing conveniently together. We were now at<lb break="yes" />an elevation of 17,300 feet; thus scarcely<lb break="yes"/>two hundred feet higher than we had bee@<lb break="yes"/>two months before, when climbing a similar<lb break="yes"/>ridge on the Antisana. It is with the deter-<lb break="no"/>mining of heights in climbing mountains, as<lb break="yes"/>with the determining of temperature in the<lb break="yes"/>heat of summer. One finds with vexation<lb break="yes" />the thermometer not so high, the barometer<lb break="yes"/>not so low, as one expected. As the air, not-<lb break="no"/>withstanding the height, was quite saturated<lb break="yes"/>with moisture, we now found the loose rock<lb break="yes"/>and the sand that filled its interstices ex-<lb break="no"/>tremely wet. The air was still 2° 8&#x2032; (37° 04&#x2032;<lb break="yes"/>Fahr.) Shortly before, we had in a dry place<lb break="yes"/>been able to bury the thermometer three<lb break="yes"/>inches deep in the sand. It indleated<lb break="yes"/>+ 5° 8&#x2032; (+42° 44&#x2032; Fahr.) The result of<lb break="yes"/>this observation, which was made at the<lb break="yes"/>height of about 2,860 toises, is very remark-<lb break="no"/>able, for 400 toises lower down, at the limit<lb break="yes"/>of perpetual snow, the mean heat of the at-<lb break="no"/>mosphere is, according to many observations,<lb break="yes"/>carefully collected by Boussingault and my-<lb break="no"/>self, only + 1°6&#x2032; (34° 88&#x2032; Fahr.) The tem-<lb break="no"/>perature of earth (sand) at +5° 8&#x2032; (42° 44&#x2032;<lb break="yes"/>Fahr.) must therefore be ascribed to the sub-<lb break="no"/>terranean heat of the dolerite mountain; I<lb break="yes"/>do not say to the whole mass, but to the cur-<lb break="no"/>rent of air ascending from the interior.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rendition="#c">(<hi rendition="#i">To be continued.</hi>)</hi>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="163" facs="#f0008"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#k">two attempts to ascend chimborazo.<lb break="yes"/>by alexander von humboldt.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <div n="3">
                        <head>(<hi rendition="#i">Continued from page</hi> 136.)</head>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rendition="#k">After</hi> an hour of cautious climbing, the<lb break="yes"/>ridge of rock became less steep; but, alas!<lb break="yes"/>the mist remained as thick as ever. We<lb break="yes" />now began gradually to suffer from great<lb break="yes"/>nausea. The tendency to vomiting was com-<lb break="no"/>bined with some giddiness; and much more<lb break="yes"/>troublesome than the difficulty of breathing.<lb break="yes"/>A coloured man (a mestize of San Juan), not<lb break="yes"/>from selfish motives, but merely out of good<lb break="yes"/>nature, had been unwilling to forsake us.<lb break="yes"/>He was a poor, vigorous peasant, and suffered<lb break="yes"/>more than we did. We had h&#x00E6;morrhage<lb break="yes"/>from the gums and lips. The conjunctiva of<lb break="yes"/>the eyes, likewise, was, in all, gorged with<lb break="yes"/>blood. These symptoms of extravasation in<lb break="yes"/>the eyes, and of oozing from the lips and<lb break="yes"/>gums, did not in the least disquiet us, as we<lb break="yes"/>had repeatedly experienced them before. In<lb break="yes"/>Europe, M. Zumstein began to experience<lb break="yes" />h&#x00E6;morrhage at a much lower elevation on<lb break="yes"/>Mont Rosa. The Spanish warriors during<lb break="yes"/>the conquest of the equinoctial region of<lb break="yes"/>America (during the Conquista), did not<lb break="yes"/>ascend above the snow line, thus but little<lb break="yes"/>above the elevation of Mont Blanc, and yet<lb break="yes"/>Acosta, in his <hi rendition="#i">Historia Natural de las In-<lb break="no"/>dias,</hi>&#x2014;a kind of physical geography, which<lb break="yes"/>may be called a master-piece of the 16th<lb break="yes"/>century,&#x2014;speaks circumstantially of &#x201C;Nau-<lb break="no"/>sea and Spasm of the Stomach,&#x201D; as painful<lb break="yes"/>symptoms of the <hi rendition="#i" >mountain-sickness,</hi> which<lb break="yes"/>in these respects is analogous to <hi rendition="#i">sea-sickness.</hi>
                            <lb break="yes"/>On the volcano of Pichincha I once felt,<lb break="yes" />without experiencing h&#x00E6;morrhage, so violent<lb break="yes"/>an affection of the stomach, accompanied by<lb break="yes"/>giddiness, that I was found senseless on the<lb break="yes"/>ground, just as I left my companions on a<lb break="yes"/>wall of rock above the defile of Verde-Cucha,<lb break="yes"/>in order to perform some electrical experi-<lb break="no"/>ments on a perfectly open space. The<lb break="yes"/>height was inconsiderable, below 13,800 feet.<lb break="yes"/>But on the Antisana, at the considerable<lb break="yes" />elevation of 17,220 feet, our young travelling<lb break="yes" />companion, Don Carlos Montufar, bled freely<lb break="yes"/>from the lips. All of these phenomena vary<lb break="yes"/>according to age, constitution, the tenderness<lb break="yes"/>of the skin, the preceding exertions of the<lb break="yes"/>muscular powers; yet for single individuals<lb break="yes"/>they are a kind of measure of the atmospheric<lb break="yes"/>tenuity, and of the absolute elevation reached.<lb break="yes"/>According to my observations in the Cordil-<lb break="no"/>leras, these symptoms manifest themselves in<lb break="yes"/>white people, with a mercurial column between<lb break="yes"/>14 inches,&#x2014;and 15 inches 10 lines. It is<lb break="yes"/>known that the estimates regarding heights,<lb break="yes"/>which &#x00E6;ronauts maintain that they have<lb break="yes"/>reached, generally deserve but little credit,<lb break="yes"/>and if a more certain and extremely accurate<lb break="yes"/>observer, M. Gay Lussac, who, on the 16th<lb break="yes"/>
                            <pb n="164" facs="#f0009"/> of September, 1804, reached the vast height<lb break="yes"/>of 21,600 feet (thus between the height of<lb break="yes"/>Chimborazo and Illimani), experienced no<lb break="yes" />h&#x00E6;morrhage, this is perhaps to be ascribed to<lb break="yes" />the absence of muscular exertion. According<lb break="yes"/>to the present condition of eudiometry, the<lb break="yes"/>air of those lofty regions appear to contain in<lb break="yes"/>proportion as much oxygen as that of lower<lb break="yes"/>heights; but since in that attenuated air&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>the barometric pressure only one half of that<lb break="yes"/>to which we are generally exposed&#x2014;the blood<lb break="yes"/>in each act of respiration takes up a smaller<lb break="yes"/>quantity of oxygen, it is certainly conceivable<lb break="yes"/>that a general feeling of weakness should<lb break="yes"/>take place. Why this asthenie as in faint-<lb break="no"/>ing, should excite nausea and a tendency to<lb break="yes"/>vomiting, it is not our purpose to determine;<lb break="yes"/>as little is it here to be proved, that the<lb break="yes"/>oozing of blood (the h&#x00E6;morrhage from the<lb break="yes"/>lips, gums, and eyes), which also has not<lb break="yes"/>been experienced by all, at such great<lb break="yes" />heights,&#x2014;can by no means be satisfactorily<lb break="yes" />explained by the absence of a &#x201C;mechanical<lb break="yes" />counterpressure&#x201D; on the vascular system;<lb break="yes"/>our attention should rather be engaged in<lb break="yes"/>examining the probability of the influence of<lb break="yes"/>a diminished atmospheric pressure, during<lb break="yes"/>fatigue, on the moving of the legs in regions<lb break="yes"/>of very attenuated air; for, according to the<lb break="yes"/>memorable discovery of two spirited inquirers,<lb break="yes"/>Wilhelm and Edward Weber,<note place="foot" n="*">
                                <hi rendition="#i">Mochanik der Merschlichen Gehwerkzeuge.</hi> 1836.<lb break="yes"/>§ 64. S. 147&#x00B7;160. More recent experiments of the<lb break="yes"/>brothers Weber, at Berlin, have fully confirmed the<lb break="yes"/>position, that the leg is carried in the acetabulum by<lb break="yes"/>the pressure of the atmosphere.</note> the hovering<lb break="yes"/>leg, hanging from the trunk, is held and<lb break="yes"/>carried mercly by the pressure of the atmos-<lb break="no"/>phere.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>The layers of mist that prevented our see-<lb break="no"/>ing distant objects, appeared suddenly, not-<lb break="no"/>withstanding the total stillnes of the air,<lb break="yes"/>perhaps through electrical processes, to be<lb break="yes"/>broken up. We recognised once more, and<lb break="yes"/>indeed immediately before us, the dome-<lb break="no"/>shaped summit of Chimborazo. It was an<lb break="yes" />earnest, momentous gaze. The hope to<lb break="yes"/>reach this summit animated our powers anew.<lb break="yes"/>The ridge of rock, only here and there covered<lb break="yes"/>with thin flakes of snow, became somewhat<lb break="yes"/>broader. We hastened onwards with certain<lb break="yes"/>steps, when all at once a ravine of some<lb break="yes"/>400 feet in depth, and 50 broad, set an insur-<lb break="no"/>mountable barrier to our undertaking. We<lb break="yes" />saw distinctly beyond the abyss, our ridge of<lb break="yes"/>rock continued forward in the same direction;<lb break="yes"/>yet I doubt its leading to the summit itself.<lb break="yes"/>The chasm was not to be gone round. On<lb break="yes"/>the Antisana. M. Bonpland indeed had found<lb break="yes"/>it possible, after a very cold night, to proceed<lb break="yes"/>for a considerable length through the snow.<lb break="yes"/>We durst not venture the attempt, because of<lb break="yes"/>the looseness of the mass, and the form of<lb break="yes"/>the precipice rendered climbing down impos-<lb break="no"/>sible. It was one o&#x2019;clock in the afternoon.<lb break="yes"/>We set up with much care the baromeler<lb break="yes" />It indicated 13 inches 11.2&#x00B7;10 lines. The<lb break="yes" />temperature of the air was now&#x2014;1° 6&#x2032; (+<lb break="yes" />29° 12&#x2032; F.), but after several years&#x2019; stay in<lb break="yes"/>the hottest regions of the Tropics, this small<lb break="yes"/>degree of cold benumbed us. Besides, our<lb break="yes" />boots were thoroughly soaked with snow@<lb break="yes"/>water, for the sand that covered here and<lb break="yes"/>there the ridge was mixed with old snow.<lb break="yes"/>According to La Place&#x2019;s barometrical formula,<lb break="yes"/>we had reached a height of 3,016 toises, or<lb break="yes"/>more precisely 18,097 Paris feet. If La<lb break="yes"/>Condamine&#x2019;s estimate of the height of Chim-<lb break="no"/>borazo, as noted on the stone-table of the<lb break="yes"/>Jesuit&#x2019;s College in Quito, be correct, there<lb break="yes"/>failed us yet of the summit of the mountain<lb break="yes"/>1,224 feet, or thrice the height of St. Peter&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>church at Rome.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>La Condamine and Bouguer say explicitly,<lb break="yes"/>that they attained, on Chimborazo, the<lb break="yes"/>height of 2,400 toises only; but they glory<lb break="yes"/>in having seen on the Corazon,&#x2014;one of the<lb break="yes"/>most picturesque snow-mountains (Nevados)<lb break="yes"/>in the immediate neigh bourhood of Quita,&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>the barometer at 15 inches 10 lines. They<lb break="yes"/>say this is &#x201C;a lower state than any human<lb break="yes"/>being has hitherto ever been in a situation to<lb break="yes"/>observe.&#x201D; At the above described point on<lb break="yes"/>Chimborazo, the pressure of the air was<lb break="yes"/>about two inches less; less also than at the<lb break="yes"/>highest point reached in 1818, sixteen years<lb break="yes"/>afterwards, by Captain Gerard, on the Tarhi-<lb break="no"/>gang, in the Himmalayan Mountains. I<lb break="yes" />have been exposed in a diving-bell in Eng-<lb break="no"/>land to an air-pressure of forty-five inches,<lb break="yes"/>for almost an hour together. The flexibility<lb break="yes"/>of the human organism consequently endures<lb break="yes"/>changes in the state of the barometer,<lb break="yes"/>amounting to thirty-one inches. Yet the<lb break="yes"/>physical constitution of the human race<lb break="yes"/>might be remarkably changed, if great cosmi-<lb break="no"/>cal causes were to make permanent such ex-<lb break="no" />tremes in atmospheric tenuity and condensa-<lb break="no"/>tion.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>We remained but a short time in this<lb break="yes"/>mournful solitude, being soon again entirely<lb break="yes"/>veiled in mist. The humid air was not<lb break="yes"/>thereby set in motion. No fixed direction<lb break="yes"/>was to be observed in single groups of the<lb break="yes"/>denser particles of vapour; I therefore cannot<lb break="yes"/>say whether at this elevation the west wind<lb break="yes"/>blows, opposing the Tropical monsoon. We<lb break="yes" />saw no longer the summit of Chimborazo,<lb break="yes"/>none of the neighbouring snow-mountains,<lb break="yes"/>still less the table-lands of Quito. We were<lb break="yes"/>as though isolated in a ball of air. Some<lb break="yes"/>stone-lichens only had followed us above the<lb break="yes"/>line of perpetual snow. The last cryptoga-<lb break="no"/>mic plants which I collected were Lecidea<lb break="yes" />atrovirens (Lichen geographicus, <hi rendition="#i">Web.</hi>), and<lb break="yes"/>a Gyrophora of <hi rendition="#i">Acharius,</hi> a new species<lb break="yes"/>(Gyrophora rugosa), at about the height of<lb break="yes"/>2,820 toises. The last moss, Grimmia longi-<lb break="no"/>rostris, grew 400 toises lower down. A<lb break="yes" />butterfly (sphinx) was caught by M. Bon-<lb break="no"/>
                            <pb n="165" facs="#f0010"/> @pland at the height of 15,000 feet; we saw a<lb break="yes"/>@y 1,600 feet higher. The following facts<lb break="yes"/>@afford the most striking proof that these ani-<lb break="no"/>@mals are involuntarily carried up into those<lb break="yes"/>@upper regions by the current of air which<lb break="yes"/>@rises from the warmed plains. As Boussin-<lb break="no"/>@gault ascended the Silla de Caracas, to repeat<lb break="yes"/>@my measurement of the mountain, he saw<lb break="yes" />@from time to time, at the height of 8,000 feet,<lb break="yes"/>@at noon, as the west wind blew, whitish<lb break="yes"/>@bodies rapidly pass through the air, which<lb break="yes"/>@he at first took for soaring birds with white<lb break="yes"/>@plumage, that reflected the sun&#x2019;s rays.<lb break="yes"/>These bodies rose with great rapidity out of<lb break="yes"/>the valley of Caracas, and surmounting the<lb break="yes"/>summit of Silla, took a north-east direction,<lb break="yes"/>and reached probably the sea. Some fell<lb break="yes" />upon the southern acclivity of the Silla; they<lb break="yes"/>were grass-halms, that had reflected the sun&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>rays. Boussingault sent me some of these,<lb break="yes"/>which still had ears, in a letter to Paris,<lb break="yes"/>where my friend and fellow-labourer, Kunth,<lb break="yes"/>instantly recognised them as the Wilfa tena-<lb break="no"/>cissima, which grows in the valley of Cara-<lb break="no"/>cas, and which he has described in our work,<lb break="yes"/>
                            <hi rendition="#i">Nova Genera et Species Plantarum Ame-<lb break="no" />ric&#x00E6; &#x00C6;quinoctialis.</hi> I must remark, that<lb break="yes"/>we met with no condor on Chimborazo, that<lb break="yes"/>powerful vulture, which is so frequent on the<lb break="yes"/>Antisana and Pichincha, and which shows<lb break="yes" />great confidence from its ignorance of man.<lb break="yes"/>The condor loves pure air, in order the easier<lb break="yes"/>from on high to recognise its prey or its food,<lb break="yes"/>for it gives dead animals the preference.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>As the weather became more and more<lb break="yes"/>cloudy, we hastened down upon the same<lb break="yes"/>ledge of rock, that had favoured our ascent.<lb break="yes"/>Cantion, however, on account of the uncer-<lb break="no"/>tainty of the steps, was more necessary than<lb break="yes"/>in climbing up. We tarried only just to col-<lb break="no"/>lect fragments of rock. We foresaw that in<lb break="yes"/>Europe &#x201C;a little bit of Chimborazo&#x201D; would<lb break="yes"/>be asked for. At that time, no mountain<lb break="yes"/>rock in any part of South America had been<lb break="yes"/>named; the rocks of all the high summits of<lb break="yes"/>the Andes were called granite. As we were<lb break="yes"/>at the height of about 17,400 feet, it began<lb break="yes"/>to hail violently. The hailstones were<lb break="yes" />opaque, and milk-white, with concentric<lb break="yes"/>layers, some appeared considerably flattened<lb break="yes"/>by rotation, twenty minutes before we reached<lb break="yes"/>the lower limit of perpetual snow, the hail<lb break="yes"/>was replaced by snow. The flakes were so<lb break="yes"/>dense, that the snow soon covered the ridge<lb break="yes"/>@f rock many inches deep; we should have<lb break="yes" />been brought into great danger, had the snow<lb break="yes"/>surprised us at the height of 18,000 feet. At<lb break="yes"/>@ few minutes after two o&#x2019;clock, we reached<lb break="yes"/>the point where our mules were standing.<lb break="yes"/>The natives that remained behind, had been<lb break="yes"/>@ery apprehensive for our safety.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 