<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-20" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. Validation.<note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="12" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#b">AN ACCOUNT OF TWO ATTEMPTS TO ASCEND<lb/>CHIMBORAZO.</hi><lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">By Alexander von Humboldt.</hi></hi>
                </head>
                <lb/>
                <div n="2">
                    <p>
                        [The following interesting narrative is abridged from an excerpt from the un-<lb/>published Journal of this distinguished traveller, communicated to the Edinburgh<lb/>Philosophical Journal.]</p> 
                    <p>The highest mountain-summits of both continents,&#x2014;in the old continent,<lb/>Dhawalagiri (White Mountain) and the Jawahir; in the new, the Sorata and the<lb/>Illimani,&#x2014;remain unsearched by man. The highest point of the earth&#x2019;s surface<lb/>attained, lies in South America on the south-east side of Chimborazo. There<lb/>travellers have reached the height of nearly 18,500 Paris feet<note place="foot" n="*">One French foot is = 1.07892, or about 1<formula notation="TeX">\left( \frac{1}{10} \right)</formula> English.&#x2014;Tr.</note>
                        &#x2014;viz. in June<lb/>1802, 3016 toises,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">A toise is = 1.94904 metres, or 6.39459 English feet.&#x2014;Tr.</note>
                        in December 1831, 3080 toises, above the level of the sea.<lb/>Barometrical measurements have thus been made, in the chain of the Andes<lb/>3720 (Paris) feet above the level of the summit of Mont Blanc. The height of<lb/>Mont Blanc is in relation to that of the Cordilleras so inconsiderable, that in the<lb/>latter, there are much-frequented passes that are higher, indeed, the upper part<lb/>of the great city of Potosi has an elevation only 323 toises inferior to that of the<lb/>summit of Mont Blanc. I have thought it needful to premise these numerical<lb/>statements in order to present to the imagination definite points of comparison<lb/>for the hypsometric, as it were plastic, contemplation of the surface of the earth.</p>
                    <p>On the 22nd of June 1799, I was in the crater of the Peak of Teneriffe. Three<lb/>years afterwards, almost on the same day (the 23d June 1802), I reached a point<lb/>6700 feet higher, near the summit of Chimborazo. After a long delay in the ta-<lb/>ble-land of Quito, one of the most wonderful and picturesque regions of the<lb/>earth, we undertook the journey towards the forests of the Peruvian bark trees<lb/>of Loxa, the upper course of the river Amazons, westward of the celebrated<lb/>strait (Pongo de Manseriche), and through the sandy desert along the Peruvian<lb/>coast of the South Sea towards Lima, where we were to observe the transit of<lb/>Mercury on the 9th November 1802. On a plain covered with pumice-stone,&#x2014;<lb/>where (after the fearful earthquake of 4th February 1797) the building of the<lb/>new city Riobamba was begun,&#x2014;we enjoyed for several days a splendid view of<lb/>the bell or dome-shaped summit of Chimborazo. We had the clearest weather,<lb/>favouring trigonometrical observation. By means of a large telescope, we had<lb/>thoroughly examined the snow mantle of the mountain, still 1570 toises distant,<lb/>and discovered several ridges, which, projecting like sterile black streaks, con-<lb/>verged towards the summit, and gave some hope that, upon them, a firm footing<lb/>might be obtained in the region of eternal snow. Riobamba Nuevo lies within<lb/>sight of the enormous and now indented mountain Capac-urcu, called by the<lb/>Spaniards El Altar, which (says a tradition of the natives) was once higher than<lb/>Chimborazo, and after having been many years in a state of eruption, suddenly<lb/>fell in.&#x2014;Riobamba Nuevo must not be confounded with the old Riobamba of the<lb/>great map of La Condamine and Don Pedro Maldonado. The latter city was<lb/>entirely destroyed by the great catastrophe of the 4th February 1797, which in a<lb/>few minutes destroyed 45,000 human beings.&#x2014;We were in the plain of Tapia,<lb/>from which, on the 22nd June, we began our expedition towards Chimborazo, be-<lb/>ing already 8898 Paris feet (1483 toises) above the level of the South Sea.&#x2014;<lb/>We gently ascended as far as the foot of the mountain, where, in the Indian<lb/>village Calpi, we were to pass the night. This plain is sparingly covered with<lb/>Cactus stems and Schinus molle, which resembles a weeping willow. Herds of<lb/>variegated llamas, in thousands, seek here a scanty subsistence. At so great a<lb/>height, the nightly terrestrial radiation of heat, when the sky is cloudless, proves<lb/>injurious to agriculture, through cold and frost.</p>
                    <p>Very near to Calpi, northwestward of Lican, there is in the barren table-land a<lb/>little isolated hill, the <hi rendition="#i">black mountain</hi>, Yana-Urcu, the name of which has not<lb/>been given by the French academicians, but which, in a geognostical point of<lb/>view, deserves much attention. The hill lies S.S.E. of Chimborazo, at a dis-<lb/>tance of less than three miles (15 to 1&#x00B0;), and separated from the same by the<lb/>high plain of Lusia only. If in it we do not recognise a lateral eruption of Chim-<lb/>borazo, the origin of the cone must certainly be ascribed to the subterraneous<lb/>forces which, under that mountain, have for thousands of years vainly sought an<lb/>opening. It is of later origin than the elevation of the great dome-shaped moun-<lb/>tain. The Yana Urcu forms, with the northern hill Naguangachi, a connected<lb/>eminence in the form of a horse shoe; the bow, more than a semicircle, is open<lb/>towards the east. There probably lies in the centre of the horse shoe the point<lb/>out of which the black slags have been thrown, that now lie spread far around.</p>
                    <p>We found there a funnel-shaped depression of about 120 feet in depth, in the<lb/>interior of which there is a small hill, whose height does not equal that of the<lb/>surrounding margin. Yana-Urcu probably signifies the southern culminating<lb/>point of the old crater-margin, which, at the most, is elevated 400 feet above the<lb/>level of Calpi. Naguangachi signifies the northern lower end.&#x2014;According to<lb/>the tradition of the natives, and according to old MSS which the Cacike or Apu<lb/>of Lican (the Conchocandi) possessed, the volcanic eruption of the Yana-Urcu<lb/>occurred immediately after the death of the Inca Tupa-Yupanqui&#x2014;thus proba-<lb/>bly in the middle of the fifteenth century. Tradition says that a fire-ball, or in-<lb/>deed a star, fell from heaven and set on fire the mountain. Such fables, connect-<lb/>ing the fall of aerolites with eruptions, are also spread among the tribes of Mex-<lb/>ico.&#x2014;On the eastern side of the Yana-Urcu, or rather at the foot of the hill to-<lb/>wards Lican, the natives conducted us to a projecting rock, an opening in which<lb/>resembled the mouth of a forsaken gallery. Here, as well as at the distance of<lb/>ten feet, there is heard a violent subterranean noise, which is accompanied by a<lb/>current of air, or subterranean wind. The current of air is much too weak to<lb/>admit of the noise being attributed to it. The noise certainly arises from a sub-<lb/>terranean brook, which is precipitated downwards into a deep hollow, and through<lb/>its fall occasions a motion in the air. A monk, the priest at Calpi, had, with the<lb/>same idea, some time before, continued on the gallery at an open fissure to pro-<lb/>cure water for his village. The hardness of the black augite rock probably in-<lb/>terrupted the work. Chimborazo, notwithstanding its enormous mass of snow,<lb/>sends down into the table-land such insignificant brooks of water, that it may be<lb/>presumed the greater part of its water flows through clefts to the interior. In the<lb/>village of Calpi itself also, there was formerly heard a great noise in a house<lb/>that had no cellar. Before the celebrated earthquake of the 4th February 1797,<lb/>there sprang forth a brook in the south west of the village at a deeper point.<lb/>Many Indians considered this brook as a part of the water that flows under the<lb/>Yana-Urea. But since the great earthquake, this brook has again disappeared.</p>
                    <p>After we had passed the night at Calpi, which, according to barometrical mea-<lb/>surement, lies 9720 feet (1620 toises) above the sea, we began, on the morning<lb/>of the 23d, our proper expedition up Chimborazo. We attempted to ascend the<lb/>mountain on the S.S.E. side, and the Indians who were to attend us as guides,<lb/>but of whom but a few had ever reached the limit of perpetual snow, gave this<lb/>course the preference. We found Chimborazo surrounded with great plains,<lb/>which rise, step like, one above the other. Proceeding first through the Llanos<lb/>de Lusia, then after rather a gradual ascent of scarcely 5000 feet in length, we<lb/>reached the table-land (Llano) of Sisgun. The first step (stufe) is at a height of<lb/>10,200 feet, the second 11,700. These grass-grown plains thus equal in eleva-<lb/>tion, respectively, the highest summit of the Pyrenees (Peak Nethou) and the<lb/>summit of the Peak of Teneriffe. The perfect horizontality of these table-<lb/>lands allows us to infer the long continuance of stagnant water. The traveller<lb/>imagines he sees before him the bottom of a lake. On the acclivity of the Swiss<lb/>Alps, there is sometimes observed this phenomenon of small step-like plains,<lb/>lying one above the other, which, like the emptied basins of alpine lakes, are<lb/>united by narrow open passes. The widely extended grass lands are on Chim-<lb/>borazo, as everywhere around the high summits of the Andes, so monotonous<lb/>that the family of the grasses are seldom interrupted by dicotyledonous plants.<lb/>There prevails almost the heathy scenery which I have seen in the barren part of<lb/>northern Asia. The Flora of Chimborazo, in general, appeared to us less rich<lb/>than that of the other snow mountains which surround the city of Quito. But<lb/>a few Calceolari&#x00E6;, Composit&#x00E6;, and Gentian&#x00E6;, among which the beautiful Gen-<lb/>tiana cernua shining forth with purple flowers,&#x2014;rear themselves on the high<lb/>plain of Sisgun, between the associated grasses. These belong, for the most<lb/>part, to the genera of Northern Europe. The temperature of the air generally<lb/>prevailing in these regions of alpine grasses, elevated respectively 1600 and 2000<lb/>toises, fluctuates by day between 4&#x00B0; and 16&#x00B0; C. (39&#x00B0;.2 and 60&#x00B0;.8 F.) by night<lb/>between 0&#x00B0; and 10&#x00B0; (32&#x00B0; and 50&#x00B0; F.)</p>
                    <cb/>
                    <p>My plan was to perform a trigonometrical operation in the beautiful perfectly<lb/>level grass land of Sisgun. I had made arrangements for measuring a base line<lb/>here. The angles of altitude would have proved very considerable in such prox-<lb/>imity to the summit of Chimborazo. There remained yet a perpendicular<lb/>height of less than 8400 feet (the height of the Canigou in the Pyrenees) to de-<lb/>termine. Yet with the enormous masses of single mountains in the chain of the<lb/>Andes, every determination of the height above the sea is compounded of a bar-<lb/>ometrical and trigonometrical observation. I had taken with me the sextant and<lb/>other instruments of measurement in vain. The summit of Chimborazo remained<lb/>densely veiled in mist. From the high plain of Sisgun the ascent is tolerably<lb/>steep as far as the little alpine lake of Yana-Coche. Thus far I had remained<lb/>on the mule, having from time to time alighted with my travelling companion M.<lb/>Bonpland merely to collect plants. Yana-Coche does not deserve the name of a<lb/>lake. It is a circular basin of scarcely 130 feet in diameter. The sky became<lb/>more and more obscured; but between and over the mist-strata there still lay<lb/>scattered single groups of clouds. The summit of Chimborazo was visible for<lb/>a few moments at a time. Much snow having fallen during the preceding night,<lb/>I left the mule where we found the lower border of this newly-fallen snow, a bor-<lb/>der which must not be confounded with the limit of perpetual snow. The barome-<lb/>ter showed that we had only now attained the height of 13,500 feet. On other<lb/>mountains, likewise near to the equator, I have seen snow fall at the height of<lb/>11,200 feet, but not lower. My companion rode as far as the line of perpetual<lb/>snow, <hi rendition="#i">i. e.</hi> to the height of Mont Blanc; which mountain, as is known, would<lb/>not in this latitude (1&#x00B0; 27&#x2032; south) be covered with snow. The horses and mules<lb/>remained there to await our return.</p>
                    <p>A hundred and fifty toises above the little basin of Yana-Coche, we saw at<lb/>length naked rock. Hitherto the grass-land had withdrawn the ground from any<lb/>geognostical examination. Great walls of rock, extending from the N.E. to-<lb/>wards the S.W., in part cleft into misshapen columns, reared themselves out of<lb/>the eternal snow&#x2014;a brownish-black augite rock shining like pitch-stone porphyry.<lb/>The columns were very thin, perhaps from fifty to sixty feet in height, almost<lb/>like the trachyte columns of Tabla-Umca on the volcano Pichincha. One group<lb/>stood alone, and reminded one of masts and stems of trees. The steep walls<lb/>led us through the snow region to a narrow ridge of rock extending towards the<lb/>summit, by which alone it was possible for us to advance any farther, for the<lb/>snow was then so soft that one scarcely dared to tread upon its surface. The<lb/>ridge consisted of very weathered crumbling rock. It was often vesicular like a<lb/>basaltic-amygdaloid.</p>
                    <p>The path became more and more narrow and steep. The natives forsook us<lb/>all but one at the height of 15,600 feet. All entreaties and threats were unavail-<lb/>ing. The Indians maintained that they suffered more than we did from breath-<lb/>lessness. We remained alone, Bonpland,&#x2014;our amiable friend the younger son<lb/>of the Marquess of Selvalegre, Carlos Montufar, who in the subsequent struggle<lb/>for freedom, was shot (at the command of General Morillo),&#x2014;a Mestize from<lb/>the neighbouring village of San Juan,&#x2014;and myself. We attained, with great<lb/>exertion and endurance, a greater height than we had dared hope to reach, as we<lb/>were almost entirely wrapped in mist. The ridge (very significantly called, in<lb/>Spanish, Cuchilla, as it were the knife-back) was in many places only eight or ten<lb/>inches broad. On the left the precipice was concealed by snow, the surface of<lb/>the latter seemed glazed with frost. The thin icy mirror-like surface had an in-<lb/>clination of about 30&#x00B0;. On the right our view sank shuddering 800 or 1000 feet<lb/>into an abyss out of which projected, perpendicularly, snowless masses of rock.<lb/>We held the body continually inclined towards this side, for the precipice upon<lb/>the left seemed still more threatening, because there no chance presented itself<lb/>of grasping the toothed rock, and because, further, the thin ice-crust offered no<lb/>security against sinking in the loose snow. Only extremely light porous bits of<lb/>dolerite could we roll down this crust of ice, and the inclined plane of snow was<lb/>so extended that we lost sight of the stones thus rolled down before they came to<lb/>rest. The absence of snow, as well upon the ridge along which we ascended,<lb/>as upon the rocks on our right hand towards the east, cannot be ascribed so much<lb/>to the steepness of the masses, and to the gales of wind, as to open clefts, which<lb/>breathe out warm air from deeper situated beds. We soon found our further<lb/>ascent more difficult, from the increase of the crumbling nature of the rock.<lb/>At single and very steep <hi rendition="#i">échélons</hi> it was necessary to apply at the same time the<lb/>hands and feet, as is so usual in all alpine journeys. As the rock was very keenly<lb/>angular, we were painfully hurt, especially in the hands. Leopold Von Buch and<lb/>I suffered very much in this manner near the crater of the Peak of Teneriffe,<lb/>which abounds in obsidian.&#x2014;The little adhesion of the rocks upon the ridge now<lb/>rendered greater caution necessary, as many masses which we supposed firm, lay<lb/>loose and covered with sand. We proceeded one after the other, and so much<lb/>the more slowly, as it was needful to try the places which seemed uncertain.<lb/>Happily the attempt to reach the summit of Chimborazo was the last of our<lb/>mountain journeys in South America; hence previous experience guided us, and<lb/>gave us more confidence in our powers. It is a peculiar character of all excur-<lb/>sions in the Andes, that above the snow line white people find themselves, in the<lb/>most perilous situations, always without guides, indeed without any knowledge of<lb/>localities.</p>
                    <p>We could see the summit no longer, even for a moment only at a time, and<lb/>were hence doubly curious to know, how much higher it remained for us to as-<lb/>cend. We examined the barometer at a point where the breadth of the ridge<lb/>permitted of two persons standing conveniently together. We were now at an<lb/>elevation of 17,300 feet, thus scarcely two hundred feet higher than we had<lb/>been two months before when climbing a similar ridge on the Antisana. It is<lb/>with the determining of heights in climbing mountains, as with the determining<lb/>of temperature in the heat of summer. One finds with vexation the thermome-<lb/>ter not so high, the barometer not so low, as one expected. As the air, notwith-<lb/>standing the height, was quite saturated with moisture, we now found the loose<lb/>rock and the sand that filled its interstices extremely wet. The air was still 2&#x00B0;<lb/>8&#x2032; (37&#x00B0; 04&#x2032; Fahr) Shortly before, we had in a dry place been able to bury the<lb/>thermometer three inches deep in the sand. It indicated +5&#x00B0; 8&#x2032; (+42&#x00B0; 44&#x2032;<lb/>Fahr) The result of this observation, which was made at the height of about<lb/>2860 toises, is very remarkable, for 400 toises lower down, at the limit of perpe-<lb/>tual snow, the mean heat of the atmosphere is according to many observations,<lb/>collected by Boussingault and myself, only +1&#x00B0; 6&#x2032; (34&#x00B0; 88&#x2032; Fahr) The tempe-<lb/>rature of earth (sand) at +5&#x00B0; 8&#x2032; (42&#x00B0; 44&#x2032; Fahr) must therefore be ascribed to<lb/>the subterranean heat of the dolerite mountain; I do not say to the whole mass,<lb/>but to the current of air ascending from the interior.</p>
                    <p>After an hour of cautious climbing, the ridge of rock became less steep, but<lb/>alas! the mist remained as thick as ever. We now began gradually to suffer<lb/>from great nausea. The tendency to vomiting was combined with some giddi-<lb/>ness, and much more troublesome than the difficulty of breathing. A coloured<lb/>man (a Mestize of San Juan), not from selfish motives, but merely out of good<lb/>nature, had been unwilling to forsake us. He was a poor vigorous peasant, and<lb/>suffered more than we did. We had h&#x00E6;morrhage from the gums and lips. The<lb/>conjunctiva of the eyes likewise, was, in all, gorged with blood. These symp-<lb/>toms of extravasation in the eyes, and of oozing from the lips and gums, did not<lb/>in the least disquiet us, as we had repeatedly experienced them before. In Eu-<lb/>rope, M. Zumstein began to experience h&#x00E6;morrhage at a much lower elevation<lb/>on Monte Rosa. The Spanish warriors during the conquest of the equinoctial<lb/>region of America (during the Conquista) did not ascend above the snow line,<lb/>thus but little above the elevation of Mont Blanc, and yet Acosta, in his &#x2018;Histo-<lb/>ria Natural de las Indias,&#x2019;&#x2014;a kind of physical geography, which may be called a<lb/>masterpiece of the sixteenth century&#x2014;speaks circumstantially of &#x201C;nausea and<lb/>spasm of the stomach,&#x201D; as painful symptoms of the <hi rendition="#i">mountain sickness</hi>, which in<lb/>these respects is analogous to <hi rendition="#i">sea-sickness.</hi> On the volcano of Pichincha I once<lb/>felt, without experiencing h&#x00E6;morrhage, so violent an affection of the stomach, ac-<lb/>companied by giddiness, that I was found senseless on the ground, just as I left<lb/>my companions on a wall of rock above the defile of Verde-Cucha, in order to<lb/>perform some electrical experiments on a perfectly open space. The height was<lb/>inconsiderable, below 13,800 feet. But on the Antisana, at the considerable ele-<lb/>vation of 17,220 feet, our young travelling companion, Don Carlos Montufar, bled<lb/>freely from the lips. All of these phenomena vary according to age, constitution,<lb/>the tenderness of the skin, the preceding exertions of the muscular powers, yet<lb/>for single individuals they are a kind of measure of the atmospheric tenuity, and<lb/>of the absolute elevation reached. According to my observations in the Cordil-<lb/>leras, these symptoms manifest themselves in white people, with a mercurial co-<lb/>lumn between 14 inches&#x2014;and 15 inches 10 lines.</p>
                    <p>The layers of mist that prevented our seeing distant objects, appeared sudden-<lb/>ly, notwithstanding the total stillness of the air, perhaps through electrical pro-<lb/>cesses, to be broken up. We recognized once more, and indeed immediately be-<lb/>fore us, the dome-shaped summit of Chimborazo. It was an earnest, momentous<lb/>gaze. The hope to reach this summit animated our powers anew. The ridge of<lb/>rock, only here and there covered with thin flakes of snow, became somewhat<lb/>broader. We hastened onwards, with certain steps, when all at once a ravine of<lb/>some 400 feet in depth, and 50 broad, set an insurmountable barrier to our un-<lb/>dertaking. We saw distinctly beyond the abyss, our ridge of rock continued for-<lb/>ward in the same direction; yet I doubt its leading to the summit itself. The<lb/>chasm was not to be gone round. On the Antisana, M. Bonpland indeed had<lb/>found it possible, after a very cold night, to proceed for a considerable length<lb/>through the snow. We durst not venture the attempt, because of the looseness<lb/>of the mass, and the form of the precipice rendered climbing down impossible.&#x2014;<lb/>It was one o&#x2019;clock in the afternoon. We set up with much care the barometer.<lb/>It indicated 13 inches 11<formula notation="TeX">\left( \frac{2}{10} \right)</formula> lines. The temperature of the air was now&#x2014;<lb/>1&#x00B0; 6&#x2032; (+29&#x00B0; 12&#x2032; Fahr.), but after several years&#x2019; stay in the hottest regions of the<lb/>Tropics, this small degree of cold benumbed us. Besides, our boots were tho-<lb/>roughly soaked with snow-water, for the sand that covered here and there the<lb/>ridge was mixed with old snow. According to La Place&#x2019;s barometrical formula,<lb/>we had reached a height of 3016 toises, or more precisely 18,097 Paris feet. If<lb/>La Condamine&#x2019;s estimate of the height of Chimborazo, as noted on the stone-<lb/>table of the Jesuit&#x2019;s College in Quito, be correct, there failed us yet of the sum-</p>
                    
                    <pb n="13" facs="#f0002"/> 
                    <p>mit of the mountain 1224 feet, or thrice the height of St. Peter&#x2019;s church at<lb/>Rome.</p>
                    <p>We remained but a short time in this mournful solitude, being soon again en-<lb/>tirely veiled in mist. The humid air was not thereby set in motion. No fixed<lb/>direction was to be observed in single groups of the denser particles of vapour,<lb/>I therefore cannot say whether at this elevation the west wind blows, opposing<lb/>the Tropical monsoon. We saw no longer the summit of Chimborazo, none of<lb/>the neighboring snow-mountains, still less the table lands of Quito. We were as<lb/>though isolated in a ball of air. Some stone lichens only had followed us above<lb/>the line of perpetual snow. The last cryptogamic plants which I collected were<lb/>Lecidea atrovirens (Lichen geographicus, <hi rendition="#i">Web.</hi>), and a Gyrophora of <hi rendition="#i">Acharius,</hi> a<lb/>new species (Gyrophora rugosa), at about the height of 2820 toises. The last<lb/>moss, Grimmia longirostris, grew 400 toises lower down. A butterfly (sphinx)<lb/>was caught by M. Bonpland at the height of 15,000 feet; we saw a fly 1600 feet<lb/>higher. I must remark, that we met with no condor on Chimborazo, that power-<lb/>ful vulture, which is so frequent on Antisana and Pichincha, and which shows<lb/>great confidence from its ignorance of man. The condor loves pure air, in order<lb/>the easier from on high to recognize its prey or its food, for it gives dead animals<lb/>the preference.</p>
                    <p>As the weather became more and more cloudy, we hastened down upon the<lb/>same ledge of rock, that had favoured our ascent. Caution, however, on ac-<lb/>count of the uncertainty of the steps, was more necessary than in climbing up.<lb/>We tarried only just to collect fragments of rock. We foresaw that in Europe<lb/>&#x201C;a little bit of Chimborazo&#x201D; would be asked for. At that time no mountain rock<lb/>in any part of South America had been named; the rocks of all the high summits<lb/>of the Andes were called granite. As we were at the height of about 18,400<lb/>feet, it began to hail violently. The hailstones were opaque, and milk-white,<lb/>with concentric layers; some appeared considerably flattened by rotation; twenty<lb/>minutes before we reached the lower limit of perpetual snow, the hail was re-<lb/>placed by snow. The flakes were so dense, that the snow soon covered the<lb/>ridge of rock many inches deep; we should have been brought into great danger,<lb/>had the snow surprised us at the height of 18,000 feet. At a few minutes after<lb/>two o&#x2019;clock, we reached the point where our mules were standing. The natives<lb/>that remained behind, had been very apprehensive for our safety.</p>
                    <p>That part of our expedition which lay above the snow-line, had lasted only 3<formula notation="TeX">\left( \frac{1}{2} \right)</formula>hours, during which, notwithstanding the tenuity of the air, we had not found it<lb/>needful to take rest by sitting down. On account of the snow newly fallen, we<lb/>found in our descent from Chimborazo, the lower limit of perpetual snow, in<lb/>accidental and temporary conjunction with the deeper sporadial spots of snow on<lb/>the naked lichen covered rocks, and on the grass plain (Pajonal); yet it was al-<lb/>ways easy to recognize the proper limit of perpetual snow, (then at the height of<lb/>2470 toises) by the thickness of the bed and by its peculiar state.</p>
                    <p>We took a somewhat more northern way back to the village of Calpi than the<lb/>Llanos de Sisgun, through the Paramo de Pungupala, a district rich in plants.<lb/>By five o&#x2019;clock in the evening we were again with the friendly clergyman of<lb/>Calpi. As usual, the misty day of the expedition was succeeded by the clearest<lb/>weather. On the 25th of June, at Riobamba Nuevo, Chimborazo presented<lb/>itself in all its splendour,&#x2014;I may say, in the calm greatness and supremacy which<lb/>is the natural character of the tropical landscape. A second attempt upon a<lb/>ridge interrupted by a chasm, would certainly have turned out as fruitless as the<lb/>first, and I was already engaged with the trigonometrical measurement of the<lb/>volcano of Tungurahua.</p>
                    <p>Boussingault, on the 16th of December 1831, with his English friend Colonel<lb/>Hall,&#x2014;who was soon afterwards assassinated in Quito,&#x2014;made a new attempt to<lb/>reach the summit of Chimborazo, first from Mocha and Chillapulla, then from<lb/>Arenal, thus by a different way from that trodden by Bonpland, Don Carlos Mon-<lb/>tufar, and myself. He was obliged to give up the ascent, when his barometer<lb/>indicated 13 inches 8<formula notation="TeX">\left( \frac{1}{2} \right)</formula>lines, with an atmospheric temperature of +7&#x00B0; 8&#x2032; (+46&#x00B0; 04&#x2032;<lb/>F.). He thus saw the uncorrected column of mercury almost three lines lower,<lb/>and reached a point 94 toises higher than I did, viz. 3080 toises. Let us have<lb/>the words of this well-known traveller of the Andes, who was the first to carry<lb/>a chemical apparatus to, and into, the craters of volcanoes. &#x201C;The way,&#x201D; says<lb/>Boussingault, &#x201C;which we opened for ourselves through the snow, in the latter<lb/>part of our expedition, permitted of our advancing but very slowly. On the<lb/>right we were enabled to grasp hold of a rock, on the left, the abyss was fearful.<lb/>We were already sensible of the effect of the attenuated air, and were obliged,<lb/>every two or three steps to sit down. As soon, however, as we were seated, we<lb/>again stood up, for our sufferings lasted only while we moved. The snow we<lb/>were obliged to tread was soft, and lay three or four inches deep, on a very<lb/>smooth and hard covering of ice. We were obliged to hew our steps. A Ne-<lb/>gro went before, to perform this work, by which his powers were soon exhaust-<lb/>ed. As I was endeavouring to pass him, for the purpose of relieving him, I slip-<lb/>ped, and happily was held back by Colonel Hall and my Negro. We were (adds<lb/>M. Boussingault) for a moment all three in the greatest danger. Further on, the<lb/>snow became more favourable, and at three quarters past three o&#x2019;clock we stood<lb/>upon the long-looked-for ridge of rock, which was only a few feet broad, and sur-<lb/>rounded by immeasurable depths. Here we became convinced that to advance<lb/>farther was impossible. We found ourselves at the foot of a prism of rock,<lb/>whose upper surface covered with a cap of snow, forms the proper summit of<lb/>Chimborazo. To have a true figure of the topography of the whole mountain,<lb/>one must imagine an enormous snow-covered mass of rock, which from all sides<lb/>appears as if supported by buttresses. The latter are the ridges, which, adhe-<lb/>rent, project through the eternal snow.&#x201D;</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 