<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/103788910X">
                        <surname>Metz</surname>
                        <forename>Bernhard</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-20" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-24" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="135" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the difference of level between the Black Sea and the<lb break="yes"/>Caspian.</hi> Communicated by the Baron <hi rendition="#k" >Alexander von<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> kindness of M. Kupffer, Corresponding Member of the<lb break="yes"/>Society at St. Petersburg, enabled us to give, at p. 426, Vol. vi.<lb break="yes"/>of the Geographical Journal, some account of the Russian expe-<lb break="no"/>dition about to be sent forth, in 1836, to determine the long-<lb break="maybe"/>contested point of the difference of level between the Black and<lb break="yes"/>the Caspian Seas. That expedition has fulfilled its object.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The trigonometric levelling along the line of country between<lb break="yes" />Novo-Tcherkask, by Stavropol, to Kisliar, is now completed, and<lb break="yes" />although the detail of the survey has not yet reached London, yet<lb break="yes"/>the fact of the determination of so remarkable a point in physical<lb break="yes"/>geography is too important not to find a place in the Geogra-<lb break="no"/>phical Journal, especially as the Society is indebted for the<lb break="yes"/>communication of it to one of its most distinguished Foreign<lb break="yes"/>Members.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2" type="letter">
                    <dateline>
                        <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Berlin, Jan.</hi> 10, 1838.</hi>
                    </dateline>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The beautiful trigonometric levelling between the Black and<lb break="yes"/>the Caspian Seas is at length finished. There is a depression, but<lb break="yes"/>a much less depression than M. Parrot had announced after his<lb break="yes"/>first barometric levelling by stations; this always appeared to<lb break="yes"/>me probable (see my letter to M. Parrot, inserted in his &#x2018;Voyage<lb break="yes"/>à l&#x2019;Ararat,&#x2019; vol. ii. p. 192), on account of the elevation of Kasan<lb break="yes"/>(level of the junction of the Kasanza and the Wolga), and on<lb break="yes"/>account of some corresponding observations which I obtained during<lb break="yes"/>my journey to the Caspian. The levelling of MM. Fuss, Sabler,<lb break="yes"/>and Sawitch, shews that the level of the Caspian is 101.2 Russian<lb break="yes"/>feet, equal to 94.9 Paris feet (old measure), lower than the<lb break="yes"/>level of the Black Sea.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The height of Kasan has been much discussed, and all tra-<lb break="no"/>vellers have assumed different heights; at page 639 of the volume<lb break="yes"/>published by M. Gustave Rose, I have given the latest results<lb break="yes"/>of the labours of the astronomer Simonoff, professor at Kasan.<lb break="yes"/>The cistern of the barometer in the building of the University<lb break="yes"/>(Universitäts Gebäude) at Kasan, has an elevation of 181 Paris<lb break="yes"/>feet; the junction of the Kasanza and the Wolga is 53 feet<lb break="yes"/>(8.9 toises) above the level of the ocean. The fall of the Wolga<lb break="yes"/>from Kasan to the Caspian would be then 148 feet, or 24.7<lb break="yes"/>toises. In a direct line it is about 157 geographical leagues (of<lb break="yes"/>15 to the degree) from Kasan to the Caspian. This is a greater<lb break="yes" />inclination than that of the Amazon or the Nile, and almost as<lb break="yes"/>great as that of the Oder. The most striking fact is the little<lb break="yes"/>elevation of part of the interior of the East of Europe above the<lb break="yes"/>level of the ocean, since from Kasan to the Icy Sea it is 135<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="136" facs="#f0002"/> geographical leagues. The city of Berlin, so near the Baltic, is<lb break="yes"/>100 feet above the level of the sea, according to an excellent<lb break="yes"/>trigonometric levelling, which the chief of the staff corps has, at<lb break="yes"/>my request, caused to be executed during last year, by the able<lb break="yes"/>observer M. <choice><sic>Bäyer</sic><corr type="editorial">Bayer</corr></choice>.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;I cannot sufficiently congratulate the Geographical Society on<lb break="yes"/>having found so excellent a traveller as M. Schomburgk: his latest<lb break="yes"/>labours, the ascent of the Rivers Corentyn and Berbice, in<lb break="yes"/>Guayana, place him very high in my opinion; and the zone of<lb break="yes"/>hieroglyphic figures, sculptured in the rocks from Encamarada,<lb break="yes"/>in 66° 50&#x2032; W. longitude, as far as the eastern limit of British<lb break="yes"/>Guayana, a distance of nearly 600 miles, is an ethnographical<lb break="yes"/>phenomenon which daily increases in interest.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The astronomical geography of the North of Asia will shortly<lb break="yes"/>be set right by the publication of the important labours of M.<lb break="yes"/>Federow, <hi rendition="#i">élève</hi> of M. Struve, who has recently returned, after a<lb break="yes"/>five years&#x2019; absence. Should I still publish the detail of my astro-<lb break="no" />nomical observations in Siberia, it will only be in order to fix<lb break="yes"/>more accurately the points where I have made observations on<lb break="yes"/>terrestrial magnetism.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;I learn with the greatest satisfaction that my letter to the<lb break="yes"/>Duke of Sussex, on the subject of Magnetic Observatories, has<lb break="yes"/>produced some useful results. As we make observations here<lb break="yes"/>both with the needle of Gambey, furnished with microscopes and<lb break="yes"/>with the new apparatus of Gauss, an apparatus furnished with a<lb break="yes"/>mirror, we have an opportunity of convincing ourselves more and<lb break="yes"/>more of the great perfection of this mirror apparatus, which doubt-<lb break="no"/>less requires greater skill and more instruction on the part of the<lb break="yes"/>observers; the tracing of the curves of horary variation, based upon<lb break="yes" />observations made across all Europe for every five minutes of time<lb break="yes"/>(see Gauss und Weber, <hi rendition="#i">Resultate aus den Beobachtungen des<lb break="yes"/>Magnetischen Vereins im <choice><sic>Yahr</sic><corr type="editorial">Jahr</corr></choice></hi> 1836; Göttingen, bei Dietrich,<lb break="yes"/>1837), will prove what advantage is derived from making use of<lb break="yes"/>the apparatus of Gauss, which doubtless will soon be employed<lb break="yes"/>in all our great observatories.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;As I think that this subject is not without importance to<lb break="yes"/>Seamen, I beg you to invite the leading Members of the Geogra-<lb break="no"/>phical Society to be good enough to propagate Gauss&#x2019; manner of<lb break="yes"/>observing in all new stations, where intelligent persons can be<lb break="yes"/>found. Points near the Magnetic Equator, and those which are<lb break="yes"/>in high latitudes in the southern hemisphere, as the Cape of<lb break="yes"/>Good Hope, Australia, Van Diemen&#x2019;s Land, would be the most<lb break="yes"/>desirable, if they would observe at the same epochs indicated by<lb break="yes"/>M. Gauss, and followed throughout the North of Asia, in Ger-<lb break="no"/>many, in Sweden, and at Milan.&#x201D;</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 