<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">An essay on the fluctuations in the supplies of gold, with relation to problems of political economy</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:07</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">V.79</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-10-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-01.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-02.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-05.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-10-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-17.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">An essay on the fluctuations in the supplies of gold, with relation to problems of political economy</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1840</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Analyst. A Quarterly Journal of Science, Literature, Natural History, and the Fine Arts&lt;/i&gt; 10:29 (April 1840), S. 181–204.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Fußnoten mit Asterisken und Kreuzen; Schmuck: Kapitälchen; Tabellensatz.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="181" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>AN ESSAY ON THE FLUCTUATIONS IN THE<lb break="yes"/>SUPPLIES OF GOLD,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">with relation to problems of political economy.<lb break="yes"/>By ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT</hi>.
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">It</hi> is an ancient remark of Herodotus (iii., 106) that in the un-<lb break="no"/>equal distribution of the goods and treasures of the earth, the fairest<lb break="yes"/>productions have been imparted to its extremities. This observation<lb break="yes"/>was not founded merely on the gloomy feeling (so characteristic of<lb break="yes"/>humanity) that happiness dwells far from us, but it expressed as well<lb break="yes"/>the fact that, by means of commercial intercourse, the Greeks, as<lb break="yes"/>inhabitants of the temperate zone, were dependent on distant lands<lb break="yes"/>for gold and spices, amber and tin. So that when, by means of the<lb break="yes"/>commerce of the Ph&#x0153;nicians, of the Edomites on the Gulf of Acaba,<lb break="yes"/>of Egypt under the Ptolemies and Romans, the long-concealed coasts<lb break="yes" />of Southern Asia came gradually to be explored, the productions<lb break="yes" />of the warmer latitudes were received more direct from their native<lb break="yes"/>soil; and in the fertile imagination of man the metallic treasures of<lb break="yes"/>the earth were driven back further and further towards the east.<lb break="yes"/>Twice have the same people (the Arabians), during the epoch so<lb break="yes"/>important for commerce, namely, the &#x00E6;ras of the Lagid&#x00E6; and the<lb break="yes"/>C&#x00E6;sars, as well as at the conclusion of the fifteenth century&#x2014;the peri-<lb break="no"/>od of the Portuguese discoveries&#x2014;pointed out to the western nations<lb break="yes"/>the route to India. Ophir (the Dorado of Solomon) extended to the<lb break="yes"/>eastward of the Ganges. There, also, was supposed to be situated<lb break="yes"/>Chrysé, which so long engaged the attention of the travellers of the<lb break="yes"/>middle ages, and which was considered, at one time, as an island, at<lb break="yes"/>another, as part of the Golden Chersonesus. The quantities of gold<lb break="yes"/>which, according to John Crawford, Borneo and Sumatra bring into<lb break="yes"/>circulation, even at the present day, explain the ancient celebrity<lb break="yes"/>of those regions. Near to Chrysé (the land of gold, according to the<lb break="yes"/>ideas of a systematizing geography) must symmetrically be situated<lb break="yes"/>a silver island (Argyré), in order to unite, as it were, the two pre-<lb break="no" />cious metals&#x2014;the wealth of Ophir and the Iberian Tartessus. The<lb break="yes"/>geography of the middle ages reflected, under various forms, the<lb break="yes"/>geographical fables of classical antiquity. In the works of the Ara-<lb break="no"/>bians, Edrisi and Bahai, we find mentioned, at the extremity of the<lb break="yes"/>Indian Ocean, an island (Salahet) possessing silver sands; and near it<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="182" facs="#f0002"/> Saila (not to be confounded with Ceylon or Serendib), where dogs<lb break="yes"/>and apes were said to wear golden collars.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In determining, however, the peculiar region of gold, and of all the<lb break="yes"/>precious productions of the earth, the idea of remote distance was mixed<lb break="yes"/>up with that of tropical heat. &#x201C;So long,&#x201D; writes, in 1495, Mossen<lb break="yes"/>Taime Teener, a Catalonian lapidary, to Christopher Columbus,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;as your excellency does not find black men, you must not look for<lb break="yes"/>great things, real treasures, such as spices, diamonds, and gold.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>This letter was recently found in a book printed at Barcelona in<lb break="yes" />1545, and bearing the singular title of &#x201C;Sentencias Catholicas del<lb break="yes"/>Divo Poeta Dante.&#x201D; Yet the gold productiveness of the Ural moun-<lb break="no"/>tains, which extend northwards to where the snow scarcely thaws<lb break="yes"/>during the summer months, and the diamonds, which (during my<lb break="yes"/>Siberian expedition, made at the request of the Emperor Nicholas in<lb break="yes"/>1829) were discovered by two of my companions on the European<lb break="yes"/>declivity of the Ural, near to the 60th deg. of lat., do not bear out<lb break="yes"/>the connexion of gold and diamonds with tropical heat and coloured<lb break="yes"/>men. Christopher Columbus, who ascribes a moral and religious<lb break="yes"/>value to gold, &#x201C;because,&#x201D; as he says, &#x201C;whoever possesses it obtains<lb break="yes"/>what he will in this world, nay, even (by the payment of masses)<lb break="yes"/>brings many souls into paradise&#x201D;&#x2014;Christopher Columbus was en-<lb break="no"/>tirely devoted to the system of the lapidary Teener. He looked for<lb break="yes" />Zipangu (Japan), which was given out as the gold-island, Chrysé;<lb break="yes"/>and while sailing (14th of November, 1492) along the coasts of<lb break="yes"/>Cuba, which he took for part of the continent of Eastern Asia (Ca-<lb break="no"/>thay), he writes, in his log-book, &#x201C;from the great heat which I suffer,<lb break="yes"/>the country must be rich in gold.&#x201D; Thus did false analogies cause to<lb break="yes"/>be forgotten what classical antiquity had recorded of the metallic<lb break="yes"/>treasures of the Massaget&#x00E6; and Arimaspi, in the extreme north of<lb break="yes" />Europe: I say of Europe, for the barren table land of Northern<lb break="yes" />Asia, the modern Siberia, with its pine forests, was considered as a<lb break="yes"/>wearisome continuation of the Belgian, Baltic, and Sarmatian plains.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If we cast a glance over the history of commercial intercourse in<lb break="yes" />Europe, we shall find the richest gold mines of ancient times in Asia.<lb break="yes"/>From the termination of the middle ages, and for three centuries<lb break="yes"/>later, they belong to the new world. At the present day, and since the<lb break="yes"/>commencement of the nineteenth century, the most abundant supplies<lb break="yes"/>are again found in Asia, although in different zones of that continent.<lb break="yes"/>This change in the direction of the current, this compensation pre-<lb break="no"/>sented by accidental discoveries in the north, when the supply of gold<lb break="yes" />suddenly ceases in the south, is deserving of serious consideration, of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="183" facs="#f0003"/> examination according to numerical data; for in political as well as in<lb break="yes"/>the observation of natural phenomena, numbers are ever decisive;<lb break="yes"/>they are the last, inexorable judges, in the much-disputed questions of<lb break="yes"/>political economy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We learn from the acute researches of Bökhs<note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Political Economy of the Athenians</hi>.
                    </note> how, on the open-<lb break="no"/>ing of the east by means of the Persian war, and the great Macedo-<lb break="no"/>nian expedition to further Asia, gold gradually accumulated among<lb break="yes"/>the Greeks of Europe; so that, in the age of Demosthenes, for in-<lb break="no"/>stance, the precious metals were of nearly five times less value than<lb break="yes"/>in that of Solon. The stream flowed at that time from east to west,<lb break="yes"/>and the influx of gold was so abundant that the relation of gold to<lb break="yes"/>silver, which in the time of Herodotus was as 1&#x2014;13, on the death of<lb break="yes" />Alexander, and for more than one hundred years afterwards, stood<lb break="yes"/>as 1&#x2014;10.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">See Letronne&#x2019;s learned rectification of the monetary hypotheses of Gar-<lb break="no"/>nier, <hi rendition="#i">Considerations générales sur l&#x2019;Evaluation des Monnaires Grecques et Ro-<lb break="no" />maines</hi>, p. 112; 1817.</note> The less general the commercial relations of the ancient<lb break="yes"/>world, the greater and more sudden the changes the relative value of<lb break="yes"/>gold and silver must necessarily undergo. Thus, we find in Rome that,<lb break="yes"/>owing to the local accumulation of one of the precious metals, shortly af-<lb break="no"/>ter the conquest of Syracuse, the relation of gold to silver as 1&#x2014;17&#x2150;;<lb break="yes"/>while under Julius C&#x00E6;sar it fell, for a time, to as low as 1&#x2014;8<formula notation="TeX">\frac{13}{14}</formula>.<lb break="yes"/>The more inconsiderable the quantity of bullion already existing in a<lb break="yes"/>country, the more easily, by means of influx from without, may these<lb break="yes"/>extraordinary fluctuations be brought about. In the modern world,<lb break="yes"/>the universality and rapidity of communication, which restores the<lb break="yes"/>equilibrium, as well as the amount of the accumulated masses of gold<lb break="yes"/>and silver already existing, tend to render still more stable the rela-<lb break="no"/>tive value of metals. After the revolution in Spanish America the<lb break="yes" />annual amount was, for several years, reduced to one-third; still the<lb break="yes"/>inconsiderable oscillations here and there remarkable are not to be<lb break="yes"/>attributed to this cause. It is quite otherwise as to the relation of<lb break="yes"/>silver to the so little accumulated, and therefore so unequally disse-<lb break="no"/>minated metal, platina.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Of statistical data, shewing, like those of modern days, the produc-<lb break="no"/>tiveness of entire countries, we find nothing among the ancients. The<lb break="yes"/>nature of their public administration did not admit of that control<lb break="yes"/>which, in more recent times, the over-refined fiscal system of the<lb break="yes"/>Arabians has imparted to the states of southern and western Europe.<lb break="yes"/>A datum like that given by Pliny (xii., 18), according to which<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="184" facs="#f0004"/> the commerce with India, Serica, and Yemen, absorbed annually<lb break="yes"/>one hundred millions of sesterces in precious metals&#x2014;that is, ac-<lb break="no"/>cording to Letronne, for the monetary value of that time a weight<lb break="yes"/>of 33,000 marks of silver, equal to about &#x00A3;70,000 sterling (only<lb break="yes"/>half the annual silver production of the Saxon Erz mountains),<lb break="yes"/>remains isolated and problematical. Where general results are<lb break="yes"/>wanting, numerical examples of the partial metallic productiveness<lb break="yes"/>of certain mountainous countries would be the more valuable, as we<lb break="yes"/>should be enabled to compare them with the modern produce of cele-<lb break="no" />brated mining districts, weight with weight in the absolute sense,<lb break="yes"/>without relation to the difficult consideration of gold as the measure<lb break="yes"/>of value of a given quantity of cereals. Treasures amassed by<lb break="yes"/>princes, the result of conquest or of long-continued extortion, are only<lb break="yes"/>evidence of what has been accumulated in extensive regions during<lb break="yes"/>an unknown number of ages. Results like these may be compared<lb break="yes"/>with the data which our staticians venture to put forth concerning<lb break="yes"/>the masses of the precious metals existing in a state at a given period.<lb break="yes"/>If Cyrus, according to Pliny (xxxiii., 15), amassed by the conquest of<lb break="yes"/>Asia 34,000&#x2114;s. in unwrought gold, without reckoning that wrought<lb break="yes"/>into vessels, still it is scarcely to be compared with two years produce<lb break="yes"/>of the Ural. On the other hand, Appian, on the authority of public<lb break="yes"/>records, estimates the treasure of Ptolom&#x00E6;us Philadelphus at 740,000<lb break="yes"/>talents, that is, according as we calculate by the Egyptian or smaller<lb break="yes" />Ptolem&#x00E6;an talent, 1017 or 254 millions of Prussian dollars. &#x201C;Such<lb break="yes"/>things,&#x201D; says the celebrated author of the <hi rendition="#i">Political Economy of the<lb break="yes" />Athenians</hi>,&#x201C; sound like fable, but I venture not to question their cre-<lb break="no"/>dibility. There was among this treasure much wrought silver and<lb break="yes"/>gold. The countries were completely exhausted; taxes and contri-<lb break="no"/>butions were collected by rapacious pr&#x00E6;tors. The revenues of<lb break="yes"/>C&#x00E6;lesyria, Ph&#x0153;nicia, Judea, and Samaria, alone were leased by Ptole-<lb break="no"/>m&#x00E6;us Evergetes for 8,000 talents, whilst a Jew purchased them for<lb break="yes"/>double that sum.&#x201D; Jacob, also, in his excellent work, <hi rendition="#i">Historical In-<lb break="no"/>quiry on Precious Metals</hi>, published at the request of Huskisson,<lb break="yes"/>confirms the data of our celebrated philologist. The above higher va-<lb break="no"/>luation will come near the present circulating medium of France and<lb break="yes"/>Belgium, the lower one to that of England. According to Strabo,<lb break="yes"/>Alexander collected in Ekbatana eighteen myriads of talents. We<lb break="yes"/>must not, however, lose sight of the fact, that while at the present<lb break="yes"/>day the precious metals are proportionately distributed over extensive<lb break="yes"/>districts, and among a numerous population, they were at that time<lb break="yes" />concentrated on a few points, or in the coffers of princes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="185" facs="#f0005"/>
                <p>That the golden treasures of the east, by which the western world<lb break="yes" />was inundated, flowed from the interior of Asia, north eastward from<lb break="yes"/>Ladakh, from the upper course of the Oxus, from Bactria and the<lb break="yes"/>eastern Satrapies of Persia, there cannot exist a doubt; still it is<lb break="yes"/>easier to point out the direction of the stream, than its particular<lb break="yes"/>sources and their relative productiveness. The scene of the fabu-<lb break="no"/>lous gold-seeking ants must be sought for far from the griffins of the<lb break="yes"/>Arimaspi. The former story would seem to belong to the table land<lb break="yes"/>of Raschgar and Aksu, between the parallel chains of the Celestial<lb break="yes"/>Mountain and the Kuenlun, where the river Tarim flows into the<lb break="yes"/>Lop. We shall again have occasion to recur to the more northern<lb break="yes"/>Arimaspi when we come to notice the gold masses of the Ural, lying<lb break="yes"/>immediately under the surface of the ground. The fame of Indian<lb break="yes"/>wealth resounded in oft mistaken echoes as far as Persia. Ctesias, of<lb break="yes"/>the tribe of the Asclepiads, physician to the king Artaxerxes Mne-<lb break="no"/>mon, without appearing to be aware of it, under the figure of a gold<lb break="yes" />spring, most distinctly describes a melting furnace, out of which the<lb break="yes"/>liquid metal flows into earthen moulds. Nearer to the Greeks were<lb break="yes"/>Lydia, and on the rivers which have their sources in the Tmolus, the<lb break="yes"/>gold-producing countries of Phrygia and Colchis. The nature of the<lb break="yes"/>quickly exhausted beds of gold sand (gold washings), renders it intel-<lb break="no"/>ligible to the practical miner why so many of the above-named and<lb break="yes"/>recently revisited countries have appeared to the traveller poor in<lb break="yes"/>gold. How easy would it be, were we to visit at the present day the<lb break="yes"/>ravines and torrent beds of Cuba and St. Domingo, or even the coasts<lb break="yes"/>of Veragua, in ignorance of the existing historical testimony, to doubt<lb break="yes"/>of the rich booty afforded by those districts at the conclusion of the<lb break="yes" />fifteenth century? More durable, when not disturbed by external<lb break="yes" />relations, is the subterraneous mining in permanent strata of gold<lb break="yes"/>ore; precisely because the entire bed cannot be discovered at once,<lb break="yes"/>as well as because, by the process of mining by galleries, the moun-<lb break="no"/>tain is only laid open by degrees, thus affording a more permanent<lb break="yes"/>employment to human activity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>How many of the forty gold washings so carefully described by<lb break="yes" />Strabo could be recognised at the present day? This remark,<lb break="yes" />founded on mining experience and analogy, is the more deserving of<lb break="yes"/>place here, now that ignorant scepticism so eagerly attacks the tra-<lb break="no"/>ditions of antiquity. That part of Europe known to the Greeks was<lb break="yes"/>as far inferior to Asia in metallic riches, as the whole European con-<lb break="no"/>tinent has proved to be, in recent times, to the New World.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The relative productiveness of Europe and America in gold at the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="186" facs="#f0006"/> commencement of the nineteenth century, the period when the mines<lb break="yes"/>of the Spanish colonies were wrought with the greatest activity, was<lb break="yes"/>as 1&#x2014;13; in silver as 1&#x2014;15. To me it even appears probable that<lb break="yes"/>during the Alexandrian and Ptolem&#x00E6;an periods, the proportion would<lb break="yes"/>have been still more unfavourable for Europe, especially in gold,<lb break="yes"/>could statistical data of this nature be obtained. In Greece itself, it<lb break="yes" />is true, that besides the originally rich silver mines of Laurion, the<lb break="yes"/>quantity of gold found in Thessaly, as well as in the mountains bor-<lb break="no"/>dering on Macedonia and Thrace, was considerable. Iberia, also<lb break="yes"/>was to the Ph&#x0153;nicians and Carthaginians not merely a country of<lb break="yes"/>silver. Tarshish and Ophir (the latter either Arabia or the eastern<lb break="yes"/>coasts of Africa, or rather, according to Heering, the general name for<lb break="yes"/>rich southern countries) were the destinations of the united Hiro-So-<lb break="no"/>lomonian fleets. Although, in the metallic abundance of Spain, silver<lb break="yes" />from B&#x0153;tica and the neighbourhood of New Carthage was the chief<lb break="yes"/>object of foreign commerce, yet Gallicia, Lusitania, and especially<lb break="yes"/>Asturias, produced, during many years, 20,000 &#x2114;s. of gold; that is to<lb break="yes"/>say, almost as much as Brazil during its most flourishing period.<lb break="yes"/>It is not surprising, therefore, that the Spanish peninsula acquired,<lb break="yes"/>among the Ph&#x0153;nicians and Carthaginians, the reputation of a west-<lb break="no" />ern El Dorado. It is certain that in many districts which at present<lb break="yes"/>discover but faint traces of metallic formation, the earth was at some<lb break="yes"/>former period covered, near the surface, with beds of gold sand, or<lb break="yes"/>traversed by solid socks containing fragments of gold ore. The local<lb break="yes"/>importance of those mines in southern Europe is not to be denied,<lb break="yes"/>though, in comparison with Asia, their productiveness in gold must<lb break="yes"/>be deemed insignificant. The latter continent remained long the<lb break="yes"/>chief source of metallic wealth; and the direction of the current of<lb break="yes"/>gold, as far as Europe is concerned, must be considered as from east<lb break="yes"/>to west.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It was Asia itself, however, or more properly the rumours spread<lb break="yes" />by travellers, during the middle ages, of the incalculable treasures of<lb break="yes"/>Japan and the Southern Archipelago, which caused a sudden change<lb break="yes"/>in the direction of the metallic current. America was discovered,<lb break="yes"/>not (as was so long falsely pretended) because Columbus <hi rendition="#i">predicted</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>another continent, but because he sought by the west a nearer way<lb break="yes"/>to the gold mines of Japan and the spice countries in the south-east<lb break="yes"/>of Asia. &#x201C;The greatest geographical error (the notion of the proxi-<lb break="no"/>mity of Spain to Asia) led to the greatest geographical discovery.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>Christopher Columbus and Amerigo Vespucci both died in the firm<lb break="yes"/>conviction that they had touched upon Eastern Asia&#x2014;the peninsula<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="187" facs="#f0007"/> of the Ganges. The reputation of having discovered a new continent,<lb break="yes"/>therefore, could give rise to no dispute between them. In Cuba, Co-<lb break="no"/>lumbus wished to deliver up the credentials of his monarch to the<lb break="yes"/>Grand Khan of the Moguls. He mistook that island for Mangi,<lb break="yes"/>the southern part of Cathay (China), and there expected to find the<lb break="yes"/>celestial city, Quinsay (now Hang-tscheu-fu), described by Marco<lb break="yes"/>Polo. &#x201C;The island of Hispaniola&#x201D; (Hayti), writes Columbus to the<lb break="yes"/>Pope Alexander the Sixth, &#x201C;is Tarschisch, Ophir, and Zipangu. In<lb break="yes"/>my second voyage I have discovered 140 islands and 333 miles of<lb break="yes"/>the continent of Asia (de la tierra firme de Asia).&#x201D; This West-In-<lb break="no"/>dian Japan shortly produced golden pebbles (pepitas de oro) of eight,<lb break="yes"/>ten, and even twenty pounds weight. The newly-discovered America<lb break="yes"/>now became the chief source of the precious metals. The fresh<lb break="yes"/>stream, flowing from west to east, shortly traversed Europe, since,<lb break="yes"/>owing to the increasing intercourse created by doubling the Cape of<lb break="yes"/>Good Hope, a more considerable value was required in return for<lb break="yes"/>the spices, silks, and colouring materials of southern and eastern<lb break="yes"/>Asia. Before the discovery of the silver mines of Tasco (1522),<lb break="yes"/>in the western declivity of the Mexican Cordilleras, America<lb break="yes"/>furnished gold only; and Queen Isabella, of Castile, saw herself<lb break="yes"/>compelled considerably to alter the legal relation of the precious me-<lb break="no"/>tals to each other. The early but hitherto little noticed edict of<lb break="yes" />Medina may be explained by this circumstance, and by the accumula-<lb break="no"/>tion of gold on a few points in Europe. I have attempted to prove,<lb break="yes"/>in another place, that from 1492 to 1500 the entire importation of<lb break="yes"/>gold from the then discovered regions of the New World, scarcely<lb break="yes"/>afforded an yearly average of 2000 marks.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Pope Alexander the Sixth, who conceived he had presented to the<lb break="yes" />Spaniards one-half of the globe, received in return, from Ferdinand<lb break="yes"/>the Catholic, a quantity of golden pebbles frum Hayti, for the gilding<lb break="yes"/>of the entablature of the basilic of Santa Maria Maggiore, &#x201C;as<lb break="yes"/>the first-fruits of the newly-discovered country.&#x201D; An inscription on<lb break="yes"/>the metal mentions, &#x201C;quod primo Catholici reges ex India recepe-<lb break="no"/>rant.&#x201D; So great was at that time the activity of the Spanish govern-<lb break="no" />ment, that so early as 1425, as we learn from the testimony of the<lb break="yes"/>historian Munoy, a miner (Paolo Belvio) was sent with a provision<lb break="yes"/>of quicksilver to Hayti, in order to expedite the gold washing by means<lb break="yes"/>of amalgamation. It is very curious to read, in a newly-discovered<lb break="yes"/>part of the geography of the sherif Edrisi, recently published, &#x201C;that<lb break="yes"/>the negroes in the interior of Western Africa, as well as the inhabi-<lb break="no"/>tants of the fertile settlement of Wadi el Alaki (between Abyssinia,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="188" facs="#f0008"/> Bodja, and Nubia), washed gold by means of quicksilver.&#x201D; The<lb break="yes"/>Nubian geographer of the middle of the twelfth century speaks of it<lb break="yes"/>as a thing long known. During the ages of classical antiquity, we<lb break="yes"/>find mention of quicksilver having been very generally used for the<lb break="yes"/>purpose of detaching the gold from the threads of old fringe, never,<lb break="yes"/>however, of a technical application of it, on a large scale, in those<lb break="yes" />processes for purifying the precious metals which have been so circum-<lb break="no"/>stantially described to us by ancient writers.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The relative value of gold and silver is at all times modified rather<lb break="yes"/>by the discovery of new than the drying up of old sources. Thus,<lb break="yes"/>for the second time since the discovery of the great Antilles, the<lb break="yes"/>price of gold rose about the middle of the sixteenth century, on the<lb break="yes"/>opening of the rich silver mines of Potosi and Zacatecas in Peru and<lb break="yes"/>North Mexico. The result of my very careful enquiries shews that,<lb break="yes"/>up to the opening of the Brazilian gold washings at the commence-<lb break="no"/>ment of the eighteenth century, the importation of American gold<lb break="yes"/>bore a relation to that of silver, weight for weight, as 1 to 65. At<lb break="yes"/>the present day, this proportion, if we embrace in one view the Euro-<lb break="no"/>pean commerce in metals with all parts of the world, is scarcely more<lb break="yes" />than 1 to 47. Such, at least, is the result of a comparison of the<lb break="yes"/>masses of both metals contemporaneously existing in Europe in a<lb break="yes"/>state of coinage. The data contained in the otherwise excellent work<lb break="yes"/>of Adam Smith, as well as the greater part of the numerical results<lb break="yes"/>therein given, are extremely incorrect, in the above-named propor-<lb break="no"/>tion, by more than the half. Among the civilized, and consequently<lb break="yes"/>the European nations carrying on immediate intercourse, the relative<lb break="yes"/>value of gold and silver fluctuated, during the first hundred years sub-<lb break="no"/>sequent to the discovery of the new continent, between 1&#x2014;10<formula notation="TeX">\frac{7}{10}</formula> and<lb break="yes"/>1&#x2014;12; in the last two centuries between 1&#x2014;14 and 1&#x2014;16. This<lb break="yes"/>fluctuation by no means exclusively depends upon the relative quan-<lb break="no"/>tities of the metals annually obtained from the bowels of the earth.<lb break="yes"/>The relative value of the two metals is dependent on a variety<lb break="yes"/>of causes; for example&#x2014;the expenses of production, the demand<lb break="yes"/>for consumption, and conversion into trinkets and other metallic<lb break="yes" />wares. So many different causes acting at once, as well as the<lb break="yes" />present facility of intercourse, and the enormous masses of pre-<lb break="no" />cious metal already accumulated in Europe, render any conside-<lb break="no" />rable or continued variation in the relative value of gold and silver<lb break="yes"/>impossible. Experience has shewn this on any sudden interrup-<lb break="no"/>tions of the production&#x2014;such as the outbreak of the revolution in<lb break="yes"/>Spanish America, or the immoderate consumption of the precious<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="189" facs="#f0009"/> metals by one of the more considerable mints. In England, for in-<lb break="no"/>stance, in the ten years from 1817 to 1827, more than 1,294,000<lb break="yes"/>marks of gold were converted into money, and yet this monopoly of<lb break="yes"/>gold only raised the proportion of it to silver in London from<lb break="yes"/>1&#x2014;14<formula notation="TeX">\frac{97}{100}</formula> to 1&#x2014;15<formula notation="TeX">\frac{60}{100}</formula>. Since then, the exchangeable value of<lb break="yes"/>gold, as compared with silver, has undergone but little depression;<lb break="yes"/>for at the conclusion of the year 1837 a pound of gold might be pur-<lb break="no" />chased in London for 15<formula notation="TeX">\frac{65}{100}</formula>&#x2114;s. silver. We shall shortly furnish nu-<lb break="no"/>merical data for the solution of the question as to what changes may<lb break="yes"/>be attributed to the combined effect of the Ural and North American<lb break="yes" />mining.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The quantity of precious metals imported into Europe, from the<lb break="yes" />discovery of America until the breaking out of the Mexican Revolu-<lb break="no"/>tion, was 10,400,000 Castilian marks (2,381,600 kilogrammes) of<lb break="yes"/>gold, and 533,700,000 marks (or 122,217,300 kil.) of silver; their<lb break="yes"/>united value amounting to 5,940 millions of piastres, of 4<hi rendition="#i">s</hi>. 4<hi rendition="#i">d</hi>.
                    <lb break="yes"/>each.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The silver obtained, during this period, from the American soil,<lb break="yes" />is calculated, in this valuation, at the standard of 0,903 for the<lb break="yes"/>piastre, which, for 122,217,300 kils. piastre silver, will give but<lb break="yes"/>110,362,222 kils. pure silver; which would form a ball of<lb break="yes"/>83<formula notation="TeX">\frac{7}{10}</formula> Parisian feet in diameter. A similar reduction to form and<lb break="yes"/>dimensions I consider as allowable, as analogous graphical descrip-<lb break="no"/>tions. If we compare the result of 318 years produce of Spanish<lb break="yes"/>America with that of one year&#x2019;s production of iron in a single country<lb break="yes"/>of Europe, we shall have, according to the datum of my friend, the<lb break="yes"/>celebrated geognost, Dechen, a ball of iron for Great Britain of<lb break="yes"/>148, for France 111, for the Prussian monarchy of 76, Parisian feet<lb break="yes"/>in diameter. So great is the difference in quantity of the two metals,<lb break="yes"/>silver and iron, in that part of the earth&#x2019;s superficies accessible to<lb break="yes" />man.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Whilst the stream of gold and silver flowed from east to west,<lb break="yes" />Spain was merely the channel of communication. But little of it<lb break="yes" />remained in the country, still less in the coffers of the king.<note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn1-1" next="#fn1-2">&#x201C;Ferdinand the catholic,&#x201D; writes his admirer and friend, Anghiesa, a few<lb break="yes"/>days after that great monarch&#x2019;s decease, &#x201C;was so poor that it was difficult to<lb break="yes"/>procure money to furnish decent clothing for the servants at his funeral.<choice><sic></sic><corr type="editorial">&#x201D;</corr></choice><lb break="yes"/>We give the remarkable passage from the letter to the Bishop of Tuy:&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Madrilegium villulam Regis tibi alias descripsi. Tot regnorum domi-<lb break="no"/>nus, totque palmarum cumulis ornatus, christian&#x00E6; religionis amplificator et<lb break="yes"/>prostrator hostium, Rex in rustican&#x00E2; obiit cas&#x00E2;, et pauper contra hominum</note> Of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="190" facs="#f0010"/> Charles the Fifth&#x2019;s pecuniary difficulties, Ranke has treated in his<lb break="yes"/>work on Spanish finance. The talented historian has, by means of<lb break="yes"/>fresh documents, enlarged and confirmed my official proofs of the<lb break="yes"/>inconsiderable quantity of precious metals furnished by the American<lb break="yes"/>mines and the so-styled Inca treasures, up to the year 1545.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A more intimate acquaintance with the history of the metallic pro-<lb break="no" />ductiveness, or gradual discovery of rich and considerable beds of<lb break="yes"/>ore in the New World, enables us to explain why the depreciation in<lb break="yes"/>the value of the precious metals, or (what is the same thing) the in-<lb break="no"/>crease in the price of grain and other necessaries, first began to be<lb break="yes"/>felt towards the middle of the sixteenth century, and more especially<lb break="yes"/>between 1570 and 1595. The abundance of silver from the mines<lb break="yes"/>of Tasco, Zacatecas, and Pachuca, in New Spain, of Potosi, Porco,<lb break="yes"/>and Oruro, in the Peruvian Andes, then first began to be regularly<lb break="yes"/>diffused throughout Europe, and effect a material alteration in the<lb break="yes"/>price of wheat, wool, and manufactured wares. The actual opening<lb break="yes"/>and working of the mines of Potosi, by the Spanish conquistadores,<lb break="yes" />took place in the year 1545; and the famous sermon preached by<lb break="yes" />Latimer before Edward the Sixth, in which he expresses his anger<lb break="yes"/>at the increasing price of all the necessaries of life, is of the<lb break="yes"/>17th of January, 1548. The English corn laws, between 1554 and<lb break="yes"/>1688, indicate the accumulation of the precious metals still better,<lb break="yes"/>perhaps, than the prices of grain collected by Fleetwood, Dupré de<lb break="yes"/>St. Maur, Garnier, and Lloyd. It is well known that the importa-<lb break="no"/>tion of wheat is only allowed when the price of a given measure has<lb break="yes"/>reached a certain standard prescribed by the law. Now, in the reign<lb break="yes"/>of Queen Mary (1554), this limit was six shillings per quarter;<lb break="yes"/>under Elizabeth (1593), about twenty; and in the year 1604, under<lb break="yes"/>James the First, more than twenty-six. These numerical data are<lb break="yes" />undoubtedly of great value; still considerable caution is required in<lb break="yes"/>the interpretation of them, since the problem of the prices of corn,<lb break="yes"/>as well as of prices in general, is a very complicated one; and varying<lb break="yes"/>theoretical views, the influence of the landowners, as well as the unequal<lb break="yes"/>local accumulation of money and wares, produce their effects on the le-<lb break="no"/>gislation of every period. Besides, the atmospheric changes (the mean<lb break="yes"/>warmth of the spring and summer months) which affect the cultiva-<lb break="no"/>tion of cereals, do not embrace at the same moment the entire agri-<lb break="no"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1">opinionem obiit, vix ad funeris pompam et paucis familiaribus pr&#x00E6;bendas<lb break="yes" />vestes pullatas, pecuni&#x00E6; apud eum, neque alibi congest&#x00E6;, repert&#x00E6; sunt, quod<lb break="yes"/>nemo unquam de vivente judicavit.&#x201D;</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="191" facs="#f0011"/> cultural Europe. An unequal increase in population, and the conse-<lb break="no"/>quently increasing intercourse, multiply the demand for metals. In<lb break="yes"/>the standard which we seek and think to find in the fluctuating prices<lb break="yes"/>of grain, we have to deal with two contemporaneously fluctuating<lb break="yes"/>quantities. The increased price of grain, even for a particular<lb break="yes"/>country, no more determines the relative increase of gold, than it<lb break="yes"/>informs us concerning the state of weather and the quantity of<lb break="yes"/>sunbeams. Data which should embrace a considerable portion of<lb break="yes"/>Europe contemporaneously, are nowhere to be found; and careful<lb break="yes" />enquiries have shewn that in the north of Italy the advance in the<lb break="yes"/>prices of grain, wine, and oil, from the fifteenth to the eighteenth cen-<lb break="no"/>tury, was much less considerable than we might have reasonably con-<lb break="no"/>cluded from what is known to us of England, France, and Spain, in<lb break="yes"/>which latter countries the prices of grain, since the discovery of Ame-<lb break="no"/>rica, have advanced four and even six-fold. Here it may not be<lb break="yes"/>superfluous to insert a numerical result, based on the average prices<lb break="yes"/>of fourteen years for the whole of the Prussian states, and drawn out<lb break="yes"/>with the greatest industry, at my request, by the Counsellor Hoffmann.<lb break="yes"/>In the year 1838, when for a pound of gold you might purchase, in<lb break="yes" />Berlin, 15<formula notation="TeX">\frac{9}{13}</formula>&#x2114;. of pure silver, 1611&#x2114;. of copper, and nearly 9700&#x2114;.<lb break="yes"/>of iron, the pound of gold, according to the averages of 1816 to<lb break="yes"/>1829, and 1824 to 1837, is exactly equal, in value, to 20,794&#x2114;. of<lb break="yes"/>wheat, 27,655&#x2114;. of rye, 31,717&#x2114;. barley, and 32,626&#x2114;. of oats.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The apprehensions respecting the diminished importation of gold<lb break="yes" />and silver from the New World&#x2014;caused by the appearance of<lb break="yes"/>the important, but in Germany not sufficiently appreciated, work<lb break="yes"/>of Jacob on precious metals&#x2014;have not been realized. The de-<lb break="no"/>depressed condition of the metallic production from 1809 to 1826,<lb break="yes"/>notwithstanding the unsettled state of the liberated Spanish America,<lb break="yes"/>has revived to three-fourths of what it was at the period when I quit-<lb break="no"/>ted those countries. In Mexico, in fact, according to the latest intel-<lb break="no"/>ligence, for which I am indebted to the active charge d&#x2019;affaires of<lb break="yes"/>Prussia, Mr. von Gerolt, the produce had risen to twenty or twenty-<lb break="no"/>two millions of piastres, to which, besides Zacatecas, the newly-opened<lb break="yes"/>mines of Fresnillo, Chihuahua, and Sonora, had principally contri-<lb break="no"/>buted. During the last peaceable period of Spanish dominion, I<lb break="yes"/>could not estimate the mean produce of the Mexican mines at more<lb break="yes"/>than twenty-three millions of piastres. The control was then easier,<lb break="yes"/>as there existed only a central mining commission, and severe laws<lb break="yes"/>restricted the commerce to a more limited number of ports. The<lb break="yes"/>greatest activity which at any time prevailed was in the central mint<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="192" facs="#f0012"/> of Mexico, which, from 1690 to 1803, furnished exactly 1353 mil-<lb break="no"/>lions of piastres in inland gold and silver; but, from the discovery of<lb break="yes"/>New Spain to the liberation of the country, probably 2,028 millions&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>that is, two-fifths of the entire amount of precious metals which the<lb break="yes"/>whole of America has poured into the old continent&#x2014;was furnished<lb break="yes"/>during this period.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The assertions so often made, in consequence of unsuccessful spe-<lb break="no" />culations, concerning the exhaustion of the Mexican mines, are dis-<lb break="no"/>proved as well by the geological formation of the country, as by the<lb break="yes"/>most recent experience. The mint of Zacatecas alone, during the<lb break="yes"/>unsettled period from 1811 to 1833, coined more than 66,332,000<lb break="yes"/>piastres, and in each of the last eleven years (1822 to 1833) between<lb break="yes"/>four and five millions of piastres.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <list>
                    <item>1829 ... ... ... ... 4,505,180 piastres</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1830 ... ... ... ... 5,189,902 &#x201E;</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1831 ... ... ... ... 4,469,450 &#x201E;</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1832 ... ... ... ... 5,012,000 &#x201E;</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1833 ... ... ... ... 5,720,000 &#x201E;</item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In Zacatecas, a single gallery&#x2014;the Veta Grande&#x2014;which had been<lb break="yes"/>wrought since the sixteenth century, and up to 1738 frequently fur-<lb break="no"/>nished as many as three million piastres in a year, has brought the<lb break="yes"/>following quantities into circulation:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <list>
                    <item>1828 ... ... ... ... 117,268 marks of silver</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1829 ... ... ... 235,741 &#x201E;</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1830 .. ... ... ... 279,288 &#x201E;</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1831 ... ... ... 272,095 &#x201E;</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1832 ... ... ... ... 258,498 &#x201E;</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1833 ... ... ... 209,192 &#x201E;</item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is true that Guanaruato, on the other hand, which, even in my<lb break="yes" />day, furnished annually 755,000 marks of silver, has of late years<lb break="yes"/>fallen to less than half. The produce was,</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <list>
                    <item>1829 ......... of gold, 852 marks; <choice><sic>... ...........</sic><corr type="editorial">...............</corr></choice> of silver, 260,494 marks</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1830 ......... &#x201E; 1058 &#x201E; ............... &#x201E; 284,386 &#x201E;</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1831 ......... &#x201E; 622 &#x201E; ............... &#x201E; 258,500 &#x201E;</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1832 ......... &#x201E; 1451 &#x201E; ............... &#x201E; 300,612 &#x201E;</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1833 <choice><sic>..... ...</sic><corr type="editorial">.........</corr></choice> &#x201E; 1144 &#x201E; ............... &#x201E; 316,024 &#x201E;</item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="193" facs="#f0013"/>
                <p>And should those highly-favoured regions ever enjoy the bless-<lb break="no" />ings of peace, the extended cultivation of the soil must necessarily lay<lb break="yes"/>open fresh strata. In what region of the globe besides, are we en-<lb break="no"/>abled to produce instances of a similar productiveness in silver? We<lb break="yes"/>must not forget that near Tombrerete, where mines were opened as<lb break="yes"/>early as 1555, the family of Fagoaga (Marquès del Apartado),<lb break="yes"/>within the space of five months, in an extent of ninety-six feet in<lb break="yes"/>length, obtained from falls of red ore of the Veta Negra, a clear pro-<lb break="no"/>fit of four millions of piastres; and in the mining district of Catorce,<lb break="yes"/>an ecclesiastic (Juan Floreo), between 1781 and 1783, from the shaft<lb break="yes"/>called, by the common people, &#x201C;the Purse of God the Father&#x201D; (la<lb break="yes"/>Bolsa de Dios Padre), obtained three and a half millions of piastres.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The quantity of gold produced in Spanish and Portuguese Ame-<lb break="no"/>rica has diminished considerably more than that of silver; this dimi-<lb break="no" />nution, however, must be dated much further back than the outbreak<lb break="yes"/>of the political revolutions in the tropical countries. I have already<lb break="yes"/>pointed out, in another place, how erroneous were our impressions in<lb break="yes"/>Europe, up to the commencement of the present century, concerning<lb break="yes"/>the continuance of the productiveness of the Brazilian gold washing,<lb break="yes"/>and how far we had confounded its flourishing days with its more re-<lb break="no"/>cent condition. The report (so important for the gold trade) of the<lb break="yes"/>Bullion committee first threw some light on this subject. I am in-<lb break="no"/>debted for the most authentic details to the communications of the<lb break="yes"/>late director general of mines, Freiherr von Eschwege. Jacob&#x2019;s work<lb break="yes"/>on the precious metals contains merely some trifling additions.<lb break="yes" />From 1752 to 1761 the gold produce of Minas Geraes varied from<lb break="yes" />6,400 to 8,600 kils. This production is certainly considerable, and<lb break="yes"/>far exceeding that of the Ural and the Altai at the present day; but<lb break="yes"/>we must recollect that, in 1804, Spanish America furnished nearly<lb break="yes"/>10,400 kils. of gold, viz.:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <list>
                    <item>New Grenada ... ... ... ... ... 4,700 kilogrammes.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Chili ... ... ... ... ... ... 2,800 &#x201E;</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Mexico ... ... ... ... ... ... 1,600 &#x201E;</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Peru ... ... ... ... ... ... 780 &#x201E;</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>Buenos Ayres ... ... ... ... ... <hi rendition="#u">500</hi> &#x201E;</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>
                        <hi rendition="#u">10,380</hi> kilogrammes.</item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The production of Minas Geraes had already fallen, in the inter-<lb break="no" />mediate 1785&#x2014;1794, to 3,300 kils; between 1818 and 1820, to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="194" facs="#f0014"/> 428 kils. This is in accordance with the account furnished by the<lb break="yes"/>Chevalier de Schäffer, according to which, in the year 1822, only<lb break="yes"/>twenty-four arrobas (350 kils.) were delivered to the smelting fur-<lb break="no"/>naces of Villarica. Since that time, owing to the exertions of some<lb break="yes"/>English companies, the Brazilian gold mining appears to have some-<lb break="no"/>what recovered itself. The decline, however, of the gold washing, is<lb break="yes"/>rather to be attributed to the disposition to cultivate colonial produce,<lb break="yes" />favoured as it is by the continued infamous importation of slaves<lb break="yes"/>from Africa, than to the exhaustion of the beds of ore. Owing to<lb break="yes"/>the enormous amount of smuggling at present carried on in the Bra-<lb break="no"/>zils, it were to be wished that some native thoroughly acquainted<lb break="yes"/>with the circumstances of the country would give himself the trouble<lb break="yes"/>to discover the annual amount of the gold produced since 1822.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is a remarkable circumstance in the history of mining carried on<lb break="yes"/>by Europeans, that, since the supplies of gold from the Brazils have<lb break="yes"/>so far diminished, those of Northern Asia and (though but momen-<lb break="no"/>tarily) of the southern districts of the United States, have attained an<lb break="yes"/>unexpected degree of importance. The mountain chain of the Ural<lb break="yes"/>is found to produce gold for nearly 17° lon. Though the Ural, in<lb break="yes"/>the years 1821 and 1822, only furnished 27 to 28 pud (440 to 456<lb break="yes"/>kils.) gold, yet the produce of the gold sand gradually rose, in the<lb break="yes"/>three following years (1823, 1824, and 1825), to 105, 206, and 237<lb break="yes"/>pud. According to the manuscript communication made me by the<lb break="yes"/>Russian minister of finance, Count Cancrien, &#x201C;Return of the Preci-<lb break="no"/>ous Metals obtained in the Russian Empire, and refined in the Mint<lb break="yes"/>of St. Petersburg,&#x201D; the amount of pure gold was, in</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <list>
                    <item>1828 ... ... ... ... ... 209 pud, and 29&#x2114;s.</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1829 ... ... ... ... 289 &#x201E; ...... 25</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1830 ... ... ... ... ... 347 &#x201E; ...... 27</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1831 ... ... ... ... 352 &#x201E; ...... 2</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1832 ... ... ... ... ... 380 &#x201E; ...... 31</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1833 ... ... ... ... 368 &#x201E; ...... 27</item>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <item>1834 <choice><sic>... ... .. ... ...</sic><corr type="editorial">... ... ... ... ...</corr></choice> 363 &#x201E; ...... 10</item>
                </list>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At the period of the expedition which I undertook into Northern<lb break="yes" />Asia, at the request of the Emperor Nicholas, the gold washing was con-<lb break="no"/>fined to the mountains on the European extremities of the Ural. The<lb break="yes"/>Altai [in Mongolisch, the golden mountain] furnished merely the<lb break="yes"/>inconsiderable quantity (about 1,900 marks) of gold which could be<lb break="yes"/>obtained from the silver ore of the rich mines of Sme&#x00EF;nogorsk, Rid-<lb break="no"/>derski, and Syrianowske. Since 1834, however, the industry of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="195" facs="#f0015"/> gold washers in this central part of Siberia has been unexpectedly<lb break="yes"/>rewarded. A bed of gold sand has been discovered, precisely simi-<lb break="no"/>lar to those on the declivity of the Ural. The house of Popof, so<lb break="yes"/>deservedly celebrated for the encouragement it has afforded for im-<lb break="no"/>proving the intercourse in the interior of Asia, has here also set a<lb break="yes"/>laudable example. Among the 398 pud (27,884 marks) of gold, pro-<lb break="no"/>duced by the entire Russian Empire in 1836, 293 pud, 26&#x2114;s., were<lb break="yes"/>from the Ural, and 104 pud, 15&#x2114;s., from the Altai. In the following<lb break="yes"/>year the produce of eastern Siberia had already so much increased<lb break="yes"/>that the Altai furnished 130 pud, the Ural (from crown and private<lb break="yes"/>washings), 309 pud, wash gold. If to these amounts we add 30 pud<lb break="yes"/>gold, contained in the ore found in the solid rocks of the Altai, it<lb break="yes"/>will give, for the entire produce of Russian gold for the year 1837,<lb break="yes"/>precisely 469 pud, or 7,644 kils. The gold washing in the Ural is,<lb break="yes"/>therefore, in a very gradual decline; the Altai, however, contributes<lb break="yes"/>so much to the general mass, that its produce, as compared with that<lb break="yes"/>of the Ural, is already as 4&#x2014;9&#x00BD;.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Concerning the actual situation of the gold sands in the Altai, the<lb break="yes"/>most recent information has been communicated by a distinguished<lb break="yes"/>geologist, my former travelling companion in the southern Ural, Mr.<lb break="yes"/>von Helmersen. The wash gold, which for some years past has<lb break="yes"/>been obtained in constantly increasing quantities in the eastern part<lb break="yes"/>of the Tunskisch district, does not belong to the great mountain<lb break="yes"/>chain itself, which we call the Altaian ore mountain, which Lede-<lb break="no"/>bour, Bunge, and Gebler, have explored, and in which the mountain<lb break="yes"/>Belucha, with its inaccessible snow peaks majestically raises itself to<lb break="yes"/>the height of the Wetterhorn, or the Peak of Teneriffe. The situa-<lb break="no"/>tion of the golden sands is observable on both, but especially in the<lb break="yes" />eastern side of a small mountain chain, which the Altai, in its course<lb break="yes"/>from east to west, sends out in the meridian of the Telezkischen<lb break="yes"/>Lake, and extends into the parallel of Tonsk. &#x201C;On the maps,&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>says my friend, Mr. von Helmersen, &#x201C;this mountain branch, produc-<lb break="no"/>ing wash gold, is distinguished by the names of the Abakauskisch,<lb break="yes"/>Kusneychrisch, and Alatau mountains. In direction, internal composi-<lb break="no"/>tion, and formation, it possesses the most striking similarity to the<lb break="yes" />Ural; it is, in fact, a repetition of it, only at less considerable length.<lb break="yes"/>The analogy goes so far that here, also, the eastern declivity is<lb break="yes"/>rich, the western much poorer, in gold. As it is precisely this<lb break="yes"/>western declivity which has been reserved by the crown, so they are<lb break="yes"/>almost entirely private adventurers who have profited by the produc-<lb break="no"/>tiveness of the Alatau (this branch of the Ural running towards the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="196" facs="#f0016"/> north).&#x201D; The importance of these observations of Mr. von Helmer-<lb break="no"/>sen cannot escape such geognosts as are familiar with my enquiries<lb break="yes"/>concerning the mountain system of the interior of Asia, and with the<lb break="yes"/>original views of Elie de Beaumont concerning parallelism and<lb break="yes"/>relative antiquity of the different mountain chains. I have not<lb break="yes"/>myself seen the northern beds of the Altaian gold sands, as the di-<lb break="no"/>rection of my journey was from Tobolsk, by Tara, through the<lb break="yes"/>Barakinskish steppes, to the western and southern Altai, and from<lb break="yes"/>thence to the Chinese frontier posts Chunimailachu, in the province<lb break="yes"/>Ili, northward from Lake Saysan.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The wash-gold of the Altai contains more silver than the gold of<lb break="yes" />the Ural. The Siberian merchants, powerfully seconded by the impe-<lb break="no"/>rial mining department, have now established winter washing also;<lb break="yes"/>and the working this new branch of Asiatic industry is the more re-<lb break="no"/>markable and satisfactory in that the workmen consist of well-paid<lb break="yes"/>volunteers. According to recent accounts, for which I am indebted<lb break="yes"/>to the minister of finance, Mr. von Cancrien, rich sand-beds have<lb break="yes"/>been discovered in the Salairskisch chain of mountains, as well as on<lb break="yes"/>the river Biriusa, which separates the governments of Teniseisk and<lb break="yes" />Irkutik. For the whole of Siberia, 240 licenses (permission to<lb break="yes" />work the sand-beds containing gold), have been granted.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Such, therefore, is the importance which the influx from the east-<lb break="no" />ward has attained in modern times (the principal object of the pre-<lb break="no"/>sent enquiry, being to point out the fluctuations of channel in the<lb break="yes"/>gold trade). Those 469 pud of Uralian and Altaian gold (the<lb break="yes"/>produce of the year 1837) are worth, in Prussian silver money,<lb break="yes"/>7,211,000 dollars, or about &#x00A3;1,031,650 sterling, which produce is<lb break="yes"/>only an eighth less than that of Minas Geraes in Brazil, in the richest<lb break="yes"/>years of the flourishing period from 1752 to 1761; one-third, how-<lb break="no"/>ever, less than the produce of New Grenada, Chili, and Mexico, shortly<lb break="yes"/>before the breaking out of the revolution in Spanish America. If<lb break="yes"/>we consider the enormous extent of the Siberian continent, and re-<lb break="no" />collect the rapid increase of gold from the Ural in the years 1822,<lb break="yes"/>1823, and 1824, it will appear extremely probable that the reflux<lb break="yes"/>from east to west (from Asia to Europe) has by no means reached<lb break="yes"/>its maximum. The produce of eastern Siberia will, perhaps, increase<lb break="yes"/>more rapidly than that of the washing of the Ural, where the richest<lb break="yes"/>beds were first (and in the beginning, unfortunately, only superfi-<lb break="no"/>cially) worked. In the hydrostatic separation on the washing floors,<lb break="yes"/>a considerable quantity of precious metals, which cling to grains of<lb break="yes"/>oxide of iron and other light substances, is undoubtedly lost. This is<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="197" facs="#f0017"/> not the place to enquire whether the ingenious and plausible method<lb break="yes"/>suggested by Colonel Anassaw, intendent at Slatoust, of amalgama-<lb break="no"/>tion with iron and the application of sulphur to the substance thus<lb break="yes"/>produced, would be successfully applicable on a large scale. When<lb break="yes"/>we consider the size of the masses to be smelted, the difficulty of<lb break="yes"/>transporting a sand so poor in gold, as well as the quantity of fuel<lb break="yes"/>required, the continued and well-directed experiments hitherto made<lb break="yes"/>would seem to have determined its impracticability.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The notions we have obtained, during the last fifteen years, con-<lb break="no" />cerning the present productiveness of Northern Asia in gold, lead us<lb break="yes"/>almost involuntarily back to the Issedones, Arimaspi, and the gold-<lb break="no"/>guarding griffins, for whom Aristeus of Proconnesus, and, two cen-<lb break="no"/>turies later, Herodotus, have obtained so lasting a reputation. I had<lb break="yes"/>the pleasure of visiting, in the southern Ural, the spot where, a few<lb break="yes"/>inches under the turf, masses of brilliant gold, weighing 13, 16, and<lb break="yes"/>even 24 Prussian pounds, were discovered. Still larger masses may<lb break="yes"/>have lain like pebbles, unobserved, on the surface of the ground.<lb break="yes"/>No wonder, therefore, if, even in remote antiquity, this gold was col-<lb break="no"/>lected by hunting and pastoral tribes; that the fame of such riches<lb break="yes"/>should resound to a distance, even to the Grecian colonies on the<lb break="yes" />Euxine&#x2014;colonies which, at a very early period, had established in-<lb break="no"/>tercourse with north-eastern Asia, beyond the Caspian Sea. Neither<lb break="yes"/>the trading Greeks nor the Scythians came themselves as far as the<lb break="yes"/>Issedones; they had intercourse only with the Argippei. Niebuhr,<lb break="yes"/>in his enquiries concerning the Scythians and Get&#x00E6; (enquiries by no<lb break="yes"/>means confirmed by what we have since learned concerning the di-<lb break="no"/>versities of race and structure of language among the northern<lb break="yes"/>tribes), places the Issedones and Arimaspi to the northward of<lb break="yes"/>Orenburg, that is, in the region so rich in gold, now become familiar<lb break="yes"/>to us, on the eastern declivity of the Ural. This opinion is supported<lb break="yes"/>in the valuable work of the privy counsellor Eichwald, recently<lb break="yes"/>published, <hi rendition="#i">On the Ancient Geography of the Caspian Sea.</hi>&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Heeren and Völchen, on the other hand, place this gold country of He-<lb break="no"/>rodotus in the Altai, and I admit that the local circumstances appear<lb break="yes"/>rather to justify the interpretation. Herodotus describes a trading<lb break="yes"/>route, along which, by means of the Issedones and Scythians, the<lb break="yes"/>gold of the northern Altai, or at least the fame of it, could reach the<lb break="yes"/>Hellespont. In order to penetrate as far as the Argippei, who are<lb break="yes"/>represented as bald-headed, with flat noses and large jaw bones, the<lb break="yes"/>Scythians and the Greeks of the Euxine colonies were compelled to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="198" facs="#f0018"/> employ seven interpreters of seven different languages.<note place="foot" n="*">Herodotus, iv., 24.</note> Since the<lb break="yes"/>discovery of such rich beds of gold sand in the mountain chain which<lb break="yes"/>the Altai sends out to the northward, in the parallel of Tonsk, the<lb break="yes"/>position of the Arimaspi in a region far to the eastward of the Ural,<lb break="yes"/>certainly gains in probability. The fable of the gold-guarding grif-<lb break="no"/>fins of Herodotus, according to the surmise of a learned and intelli-<lb break="no"/>gent traveller, Adolph <choice><sic>Herman</sic><corr type="editorial">Erman</corr></choice>, is connected with the fossil remains<lb break="yes"/>of antediluvian Pachyderm&#x00E6;, so frequently met with in Siberia, which<lb break="yes"/>the imagination of the native tribes has transformed into the claws<lb break="yes" />and head of a gigantic bird. &#x201C;Were we,&#x201D; concludes Mr. Erman,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;disposed to find in this arctic saga the prototype of the Grecian one<lb break="yes"/>of the griffins, it is strictly true that the northern searchers for ore<lb break="yes"/>draw the gold from under the griffins; for gold under beds of earth<lb break="yes"/>and peat, filled with these bones, is now, as formerly, one of the com-<lb break="no"/>monest phenomena.&#x201D; However attractive this explanation, the cir-<lb break="no" />cumstance of the fabulous beings (the griffins) being mentioned in<lb break="yes"/>the poems of Hesiod is somewhat opposed to it, as is also the fact of<lb break="yes"/>their decorating the gates of Persepolis as lion eagles, or Sphinges.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have already noticed the fact that in the Ural enormous masses<lb break="yes" />of gold are found a few inches below the turf; running water, or<lb break="yes"/>other trifling causes, may have so far laid them bare that they<lb break="yes"/>touched the very surface of the earth. The discovery of beds of sand<lb break="yes"/>containing gold beyond the Obi in Northern Asia, the increase in<lb break="yes"/>amount of one years&#x2019; produce of the Altaian or Kusnezkisch wash<lb break="yes"/>gold to the weight of 130 pud, is an event in the history of the gold<lb break="yes"/>trade; an event the more remarkable inasmuch as it belongs to that<lb break="yes"/>part of Asia more immediately subject to Europe, and the entire pro-<lb break="no"/>duce will consequently be thrown into the European gold market.<lb break="yes"/>However ancient may be the mining in solid ore in Siberia, under<lb break="yes"/>the indefinite denomination of &#x201C;Tschudischer Tchürfe,&#x201D; still the<lb break="yes"/>considerable masses of wrought gold found in the graves on first<lb break="yes"/>taking possession of that country, may be more readily accounted for<lb break="yes"/>by an early discovery of gold pebbles in diluvial soil near the surface<lb break="yes"/>of the earth. Müller, the excellent historian of Siberia, relates that<lb break="yes"/>a remarkable depreciation in the value of gold in Krasnojarsh took<lb break="yes"/>place on the first discovery of the treasures contained in the graves<lb break="yes" />(Karganui).</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The interior of Asia, between the mountain ranges of the Himay-<lb break="no" />laya and the Vulcanic Celestial mountain, forms, like China, one great<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="199" facs="#f0019"/> political and commercial community. However little we may know<lb break="yes"/>of those regions since the brilliant periods of the Mongol dynasty,<lb break="yes"/>at the close of the thirteenth century (from the travels of Marco<lb break="yes"/>Polo), still much information has recently been obtained (in the<lb break="yes"/>south through India, in the north through Siberia) by Europeans<lb break="yes"/>concerning the gold-sand beds of that extensive tract. The journals<lb break="yes"/>of Calcutta inform us that the rivers in the whole of western Thi-<lb break="no"/>bet contain gold, which the natives obtain by amalgamation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The old Indian mythologists make the ruler of the north (Kuwera)<lb break="yes" />the god of riches also; and it is remarkable enough that the resi-<lb break="no"/>dence of this deity (Alak&#x00E2;) must be sought for, not on the Himay-<lb break="no"/>laya itself, but on the Kail&#x00E2;sa, beyond the Himaylaya, in Thibet.<lb break="yes"/>Still further to the north-west, beyond the mountain chain of the Ku-<lb break="no"/>enlan, which separates the districts of Ladak and Khotan, Heeren<lb break="yes"/>places, and, I think, with much probability, the great golden sand<lb break="yes"/>deserts, visited by the Indians bordering on Kaschmir; and contain-<lb break="no"/>ing &#x201C;ants less than dogs, but larger than foxes.&#x201D; It is on the west-<lb break="no"/>ern declivity of Bolor that the most recent and intelligent explorer of<lb break="yes"/>this terra incognita (Alexander Burnes) has described the gold sand-<lb break="no"/>beds of Durwaz and the upper course of the Oxus.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Almost at the same moment in which the Ural opened its golden<lb break="yes" />treasures, and began to replace what the diminished produce of Bra-<lb break="no"/>zils was no longer in a condition to supply, strata containing gold<lb break="yes"/>were discovered in the southern part of the Alleghany, in Virginia,<lb break="yes"/>North and South Carolina, Georgia, Tennessee and Alabama. The<lb break="yes"/>most flourishing period of these American gold washings was from<lb break="yes"/>1830 to 1835.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is true that, in the last eight years, they have not produced<lb break="yes" />morethan 4&#x00BD; millions of dollars; the appearance, however, of gold so<lb break="yes"/>near to the coasts of the Atlantic is, in a geological point of view,<lb break="yes"/>deserving of more attention than has been given to it in Europe. It<lb break="yes"/>is a circumstance possessing great historical interest also, since the<lb break="yes"/>quantity of gold found by the first Spanish conquistadores, among<lb break="yes"/>the natives of Florida, need no longer be considered as the result of<lb break="yes"/>ancient intercourse with Mexico or Hayti. Jacob, in his oft-cited<lb break="yes"/>work, was only enabled to estimate the produce of the North Ame-<lb break="no"/>rican gold washing at 130,000 dollars; but in a few years subse-<lb break="no"/>quently it rose to 800,000, and even a million. In the county Ca-<lb break="no"/>varras (North Carolina) was discovered a golden pebble weighing<lb break="yes"/>28&#x2114;s. English, and near it several from 4 to 10&#x2114;s. Since my re-<lb break="no" />turn from Siberia I have incessantly, but almost fruitlessly, attempt-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="200" facs="#f0020"/> ed to procure more precise information concerning the progress of<lb break="yes"/>the gold washing in the southern states; and it is only quite recently<lb break="yes"/>that (owing to the kindness of the present bank director, Mr. Albert<lb break="yes"/>Gallatin, one of the most intelligent men of the present day) my<lb break="yes"/>wishes have been gratified. I here insert some extracts from the<lb break="yes"/>letter of this distinguished traveller. &#x201C;The productiveness of the<lb break="yes"/>gold mines of the Ural, and perhaps of the entire of Northern Asia,<lb break="yes" />must certainly have drawn your attention to our gold washing and<lb break="yes"/>mining in the southern States. I hope shortly, by the assistance of<lb break="yes"/>Professor Patterson (who is at the same time director of the mint),<lb break="yes"/>and Professor Renwick, of New York, both distinguished mineralo-<lb break="no"/>gists, to be in a condition to answer your geological questions. I<lb break="yes"/>send you, from official documents, a special report of what has been<lb break="yes"/>coined at the mint, from our inland gold, since 1824.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">ANNUAL DELIVERY OF GOLD AT THE MINT FROM THE MINES<lb break="yes"/>OF THE UNITED STATES.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Year</cell>
                        <cell>Virginia.</cell>
                        <cell>North<lb break="yes"/>Carolina.</cell>
                        <cell>South<lb break="yes"/>Carolina.</cell>
                        <cell>Georgia.</cell>
                        <cell>Tennes-<lb break="no"/>see.</cell>
                        <cell>Alabama.</cell>
                        <cell>Total.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Dollars.</cell>
                        <cell>Dollars.</cell>
                        <cell>Dollars.</cell>
                        <cell>Dollars.</cell>
                        <cell>Dollars.</cell>
                        <cell>Dollars.</cell>
                        <cell>Dollars.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1824</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>5,000</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>5,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1825</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>17,000</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>17,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1826</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>20,000</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>20,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1827</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>21,000</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>21,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1828</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>46,000</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>46,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1829</cell>
                        <cell>2,500</cell>
                        <cell>134,000</cell>
                        <cell>3,500</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>140,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1830</cell>
                        <cell>24,000</cell>
                        <cell>204,000</cell>
                        <cell>26,000</cell>
                        <cell>212,000</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>466,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1831</cell>
                        <cell>26,000</cell>
                        <cell>294,000</cell>
                        <cell>22,000</cell>
                        <cell>176,000</cell>
                        <cell>1,000</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>520,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1832</cell>
                        <cell>34,000</cell>
                        <cell>458,000</cell>
                        <cell>45,000</cell>
                        <cell>140,000</cell>
                        <cell>1,000</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>698,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1833</cell>
                        <cell>104,000</cell>
                        <cell>475,000</cell>
                        <cell>66,000</cell>
                        <cell>216,000</cell>
                        <cell>7,000</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>868,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1834</cell>
                        <cell>62,000</cell>
                        <cell>380,000</cell>
                        <cell>38,000</cell>
                        <cell>415,000</cell>
                        <cell>3,000</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>898,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1835</cell>
                        <cell>60,000</cell>
                        <cell>263,000</cell>
                        <cell>42,400</cell>
                        <cell>319,000</cell>
                        <cell>0,100</cell>
                        <cell>12,200</cell>
                        <cell>698,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1836</cell>
                        <cell>62,000</cell>
                        <cell>148,000</cell>
                        <cell>55,200</cell>
                        <cell>201,400</cell>
                        <cell>0,300</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2014;</cell>
                        <cell>467,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>374,000</cell>
                        <cell>2,465,000</cell>
                        <cell>298,100</cell>
                        <cell>1,680,300</cell>
                        <cell>12,400</cell>
                        <cell>12,200</cell>
                        <cell>4,844,500</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The profit, and with it the taste for mining speculations, have<lb break="yes" />rapidly declined since 1835. In a country in which uniform<lb break="yes" />prosperity is accompanied by unfettered intercourse, channels for<lb break="yes"/>the more profitable employment of capital will necessarily present<lb break="yes"/>themselves; in the history of the bullion trade, however, the masses<lb break="yes"/>obtained from the bowels of the earth and brought into circulation, as<lb break="yes"/>well as their ebb and flow in different directions, offer greater inte-<lb break="no"/>rest than the temporary profit afforded by the working of the mines.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The flow of the precious metals from Asia and America to our<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="201" facs="#f0021"/> smaller continent, and from it partially back again to the parent<lb break="yes"/>source, follows, like fluids, the laws of equilibrium. The rich, but<lb break="yes"/>almost unexplored, regions of central Asia and Africa, form smaller<lb break="yes"/>insulated basins, possessing slight intercourse with the coasts, and,<lb break="yes"/>consequently, with general commerce. Under the influence of<lb break="yes"/>western civilization, however, from Nertsckinsk, the Altai, and<lb break="yes"/>Ural, and beyond the Atlantic from the Missouri, there exists a conti-<lb break="no"/>nual flow in the intercourse of the precious metals; the exchangeable<lb break="yes"/>value of which, whether we consider the metals in relation to each<lb break="yes" />other, or as the standard of the price of wares, is by no means entire-<lb break="no"/>ly or principally determined by the increase or diminution in metallic<lb break="yes"/>production. This exchangeable value (I here repeat it) is affected in<lb break="yes"/>an equal degree by the complicated arrangements and fluctuating re-<lb break="no"/>lations of modern society; by an increasing and decreasing popula-<lb break="no"/>tion, and its progress in civilization; by the demand (regulated by<lb break="yes"/>the population) for an increased circulating capital; by the frequent-<lb break="no"/>ly recurring necessity of remittances of bullion, as well as their desti-<lb break="no" />nation; by the unequal wear and tear of the two precious metals;<lb break="yes"/>by the amount of paper money, as part of the circulating medium; all<lb break="yes"/>acting upon the existing metallic medium of exchange. A rise in<lb break="yes"/>the relative value of gold as compared with that of silver, may as<lb break="yes"/>easily occur during a general increase in production, as a temporary<lb break="yes"/>depression of the barometer, and an increased elevation of tempera-<lb break="no"/>ture, with a strong north-east wind. In the meterological changes<lb break="yes"/>of the atmosphere, as well as in the general exchange of the pre-<lb break="no"/>cious metals, many disturbing causes are contemporaneously at work.<lb break="yes"/>The effect of each individual cause, in raising or depressing prices, is<lb break="yes" />determinable; not, however (in the infinite number of accumulating<lb break="yes"/>disturbances), the amount of partial compensations, the nature and<lb break="yes"/>amount of the aggregate influence.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Any increase in the production which our imagination could call<lb break="yes" />into existence, would appear infinitely trifling compared with the ac-<lb break="no"/>cumulation of thousands of years now in circulation, were we to con-<lb break="no"/>sider these existing in coin or wrought up for useful purposes.<lb break="yes"/>Every increase, however inconsiderable, certainly produces its effects<lb break="yes"/>in the long run; but as an accumulating population, with increased<lb break="yes"/>acquirements, has occasion for a greater circulating capital, so, not-<lb break="no"/>withstanding the influx, by too frequent repartition, a sensible defici-<lb break="no"/>ency may be brought about. Before the important discoveries on<lb break="yes"/>the eastern side of the Ural, which began to produce their effects in<lb break="yes"/>the years 1823 and 1824 only, the exchangeable value of silver, as<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="202" facs="#f0022"/> compared with gold, in the important market of Hamburgh, was,<lb break="yes"/>taking the average of the years 1818 to 1822, as 1 : <formula notation="TeX">\frac{15}{75}</formula>; while,<lb break="yes"/>subsequently it fell, on the average of the five years from 1830 to<lb break="yes"/>1835, to 1: <formula notation="TeX">\frac{15}{73}</formula> only. In the same interval, in order to restore<lb break="yes"/>the metallic currency in England, as I have already stated, 1,294,000<lb break="yes" />marks were brought into circulation. What share, therefore, has<lb break="yes" />the diminished exportation of precious metals from the New World,<lb break="yes"/>had upon this alteration in the exchangeable value? It is scarcely<lb break="yes"/>necessary to take into calculation the Brazilian gold washing, since<lb break="yes"/>its annual supply, during that period, scarcely amounted to 1700<lb break="yes"/>marks.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Now if we assume that, in the twelve years immediately subse-<lb break="no" />quent to the revolution, the production of Spanish America had sunk<lb break="yes"/>to below one-third of what it had beeen during its last flourishing pe-<lb break="no"/>riod (1800&#x2014;1806), still the twelve years diminution only amounts to<lb break="yes"/>83,200 kils. Now the Ural, in the years 1823 to 1827, has already<lb break="yes"/>furnished compensation to the amount of 19,300 kils; so that the di-<lb break="no"/>minution in the quantity of gold received in Europe only amounts, for<lb break="yes"/>the whole of these twelve years, to 286,000 marks. I have purposely<lb break="yes"/>selected an example presenting tolerably exact numerical elements.<lb break="yes"/>The result is, a decrease in the importation of gold, amounting to<lb break="yes" />between one-fourth and one-fifth of the quantity coined, during the<lb break="yes"/>twelve years, by the London mint. If, therefore, we consider the ex-<lb break="no"/>changeable value of the precious metals, freed from the inconsidera-<lb break="no"/>ble local casualties&#x2014;the value of gold bars at Hamburg, namely&#x2014;we<lb break="yes"/>shall be unable to discover, between 1816 and 1837, either the in-<lb break="no"/>fluence of the Asiatic mines, or the diminished production of Spa-<lb break="no"/>nish America.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The maximum which the exchangeable value of gold attained in<lb break="yes" />1827, has been maintained, with trifling variations, till 1832; at<lb break="yes"/>which period a gradual, but regularly progressing, depreciation is<lb break="yes"/>observable. The Russian gold, from the Ural and Siberia, has par-<lb break="no"/>tially contributed to this result. We must not, however, forget<lb break="yes"/>that the entire produce of Russia, whatever importance we may<lb break="yes"/>attach to it in other respects, in the years 1823 to 1837, only<lb break="yes"/>amounts to about 302,000 marks&#x2014;one-nineteenth less than the di-<lb break="no"/>minished production of Spanish America, in the years 1816&#x2014;1829.<lb break="yes"/>And even at the present moment, the renewed working of the gold<lb break="yes"/>mines in the free states of South America, has not been so general<lb break="yes"/>as that of silver. Besides, the North American states, scarcely re-<lb break="no"/>covered from their financial difficulties, have occasion for considera-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="203" facs="#f0023"/> ble remittances of bullion from Europe. This causes a drain to the<lb break="yes"/>westward, which, together with the other continually acting causes,<lb break="yes"/>may have brought about the effects which we are disposed to attri-<lb break="no"/>bute to the increased produce of Asia alone. The principal ground,<lb break="yes"/>however, of the inconsiderable influence produced by the contribu-<lb break="no"/>tions from the Ural and Northern Asia lies, as I have already re-<lb break="no"/>marked, in the relative insignificance of the influx, compared with<lb break="yes"/>the quantity of precious metals already existing. The exports to<lb break="yes"/>Asia, which, in another place and at different periods, I have had<lb break="yes"/>occasion to examine, are decidedly on the decline. In the year 1831<lb break="yes"/>Jacob still estimated the annual loss in balance of trade by the Cape<lb break="yes" />of Good Hope at &#x00A3;2,000,000 sterling. As far as I can recollect,<lb break="yes"/>this was also the opinion of that great statesman, Huskisson, so pre-<lb break="no"/>maturely taken from us. Notwithstanding the general use of cof-<lb break="no"/>fee, tea, sugar, and cocoa&#x2014;articles unknown in the fifteenth century<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;the trade in spices is still a considerable article in the passive com-<lb break="no"/>mercial balance of Europe. In the states of the German Union, the<lb break="yes"/>consumption of spices, according to the most recent official enquiries,<lb break="yes"/>has increased, during the years 1834, 1835, and 1836, from<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#et">2,426,000<lb break="yes"/>2,592,000<lb break="yes"/>To 2,876,000 Prussian dollars.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In France, the consumption in the same years was only<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#et">5,476,000<lb break="yes"/>3,982,000<lb break="yes" />4,856,000 francs.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the whole of Europe, however, with a population of at least<lb break="yes" />228 millions, it is probably not less than fourteen to sixteen millions<lb break="yes"/>of dollars, two-thirds of which consist of vanilla, nutmegs, pepper,<lb break="yes"/>and cinnamon. When we reflect how considerable must be the<lb break="yes"/>amount of the value of spices in the present consumption of Europe,<lb break="yes"/>compared with what it was at the conclusion of the fifteenth cen-<lb break="no"/>tury, though constituting the most important part of the then exist-<lb break="no"/>ing commerce, we shall discover another remarkable example of the<lb break="yes"/>potency of the metals, when exercising their concentrated force on<lb break="yes"/>a narrow space (at that time, the shores of the Mediterranean and<lb break="yes"/>western Europe). The trade in spices accidentally caused the dis-<lb break="no"/>covery of the new continent; it led the Portuguese round the<lb break="yes"/>southern extremities of Africa to India, as it had the Greeks<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="204" facs="#f0024"/> and Romans to Taprobane. At the time when Christopher Colum-<lb break="no"/>bus sought to &#x201C;reach the east through the west,&#x201D; Paul Toscanelli,<lb break="yes"/>of Florence, writes to him, as early as the 24th of June, 1474, &#x201C;I<lb break="yes"/>am rejoiced to hear that you are approaching the accomplishment of<lb break="yes"/>your great and laudable desire, to reach, by a nearer route, <hi rendition="#i">there,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>where spices grow, &#x2018;onde naccen las especerias.&#x2019;&#x201D; With what com-<lb break="no"/>plaints do the writings of the Italians abound, what imprecations<lb break="yes"/>are heaped upon the Portuguese, because they had penetrated by<lb break="yes"/>sea to India, and threatened to annihilate the spice trade of the Ve-<lb break="no" />netian, Pisan, and Genoese merchants! Cardinal Bembo calls it a<lb break="yes" />&#x201C;malum inopinatum,&#x201D; and seeks for philosophical grounds of conso-<lb break="no"/>lation. Petrus Martyr d&#x2019;Anghiera writes to his learned friend,<lb break="yes"/>Pomponius Latus, &#x201C;Portugalenses trans &#x00E6;quinoctium aliamque <hi rendition="#i">arc-<lb break="no"/>ton</hi>, aromatum commercia prosequuntur, Alexandrinos ac Damas-<lb break="no"/>cenos mercatores ad medullas extenuant.&#x201D; The opinion propagated<lb break="yes" />by the Genoese, that the new route by the Cape of Good Hope<lb break="yes" />would soon be relinquished, because the spices suffered from the sea<lb break="yes"/>air in the long transit, found but little credence; and the long ca-<lb break="no"/>lumniated Amerigo Vespucci (only three years after Gama), with<lb break="yes"/>his usual acuteness, detected the right point of view here also.<lb break="yes"/>He observes, in a newly-discovered letter, written to Lorenzo Pietro<lb break="yes"/>de Medici, 4th June, 1501, from the Cape de Verde islands, on<lb break="yes"/>meeting the remains of Cabral&#x2019;s fleet, on its return to the Tagus,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;You will soon hear great news from Portugal. The king has<lb break="yes"/>now a rich and most important commerce in his hands (grandissimo<lb break="yes"/>traffico e gran richezza). May Heaven lend its blessing thereto<lb break="yes"/>[Vespucci was at that time in the Portuguese pay]! Now will<lb break="yes"/>the spices go from Portugal to Alexandria and Italy, instead of (as<lb break="yes"/>hitherto) from Alexandria to Portugal. Such is the way of the<lb break="yes"/>world (Cosi va el mundo)!&#x201D;<note place="foot" n="*">A pud is equal to thirty-six pounds weight. The kilogramme is about<lb break="yes"/>two and a quarter pounds weight. The mark of silver is two pounds two<lb break="yes"/>shillings sterling; the mark of gold, eight ounces. The piastre is four shil-<lb break="no"/>lings and fourpence sterling.</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <dateline>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Berlin, June,</hi> 1838.</dateline>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 