<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On the production of gold and silver and its fluctuations</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:07</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">V.79</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-18-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-01.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-02.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-05.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-17.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-18-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On the production of gold and silver and its fluctuations</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1849</date>
          <pubPlace>Baltimore, Maryland</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Bankers’ Magazine, and State Financial Register&lt;/i&gt; 3:9 (März 1849), S. 538–545; 3:10 (April 1849), S. [589]–595; 3:12 (Juni 1849), S. [709]–718.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Fußnoten mit Asterisken, Kreuzen, Doppelstrichen, Paragraphen und Absatzmarken; Schmuck: Kapitälchen; Tabellensatz.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="538" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">ON THE PRODUCTION OF GOLD AND SILVER AND<lb break="yes"/>ITS FLUCTUATIONS.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#k">by baron alexander von humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Translated for the Bankers&#x2019; Magazine, from the Journal des Economistes; March,<lb break="yes"/>April, May, 1848.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>According to Herodotus (iii. 106) the richest productions have been<lb break="yes"/>assigned to the ends of the earth, in the unequal distribution of the<lb break="yes"/>wealth and treasures of the soil. This assertion is made not only upon<lb break="yes"/>that mournful sentiment, belonging to the human race, of happiness be-<lb break="no"/>ing always at a distance; but it expresses the fact that the Greeks,<lb break="yes"/>inhabiting a temperate zone, received in their commerce with other<lb break="yes"/>people, gold and spices, amber and tin, from countries far remote. In<lb break="yes"/>proportion as the commerce of the Phenicians, of the Edomites on the<lb break="yes"/>gulf of Akaba [Ezion-geber<note place="foot" n="*">Passages and words in brackets are the Translator&#x2019;s.</note>] and of the Egyptians under the Ptolemies<lb break="yes"/>and the Romans, lifted slowly the veil which had so long hung over<lb break="yes"/>the coasts of Southern Asia, were received at first hand the products of<lb break="yes"/>the torrid zone; and men&#x2019;s lively and active imagination continually<lb break="yes"/>carried farther and farther east, the deposites of the metallic treasures<lb break="yes"/>of the earth. Twice, at epochs so important to commerce, (that of the<lb break="yes"/>Lagides and of the Cesars) as well as at the close of the 15th century,<lb break="yes" />during the Portuguese discoveries, the same people, the Arabs, showed<lb break="yes"/>to the West the route to India. At this moment, Ophir (the El-Dorado<lb break="yes"/>for Solomon) was pushed to the east of the Ganges. There, was ima-<lb break="no"/>gined to be that <hi rendition="#i">Chrysos,</hi> sought so long by the travellers of the middle<lb break="yes"/>ages and regarded, now as an island, now as a district of the Golden<lb break="yes" />Chersonese. The quantity of gold which Borneo and Sumatra still put<lb break="yes"/>in circulation, according to John Crawford, accounts for the ancient<lb break="yes"/>fame of this region. Close by Chrysos, country of <hi rendition="#i">gold</hi> and aim of<lb break="yes"/>Indian adventurers, must be found, by necessary relation and a sort of<lb break="yes"/>symmetry, according to the then ideas of systematic geography, a<lb break="yes"/>country of <hi rendition="#i">silver,</hi> an island, <hi rendition="#i">Argyros;</hi> as if to blend the two precious<lb break="yes"/>metals&#x2014;the riches of Ophir and of Iberian Tartessus [Tarshish.] The<lb break="yes"/>geographical myths of classic antiquity are reflected, but with varying<lb break="yes" />phases, in the geography of the middle ages. In the system of the Arab<lb break="yes"/>Edrisi and Bakoui, we find at the extremity of the Indian Ocean, an<lb break="yes"/>island <hi rendition="#i">Sahabet</hi> with sands of gold; and beside it, <hi rendition="#i">Saila</hi> (which must<lb break="yes" />not be confounded with Ceylon or Serendib) where the dogs and mon-<lb break="no"/>keys wear golden collars.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>To this idea of <hi rendition="#i">remoteness,</hi> was joined another, as a characteristic<lb break="yes"/>sign of the veritable country of gold and of all the precious products of<lb break="yes"/>the earth, viz. that of <hi rendition="#i">tropical heat.</hi> &#x201C;Until your Excellency shall have<lb break="yes"/>been finding men who are black,&#x201D; writes in 1495, a Catalan lapidary,<lb break="yes"/>Jaime Ferrer, to the admiral Christopher Columbus, &#x201C;you need not<lb break="yes"/>expect any great things nor veritable treasures, such as spices, diamonds<lb break="yes"/>or gold.&#x201D; This letter has been recently found in a book printed at<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="539" facs="#f0002"/> Barcelona, in 1845, bearing this singular title: <hi rendition="#i">Sentencias Catholicas<lb break="yes"/>del divi poeta Dant.</hi> [Catholic Maxims of the divine poet, Dante.]<lb break="yes"/>The richness of the gold mines of the Ural, which extend in the north-<lb break="no" />ern basin of the Volga up to where the ground hardly thaws in the<lb break="yes"/>summer months; the diamonds which have been discovered, near 60°<lb break="yes"/>N. latitude, on the European slope of the Ural, by two of my compan-<lb break="no"/>ions in the Expedition, which I made in 1829 by order of the Emperor<lb break="yes"/>Nicholas,<note place="foot" n="*">Reise nach dem Ural, etc. [Journey to the Ural, the Alta&#x00EF; and the Caspian<lb break="yes"/>Sea; by A. v. Humboldt, G. Rose and G. Ehrenberg,] t. i. p. 352&#x2014;373.</note> do not, to be sure, exactly support the hypothesis that would<lb break="yes"/>connect the existence of gold and diamonds on the one hand, with the<lb break="yes"/>heat of the tropics and colored races on the other. Christopher Co-<lb break="no"/>lumbus, who attached a moral and religious value to gold, since, (says<lb break="yes"/>he,) &#x201C;the possessor of it attains every thing in this world and even can<lb break="yes"/>open&#x201D; (no doubt, by paying for masses,) &#x201C;the gate of paradise to many<lb break="yes"/>a soul,&#x201D;<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">
                        <hi rendition="#i">El oro,</hi> (writes Columbus to Queen Isabella,) es excellentissimo, con el se hace<lb break="yes"/>tesoro y con el tesoro quien lo tiene, hace quanto quiere con el mundo y llega a que<lb break="yes" />hecha las animas a paraiso. See upon this gold-eulogy my <hi rendition="#i">Examen Critique,</hi> etc.<lb break="yes"/>[Critical Review of the History of Geography and the Progress of Nautical As-<lb break="no"/>tronomy during the 15th and 16th centuries, in fol.] pp. 38 and 131.</note> Christopher Columbus, I say, was altogether a partisan of<lb break="yes"/>the system of the lapidary Ferrer. He looked for Zipangou (Japan)<lb break="yes"/>which then was passing for the golden island Chrysos; and when on<lb break="yes"/>14 November 1492, he was coasting along the island of Cuba, which<lb break="yes"/>he considered a part of the continent of Eastern Asia (Cathay), he wrote<lb break="yes"/>in his journal: &#x201C;Judging by the <hi rendition="#i">great heat</hi> which I am suffering, the<lb break="yes"/>country must be rich in gold.&#x201D; It was thus that false analogies made<lb break="yes"/>men forget what classical antiquity had told us of the treasures in metal<lb break="yes"/>of the Massaget&#x00E6; and the Arismaspi in the extreme north of Europe;<lb break="yes"/>I say, <hi rendition="#i">of Europe,</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Herodotus, iii. 116.</note> for the flat and desert country of Northern Asia,<lb break="yes"/>the Siberia of modern times, passed then with its forests of pine, for a<lb break="yes"/>monotonous continuation of the low countries of Belgium, along the<lb break="yes"/>Baltic and of Sarmatia.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If we glance at once over the whole history of the commercial rela-<lb break="no" />tions of Europe, we see that antiquity seeks in Asia for the richest<lb break="yes"/>sources of gold; while the middle ages and the three centuries since,<lb break="yes"/>place them in the New continent. But in fact, and since the commence-<lb break="no"/>ment of the 19th century, it is once more in Asia, but only in a different<lb break="yes"/>zone, that these richest sources spring. This change in the direction of<lb break="yes"/>the current, this compensation which accidental discoveries in the north<lb break="yes"/>afford, when in the south the extraction of this metal seemed suddenly<lb break="yes" />to fall off, calls for a grave and deep research founded upon numerical<lb break="yes"/>data; for in political economy, as well as in the study of physical phe-<lb break="no"/>nomena, <hi rendition="#i">numbers</hi> are always the most decisive element; they become<lb break="yes"/>judges, without appeal and inflexible, of the causes so variously reasoned<lb break="yes"/>by political economists.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We learn from the profound researches of Boeckh<note place="foot" n="||">Economie
                        Politique des Atheniens, vol. i. p. 6&#x2013;31.</note> how, when the<lb
                        break="yes"/>Persian wars and the expedition of Alexander to India, had
                        broken<lb break="yes"/>down the barriers of the East, gold accumulated by
                    degrees among the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="540" facs="#f0003"/> European Greeks; how in the times of Demosthenes,
                    for instance, the<lb break="yes"/>precious metals were worth five times less
                    than in the days of Solon.<lb break="yes"/>The current then was from the east to
                    the west; and the influx of gold<lb break="yes"/>was so great that while, when
                    Herodotus lived, the ratio of gold to<lb break="yes"/>silver was as 1:13, it
                    became at the death of Alexander and for a<lb break="yes"/>hundred years after,
                    as 1:10.<note place="foot" n="*">See the learned rectification of the monetary
                        hypothesis of Garnier by Letronne:<lb break="yes"/>Considerations,
                        &#x0026;c. [General Considerations upon the value of the Greek and<lb
                            break="yes"/>Roman Money.] 1817, p. 112.</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The less general and extensive were commercial relations in the<lb break="yes"
                    />ancient world, the more great and sudden must, of course, have been the<lb
                        break="yes"/>variations in relative value of gold and silver. Thus, in Rome,
                    we find<lb break="yes"/>that in consequence of a local accumulation of one of
                    the precious<lb break="yes"/>metals, a little while after the conquest of
                    Syracuse, the ratio of gold to<lb break="yes"/>silver was as 1:17&#x2150;; while
                    under Julius C&#x00E6;sar, it fell for some time<lb break="yes"/>to 1:8<formula
                        notation="TeX">\frac{13}{14}</formula>. Also the less the quantity of one
                    metal existing in any<lb break="yes"/>country, the more easy it is to produce
                    these enormous fluctuations<lb break="yes"/>by an importation from abroad. The
                    world at present, by the uni-<lb break="no"/>versality and promptness of
                    relations which must balance throughout,<lb break="yes"/>and by the magnitude of
                    the existing quantities of gold and silver, tends<lb break="yes"/>to maintain a
                    stability in the relative value of the two metals. After<lb break="yes"/>the
                    wars of Independence, the product in metal of Spanish America<lb break="yes"
                    />continued for some years to be only the third of its previous annual<lb
                        break="yes"/>mean; and yet it is not to this circumstance even, that we are
                    to attri-<lb break="no"/>bute the slight oscillations which are manifested here
                    and there. It is<lb break="yes"/>quite otherwise with the ratio of silver to
                    another metal which has<lb break="yes"/>been obtained as yet only in small
                    quantity, and which is besides very<lb break="yes"/>unequally
                    distributed&#x2014;I mean, <hi rendition="#i">platinum.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We do not find among the ancients any statistical data indicating<lb break="yes" />some general result to be compared with what we know of the actual<lb break="yes"/>metallic product of entire countries. Their administrative policy<lb break="yes"/>offered none of those controls which the complex and refined tariff-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>system of the Arabs&#x2014;that commercial people, who calculated every<lb break="yes"/>thing and tabulated all&#x2014;communicated in after-times to the States of<lb break="yes"/>southern and western Europe. The assertion of Pliny (xii. 18,) that<lb break="yes"/>the commerce with India, Serica, [China] and Yemen was drawing every<lb break="yes" />year from the Roman Empire a hundred million sesterces in the pre-<lb break="no"/>cious metals, that is to say, according to Letronne, estimating these<lb break="yes"/>sesterces according to the value of silver at that epoch, 33000 mark-<lb break="no"/>weights of silver; (the half only of what the silver mines of Saxony<lb break="yes"/>produce annually)&#x2014;this assertion is isolated and problematical.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In this defect of general results, it would be important to have<lb break="yes" />numerical instances of the partial wealth in money of certain mining<lb break="yes"/>districts; which we might compare with the yield of similar regions<lb break="yes"/>now, weight for weight in an absolute sense, and without considering<lb break="yes"/>gold as the measure in value of determinate quantities of cereal grains.<lb break="yes"/>The treasure which a sovereign leaves as the fruit of conquest or of<lb break="yes"/>long exactions, testifies only what may have been accumulated over an<lb break="yes"/>indefinite extent of country and in a period which we cannot count.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="541" facs="#f0004"/> Results of this last kind may, however, be compared with the data<lb break="yes"/>which statists venture to give upon the quantity of precious metals<lb break="yes"/>existing in a State at some certain epoch. Thus Cyrus, in the account<lb break="yes"/>of Pliny (xxxiii. 15,) collected from his conquest of Asia, 34000 pounds<lb break="yes"/>of gold, not counting what had been converted into plate; and yet this<lb break="yes"/>quantity hardly equals the fruit of two years work in the mines of the<lb break="yes"/>Ural. Again, Appian, upon documents, estimates the treasure of Ptolemy<lb break="yes" />Philadelphus at 740000 talents; that is to say, 700 millions of Spanish<lb break="yes"/>dollars, if they were Egyptian talents, or 180 millions if they were the<lb break="yes"/>smaller talents of Ptolemy. &#x201C;This assertion seems fabulous&#x201D; says the<lb break="yes"/>celebrated author of the <hi rendition="#i">Political Economy of the Athenians,</hi> &#x201C;but I do<lb break="yes"/>not venture to question the veracity of the historian. In this treasure<lb break="yes"/>was a large quantity of gold and silver manufactured. The States of<lb break="yes"/>this Prince were entirely exhausted; imposts and taxes were extorted<lb break="yes"/>by greedy farmers-general with arms. The revenues of C&#x0153;le-Syria,<lb break="yes"/>Phenicia, Judea and Samaria, alone, were farmed out by Ptolemy<lb break="yes"/>Evergetes for 8000 talents; and a Jew bought them at a hundred per<lb break="yes"/>cent. advance.&#x201D; Mr. William Jacob, in an excellent work published at<lb break="yes"/>the request of Mr. Secretary Huskisson, under the title of <hi rendition="#i">Historical<lb break="yes"/>Enquiry on Precious Metals,</hi> (vol. i. p. 23,) confirms the assertion of<lb break="yes"/>the great German philosopher. The higher of the two estimates above<lb break="yes"/>would approach the quantity of coin actually in circulation in France<lb break="yes" />and Belgium; the lower would nearly equal the coin circulating in<lb break="yes"/>England.<note place="foot" n="*">From the researches of Mr. Michel Chevalier, (Letters on N. America, v. i. p.<lb break="yes"/>394) the coin circulating in France, is valued at 3000 millions and, in England, at<lb break="yes"/>1000 millions of francs. Neckar had before estimated the circulation of France at<lb break="yes"/>2200 millions of francs; while Adam Smith rates that of Great Britain at 30 millions<lb break="yes"/>of pounds sterling only. In the Prussian States, the circulation is, according to<lb break="yes"/>Hoffmann, only from 90 to 120 millions of thalers. The minting in Prussia from<lb break="yes"/>1764 to 1836, of all kinds of coin, including the fifteenths of a thaler, amounts, sub-<lb break="no" />tracting what has been withdrawn during that time by the mint itself, to 182.856.020<lb break="yes"/>thalers. (Die Lehre <choice><sic>von</sic><corr type="editorial">vom</corr></choice> Gelde, [Science of the Mint, by J. G. Hoffmann,] 1838,<lb break="yes"/>p. 171.) The assemblage of such large sums as these may throw some light upon<lb break="yes"/>the data left us by antiquity.</note> According to Strabo, Alexander succeeded in collecting at<lb break="yes"/>Ecbatana 380000 talents.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">The treasure left by Cyrus was almost three times as large as this. Pliny<lb break="yes"/>(xxx. 3,) values it at 500000 talents in gold and silver. As this treasure may have<lb break="yes"/>diminished considerably after the death of Cyrus, Sainte-Croix (<hi rendition="#i" >Examen Crit. des<lb break="yes"/>Historiens d&#x2019; Alexandre,</hi> p. 429,) concludes that the whole of the precious metal<lb break="yes" />which the Macedonian collected in Persia, amounted but to 330000 talents. Upon<lb break="yes"/>the almost unexampled concentration of precious metals in Italy, under the C&#x00E6;sars,<lb break="yes"/>see Letronne, u. s. p. 121.</note> It must not be forgotten, that whilst now,<lb break="yes" />the precious metals are spread more equally over great extents of<lb break="yes"/>country and among dense populations; then, they were concentrated at<lb break="yes"/>a few points of the earth and in the treasuries of sovereigns.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Undoubtedly, the great quantity of gold which was pouring west-<lb break="no" />ward, came from the interior of Asia, from the north-north-east of La-<lb break="no"/>dakh [Western Thibet] from the upper part of the basin of the Oxus<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Burnes: Travels in Bokhara, v. ii. p. 265.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>(between the Hindoo-Khosh and the highlands of Pamez, on the western<lb break="yes"/>slope of the Bolor) from Bactriana and the eastern satrapies of the Per-<lb break="no"/>sian Empire; but it is easier to determine the direction of the current<lb break="yes"/>
                    
                    
                    <pb n="542" facs="#f0005"/> of specie than the particular position of its different sources and their<lb break="yes"/>relative abundance. The place where grew the story of the gold-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>guarding <hi rendition="#i" >ants,</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">[Herod. iii. 102. Plin. H. N. xi. 36.]</note> scattered over the mountains of Derden, must be far off<lb break="yes"/>from the griffins of the Arimaspians. This story seems to belong to<lb break="yes"/>the plains of Kaschgar and Askou, between the parallel chains of the<lb break="yes"/>celestial mountains [the Thian-chan of the Chinese and Mouzdagh of<lb break="yes"/>the Turks] and of the Kouenloun where the river Tarim pours itself<lb break="yes" />into the Lop. We shall recur presently to the Arimaspians dwelling<lb break="yes"/>much farther to the north, when we come to speak of the great masses of<lb break="yes"/>gold found in the Ural, immediately under the surface. The fame of the<lb break="yes"/>riches of India echoed even as far as Persia; to be there, it is true, very<lb break="yes"/>often misinterpreted. Ctesias,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Opp. reliq. ed. Bähr. Ind. cap. iv. p. 248, 271.</note> of the family of the Asclepiades, the<lb break="yes"/>physician of Artaxerxes Mnemon, describes, almost without being aware,<lb break="yes" />under the image of a fountain of gold, an actual furnace whence the<lb break="yes"/>fluid metal run into vases, i. e. into clay moulds. Nearer to the Greeks<lb break="yes"/>were found Lydia channelled with rivers that flow from the Tmolus,<lb break="yes"/>Phrygia and Colchis, districts rich in gold. The nature of the auriferous<lb break="yes"/>soil here, so easy to exhaust, explains to the practical miner how some<lb break="yes"/>of these countries visited again, seem barren to the explorer. If for<lb break="yes"/>instance now, one were to examine the ravines and vallies of Cuba and<lb break="yes"/>of S. Domingo, or even the coast of Veragua, how difficult, without the<lb break="yes" />historical evidence which we possess, would it be to believe the rich-<lb break="no"/>ness of the mines of these very regions at the close of the 15th century!<lb break="yes"/>Under-ground mining, properly so called, of auriferous veins, lasts a<lb break="yes"/>much longer time, when no external circumstance disturbs it. Precisely<lb break="yes"/>because we do not know in advance the whole deposite, for the mine<lb break="yes"/>discovers itself in proportion as it is worked, a more durable element is<lb break="yes"/>offered to human activity. How few of the forty gold-washing sites,<lb break="yes"/>so carefully described by Strabo, can be recognized now! This obser-<lb break="no" />vation, founded upon positive analogies and upon the recognized prin-<lb break="no"/>ciples of mining, is all the more to be made here, since a vain scepticism<lb break="yes"/>triumphs in attempting to shake the traditions of Antiquity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The part of Europe known to the Greeks, was in respect to its me-<lb break="no"
                    />tallic wealth, as much behind Asia, as later, the whole European Con-<lb
                        break="no"/>tinent was behind the New World. This last ratio,<note
                        place="foot" n="&#x2021;">The elements of this estimate are contained in the
                        11th chapter of my Essai<lb break="yes"/>Politique, &#x0026;c. [Political
                        Essay on the Kingdom of New Spain] t. iii. p. 400.<lb break="yes"/>[Paris,
                        1811, 8vo.] The relative produce of gold was then 1300 kil. and 17300<lb
                            break="yes"/>kil. [2800 lb. and 38000 lb. avoirdupois, nearly:] and the
                        relative produce of silver<lb break="yes"/>was 52700 kil. and 795600 kil.
                        [equal to 116000 lb. and 1750000 lb. avdp. nearly.]</note> that is to
                        say,<lb break="yes"/>the relative intensity of product in Europe and
                    America, was, at the<lb break="yes"/>commencement of the 19th century, when the
                    mines of the Spanish<lb break="yes"/>colonies were worked in their greatest
                    activity, for gold as 1:13 and<lb break="yes"/>for silver as 1:15. I apprehend
                    even, that such a ratio, at the period<lb break="yes"/>of Alexander and of the
                    Ptolemies, would be found, if one had only<lb break="yes"/>statistical data upon
                    it, still more unfavorable for Europe, especially in<lb break="yes"/>regard to
                    gold. Greece herself, it is true, together with the at first very<lb break="yes"
                    />productive silver mines of Laurium, had a considerable amount of gold<lb
                        break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="543" facs="#f0006"/> in the mines of Thessaly, in the Pang&#x00E6;an
                    mountains on the frontiers of<lb break="yes"/>Macedon and Thrace, and amid the
                    early establishments<note place="foot" n="*">Otfr. Müller, History of the
                        Hellenic tribes, t. i. p. 115. Gold-mine near Skapte<lb break="yes"/>Hyle
                        (Böckh, Corp. Inscrip. t. i. p. 219.)</note> of the Phe-<lb break="no"
                    />nicians opposite to the island of Thrasos. Iberia, too, was a region of<lb
                        break="yes"/>silver for others than the Phenicians and Carthaginians.
                        Tartessus<lb break="yes"/>and Ophir, (this last being either Arabia<note
                        place="foot" n="&#x2020;">On this subject so often treated, see a Memoir of
                        remarkable philological criti-<lb break="no"/>cism, by Dr. Keil, of Dorpat.
                        De la Navigation, &#x0026;c. [On the Voyage to Ophir and<lb break="yes"
                        />Tarshish,] 1834, p. 61, 70.</note> or the eastern coast of Africa,<lb
                        break="yes"/>or even, as Heeren will have it, a generic appellative
                    designating indefi-<lb break="no"/>nitely the rich countries of the South) were
                    the double object of the<lb break="yes"/>united fleets of Solomon and Hiram.
                    Although amid all the metallic<lb break="yes"/>wealth of Spain, the silver of
                    B&#x0153;tica [Andalusia] and of the district of<lb break="yes"/>Carthagena, a
                    city founded by Hamilcar Barca, was for a long while<lb break="yes"/>the
                    principal object of foreign commerce; nevertheless, during many a<lb break="yes"
                    />year, Gallicia, Lusitania, and above all, the Asturias, furnished 20000<lb
                        break="yes"/>pounds of gold,<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Böckh, Economie
                        Politique, t. i. p. 15. The port of Carthage even holds a sand<lb
                            break="yes"/>of gold thrown in by the Mediterranean, between the river
                        Miliana and cape Sidi-<lb break="no"/>Bou-Sa&#x00EF;d. The inhabitants, who
                        are poor, turn it to profit at this day. Dureau de<lb break="yes"/>la Malle,
                        Recherches, &#x0026;c. [Researches into the topography of Carthage,] 1835,
                            p.<lb break="yes"/>251.</note> that is to say, almost as much as Brazil
                    at the most<lb break="yes"/>flourishing epoch of its mines. There is nothing
                    astonishing, therefore,<lb break="yes"/>in the Iberian peninsula, early visited,
                    acquiring with the Phenicians and<lb break="yes"/>Carthaginians the reputation
                    of a Western El-dorado. There is no doubt<lb break="yes"/>that in many
                    localities which shew now only faint metallic traces, the<lb break="yes"
                    />original soil formerly was covered quite near the surface with beds of<lb
                        break="yes"/>auriferous sand, or sown with the debris of some formerly
                    massive ore<lb break="yes"/>containing gold. The local importance of these mines
                    of southern<lb break="yes"/>Europe is incontestable; but in comparison with
                    Asia, their metallic<lb break="yes"/>product was small. This last continent
                    remained for a long time the<lb break="yes"/>principal source of the precious
                    metals; and the direction<note place="foot" n="||">Letronne, p. 105, 123.</note>
                    of the current<lb break="yes"/>that brought gold into Europe, could only be from
                    East to West.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But Asia itself, that is to say, the report spread by travellers in the<lb
                        break="yes"/>middle ages of immense treasures existing in Zipangou, (Japan)
                    and the<lb break="yes"/>Southern Archipelago, [Oronesia] produced a sudden
                    change in the<lb break="yes"/>direction of this metallic current. America was
                    discovered, not as has<lb break="yes"/>been erroneously said so long, because
                    Columbus foresaw the existence<lb break="yes"/>of another continent; but because
                    he was seeking westward a shorter<lb break="yes"/>road to Zipangou, so rich in
                    gold, and to the spice countries in south-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>eastern Asia.
                    Thus the greatest mistake of geography, (that is, the<lb break="yes"/>idea of
                    Spain&#x2019;s proximity to India) led to the greatest discovery of<lb
                        break="yes"/>geography. Christopher Columbus and Americus Vespucius both
                        died<lb break="yes"/>under the firm conviction of having reached Eastern
                    Asia, (India with<lb break="yes"/>the basin of the Ganges, the peninsula of
                    Cattigara;) and hence there<lb break="yes"/>can never arise any dispute between
                    them as to the glory of discovering<lb break="yes"/>a new continent.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>At Cuba, Columbus meant to deliver to the Great Khan of the Mon-<lb break="no" />gols, the letters of his sovereign. He believes himself in Mangi, the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="544" facs="#f0007"/> southern region of Cathay, (China;) he looks for Quien-sai, the celestial<lb break="yes"/>city described by Marco Polo, now Hang-tchen-fou. &#x201C;The island of<lb break="yes"/>Hispaniola (Hayti)&#x201D; writes he<note place="foot" n="*">Letter of February, 1502, found in the archives of the Duke of Varaguas. The<lb break="yes"/>third voyage, in which the continent of South America was discovered, (on 1 August,<lb break="yes" />1498, thirteen months after the discovery of North America by Sebastian Cabot)<lb break="yes"/>and the fourth voyage which gave the first information as to the western coast of the<lb break="yes"/>New world, only confirmed the aged Admiral in his preconceived opinion. It is not<lb break="yes"/>from any confusion of ideas that, in his letter to the pope and his manifest inclina-<lb break="no"/>tion to shew there a certain amount of biblical learning, he represents the names<lb break="yes"/>Tarshish, Ophir and Zipangou as synonyms of San Domingo: this belonged, as we<lb break="yes"/>see by other writings of Columbus, to his systematic notions. He considered, not<lb break="yes"/>India exactly, but Japan (Zipangou) certainly to be the Ophir of Solomon, which<lb break="yes"/>he calls also sometimes <hi rendition="#i">Sopora.</hi> He regarded Tarshish, not as the Iberian Tartes-<lb break="no"/>sus, but with the Septuagint and many theologians of the middle ages, as a common<lb break="yes"/>name. The voyage of Solomon, was not, in his view, a double navigation, having<lb break="yes"/>a part in the Red Sea and the Mediterranean. It had no other point of departure<lb break="yes"/>than Ezimgeber. Columbus knew Quien-sai from a letter of Toscanelli, and not<lb break="yes"/>through Marco Polo, whom he never mentions, though the contrary has been<lb break="yes" />hitherto maintained.</note> to Pope Alexander VI. &#x201C;is Tarshish,<lb break="yes"/>Ophir and Zipangou. In my second voyage I have discovered 1400<lb break="yes"/>islands and a shore of 333 miles, belonging to the continent of Asia (<hi rendition="#i">de<lb break="yes"/>la tierra firma de Asia.</hi>)&#x201D; This West-Indian Zipangou produced gold-<lb break="hyph-yes" />spangles (<hi rendition="#i">pepitas de oro</hi>) weighing 8, 10, and up to 20 pounds.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>America, from the moment of its discovery, became the principal<lb break="yes" />source of the precious metals. The new current directed itself from<lb break="yes"/>West to East; indeed, it crossed Europe, inasmuch as in the develope-<lb break="no"/>ment of commerce after navigators had doubled Africa, it became neces-<lb break="no"/>sary to give to southern and eastern Asia a larger equivalent in exchange<lb break="yes"/>for spices, silk and pigments.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As before the discovery of the silver mines of Tasco, upon the<lb break="yes"
                    />western slope of the Mexican Cordilleras, (in 1522) America furnished<lb
                        break="yes"/>only gold, Isabella of Castile found herself obliged, already
                    in 1497, to<lb break="yes"/>modify considerably the legal ratio of the two
                    precious metals. The<lb break="yes"/>monetary edict of Medina,<note place="foot"
                        n="&#x2020;">Memorias de la R. A. &#x0026;c. [Memoirs of the Royal Academy
                        of History,] t. vi.<lb break="yes"/>p. 525. The edict of Medina changed the
                        old legal ratio of 1:10,7.</note> whose date is so remote, and to which
                        up<lb break="yes"/>to this time so little importance has been attached, can
                    only be ac-<lb break="no"/>counted for by this circumstance and by the
                    accumulation of gold at a<lb break="yes"/>few points in Europe. I have elsewhere
                    sought to demonstrate how,<lb break="yes"/>from 1492 to 1500, the whole quantity
                    of gold drawn from the then<lb break="yes"/>discovered portions of the New
                    World, amounted hardly to an annual<lb break="yes"/>mean of 2000 marcs, [1000
                    lb. avoirdupois, nearly.] Pope Alexander<lb break="yes"/>VI. who thought that he
                    was bestowing one-half of the earth upon the<lb break="yes"/>Spaniards, received
                    in return as a present from Ferdinand the Catholic,<lb break="yes"/>some little
                    spangles of gold from Hayti &#x201C;as the first fruits of a country<lb
                        break="yes"/>newly discovered,&#x201D; to gild the magnificent dome [the <hi
                        rendition="#i">soffit</hi> of the dome,<lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i"
                        >soffitto</hi>)] of the basilica of the S. Maria Maggion. Mention is made
                        of<lb break="yes"/>the metal in an inscription; as being quod primo
                    Catholici reges ex<lb break="yes"/>Indi&#x00E2; receperant [what the Catholic
                    Sovereigns had first received from<lb break="yes"/>India.]</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>So great was then the activity of the Spanish Government, that already<lb break="yes"/>in 1495, as the historian Mun&#x0304;oz has shown, a miner, Pablo Belvis, was<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="545" facs="#f0008"/> sent to Hayti with provision of quicksilver to facilitate the separation<lb break="yes"/>of the gold by amalgamation. Something very striking in this regard,<lb break="yes"/>we read in a passage, recently discovered and but lately published, of<lb break="yes"/>the Geography of Scherif Edrisi,* &#x201C;that the negroes in the interior of<lb break="yes"/>Western Africa, as well as the inhabitants of the low and fertile district<lb break="yes"/>called Wady el Alaki (between Abyssinia, Bedja and Nubia) work the<lb break="yes"/>gold-earth by means of quicksilver.&#x201D; The Nubian geographer speaks<lb break="yes"/>in the middle of the 12th century, of this mode of extraction as a thing<lb break="yes"/>known for a long time. Could this knowledge have been communicated<lb break="yes"/>from the East, across Egypt to the country of Blacks, (Chemi) subtle in<lb break="yes" />decompositions&#x2014;to Africa? Antiquity, Greek and Roman, makes men-<lb break="no"/>tion, it is true, of a very frequent employment of quicksilver to detach<lb break="yes"/>the gold from the threads of old lace; but it never speaks of an artistical<lb break="yes"/>application of mercury on a large scale in the detailed descriptions of<lb break="yes"/>gold-washings it so often gives.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">[<hi rendition="#i">Continued on p.</hi> 601, <hi rendition="#i">April No.</hi>]</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <pb n="589" facs="#f0009"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">ON THE PRODUCTION OF GOLD AND SILVER AND<lb break="yes"/>ITS FLUCTUATIONS.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#k">by baron alexander von humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Translated for the Bankers&#x2019; Magazine, from the Journal des Economistes, March,<lb break="yes"/>April, May, 1848.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>[<hi rendition="#i">Continued from p.</hi> 545, <hi rendition="#i">March No.</hi>]</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p><hi rendition="#k">It</hi> is rather the discovery of new and abundant
                        sources than the dis-<lb break="no"/>appearance of the old, which has
                        modified the relative value of gold<lb break="yes"/>and silver at a given
                        epoch. It is to this cause, subsequently to the<lb break="yes"/>discovery of
                        the greater Antilles, that we must attribute the new rise in<lb break="yes"
                        />the price of gold about the middle of the 16th century; when the rich<lb
                            break="yes"/>silver mines of Potosi and Zacatecas had been opened in
                        Peru and in<lb break="yes"/>the north of Mexico. From researches which I
                        have carefully made, it<lb break="yes"/>results that the importation of
                        American gold was by weight to that of<lb break="yes"/>silver, in the ratio
                        of 1:65; down to the first year of the 18th century,<lb break="yes"/>when
                        they commenced the gold workings in Brazil. At this moment,<lb break="yes"
                        />taking in at one view the aggregate of the metallic commerce of Europe,<lb
                            break="yes"/>the ratio is not higher than as 1:47; which is, at least,
                        the result given<lb break="yes"/>by comparison<note place="foot" n="*">See
                            my Essai Politique t. iii. pp. 400, 436, 448, 463. Jacob, Precious
                                Metals,<lb break="yes"/>t. ii. p. 187. The result which I have
                            found, has been illustrated with profound<lb break="yes"/>penetration by
                            Say, [Political Econ.] t. ii. ch. 10, by analogies drawn from general<lb
                                break="yes"/>commerce.</note> of the quantities of the two metals
                            simultaneously<lb break="yes"/>existing in Europe in the state of coin.
                        The data in the work, in other<lb break="yes"/>points so excellent, of Adam
                        Smith, are very inexact; in respect to<lb break="yes"/>this ratio, they are
                        in error by more than one-half. In commerce, the<lb break="yes"/>relative
                        value of gold and silver among the civilized nations of Europe<lb
                            break="yes"/>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="590" facs="#f0010"/> in immediate intercourse with each other,
                        oscillated during the first hun-<lb break="no"/>dred years subsequent to the
                        discovery of the new continent, between<lb break="yes"/>1:10,7 and 1:12; and
                        in the two last, continues between 1:14 and<lb break="yes"/>1:16. This
                        fluctuation is very far from depending solely upon the<lb break="yes"
                        />relative quantities of the two metals annually obtained from the bosom<lb
                            break="yes"/>of the earth. The ratio of their values is very soon
                        modified by the<lb break="yes"/>cost of mining, by the demand or necessities
                        of consumers, by the<lb break="yes"/>greater or less expense of transport,
                        by the application of metals in the<lb break="yes"/>manufacture of plate and
                        other metallic articles. The simultaneous<lb break="yes"/>action of so many
                        elements, joined to the facility of transmission amid<lb break="yes"/>the so
                        general and so rapid commerce of the world, and to the immense<lb
                            break="yes"/>quantity of metals accumulated in Europe, prevents now any
                            partial<lb break="yes"/>oscillation in the relative value of gold and
                        silver, from being very con-<lb break="no"/>siderable or long continued. Of
                        this, we may be convinced at any sud-<lb break="no"/>den interruption in
                        production, as for instance, after the revolution in<lb break="yes"/>Spanish
                        America; or even by instances of extraordinary employment of<lb break="yes"
                        />one only of the precious metals in the operations of an active mint.<lb
                            break="yes"/>Thus, during the ten years from 1817 to 1827, there has
                        been coined in<lb break="yes"/>England more than 1.294.000 marcs [650.000
                        lbs. avoirdupois nearly]<lb break="yes"/>of gold; and yet this consumption
                        of gold raised the rate of gold and<lb break="yes"/>silver in London<note
                            place="foot" n="*">See the recent excellent work of J. G. Hoffman,
                            entitled Lehre vom Gelde,<lb break="yes"/>[Science of the Mint] 1838, p.
                            7.</note> only from 1:14,97 to 1:15,60. And still, at the<lb break="yes"
                        />close of 1837, one buys in London a pound of gold for 16,65 pounds<lb
                            break="yes"/>of silver. We shall offer presently the numerical elements
                        for the solu-<lb break="no"/>tion of a problem, in which it is proposed to
                        determine what modifica-<lb break="no"/>tions are to be expected from the
                        gradual and simultaneous action of<lb break="yes"/>the recent mines in the
                        Ural and those of North America.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The mass of precious metal reaching Europe since the discovery of<lb break="yes"/>America up to the Mexican revolution, amounts for gold, to 10.400.000<lb break="yes"/>marcs of Castile, [5.284.686 lbs. avoirdupois] and for silver, to<lb break="yes"/>533.700.000 marcs [271.195.843 lbs. avoirdupois;] and in value to-<lb break="no"/>gether to 5940 millions piastres [say 6000 millions of American dollars.]<lb break="yes"/>The silver taken in this interval from the American soil is here calcu-<lb break="no"/>lated upon the intrinsic value of the piastre, that is to to say, 0,903 fine;<lb break="yes"/>so these 533.700.000 marcs of standard silver make only 481.931.100<lb break="yes"/>marcs [i. e. 244.889.846 lbs. avdp.] of pure silver. This would be<lb break="yes" />equivalent to a sphere of pure silver having a diameter of [90,15<lb break="yes"/>English feet.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Such a sphere represents the mass of pure silver which has come from America<lb break="yes"/>to Europe in the space of 318 years, from 1492 to 1809. The marc of Castile is<lb break="yes"/>0,229 killogramme. [Taking its better attested weight of 3557 grains English, it<lb break="yes" />corresponds more nearly to 0,2305 kilogr. or 0,5081 lb. avdp. which is the factor<lb break="yes"/>actually used in the reduction for the text; which has retained] the specific gravity<lb break="yes"/>of silver at 10,474. Of the two analogous valuations in spheres given in the second<lb break="yes"/>edition of my Essai Politique, &#x0026;c. (t. iii. p. 418, 459,) and expressing the mass of<lb break="yes"/>silver from 1492 to 1830, both in silver of the piastre-standard and of fine, the first<lb break="yes"/>is exact; in the second must be read 26,37 instead of 20,47 metres in diameter.</note>] Such a reduction to form and size is as admissible as<lb break="yes"/>other analogous figurative valuations. If, for instance, the product of<lb break="yes"/>silver from Spanish America for the whole period of 318 years, be com-<lb break="no" />pared with the product of <hi rendition="#i">iron</hi> from some European States for only a sin-<lb break="no"/>gle year, [while we have for the former as before, a sphere of 90 English<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="591" facs="#f0011"/> feet in diameter] we find according to the estimate of M. de Dechen, a<lb break="yes"/>distinguished geologist, spheres of pure [malleable] iron for Great Britain<lb break="yes"/>of 148 Paris feet, [157,7 English feet] for France 111 feet, [118,3 Eng-<lb break="no" />lish] and for the Prussian monarchy 76 feet [81 feet English;] so great<lb break="yes"/>is the difference of quantity in these two metals, silver and iron, found<lb break="yes"/>in that portion of the earth&#x2019;s crust which man has been able to pene-<lb break="no"/>trate.<note place="foot" n="*">The estimate for Great Britain is upon the mean product of crude iron during<lb break="yes"/>1828&#x2014;30. (McCulloh, Dict. of Commerce, 1834, p. 736.) This mean is 617.352<lb break="yes"/>tons or 12.149.487 Prussian quintals. The diameter of a sphere of <hi rendition="#i">crude</hi> iron, the<lb break="yes"/>product of one year, will be consequently 175 Prussian feet, or 169 Paris feet, [180<lb break="yes"/>English feet.] Crude iron yields, when converted into bars, 5-7 of its weight.<lb break="yes"/>For the production of France has been taken that of the year 1835, (Resumé der<lb break="yes" />Travaux Statistique, p. 61) 2.690.636 metrical quintals [of 100 kilog.] equal to<lb break="yes"/>5 227 905 Prussian quintals or 1.345.000 tons English very nearly. In the States of<lb break="yes" />Prussia, the production of crude iron was for the year 1836, 1.651.598 quintals [or<lb break="yes"/>83.932 tons English.]</note>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>While the current of gold and silver was thus directed from West to<lb
                            break="yes"/>East, it only passed through Spain. Very little of it
                        remained with the<lb break="yes"/>nation; still less was deposited in the
                        royal treasury. Ferdinand the<lb break="yes"/>Catholic (as the admirer and
                        friend of the great monarch, writes a few<lb break="yes"/>days after his
                        death) died so poor that they did not know how to pro-<lb break="no"/>cure
                        the money necessary for the suitable habiliments of the attendants<lb
                            break="yes"/>who were to wait upon the funeral procession. I give this
                            remarkable<lb break="yes"/>passage of his letter to the Bishop of
                            Tuy:<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Petri Mart. Epist. lib. xxix. No.
                            556 (xxiii. Jan. 1516.) Nine years later, the<lb break="yes"
                            />gold-washings of Hispaniola were already exhausted. Sugar and hides
                            are alone<lb break="yes"/>mentioned as articles of export. Tres habemus
                            ab Hispaniol&#x00E2; naves (writes again<lb break="yes"/>Anghiera)
                            saccareis panibus et coriis boüm onustas. (Ep. No. 806, Kal. Mart.<lb
                                break="yes"/>1525.) This passage is important in the history of
                            commerce; since the first sugar-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>cane was planted
                            in S. Domingo only in 1520 by <hi rendition="#i">Pedro Atienza.</hi>
                        </note> Madrigalegium villulam<lb break="yes"/>Regis tibi alias descripsi.
                        Tot regnorum dominus totq. palmarum cu-<lb break="no"/>mulis ornatus,
                        Christian&#x00E6; religionis amplificator et prostrator hostium,<lb
                            break="yes"/>Rex in rusticana obiit casa; et pauper contra opinionem
                        hominum obiit.<lb break="yes"/>Vix ad funeris pompam et paucis familiaribus
                        pr&#x00E6;bendas vestes pullatas<lb break="yes"/>pecum&#x00E6; apud eum
                        neque alibi congest&#x00E6;, repert&#x00E6; sunt; quod nemo<lb break="yes"
                        />unquam de vivente judicavit. [Madrigalejos, the country-seat of the<lb
                            break="yes"/>King, I have elsewhere described for you. Lord of so many
                            realms,<lb break="yes"/>wearer of so many laurels, diffuser of the
                        Christian religion, and van-<lb break="no"/>quisher of its enemies, the King
                        died in a rustic cabin; and, contrary to<lb break="yes"/>all opinion, died
                        poor. Hardly money enough for the ceremony of the<lb break="yes"/>funeral
                        and furnishing the few domestics with mourning suits, was<lb break="yes"
                        />found either upon him or elsewhere; what no one, while he lived, ever<lb
                            break="yes"/>would have thought.] Ranke,<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;"
                            >Ranke; Fürsten u. Völker, &#x0026;c. [Princes and People of the South
                            of Europe]<lb break="yes"/>t. i. p. 347&#x2014;355.</note> in his
                        dissertation on Spanish finances,<lb break="yes"/>has treated of the
                        pecuniary embarrassments of Charles V. The inge-<lb break="no"/>nious
                        historian has completed and confirmed by new documents the<lb break="yes"
                        />official vouchers<note place="foot" n="||">Essai Politique, &#x0026;c. t.
                            iii. pp. 361&#x2014;482, 421&#x2014;428. The working of the<lb
                                break="yes"/>mines did not yield 3 million of piastres [dollars] a
                            year, until 1545. The ransom<lb break="yes"/>of Atahualpa amounted,
                            according to Gomara, to 52000 marcs of silver [about<lb break="yes"
                            />425.000 dollars of our standard] and the booty (the pillage of the
                            temples at Cuzco)<lb break="yes"/>according to Herrera, to the value of
                            25700 marcs, only.</note> which I have given [elsewhere] of the small
                            quantity<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="592" facs="#f0012"/> of precious metals which the mines of America
                        and the pretended trea-<lb break="no"/>sures of the Incas yielded.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A more exact knowledge of the history of the metallurgic production<lb
                            break="yes"/>or of the gradual developement of the great metalliferous
                        beds in the<lb break="yes"/>New World, shews us why the lowering of the
                        value of the precious<lb break="yes"/>metals, or (what is the same) the rise
                        in price of wheat and other in-<lb break="no"/>dispensable products of the
                        soil and of human industry, was felt most<lb break="yes"/>sensibly only
                        about the middle of the 16th century, and especially<lb break="yes"/>from
                        1570 to 1595. It was then only that the masses of silver from<lb break="yes"
                        />the mines of Tasco, of Zacatecas and of Pachuca in New Spain, of<lb
                            break="yes"/>Potosi, of Porco and of Oruro, in the chain of the Peruvian
                            Andes,<lb break="yes"/>begun to be distributed more uniformly over
                        Europe and to affect the<lb break="yes"/>price of grain, of wool and of
                        manufactured goods. The true opening<lb break="yes"/>and working of the
                        mines of Potosi by the Spanish <hi rendition="#i">conquistadores,</hi>
                            dates<lb break="yes"/>from the year 1545; and the celebrated sermon of
                        Bishop Latimer<lb break="yes"/>before Edward VI.,<note place="foot" n="*"
                            >Jacob: On Precious Metals: t. ii. p. 77, 132 and 138.</note> in which
                        he expresses his indignation at the rise in<lb break="yes"/>price of all the
                        most necessary articles, dates on 17 January, 1548.<lb break="yes"/>The laws
                        relating to cereal grains, promulgated in England from 1554<lb break="yes"
                        />to 1688, evince still better, if possible, than the prices of grain
                            which<lb break="yes"/>have been collected by Fleetwood, Dupré des Saint
                        Maur, Garnier and<lb break="yes"/>Lloyd, the accumulation of specie. The
                        exportation of coin is, as we<lb break="yes"/>know, only allowed there when
                        the price of a certain measure reaches<lb break="yes"/>a scale determined by
                        law. This limit was under Queen Mary, in<lb break="yes"/>1554, 6 shillings a
                        quarter; under Elizabeth, in 1593, about 20 shil-<lb break="no"/>lings; and
                        in 1604, under James I. more than 26 shillings. These<lb break="yes"
                        />figures are without doubt of great importance; but their explanation<lb
                            break="yes"/>requires special circumspection, inasmuch as the problem of
                        the price<lb break="yes"/>of grain, and indeed of prices generally, is
                        highly complicated, and as<lb break="yes"/>the legislation of each epoch was
                        under the domain of theoretical<lb break="yes"/>opinions very variable, was
                        influenced by the aristocracy, the proprie-<lb break="no"/>tors of the soil,
                        and was controlled even by the unequal accumulation<lb break="yes"/>of money
                        and merchandise at different points. Besides the changes of<lb break="yes"
                        />temperature, (the mean of the Spring and Summer months) which<lb
                            break="yes"/>favour the culture of cereal grains, do not extend at the
                        same time over<lb break="yes"/>the whole of agricultural Europe. Even the
                        improvement in culture,<lb break="yes"/>the better employment of the
                        productive forces of the Earth, modifies<lb break="yes"/>prices. Material
                        increase of population and the development of com-<lb break="no"/>merce
                        which results from this increase, augment the demand for specie.<lb
                            break="yes"/>Thus, along with the standard which we look for and think
                        to find<lb break="yes"/>among the variable prices of grain, we have yet to
                        keep count of two<lb break="yes"/>magnitudes which may be simultaneously
                        modifying themselves. The<lb break="yes"/>rise in the prices of cereals does
                        not express, even for any country<lb break="yes"/>taken by itself, the
                        proportionate increase in the quantity of gold and<lb break="yes"/>silver,
                        any more than it informs us of the general mean temperature,<lb break="yes"
                        />and (according to the theory of a great Astronomer) the number of<lb
                            break="yes"/>spots on the Sun. We are absolutely without synchronizing
                        data to<lb break="yes"/>embrace a large part of Europe; and exact researches
                        have shewn that<lb break="yes"/>in Upper Italy, for instance, the rise in
                        price of wheat, wine and oil<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="593" facs="#f0013"/> was much less<note place="foot" n="*"
                            >Gianrinaldo Carli; Opp. t. vii. p, 190. Savigny: Geschichte <choice>
                                <sic>der</sic>
                                <corr type="editorial">des</corr>
                            </choice> Rechts [His-<lb break="no"/>tory of Jurisprudence] t. iii. p.
                            567. Information upon prices in Southern Europe,<lb break="yes"/>goes
                            certainly as far back as the 14th century; for, in 1321, Marino Sanuto
                                pre-<lb break="no"/>sented to Pope John XXII. an estimate of the
                            expenses of a crusade which was to<lb break="yes"/>divert all the
                            commerce of the East. From this estimate, as well as from the prices<lb
                                break="yes"/>given by Balducci Pegoletti, the standard of coins is
                            susceptible of being determined<lb break="yes"/>much more carefully than
                            it has been yet by those who have occupied themselves<lb break="yes"
                            />with the doctrine of trade and the history of commerce.</note> between
                        the 15th and 16th centuries, than might have<lb break="yes"/>been reasonably
                        expected from what was known in England, France<lb break="yes"/>and
                            Spain,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Elemencin, in the Mem. of the Roy.
                            Acad. of History; t. vi. p. 553. Wheat<lb break="yes"/>(<hi
                                rendition="#i">trigo</hi>) per fanega [1,6-10 U. S. bushel very
                            nearly] was worth in Spain, from<lb break="yes"/>1406 to 1502, at a
                            mean, 10 reals; from 1793 to 1808, 62 reals, the coin being re-<lb
                                break="no"/>duced to the same standard. This result accords with the
                            researches of Say into<lb break="yes"/>the prices of cereals in France
                            (Traité d&#x2019;Econ. Polit. t. i. p. 352.) In the days of<lb
                                break="yes"/>the Maid of Orleans, under Charles VII. the hectolitre
                            of wheat, (weighing 75<lb break="yes"/>kilog.) [165&#x215C; lb. avdp.
                            nearly = 2&#x00BE; bushels by Maryland standard] had fallen as<lb
                                break="yes"/>low as 219 grains of silver [267,45 English grains = 72
                            cents in money of American<lb break="yes"/>silver standard.] The average
                            price a little before the discovery of America was<lb break="yes"/>268
                            grains [88 cents;] it had risen to 333 grains [$1 10, nearly] in 1514;
                                under<lb break="yes"/>Francis I., to 731 grains [$2 40;] under Henry
                            IV., to 1130 grains [$3 72.]<lb break="yes"/>Lavoisier found that from
                            1610 to 1789, there had been an appreciation in the ratio<lb break="yes"
                            />of 1130 to 1342 grains. In 1820, a hectolitre cost in France 1610
                            grains [$5 30;]<lb break="yes"/>counting 9216 of these grains in a
                            pound, or 0,489 kil. (See also Letronne: Con-<lb break="no"/>siderations
                            gener. sur les Monn. Grecques: p. 118, 123.) Ascending from the<lb
                                break="yes"/>middle ages, we find a rise in the price of cereals.
                            Under Valentinian III., in 446,<lb break="yes"/>the hectolitre was worth
                            344 grains of silver; and in the decline of the Republic, at<lb
                                break="yes"/>the time of Cicero, as much as 528 grains. The results
                            of Durean de la Malle give<lb break="yes"/>prices still higher. (Comptes
                            Rendus, July, 1838, p. 84.)</note> where the prices of cereals rose
                        quadruple and even sex-<lb break="no"/>tuple. It is worth while to mention
                        here a numerical result established<lb break="yes"/>upon the average prices
                        for a period of fourteen years in the whole<lb break="yes"/>Prussian
                        monarchy. This has been calculated with the greatest care,<lb break="yes"
                        />at my request, by the Director of our Statistical Bureau, Mr. Privy-<lb
                            break="no"/>Councillor Hofmann. In the year 1838, while we can buy at
                            Berlin,<lb break="yes"/>for 1 pound of gold, 15<formula notation="TeX"
                            >\frac{9}{16}</formula> pounds of fine silver, 1611 pounds of copper,<lb
                            break="yes"/>and nearly 9700 pounds of iron; the pound of gold is worth,
                        upon the<lb break="yes"/>means of the periods 1816&#x2013;29, and
                        1824&#x2013;37, likewise 20794 lb. of<lb break="yes"/>wheat, 27655 lb. of
                        rye, 31717 lb. of barley, and 32626 lb. of oats. <note place="foot"
                            n="&#x2021;" xml:id="fn1-1" next="#fn1-2">The basis of this important
                            statement are as follows: In the Statistical Bureau<lb break="yes"/>at
                            Berlin, is registered, monthly, the market-price of the four principal
                            kinds of<lb break="yes"/>grain in every port of Prussia; and the average
                            is then taken for each separate<lb break="yes"/>province. From these
                            averages, is then deduced at the end of the year, the mean<lb
                                break="yes"/>prices for the whole year; and from a series of these
                            means has been made up the<lb break="yes"/>averages for fourteen years
                            in this manner: from among the prices of the following<lb break="yes"
                            />fourteen years is taken out, every time, the two highest and the two
                            lowest, and the<lb break="yes"/>ten terms left are then added; the tenth
                            of this aggregate is considered as the mean<lb break="yes"/>price of the
                            fourteen years in question. In this operation, which embraces the
                            time</note>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <table>
                        <head>[<hi rendition="#i">For greater illustration, the following Table is constructed to shew at the given<lb break="yes"/>epochs the relative value of</hi>
                            <hi rendition="#k">
                                <hi rendition="#g">equal</hi> weights</hi>
                            <hi rendition="#i">of the several substances: Gold<lb break="yes"/>being unity; as follows:</hi>
                        </head>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <row>
                            <cell cols="2">
                                <hi rendition="#g">
                                    <hi rendition="#k">metals.</hi>
                                </hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell cols="2">
                                <hi rendition="#g">
                                    <hi rendition="#k">cereals.</hi>
                                </hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Gold: 1.</cell>
                            <cell>Copper: 0,000621</cell>
                            <cell>Wheat: 0,000048</cell>
                            <cell>Barley: 0,000032</cell>
                        </row>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Silver: 0,064103</cell>
                            <cell>Iron:  0,000103</cell>
                            <cell>Rye:  0,000036</cell>
                            <cell>Oats:  0,000028]</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The fears which, on the appearance of the work of Jacob (on Pre-<lb break="no"/>cious Metals,) a book of great merit, and which has not received in<lb break="yes"/>
                        
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="594" facs="#f0014"/> Germany the attention it deserves, were spreading on account of the<lb break="yes"/>diminished import of precious metals from the New Continent, have<lb break="yes"/>not been realized. The metallic production, fallen so low from 1809<lb break="yes"/>to 1826, has nevertheless, in spite of the troubled state of Spanish<lb break="yes" />America, risen afresh to three-fourths of what it was when I left those<lb break="yes"/>countries. In Mexico, according to the most recent intelligence, which<lb break="yes"/>I owe to the attention of the Prussian Chargé d&#x2019;Affaires, Mr. de Gerolt,<lb break="yes"/>the working has amounted to 20 and even 22 millions of piastres; a<lb break="yes"/>result for which, the chief contributions (besides that of Zacatecas)<lb break="yes"/>have come from the recently worked mines of Tresnilla, of Chihuahua,<lb break="yes"/>and of Sonora.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>During the last peaceful epoch of the Spanish domination, I could<lb
                            break="yes"/>not estimate the mean yield of the mines of Mexico at more
                        than 23<lb break="yes"/>millions piastres (about 53.700 kil. [1.184.000 lb.
                        avdp. nearly] of sil-<lb break="no"/>ver, and 1600 kil. [3500 lb. avdp.] of
                        gold. The account was then more<lb break="yes"/>easily ascertained; for
                        there was but one central mint, and the laws<lb break="yes"/>restricted the
                        commerce to a few ports. In no other place in the world<lb break="yes"/>was
                        the activity greater then than in this central mint, which coined in<lb
                            break="yes"/>domestic gold and silver, from 1690 to 1803, 1353 million
                            piastres;<lb break="yes"/>and from the discovery of New Spain until its
                            Independence,<note place="foot" n="*">It is only this year [1837] that
                            Mr. Ternaux Campans, in his extremely inter-<lb break="no"/>esting
                            collection of <hi rendition="#i">Original Memoirs of the Discovery of
                                America</hi> (Conquest of<lb break="yes"/>Mexico, p. 451,) has
                            published an official list of the sums sent between 1522 and<lb
                                break="yes"/>1587 by the Viceroys of New Spain to the mother
                            country. I did not find this list<lb break="yes"/>in the Mexican
                            archives. It is very remarkable, and shews that my former esti-<lb
                                break="no"/>mates of the metallic yield of Mexico, (Essai Polit. t.
                            iii. p. 414) were yet a little<lb break="yes"/>too high. A contrary
                            opinion has been of late frequently expressed. From the ad-<lb
                                break="no"/>ministration of Fernando Cortez up to the year 1552,
                            when the mines of Zacatecas<lb break="yes"/>were just opened, the export
                            rarely amounted in a year to 100000 peros [or piastres,<lb break="yes"
                            />dollars very nearly.] From this epoch, it took a rapid rise. In the
                            years 1569,<lb break="yes"/>1578, and 1587, it was already respectively
                            931.564, 1.111.202, and 1.812.051 <hi rendition="#i">peros<lb
                                    break="yes"/>of gold.</hi> These sums are calculated, not upon
                            the piastres, but upon these <hi rendition="#i">peros of<lb break="yes"
                                />gold,</hi> [they must be multiplied at a mean by 11&#x00BC; in
                            order to represent the value in<lb break="yes"/>dollars.] See the
                            instructive work of Mr. Joseph Burkhardt: Aufenthalt ú. Reisen<lb
                                break="yes"/>in Mexico, &#x0026;c. [Residence and Travel in Mexico
                            from 1824 to 1834] 1st Part:<lb break="yes"/>p. 360, 385. Second Pt.: p.
                            74, 152.</note> about<lb break="yes"/>2028 million piastres, i. e.
                        two-fifths of all the precious metals which<lb break="yes"/>
                        <note place="foot" n="&#x2021;" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1">from 1816 to
                            1837, there results for the Prussian bushel [scheffel = 1,56 U. S.<lb
                                break="yes"/>bushel, very nearly] the following prices: viz.<lb
                                break="yes"/>
                            <table cols="4">
                                <row>
                                    <cell> </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rendition="#i">Thaler.</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rendition="#i">Silbergroschen.</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rendition="#i"><choice><sic>Pfenins</sic><corr type="editorial">Pfennig</corr></choice>.</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Wheat,</cell>
                                    <cell>1.</cell>
                                    <cell>23.</cell>
                                    <cell>10,5-9</cell>
                                </row>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Rye,</cell>
                                    <cell>1.</cell>
                                    <cell>8.</cell>
                                    <cell>1,5-9</cell>
                                </row>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Barley,</cell>
                                    <cell>1.</cell>
                                    <cell>28.</cell>
                                    <cell>8,1-9</cell>
                                </row>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Oats,</cell>
                                    <cell>1.</cell>
                                    <cell>21.</cell>
                                    <cell>8,1-3</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <lb break="yes"/>[This table is given here just as it is printed; but
                            there is manifestly an error.<lb break="yes"/>The two last cyphers in
                            the column of thalers should be zeros] The corresponding<lb break="yes"
                            />points for the four cereals are per bushel in Prussian lbs. (of two
                            marcs of Cologne)<lb break="yes"/>85, 80, 69, and 52. The pound of gold
                            is estimated in the silver coin of Prussia at<lb break="yes"/>439 th. 11
                            sgr. 6,6-13 pf. The comparison of the two periods, 1816&#x2014;29,
                                and<lb break="yes"/>1824&#x2014;37, shews a fall in prices in the
                            Prussian States of 14,2-7 per cent. for<lb break="yes"/>wheat;
                            11&#x00BD; per cent. for rye; 12 per cent. for barley; and 11,13-17 for
                                oats;&#x2014;a<lb break="yes"/>diminution which is attributable in
                            great degree to enhanced production and better<lb break="yes"/>use of
                            the soil. (Dieterich; Uebersicht des Verkaufs [View of Commerce]
                                1838,<lb break="yes"/>p. 174.) I consider this diminution here as
                            entirely independent of the influence<lb break="yes"/>or supply of
                            precious metals.</note>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="595" facs="#f0015"/> the whole of the New Continent has furnished
                        during the same period<lb break="yes"/>to the Old.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The allegations, then, growing out of the disappointments in fruitless<lb break="yes"/>undertakings, as to the exhaustion of the mineral wealth of Mexico, is<lb break="yes"/>in contradiction with the geognostic facts of the country, and even with<lb break="yes"/>the most recent experience. The Zacatecas mint alone, during the<lb break="yes"/>troubled period from 1811 to 1838, has struck more than 66.332.000<lb break="yes"/>piastres from 7.758.000 marcs of silver; and in eleven latter years (from<lb break="yes" />1822 to 1833) has yielded uninterruptedly from 4 to 5 million piastres;<lb break="yes"/>viz:</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <table rows="5" cols="3">
                        <row>
                            <cell>1829:</cell>
                            <cell>4.505.103</cell>
                            <cell>piastres.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1830:</cell>
                            <cell>5.189.902</cell>
                            <cell>&#x201C;</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1831:</cell>
                            <cell>4.469.450</cell>
                            <cell>&#x201C;</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1832:</cell>
                            <cell>5.012.000</cell>
                            <cell>&#x201C;</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1833:</cell>
                            <cell>5.720.000</cell>
                            <cell>piastres.</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <pb n="709" facs="#f0016"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">ON THE PRODUCTION OF GOLD AND SILVER AND<lb break="yes"/>ITS FLUCTUATIONS.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#k">by baron alexander von humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Translated for the Bankers&#x2019; Magazine, from the Journal des Economistes, March,<lb break="yes"/>April, May, 1848.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                
                    <p>[<hi rendition="#i">Continued from p.</hi> 595, <hi rendition="#i">April No.</hi>]</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p><hi rendition="#k">At</hi> Zacatecas, a single vein, <hi rendition="#i">la
                        Veta Grande,</hi> which has been worked<lb break="yes"/>since the 16th
                    century, and which up to 1738 furnished often in one<lb break="yes"/>year as
                    much as 3 million piastres, has put in circulation the masses of<lb break="yes"
                    />metal, as below:</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                <table rows="5" cols="5">
                    <row>
                        <cell>1828:</cell>
                        <cell>117.268</cell>
                        <cell>marcs of silver </cell>
                        <cell>[=59.572</cell>
                        <cell>lb. avdp.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1829:</cell>
                        <cell>235.741</cell>
                        <cell>&#x201C; &#x201C;</cell>
                        <cell>119.706</cell>
                        <cell>&#x201C;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1830:</cell>
                        <cell>279.288</cell>
                        <cell>&#x201C; &#x201C;</cell>
                        <cell>141.878</cell>
                        <cell>&#x201C;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1831:</cell>
                        <cell>272.095</cell>
                        <cell>&#x201C; &#x201C;</cell>
                        <cell>138.224</cell>
                        <cell>&#x201C;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1832:</cell>
                        <cell>258.498</cell>
                        <cell>&#x201C; &#x201C;</cell>
                        <cell>131.317</cell>
                        <cell>&#x201C;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1833:</cell>
                        <cell>209.192</cell>
                        <cell>&#x201C; &#x201C;</cell>
                        <cell>106.270</cell>
                        <cell>lb. avdp.]</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Guanaxuato which, it is true, used to furnish even in my time as much<lb break="yes"/>as 755.000 marcs of silver [383.500 lbs. avdp.] a year, has on the other<lb break="yes"/>hand fallen latterly to less than the half of this yield. Thus it gave in</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <table>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rendition="#g">
                                    <hi rendition="#k">gold.</hi>
                                </hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rendition="#g">
                                    <hi rendition="#k">silver.</hi>
                                </hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1829, 852 marcs [433 lb. avdp.</cell>
                            <cell>269.494 marcs [136.903 lb. avdp.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1830, 1058 &#x201C; 537 &#x201C;</cell>
                            <cell>284.386 &#x201C; 144.468 &#x201C;</cell>
                        </row>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1831, 622 &#x201C; 316 &#x201C;</cell>
                            <cell>258.500 &#x201C; 131.318 &#x201C;</cell>
                        </row>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1832, 1451 &#x201C; 737 &#x201C;</cell>
                            <cell>300.612 &#x201C; 152.711 &#x201C;</cell>
                        </row>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1833, 1144 &#x201C; 581 lb. avdp.]</cell>
                            <cell>316.024 &#x201C; 160.540 lb. avdp.]</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Whenever these superb countries, favored by nature in so many<lb break="yes"
                    />regards, shall come, after a long fermentation and profound internal<lb
                        break="yes"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="710" facs="#f0017"/> agitations, to enjoy peace&#x2014;new metallic
                    deposites must necessarily be<lb break="yes"/>opened and developed in the
                    cultivation of the soil. In what region<lb break="yes"/>of the globe, outside of
                    America, can be cited examples of wealth in<lb break="yes"/>silver so abundant?
                    Let it not be forgotten that near Sombrereta,<lb break="yes"/>where some mines
                    were opened as far back as 1555, the family of<lb break="yes"/>Fagoaga
                    (Marquesses of Apartado) have derived, in the short space of<lb break="yes"
                    />five months, from a front of 16 toises [102 feet English] in the outcrop<lb
                        break="yes"/>of a silver mine, a net profit of 4 million piastres; and that
                    in the<lb break="yes"/>mining district of Cator&#x00E7;a in the space of two
                    years and a half (1781&#x2013;<lb break="yes"/>1783) in ground full of mines of
                    chloride of silver and of <hi rendition="#i">colorados,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>which the common people call <hi rendition="#i">the purse of
                        God</hi> (la bolsa de Dios<lb break="yes"/>padre) an ecclesiastic, Juan
                    Flores, made likewise a gain of 3&#x00BD; million<lb break="yes"/>piastres.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The production of <hi rendition="#i">gold</hi> in Spanish and Portuguese
                    America has<lb break="yes"/>diminished in much greater proportion than that of
                        <hi rendition="#i">silver;</hi> but such<lb break="yes"/>diminution dates
                    from an epoch long anterior to the political troubles<lb break="yes"/>of the
                    tropical regions. I have already adverted in another place<note place="foot"
                        n="*">Essai Polit. t. iii. pp. 448 &#x2013; 452.</note> to<lb break="yes"
                    />the error existing till the beginning of this century as to the duration<lb
                        break="yes"/>of the richness of the Brazilian washings, and how the
                    flourishing state<lb break="yes"/>of these workings (from 1752 to 1773) has been
                    confounded with its<lb break="yes"/>subsequent condition. The report of the <hi
                        rendition="#i">Bullion-Committee,</hi> so im-<lb break="no"/>portant for the
                    history of commerce, began to throw some light on this<lb break="yes"
                        />subject.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Report of the Bullion-Committee of
                        1810. Append, 17&#x2013;22.</note> I am indebted for the most authentic
                    information to the pri-<lb break="no"/>vate communications of the former
                    Director-General of Mines, Baron<lb break="yes"/>von Eschwege. Jacob&#x2019;s
                    work upon precious metals contains only addi-<lb break="no"/>tions of little
                        moment.<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Vol. ii pp. 266 and 295.</note> From
                    1752 to 1761, the gold-workings of<lb break="yes"/>Minas Geraes, upon the
                    returns of the fifth part for royalty, oscillated<lb break="yes"/>between 6400
                    and 8600 kilogrammes [14.000 and 19.000 lbs. avdp.]<lb break="yes"/>(The
                    Portuguese <hi rendition="#i">arroba</hi> is equal according to Franzini to
                    14,656 kil.)<lb break="yes"/>[Balbi says 14,686&#x2153; kil. = 32,378 lbs.
                    avdp.] This yield is certainly<lb break="yes"/>very considerable and much above
                    that of the Ural and Alta&#x00EF;, [until<lb break="yes"/>1838; when the yield
                    from the Russian districts equalled the higher<lb break="yes"/>of the Brazilian
                    numbers;] but we must remember that in 1804, Span-<lb break="no"/>ish America
                    gave likewise nearly 10.400 kilog. of gold, as under:</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <list>
                        <item>New Granada, ........ 4700 kil. [10.340 lb. avdp.</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>Chili, ........... 2800 &#x201C; 6.160 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>Mexico, .......... 1600 &#x201C; 3.520 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>Peru, ........... 780 &#x201C; 1.716 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>Buenos Ayres, ........ <hi rendition="#u">500</hi> &#x201C; <hi rendition="#u">1.100</hi> &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>10.380 kil. = 22.836 lb. avdp.]</item>
                    </list>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The yield of the Minas Geraes had already fallen, at a mean among<lb break="yes"/>the years</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <list>
                        <item>1785&#x2013;1794, to 3300 kil. [7260 lb. avdp.</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1810&#x2013;1817, 1600 &#x201C; 3520 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1818&#x2013;1820, 428 &#x201C; 932 lb. avdp.]</item>
                    </list>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="711" facs="#f0018"/>
                    <p>The assertion of Chev. Schaeffer, that in 1822 only 24 arrobas [775<lb break="yes"/>lbs. avdp.] went to the smelting furnace of Villa Rica agrees with the<lb break="yes"/>result given before. Since this period, the working of the Brazilian<lb break="yes"/>gold mines seems to have been a little stimulated by the industry of<lb break="yes"/>some English companies; but what has contributed more than the ex-<lb break="no"/>haustion of the mineral deposites to the decline of the gold washings,<lb break="yes"/>is the inclination to the culture of colonial products favored by the<lb break="yes"/>trade in slaves which always is kept up. Unauthorized commerce is<lb break="yes"/>so extensive in Brazil that it is much to be wished that some citizen<lb break="yes"/>there, thoroughly acquainted with the situation of the country, would<lb break="yes"/>charge himself with the task of elucidating the general relations of the<lb break="yes"/>annual production of gold since 1822.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It is a fact worthy of remark in the history of mining by Europeans,<lb
                        break="yes"/>that since the gold-workings in Brazil have fallen so low, the
                        product<lb break="yes"/>of this metal should have risen to an unexpected
                    height in northern<lb break="yes"/>Asia and in the southern portions of the
                    United States;&#x2014;in this last<lb break="yes"/>country, it is true, but
                    transiently. The chain of the Ural prolonging<lb break="yes"/>itself under the
                    same meridian, like a wall, from Oust-ourt in the<lb break="yes"/>northern part
                    of the isthmus of Truchmena up to the lcy Sea, and even<lb break="yes"
                    />according to the excellent observations of the botanist, Alexander<lb
                        break="yes"/>Schrenk, and of Baer, to the islands of Wa&#x00EF;gatz and to
                    Nova Zembla,<lb break="yes"/>yields gold in an extent of more than 17 degrees of
                    latitude. Though<lb break="yes"/>in 1821 and 1822, the Ural furnished only 27 or
                    28 poods [973,8 lb.<lb break="yes"/>to 1009,9 lb. avdp.] the ratio of its
                    auriferous sands rose in the three<lb break="yes"/>following years,
                    1823&#x2013;4 and 5 successively to 105, 266 and 237<lb break="yes"/>poods [3787
                    lb., 9594 lb. and 8548 lb. avdp., respectively.] Accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to a
                        <hi rendition="#i">table of the precious metals mined in the Russian Empire
                            and<lb break="yes"/>obtained pure at the mint of Saint Petersburg,</hi>
                    a table which has been<lb break="yes"/>sent to me in MS. by Count Cancrin,
                    Minister of Finance of Russia,<lb break="yes"/>the production of gold was in</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <list>
                        <item>1828, 290 poods 39 pounds [10.494,77 lb. avdp.</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1829, 289 &#x201C; 25 &#x201C; 10.446,08 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1830, 347 &#x201C; 27 &#x201C; 12.539,80 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1831, 352 &#x201C; 2 &#x201C; 12.697,59 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1832, 380 &#x201C; 31 &#x201C; 13.709,29 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1833, 368 &#x201C; 27 &#x201C; 13.297,23 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1834, 363 &#x201C; 10 &#x201C; 13.101,56 lb. avdp.]</item>
                    </list>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>[These quantities differ from what has been more recently officially<lb break="yes"/>published; and the following more complete table is therefore annexed.<note place="foot" n="*">Tooke: History of Prices, p. 451, ed. 1848.</note>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The discovery of gold in the Ural dates back to 1819: the aurife-<lb break="no"/>rous sands of Siberia were not developed until 1829. Since then the<lb break="yes"/>yield has been</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <list>
                        <item>1819, 40 poods 9 pounds 55 zolotnics : 1451,34 lb. avdp.</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1820, 44 &#x201C; 3 &#x201C; &#x2013; &#x201C; : 1589,68 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1821, 52 &#x201C; 4 &#x201C; 65 &#x201C; : 1879,73 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1822, 79 &#x201C; 21 &#x201C; 36 &#x201C; : 2865,61 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1823, 125 &#x201C; 19 &#x201C; 79 &#x201C; : 4526,32 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1824, 228 &#x201C; 13 &#x201C; 38 &#x201C; : 8235,49 &#x201C;</item>
                    </list>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="712" facs="#f0019"/>
                    <list>
                        <item>1825, 257 poods 12 pounds 54 zolotnic : 9280,70 lb. avdp.</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1826, 257 &#x201C; 25 &#x201C; 15 &#x201C; : 9292,90 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1827, 307 &#x201C; 30 &#x201C; 95 &#x201C; : 11100,70 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1828, 317 &#x201C; 39 &#x201C; 44 &#x201C; : 11469,01 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>Epoch in Siberia: 1829, 314 &#x201C; 31 &#x201C; 1 &#x201C; : 11353,19 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1830, 378 &#x201C; 15 &#x201C; 79 &#x201C; : 13648,71 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1831, 396 &#x201C; 29 &#x201C; 37 &#x201C; : 14309,28 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1832, 410 &#x201C; 8 &#x201C; 61 &#x201C; : 14795,50 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1833, 408 &#x201C; 22 &#x201C; 71 &#x201C; : 14736,08 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1834, 406 &#x201C; 4 &#x201C; 64 &#x201C; : 14647,68 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1835, 413 &#x201C; 1 &#x201C; 8 &#x201C; : 14896,90 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1836, 426 &#x201C; 3 &#x201C; 74 &#x201C; : 15368,21 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1837, 469 &#x201C; 20 &#x201C; 75 &#x201C; : 16934,45 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1838, 524 &#x201C; 36 &#x201C; 69 &#x201C; : 18932,52 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1839, 525 &#x201C; 6 &#x201C; 38 &#x201C; : 18941,27 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1840, 585 &#x201C; 15 &#x201C; 60 &#x201C; : 21114,54 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1841, 681 &#x201C; 20 &#x201C; 34 &#x201C; : 24580,39 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1842, 950 &#x201C; 26 &#x201C; 68 &#x201C; : 34288,30 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1843, 1283 &#x201C; 2 &#x201C; 60 &#x201C; : 46277,09 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1844, 1341 &#x201C; 25 &#x201C; 60 &#x201C; : 48389,75 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1845, 1386 &#x201C; 6 &#x201C; 41 &#x201C; : 49995,50 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>1846, <hi rendition="#u">1722</hi> &#x201C; <hi rendition="#u">29</hi> &#x201C; <hi rendition="#u">87</hi> &#x201C; : <hi rendition="#u" >62135,38</hi> &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>14335 &#x201C; 28 &#x201C; 45 &#x201C; : 517054,72 &#x201C;</item>
                    </list>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The Russian pood is divided into 40 pounds; and the pound into<lb break="yes" />96 zolotnics. In the reduction, the pound is rated at 0,90169 lb.<lb break="yes"/>avdp. The aggregate amount is what is given in the authority quoted<lb break="yes"/>from. It will be seen from the table that the yield of the year 1846 is<lb break="yes"/>more than the aggregate of the 10 years preceding the Siberian epoch.<lb break="yes"/>Taking the value of our gold coin as the index, fine gold is worth per<lb break="yes"/>lb. avdp. 301,46 dollars; which may be called in round numbers 300<lb break="yes" />dollars per lb.: and the yield of 1846 was worth 18.640.614 dollars.<lb break="yes"/>The average yield of the whole 28 years is 18.466,24 lb. or 5.539.872<lb break="yes"/>dollars.]</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>When, by order of the Emperor Nicholas, I made with my friends,<lb break="yes"/>Gustavus Rose and Ehrenberg, my expedition to Northern Asia, the<lb break="yes"/>extraction of gold by washing was restricted to that portion of the Ural<lb break="yes"/>which serves as the boundary of Europe. The Alta&#x00EF; (in Mongol, <hi rendition="#i">the<lb break="yes" />gold-mountains,</hi> Alta&#x00EF;in-Oola<note place="foot" n="*">
                            <hi rendition="#i">Alta&#x00EF;in</hi> is a genitive form of the Mongol tongue. Klaproth, Memoires, [Asiatic<lb break="yes"/>Memoirs] vol. ii. p. 382.</note>) furnished only a small quantity (about<lb break="yes" />1900 marcs, say 950 lb. avdp.) which was extractible from the silver<lb break="yes"/>ores (containing also gold) of the rich mines of Schlangenberg or Sme&#x00EF;-<lb break="no"/>nogorsk, of Ridderski and of Syrianowski. But since 1844, this has<lb break="yes"/>been amply compensated for in Siberia. Beds of auriferous sand have<lb break="yes"/>been discovered entirely resembling those on the slopes of the Ural.<lb break="yes"/>The House of Popof, whose influence has been so beneficial to the<lb break="yes" />commerce of the interior of Asia, has given here also a praiseworthy<lb break="yes"/>example. Of 398 poods of gold which the whole Russian Empire<lb break="yes"/>furnished in 1836,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;" >Besides, in <hi rendition="#i">platinum</hi> from the Ural, 118 p. 2 pds. or 8269 marcs of Cologne.</note> 293 p. 26 pds. came from the Ural and 104 p. 15<lb break="yes"/>pds. from the Alta&#x00EF;. [i. e. 75 and 25 per centum respectively.] In the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="713" facs="#f0020"/> year following, 1837, the workings in Eastern Siberia had become so<lb break="yes"/>extended that the Alta&#x00EF; gave 130 poods of washed gold; and the Ural<lb break="yes"/>(both from the Imperial and private mines) 309 poods. If to these be<lb break="yes"/>added 30 poods, extracted from the friable strata of the Alta&#x00EF; and of<lb break="yes"/>Nertschinsk, we have for the whole production of gold in Russia for<lb break="yes"/>1837 an exact result of 469 poods. [This quantity is almost exactly<lb break="yes"/>he same with what is given in the preceding table. It may be added<lb break="yes"/>that of the whole aggregate of that table, there was furnished from the</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <list>
                        <item>Ural Imperial mines, .... 2926 P. 24 p. 32 z. = 105.555,74 lb. avdp.</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>&#x201C; Private mines, .... 4299 39 70 152.205,03 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>Siberian Imperial mines, ... 1293 7 28 46.641,98 &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>&#x201C; Private mines, ... <hi rendition="#u">5895 37 11 212.651,96</hi> &#x201C;</item>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <item>14335 28 45 = 517.054,71 lb. avdp.</item>
                    </list>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The proportion therefore of the Ural to the Siberian yield is as<lb break="yes"/>257.760,77 lb. to 259.293,94 lb., which is a ratio of equality very nearly;<lb break="yes"/>and the productiveness of the Imperial mines to the private ones has<lb break="yes"/>been as 152.197,72 lb. to 364.856,99 lb., or nearly as 2 to 5. The<lb break="yes"/>whole of the gold from the Russian mines since 1819 to 1846, inclu-<lb break="no"/>sive, is equivalent to a sphere of 9,36 feet in diameter.]</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It is only very recently that we have had information upon the ex-<lb break="no"/>traction, properly so called, of the beds of auriferous sand by a very<lb break="yes"/>distinguished geologist, my former comrade in the Southern Ural. Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Helmersen. The gold washed out for some years and in constantly<lb break="yes"/>increasing quantity in the Eastern part of the government of Tomsk<lb break="yes"/>does not belong to the great mass of mountain which we call the prin-<lb break="no"/>cipal chain of the Alta&#x00EF;<note place="foot" n="*">This has been called, very improperly, the little Alta&#x00EF;. Mr. Helmersen par-<lb break="no" />takes of my incredulity as to the existence of the great Alta&#x00EF; (Asiatic Fragments;<lb break="yes"/>vol. i. p. 28.) He says: &#x201C;one of those wide and long vallies traversing the central<lb break="yes" />chain of the Alta&#x00EF;, is the valley of the upper Buchtarma: it separates the northern<lb break="yes"/>portion, belonging to Russia, from the southern belonging to China. This southern<lb break="yes"/>part has been frequently and even very recently designated as the Great Alta&#x00EF;, as<lb break="yes"/>distinguished from the northern, called the Little Alta&#x00EF;. Apart from the impro-<lb break="no"/>priety of these denominations, which do not appear founded in nature, and which<lb break="yes"/>are not accepted by the inhabitants of those regions, they only serve to perpetuate<lb break="yes"/>the error which one map-maker hands over to another. The Chinese and the Rus-<lb break="no" />sian Alta&#x00EF; make only one and the same whole; and there is no motive for consider-<lb break="no"/>ing them as two mountain chains different even in their direction.&#x201D;</note> which Ledebour, Bunge and Gebler have<lb break="yes"/>visited; and in which Mount Beloucha with its snowy peaks rises above<lb break="yes"/>the sources of the Catou&#x00EF;nia to a height of 11.000 feet, the level of the<lb break="yes" />Wetterhorn and of the Peak of Teneriffe. The beds of sand mixed<lb break="yes"/>with gold shew themselves upon the two slopes; but more especially<lb break="yes"/>upon the eastern exposure of a little spur which the Alta&#x00EF; (whose<lb break="yes"/>direction is east and west) throws out to the north under the meridian<lb break="yes"/>of the lake of Telesk, and which is prolonged up to the parallel of<lb break="yes"/>Tomsk. My friend, Mr. Helmersen, says: &#x201C;Upon the maps, this<lb break="yes" />spur which contains gold capable of being washed out, is designated<lb break="yes"/>by the names of the Abassanki, the Kusnezki and the Alatan Moun-<lb break="no"/>tains. In respect to direction, structure<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Helmersen, in the Bulletin of the Academy of S. Petersburg; vol. ii. p. 107.<lb break="yes"/>See also Erman; Reise, [Journey round the World] vol. ii. p. 19 &#x2013; 21.</note> and form, it has the most<lb break="yes"/>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="714" facs="#f0021"/> entire similarity with the Ural; it is, in fact, a repetition of the Ural<lb break="yes"/>upon a smaller scale. The analogy even holds that there also the<lb break="yes"/>eastern slope is rich in gold while the western is much less so. As it<lb break="yes"/>happens that this western slope is the side reserved for the crown, up<lb break="yes"/>to this time private undertakers only have realized a profit from the<lb break="yes" />workings of the Alatan, the northern spur of the Alta&#x00EF;.&#x201D; Geologists,<lb break="yes"/>familiar with my researches upon the direction of the mountain-systems<lb break="yes"/>of inner Asia, and with the ingenious ideas of Elie de Beaumont upon<lb break="yes"/>the parallelism and the relative succession in age of the spurs and<lb break="yes"/>chains of mountains, cannot fail to recognize the importance of Mr.<lb break="yes" />Helmersen&#x2019;s observations. I have not myself seen the northern depo-<lb break="no"/>sites of the auriferous sand of the Alta&#x00EF; (of the Kusnezki) because my<lb break="yes"/>journey was from Tobolsk, by Tara and across the steppe of Barabinski,<lb break="yes"/>towards the western and southern Alta&#x00EF;; and thence towards the boun-<lb break="no"/>dary point of China, Chounima&#x00EF;lekhou, in the province of Ili north of<lb break="yes"/>the Lake Sa&#x00EF;san.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The auriferous sand of the Alta&#x00EF; is a little richer in <hi rendition="#i">silver</hi> than that<lb break="yes"/>of the Ural. Siberian establishments, strongly encouraged by the Im-<lb break="no" />perial administration of the Mines, have even set up washing-concerns,<lb break="yes"/>[lavoirs,] for winter time; and the results of this new branch of indus-<lb break="no"/>try are the more remarkable and satisfactory since the workmen are<lb break="yes"/>only voluntary and are well paid. According to very recent informa-<lb break="no"/>tion which I owe to the Minister of Finance, Count Cancrin, there have<lb break="yes"/>been just discovered rich beds of sand both in the chain of Salairski<lb break="yes" />and along the river Biriousa which separate the governments of Jenis-<lb break="no"/>e&#x00EF;sk and Irkoutsk.<note place="foot" n="*">The village of Biriussinsk, upon the road from Kansk to Nijne&#x00EF;-Udinsk, occu-<lb break="no"/>pies a very picturesque position between two very deep glens; even on the eastern<lb break="yes" />side, the ground is very much broken up to the sandstone escarpments of Nijne&#x00EF;-<lb break="no"/>Udinsk. (Erman, Handschriftliche Nachr. [Epistolary Correspondence.])</note> For the whole of Siberia, there have been already<lb break="yes"/>distributed 240 licenses to work the auriferous beds.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Such is the importance attributable in these later times to the current<lb break="yes"/>of gold from the East to the West; the changes in which current, it<lb break="yes"/>has been the principal object of these researches to indicate. The 469<lb break="yes"/>poods [16.934 lb. avdp.] of gold from the Ural and the Alta&#x00EF;, the yield<lb break="yes"/>of the year of 1837 are worth in Prussian money 7.211.000 thalers [say<lb break="yes"/>5.080.000 dollars.] This amount is only the one-eighth less than the<lb break="yes"/>product of the Minas Geraes in Brazil during the most favorable years<lb break="yes"/>of the brilliant period from 1752 to 1761; but it is almost one-third<lb break="yes"/>less than the precise product of New Granada, Chili and Mexico a<lb break="yes"/>short time before the commencement of the Revolution in Spanish<lb break="yes"/>America. When we consider the immense extent of the Siberian Con-<lb break="no"/>tinent and advert, too, to the rapid increase of the Ural mines during<lb break="yes"/>1822, 1823 and 1824, we have ground for believing that the afflux of<lb break="yes"/>gold from Siberia, from the East to the West, from Asia to Europe has<lb break="yes"/>not attained its maximum. [We have the more ground for such antici-<lb break="no"/>pation when we see that the actual yield of the ninth year afterwards<lb break="yes"/>has nearly quadrupled that of 1837: and that the 20.000.000 dollars of<lb break="yes" />1846 almost equals the product of both gold and silver of Mexico in<lb break="yes"/>her palmiest state.] The yield of Eastern Siberia will augment perhaps<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="715" facs="#f0022"/> more rapidly than the decrease of the <hi rendition="#i">lavoirs</hi> of the Ural; where have<lb break="yes"/>been worked at first and unfortunately in too hasty a manner, the rich-<lb break="no"/>est beds of sand. In the hydrostatic methods used, there is undoubt-<lb break="no"/>edly wasted a large quantity of precious metal, attached as it is to grains<lb break="yes"/>of oxide of iron and other light substances. This is not the place to<lb break="yes"/>discuss if the ingenious mode proposed by Colonel Anossow, the in-<lb break="no"/>tendant at Slatoust, which promises such excellent results and which<lb break="yes" />consists in fusing the mineral with iron and treating the mass with sul-<lb break="no"/>phuric acid&#x2014;is susceptible of employment on a large scale under all<lb break="yes"/>the circumstances of the size of the fused masses, the labor in trans-<lb break="no"/>porting sand containing such a small per centage of gold, and the great<lb break="yes"/>quantity of fuel which would be required. Trials, long and well-<lb break="hyph-yes" />directed, seem hitherto to pronounce against the practicability of this<lb break="yes"/>method.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The notions, which have been obtained in the last fifteen years, of the<lb break="yes"/>gold-riches still waiting to be derived from Northern Asia, make one<lb break="yes"/>involuntarily think of the Issedonians, the Arimaspians and those grif-<lb break="no"/>fins, guardians of immense treasures, which Arist&#x00E6;us of Proconnesus<lb break="yes"/>and, two hundred years after him, Herodotus, have made so famous.<note place="foot" n="*">In the <hi rendition="#i">Fragments of Alcman</hi> which Mr. Welcker has commented on, as well as<lb break="yes"/>in those of Hecat&#x00E6;us and of Damastes, there is alike mention made of the Issedones.<lb break="yes"/>(Hec. Milet. Fragm. ed. Klausen. n. 168, p. 92.)</note>
                        <lb break="yes"/>I have had the good fortune to visit, in the Southern Ural, localities<lb break="yes"/>where, a few inches below the surface, have been discovered, near to-<lb break="no"/>gether, brilliant masses of gold of 13, of 15, and even of 24 Russian<lb break="yes"/>pounds: [11.7 lb., 13.5 lb. and 21.6 lb. avdp. respectively.]<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">The largest lump of gold found as yet in the Ural (at Alexandrowsk, near<lb break="yes"/>Miask) is 8 inches long by 5&#x215C; wide and 4&#x00BE; thick. It weighs 24 pounds 69 zolotnic<lb break="yes"/>Russian [22.29 lb. avdp.] and is preserved at S. Petersburg in the magnificent col-<lb break="no"/>lection of minerals of the Mining Corps. Among the lumps of platina of Nischne-<lb break="no"/>Tagilsk (the property of Demidoff) have been found three weighing 13, 19 and 20<lb break="yes"/>pounds Russian, respectively. Rose: Reise nach dem Ural, vol. i. p. 41.</note> It may<lb break="yes"/>be that masses much larger have been found formerly in the shape of<lb break="yes"/>rounded lumps and lying exposed on the surface. There would be<lb break="yes"/>nothing astonishing, then, if from the most remote antiquity, this gold<lb break="yes"/>has been gathered by a hunting and pastoral people,&#x2014;if the report of<lb break="yes"/>riches so considerable, echoed afar and spread from the shores of the<lb break="yes"/>Euxine Sea to the Hellenic colonies who very soon had relations with<lb break="yes"/>the North-east of Asia beyond the Caspian Sea and Lake Aral.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The merchant Greeks and even the Scythians did not themselves<lb break="yes" />penetrate as far as to the Issedonians; they trafficked only with the<lb break="yes"/>Argipp&#x0153;ans. Niebuhr, in his researches upon the Scythians and the<lb break="yes"/>Getians (researches that have failed of confirmation from what we<lb break="yes"/>know at the present day of the difference of races and the affinities of<lb break="yes"/>languages among the people of Northern Asia) places the Issedonians<lb break="yes"/>and the Arimaspians to the north of Orenburg<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Klein historiche und philologische Schriften; p. 361. (See also the <hi rendition="#i">Herodotische<lb break="yes"/>Welt-tafel</hi> of Niebuhr.)</note> and therefore just in<lb break="yes"/>that gold region now so well known, lying on the eastern slope of the<lb break="yes" />Southern Ural. This opinion is supported in the solid work (quite re-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="716" facs="#f0023"/> cently published) by the Counsellor of State, Eichwald, under the title:<note place="foot" n="*">Eichwald, like Reichard, derives the name <hi rendition="#i">Issedonian</hi> from the river <hi rendition="#i">Isset;</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>regards this people as a tribe of the Vogul.</note>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Ancient Geography of the Caspian Sea.</hi> Heeren and Völker place the<lb break="yes"/>gold-region of Herodotus in the Alta&#x00EF;;<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Heeren: Ideen über Politik und Verkehr; vol. i. sec. 2, p. 281&#x2014;287, ed. 1824.</note> and, I confess, this opinion<lb break="yes"/>seems to me the more justified by the configuration of the localities.<lb break="yes"/>Herodotus describes a commercial route by which the gold of the<lb break="yes"/>Northern Alta&#x00EF; (or rather as I suppose the repute of this gold) might<lb break="yes"/>reach the Euxine by the intermediary Issedonians and Scythians.<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Völker: Mythische Geographie der Griechen und Römer; vol. i. p. 188 and<lb break="yes"/>191, and the commentary on this work by Klausen in the <hi rendition="#i" >Scheuzeitung</hi> for 1832, p.<lb break="yes"/>653. Völker has collected with the greatest care the passages from the ancient au-<lb break="no"/>thors, which I do not specially cite here.</note> To<lb break="yes"/>penetrate to the Argipp&#x00E6;ans with their bald heads, flat noses and large<lb break="yes"/>chins,<note place="foot" n="||">These Argipp&#x00E6;ans lived on the fruit of the <hi rendition="#i">arbor Ponticus</hi> whose juice was<lb break="yes"/>called <hi rendition="#i">aschy;</hi> the mass of which after having been strained is kneaded into cakes or<lb break="yes"/>balls. [Herod. Melpom. c. 23.] Nemnich and Heeren have already thought to find<lb break="yes" />in this the <hi rendition="#i">Prunus padus</hi> (vol. i. sec. 2, p. 385.) See also Erman: Reise um die<lb break="yes"/>Erde; vol. i. p. 307.</note> the Scythians and the Greeks of the Pontic colonies had to<lb break="yes"/>have recourse in their commerce to seven interpreters of as many dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent languages.<note place="foot" n="§" >Herodotus: iv. 24.</note>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Since the discovery of such rich deposites of auriferous sand in the<lb break="yes"/>spur which the Alta&#x00EF; throws out to the North as far as the parallel of<lb break="yes"/>Tomsk, the opinion of the Arimaspians having inhabited a country east<lb break="yes"/>of the Ural and very far from this mountain-chain, gains certainly prob-<lb break="no"/>ability. In the conjecture of a learned and acute traveller, Adolph<lb break="yes" />Erman, the myth of the <hi rendition="#i">griffins</hi> attaches to the fossil remains of the<lb break="yes"/>antediluvian pachyderms so frequently occurring in Northern Siberia,<lb break="yes"/>and in which the hunters believe they see the talons and head of a<lb break="yes"/>gigantic bird. If, concludes Mr. Erman, we will agree to see in this<lb break="yes"/>ancient tradition the prototype of the Greek myth, we have entire foun-<lb break="no"/>dation for saying that the miners took the gold <hi rendition="#i">from the bosom of the<lb break="yes"/>griffins;</hi> for nothing is more common at this day, as formerly, than to<lb break="yes" />meet with auriferous sand in strata containing fossils of the kind.<lb break="yes"/>However plausible this explication, there is one fact against it, viz. the<lb break="yes"/>mention of these fabulous creatures, the griffins, in the poems of Hesiod<lb break="yes"/>where under the form of monsters half lion, half eagle, they adorn the<lb break="yes"/>gates of Persepolis; and that they early reached Greece by way of<lb break="yes" />Miletus.<note place="foot" n="¶">C. O. Muller: Dorier [the Dorians] vol. ii. p. 276. Upon the Griffin of Ctesias,<lb break="yes"/>as a Bactro-Indian animal, see Heeren n. s. vol. i. sec. i. p. 239; and Böttiger:<lb break="yes"/>Griech. Vasengemälde; vol. i. n. 3, p. 105. Herodotus also (iv. 79. 152) speaks<lb break="yes"/>twice of griffins as images and ornaments.</note>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A celebrated Russian academician, Mr. Gräfe, is inclined to regard a<lb break="yes"/>monster with enormous teeth&#x2014;the <hi rendition="#i" >odontotyrannus</hi> spoken of by the<lb break="yes"/>Byzantine Historians<note place="foot" n="**">[Cedrenus: Collect. Byzant. T. ix. p. 153. Glycas: ib. T. xi. p. 142&#x2014;143.]</note> and by Julius Valerius whose works have been<lb break="yes"/>discovered by Ma&#x00EF;&#x2014;as a vague reminiscence of the Siberian mammoth,<lb break="yes"/>as a distant echo from the primeval world.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;&#x2020;">Gräfe: in the Mem. of the Acad. of S. Petersburg; 1830, p. 71 and 74. Julius<lb break="yes"/>Valerius in the Res Gest&#x00E6; Alexandri etc. [Milan 1817] lib. iii. c. 33. See besides<lb break="yes"/>the Chronique Hamartol; which Hase has obtained in the MS. of the Paris Library.</note> This <hi rendition="#i" >tyrannus,</hi> however,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="717" facs="#f0024"/> as well as the ancient myth of the griffins does not seem to me to have<lb break="yes"/>risen from the icy bosom of these northern alluvial lands; they appear<lb break="yes"/>to me rather the imaginative creatures of a southern zone and a warmer<lb break="yes" />clime.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I mentioned just now that they find in the Ural enormous masses of<lb break="yes"/>gold some inches below the surface. Little water-drains, or a good<lb break="yes"/>many other operations equally insignificant, may have by degrees bared<lb break="yes"/>those masses until they appear some day at the very surface itself. Can<lb break="yes"/>we see aught but a myth in the story of the sacred gold of the Scythians<lb break="yes"/>which Herodotus tells, and in that of the agricultural implements of<lb break="yes"/>gold which fell from Heaven and which the two princes, the sons of the<lb break="yes"/>king [Targitaus] who first approached could not touch without being<lb break="yes"/>burnt, while the youngest, Colaxais, bore unharmed the cooling metal<lb break="yes"/>home? or is it rather a remote memory of a fall of a&#x00EB;roliths in a state<lb break="yes"/>of ignition?<note place="foot" n="*">[Herodotus: Melpom. c. 5. Mr. Humboldt has here given at length the whole<lb break="yes"/>chapter in the Latin of Schweighaüser. It is a perplexed passage in the original;<lb break="yes"/>but as the undoubted substance is retained above in the text, I have thought it<lb break="yes"/>allowable to be omitted.] The Massagetians, a tribe of Alans according to Am-<lb break="no"/>mianus Marcellinus, used for the furniture of their horses <hi rendition="#i" >gold</hi> as other people do<lb break="yes"/>iron. Herod. Clio, c. 215. [See also Judges viii. 26, for the mention of the golden<lb break="yes"/>chains for the camels; which the Ishmaelitish Midianites yielded to Jerubbaal.]</note> Iron and gold, are they here taken for one another; and<lb break="yes"/>was the sacred gold but a meteoric stone, like the mass found by Pallas,<lb break="yes"/>out of which implements of labor could be forged, just as the Esqui-<lb break="no"/>maux of Baffin&#x2019;s Bay make yet to this day their knives from a&#x00EB;roliths<lb break="yes"/>half buried in the snow? I know that physical explanations of ancient<lb break="yes"/>myths and of modern miracles are not in favor now, and that I run the<lb break="yes"/>risk of straying into the errors of the Alexandrian grammarians: but it<lb break="yes"/>is pardonable for a naturalist to suggest the fall of bolids. Perhaps the<lb break="yes"/>heavenly metal only burned to drive off the elder brothers? Even ac-<lb break="no"/>cording to the popular belief in Germany, the place of buried treasures<lb break="yes"/>always bakes and burns. But considerations like these take us off from<lb break="yes" />researches purely physical.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>These beds of auriferous sand in Northern Asia on this side the Obi,<lb break="yes"/>this amount of 130 poods [4688.77 lb. avdp.] the yield of one year<lb break="yes"/>[1837] in the Alta&#x00EF; or Kusnezki, is an event in the history of the com-<lb break="no"/>merce of gold; and an event the more important, since it happens in<lb break="yes"/>that part of Asia which is under the immediate domination of Europe,<lb break="yes"/>and since the product of the workings, flowing towards the West, ex-<lb break="no" />ercises its influence altogether upon the commerce of Europe. How-<lb break="no"/>ever ancient may be in Asia the workings of the mineral (so to speak)<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">in place</hi>&#x2014;known under the vague denomination of Tchoudic veins,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">What are called <hi rendition="#i">Tchoudic veins</hi> and the Tchoudic mines of North Asia do not<lb break="yes"/>belong to the same stock. The name of this Cabirian race who hunted the mineral<lb break="yes"/>and forged the metal, originally signified only <hi rendition="#i">foreigners, not Russians</hi> [outside bar-<lb break="no"/>barians;] but in a more emphatic manner among the Russian annals, according to<lb break="yes" />Klaproth (Asia Polyglotta, p. 184) and the more recent and learned researches of<lb break="yes"/>Siogren (Mem. of the Acad. of S. Petersburg; vi. series, vol. i. p. 308) it covers<lb break="yes"/>all the Finnish and the Uralian tribes.</note>
                        <lb break="yes"/>the existence of considerable masses of manufactured gold found at the<lb break="yes"/>earliest occupation of the country in the sepulchres and of which such<lb break="yes"/>remarkable specimens exist in the collections of S. Petersburg, is ex-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="718" facs="#f0025"/> plained more perfectly by the discovery at remote epochs of lumps of<lb break="yes"/>gold in the alluvium immediately below the surface of the ground.<lb break="yes"/>Müller, the excellent historian of Siberia, says that the first discoveries<lb break="yes"/>of gold in the sepulchres (<hi rendition="#i">kourganoui</hi>) lowered in a most surprising<lb break="yes"/>manner the value of this metal at Krasnojarsk.<note place="foot" n="*">Journal Asiatique, t. ii. p. 12.</note> Internal Asia, confined<lb break="yes"/>between the chain of the Himalaya and the volcanic range called the<lb break="yes"/>Celestial Mountains [Thian-chan] forms like China a close realm, as<lb break="yes" />well in a political as (almost in the same degree) in a commercial point<lb break="yes"/>of view. However uncertain may be our notions as to this part of the<lb break="yes"/>globe, nevertheless from the brilliant epoch of the Mongol Dynasties to<lb break="yes"/>the end of the 13th century, since the travels of the Venetian Polo, the<lb break="yes"/>fame of these beds of auriferous sand in the interior of Asia has been<lb break="yes"/>penetrating to Europe&#x2014;on the south by the way of India, on the north,<lb break="yes"/>through Siberia.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The Calcutta journals report that in all Western Thibet, the streams<lb break="yes"/>bring down gold; and that the natives extract the metal by amalgamation.<lb break="yes"/>Ancient Indian myths make the sovereign of the North, Kouwera, to<lb break="yes"/>be the god of riches; and it is remarkable that the residence of this<lb break="yes"/>god (Alak&#x00E2;) is not upon the range of the Himalaya itself, but on the<lb break="yes" />Kail&#x00E2;sa on this side of the Himalaya, in Thibet.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Albert Höfer: Translation of the Urwasi and the Kalid&#x00E2;sa; 1837, p. 90.</note> It is more to<lb break="yes"/>the north-west, on this side of the chain of Kouen-loun which<lb break="yes" />separates the districts of Ladakh and Khotan, that Heeren<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Herod. iii. 102&#x2014;106. Heeren: 1st part, 2d sect. p. 90, 102, 340&#x2014;345. Com-<lb break="no"/>pare Ritter: Asia, vol. ii. 657&#x2014;660.</note> places, with<lb break="yes"/>much probability in my opinion, the great Sandy Desert so rich in gold<lb break="yes"/>which the Indians bordering on Caspatyrus visited and where ants,<lb break="yes"/>smaller than dogs but larger than foxes, burrowed for their nests. The<lb break="yes"/>Bolor, whose eastern slope leads to Khoufaloun (a region which the<lb break="yes"/>geographers designate under the name of Little Thibet or Kaschgar,)<lb break="yes"/>and to the Lake Lop among the steppes, offered also on its western<lb break="yes"/>slope to the distinguished traveller who has last explored this <hi rendition="#i">terra in-<lb break="no"/>cognita,</hi> Alexander Burnes, the auriferous beds of Durrvaz and of the<lb break="yes"/>upper waters of the Oxus, which he has described.<note place="foot" n="||">Burnes: Travels, vol. ii. p. 165. In 1831, they still found in the Oxus lumps of<lb break="yes"/>gold as large as a pigeon&#x2019;s-egg. Like the Rhine, the Oxus (Djihoun) rolls its sands<lb break="yes"/>of gold down to its mouth; and the unfortunate expedition of Prince Alexander<lb break="yes"/>Bekewitsch, undertaken for Peter the Great in 1716, was induced by exaggerated<lb break="yes" />and untruthful statements as to the accumulation of gold near the ancient embou-<lb break="no"/>chure of the Oxus, south of the little chain of the Balkan and near the eastern<lb break="yes"/>shore of the Caspian Sea.</note> In China the<lb break="yes"/>extraction of gold by washing, dates from the highest antiquity; and<lb break="yes"/>we can distinguish in the metallurgic nomenclature of this pedantic<lb break="yes" />people <hi rendition="#i">the fields of gold</hi>
                        <note place="foot" n="§">Landresse: upon the Auriferous Alluvion of China, in the Asiatic Journal,<lb break="yes"/>vol. ii. p. 90.</note> (beds of gold-ore of vast extent in the plains)<lb break="yes"/>and lumps of gold under the name of <hi rendition="#i">dog-heads,</hi> of <hi rendition="#i" >wheat-grains,</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>of <hi rendition="#i" >millet-seed.</hi> Unfortunately in Choco, in Sonora and in the Ural, as<lb break="yes"/>every where, there are fewer <hi rendition="#i" >dog-heads</hi> than <hi rendition="#i">millet-seed.</hi>
                    </p>
                
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 