<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-20" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Humbolt on the Precious Metals.</hi>&#x2014;In a tract<lb/>upon the fluctuations in the production of gold, recently put<lb/>forth by M. Von Humboldt, the following facts are given:&#x2014;<lb/>&#x201C;We learn from the acute researches of Boekh, how on the<lb/>opening of the East by the Persian wars, and by the expe-<lb/>dition of the great Macedonian to India, gold gradually<lb/>accumulated in European Greece, so that in the time of<lb/>Demosthenes, for example, the precious metals had sunk to<lb/>a fifth of the value which they had in the days of Solon. The<lb/>stream then ran from east to west, and so copious was the<lb/>influx of gold, that its relative value to silver, which in the<lb/>time of Herodotus, was 13 to 1, was at the death of Alex-<lb/>ander, only as 10 to 1. The less universal were the commu-<lb/>nications of trade in the ancient world, the greater and more<lb/>sudden must have been the alterations in the relative value of<lb/>gold and silver. Thus, in consequence of the local accu-<lb/>mulations of the precious metals, we find that in Rome, just<lb/>after the conquest of Syracuse, gold was to silver as 17 1-7<lb/>to 1: whereas, under Julius C&#x00E6;sar, its relative value was, for<lb/>some time, but as 8 1-&#x00BE; to 1. The less the quantity of the<lb/>precious metals actually existing in a country, the more easily<lb/>can a sudden influx of them occasion these excessive varia-<lb/>tions of their value. The civilized world is at present assured<lb/>of stability in the value of the precious metals, by the extent<lb/>and rapidity of the commerce which establishes their equili-<lb/>brium, and by the great quantities of gold and silver already<lb/>collected. After the revolution in Spanish America, the an-<lb/>nual production of the precious metals fell, for some years,<lb/>to one-third of its former amount, yet the oscillations of their<lb/>relative value, during that period, were slight, and hardly as-<lb/>cribable to the decreased production.&#x201D; The writer further<lb/>states that the mass of the precious metals brought to Europe<lb/>from the discovery of America till the outbreak of the Mexi-<lb/>can revolution, was 10.400,000 Castilian marks of gold,<lb/>(worth about three hundred millions sterling,) and 533.700,000<lb/>marks of silver; together worth 5,940 millions of piastres.<lb/>The silver taken from the American mines in the above-<lb/>mentioned period would be, when refined, sufficient to form a<lb/>ball, or solid globe, of pure silver, eighty-nine feet in diameter.<lb/>The produce of the Russian gold mines in 1837 was valued at<lb/>800,000@. In the United States, the production of gold in-<lb/>creased, from 1824 to 1834&#x2014;from the value of 5.000 to that<lb/>of 898,000 dollars; since that time it has considerably de-<lb/>clined. The gold was found chiefly in North Carolina and<lb/>Georgia. The amount of the precious metals drawn from the<lb/>mines of Siberia and of the United States are inconsiderable<lb/>in comparison with that from the mines of Mexico and Peru;<lb/>yet they are sufficient to disprove the supposition formerly<lb/>entertained, that large deposits were confined to tropical<lb/>countries.</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>