<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On the Fluctuations in the Production of Gold, considered with reference to the Problems of State Economy</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:07</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">V.79</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-05</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-01.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-02.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-05.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-17.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1838-Ueber_die_Schwankungen-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On the Fluctuations in the Production of Gold, considered with reference to the Problems of State Economy</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1839</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Athenæum. Journal of English and Foreign Literature, Science, and the Fine Arts&lt;/i&gt; 584 (5. Januar 1839), S. 8–9.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Schmuck: Kapitälchen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
      <pb n="8" facs="#f0001"/>
      <cb/>
      <cb/>
      <cb/>
      <lb/>
      <div n="1">
        <head><hi rendition="#i">On the Fluctuations in the Production of Gold,<lb/>considered with
            reference to the Problems of<lb/>State Economy.</hi> By Alex. von Humboldt.</head>
        <lb/>
        <p><hi rendition="#k">In</hi> this little tract, obligingly forwarded to us,<lb/>(and
          intended, we presume, for some of the lite-<lb/>rary periodicals of Germany,) we find a
          curious<lb/>theme, handled with great neatness and inge-<lb/>nuity. There is not, indeed,
          disclosed in it much<lb/>positive novelty, either of fact or speculation;<lb/>but
          comprehensive views, variety of topics, con-<lb/>siderable sprightliness, and an habitual
          clearness<lb/>of expression, capable of making philosophic<lb/>truth intelligible to the
          multitude, without sacri-<lb/>ficing, in any degree, its dignity or
          essential<lb/>strictness&#x2014;these, the common recommendations<lb/>of all M. von
          Humboldt&#x2019;s works, are conspicuous<lb/>in this; and throw attractions over a
          subject<lb/>apparently exhausted in dry reports on bullion<lb/>and cash payments.</p>
        <lb/>
        <p>A few centuries ago, it was thought that<lb/>gold was a production only of the hottest
          coun-<lb/>tries. Columbus, when sailing along the coast<lb/>of Cuba, wrote in his
          journal,&#x2014; &#x201C;to judge by<lb/>the great heat, this country must be rich
          in<lb/>gold.&#x201D; A similar groundless belief, we may<lb/>remark, respecting the
          climate prolific of dia-<lb/>monds is maintained in some publications of<lb/>our own day.
          Nevertheless, diamonds, and still<lb/>more abundantly, gold, are now found in
          the<lb/>Uralian Mountains, under the 65th degree of<lb/>north latitude: and the Siberian
          gold mines,<lb/>situated on the slopes of the northern ramifica-<lb/>tions of the Altai
          Mountains, are daily disclosing<lb/>new treasures. The increased productiveness of<lb/>the
          Siberian gold mines, within the last quarter<lb/>of a century, stimulates M. von Humboldt
          to<lb/>vindicate the statements of Herodotus and<lb/>Ctesias, the former of whom places,
          in the heart<lb/>of Asia, in the country of the Aramasps, mines<lb/>of gold guarded by
          griffons; the latter sets<lb/>somewhere between Persia and India, the auri-<lb/>ferous
          soil which was excavated and exposed to<lb/>view by ants nearly as large as foxes. But
          what-<lb/>ever may have been the veritable groundwork of<lb/>these stories, it appears to
          us to be out of the<lb/>power of ingenious erudition to strip them of<lb/>their vagueness
          and fabulous character. M. von<lb/>Humboldt, whose imagination is as active as
          his<lb/>reasoning faculty, struggles in vain to give them<lb/>precision and authenticity.
          He might, however,<lb/>have corroborated his conjecture that the gold<lb/>mines of Central
          Asia, and the Ural, were<lb/>wrought in very ancient times, by stating that in<lb/>all
          those mines, at the present day, are found<lb/>relics of antiquity belonging to a people
          different<lb/>from those who now possess the soil. The fol-<lb/>lowing observations have
          greater value:&#x2014;</p>
        <lb/>
        <p>We learn from the acute researches of Boekh,<lb/>how, on the opening of the East by the
          Persian wars,<lb/>and by the expedition of the great Macedonian to<lb/>India, gold
          gradually accumulated in European<lb/>Greece, so that in the time of Demosthenes, for
          ex-<lb/>ample, the precious metals had sunk to a fifth of the<lb/>value which they had in
          the days of Solon. The<lb/>stream then ran from east to west, and so copious<lb/>was the
          influx of gold, that its relative value to silver,<lb/>which, in the time of Herodotus,
          was as 13 to 1, was,<lb/><pb n="9" facs="#f0002"/>
          <cb/> at the death of Alexander, only as 10 to 1. The<lb/>less universal were the
          communications of trade in<lb/>the ancient world, the greater and more sudden
          must<lb/>have been the alterations in the relative value of<lb/>gold and silver. Thus, in
          consequence of local ac-<lb/>cumulations of the precious metals, we find that in<lb/>Rome,
          just after the conquest of Syracuse, gold was<lb/>to silver as 17<formula notation="TeX"
            >\frac{1}{7}</formula> to 1; whereas, under Julius C&#x00E6;sar,<lb/>its relative value
          was, for some time, but as 8<formula notation="TeX">\frac{13}{14}</formula><lb/>to 1. The
          less the quantity of the precious metals<lb/>actually existing in a country, the more
          easily can a<lb/>sudden influx of them occasion these excessive vari-<lb/>ations of their
          value. The civilized world is at pre-<lb/>sent assured of stability in the value of the
          precious<lb/>metals, by the extent and rapidity of the commerce<lb/>which establishes
          their equilibrium, and by the great<lb/>quantities of gold and silver already collected.
          After<lb/>the revolution in Spanish America, the annual pro-<lb/>duction of the precious
          metals fell, for some years,<lb/>to one-third of its former amount, yet the
          oscillations<lb/>of their relative value, during that period, were<lb/>slight, and hardly
          ascribable to the decreased pro-<lb/>duction.</p>
        <lb/>
        <p>In confirmation of this remark, we may refer<lb/>to the recent experience of this
          country. In the<lb/>course of ten years&#x2014;from 1817 to 1827&#x2014;the<lb/>Bank of
          England coined 1,294,000 marks of<lb/>gold, (in value 38,130,000<hi rendition="#i">l.</hi>
          sterling); and yet<lb/>this great demand for gold raised its relative value<lb/>only
          four-and-a-half per cent. In the present<lb/>state of the civilized world, so many
          circum-<lb/>stances operate together on the price of the pre-<lb/>cious metals, that
          considerable and partial fluc-<lb/>tuations in their relative value are almost
          im-<lb/>possible. Formerly, however, society felt many<lb/>shocks from this cause, without
          knowing whence<lb/>they came: Bishop Latimer preached his famous<lb/>sermon before Edward
          VI., complaining indig-<lb/>nantly of the great increase in the prices of all<lb/>the
          necessaries of life, in the year 1548, just<lb/>three years after the discovery of the
          mines of<lb/>Potosi.</p>
        <lb/>
        <p>The mass of the precious metals (says M. von<lb/>Humboldt) which was brought to Europe
          during the<lb/>period that elapsed from the discovery of America<lb/>till the outbreak of
          the Mexican revolution, was<lb/>10,400,000 Castilian marks of gold, (worth about<lb/>three
          hundred millions sterling,) and 533,700,000<lb/>marks of silver; together worth 5,940
          millions of<lb/>piastres. The due allowance being made for the<lb/>loss of bulk sustained
          in the process of refinement,<lb/>the silver taken from the American mines in
          the<lb/>above-mentioned period would be sufficient to form<lb/>a ball, or solid globe, of
          pure silver, eighty-nine feet<lb/>in diameter.</p>
        <lb/>
        <p>It is curious to compare the mass of silver<lb/>yielded by Spanish America, during 318
          years,<lb/>with the mass of that useful metal, iron, annually<lb/>wrought by single
          European states. According<lb/>to M. von Dechen, a well-informed geologist,<lb/>globes of
          pure iron, representing the quantities<lb/>annually produced, would require, for Great
          Bri-<lb/>tain 157, for France 118, and for Prussia 80<lb/>feet in diameter.</p>
        <lb/>
        <p>M. von Humboldt, after calling attention to<lb/>the circumstance that the fountains of
          mineral<lb/>wealth are not perennial; that the richest mines<lb/>are, in time, exhausted;
          and that, owing to these<lb/>alterations in the springs, the stream of riches<lb/>has
          sometimes flowed from east to west, and<lb/>sometimes in the contrary direction;
          proceeds<lb/>to show that the world has no cause to dread a<lb/>lack of gold. From the
          earliest ages, as soon as<lb/>one auriferous deposit has ceased to be produc-<lb/>tive,
          another has replaced it; and the precious<lb/>metals, wherever they are found, soon force
          their<lb/>way into universal circulation. Contemporane-<lb/>ously with the decline in the
          productiveness of<lb/>the Spanish American mines, (which, owing to<lb/>the energy of some
          English companies, however,<lb/>have in some measure recovered their
          former<lb/>importance), the gold of the Uralian Mountains<lb/>began to flow into the
          European markets. In<lb/>1821 the produce of the Ural was about 1000lb.<lb/><cb/> weight;
          it continued, however, to increase regu-<lb/>larly till 1832, when it amounted to
          15,200lb.<lb/>(worth about 670,000<hi rendition="#i">l.</hi> sterling). From that<lb/>time
          it has slowly declined; but its diminished<lb/>value has been compensated, since 1834, by
          the dis-<lb/>covery of new gold mines in the Altai, or Altaiin<lb/>Oola, (that is, in
          Mongolian, <hi rendition="#i">the gold mountain</hi>).<lb/>These have gone on increasing
          in value; so that<lb/>their produce is now nearly half of that of the<lb/>Uralian mines,
          and in 1837 the Russian gold<lb/>produced was worth 800,000<hi rendition="#i">l.</hi>
          sterling.</p>
        <lb/>
        <p>In the United States also, the production of<lb/>gold increased, in ten years&#x2014;from
          1824 to 1834<lb/>&#x2014;from the value of 5,000 to that of 898,000 dol-<lb/>lars: from
          that time it has considerably declined.<lb/>The gold was found chiefly in North
          Carolina<lb/>and Georgia. The amount of the precious metals<lb/>drawn from the mines of
          Siberia and of the United<lb/>States are inconsiderable indeed in comparison<lb/>with that
          poured forth from the mines of Mexico<lb/>and Peru, yet they are sufficient to
          invalidate<lb/>the opinion which confines the great deposits of<lb/>the noble metals to
          tropical countries. The mul-<lb/>tiplication of sources also, however feeble they<lb/>may
          severally be, obviously lessens the impor-<lb/>tance which might be attached to the drying
          up<lb/>of the great streams of the precious metals, and<lb/>must tend to quiet the
          apprehensions of those<lb/>who contemplate with anxiety a dearth of bullion.</p>
        <lb/>
        <p>It is impossible to read this little treatise of<lb/>M. von Humboldt, without feeling an
          earnest<lb/>desire to investigate closely the operation of<lb/>money as an element of
          national prosperity. It<lb/>would appear, at first view, that the greater the<lb/>quantity
          of money in circulation&#x2014;the prices of<lb/>necessaries, and the amount of population
          being<lb/>supposed to remain unchanged&#x2014;the greater<lb/>must be the prosperity of
          the community. The<lb/>value of the money in circulation indicates the<lb/>activity of the
          traffic which ministers to the com-<lb/>forts of society. But this problem is, in
          reality,<lb/>extremely complicated; inasmuch as all the ele-<lb/>ments vary, from the
          operation of many circum-<lb/>stances besides those which fall under
          immediate<lb/>consideration. We, therefore, recommend it to<lb/>the care of statists, to
          be carefully analyzed and<lb/>fitted for application.</p>
        <lb/>
      </div>
    </body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
