<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-20" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <p><hi rendition="#i">Humboldt on the Precious Metals.</hi>&#x2014;In a tract upon the<lb/>fluctuations in the production of gold, recently put forth by<lb/>M. Von Humboldt, the following facts are given:&#x2014;&#x201C;We<lb/>learn from the acute researches of Boekh, how, on the opening<lb/>of the East by the Persian wars, and by the expedition of the<lb/>great Macedonian to India, gold gradualy accumulated in<lb/>European Greece, so that in the time of Demosthenes, for<lb/>example, the precious metals had sunk to a fifth of the value<lb/>which they had in the days of Solon. The stream then ran<lb/>from east to west, and so copious was the influx of gold, that<lb/>its relative value to silver, which in the time of Herodotus,<lb/>was as 13 to 1, was at the death of Alexander, only as 10 to 1.<lb/>The less universal were the communications of trade in the<lb/>ancient world, the greater and more sudden must have been<lb/>the alterations in the relative value of gold and silver. Thus,<lb/>in consequence of local accumulations of the precious metals,<lb/>we find  that in Rome, just after the conquest of Syracuse,<lb/>gold was to silver as 17 1-7 to 1; whereas, under Julius<lb/>C&#x00E6;sar, its relative value was, for some time, but as 8 1-&#x00BE; to 1.<lb/>The less the quantity of the precious metals actually existing<lb/>in a country, the more easily can a sudden influx of them<lb/>occasion these excessive variations of their value. The<lb/>civilized world is at present assured of stability in the value<lb/>of the precious metals, by the extent and rapidity of the<lb/>commerce which establishes their equilibrium, and by the<lb/>great quantities of gold and silver already collected. After<lb/>the revolution in Spanish America, the annual production of<lb/>the precious metals fell, for some years, to one-third of its<lb/>former amount, yet the oscillations of their relative value,<lb/>during that period, were slight, and hardly ascribable to the<lb/>decreased production.&#x201D; The writer further states that the<lb/>mass of the precious metals brought to Europe from the<lb/>discovery of America till the outbreak of the Mexican<lb/>revolution, was 10,400,000 Castilian marks of gold, (worth<lb/>about three hundred millions sterling,) and 533,700,000 marks<lb/>of silver; together worth 5,940 millions of piastres. The silver<lb/>taken from the American mines in the above-mentioned<lb/>period would be, when refined, sufficient to form a ball, or<lb/>solid globe, of pure silver, eighty-nine feet in diameter. The<lb/>produce of the Russian gold mines in 1837 was valued at<lb/>800,000&#x00A3;. In the United States, the production of gold<lb/>increased, from 1824 to 1834&#x2014;from the value of 5,000 to that<lb/>of 898,000 dollars; since that time it has considerably declined.<lb/>The gold was found chiefly in North Carolina and Georgia.<lb/>The amount of the precious metals drawn from the mines of<lb/>Siberia and of the United States are inconsiderable in com-<lb/>parison with that from the mines of Mexico and Peru; yet<lb/>they are sufficient to disprove the supposition formerly enter-<lb/>tained, that large deposits were confined to tropical countries.</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>