<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/103788910X">
                        <surname>Metz</surname>
                        <forename>Bernhard</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-20" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-09-24" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="502" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Longitude of Valparaiso and Callao, in a Letter<lb break="yes"/>from</hi> Baron <hi rendition="#k">
                        <hi rendition="#g">Alexander von Humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <hi rendition="#et">
                            <hi rendition="#i">Sans Souci, near Potsdam, Sept.</hi> 6, 1839.</hi>
                    </dateline>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#k">
                            <hi rendition="#g">Sir,</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </salute>
                </opener>
                <p>&#x2014;I have long delayed to express the homage of my lively<lb break="yes" />gratitude for your kindness in enabling me so soon to profit by<lb break="yes" />the important observations which enrich the Second Part of<lb break="yes" />Volume IX. of the London Geographical Journal. A journey<lb break="yes"/>with the King of Prussia into Bohemia has delayed the renewed<lb break="yes" />expression of my high esteem, and of the always increasing in-<lb break="no" />terest caused by reading a journal so rich in original material and<lb break="yes"/>so carefully edited.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The too flattering manner in which the President of the Society,<lb break="yes" />Mr. W. Hamilton, has in his excellent address mentioned my<lb break="yes" />trifling and <hi rendition="#i">antediluvian</hi> astronomical labours in tropical America<lb break="yes"/>has imposed upon me the task of examining again, and by com-<lb break="no"/>parison with new and good observations, the position of some<lb break="yes"/>points to which Captain Fitz Roy, in his admirable work <hi rendition="#i">(Ap-<lb break="no"/>pendix to the Voyages of the Beagle),</hi> has attached especial in-<lb break="no"/>terest. Among the points which I have determined on the coast<lb break="yes"/>of the Pacific Ocean, Callao, the port of Lima, is perhaps the<lb break="yes"/>most important of all. It is as much so as Cumana, Porto Rico,<lb break="yes"/>and Havanah, are in the West Indies. In the luminous and<lb break="yes"/>rigorous statement which Captain Fitz Roy has given of the<lb break="yes"/>whole of his chronometric determinations, in which, in the entire<lb break="yes"/>circuit of the globe, only 33 seconds of time are to be accounted<lb break="yes"/>for, to be divided over a great number of separate meridian dis-<lb break="no"/>tances, Captain Fitz Roy says, &#x201C;Callao, Sydney, and the Cape<lb break="yes"/>of Good Hope <hi rendition="#i">(App.</hi> p. 345), are three remote points which<lb break="yes"/>might be selected (for comparison), rather than others, because<lb break="yes"/>generally supposed to be well determined; if the <hi rendition="#i">Beagle&#x2019;s</hi> posi-<lb break="no"/>tion of Callao be proved incorrect, then must Humboldt&#x2019;s (calcu-<lb break="no"/>lated by Oltmanns) be also incorrect.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It will probably be agreeable to you, sir, to be acquainted with<lb break="yes" />the results of some new researches on this point. My longitude<lb break="yes" />of Callao rests, as you know, on the passage of Mercury of the<lb break="yes" />9th November, 1802. The interior contact, the surer of the<lb break="yes" />two, gave 5h. 18m. 18s.; the mean of the two contacts 5h. 18m. 16s.,<lb break="yes"/>reckoning always from the meridian of Paris. M. Oltmanns has<lb break="yes"/>compared my observation with others made at Greenwich, Paris,<lb break="yes"/>Sieberg, Lilienthal, Berlin, Cette, and Copenhagen (Humboldt,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Rec. d&#x2019;Obs. Astr.,</hi> vol. ii. p. 421-427). A long series of lunar<lb break="yes"/>distances taken in the voyage of Captain Duperrey gives<lb break="yes"/>5h. 18m. 16&#x00B7;3s.; Lartigue finds, by distances and chronometric<lb break="yes"/>measurements from Quilca, 5h. 18m. 0&#x00B7;7s. (Givry, <hi rendition="#i">Conn. des<lb break="yes"/>Tems,</hi> 1827, p. 258); and Captain Fitz Roy decides upon<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="503" facs="#f0002"/> 5h. 18m. 16s. (<hi rendition="#i">App.,</hi> p. 349), resting upon the longitude of Val-<lb break="no"/>paraiso. Now, in the expedition of the <hi rendition="#i">Beagle,</hi> 4h. 56m. 7s. is<lb break="yes" />adopted as the longitude of Valparaiso, and for the difference of<lb break="yes"/>longitudes between Valparaiso and Callao, 0h. 22m. 9s. Now,<lb break="yes"/>5h. 18m. 16s. is precisely the longitude which the <hi rendition="#i">two</hi> contacts<lb break="yes"/>gave me, and 2 seconds of time less than that by the exterior con-<lb break="no"/>tact of the passage of Mercury in 1802.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The passage of Mercury over the disk of the sun in 1832 hav-<lb break="no"/>ing been observed by M. Scholtz at Lima, and at Breslaw by M.<lb break="yes" />Boguslawski, I requested M. Galle, assistant astronomer at the<lb break="yes" />Royal Observatory at Berlin, to calculate the passage.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. Galle found, for the longitude of Lima,</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>h.</cell>
                        <cell>m.</cell>
                        <cell>s.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>41&#x00B7;4</cell>
                        <cell>by the interior contact,</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>48&#x00B7;5</cell>
                        <cell>by the exterior contact,</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>mean, 5h. 17m. 45s. Now, I found Lima to the east of Callao<lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">Rec. d&#x2019;Obs. Astr.,</hi> tome ii. p. 428), by chronometer,&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>s.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1802, Nov. 9 ...</cell>
                        <cell>28&#x00B7;6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>&#x201E; Dec. 14 ...</cell>
                        <cell>31&#x00B7;2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>&#x201E; &#x201E; 17 ...</cell>
                        <cell>27&#x00B7;8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>&#x201E; &#x201E; 27 ...</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rendition="#u">27&#x00B7;2</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>28&#x00B7;7</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>whence it results that, by the transit of Mercury in 1832, the<lb break="yes" />longitude of Callao is, according to M. Galle, 5h. 18m. 13&#x00B7;7s.,<lb break="yes"/>while the passage of 1802 gives 5h. 18m. 18s., and Captain Fitz<lb break="yes"/>Roy decides upon 5h. 18m. 16s. The accuracy of the determi-<lb break="no"/>nation of the longitude of Callao seems thus, for the last 30 years,<lb break="yes"/>to have been circumscribed within sufficiently narrow limits.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As absolute astronomical observations ought to claim attention in<lb break="yes" />preference to relative and chronometric observations, allow me to<lb break="yes"/>dwell for a moment on the position of Valparaiso. The occulta-<lb break="no"/>tion of the star, 644 of the Scorpion, was observed on the 28th of<lb break="yes"/>October, 1821, with much accuracy, by Captain Basil Hall. Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Foster, an observer and calculator generally very exact, acci-<lb break="no"/>dentally made a mistake in the calculation of this occultation,<lb break="yes"/>which gives, not 4h. 55m. 15s., as Mr. Foster thought, but<lb break="yes"/>4h. 56m. 16&#x00B7;6s., for the fort of San Antonio at Valparaiso. M.<lb break="yes"/>Oltmanns, according to Bode (<hi rendition="#i">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Astronomische</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">Astronomisches</corr>
                        </choice> Lehrbuch für</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>1829, p. 197), in a memoir already written in September, 1826,<lb break="yes"/>pointed out the mistake in the calculation by the comparison<lb break="yes"/>of the elements. Now, the occultation of Antares<note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn1-1" next="#fn1-2">This occultation of Antares is also an observation of Captain Basil Hall. The<lb break="yes"/>observation is good, but the calculation made of it at first was wrong, as is proved</note> gives<lb break="yes"/>4h. 56m. 42s.: we have, therefore, by the mean of two occulta-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="504" facs="#f0003"/> tions 4h. 56m. 29s. = 74° 7&#x2032; 15&#x2033;; but, as lunar distances and the<lb break="yes"/>satellites give 74° and 73° 59&#x2032;, M. Oltmanns, in a MS. memoir<lb break="yes"/>which he communicated to me shortly before his death, as-<lb break="no"/>sumes as longitude of Fort San Antonio at Valparaiso, 74° 2&#x2032; =<lb break="yes"/>4h. 56m. 8s., which only differs a second in time from the result<lb break="yes"/>obtained in the memorable expedition under Captains King and<lb break="yes"/>Fitz Roy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Captain Beechey has published (<hi rendition="#i">Naut. Mag.,</hi> April, 1838)<lb break="yes"/>an important result obtained by the moon&#x2019;s passage over the<lb break="yes"/>meridian. Fourteen days&#x2019; observations, compared with Cambridge,<lb break="yes"/>Paris, Edinburgh, and the Cape of Good Hope, differ only 27 se-<lb break="no"/>conds in time, and the whole of these transits gives 4h. 55m. 59&#x00B7;1s.:<lb break="yes"/>120 lunar distances give Captain Beechey 4h. 55m. 53&#x00B7;4s.; mean<lb break="yes"/>4h. 55m. 56&#x00B7;2s., only 12 seconds of time less than the whole of<lb break="yes" />the occultations, satellites, and lunar distances had given to my<lb break="yes"/>friend and colleague, Oltmanns. If we take the mean of the<lb break="yes"/>first-class observations only, for Callao of the two passages of<lb break="yes"/>Mercury over the sun&#x2019;s disk, for Valparaiso of the two occulta-<lb break="no"/>tions calculated by M. Oltmanns, and of the lunar transits of<lb break="yes"/>Captain Beechey, we have&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>h.</cell>
                        <cell>m.</cell>
                        <cell>s.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Callao ...</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>15&#x00B7;8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Valparaiso ..</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>56</cell>
                        <cell>12&#x00B7;4 <note place="foot" n="*">To remind us how useful it is to submit old observations to rigorous calcula-<lb break="no"/>tions, I will cite the eclipse of the sun of the 11th of March, 1709, observed by<lb break="yes"/>Feuillée. This eclipse gave Triesnecker 4h. 56m. 29&#x00B7;4s.; Mechain, 4h. 56m. 33s.;<lb break="yes" />Oltmanns, 4h. 56m. 41s. (Paris). I acknowledge that the longitude which results<lb break="yes"/>from the transits by Captain Beechey, generally so worthy of confidence, appeared<lb break="yes"/>to me to give a longitude rather too much to the east; for we have now definitively<lb break="yes"/>for Valparaiso, &#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>
                                <table>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>h.</cell>
                                        <cell>m.</cell>
                                        <cell>s.</cell>
                                        <cell/>
                                    </row>
                                    <lb break="yes"/>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>4</cell>
                                        <cell>56</cell>
                                        <cell>41</cell>
                                        <cell>Feuillée and Oltmanns.</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <lb break="yes"/>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>4</cell>
                                        <cell>56</cell>
                                        <cell>7</cell>
                                        <cell>Fitz Roy.</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <lb break="yes"/>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>4</cell>
                                        <cell>56</cell>
                                        <cell>29</cell>
                                        <cell>Occultation of Basil Hall.</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <lb break="yes"/>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>4</cell>
                                        <cell>55</cell>
                                        <cell>56</cell>
                                        <cell>Beechey.</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <lb break="yes"/>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell cols="4">Oltmanns preferred 4h. 56m. 8s.</cell>
                                    </row>
                                </table>
                            </note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell cols="3">
                            <milestone rendition="#hr" unit="section"/>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Difference of longitude</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>3&#x00B7;4</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>which agrees very well with the four chronometric trials of &#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>°</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2032;</cell>
                        <cell>&#x2033;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Malespina ..</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Captain B. Hall .</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>47</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Lartigue ...</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Fitz Roy ...</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell cols="3">
                            <milestone rendition="#hr" unit="section"/>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>1&#x00B7;4</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Perhaps it would be prudent to exclude the result by Malespina<lb break="yes"/>as differing the most.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1">by the comparison of the elements of calculation given by <hi rendition="#i">Bode, Astr. Jahrb. für<choice>
                                <sic>,</sic>
                                <corr type="editorial"/>
                            </choice>
                        </hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>1828, p. 182. The result is not 71° 30&#x2032; 50&#x00B7;5&#x2033;, but 71° 51&#x2032; 25&#x2033; west of Greenwich.</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="505" facs="#f0004"/>
                <p>As astronomical tables are gradually corrected, it becomes ne-<lb break="no" />cessary to revise former calculations.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>I found Cumana by an eclipse of the sun</cell>
                        <cell>4h.</cell>
                        <cell>25m.</cell>
                        <cell>51s.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>By chronometers</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>By the satellites</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell cols="3">
                            <milestone rendition="#hr" unit="section"/>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>0&#x00B7;4</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x2014;(<hi rendition="#i">Rec. d&#x2019;Obs. Astr.,</hi> tome i. p. 86).</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On the 7th of November, 1799, I had a good observation<lb break="yes"/>of the Imm. II. Satellite, with a very clear sky. This observation,<lb break="yes" />published by Baron von Zach during my journey on the Orinoco,<lb break="yes" />gives, by the tables of Delambre, 4h. 25m. 32s.; a corresponding<lb break="yes"/>observation at Marseilles makes Cumana in 4h. 26m. 21s. This<lb break="yes"/>observation of the II. Satellite has just been calculated with the ex-<lb break="no"/>cellent tables of Damoiseau, by M. Wolfers, a very exact and prac-<lb break="no"/>tised calculator. It gives 4h. 26m. 3&#x00B7;9s., which, as a single observa-<lb break="no"/>tion, only differs 4 seconds from the general mean. At this moment<lb break="yes"/>there are so few persons who occupy themselves perseveringly, and<lb break="yes"/>with the accuracy that the present state of science admits of, with<lb break="yes"/>astronomical geography, especially for points situated out of<lb break="yes"/>Europe, that you will oblige us much if from time to time you<lb break="yes"/>would transmit to me observations for occultations, eclipses of the<lb break="yes"/>sun, and of moon-culminating stars, as I have the means here of<lb break="yes"/>submitting them to a rigorous calculation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The volume of Mr. Charles Darwin is an admirable supple-<lb break="no"/>ment to the voyage of the <hi rendition="#i">Beagle:</hi> it is one of the most remark-<lb break="no"/>able works that, in the course of a long life, I have had the pleasure<lb break="yes"/>to see published. Mr. Darwin unites to sagacity for detailed<lb break="yes"/>observations enlarged views in general physics, I should rather<lb break="yes"/>say in natural philosophy,&#x2014;views which embrace at once geology,<lb break="yes"/>the geographical distribution of plants, and the influence of tem-<lb break="no"/>perature on the organic types of the primitive world.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is also fortunate that this great expedition to the southern<lb break="yes" />regions of America should have induced your able geographer,<lb break="yes" />Mr. John Arrowsmith, to compile his beautiful map of the whole<lb break="yes" />of the continent of South America.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I offer up the most ardent wishes for the success of the magnetic<lb break="yes" />expedition under Captain James Ross, and for the establishment<lb break="yes" />of the stations which we owe to the munificence of the British<lb break="yes" />government: if it is true that the letter I addressed to H. R. H.<lb break="yes"/>the Duke of Sussex and to the Royal Society has contributed to<lb break="yes"/>these undertakings so useful to science, I should congratulate<lb break="yes"/>myself on having had the courage to plead so excellent a cause.<lb break="yes"/>I hope that Captain Ross has on board the necessary apparatus<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="506" facs="#f0005"/> for observing magnetic dip at sea, as M. Adolph Erman<note place="foot" n="*">M. Erman has described his apparatus in <hi rendition="#i">Schumacher&#x2019;s Astr. Nach.,</hi> 1839,<lb break="yes"/>p. 364.</note> and<lb break="yes"/>myself have done. As a stratum of water of immense thickness<lb break="yes"/>covers the surface of the globe, these observations, being less<lb break="yes"/>affected by local perturbations, are of great importance even when<lb break="yes"/>they may be made with less precision.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We shall also learn if the showers of shooting-stars from the<lb break="yes" />10th to the 12th of August, and from the 12th to the 13th of No-<lb break="no" />vember, are visible far towards the South Pole.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>During the last six or eight months I have been daily occupied<lb break="yes" />with the directions of the chains of mountains in Central Asia,<lb break="yes" />and with a new edition of the two volumes of <hi rendition="#i">Fragmens de Géo-<lb break="no"/>logie et de Climatologie Asiatiques,</hi> which I published after my<lb break="yes"/>return from Siberia. There still remains much doubt as to the<lb break="yes"/>position and names of the lakes which in the plateau of Pamer are<lb break="yes"/>the sources of the Oxus; I know nothing more of the discovery<lb break="yes"/>of the Sini-gúl and &#x201C;Lake Victoria&#x201D; of Lieutenant Wood, except<lb break="yes"/>the few lines contained in the &#x2018;Bombay Gazette&#x2019; and the &#x2018;Asiatic<lb break="yes"/>Journal&#x2019; for November, 1838.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Has the Geographical Society nothing more precise on the<lb break="yes" />topography of Pamer, than some astronomical observations of<lb break="yes" />Lieutenant Wood, companion of the courageous Sir Alexander<lb break="yes" />Burnes? This lake, at 15,600 feet above the sea, is of the more<lb break="yes" />importance to me, as, thanks to the kindness of M. Stanislas<lb break="yes" />Julien, professor of Chinese literature at the College de France<lb break="yes"/>at Paris, I shall publish a very curious notice on the plateau of<lb break="yes"/>Pamer, extracted from the unpublished travels of Hiouenthsong,<lb break="yes"/>a Buddhist traveller of the 7th century.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rendition="#et">
                            <hi rendition="#k">
                                <hi rendition="#g">Alexander Humboldt.</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 