<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>

<pb n="64" facs="#f0001" />

    <div n="1">
        <head>
            A WORD BETWEEN SCIENCE AND POETRY: MEMNON<lb/>UNMEMNONED.
        </head>
        <p>The granitic rock on which we lay is one of those<lb/>where travellers on the Orinoco have heard from time to<lb/>time, towards sunrise, subterraneous sounds, resembling<lb/>those of the organ. The missionaries call these stones <hi rendition="#i">laxas<lb/>de musica.</hi> &#x2018;It is witchcraft&#x2019; (cosa de bruxas, said our<lb/>young Indian pilot, who could speak Spanish). We never<lb/>heard ourselves these mysterious sounds, either at Cori-<lb/>chana Viega or in the Upper Orinoco; but, from information<lb/>given us by witnesses worthy of belief, the existence of a<lb/>phenomenon that seems to depend on a certain state of the<lb/>atmosphere cannot be denied. The shelves of rock are<lb/>full of very narrow and deep crevices. They are heated<lb/>during the day to 48° or 50°. I several times found their<lb/>temperature at the surface, during the night, at 39°, the<lb/>surrounding atmosphere being at 28°. It may easily be<lb/>conceived that the difference of temperature between the<lb/>subterranean and the external air attains its maximum<lb/>about sunrise, or at that moment which is at the same time<lb/>farthest from the period of the maximum of the heat of the<lb/>preceding day. May not these organ-like sounds, which<lb/>are heard when a person lays his ear in contact with the<lb/>stone, be the effect of a current of air that issues out<lb/>through the crevices? Does not the impulse of the air<lb/>against the elastic spangles of mica that intercept the<lb/>crevices, contribute to modify the sounds? May we not<lb/>admit that the ancient inhabitants of Egypt, in passing in-<lb/>cessantly up and down the Nile, had made the same obser-<lb/>vation on some rock of the Thebaid; and that the &#x2018;music<lb/>of the rocks&#x2019; there led to the jugglery of the priests in the<lb/>statue of Memnon? Perhaps, when &#x2018;the rosy-fingered<lb/>Aurora rendered her son, the glorious Memnon, vocal,&#x2019; the<lb/>voice was that of a man hidden beneath the pedestal of the<lb/>statue; but the observation of the natives of the Orinoco,<lb/>which we relate, seems to explain in a natural manner<lb/>what gave rise to the Egyptian belief of a stone that<lb/>poured forth sounds at sunrise. &#x2014; <hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
