<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="326" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#i">An Attempt to determine the mean height of Continents</hi>.
                    By<lb/>Baron Von <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi>.</head>
                <lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">At</hi> the meeting of the Berlin Academy of Sciences, on
                    18th<lb/>July 1842, a memoir by M. de Humboldt was read, of which<lb/>we think
                    it necessary to give a somewhat lengthened account.<lb/>It is entitled
                    &#x201C;An attempt at determining the mean height<lb/>of Continents.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>&#x201C;Among the numerical elements on which the progress of<lb/>physical
                    geography appears more particularly to depend, there<lb/>is one which no attempt
                    has been hitherto made to determine.<lb/>The notion which seemed to prevail,
                    that it was impossible<lb/>to come to such a determination, has perhaps been the
                    prin-<lb/>cipal cause of the subject being neglected. However, the
                    ex-<lb/>tension of our orographical knowledge, as well as the great-<lb/>er
                    accuracy of the maps which represent large portions of<lb/>country, determined
                    me, says M. de Humboldt, to undertake,<lb/>some years ago, a work of great
                    labour, and in appearance<lb/>barren in results, the object of which is the
                    knowledge of the<lb/>mean height of continents, and the determination of the
                    mean<lb/>height of the <hi rendition="#i">centre of gravity of their
                        volume</hi>. In such a case<lb/>as this, as with many others, such as the
                    dimensions of the<lb/>globe, the probable distance of the fixed stars, the mean
                    tem-<lb/>perature of the poles of the earth, the thickness of the
                    atmo-<lb/>spheric stratum above the level of the sea, or the enumeration<lb/>of
                    the general population of the globe, we arrive at <hi rendition="#i"
                        >limited<lb/>numbers,</hi> between which the results must fall. In like
                    man-<lb/>ner, it is by the perfect knowledge of the geometrical
                    and<lb/>hypsometrical surface of a country, of France, for example,<lb/>that we
                    may thus be led, by analogy, to extend the conclu-<lb/>sions to a great part of
                    Europe and America, and are en-<lb/>abled to establish numerical data, which
                    have recently been<lb/>completed in a very satisfactory manner in regard to
                    central<lb/>and western Asia.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>&#x201C;It was likewise necessary to collect, with the greatest
                    care,<lb/>astronomical determinations of the height of places, in order<lb/>to
                    establish, to about 300 or 400 metres of absolute height,<lb/>the limits between
                    the acclivities of the mountains and the<lb/>edges of the valleys. I long since
                    demonstrated the possibi-<lb/><pb n="327" facs="#f0002"/> lity of such a
                    determination of limits, and, from the comparison<lb/>which depends on it, I
                    have deduced the extent of the surface<lb/>of the plains, and the horizontal and
                    flat portions of moun-<lb/>tains, in my geognostical researches on South
                    America; a por-<lb/>tion of the globe in regard to which the length of the
                    im-<lb/>mense wall which forms the Cordillera of the Andes, and of<lb/>the
                    elevated masses of Parima and Brazil, was so incorrectly<lb/>limited and
                    circumscribed on all maps. In fact, there is a<lb/>general tendency in all
                    graphic representations to give the<lb/>mountains a greater degree of breadth
                    than they really pos-<lb/>sess, and even in the flat portions to confound
                    plateaux of va-<lb/>rious kinds with each other.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>M. de Humboldt published, in 1825, two memoirs inserted<lb/>in the Memoires dé
                    l&#x2019;Académie des Sciences of Paris, on the<lb/>mean height of continents,
                    and an estimate of the volume<lb/>of the elevated ridges of mountains, compared
                    with the<lb/>extent of the surface of the lower regions. An assertion
                    of<lb/>Laplace in the <hi rendition="#i">Mécanique Céleste</hi> (vol. v., book
                    xi. chap. i.<lb/>page 13), gave rise to these researches. This great
                    geo-<lb/>meter had established in principle, that the agreement ob-<lb/>served
                    between the results of experiments made with the pen-<lb/>dulum and the
                    compression of the earth, deduced as well<lb/>from the trigonometrical
                    measurement of the degrees of the<lb/>meridian as from the inequality of the
                    moon, furnished a<lb/>proof &#x201C;that the surface of the terrestrial spheroid
                    would<lb/>be nearly that of equilibrium, if that surface became
                    fluid.<lb/>Hence, and from the consideration that the sea leaves
                    vast<lb/>continents uncovered, we conclude that it cannot be of great<lb/>depth,
                    and that its mean depth is of the same order as the<lb/>mean height of the
                    continents and islands above its level,<lb/>a height which does not exceed 1000
                    metres&#x201D; (or 3073<lb/>Parisian feet, that is to say, only 463 feet less
                    than the sum-<lb/>mit of the Brocken, according to M. Gauss, or a little
                    more<lb/>than the most elevated mountains of Thuringia). Laplace<lb/>further
                    adds, &#x201C;This height is, then, a small fraction of the<lb/>excess of the
                    radius of the equator over that of the pole, an<lb/>excess which exceeds 20,000
                    mètres. Just as high moun-<lb/>tains cover some parts of continents, so there
                    may be great<lb/>cavities in the bed of the sea; but it is natural to
                        suppose<lb/><pb n="328" facs="#f0003"/> that their depth is less than the
                    elevation of high mountains,<lb/>as the deposits from the waves, and the remains
                    of marine<lb/>animals, must have tended, in the lapse of time, to fill up
                    these<lb/>great cavities.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Considering the profound and extensive knowledge which<lb/>the author of the <hi
                        rendition="#i">Mécanique Céleste</hi> possessed in the highest<lb/>degree,
                    an assertion of this nature was the more striking, as<lb/>he could not be
                    ignorant that the most elevated plateau of<lb/>France, that from which the
                    extinct volcanoes of Auvergne<lb/>have risen, does not rise, according to
                    Ramond, to more than<lb/>1044 feet, and that the great Iberian plateau is not,
                    according<lb/>to my own measurements, more than 2100 feet above the level<lb/>of
                    the sea. Laplace has therefore fixed the upper limit at<lb/>1000 metres, merely
                    because he has considered the extent and<lb/>the mass of the elevations of
                    mountains to be much greater than<lb/>they really are, inasmuch as he has
                    confounded the height of<lb/>the insulated peaks or culminating points with the
                    mean height<lb/>of the mountain ridges; he has admitted much too low
                    a<lb/>number for the depth of seas, because, in his time, data could<lb/>not be
                    found on the subject, and he has thence inferred the<lb/>proportion of the
                    extent of the surface (in square miles) in re-<lb/>gard to all continents, to
                    the extent of the projection of the<lb/>surfaces covered by mountains.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>A very exact calculation has shewn that the mass of the<lb/>chain of the Andes,
                    in South America, from where it leaves the<lb/>whole portion of the eastern
                    plains of the pampas and forests,<lb/>regions whose surface is one-third larger
                    than that of Europe,<lb/>does not rise above 486 feet. M. de Humboldt hence
                    con-<lb/>cludes, &#x201C;That the mean height of continental lands
                    depends<lb/>much less on those chains or longitudinal ridges of
                    little<lb/>breadth which traverse continents, and on their
                    culminating<lb/>points or domes, which attract common observation, than
                    on<lb/>the general configuration of the different orders of plateaux
                    and<lb/>their ascending series, and on those gently undulating plains<lb/>with
                    alternating slopes, which have an influence, by their mass<lb/>and extent, on
                    the position of a mean surface, that is to say, on<lb/>the height of a plain
                    placed in such a manner that the sum of<lb/>its positive ordinates shall be
                    equal to the sum of its negative<lb/>ordinates.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb/>
                <pb n="329" facs="#f0004"/>
                <p>The comparison which Laplace has instituted in the pas-<lb/>sage quoted from the
                        <hi rendition="#i">Mécanique Céleste</hi> between the depth of<lb/>the sea
                    and the height of continents, recalls a passage of Plu-<lb/>tarch, in the 15th
                    chapter of his Life of &#x00C6;milius Paulus (ed.<lb/>Reiskii, vol. ii. page
                    276),&#x2014;a passage the more remarkable, as<lb/>it makes us acquainted with
                    an opinion which generally pre-<lb/>vailed among the philosophers of the
                    Alexandrian school.<lb/>After quoting an inscription found on Mount Olympus,
                    and<lb/>giving the result of the measurement of its height by Xenago-<lb/>ras,
                    Plutarch adds, &#x201C;But geometricians (probably those of<lb/>Alexandria)
                    believe that <hi rendition="#i">there is no mountain higher, and no<lb/>sea
                        deeper, than ten stadia</hi>.&#x201D; We can entertain no doubt
                    about<lb/>the exactness of the measurement made by Xenagoras; but it<lb/>is
                    striking to observe, that the philosophers of this school esta-<lb/>blished in
                    the structure of the earth a perfect equality be-<lb/>tween the heights or
                    positive and negative ordinates. Here<lb/>the maximum of the heights and depths
                    is alone taken into<lb/>account, and not the mean height,&#x2014;a consideration
                    which<lb/>rarely presented itself to the mind of the ancient
                    philosophers,<lb/>and which, for variable magnitudes, was applied in a
                    useful<lb/>manner to astronomy by the Arabs. Even in the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Metereologius</hi><lb/>of Cleomedes (i. 10), we meet with an assertion
                    similar to that<lb/>of Plutarch; while in the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Meteorologicis</hi> of the philosopher of<lb/>Stagira (Arist. Met. ii. 2),
                    the only point considered is the in-<lb/>fluence of the inclination of the
                    bottom of the sea, from east<lb/>to west, on its currents.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>When we try to determine the mean height of the elevation<lb/>of continents above
                    the present level of the seas, it means<lb/>that the object is to find the
                    centre of gravity of the volume<lb/>of these continents above that
                    level,&#x2014;an investigation very dif-<lb/>ferent from that which consists in
                    searching for the centre of<lb/>gravity of the volume of the continental mass,
                    or the centre of<lb/>gravity of the masses, seeing that the portion which rises
                    above<lb/>the sea, in the crust of the globe, is by no means of the
                    same<lb/>density, as has been demonstrated both by geognosy and
                    ex-<lb/>periments with the pendulum. The mode of simple calculation<lb/>is as
                    follows:&#x2014;Each chain of mountains is considered as a tri-<lb/>angular
                    prism placed horizontally. The mean height of the<lb/>defiles or passes, which
                    determine the mean height of the crest<lb/><pb n="330" facs="#f0005"/> of the
                    mountains, is the height of the ridge of the prism ver-<lb/>tically above the
                    surface, which constitutes the base of the<lb/>chain. The plateaux are
                    calculated as straight prisms, in or-<lb/>der to establish their solidity.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>For the purpose of giving an example, taken from Europe,<lb/>of this kind of
                    calculation, M. de Humboldt states, that the<lb/>surface of France contains
                    10,087 square geographical miles.<lb/>According to M. Charpentier, the Pyrenees
                    cover 430 of these<lb/>square miles; and, although the mean height of the
                    summits<lb/>of the Pyrenees rises to 7500 feet, M. de Humboldt makes
                    a<lb/>reduction upon it, on account of the erosions produced on the<lb/>prism
                    supposed to be lying horizontally, and which have tended<lb/>specially to
                    diminish the size of the deep transverse valleys.<lb/>The effect of the Pyrenees
                    on the whole of France is not more<lb/>than 35 metres or 108 feet; that is to
                    say, it is to that extent<lb/>that the normal surface of the entire plain of
                    France would be<lb/>increased, and the elevation of that surface by the
                    comparison<lb/>of a great number of very accurate measurements at
                    places<lb/>towards the centre (such as Bourges, Chartres, Nevers,
                    Tours,<lb/>&amp;c.) has been found to be 480 feet. This calculation,
                    which<lb/>M. de Humboldt has made along with M. Elie de Beaumont,<lb/>furnishes
                    the following general result, in measures thus given<lb/>by the
                    author:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell></cell>
                        <cell>Toises.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1. Effect of the Pyrenees,</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2. The French Alps, the Jura, and the Vosges, a few<lb/>toises more than
                            the Pyrenees; common effect,</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>3. The plateaux of Limousin, Auvergne, the Cevennes,<lb/>Aveyron, Forez,
                            Morvant, Cote d&#x2019;Or; common ef-<lb/>fect, nearly equal to that of the
                            Pyrenees,</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Now, as the normal height of the plain of France is at<lb/>its maximum
                            about</cell>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>It follows that the mean height of France does not ex-<lb/>ceed</cell>
                        <cell>136 toises,<lb/>or 816 feet.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb/>
                </table>
                <lb/>
                <p>The Baltic, Sarmatian, and Russian plains are separated<lb/>from those of the
                    north of Asia only by the meridian chain<lb/>of the Oural. It is for this reason
                    that Herodotus, who was<lb/>acquainted with the connection of the southern
                    extremity of<lb/><pb n="331" facs="#f0006"/> the Oural in the country of the
                    Issidones, called the whole of<lb/>Europe to the north of the Altai Mountains,
                    Asia. In the<lb/>neighbouring region of the Baltic plains, near the shores
                    of<lb/>the Baltic Sea, there are partial elevated masses which
                    deserve<lb/>particular attention. To the west of Dantzic, between that<lb/>town
                    and Butow, at the point where the shore of the sea ad-<lb/>vances much to the
                    north, there are many villages situated at a<lb/>height of 400 feet; the
                    Thurmberg, moreover, the measure-<lb/>ment of which has given rise to many
                    hypsometrical contro-<lb/>versies, rises, according to the trigonometrical
                    observations<lb/>of Major Baeyer, to 1024 feet, which is perhaps the
                    greatest<lb/>elevation to be found between the Harz and Oural. It is
                    sur-<lb/>prising that, according to the measurements made by M.<lb/>Struve of
                    the culminating point of Livonia, the Munamaggi,<lb/>this mountain rises only 4
                    toises higher than the Thurmberg<lb/>of Pomerania; while, on the other hand,
                    according to Captain<lb/>Albrecht&#x2019;s chart, the greatest depth of the
                    Baltic Sea, between<lb/>Gothland and Windau, is not more than 167 toises, a
                    mea-<lb/>surement almost identical with that of the Thurmberg.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The flat countries exclusively European, the normal height<lb/>of which cannot be
                    estimated at more than 60 toises, occupy,<lb/>according to exact measurements, a
                    surface nine times that<lb/>of France. The extraordinary extent of this low
                    region is<lb/>the cause of the mean continental height of all Europe,
                    over<lb/>an extent of 17,000 square geographical miles, being 30
                    toises<lb/>below the result we have found for France. As to the rest,<lb/>not to
                    occupy more time with numbers, M. de Humboldt adds,<lb/>that an important
                    consideration in the study of the general<lb/>phenomena of geology is, that the
                    elevated masses, over ex-<lb/>tensive countries, in the form of plateaux,
                    produce an entirely<lb/>different effect on the elevation of the centre of
                    gravity of<lb/>the volume from that of chains of mountains, when they
                    have<lb/>the same importance in breadth and in height. While the<lb/>Pyrenees
                    produce scarcely the effect of a single toise on the<lb/>whole of Europe, the
                    system of the Alps, which cover a<lb/>surface almost quadruple that of the
                    Pyrenees, has the effect<lb/>of 3<formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{2}</formula> toises; the Iberian peninsula, with
                    its compact massive<lb/>plateau of 300 toises, produces the effect of 12 toises.
                    The<lb/>plateau just named, therefore, has an effect on the whole of<lb/><pb
                        n="332" facs="#f0007"/> Europe four times more considerable than the system
                    of the<lb/>Alps. This result of calculations is the more satisfactory<lb/>as it
                    appears to be deduced without reference to any pre-<lb/>vious hypothesis.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>We have recently acquired many new ideas respecting the<lb/>configuration of
                    Asia. The effect of the elevated colossal<lb/>masses of the southern portion is
                    found to be weakened, since<lb/>one-third of the whole continent of Asia, a
                    portion of Siberia,<lb/>which alone exceeds by a third the entire surface of
                    Europe, does<lb/>not reach a normal height of 40 toises. This is,
                    likewise,<lb/>the height of Orenbourg, on the northern shore of the
                    Cas-<lb/>pian Sea. Tobolsk does not attain the half of this height,<lb/>and
                    Casan, which is five times more distant from the shore of<lb/>the Icy Sea than
                    Berlin is from the Baltic, is scarcely half<lb/>the height of the last mentioned
                    city. In Upper Irtysch, be-<lb/>tween Buktormensy and Lake Saysan, at a point
                    nearer the<lb/>Indian than the Icy Ocean, M. de Humboldt has found that<lb/>the
                    plains only reached a height of about 800 feet; this, how-<lb/>ever, has been
                    called the plateau of Central Asia, and is not<lb/>half the height of the
                    streets of the city of Munich above the<lb/>sea-level. The celebrated plateau
                    between Lake Baikal and<lb/>the Wall of China (the stony desert of Gobi and
                    Cha-mo),<lb/>which the Russian academicians, MM. Bunge and Fuss,
                    have<lb/>measured with the barometer, has a mean height of only 660<lb/>toises,
                    which is nearly the same as that of the Müggelsberg at<lb/>the summit of the
                    Brocken. There is, moreover, in the centre<lb/>of this plateau, at the point
                    where Ergi is situated (lat. 45°31&#x2032;)<lb/>a cauldron-shaped depression,
                    the bottom of which descends<lb/>to 400 toises, that is to say, the height of
                    Madrid. &#x201C;This de-<lb/>pression,&#x201D; says M. Bunge, in a memoir not
                    yet published,<lb/>&#x201C;is covered with Halophytes and species of the genus
                        <hi rendition="#i">Arundo</hi>,<lb/>and, according to the tradition of the
                    Mongolians who ac-<lb/>companied us, it was formerly a great inland sea.&#x201D;
                    The<lb/>two extremities of this ancient inland sea are bounded by<lb/>steep
                    rocks, just like an ordinary sea, in the neighbourhood of<lb/>Olonbaischan and
                    Zukeldakan.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The surface of Gobi, in its masses of uniform elevation, and<lb/>from the
                    south-west to north-west, is twice as large as that<lb/>of all Germany, and will
                    raise the centre of gravity of Asia<lb/><pb n="333" facs="#f0008"/> 20 toises;
                    while the Himalaya and the Houen-lun, which is<lb/>a prolongation of the
                    Hindoo-Kho, with the plateaux of Thibet,<lb/>which connect the Himalaya with the
                    Kouen-lun, will only pro-<lb/>duce an effect of 56 toises. In the examination of
                    the consi-<lb/>derable relief between the plains of the Indus and the
                    de-<lb/>pressed plateau of Tarim, which, on leaving Kaschgar, in-<lb/>clines to
                    the east towards Lake Lop, it is necessary to exa-<lb/>mine with more care the
                    point near the meridian of Kaylasa,<lb/>and the two sacred lakes of Manasa and
                    Ravana-Brada, on<lb/>leaving which the Himalaya no longer runs from east to
                    west<lb/>parallel with the Kouen-lun, but takes the direction
                    from<lb/>south-east to north-west, and reunites at the projecting ridges
                    of<lb/>Tsun-ling. The altitudes of the numerous passes of Bamian,<lb/>as far as
                    the meridian of Tschamalari (24,400 feet), by which<lb/>Turner reached the
                    Thibetian plateau of H&#x2019;Lassa, are likewise<lb/>known for an extent of 21°
                    of longitude. The greater part<lb/>of them present a very uniform height of
                    14,000 English feet,<lb/>or 2200 toises, a height which is not of rare
                    occurrence in the<lb/>passes of the chain of the Andes. The great route which
                    M.<lb/>de Humboldt followed from Quito, on his way to Cuen&#x00E7;a,<lb/>was,
                    for example, at Assuay (Ladera de Cadlud), and without<lb/>snow, of the height
                    of 2428 toises, that is to say, 1400 feet<lb/>higher than this pass of the
                    Himalaya. The passes, as has<lb/>been stated, give the mean height of
                    mountains.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In a memoir on the relations between elevated summits or<lb/>culminating points,
                    and the height of mountain chains, M.<lb/>de Humboldt has demonstrated that the
                    chain of the Pyre-<lb/>nees, calculated from twenty-three passes, was 50 toises
                    high-<lb/>er than the mean chain of the Alps, although the
                    culminating<lb/>points of the Pyrenees and the Alps were in the proportion
                    of<lb/>1 to 1 <formula notation="TeX">\frac{4}{10}</formula>. As the insulated
                    passes of the Himalaya, for ex-<lb/>ample, the Niti-Gate, by which we penetrate
                    into the plain<lb/>of the Cashmere goats, rise to the height of 2629 toises,
                    M.<lb/>de Humboldt has not admitted for the height of the Himalayan<lb/>chain
                    14,000 English feet, but he proposes to fix it, although<lb/>perhaps the
                    elevation may be still too considerable, at 15,500<lb/>feet, or 2432 toises. The
                    plateau of the three Thibets of<lb/>Iscardo, Ladak, and H&#x2019;Lassa, is a
                    prominence between two<lb/>chains which unite with each other (the Himalaya and
                        the<lb/><pb n="334" facs="#f0009"/> Kouen-Lun). Mr Vigne&#x2019;s travels in
                    Baltistan, which have just<lb/>appeared, the journal of the brothers Gerard,
                    published by<lb/>Lloyd, as well as the recent investigations undertaken in
                    India<lb/>respecting the relative height of perpetual snow on the Indian<lb/>and
                    Thibetian declivities of the Himalaya, have demonstrated<lb/>that the mean
                    height of the Thibetian plateaux has hitherto<lb/>been greatly exaggerated. In
                    his work entitled &#x201C;Central<lb/>Asia,&#x201D; of which only a few pages of
                    the third volume have<lb/>been yet printed, and which will be accompanied by a
                    hypso-<lb/>metrical map of Asia from the Phasis, as far as the gulf
                    of<lb/>Petcheli, and from the common embouchures of the Ob and<lb/>the Irtysch
                    to the parallel of Delhi, M. de Humboldt thinks<lb/>that he has demonstrated, by
                    bringing together a multitude<lb/>of facts, that the prominence between the
                    Himalaya and the<lb/>Kouen-Lun (chains which form the southern and
                    northern<lb/>limits of Thibet), does not rise above the mean height of
                    1800<lb/>toises, and that it is, consequently, 200 toises lower than
                    the<lb/>plateau of Lake Titicaca.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The hypsometrical configuration of the Asiatic continent<lb/>is perhaps still
                    more remarkable for its plains and depres-<lb/>sions, than for its colossal
                    heights. This continent is distin-<lb/>guished by two principal characteristic
                    features; 1st, by the<lb/>long series of meridian chains, which, with parallel
                    axes,<lb/>but alternating with each other (having perhaps been pro-<lb/>jected
                        <hi rendition="#i">comme des filons</hi>) extend from Lake Comorin,
                    opposite<lb/>Ceylon, to the shores of the Icy Sea, in a uniform
                    direction<lb/>from south-south-east to north-north-west, under the name
                    of<lb/>Ghates, the Soliman chain, Paralasa, Bolor, and Oural.
                    This<lb/>alternating situation of auriferous meridian chains (Vigne
                    has<lb/>recently visited, on the eastern declivity of Bolos, in the
                    valley<lb/>of Basha, in Baltistan, the auriferous sands mined, according<lb/>to
                    the Thibetians, by marmots, and, according to Herodotus,<lb/>by large ants)
                    reveals to us this law, that none of the meridian<lb/>chains just named, between
                    64° and 75° of longitude, extend<lb/>themselves upon the adjoining ones, either
                    towards the east<lb/>or the west, and that each of these longitudinal elevations
                    does<lb/>not begin to shew its extent, until a point is reached where<lb/>the
                    preceding has completely disappeared. 2d, Another cha-<lb/>racteristic trait in
                    the configuration of Asia, and which has<lb/><pb n="335" facs="#f0010"/> not
                    been sufficiently observed, is the continuity of a consider-<lb/>able elevation,
                    east and west, between 35° and 36<formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{2}</formula>° of lati-<lb/>tude, from Takhialoudag,
                    in ancient Lycia, as far as the Chinese<lb/>province of Houpih, an elevation
                    thrice intersected by meridian<lb/>chains (Zagros, in Western Persia, Bolos, in
                    Affghanistan, and<lb/>the chain of Assam, in the valley of Dzangho) from the
                    west<lb/>to the east of this chain, from the parallel of Dicearchus,
                    which<lb/>is at the same time that of Rhodes, Taurus, Elbrouz, Hindou-<lb/>Kho,
                    and Kouen-Lun or A-Neoutha. In the third book of the<lb/>geography of
                    Eratosthenés, we find the first germ of the no-<lb/>tion of a chain of mountains
                    (Strabo, xv. p. 689, Cas.) run-<lb/>ning in a continuous manner, and dividing
                    Asia into two<lb/>parts. Dicearchus perceived the connection between
                    the<lb/>Taurus of Asia Minor and the snow-covered mountains of<lb/>Asia, which
                    had acquired so much celebrity among the Greeks<lb/>by the false accounts of
                    those who had accompanied the<lb/>Macedonians. Importance was assigned to the
                    parallel of<lb/>Rhodes, and to the direction of this endless chain of
                    moun-<lb/>tains. The chlamyde of Asia ought to be found further on
                    under<lb/>this parallel (Strabo, xi. p. 519), and perhaps, says Strabo,
                    a<lb/>little more to the east there may be another continent. The<lb/>Taurus and
                    the plateaux of Asia Minor disclosed for the first<lb/>time to the Greek
                    philosophers the influence of height on tem-<lb/>perature. &#x201C;Even in the
                    southern latitudes,&#x201D; says the great<lb/>geographer of Amasis, (Strabo,
                    ii. p. 73) when the climate of<lb/>the northern coasts of Cappadocia is compared
                    with that of the<lb/>plains of Argaios, situated 3000 stadia further south,
                    the<lb/>mountains and all the elevated lands are cold, even when<lb/>these lands
                    consist of plains.&#x201D; Strabo is the only one among<lb/>Greek authors who
                    has made use of the word
                    <hi rendition="#i">&#x03BF;&#x03C1;&#x03BF;&#x03C0;&#x03B5;&#x03B4;&#x03B9;&#x03B1;</hi> or<lb/>mountain
                    plain.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>According to the final result of the whole of M. de Hum-<lb/>boldt&#x2019;s
                    investigations, the maximum assigned by Laplace for<lb/>the mean height of
                    continents is too considerable by two-thirds.<lb/>He found the following
                    numerical elements for the three<lb/>quarters of the world which have been the
                    object of his cal-<lb/>culations (Africa not yet presenting a sufficient number
                    of<lb/>data to be included).</p>
                <lb/>
                <pb n="336" facs="#f0011"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Europe,</cell>
                        <cell>105 toises</cell>
                        <cell>(205 metres).</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>North America,</cell>
                        <cell>117 ...</cell>
                        <cell>(228 ...).</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>South America,</cell>
                        <cell>177 ...</cell>
                        <cell>(345 ...).</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Asia,</cell>
                        <cell>180 ...</cell>
                        <cell>(351 ...).</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb/>
                <p>For the whole of the new continent we have 146 toises<lb/>(285 metres), and for
                    the height of the centre of gravity of the<lb/>volume of all the continental
                    masses (Africa excepted) above<lb/>the level of the present seas, 157.8 toises
                    or 307 metres.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Von Hoff, who has measured with extreme accuracy 1076<lb/>different points, the
                    greater part of them in the mountainous<lb/>portion of Thuringia, over an extent
                    of 224 square geographical<lb/>miles, estimates that there are about five
                    heights for each<lb/>square mile, but that these heights are unequally
                    scattered.<lb/>M. de Humboldt has asked Von Hoff, always for the purpose<lb/>of
                    verifying Laplace&#x2019;s hypothesis respecting the mass of con-<lb/>tinents,
                    to calculate the mean height of the hypsometrical<lb/>measurements which he has
                    made. This philosopher has found<lb/>it to be 166 toises, that is to say, 8
                    toises more than the result<lb/>at which M. de Humboldt had arrived. We ought
                    thence to<lb/>conclude, that, since a very mountainous country of
                    Thuringia<lb/>was measured, the number, 157 toises, or 942 feet, is a
                    limit<lb/>rather too high than too low.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In the certainty in which we now are respecting the pro-<lb/>gressive and partial
                    rising of Sweden (one of the most im-<lb/>portant facts in physical geography,
                    for a knowledge of which<lb/>we are indebted to M. de Buch), we may suppose that
                    the<lb/>centre of gravity will not always continue the same. At the<lb/>same
                    time, considering the smallness of the masses which are<lb/>raised and the
                    weakness of the subterranean forces in action,<lb/>it may be presumed, regarding
                    such variations, that they will<lb/>in a great measure compensate each other,
                    and that the posi-<lb/>tion of the centre of gravity above the ocean will not be
                    much<lb/>changed; but a new circumstance, which appears to result<lb/>from the
                    numerical calculations of this hypsometrical labour,<lb/>is, that the smallest
                    heights in our hemisphere belong to the<lb/>continental masses of the north.
                    Thus Europe has furnished<lb/>105 toises, North America 117 toises. The
                    prominent cha-<lb/>racter of Asia between 28° and 40° of latitude
                    compensates<lb/>the subtractive effect of the lower portions of Siberia.
                        Asia<lb/><pb n="337" facs="#f0012"/> and South America give 180 and 177
                    toises. We thus read,<lb/>so to speak, in these numbers, in what portions of the
                    surface<lb/>of our globe vulcanism, that is to say, the reaction of
                    the<lb/>interior on the exterior, has been felt with greatest intensity<lb/>in
                    the ancient <hi rendition="#i">soulèvements</hi>. (<hi rendition="#i"
                        >L&#x2019;Institut</hi>,
                    <date>5th Jan. 1843 p. 4.</date>)</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>

    </text>
</TEI>
