<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<dateline>JANUARY&#x2014;APRIL, 1842.</dateline><lb/><pb n="380" facs="#f0001" />
<cb/>
    <p><hi rendition="#k">Colonial Society</hi>.&#x2014; At a special<lb/>meeting of the Colonial Society, con-<lb/>vened to congratulate that distinguished<lb/>philosopher, the Baron von Humboldt,<lb/><cb/>upon his arrival in England, and to elect<lb/>him an honorary member of the Society,<lb/>the following letter was drafted by Mr.<lb/>Montgomery Martin, and transmitted<lb/>by the Committee to the Baron.</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Colonial Society, Jan. 29.</hi></p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Sir,&#x2014;The committee of the Colonial So-<lb/>ciety, in conformity with a resolution unani-<lb/>mously adopted this day, beg leave to express<lb/>their gratification at your visit to this country<lb/>in the suite of your distinguished Sovereign.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Identified as the Colonial Society is with<lb/>the extension of civilization, and the develop-<lb/>ment of the internal resources of distant and<lb/>imperfectly known foreign regions, the Society<lb/>gladly avails itself of the present opportunity to<lb/>tender its respectful congratulations to a philo-<lb/>sopher, whose invaluable services in the cause<lb/>of geographical discovery and humanity, are<lb/>acknowledged and justly appreciated by all<lb/>civilized nations; for they have had for their<lb/>special object the welfare and advancement of<lb/>mankind.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Understanding that your sojourn in England<lb/>is necessarily brief, the Society is obliged to<lb/>refrain from tendering at present any other<lb/>mark of their sincere esteem than that of nam-<lb/>ing you an honorary member of their body;<lb/>and, in doing so, they would beg to offer their<lb/>heartfelt wishes for your continued health and<lb/>happiness.</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#c">&#x201C;By Order of the Committee,<lb/>&#x201C;JULIUS LE SOUEF, Secretary.</hi></p><lb/><p>&#x201C;The Baron von Humboldt,&#x201D; &#x0026;c.</p><lb/><p>Baron von Humboldt returned the<lb/>following answer:&#x2014;</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Windsor Castle, le 30me Janvier, 1842.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Monsieur,&#x2014;Dans la vie agitée que nous<lb/>menons pendant le trop court sejour de mon<lb/>Souverain en Angleterre, il ne me reste que le<lb/>regret de ne pas avoir un moment de libre pour<lb/>exprimer personellement au comité de l&#x2019;illustre<lb/>&#x2018;Colonial Society&#x2019; la vive reconnaissance dont<lb/>je me sens pénétré. Je vous supplie, Monsieur,<lb/>de vouloir bien &#x00EA;tre l&#x2019;interprete de mes senti-<lb/>mens respectueux. Rien ne pourrait etre plus<lb/>flatteur pour mol que l&#x2019;intéret que mes faibles<lb/>efforts ont pu inspirer à une réunion dont les<lb/>travaux tendent à un but si noble et si bien-<lb/>faisant pour l&#x2019;humanité.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Agréez, Monsieur, je vous supplie, l&#x2019;homage<lb/>de la haute <choice><sic>consi eration</sic><corr type="editorial">consideration</corr></choice> avec
                laquelle j&#x2019;al<lb/>l&#x2019;honneur d&#x2019;etre, Monsieur, votre très
                humble<lb/>et très obéissant serviteur,</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Le Baron von HUMBOLDT.</hi></p><lb/><p>&#x201C;M. Julius le Souef,&#x201D; &#x0026;c.</p><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
