<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front>
    
<body> <pb n="66" facs="#f0001"/> <div n="1"> <head>
    <hi rendition="#i">Deposit of Gold recently discovered in the Ural.</hi><note place="foot" n="*"> This article is an extract of a letter from M. de Kokcharoff, officer of the Royal Mining<lb/>Company, to M. de Humboldt.&#x2014;Translated from the <hi rendition="#i">Annales des Mines.</hi></note></head> <lb/> 
    <p>The mass of gold recently discovered in the Ural, is the largest<lb/>known in the whole world. It was found in the gold bearing sands<lb/>of Miask, in the district of Zlatooust, not far from the celebrated mines<lb/><pb n="67" facs="#f0002"/>of Tzarevo Nikol&#x00E6;fsk, and of Tzarevo Alexandrofsk, in the southern<lb/>Ural. These two mines, which you have visited with so much<lb/>interest, have already yielded, as you are aware, nearly 400 pouds of<lb/>gold (6552 kil.), equal to about 17,544.5 lbs.,&#x2014;and, more than once,<lb/>very remarkable masses have been collected there; thus, in 1825,<lb/>they found there the specimen weighing 24 phounds 68 zolotniks<lb/>(10 kilog. <choice> <sic>118</sic> <corr type="editorial">.118</corr> </choice>) about 27.017 lbs. These mines beginning<lb/>to be exhausted, they were compelled to make explorations near the<lb/>course of the river Tachkou-Targanka, which soon led to the dis-<lb/>covery of a bed of gold-bearing sands of very great richness, but<lb/>within very narrow limits. This bed once found, they turned off the<lb/>stream, wich had served for washing the sands, up the whole length<lb/>of this river, and commenced their examinations in the dry bed of the<lb/>stream. Their success was complete; they came at once upon a<lb/>stratum of gold-bearing sands, of considerable extent, where the yield<lb/>of gold was 100 pouds to 8 zolotniks, (a very great proportion, when<lb/>it is remembered that sands giving 100 pouds to 1&#x00BD; zolotniks have<lb/>been before considered well worth exploring;) then other beds were<lb/>discovered, of a yet greater capacity, which terminated in the exam-<lb/>ination of the whole valley of the Tachkou-Targanka, with the ex-<lb/>ception of the spot occupied by the buildings necessary for the wash-<lb/>ings. In the course of 1842, they pushed the works under the<lb/>foundations of the building; the first attempts were not successful,<lb/>but they soon came upon a spot of marvellous richness, where the<lb/>yield was from 50 to 70 zolotniks of gold in one poud of sand; its<lb/>extent, however, was very limited. At last, on the 26th of October,<lb/>1842, they found this monstrous mass, weighing 2 pouds 7 phounds<lb/>92 zolotniks (36 kil. .020758), 100.078 lbs. It lay upon the strata of<lb/>diorite (a variety of trap) in the bed of gold sand, at the depth of 4&#x00BD;<lb/>archines from the surface, and under the corner of the building. The<lb/>mass in question has already reached St. Petersburgh, and is placed<lb/>at the museum of the Institute of Mining Engineers. A discovery<lb/>which is equally worthy of our attention, is that of a bed of gold-<lb break="maybe"/>bearing sands on the left bank of the same river before the dike, con-<lb/>taining a considerable number of masses; already they have taken<lb/>thence 52, weighing each from 1 lb. to 7 lbs. Russian.</p>
<p><hi rendition="#i">Note by M. Humboldt.</hi>&#x2014;The largest piece of platina found, up to<lb/>this time, at Nijni Tageulsg weighs 20 lbs., (Russian) 34 zolotniks.<lb/>Piece of gold found at Miask, 10 kil. .119 = 27.0021 lbs. Piece of<lb/>gold found in the United States, Anson county, N. C., 21.70 kil. =<lb/>57.939 lbs. Piece found at Rio Hayna, (1502) and lost in the depths<lb/>of the sea, (see my critical examination of the geography of the new<lb/>continent,) 14.500 kil. = 38.715 lbs. Wonderful mass of miask found<lb/>1842, 36.020 kil. = 100.077 lbs.</p><lb/><p>According to a letter from Count Cancrine, Dec. 3, 1842, Siberia,<lb/>to the east of the Ural, produced, in 1842, the quantity of 479 pouds<lb/>of gold = 7.846 kil. = 21,058 lbs., and the whole of Russia about 970<lb/>pouds = 15.889 kil. = 42,323.63 lbs.</p>
</div><lb/>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
