<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1">
    <head><hi rendition="#i">Isthmus of Panama.</hi></head><p>&#x2014; We subjoin a copy<lb/>of the letter from Baron Humboldt to M. Salomon,<lb/>read by M. Guizot:&#x2014;&#x201C;August, 1842. Sir I learn <choice><sic>with<lb/> with</sic><corr type="editorial">with<lb/></corr></choice>regret, that you are not more advanced in your<lb/>interesting enterprise than you were when I last had<lb/>the pleasure of seeing you at Paris. It is 25 years<lb/>since a project for a communication between the two<lb/>oceans, either by the Isthmus of Panama, by the Lake<lb/>Nicaragua, or by the Isthmus of Capica, has been<lb/>proposed and topographically discussed, and yet nothing<lb/>has been yet commenced. I had believed that the<lb/>English embassy would have found the means of<lb/>inspiring confidence, by sending an engineer to survey<lb/>the valley which separates the two seas, and across<lb/>which a canal might be cut. Be assured that the<lb/>parties who have made use of my name in saying that<lb/>the two seas have not the same level, have done<lb/>so for the purpose of an excuse for not entering on the<lb/>undertaking.&#x201D; We likewise subjoin the extract from<lb/>the document addressed to the Academy of Sciences on<lb/>the subject by an American gentleman, Mr. Warden:<lb/>&#x2014;&#x201C;The cutting necessary to unite the two seas by<lb/>means of the three rivers, Vinotinto, Bernardino, and<lb/>Farren, is only 12<choice><sic>miles+miles</sic><corr type="editorial">&#x00BD; miles</corr></choice> in length. The canal<lb/>in all would be 29 miles in length. It might be made<lb/>navigable for vessels of from 11,000 to 12,000 tons bur-<lb/>den, and the water may be kept at its proper level by<lb/>means of only two locks. All the materials neces-<lb/>sary for the construction of the canal are found in<lb/>abundance on the spot. The total expense is estimated<lb/>at 2,778,615 dollars (14,821,800f.), including the<lb/>expense of four steam boats and two iron bridges to<lb/>open for the passage of ships.&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
