<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<dateline>LONDON, SATURDAY, JULY 8, 1843.</dateline><lb/><pb n="638" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">Isthmus of Panama.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;In the French Chamber of<lb/>Deputies, a short time since, M. Guizot, in answer to<lb/>some observations throwing doubts upon the practica-<lb/>bility of the proposed works for piercing the Isthmus<lb/>of Panama, read the following letter from the Baron<lb/>de Humboldt to one of the heads of the parties in-<lb/>terested in the proposed operation:&#x2014;&#x201C;I learn, with<lb/>regret, that you are not further advanced in your im-<lb/>portant enterprise than you were when I had last the<lb/>pleasure of seeing you in Paris. For the last twenty-<lb break="maybe"/>five years, the project of a communication between the<lb/>two seas, either by the Isthmus of Panama, by Lake<lb/>Nicaragua, or by the Isthmus of Capica, has been<lb/>proposed, and topographically debated; and yet no<lb/>beginning has been made. I should have thought<lb/>that the British Embassy would have found a means<lb/>of inspiring confidence in the proposal to send a scien-<lb/>tific man (an engineer) for the purpose of examining<lb/>the valley which separates the two seas, through<lb/>which the canal might be dug to the western side<lb/>of the Port of Chagres. Be assured that those<lb/>persons who use the authority of my name in<lb/>support of the opinion that the two seas have dif-<lb/>ferent levels, do so only to excuse themselves from<lb/>engaging in the enterprise.&#x201D; The Minister also<lb/>read an extract from a document addressed to the<lb/>Academy of Sciences, by M. Warden, a distinguished<lb/>American citizen, long consul for that country in<lb/>Paris:&#x2014;&#x201C;The cutting necessary to unite the two seas,<lb/>by means of the three rivers, Vino-Tinto, Bernar-<lb/><cb/>dino, and Farren, is but twelve and a half miles in<lb/>length. The fall will be regulated by four double<lb/>locks of 45 mètres long. The canal will be altogether<lb/>49 miles in extent, 43 mètres 50 centimètres wide at<lb/>the surface, 17 mètres 50 centimètres at the bottom,<lb/>and having a depth of 6 mètres 50 centimètres. It<lb/>will be navigable for vessels of from 1,000 to 1,400<lb/>tons burthen. The rivers, in those portions of them<lb/>where they have from 2&#x00BD; to 4&#x00BD; mètres of water, will<lb/>serve for the canal, by deepening to 6&#x00BD; mètres; and<lb/>the water will be maintained at that height by two<lb/>guard-locks. All the materials necessary for the con-<lb/>struction of the canal are found on the soil which it<lb/>has to traverse; and the total cost has been estimated<lb/>at 2,778,615 dollars, including the price of four steam-<lb break="maybe"/>boats, and two iron bridges, 46 mètres long, and<lb/>opening for the passage of ships.&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
