<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<dateline><hi rendition="#b"><hi rendition="#g">OCTOBER, 1843.</hi></hi></dateline><lb/><pb n="283" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Isthmus of Panama.</hi></head>
    <p>&#x2014;In the French Chamber<lb/>of Deputies, a short time since, M. Guizot, in an-<lb/>swer to some observations throwing doubts upon<lb/>the practicability of the proposed works for piercing<lb/>the Isthmus of Panama, read the following letter<lb/>from the Baron de Humboldt to one of the heads of<lb/>the parties interested in the proposed operation:&#x2014;<lb/>&#x201C;I learn, with regret, that you are not further ad-<lb/>vanced in your important enterprise than you were<lb/>when I had last the pleasure of seeing you in Paris.<lb/>Fot the last twenty-five years, the project of a com-<lb/>munication between the two seas, either by the<lb/>Isthmus of Panama, by Lake Nicaragua, or by the<lb/>Isthmus of Capica, has been proposed, and topo-<lb/>graphically debated; and yet no beginning has been<lb/>made. I should have thought that the British Em-<lb/>bassy would have found a means of inspiring con-<lb/>fidence in the proposal to send a scientific man (an<lb/>engineer) for the purpose of examining the valley<lb/>which separates the two seas, through which the<lb/>canal might be dug to the western side of the Port<lb/>of Chagres. Be assured that those persons who use<lb/>the authority of my name in support of the opinion<lb/>that the two seas have different levels, do so only<lb/>to excuse themselves from engaging in the enter-<lb/></p> <pb n="284" facs="#f0002"/> <p>prise.&#x201D; The Minister also read an extract from a<lb/>document addressed to the Academy of Sciences,<lb/>by M. Warden, a distinguished American citizen,<lb/>long consul for that country in Paris:&#x2014;&#x201C;The cut-<lb/>ting necessary to unite the two seas, by means of<lb/>the three rivers, Vino-Tinto, Bernardino, and Far-<lb/>ren, is but twelve and a half miles in length. The<lb/>fall will be regulated by four double locks of 45<lb/>mètres long. The canal will be altogether 49 miles<lb/>in extent, 43 mètres 50 centimètres wide at the<lb/>surface, 17 mètres 50 centimètres at the bottom,<lb/>and having a depth of 6 mètres 50 centimètres. It<lb/>will be navigable for vessels of from 1,000 to 1,400<lb/>tons burthen. The rivers, in those portions of them<lb/>where they have from 2&#x00BD; to 4&#x00BD; mètres of water, will<lb/>serve for the canal, by deepening to 6&#x00BD; mètres; and<lb/>the water will be maintained at that height by two<lb/>guard-locks. All the materials necessary for the<lb/>construction of the canal are found on the soil<lb/>which it has to traverse; and the total cost has<lb/>been estimated at 2,778,615 dollars, including the<lb/>price of four steam-boats, and two iron bridges, 46<lb/>mètres long, and opening for the passage of ships.&#x201D;<lb/><hi rendition="#i" >&#x2014;Athen&#x00E6;um.</hi></p>
</div>
    <lb/>
</body>
    <back/></text>
</TEI>
