<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/111602781X">
                        <surname>Müller-Tamm</surname>
                        <forename>Jutta</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.1" when="2019-05-21" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.1" when="2018-11-02" who="#wernicke_nd">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Vergessene @ gelöscht.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-10-21" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="323" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Comparative Level of Lakes and Seas, as the Caspian,<lb break="yes"/>Lake Aral, Black Sea, Red Sea, Mediterranean, Lake Ti-<lb break="no"/>berias, Dead Sea, Atlantic, Pacific, &#x0026;c.</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">By Baron<lb break="yes"/>Alexander von Humboldt.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Caspian Sea has presented two problems which have long been<lb break="yes" />subjects of discussion,&#x2014;the problem of its isolation, and that of the<lb break="yes"/>relative height of its mean level; and there has been a similar fluctuation<lb break="yes"/>on both these points. Inasmuch as, by the assiduous labours of Messrs G.<lb break="yes"/>Fuss, Sabler, and Sawitsch, the height of the waters of the Caspian was<lb break="yes"/>perfectly ascertained in the year 1837, we might pass in silence the<lb break="yes"/>attempts which were made by means of barometrical measurements. I<lb break="yes"/>wish, however, to record here some of the results which, for 60 or 70<lb break="yes"/>years, most engaged public attention.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Chappe</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">Voy. en Sibérie, T. ii. pp. 487-491.</note> found from the barometrical observations made by Dr Leere<lb break="yes"/>at Astrakhan, from the years 1732 to 1749, that the Caspian was depressed<lb break="yes"/>51 toises. This result he designated as &#x201C;evidently absurd.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Inochodzow</hi>, in comparing the mean barometric heights of Kamychine,<lb break="yes"/>a small town in the government of Saratov (means deduced from ob-<lb break="no"/>servations from October 1770 to August 1774), with the corresponding<lb break="yes"/>barometric means of St Petersburg, concluded from this comparison, that<lb break="yes"/>Kamychine (lat 50° 5&#x2032;), upon the banks of the Volga, is 171 French<lb break="yes"/>feet, (28.5 toises), below the level of the surface at St Petersburgh.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Nov. Acta Acad. Petrop. T. xii. p. 506, 1801.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>There is a difference of 4° of latitude between Kamychine and the<lb break="yes"/>mouth of the Volga; and there is 10° between Kamychine and St<lb break="yes"/>Petersburgh. It is very likely that a remark respecting the depression<lb break="yes"/>of the basin of the Caspian, which is to be found in the celebrated work<lb break="yes"/>of the Abbé Raynal upon the colonies, is grounded upon his cognizance<lb break="yes"/>of the barometric calculations of Inochodzow. This eminent Russian<lb break="yes"/>philosopher mentions that, previous to his time, <hi rendition="#i">Chretien Mayer</hi>, in a<lb break="yes"/>memoir regarding the transit of Venus (p. 316), had valued the negative<lb break="yes"/>height of the Caspian at 101 feet (17 toises), grounding his calculation<lb break="yes"/>upon the barometrical observations of the traveller <hi rendition="#i">Lerche.</hi> It is almost<lb break="yes" />superfluous to point out, that this coincidence, with the first provisional<lb break="yes"/>result derived from the grand trigonometric levelling of 1837, is alto-<lb break="no"/>gether accidental. In fact, it is in hypsometry as in the determination<lb break="yes"/>of different astronomical positions. When a point has for a long time<lb break="yes"/>oscillated in our charts from north to south, we always find some one or<lb break="yes"/>other ancient chart which indicates the true latitude, in agreement with<lb break="yes"/>the result of the latest and most difficult operations. Pallas<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;" >Reise, T. iii. p. 316.</note> preferred<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="324" facs="#f0002"/> a valuation which differed but little from that of Mayer. He assigns 10<lb break="yes"/>toises for the difference of the level of the waters of the Volga and the<lb break="yes"/>Don, at the place where the rivers most approximate. When to this we<lb break="yes"/>add the 8 toises which M. Goebel found Zaritzin higher than the level of<lb break="yes"/>the Caspian, by a very accurate barometrical levelling, we have for this<lb break="yes" />level &#x2014;18 toises. Nevertheless, we must remember that, according to a<lb break="yes"/>geometric levelling recently made by the officers of the Imperial Corps of<lb break="yes"/>Roads and Highways, the differences of the level of the Don and Volga,<lb break="yes"/>between Katchalinsk and Zaritzin, is twice as much as that stated above,<lb break="yes"/>or 21.2 toises. MM. Parrot and Behagel have found it barometrically<lb break="yes"/>to be 27 toises. From my own observation (on the 21st October 1829), I<lb break="yes"/>found a difference some what less between the Volga and Tchivskaya upon<lb break="yes" />the Don.<note place="foot" n="*">Parrot, Reise zum Ararat, 1834, p. 13, 192.</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The barometrical means which the <hi rendition="#i">Acta Acad. Petrop,</hi> 1782, p. 24, sup-<lb break="no"/>ply for Astrakhan, Irkoutsk, Moscow, and St Petersburg, make the<lb break="yes"/>Caspian &#x2014;45 toises.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The astronomer <hi rendition="#i">Wisniewski</hi>, from barometric observations of 3 years&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>continuance, fixed the level at &#x2014; 257 feet, or 42.8 toises. It is not, how-<lb break="no"/>ever, probable, that it was to this conclusion that Thomas Young refers,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;" >Course of Lectures, 1807, vol. i. p. 571; vol. ii. p. 367.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>where he affirms that the depression of the Caspian appears to be nearly<lb break="yes"/>300 English feet (&#x2014;47 toises).</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The barometric levelling by stations, executed in the year 1811, by<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">MM. Parrot</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Engelhardt</hi>, between the Caspian and the Black Sea, gave<lb break="yes"/>in going and returning, in 27 days, &#x2014;54.2 toises; in 30 days, &#x2014;47.1<lb break="yes"/>toises; mean, 50.6 toises.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Monteith</hi> believed that he ascertained by the determination of the boil-<lb break="no"/>ing point of water, that the level was &#x2014;61 toises; and <hi rendition="#i">Loktin</hi>, from baro-<lb break="no" />metrical observations from 1805 to 1811, made at Astrakhan, that it was<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;39 toises.<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;"><choice><sic>Pansner</sic><corr type="editorial">Pansner,</corr></choice> Höhen im Europ. <choice><sic>et</sic><corr type="editorial">und</corr></choice> Asiat. Russland, 1836, p. 23.</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">MM. Hofmann</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Helmersen</hi> conducted with much care, in 1825, a<lb break="yes"/>barometric levelling by stations from Orenbourg to Gourief, situated at<lb break="yes"/>the embouchure of the Ja&#x00EF;k (Oural) into the Caspian Sea. They found by<lb break="yes" />this levelling, and from corresponding barometric observations at the ex-<lb break="no"/>treme points, that Orenbourg was elevated 52 toises above the level of<lb break="yes"/>the Caspian Sea. Now, M. Galle assigns from the whole barometric ob-<lb break="no"/>servations of MM. Hofmann and Karelin at Orenbourg, that this for-<lb break="no"/>tress is 39 toises above the ocean. From this it may be deduced, that<lb break="yes"/>the Caspian has a depression of&#x2014;13 toises, a result which is remarkably<lb break="yes"/>accurate, but which was for long misunderstood, because it was supposed<lb break="yes"/>that Orenbourg stood but little above the level of the ocean. The baro-<lb break="no" />metric observations which were made together by MM. Hofmann, Hel-<lb break="no"/>mersen, Rose, and myself, from the 12th to the 21st of October 1829 on the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="325" facs="#f0003"/> shores of the Caspian, were compared with corresponding observations<lb break="yes"/>at Kasan; and they have made us sceptical ever since respecting any<lb break="yes"/>very great depression of the Caspian.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. Parrot, whose premature loss science has to regret, during his me-<lb break="no"/>morable journey to Ararat, conceived doubts concerning the accuracy of<lb break="yes"/>two barometric levellings by stations which he had executed with extreme<lb break="yes"/>care, though labouring under fever, in the year 1811. In 1830, he had<lb break="yes"/>the energy to repeat this painful labour between Astrakhan and New<lb break="yes"/>Tcherkask, which occupied him for twelve days. From these observa-<lb break="no"/>tions, he concluded, that there exists only a slight difference in the level<lb break="yes"/>of the surfaces of the water of the Black Sea and the Caspian.<note place="foot" n="*" >See <hi rendition="#i">Reise nach dem Ararat</hi>, T. ii. p. 12-31; likewise Letter of M. de<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt, of date 28th May 1834, stating doubts of a depression of 200 or 300<lb break="yes"/>feet attributed to the basin of the Caspian Sea. T. ii., p. 191-198.</note> It would<lb break="yes"/>not be easy sufficiently to commend the stern and noble candour which<lb break="yes"/>M. Parrot has displayed in discussing his own barometrical observations.<lb break="yes"/>The source of error ought to be sought for alone in the barometric me-<lb break="no"/>thod of levelling by stations, to which the mode of observations made at<lb break="yes"/>the extremities of a geod&#x00E6;sical line is greatly preferable. In the partial<lb break="yes"/>levelling by stations, the errors accumulate by the influence of the frequent<lb break="yes"/>change of local temperature, and by the comparison of two instruments,<lb break="yes"/>the one of which, and the same one, always preceding the other. Another<lb break="yes"/>barometric levelling by stations was likewise executed in the years 1838<lb break="yes"/>and 1839, simultaneously with the geod&#x00E6;sical levelling by M. Fuss. By<lb break="yes"/>various accidental causes it again yielded a result of&#x2014;47 toises, a depres-<lb break="no"/>sion almost identical with that given by the first operation by stations,<lb break="yes"/>in 1811, by M. Parrot.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The results derived from the barometric observations taken on the<lb break="yes" />shores of the Caspian and Black Seas have been very different. M. Sa-<lb break="no"/>witsch, from observations made at Taganrog and at Astrakhan, has made<lb break="yes"/>the depression &#x2014; 22.2 toises; M. Göbel<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">M. Göbel has compared the barometric observations of M. Offe at Astrakhan,<lb break="yes"/>those of M. Steven at Sympheropol, and his own at the Sea of Azov. Göbel,<lb break="yes"/>Reise, T. ii. p. 193.</note> from observations at Astrakhan<lb break="yes"/>and Sympheropol, has made it 15.9 toises; and M. Lenz, by comparing<lb break="yes"/>3510 barometric observations made in 1830 at Bakou by M. Meyer, and<lb break="yes" />at Taganrog by M. Meyer, 16.8 toises.<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Recueil des Actes de l&#x2019;Acad. de St Petersburg, 1836, p. 29.</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If, thanks to the admirable labours of MM. Fuss, Sabler, and Sawitsch,<lb break="yes"/>we now know with mathematical precision the real depression of the level<lb break="yes"/>of the Caspian Sea, amounting to 12.7 toises, the accounts of the height<lb break="yes"/>between the Caspian and the Lake Aral are not equally certain. These<lb break="yes"/>accounts have been taken only by means of <hi rendition="#i">barometric levelling by stations</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>conducted during the military expedition of l&#x2019;Oust-Ourt,<note place="foot" n="§" xml:id="fn1-1" next="#fn1-2">See T. i. p. 421. The direct result obtained by MM. Sagoskin, Anjou, and</note> during the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="326" facs="#f0004"/> winter of 1826. After the troublesome and unsatisfactory experiment<lb break="yes"/>of comparing the geod&#x00E6;sical levelling with the barometrical of the year<lb break="yes"/>1837, it is impossible to have much confidence in the barometric method<lb break="yes" />employed.<note place="foot" n="*">See an interesting Memoir of M. Lenz: <hi rendition="#i">Considerations Mathematiques sur les<lb break="yes" />nivellements par Stations an moyen du barometre.</hi> (Bull. de St Petersburg, T. i.<lb break="yes"/>p. 51 and 63.</note> As the Lake Aral has been found to be only 34 feet (5.6<lb break="yes"/>toises) above the level of the Black Sea, and that in the two barometric<lb break="yes"/>levellings by stations in 1811 and 1837, the error exceeded 224 feet<lb break="yes"/>(37.3 toises), it may well be that the Lake Aral may be at the level of<lb break="yes" />the waters of the Caspian, and that all the Aralo-Caspian basin has a<lb break="yes"/>depression of 76 feet (&#x2014;12.7 toises). But without adopting this conclu-<lb break="no"/>sion, grounded upon the analogy of the barometrical operations of 1811,<lb break="yes"/>1826, and 1837, and excluding also the whole shores of Lake Aral, we<lb break="yes"/>still find, as the result of our actual knowledge, an extent of <hi rendition="#i">continental<lb break="yes"/>land</hi> of more than 8000 square marine leagues depressed below the sur-<lb break="no"/>face of the Black Sea. The geod&#x00E6;sical line of <hi rendition="#i">zero height</hi>, that is to say,<lb break="yes"/>that which unites the points of the surface placed on the level of the<lb break="yes" />Black Sea, traverses the Volga between Zaritzin and Saratov. Now,<lb break="yes"/>from the extremity of the delta of the Volga to Zaritzin, there are 3° 40&#x2032;<lb break="yes"/>of latitude&#x2014;a distance equal to that from Paris to Grenoble, or equal to<lb break="yes"/>four-fifths of the extent of Spain. To the east of Zaritzin, the shores of<lb break="yes"/>Lake Elton<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">I have found the south-west extremity of this lake generally very erroneously<lb break="yes"/>placed in our maps in lat. 49° 7&#x2032; 17&#x2033;, and long. 44° 15&#x2032; 36&#x2033;.</note> and Kalmykova, upon the river Ja&#x00EF;k, are from 5 to 12 toises<lb break="yes" />below the level of the Black Sea. It is also believed that the country<lb break="yes"/>which encloses, to the west of Kalmykova, the salt-lakes of Kamych-<lb break="maybe"/>Samara, have a depression of &#x2014; 23 toises, consequently being ten toises<lb break="yes"/>beneath the level of the Caspian Sea.<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Göbel, <hi rendition="#i">Reise</hi>, T. ii. p. 200.</note> M. de Struve remarks, &#x201C;that<lb break="yes"/>the line of the <hi rendition="#i">zero</hi> level surrounds a submarine space (placed beneath<lb break="yes"/>the surface of the Black Sea) greater even than the surface of the Cas-<lb break="no"/>pian; and that in the geod&#x00E6;sical levelling of 1836 and 1837, the limits<lb break="yes"/>of this <hi rendition="#i">vast Asiatic depression</hi> towards the west, was at a distance of 12<lb break="yes"/>marine leagues from shore.<choice><sic></sic><corr type="editorial">&#x201D;</corr></choice><note place="foot" n="§">Bull. de l&#x2019;Acad. de St Petersb., T. iii. p. 368.</note> We have seen that to the north<note place="foot" n="||" xml:id="fm2-1" next="#fm2-2">It results from the barometric observations of M. Göbel, considering the zero<lb break="yes"/>at the level of the Black Sea, and admitting &#x2014; 12.7 toises for the Caspian Sea;<lb break="yes"/>that the Volga, near to Saratov, is at an elevation of + 6 toises; Zaritzin is &#x2014; 5<lb break="yes"/>toises; the Steppe Khotchetaevka &#x2014; 12 t.; the Lake Bogdo &#x2014; 3 t.; the Lake<lb break="yes"/>Arsangar + 12 t.; and the Mount Grand-Bogdo + 87 t. According to MM. Parrot</note> and<lb break="yes" />north-east, the depression extends above 70 leagues. Limiting ourselves,<lb break="yes"/>then, to an estimate of 8000 square marine leagues less than that of<lb break="yes"/>M. de Struve, we obtain for the <hi rendition="#i" >area</hi> of the total depression,&#x2014;includ-<lb break="no"/>ing that which is actually covered with the waters of the Caspian Sea,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="§" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1">Duhamel, was, that the level of the waters of Lake Aral was 117.6 English feet<lb break="yes" />(18.3 toises) above the level of the waters of the Caspian.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="327" facs="#f0005"/> and always excluding Lake Aral,&#x2014;more than 18,000 square marine<lb break="yes"/>leagues; in other words, a surface of 900 square leagues larger than that<lb break="yes"/>of France. It is earnestly to be wished that the Imperial Academy of<lb break="yes"/>St Petersburg will continue the beautiful geod&#x00E6;sical survey commenced<lb break="yes"/>under its auspices, and that that illustrious society will not only ascertain<lb break="yes"/>the true difference of the heights of the Aral and the Caspian, but that,<lb break="yes"/>so far as these regions are accessible to such peaceful occupations, they<lb break="yes"/>will also succeed in procuring the <hi rendition="#i">zero geod&#x00E6;sical line</hi> between <choice><sic>he</sic><corr type="editorial">the</corr></choice> Volga<lb break="yes"/>and the Ia&#x00EF;k, between the Ia&#x00EF;k, the Emba, and the north-east extremity<lb break="yes"/>of the Aral Sea, and finally, between this sea and the Aksakal-Barbi.<note place="foot" n="*">I attach great importance to the determination of the height of the land in<lb break="yes"/>the Steppe, which the ancient hollow, running S.S.E. and N.N.E., and of which I<lb break="yes"/>have often spoken, follows. I find in my correspondence with M. St Martin, that<lb break="yes"/>this <hi rendition="#i">savant</hi> had heard of &#x201C;a tradition of the Avares, according to which this people<lb break="yes"/>allege that they had quitted their original place of abode (at the foot of Alta&#x00EF;?)<lb break="yes"/>on account of the sudden drying up of an interior sea, and of an increased dryness<lb break="yes"/>of the Steppe.&#x201D; I am quite ignorant of the source whence M. St Martin pro-<lb break="no"/>cured this notice, which we might be tempted to associate with the Chinese story<lb break="yes"/>of the disappearance of the &#x201C;Sea of bitter waters.&#x201D;</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. Arago who, in his writings, always ascends with success to first prin-<lb break="no"/>ciples concerning the physical constitution of the globe, has, in his memoir<lb break="yes"/>upon comets, pointed out a curious work of Halley,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Some considerations about the cause of the Universal Deluge,</hi> Phil. Trans, vol.<lb break="yes"/>xxxiii. p. 122. &#x201C;A shock of a comet may have occasioned that <hi rendition="#i">vast depression</hi> of<lb break="yes"/>the Caspian Sea and other great lakes in the world.&#x201D;</note> in which the English<lb break="yes" />astronomer, as early as December 1694, mentioned the <hi rendition="#i">great depression</hi> of<lb break="yes"/>the Caspian, which he attributes to the shock of a ball of immense dimen-<lb break="no"/>sions; in other words, of a comet. &#x201C;The vast depression,&#x201D; observes M.<lb break="yes"/>Arago, &#x201C;of a whole country, in former times appeared of an explanation too<lb break="yes"/>difficult for the action of any ordinary forces; and in despair of such<lb break="yes"/>causes, recourse was had, as in many other circumstances, to an action pro-<lb break="no"/>ceeding from the celestial spaces. In the present state of our geological<lb break="yes"/>knowledge, this idea of Halley will not receive much favour. Scarcely any<lb break="yes"/>one now doubts that the isolated peaks, and the longest and most eleva-<lb break="no"/>ted ranges of mountains, have proceeded from the interior of the globe<lb break="yes"/>by the way of upheaving. But does not this very upheaving imply the<lb break="yes"/>production of a void beneath the surrounding districts, and the possibi-<lb break="no"/>lity of this subsequent subsidence? When we cast our eyes upon a<lb break="yes"/>geographical chart, we easily perceive that no part of the world exhibits<lb break="yes"/>so many upraised masses as Asia. Around the Caspian Sea, at greater<lb break="yes"/>or less distances, we find the high lands of Iran and of Central Asia, the<lb break="yes"/>mountain chains of Kouen-lun, and of Hindoo-Kho, the mountains of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="||" xml:id="fn2-2" prev="#fm2-1">and Behaghel, the Volga near Zaritzin is 27 toises lower than the Don 72 versts<lb break="yes" />above the Patiisbansk. I assign these valuations, remembering how uncertain a<lb break="yes"/>barometric levelling is in the plains and for the measurement of small heights,<lb break="yes"/>when the differences in the height of the columns of mercury do not attain to<lb break="yes"/>2 millimetres, and are grounded upon a small number of observations.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="328" facs="#f0006"/> Armenia, and those of the Caucasus. Hence, without having recourse<lb break="yes"/>to a comet, is it not natural to suppose that the upraising of the enor-<lb break="no"/>mous masses of rock we have just named, was sufficient to induce the<lb break="yes"/>sensible depression of the intermediate localities? This solution of a<lb break="yes"/>curious problem in physical geography which the shores of the Caspian<lb break="yes"/>has originated, may so much the less give rise to serious difficulties,<lb break="yes"/>inasmuch as in these very regions the surface, even at the present day, is<lb break="yes"/>not altogether stable; and the bottom of the Caspian Sea itself presents<lb break="yes"/>alterations of elevations and depressions. It is, however, true, that the<lb break="yes"/>fact under discussion will lose much of its interest, if we investigate it as<lb break="yes"/>a simple <hi rendition="#i">meteorological phenomenon.</hi> Suppose that a Julia island should<lb break="yes"/>happen to rise in the middle of the Straits of Gibraltar, and close up the<lb break="yes"/>entrance. Immediately, the rapid current which a portion of the waters<lb break="yes"/>of the ocean constantly pours into the Mediterranean would cease; im-<lb break="no" />mediately the level of the Mediterranean would fall, for the total volume<lb break="yes"/>of the rivers it receives would not compensate, as it appears, for the loss<lb break="yes"/>resulting from evaporation. During this gradual lowering of the level<lb break="yes"/>of the sea, parts which are now submerged would appear above the<lb break="yes"/>waves, would connect themselves with the neighbouring continents, and<lb break="yes"/>would remain, as at present, beneath the level of the ocean. This, per-<lb break="no"/>haps, is the solution of the whole problem of the Caspian, and especially,<lb break="yes"/>if with some geologists we add, that, in this sea, large volcanic crevices,<lb break="yes"/>from time to time, permit its waters to dissipate themselves in the bowels<lb break="yes"/>of the earth, and thus render the difference more sensible which, even<lb break="yes"/>without this occurrence, already existed between the effects of the annual<lb break="yes"/>evaporation, and the waters supplied by the Volga, the Oural, the Terek,<lb break="yes"/>and other rivers.&#x201D;<note place="foot" n="*">See <hi rendition="#i">Notices Scientifiques</hi> by M. Arago, inserted in the <hi rendition="#i" >Annuaire du Bureau des<lb break="yes"/>Longitudes</hi>, 1832, p. 352.</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These judicious considerations acquire still greater importance when<lb break="yes"/>we consider the additional information collected since the days of the<lb break="yes"/>illustrious Pallas,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;" >Pallas, <hi rendition="#i">Voyage dans les Provinces méridionales de la Russie</hi> in 1793 and 1794,<lb break="yes"/>T. i. p. 235. Dureau de La Malle, <hi rendition="#i">Geographie physique de la Mer-Noire</hi>, p. 176,<lb break="yes"/>194, and 264. Compare also Pansner and Zeune, in the Journal of M. Berghaus,<lb break="yes"/>1836, No. 140, p. 179 and 187.</note> especially from the maps of Major Khatov,<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Maps (in 10 sheets), published by <hi rendition="#i" >l&#x2019;Etat-Major</hi> of the Imperial Army, repre-<lb break="no" />senting the country between the Black Sea and the Caspian.</note> and<lb break="yes"/>from the detailed investigations of M. Parrot, upon the plains which ex-<lb break="no"/>tend in the steppe of the Kalmucs and Turcomans, between the Black<lb break="yes"/>and Caspian Seas, in the 45° and 47° of latitude. A slightly elevated<lb break="yes"/>ridge detaches itself from the Caucasus, running from the Elbrouz to-<lb break="no"/>wards Stavropol, in the direction from south to north. Upon the oppo-<lb break="no"/>site slopes of this ridge there take their origin, first, the Kouban and the<lb break="yes" />Terek,<note place="foot" n="§" xml:id="fn3-1" next="#fn3-2">Since the commencement of the 17th century, great changes have taken place</note> and then the Iegorlik and the Kouma, which, at the end of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="329" facs="#f0007"/> summer, sometimes lose themselves in a lake of the Steppe, without ever<lb break="yes"/>reaching the Caspian Sea. Still farther on, at the northern extremity of<lb break="yes"/>the ridge, the bifurcated Kalaüs takes its rise.<note place="foot" n="*">Parrot, <hi rendition="#i">Reise zum Ararat,</hi> T. ii. p. 12-25, and p. 33-36. The waters of the Kouban,<lb break="yes"/>the Iegorlik, and the eastern Manetch, flow to the Black Sea; those of the Terek<lb break="yes"/>and of the Kouma to the Caspian Sea. The Kalaüs forms, by its bifurcation, to<lb break="yes"/>the west, the western Manetch, which dilates into a salt lake (the lake Manetch),<lb break="yes"/>and receives the Iegorlik before it reaches the Don. The eastern branch of the<lb break="yes"/>Kalaüs, which merits a more special examination, seems to form the eastern Ma-<lb break="no"/>netch. The river Kouma does not in all seasons reach as far as the Caspian, often<lb break="yes"/>terminating in summer in a fresh-water lake, the lake of Iarligor.</note> This last river, whose<lb break="yes"/>course is very variable, commingles its waters with those of the Manetch,<lb break="yes"/>an affluent of the Don. It is even regarded as the principal source of<lb break="yes"/>the western Manetch. Another branch of the Kalaüs proceeds to the<lb break="yes"/>eastern Manetch, and spreads out near to Gouidouc, a post-station on<lb break="yes"/>the road from Astrakhan to Tiflis, into a large lake which the Kal-<lb break="no"/>mucs call by the name of Kokoussoun. The conformation of the district,<lb break="yes"/>which gently undulates along the Manetch, and to the north of the Kouma,<lb break="yes"/>is very remarkable. The course of the Manetch or Manytch is 500 versts<lb break="yes"/>in length; its fall is so trifling that, according to the testimony of General<lb break="yes" />Bogdanovitch, who has examined its windings, its waters during the<lb break="yes"/>summer actually follow the direction of the wind. The river at the pre-<lb break="no"/>sent time does not throughout the upper course approximate nearer than<lb break="yes"/>70 versts to the weedy shores of the Caspian Sea; and yet, without<lb break="yes"/>doubt, it was in this part of the Kalmuc Steppe, we must suppose, that,<lb break="yes"/>previous to those times we designate historical, a communication exist-<lb break="no"/>ed between the basins of the Caspian and Black Seas.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The work in which MM. Fuss, Sawitsch, and Sabler are about to de-<lb break="no" />scribe the district which has been the theatre of their very careful geo-<lb break="no"/>d&#x00E6;sical labours, will shed new light on these views, several of which may<lb break="yes"/>appear to be rash. I shall here limit myself to the statement of a very<lb break="yes"/>curious fact which, according to the report of some of the natives who<lb break="yes"/>seem worthy of credit, was received by M. Parrot at Gouidouc, namely,<lb break="yes"/>that there existed, in times quite modern, a communication between the<lb break="yes" />eastern Manetch and the Caspian Sea. All these facts, however, render<lb break="yes"/>it highly probable, that, in ancient times, previous to the time when the<lb break="yes"/>sand embankments and the downs, accumulated by the winds, had changed<lb break="yes"/>the surface of the soil; and, previous to the sea of Asov being restricted<lb break="yes"/>to its present limits, a strait or natural canal had conducted the waters of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="§" xml:id="fn3-2" prev="#fn3-1">at the embouchure of the Terek and the Tumen, near which was situated the fortress<lb break="yes"/>of Terki, which was constructed under the Czars Michel-Feodorovitch and Alexi-<lb break="maybe"/>Michailovitch, and destroyed by the orders of Peter the Great in the year 1722.<lb break="yes"/>The site of this fortress has since been entirely covered by the Caspian Sea; a<lb break="yes" />phenomenon the more extraordinary, that at the same epoch the waters of this<lb break="yes"/>sea apparently sank at the custom-house of Astrakhan, and towards the mouths<lb break="yes"/>of the Volga. See the Memoir of M. Hamel, <hi rendition="#i">Sur <choice><sic>un</sic><corr type="editorial">une</corr></choice> expedition minéralogique au<lb break="yes"/>Caucase, faite <choice><sic>in</sic><corr type="editorial">en</corr></choice> 1628, sur les auspices du Czar Michel Feodorovitch.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="330" facs="#f0008"/> the Euxine to the Caspian Sea.<note place="foot" n="*">The mean level of lake Manetch, the enlargement of the western Manetch,<lb break="yes"/>and consequently also of the western branch of the Kalaüs, does not appear to be<lb break="yes"/>elevated above 3 or 4 toises above the level of the Black Sea.</note> This strait must have produced a<lb break="yes"/>marine current from west to east, similar, on a small scale, to that which<lb break="yes"/>issues by the pillars of Hercules into the Mediterranean, and which<lb break="yes"/>may be traced even to the coast of Pelusium, where it opposes the too<lb break="yes"/>rapid increase of the Delta of Egypt.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Letronne, <hi rendition="#i">Mém. sur l&#x2019;isthme de Suez, et le canal de jonction des deux mers</hi> (Rev.<lb break="yes"/>des deux mondes, July 1841.)</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Without having recourse to the oscillations which, at the epoch of<lb break="yes" />great geological revolutions, have made the recently solidified crust of<lb break="yes"/>our planet often rise and fall in the plains, we may suppose that, even<lb break="yes"/>still, many continental regions, supported by solid rocks, are found at a<lb break="yes"/>level inferior to that of the ocean, but that, from the large accumulation<lb break="yes"/>of abraded soil, superimposed upon the tertiary and secondary rocks be-<lb break="no"/>neath, the ancient difference of level is hid from our observation. Such<lb break="yes"/>a difference, notwithstanding, remains very visible in many parts of the<lb break="yes"/>coast of Holland, and in the north-east of Germany; as it is also in<lb break="yes"/>Egypt in the <hi rendition="#i">Natron lakes</hi>, visited by General Andreossy; as also in the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">bitter lakes</hi> of the isthmus of Suez, when they are left dry,<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">In this state, the <hi rendition="#i" >Bitter lakes</hi> are 20 feet beneath the level of the Mediterra-<lb break="no"/>nean.</note> or contain but<lb break="yes"/>an inconsiderable depth of water. The difference of the level of the sur-<lb break="no"/>face of the seas, rated at five toises at the isthmus of Suez by M. Le<lb break="yes"/>Père, and of half a toise at the isthmus of Panama, by MM. Lloyd and<lb break="yes"/>Falmarc, are phenomena of an entirely different kind from that with<lb break="yes"/>which we are now engaged. They are the effect of currents, of the pre-<lb break="no"/>ponderating direction of certain winds, of the height of the tides reflected<lb break="yes"/>by the windings of the coasts, of the form of the canal<note place="foot" n="§">M. Arago, in discussing the height to which the level of water maintains itself<lb break="yes"/>in a gulf which communicates with the ocean by a narrow canal, has pointed out<lb break="yes"/>that it is not mathematically proved, that, by a canal of a certain form, the quan-<lb break="no"/>tity that enters and escapes will be the same. An accumulation of water, or a<lb break="yes"/>rise in the level of a gulf or a narrow sea, may be produced by this cause alone.</note> by which they<lb break="yes"/>flow or ebb, and finally, of the variations of the density of our planet.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is the isolated basin of the Jordan and the Dead Sea, whose hypsome-<lb break="no"/>tric relations have so recently engaged the attention of travellers, which<lb break="yes"/>offers the closest analogy with the isolated basin of the Caspian Sea. The<lb break="yes"/>determination of the boiling point of water, which, to be exact, requires<lb break="yes"/>much care, and barometrical measurements, which, unfortunately, did<lb break="yes"/>not accord, at first gave for the depression of the level of the Dead Sea<lb break="yes" />beneath the level of the Mediterranean results which varied between 500<lb break="yes"/>and 1100 French feet (between 83 and 183 toises). The barometer of<lb break="yes"/>M. Schubert, and the barometer of Messrs Moore and Beck, indicated<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="331" facs="#f0009"/> almost at the same time, in the month of April 1837, the existence of an<lb break="yes"/>enormous hollow.<note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Roy. Geog. Soc.</hi> vol. viii., p. 250. <hi rendition="#i">Jameson&#x2019;s Edin. Phil. Journ.</hi> vol.<lb break="yes"/>xxix. p. 96. &#x201C;Professor Schubert of Munich, two Englishmen Messrs Moore and<lb break="yes"/>Beck, and M. J. de Bertou a Frenchman, almost simultaneously, and quite inde-<lb break="no"/>pendently of one another, have made the discovery that the Dead Sea and the en-<lb break="no"/>tire lower valley of the Jordan, are situated considerably below the level of the<lb break="yes"/>Mediterranean Sea.&#x201D;</note> The two English travellers estimated the depression<lb break="yes"/>of the Dead Sea at &#x2014;93 toises. M. le Comte de Bertou has the merit<lb break="yes"/>of having first determined the amount of the depression by barometrical<lb break="yes"/>measurements. M. Caillier,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Bulletin de la Soc. de Geogr.</hi> T. x. (1838) p. 84; and Nouv. Ann. de Voy. T. i.<lb break="yes"/>1839, p. 8.</note> after discussing a portion of the measure-<lb break="no"/>ments, concluded it amounted to &#x2014; 208 toises (&#x2014;406 metres). More<lb break="yes" />recently,<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Bull. de la Soc. de Geogr.</hi> T. xii. 1839, p. 166.</note> M. de Bertou, by combining, in his memoir, all the observa-<lb break="no"/>tions made in March 1838, and in May 1839, estimated it at &#x2014; 215<lb break="yes"/>toises (&#x2014;419 metres). M. Schubert calculated the level of the Sea of<lb break="yes"/>Tiberias at &#x2014; 89 toises (&#x2014;535 feet), but he did not measure the Dead<lb break="yes"/>Sea. M. Russegger, whose journies in Africa and Asia have enriched<lb break="yes" />geology with many important observations, has watched the indications<lb break="yes"/>of the barometer in November and December 1838, during 15 days at<lb break="yes"/>Jaffa, at Jerusalem, and at the Dead Sea. He thinks it possible, owing<lb break="yes"/>to the want of corresponding observations, that the result of his measure-<lb break="no"/>ments may leave a mean doubt of 200 feet at most; but, allowing for<lb break="yes"/>this doubt, he calculates that <hi rendition="#i">higher</hi> than the level of the Mediterranean,<note place="foot" n="§">M. Russegger has published a detailed account of his labours, in Poggendorff&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>Annals, 1841, Numb. 5, p. 186.</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Jerusalem stands + 2479 feet (413 toises), and Bethlehem + 2538 feet<lb break="yes"/>(423 toises); and <hi rendition="#i">below</hi> the level of the Mediterranean, the Lake Tibe-<lb break="no"/>rias is &#x2014;625 feet (&#x2014;104 toises), and the Dead Sea &#x2014; 1341 feet<lb break="yes" />(&#x2014;223 toises, or &#x2014;435 metres). In proportion as, in the geod&#x00E6;sical la-<lb break="no"/>bours, from the variations of successive results, the level of the Caspian has<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">ascended</hi> from &#x2014;50 to &#x2014;13 toises in relation to the Mediterranean, the<lb break="yes"/>level of the Dead Sea has proportionally <hi rendition="#i">descended.</hi> After the numerous<lb break="yes"/>doubts which have prevailed regarding the great depression of this last<lb break="yes"/>level, a trigonometrical survey, executed in the autumn of 1841 by Lieu-<lb break="no"/>tenant Symond of the British Royal Navy, has given the result, that<lb break="yes"/>the surface of the waters of the Dead Sea is 251 toises (489 metres)<lb break="yes"/>lower than the highest house of Jaffa, and probably 219 toises (427 metres)<lb break="yes"/>lower than the surface of the Mediterranean. This trigonometrical re-<lb break="no"/>sult differs accidentally only 8 metres from the result of the barome-<lb break="no" />trical measures of MM. Bertou and Russegger. The geological pro-<lb break="no" />blem of the depression of the valley of the Jordan and of the Dead Sea<lb break="yes"/>is all the more important, that it is intimately connected, I will not say<lb break="yes"/>with the destruction of the five cities of the plain, but with the impossi-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="332" facs="#f0010"/> bility, long ago established by M. Letronne, of the non-communication<lb break="yes"/>of the Jordan, in historic times, with the Elanitic gulf of the Red Sea.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If the depression of the Caspian Sea and of the surrounding country is<lb break="yes"/>inconsiderable, in comparison of the barometrical and trigonometrical<lb break="yes"/>measurements made in Palestine, and which, numerically, seem to be<lb break="yes"/>very near the truth, it, on the contrary, gains in importance when com-<lb break="no"/>pared with the differences presented by the different parts of the ocean<lb break="yes"/>which are in free communication with each other. In the sequel, in the<lb break="yes" />way of comparison, I shall cite those only which are based on geod&#x00E6;si-<lb break="no"/>cal levelling, which are altogether worthy of confidence.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#i">The Gulf of Mexico</hi> (Mer des Antilles) <hi rendition="#i">and the Pacific Ocean.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>General Bolivar, at my request, in the years 1828 and 1829, engaged<lb break="yes"/>the services of an officer of his staff, Mr Lloyd, an American, and of M.<lb break="yes"/>Falmarc, a Swede, carefully to survey the isthmus of Panama. In this<lb break="yes"/>operation they employed a levelling telescope of Carey&#x2019;s. At the mouth<lb break="yes"/>of the Rio Chagres, in the Gulf of Mexico, the difference of the elevation<lb break="yes"/>at the full and ebb tide was only 0.16 of a toise; at Panama, on the shores<lb break="yes"/>of the Pacific Ocean, it was 3.3 toises. From the survey of Messrs<lb break="yes" />Lloyd and Falmarc, it results that the <hi rendition="#i">mean level</hi> of the Pacific Ocean<note place="foot" n="*">Philos. Transact., 1830, p. 84.</note> is<lb break="yes"/>at the most but 0.54 of a toise more elevated than the water of the Gulf<lb break="yes"/>of Mexico, but at the time of the neap tide upon the two coasts, the Pa-<lb break="no"/>cific Ocean is lower than the Gulf of Mexico, to the extent of 1.01 toises.<lb break="yes"/>At different hours of the day, then, it is now the one sea, and now the<lb break="yes"/>other that is highest. M. Arago has accurately observed, that, in an un-<lb break="no" />cultivated country, beset with difficulties, in going over a line of 33<lb break="yes"/>leagues, and taking 935 observations, the small error of three feet may<lb break="yes"/>readily occur; and, consequently, that every proof exists that the differ-<lb break="no"/>ence of level between the two great seas, which communicate by the<lb break="yes"/>Straits of Magellan round Cape Horn, is so small as to be inappreciable.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Notices Scientifiques</hi> of M. Arago, in the <hi rendition="#i">Annuaire</hi> for 1831, p. 319.</note> I<lb break="yes" />myself believe that I established, by means of barometrical observations<lb break="yes"/>taken from 1799 to 1804, and corrected from the effects of hourly vari-<lb break="no"/>ations, that if any sensible difference existed between the waters of the<lb break="yes"/>Mexican Gulf and the Pacific Ocean, this difference was probably not<lb break="yes"/>more than three yards (metres). My barometrical observations,<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Humboldt, <hi rendition="#i">Relation Hist.</hi> T. iii., p. 355-7. Arago, in les Ann. de Chimie, T. i.<lb break="yes"/>p, 55 and 64.</note> as well<lb break="yes" />as the comparison of those of M. Boussingault in 1822 at La Guayra,<lb break="yes"/>and those of M. Pentland at Callao of Lima, in 1826, seem to assign even<lb break="yes"/>a lower level to the waters of the Mexican Gulf; but the variable influence<lb break="yes"/>of capillarity throws a doubt upon the obtained results where they refer<lb break="yes"/>to the decimals of millimetres in the column of mercury.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">The Mediterranean and the Red Sea.</hi>&#x2014;The problem of the relative height<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="333" facs="#f0011"/> of the Red Sea and the Mediterranean, after having occupied the attention<lb break="yes"/>of classical antiquity, has been examined in a very general point of view in<lb break="yes"/>Varenius&#x2019; Treatise on Physical Geography,<note place="foot" n="*">Chap. xiii. prop. 5., chap. xv. prop. 8. I will not attempt to justify the ex-<lb break="no"/>aggerated ideas of the author upon the volume of water, which the rivers, and es-<lb break="no"/>pecially the Volga, pour into the Caspian, xvi. prop. 5.</note> for which Newton exhibited<lb break="yes"/>so decided a predilection. Anything, however, like accurate measure-<lb break="no"/>ment, was not made previous to the time of the French Expedition to Egypt.<lb break="yes" />The observations conducted by M. Le Père, have established that the<lb break="yes"/>level of the Mediterranean, at the embouchure of the Delta, is inferior by<lb break="yes"/>4.1 toises to the neap tides of the Red Sea, near Suez, and 5.1 toises to<lb break="yes"/>the level of full tide. It is probable that the cause of this remarkable<lb break="yes"/>difference of level is the <hi rendition="#i">elevation</hi> of the water in the Arabian Gulf to the<lb break="yes"/>north of the Strait of Bab-el-Mandeb, and not, as M. de Corancez<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Itinéraire d&#x2019;une partie peu connue de l&#x2019;Asie mineure</hi>, prop. 27.</note> has at-<lb break="no" />tempted to prove by the hydraulic hypothesis of the reciprocal attrac-<lb break="no"/>tion of the molecules of water, to the <hi rendition="#i" >depression</hi> of the eastern portion of<lb break="yes"/>the Mediterranean, in which a copious evaporation is not compensated<lb break="yes" />by the volume of water which is poured in by the rivers.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">The Mediterranean and Atlantic.</hi>&#x2014;This comparison of levels, based upon<lb break="yes"/>trigonometrical operations, whose precision surpasses all that has hitherto<lb break="yes"/>been published in this kind of labour, is two-fold. The former exhibits<lb break="yes"/>the almost insensible difference of the Mediterranean and the Atlantic by<lb break="yes" />the Pyrenees; the latter connects the Zuider-Zee, near Amsterdam,<lb break="yes"/>with Marseilles. &#x201C;Delambre had previously endeavoured to deduce from<lb break="yes"/>the great chain of triangles which extends from Dunkirk to Barcelona,<lb break="yes"/>the levels of the two seas. The triangles included between Rhodez and<lb break="yes"/>the Mediterranean gave, for the vertical height of that town, a result<lb break="yes"/>which agrees to a fraction of a metre with the height calculated from the<lb break="yes"/>ocean, which was deduced from that portion of the chain interposed be-<lb break="no" />tween Rhodez and Dunkirk. A trigonometrical survey, executed by<lb break="yes" />MM. Coraboeuf, Peytier, Hossard, and Testu, during the years 1825&#x2015;<lb break="no"/>1827, and running along the southern frontier of France, supplied all<lb break="yes"/>that remained doubtful for the solution of the problem. The station<lb break="yes"/>of Crabère occupies nearly the middle of the interval which separates<lb break="yes"/>the Atlantic from the Mediterranean. Its height has been calculated<lb break="yes"/>by three distinct combinations. One has been conducted by proceed-<lb break="no"/>ing from the Atlantic and from the Mediterranean to Crabère, pass-<lb break="no"/>ing by the single series of the summits of the triangles which bound the<lb break="yes" />chain on the <hi rendition="#i">south;</hi> a second by selecting exclusively the <hi rendition="#i">northern</hi> sum-<lb break="no"/>mits; and the third and last, by taking the <hi rendition="#i">diagonal</hi> directions, in other<lb break="yes"/>words, by taking alternately a northern and a southern summit.&#x201D;<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Arago in the <hi rendition="#i">Annuaire</hi> for 1831, p. 325. Also Mémoires présentés à l&#x2019;Acad.<lb break="yes"/>des Sciences, Tom. iii. p. 81.</note> I<lb break="yes"/>supply below the results of that combination along the chain of the Py-<lb break="no"/>renees, and of that triangulation which traverses Holland, Germany, and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="334" facs="#f0012"/> France, from Amsterdam to Marseilles.<note place="foot" n="*">Taken from a Note which the Commandant M. Delcros has been so kind as<lb break="yes"/>give me.</note> Geographers and natural phi-<lb break="no"/>losophers who do not rest satisfied with vague approximative methods,<lb break="yes"/>know not how much the admirable labours of M. Delcros have advanced<lb break="yes"/>at once hypsometry, geod&#x00E6;sy, and barometrical mensuration.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p><choice><sic>&#x201C;</sic><corr type="editorial"></corr></choice><hi rendition="#i">Comparison by the Pyrenees.</hi>&#x2014;Colonel Coraboeuf, starting from Fort<lb break="yes"/>St Ange, upon the shores of the Mediterranean near Perpignan, and<lb break="yes"/>from the Fort Socoa, near Bayonne, on the Atlantic, reached the sum-<lb break="no"/>mit of Crabère by four series of points, and found that this point is ele-<lb break="no" />vated&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Metres</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell rows="4" rendition="#rightBraced">From the<lb break="yes" />Mediterranean<lb break="yes"/>by</cell>
                        <cell>the Southern Series,</cell>
                        <cell>2633.37</cell>
                        <cell rows="4" rendition="#leftBraced">Mean = 2633.50 metres.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>the Northern . </cell>
                        <cell>2633.99</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>the Diagonals . </cell>
                        <cell>2633.87</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>the Diagonals . </cell>
                        <cell>2632.79</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell rows="4" rendition="#rightBraced">From the<lb break="yes"/>Atlantic<lb break="yes"/>by</cell>
                        <cell>the Southern Series,</cell>
                        <cell>2632.95</cell>
                        <cell rows="4" rendition="#leftBraced">Mean = 2632.77 metres.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>the Northern . </cell>
                        <cell>2632.02</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>the Diagonals . </cell>
                        <cell>2633.61</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>the Diagonals . </cell>
                        <cell>2632.49</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Difference of mean results = to the different levels of the two seas = 0.73 metres.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;This mean discordance in the level of the two seas, being within<lb break="yes"/>the limits of probable errors, it may be concluded that the mean levels<lb break="yes"/>are nearly identical.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>(b) <hi rendition="#i">Comparison through Germany and Holland.</hi>&#x2014;M. Delcros having mea-<lb break="no"/>sured a geod&#x00E6;sical chain from the Mediterranean to Darmstadt, by Stras-<lb break="no"/>burg and Geneva, found&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The height of the gallery of the tower of Darmstadt above the Mediterra-<lb break="no"/>nean, ...... metres </cell>
                        <cell>187.39</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Same height by German mensuration, above the Northern Ocean<lb break="yes"/>(Zuider-Zee), near Amsterdam, ... </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rendition="#u">187.30</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Whence it follows that the difference of the mean levels of the two<lb break="yes"/>seas, ....... </cell>
                        <cell>= + 0.09</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>By the parallel of Bourges from the ocean to Noirmoutiers, mea-<lb break="no"/>sured by Colonel Coraboeuf, the difference is, .. </cell>
                        <cell>= + 0.30</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Colonel Broussaud, by the mean parallel proceeding from the ocean<lb break="yes"/>to Cordouan, near Saintes, is .... </cell>
                        <cell>= + 0.52</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;These discordances being all comprised within the limits of the pro-<lb break="no"/>bable errors of geod&#x00E6;sical levellings, prove that no difference exists in<lb break="yes"/>the sensible level between the surfaces of equilibrium of these two seas.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We have still to add, and also from a note supplied by M. Delcros,<lb break="yes" />some considerations concerning the rise which recently is alleged to have<lb break="yes"/>taken place in the northern part of the Adriatic Gulf. <choice><sic>&#x201C;</sic><corr type="editorial"></corr></choice>The Command-<lb break="no"/>ant Delcros and Captain Choppin having connected the geod&#x00E6;sical<lb break="yes"/>operations executed in France and Switzerland with those effected in<lb break="yes"/>Bavaria by General Bonne, have determined the altitudes of Hornliberg,<lb break="yes"/>Rigiberg, &#x0026;c., above the level of the Mediterranean. The Swiss en-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="335" facs="#f0013"/> gineers have thus connected these points with those determined in the<lb break="yes"/>Tyrol by the Austrian engineers, so furnishing the following results,<lb break="yes"/>starting from the Mediterranean:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Metres.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Metres.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Altitude of Kumenberg above the Mediter-<lb break="no"/>ranean at Marseilles, ...</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#leftBraced">= 670.00</cell>
                        <cell rows="2" rendition="#leftBraced">Difference </cell>
                        <cell rows="2">= 7.63</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The Austrians give it, above the Adriatic,</cell>
                        <cell>= 662.00</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Altitude of Frastenzersand above the Medi-<lb break="no"/>terranean at Marseilles, ...</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#leftBraced">= 1636.33</cell>
                        <cell rows="2" rendition="#leftBraced">Difference </cell>
                        <cell rows="2">= 8.75</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The Austrians make it, above the Adriatic,</cell>
                        <cell>= 1627.58</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Altitude of the Fundelkopf above the Medi-<lb break="no"/>terranean at Marseilles, ...</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#leftBraced">= 2403.80</cell>
                        <cell rows="2" rendition="#leftBraced">Difference </cell>
                        <cell rows="2">
                            <hi rendition="#u">= 9.12</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The Austrians give it, above the Adriatic,</cell>
                        <cell>= 2394.68</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Hence the mean height of the Adriatie Gulf above the Mediterra-<lb break="no"/>nean at Marseilles, ....... </cell>
                        <cell>8.50</cell>
                    </row>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The Swiss engineers make it in reference to the ocean, .. </cell>
                        <cell>= 7.63</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;M. Delcros is persuaded that this difference between the levels<lb break="yes"/>cannot exist. Admitting a filling of the Adriatic, from the feeble tides<lb break="yes"/>which occur, and from the counter-current that is well known, these<lb break="yes"/>effects together cannot amount to 7 or 8 metres. He has been assured<lb break="yes"/>that the Swiss engineers, in discussing the partial results inserted in the<lb break="yes"/>hypsometry of Austria by Colonel Fallon, have been led to reduce this<lb break="yes" />pretended difference of level from 8 metres to 2. He is not yet informed<lb break="yes"/>upon what grounds this reduction is made; but he takes the liberty of<lb break="yes"/>expressing a hope that the Austrian Government will direct that the<lb break="yes"/>most southern points of Switzerland and Bavaria shall be linked in a<lb break="yes"/>manner more satisfactory and accurate with the Adriatic.&#x201D;<note place="foot" n="*">M. Delcros supplies the following results of the correction of the triangles of<lb break="yes" />Bavaria:&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Metres.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1. Summit of the tower of Notre-Dame of Munich, .. = </cell>
                                <cell>615.67</cell>
                            </row>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Pavement of the same church, ..... = </cell>
                                <cell>518.67</cell>
                            </row>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <row>
                                <cell>2. Peissenberg, at the surface, pavement of the church, .. = </cell>
                                <cell>985.14</cell>
                            </row>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <row>
                                <cell>3. Benedictenwand, summit of the mountain, ... = </cell>
                                <cell>1798.96</cell>
                            </row>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <row>
                                <cell>4. Wendelstein, summit of the mountain, .... </cell>
                                <cell>1843.60</cell>
                            </row>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <row>
                                <cell cols="2">
                                    <hi rendition="#et">(<hi rendition="#i">Note, September</hi> 1841.)</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It has appeared to me important to collect in this work all that we<lb break="yes"/>know at the present time, concerning the <hi rendition="#i" >comparative hydraulic hypsometry</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>of the waters which belong, and those which do not belong, to the same<lb break="yes"/>surface of level. Physical geography can make progress only by grasp-<lb break="no"/>ing the results already obtained, by discussing the bases of numerical<lb break="yes"/>elements, and mounting up to those general views which alone give dig-<lb break="no"/>nity and life to the sciences.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">From Humboldt&#x2019;s <hi rendition="#i">Asie Centrale</hi>, 1843, vol. ii., p. 301.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 