<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p></p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="" facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Isthmus of Panama.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;In the French Chamber of Depu-<lb/>ties, a short time since, M. Guizot, in answer to some ob-<lb/>servations throwing doubts upon the practicability of the pro-<lb/>posed works for piercing the Isthmus of Panama, read the<lb/>following letter from the Baron de Humboldt to one of the<lb/>heads of the parties interested in the proposed operation.<lb/>&#x201C;I learn, with regret, that you are not further advanced in<lb/>your important enterprise than you were when I had last the<lb/>pleasure of seeing you in Paris. For the last twenty-five<lb/>years, the project of a communication between the two seas,<lb/>either by the Isthmus of Panama, by Lake Nicaragua, or by<lb/>the Isthmus of Capica, has been proposed, and topographically debated;<lb/>and yet no beginning has been made. I should<lb/>have thought that the British Embassy would have found a<lb/>means of inspiring confidence in the proposal to send a scien-<lb/>tific man (an engineer) for the purpose of examining the<lb/>valley which seperates the two seas, through which the canal<lb/>might be dug to the western side of the Port of Chagres. Be<lb/>assured that those persons who use the authority of my name<lb/>in support of the opinion that the two seas have different<lb/>levels, do so only to excuse themselves from engaging in the<lb/>enterprise.&#x201D; The Minister also read an extract from a docu-<lb/>ment addressed to the Academy of Sciences, by M. Warden,<lb/>a distinguished American citizen, long consul for that country<lb/>in Paris:&#x2014;&#x201C;The cutting necessary to unite the two seas, by<lb/>means of the three rivers, Vino-Tinto, Bernardino, and Farren,<lb/>is but twelve and a half miles in length. The fall will be<lb/>regulated by four double locks of 45 mètres long. The canal<lb/>will be altogether 49 miles in extent, 43 mètres 50 centimètres<lb/>wide at the surface, 17 mètres 50 centimètres at the bottom,<lb/>and having a depth of 6 mètres 50 centimètres. It will be<lb/>navigable for vessels of from 1,000 to 1,400 tons burthen. The<lb/>rivers, in those portions of them where they have from 2&#x00BD; to<lb/>4&#x00BD; mètres of water, will serve for the canal, by deepening to<lb/>6&#x00BD; mètres; and the water will be maintained at that height<lb/>by two guard-locks. All the materials necessary for the con-<lb/>struction of the canal are found on the soil which it has to<lb/>traverse; and the total cost has been estimated at 2,778,615<lb/>dollars, including the price of four steam-boats, and two iron<lb/>bridges, 46 mètres long, and opening for the passage of ships.&#x201D;</p></div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>