<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="128" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Singular Ceremony of the Native Mexicans.</hi></head><lb/>
        <p>&#x2014;On the last day of the great cycle (of the Mexicans<lb/>consisting of 52 years) the sacred fires were extinguished<lb/>in all their temples and dwellings, and the people devoted<lb/>themselves to prayer, At the approach of night no one<lb/>dared to kindle a flame&#x2014;their vessels of clay were<lb/>broken, their garments rent, and whatever was precious<lb/>destroyed as <choice> <sic>useles</sic> <corr type="editorial">useless</corr> </choice>, in the approaching run. In this<lb/>mad superstition, pregnant women became the objects of<lb/>peculiar horror to men; they covered their faces with<lb/>paper masks, they imprisoned them in their granaries;<lb/>and believed that, when the final catastrophe occurred,<lb/>these <choice> <sic>unfor unate</sic> <corr type="editorial">unfortunate</corr> </choice> females, transformed into tigers, would<lb/>join with the demons and avenge themselves for the <choice> <sic>i</sic> <corr type="editorial">in</corr> </choice>- <lb/>justice and cruelty of men. As soon as it became dark<lb/>on that awful evening, a grand and solemn procession of<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i" >new fire</hi> was commenced. The priests put on the<lb/>garments of the various idols, and, followed by the sad<lb/>and bewildered people, ascended a hill about six miles<lb/>from the city. This mournful march was called the<lb/>&#x201C;procession of the gods,&#x201D; and was supposed to be their<lb/>final departure from their temples and altars. When the<lb/>solemn train had reached the top of the hill, it rested<lb/>until the <hi rendition="#i">pleiades</hi> ascended the zenith, and then com-<lb/>menced the sacrifice of a human victim, stretched on the<lb/>stone of sacrifice, and covered on the breast with a<lb/>wooden shield which the chief priest <hi rendition="#i">inflamed by friction</hi>.<lb/>The victim received the fatal blow, or wound, from the<lb/>usual obsidian knife of sacrifice; and, as soon as life was<lb/>extinct, the machine to <choice> <sic>cre te</sic> <corr type="editorial">create</corr> </choice> fire was put in <choice> <sic>mo ion</sic> <corr type="editorial">motion</corr> </choice> on<lb/>the board over his bosom. When the blaze had kindled,<lb/>the body was thrown on an immense pile, the flames of<lb/>which instantly ascended into the air, and denoted the<lb/>promise of the sun&#x2019;s return! All who had been unable<lb/>to join in the sacred procession of the departing gods had<lb/>climbed to the terraces of houses and the tops of<lb/>Teocallis, whence they strained their eyes toward the<lb/>spot where the hoped-for flame was to appear, and, as soon<lb/>as it burst upon their sight, hailed it with joyful shouts<lb/>and acclamations, as a token of the benevolence of the<lb/>gods and the preservation of their race for another<lb/>cycle. Runners, placed at regular distances from each<lb/>other, held aloft torches of resinous pine, by which they<lb/>transferred the new fire to each other, and carried it<lb/>from village to village, throughout the empire, depositing<lb/>it anew in every temple, whence it was again distributed<lb/>to the dwellings of the people. When the sun arose<lb/>above the horizon on the succeeding day, the shouting<lb/>and joy were renewed by the people in the city, toward<lb/>which at that moment the priests and crowd took up the<lb/>line of returning march. It was the restoration of their<lb/>gods to their deserted shrines! The imprisoned women<lb/>were immediately released; the whole population clad<lb/>themselves in new garments; the temples were purified<lb/>and whitened, and everything that was requisite for<lb/>domestic comfort, splendour, or necessity, was renewed<lb/>under the promise of renewed life and protection from<lb/>the gods. &#x2014; <hi rendition="#i">Baron Humboldt.</hi></p>        
</div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
