<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<dateline>MAY 23, 1846.</dateline><lb/><pb n="352" facs="#f0001" />
<cb/>
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Singular Ceremony of the Native Mexi-<lb/>cans.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;On the last day of the great cycle (of the<lb/>Mexicans, consisting of 52 years) the
                    sacred fires were<lb/>extinguished in all their temples and dwellings;
                    and<lb/>the people devoted themselves to prayer. At the<lb/>approach of night no
                    one dared to kindle a flame:<lb/><cb/> their vessels of clay were broken, their
                    garments rent,<lb/>and whatever was precious destroyed as useless, in<lb/>the
                    approaching ruin. In this mad superstition, preg-<lb/>women became the objects
                    of peculiar horror to<lb/>men. They covered their faces with paper masks;
                    they<lb/>imprisoned them in their granaries; and believed that,<lb/>when the
                    final catastrophe occurred, these unfortunate<lb/>females, transformed into
                    tigers, would join with the<lb/>demons, and avenge themselves for the injustice
                    and<lb/>cruelty of men. As soon as it became dark, on that<lb/>awful evening, a
                    grand and solemn procession of the<lb/>&#x201C;new fire&#x201D; was commenced.
                    The priests put on the<lb/>garments of the various idols, and, followed by
                    the<lb/>sad and bewildered people, ascended a hill about six<lb/>miles from the
                    city. This mournful march was called<lb/>&#x201C;the procession of the
                    gods,&#x201D; and was supposed to be<lb/>their final departure from their
                    temples and altars.<lb/>When the solemn train had reached the top of the
                    hill,<lb/>it rested until the pleiades ascended the zenith; and<lb/>then
                    commenced the sacrifice of a human victim,<lb/>stretched on the stone of
                    sacrifice, and covered on the<lb/>breast with a wooden shield, which the chief
                    priest<lb/>inflamed by friction. The victim received the fatal<lb/>blow, or
                    wound, from the usual obsidian knife of sacri-<lb/>fice; and, as soon as life
                    was extinct, the machine to<lb/>create fire was put in motion on the board over
                    his<lb/>bosom. When the blaze had kindled, the body was<lb/>thrown on an immense
                    pile, the flames of which<lb/>instantly ascended into the air, and denoted
                    the<lb/>promise of the sun&#x2019;s return. All who had been unable<lb/>to join
                    in the sacred procession of the departing gods<lb/>had climbed to the terraces
                    of houses and the tops of<lb/>Teocallis, whence they strained their eyes toward
                    the<lb/>spot where the hoped-for flame was to appear; and,<lb/>as soon as it
                    burst upon their sight, hailed it with<lb/>joyful shouts and acclamations, as a
                    token of the<lb/>benevolence of the gods and the preservation of their<lb/>race
                    for another cycle. Runners, placed at regular<lb/>distances from each other,
                    held aloft torches of resi-<lb/>nous pine, by which they transferred the new
                    fire to<lb/>each other, and carried it from village to village,<lb/>throughout
                    the empire, depositing it anew in every<lb/>temple, whence it was again
                    distributed to the dwel-<lb/>lings of the people. When the sun arose above
                    the<lb/>horizon, on the succeeding day, the shouting and joy<lb/>were renewed by
                    the people in the city; toward which,<lb/>at that moment, the priests and crowd
                    took up the<lb/>line of returning march. It was the restoration of<lb/>their
                    gods to their deserted shrines. The imprisoned<lb/>women were immediately
                    released, the whole popu-<lb/>lation clad themselves in new garments, the
                    temples<lb/>were purified and whitened; and everything that was<lb/>requisite
                    for domestic comfort, splendour, or neces-<lb/>sity, was renewed under the
                    promise of renewed life<lb/>and protection from the gods. &#x2014; <hi
                        rendition="#i">Baron Humboldt.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
