<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/111602781X">
                        <surname>Müller-Tamm</surname>
                        <forename>Jutta</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-21" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision" >Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-10-21" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision" >Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Singular Ceremony of Native Mexicans.</hi>
                </head>
                <p>&#x2014;On<lb break="yes"/>the last day of the great cycle (of the Mexican constitu-<lb break="no"/>tion of fifty-two years), the sacred fires were extinguish-<lb break="no"/>ed in all their temples and dwellings, and the people de-<lb break="no"/>voted themselves to prayer. At the approach of night no<lb break="yes"/>one dared to kindle a flame&#x2014;their vessels of clay were<lb break="yes"/>broken, their garments rent, and whatever was precious<lb break="yes" />destroyed as useless in the approaching ruin. In this<lb break="yes"/>mad superstition, pregnant women became the objects of<lb break="yes"/>peculiar horror to men; they covered their faces with pa-<lb break="no"/>per masks, they imprisoned them in their grenaries; and<lb break="yes"/>believed that when the final catastrophe occurred, these<lb break="yes" />unfortunate females, transformed into tigers, would join<lb break="yes"/>with the demons and avenge themselves for the injustice<lb break="yes"/>and cruelty of men. As soon as it became dark on that<lb break="yes"/>awful evening, a grand and solemn procession of the new<lb break="yes"/>fire was commenced. The priests put on the garments<lb break="yes"/>of the various idols, followed by the sad and bewildered<lb break="yes"/>people, ascended the hill about six miles from the city.<lb break="yes"/>This mournful march was called the &#x201C;procession of the<lb break="yes"/>gods,&#x201D; and was supposed to be their final departure from<lb break="yes"/>their temples and altars. When the solemn train had<lb break="yes"/>reached the top of the hill, it rested until the <hi rendition="#i">pleiades</hi> as-<lb break="no"/>cended the zenith, and then commenced the sacrifice of a<lb break="yes" />human victim, stretched on the stone of sacrifice, and<lb break="yes"/>covered on the breast with a wooden shield which the<lb break="yes"/>chief priest <hi rendition="#i">inflamed by friction.</hi> The victim received<lb break="yes"/>the fatal blow, or wound, from the usual obsidian knife<lb break="yes"/>of sacrifice: and, as soon as life was extinct, the machine<lb break="yes"/>to create fire was put in motion on the board over his<lb break="yes"/>bosom. When the blaze had kindled, the body was<lb break="yes"/>thrown on an immense pile, the flames of which instantly<lb break="yes"/>ascended into the air, and denoted the promise of the<lb break="yes"/>sun&#x2019;s return! All who had been unable to join in the sa-<lb break="no" />cred procession of the departing gods, had climbed to the<lb break="yes"/>terraces of houses and the <choice><sic>toms</sic><corr type="editorial">tops</corr></choice> of Teocallis, whence they<lb break="yes"/>strained their eyes towards the spot where the hoped-for<lb break="yes"/>flame was to appear, and as soon as it burst upon their<lb break="yes"/>sight, hailed it with joyful shouts and acclamations, as a<lb break="yes"/>token of the benevolence of the gods and the preservation<lb break="yes"/>of their race for another cycle. Runners, placed at re-<lb break="no"/>gular distances from each other, held aloft torches of re-<lb break="no"/>sinous pine, by which they transferred the new fire to<lb break="yes"/>each other, and carried from village to village, through-<lb break="no"/>out the empire, depositing it anew in every temple, whence<lb break="yes"/>it was again distributed to the dwellings of the people.<lb break="yes"/>When the sun arose above the horizon on the succeeding<lb break="yes"/>day, the shouting and joy were renewed by the people in<lb break="yes"/>the city, toward which at that moment the priest and<lb break="yes"/>crowd took up the line of returning march. It was the<lb break="yes"/>restoration of their gods to their deserted shrines, the<lb break="yes"/>imprisoned women were immediately released; the whole<lb break="yes"/>population clad themselves in new garments; temples<lb break="yes"/>were purified and whitened, and everything that was re-<lb break="no"/>quisite for domestic comfort, splendour or necessity, was<lb break="yes"/>renewed under the promise of renewed life and protection<lb break="yes"/>from the gods.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Baron Humboldt.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 