<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On the known Thickness of the Crust of the Earth</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:11</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VI.62</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1845-On_the_known-1-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-1-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-7-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-8-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-9-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos: A General Survey of the physical phenomena of the universe&lt;/i&gt;, Bd. 1, London: Hippolyte Baillière 1845, S. 418–420.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Cosmos: A sketch of a physical description of the universe&lt;/i&gt;, übersetzt von Elise C. Otté, London: Henry G. Bohn 1849, S. 148–150. (Abweichende Übersetzung.)</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos. Entwurf einer physischen Weltbeschreibung&lt;/i&gt;, Band 1, Stuttgart und Tübingen: J. G. Cotta 1845, S. 416–419.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On the known Thickness of the Crust of the Earth</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1845</date>
          <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal&lt;/i&gt; 39:78 (Oktober 1845), S. 397–400.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="397" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>9. <hi rendition="#i">On the known Thickness of the Crust of the Earth.</hi>
                </head>
                <p>&#x2014;It is proper<lb break="yes"/>to distinguish between the <hi rendition="#i">absolute</hi> depth to which man has penetrated<lb break="yes"/>in his mining operations, or the depth from the surface of the earth<lb break="yes"/>at the place where the operations are carried on, and the <hi rendition="#i">relative</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="398" facs="#f0002"/> depth, <hi rendition="#i">i. e.,</hi> the depth below the level of the sea. The greatest re-<lb break="no"/>lative depth that has been reached is, perhaps, the bore at New<lb break="yes"/>Salzwerk, Minden, in Prussia. In June 1844, it was exactly 1844&#x00BD;<lb break="yes"/>Parisian feet; the absolute depth was, however, 2094&#x00BD; Par. feet.<lb break="yes" />The temperature of the water in the deepest bore was 32&#x00B7;7° C.<lb break="yes"/>(90&#x00B7;8° F.) which, assuming 9&#x00B7;6° C. as the mean temperature of the<lb break="yes"/>air, gives a rise of 1&#x00B7;6° for 29&#x00B7;6 metres (upwards of 97&#x00B7;6 feet Eng-<lb break="no"/>lish). The Artesian well of Grenelle, at Paris, is only 1683 feet<lb break="yes"/>in absolute depth. From the accounts of the missionary Imbert<lb break="yes"/>from China, the depth of our Artesian wells is far surpassed by that<lb break="yes" />of the fire-spring, Ho-tsing, which yields inflammable gas, employed<lb break="yes"/>in salt boiling. In the Chinese province Szü-tschuan, these fire-<lb break="no"/>springs are said very commonly to reach a depth of from 1800 to<lb break="yes"/>2000 feet; and at Tseu-lieu-tsing (place of perpetual flux) a Ho-<lb break="no"/>tsing bored with the rod in the year 1812, is reported to extend to<lb break="yes"/>the depth of 3000 feet (Humboldt, Asie Centrale, t. ii., p. 521<lb break="yes"/>and 525; Annales de l&#x2019;Association de la Propagation de la Foi,<lb break="yes"/>1829, No. 16, p. 369.) The relative depth attained at Monte Massi,<lb break="yes"/>in Tuscany, south from Volterra, according to Matteucci, is about<lb break="yes"/>1175 feet. The bore at New Salzwerk approaches very nearly in<lb break="yes"/>relative depth the coal pit at Apendale, Newcastle-under-Lyme<lb break="yes" />(Staffordshire). There the works are carried on 725 yards, or 2045<lb break="yes"/>French feet, under the surface (Th. Smith, The Miner&#x2019;s Guide,<lb break="yes"/>1836, p. 160). Unfortunately, the height of the ground above the<lb break="yes"/>level of the sea is not accurately ascertained. The relative depth<lb break="yes"/>of the Monkwearmouth pit, near Newcastle-on-Tyne, is only 1404<lb break="yes"/>feet (Phillips, Philos. Mag. vol. v., 1834, p. 446); that of the<lb break="yes"/>Esperance pit, at Liege, 1271; and that of the lately-worked pit<lb break="yes"/>Marihaye, at Val St. Lambert, is 1157 feet. The greatest absolute<lb break="yes"/>depths to which man has penetrated are in mines that are either<lb break="yes"/>among lofty mountains or in mountain-valleys, so much raised above<lb break="yes"/>the sea level, that this has either not been reached at all, or has only<lb break="yes" />been surpassed by a very small quantity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Eselschacht at Kuttenberg, Bohemia, before it was abandoned,<lb break="yes" />had reached the enormous depth of 3545 feet (Schmidt, Berggesetze,<lb break="yes"/>Bd. 1, S. 32). At St Daniel, and at Geist, on the Röhrerbühel,<lb break="yes"/>the works, in the 16th century, were 2916 feet deep. A drawing of<lb break="yes"/>these workings of the year 1539 is still preserved. (Joseph Von<lb break="yes"/>Sperges, Tyroler Bergwerks-Geschichte, S. 121. See also Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt, Gutachten über Herantreibung des Meissner Stollens in die<lb break="yes"/>Freiberger Erzrevier, published in Herder über den jetzt begon-<lb break="no"/>nenen Erbstollen, 1838, S. 124). It may be imagined that informa-<lb break="no"/>tion of the extraordinary depth of the workings at Röhrerbühel had<lb break="yes"/>reached England at an early period, for in Gilbert&#x2019;s work, De Mag-<lb break="no"/>nete, I find the statement that man had penetrated from 2400 to<lb break="yes"/>3000 feet into the bowels of the earth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The absolute depth of the mines in the Saxon Erzgebirge are 1824<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="399" facs="#f0003"/> and 1714 feet; the relative depths of these respectively are only<lb break="yes"/>626 and 260. The absolute depth of the rich workings in Joach-<lb break="no"/>imsthal, Bohemia, is 1919 feet; but taking the height of the surface<lb break="yes"/>upon Dechen&#x2019;s estimate at 2250 feet above the level of the sea, it is<lb break="yes"/>obvious that there the sea level has not even been attained. In the<lb break="yes"/>Harz, the workings in the Samson pit, at Andreasberg, are carried<lb break="yes"/>on at the absolute depth of 2062 feet. In Old Spanish America,<lb break="yes"/>I know of no deeper mines than those of Valenciana, near Guanax-<lb break="no"/>uato, Mexico; I found the Planes de San Bernard 1582 feet deep;<lb break="yes"/>but this mine does not reach the level of the sea by 5592 feet. If<lb break="yes" />we compare the depth of the old Kuttenberg works (a depth which<lb break="yes" />exceeds the height of the Brocken, and only falls short of that of<lb break="yes"/>Etna by 200 feet) with the heights of the loftiest buildings that<lb break="yes"/>have been reared by man (the Pyramid of Cheops and the Minster<lb break="yes"/>at Strasburg), we find that the mines are to these in proportion of<lb break="yes"/>8 to 1.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Basin-shaped curved strata, which dip down on one hand and rise<lb break="yes" />at a measureable distance, although not penetrated by mines or<lb break="yes" />shafts, still suffice to give us accurate information of the constitution<lb break="yes"/>of the crust of the earth at great depths from the surface. I have<lb break="yes"/>to thank the excellent geologist M. Von Dechen for the following:&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>He writes to me, &#x201C;The depth of the coal measures at Mont St Gilles,<lb break="yes"/>Liege, which our friend M. Von Oeynhausen has estimated at 3650<lb break="yes"/>feet below the surface, must lie at the depth of 3250 feet below the<lb break="yes"/>sea level, inasmuch as Mont St Gilles is certainly not 400 feet<lb break="yes"/>high; and the coal basin at Mons lies fully 1750 feet deeper. These<lb break="yes"/>depressions, however, are trifling when compared with that of the<lb break="yes"/>coal strata of the Saar-Revier (Saarbrücken). After repeated trials,<lb break="yes"/>have found that the lowest coal strata known in the country of Dutt-<lb break="no" />weiler near Bettingen, north-eastward from Saarlouis, dip 19,406,<lb break="yes"/>and 20,656 feet under the level of the sea.&#x201D; This conclusion ex-<lb break="no"/>ceeds by 8000 feet the estimate which I have given in the text of<lb break="yes"/>Cosmos for the basin of Devonian strata. These Belgian coal mea-<lb break="no"/>sures, therefore, lie as far below the level of the sea as Chimborazo<lb break="yes"/>rises above it, at a depth where the temperature of the earth must<lb break="yes"/>be 224° C. (435° F.). From the highest summit of the Himalaya<lb break="yes"/>to the bottom of this basin, containing vegetable remains of the<lb break="yes"/>primeval world, we have a perpendicular depth of 45,000 feet, <hi rendition="#i">i. e.,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{435}</formula> of the semi-diameter of the earth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have thought it important thus to bring together these data in<lb break="yes" />relation to the absolute and relative depths that have been reached<lb break="yes"/>by man, a subject in connection with which many errors have been<lb break="yes"/>constantly committed, principally, as it seems, through faulty reduc-<lb break="no"/>tions of the measurements from one standard to another. On pro-<lb break="no"/>ceeding eastward from Jerusalem toward the Dead Sea, a prospect is<lb break="yes"/>gained which, according to our present hypsometrical knowledge, is<lb break="yes"/>unparalleled on the face of the earth. There, on approaching the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="400" facs="#f0004"/> chasm in which the Jordan flows, we advance, in open day, along<lb break="yes"/>beds of rock, which, according to Bertou&#x2019;s and Russegger&#x2019;s barome-<lb break="no"/>trical levellings, lie 1300 feet in perpendicular depth below the level<lb break="yes"/>of the Mediterranean Sea. (<hi rendition="#i">Vide</hi> Humboldt, Asie Centrale, t. ii.<lb break="yes" />p. 323.)&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Cosmos</hi>, No. iv. p. 418. <hi rendition="#i">By Alex. Von Humboldt.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 