<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<dateline>JUNE, 1847.</dateline><lb/><pb n="194" facs="#f0001" />
<milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<cb/>
<div n="1"><head>EARTHQUAKES.</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">Before</hi> we quit this great phenomenon,<lb/>which has been considered not
                    so much in<lb/>its individual, as in its general, physical, and<lb/>geognostical
                    relations, we must advert to the<lb/>cause of the indescribable, deep, and
                    quite<lb/>peculiar impression which the first earth-<lb/>quake we experience
                    makes upon us, even<lb/>when it is unaccompanied by subterranean<lb/>noises. The
                    impression here is not, I believe,<lb/>the consequence of any recollection of
                    de-<lb/>structive catastrophes presented to our ima-<lb/>gination by narratives
                    of historical events:<lb/>what seizes upon us so wonderfully is the<lb/>disabuse
                    of that innate faith in the fixity<lb/>of the solid and sure-set foundations of
                    the<lb/>earth. From early childhood we are habitu-<lb/>ated to the contrast
                    between the mobile<lb/>element, water, and the immobility of the<lb/>soil on
                    which we stand. All the evidences<lb/>of our senses have confirmed this
                    belief.<lb/>But when suddenly the ground begins to<lb/>rock beneath us, the
                    feeling of an unknown,<lb/>mysterious power in nature coming into<lb/>action,
                    and shaking the solid globe, arises in<lb/>the mind. The illusion of the whole
                    of our<lb/>earlier life is annihilated in an instant. We<lb/>are undeceived as
                    to the repose of nature;<lb/>we feel ourselves transported to the realm,<lb/>and
                    made subject to the empire, of destructive<lb/>unknown powers. Every sound, the
                    slightest<lb/>rustle in the air, sets attention on the stretch.<lb/>We no longer
                    trust the earth upon which we<lb/>stand. The unusual in the
                    phenomenon<lb/>throws the same anxious unrest and alarm<lb/>over the lower
                    animals. Swine and dogs are<lb/>particularly affected by it; and the
                    very<lb/><cb/> crocodiles of the Orinoco, otherwise as dumb<lb/>as our little
                    lizards, leave the shaken bed of<lb/>the stream, and run bellowing into the
                    woods.<lb/>To man, the earthquake presents itself as an<lb/>all-pervading
                    unlimited something. We<lb/>can remove from an active crater; from
                    the<lb/>stream of lava that is pouring down upon<lb/>our dwelling we can escape;
                    with the earth-<lb/>quake we feel that whithersoever we fly we are<lb/>still on
                    the hearth of destruction. Such a<lb/>mental condition, though evoked in our
                    very<lb/>innermost nature, is not, however, of long<lb/>duration. When a series
                    of lighter shocks<lb/>occur in a district one after another, every<lb/>trace of
                    alarm soon vanishes among the in-<lb/>habitants. On the rainless coasts of
                    Peru,<lb/>nothing is known of hail, nor of explosions of<lb/>lightning and
                    rolling thunder in the bosom<lb/>of the atmosphere. The subterraneous
                    noise<lb/>that accompanies the earthquake, comes<lb/>in lieu of the thunder of
                    the clouds. Use<lb/>and wont for a series of years, and the very<lb/>prevalent
                    opinion that dangerous earthquakes<lb/>are only to be apprehended two or
                    three<lb/>times in the course of a century, lead the<lb/>inhabitants of Lima
                    scarcely to think more<lb/>of a slight shock of an earthquake than
                    is<lb/>thought of a hail-storm in the temperate<lb/>zone. &#x2014; <hi
                        rendition="#i">Cosmos: a Survey of the General<lb/>Physical History of the
                        Universe. By Alex-<lb/>ander von Humboldt.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
