<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On the Aurora Borealis</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:11</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VI.60</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1845-On_the_Aurora-1-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_Aurora-1-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_Aurora-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_Aurora-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_Aurora-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_Aurora-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_Aurora-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_Aurora-7-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_Aurora-8-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos: A General Survey of the physical phenomena of the universe&lt;/i&gt;, Bd. 1, London: Hippolyte Baillière 1845, 201–211.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Cosmos: A sketch of a physical description of the universe&lt;/i&gt;, übersetzt von Elise C. Otté, London: Henry G. Bohn 1849, S. 187–197. (Nicht dieselbe Übersetzung.)</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos. Entwurf einer physischen Weltbeschreibung&lt;/i&gt;, Band 1, Stuttgart und Tübingen: J. G. Cotta 1845, S. 198–208.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On the Aurora Borealis</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1845</date>
          <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Practical Mechanic and Engineer’s Magazine&lt;/i&gt; 1 (20. Dezember 1845), S. 64–66.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="64" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>ON THE AURORA BOREALIS.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#k">By Alex. Von Humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Terrestrial</hi> magnetism, the electro-dynamic forces which have<lb break="yes"/>been calculated by the able <choice><sic>Ampére</sic><corr type="editorial">Ampère</corr></choice>, stands at the same time in<lb break="yes"/>intimate relationship with the Earth or Northern-Lights [Aurora<lb break="yes"/>borealis], as with the internal and external temperature of our<lb break="yes"/>globe, whose magnetic poles must be regarded as poles of cold.<lb break="yes"/>If Halley, some 128 years ago, gave it out as a mere bold conjec-<lb break="no"/>ture, that the northern light was a magnetic phenomenon, Fara-<lb break="no"/>day&#x2019;s brilliant discovery of the evolution of light through magnetic<lb break="yes"/>power has raised that conjecture to the rank of an empirical cer-<lb break="no"/>tainty. There are heralds or harbingers of the northern lights.<lb break="yes"/>In the course of the day on which the lights are to appear, irregu-<lb break="no"/>lar horary movements of the magnetic needle usually indicate an<lb break="yes" />interruption of equilibrium in the distribution of the terrestrial<lb break="yes"/>magnetism. When this disturbance has attained a great intensity,<lb break="yes"/>the equilibrium of the distribution is restored by a discharge, ac-<lb break="no"/>companied with an evolution of light. &#x201C;The northern light itself<lb break="yes"/>is not, therefore, to be regarded as an external cause of the dis-<lb break="no"/>turbance, but rather as a terrestrial activity raised to the pitch of<lb break="yes"/>a luminous phenomenon, one of the sides of which is the light, the<lb break="yes"/>other the oscillations of the needle.&#x201D;<note place="foot" n="*">The dipping needle comports itself very nearly as an atmospherical<lb break="yes" />electrometer, whose difference in like manner shows the increased tension<lb break="yes"/>of the electricity before it <choice><sic>h s</sic><corr type="editorial">has</corr></choice> risen to such a height that a spark is elicited.<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i" >Dove.</hi>
                    </note> The splendid phenomenon<lb break="yes"/>of coloured northern lights is the act of discharge, the conclusion<lb break="yes"/>of a magnetic storm; in the same way as, in the electrical storm,<lb break="yes"/>an evolution of light&#x2014;lightning&#x2014;indicates the restoration of the<lb break="yes" />disturbed equilibrium in the distribution of electricity. The elec-<lb break="no"/>trical storm is usually limited to a small space, beyond which the<lb break="yes"/>state of the electricity remains unchanged. The magnetic storm,<lb break="yes"/>on the contrary, reveals its influence on the march of the needle<lb break="yes"/>over large portions of continents, as Arago first observed, and far<lb break="yes"/>from the place where the developement of light is visible. It is not<lb break="yes"/>improbable that, as in the case of heavily charged and threatening<lb break="yes"/>clouds, and of frequent transitions of the atmospheric electricity<lb break="yes"/>into opposite states, it does not always come to discharges by<lb break="yes"/>lightning, so also may magnetic storms produce great disturbances<lb break="yes"/>in the horary motions of the needle over extensive circles, without<lb break="yes"/>there being any necessity for explosions, for luminous effusions<lb break="yes"/>from the pole to the equator, or from one pole to another, in order<lb break="yes"/>to restore the equilibrium.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>He who would have all the particulars of the phenomenon em-<lb break="no"/>braced in one picture, should have the origin and course of a com-<lb break="no"/>plete appearance of the northern lights set before him. Deep on<lb break="yes"/>the horizon, nearly in the situation where it is intersected by the<lb break="yes" />magnetic meridian, the heaven, up to this moment clear, grows<lb break="yes" />black. There is a kind of hazy bank or screen produced, which<lb break="yes" />rises gradually, and attains to an altitude of from 8 to 10 degrees.<lb break="yes"/>The colour of the dusky segment passes over into brown or violet.<lb break="yes"/>Stars arc visible in it, but they are seen as in a portion of the sky<lb break="yes"/>obscured with dense smoke. A broad bright luminous arc or seam,<lb break="yes"/>first white, then yellow, bounds the dusky segment; but as the<lb break="yes"/>brilliant bow arises later than the smoky-grey segment it is im-<lb break="no"/>possible, according to Argelander, to ascribe the latter to the<lb break="yes"/>effect of mere contrast with the bright luminous border. The<lb break="yes"/>highest point of the luminous arc, when it has been carefully mea-<lb break="no"/>sured, has usually been found to be not exactly in the magnetic<lb break="yes"/>meridian, but to vary between 5 and 18 degrees from it, towards<lb break="yes"/>the side on which the magnetic declination of the place of obser-<lb break="no"/>vation lies. In high northern latitudes, very near the north pole,<lb break="yes"/>the smoky-looking spherical segment appears less dark; sometimes<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> it is even entirely absent. In the situation, too, where the hori-<lb break="no"/>zontal force is least, the middle of the luminous arc is seen to depart<lb break="yes"/>farthest from the magnetic meridian.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The luminous bow, in constant motion, flickering and changing<lb break="yes"/>its form incessantly, sometimes remains visible for hours before<lb break="yes" />anything like rays and pencils of rays shoot from it, and rise to<lb break="yes"/>the zenith. The more intense the discharges of the northern<lb break="yes"/>lights, the more vividly do the colours play from violet and bluish-<lb break="maybe"/>white, through every shade and gradation, to green and purplish-<lb break="maybe"/>red. In our ordinary electricity produced by friction, in the same<lb break="yes"/>way, the spark first becomes coloured when the tension is high,<lb break="yes"/>and the explosion is violent. The magnetic fiery columns shoot<lb break="yes"/>up at one time singly from the luminous arch, even mingled with<lb break="yes"/>black rays, like thick smoke; at another, many columns arise<lb break="yes"/>simultaneously from several and opposite points of the horizon,<lb break="yes"/>and unite in a flickering sea of flame, to the splendour of which<lb break="yes"/>no description can do justice, and whose luminous waves assume<lb break="yes"/>another and a different shape at every instant. The intensity of<lb break="yes"/>the northern light is at times so great, that Lowenörn perceived<lb break="yes"/>its oscillations, in bright sunshine, on the 29th of January, 1786.<lb break="yes"/>The motion increases the brilliancy of the phenomenon. Around<lb break="yes"/>the point of the vault of heaven which corresponds with the direc-<lb break="no"/>tion of the dipping needle, the rays at length collect together, and<lb break="yes"/>form the corona or crown of the northern lights. This surrounds<lb break="yes"/>the summit, as it were, of a vast canopy, the dome of heaven,<lb break="yes"/>with the mild radiance of its streaming but not flickering rays.<lb break="yes"/>It is only in rare instances that the phenomenon proceeds the<lb break="yes"/>length of forming the corona completely. With its appearance,<lb break="yes"/>however, the whole is at an end. The rays now become rarer,<lb break="yes"/>shorter, less intensely coloured. The crown and the luminous<lb break="yes"/>arches break up. By and bye nothing but broad, motionless, and<lb break="yes"/>almost ashy-grey, pale gleaming fleecy masses, appear irregularly<lb break="yes"/>dispersed over the whole vault of heaven; these vanish in their<lb break="yes"/>turn, and before the last trace of the murky fuliginous segment,<lb break="yes"/>which still shows itself deeply on the horizon, has disappeared. Of<lb break="yes" />the whole brilliant spectacle, nothing at length remains but a<lb break="yes" />white delicate cloud, feathered at the edges, or broken up, as a<lb break="yes"/>cirro-cumulus, into small rounded masses or heaps, at equal dis-<lb break="no"/>tances.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This connection of the polar light with the most delicate cirrus-<lb break="maybe" />clouds, deserves to be particularly mentioned; inasmuch as it<lb break="yes" />shows us the electro-magnetic evolution of light as part of a<lb break="yes" />meteorological process. The terrestrial magnetism here manifests<lb break="yes"/>itself in its effects upon the atmosphere, in a condensation of the<lb break="yes"/>watery vapour which it holds dissolved. The observations, made<lb break="yes"/>in Iceland by Thienemann, who regards the cirro-cumulus, or<lb break="yes"/>divided fleecy clouds, as the substrate of the northern lights, have<lb break="yes"/>been confirmed in later times by Franklin and Richardson, near<lb break="yes"/>the North American magnetic pole, and by Admiral Wrangel, on<lb break="yes"/>the Siberian coasts of the icy sea. All observed &#x201C;that the<lb break="yes"/>northern lights sent forth the most brilliant rays when masses of<lb break="yes"/>cirro-stratus floated in the upper regions of the atmosphere; and<lb break="yes"/>when these were so thin that their presence was only known by<lb break="yes"/>the formation of a halo about the moon.&#x201D; These light clouds oc-<lb break="no"/>casionally arranged themselves, by day, in the same manner as<lb break="yes"/>the rays of the Aurora, and had the same effect as these in dis-<lb break="no"/>turbing the magnetic needle. After a grand nocturnal display of<lb break="yes"/>the northern lights, the same streaks of clouds that had been lu-<lb break="no"/>minous over night, were discovered in the morning arranged in<lb break="yes"/>the same manner.<note place="foot" n="*">Parry saw a great Aurora continue through the day. Something of the<lb break="yes"/>same kind was seen in England, 9th Sept., 1827. At mid-day a luminous<lb break="yes"/>arch, 20° high, and rays shooting from it, were perceived after rain, in a<lb break="yes"/>part of the heavens that had become clear.</note> The apparently converging polar zones of<lb break="yes"/>clouds (streaks of clouds, in the direction of the magnetic meri-<lb break="no"/>dian), which constantly attracted my attention in the course of<lb break="yes"/>my travels on the lofty platforms of Mexico, as well as in Northern<lb break="yes"/>Asia, belong apparently to the same group of diurnal phenomena.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;" xml:id="fn1-1" next="#fn1-2" >After my return from my American travels, I described the cirro-<lb break="maybe"/>cumulus cloud,&#x2014;when it appears very regularly divided into round masses<lb break="yes"/>as if by the agency of repulsive forces&#x2014;under the name of polar streaks<lb break="yes"/>(bandes polaires), because their perspective point of convergence is mostly<lb break="yes"/>in the magnetic meridian in the first instance, so that the parallel rows of<lb break="yes"/>cumuli follow the magnetic meridian. One peculiarity of this enigmatical<lb break="yes"/>phenomenon is, the swaying hither and thither of the point of convergence.<lb break="yes"/>Usually the streaks are only completely developed in one region of the<lb break="yes" />sky, and in their motion they are seen directed first from south to north,<lb break="yes"/>and then gradually veering round from east to west. I cannot ascribe the<lb break="yes"/>advance of the zones to any change in the quarter of the wind in the sup-</note>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="65" facs="#f0002"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>Southern lights have been frequently seen in England by that<lb break="yes"/>able and diligent observer, Dalton; northern lights in the southern<lb break="yes" />hemisphere, as low as 45° of latitude (Jan. 14, 1831). In in-<lb break="no" />stances that are not very rare, the magnetic equilibrium is dis-<lb break="no" />turbed at both poles simultaneously. I have distinctly stated that<lb break="yes"/>northern polar lights are seen within the tropics, even as far south<lb break="yes"/>as Mexico and Peru. It is necessary to distinguish, however, be-<lb break="no"/>tween the sphere of a simultaneous apparition of the phenomenon,<lb break="yes"/>and the zone of the earth in which the phenomenon is displayed<lb break="yes"/>almost every night in the year. As each observer sees his own<lb break="yes"/>rainbow, so also, doubtless, does he see his own polar light. A<lb break="yes"/>great portion of the earth engenders the radiating Light-pheno-<lb break="no"/>mena at the same time. Many nights can be mentioned in which<lb break="yes"/>it was observed simultaneously in England, in Pennsylvania, in<lb break="yes"/>Rome, and in Pekin. When it is maintained that the northern<lb break="yes"/>lights decline with the decrease of latitude, this must be understood<lb break="yes"/>as referring to magnetic latitude, measured from the magnetic<lb break="yes"/>pole. In Iceland, Greenland, and Newfoundland, on the banks of<lb break="yes"/>the Slave lake, and at Fort Enterprise (in North Canada), the<lb break="yes"/>Aurora is lighted up, at certain seasons, almost every night, and<lb break="yes"/>with its shifting, shivering rays, performs its &#x201C;merry dance&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>through the sky, as the natives of the Shetland Islands term it.<lb break="yes"/>Whilst in Italy the northern light is a great rarity, it is seen with<lb break="yes"/>extreme frequency in the latitude of Philadelphia (39° 57&#x2032; N.L.),<lb break="yes"/>in consequence of the southern position of the American magnetic<lb break="yes"/>pole. But in the districts of the new continent, and also of the<lb break="yes"/>shores of Siberia, which are remarkable for the frequency of the<lb break="yes" />phenomenon, there occur what may be called especial regions of the<lb break="yes"/>northern lights&#x2014;longitudinal zones in which they are peculiarly<lb break="yes"/>splendid. Local influences are, consequently, not to be overlooked.<lb break="yes"/>Wrangel observed their brilliancy decline as he left the shores of<lb break="yes"/>the icy sea, about Nijne-Kolymsk, behind him. The experience<lb break="yes"/>of the Northern Polar Expedition seems to indicate that the evolu-<lb break="no"/>tion of light is not greater in the immediate vicinity of the mag-<lb break="no"/>netic pole than it is at some distance from this spot.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>What we know of the altitude of the northern light is based on<lb break="yes" />measurements, which, by reason of the incessant oscillations of the<lb break="yes"/>luminous rays, and the consequent uncertainty of the parallactic<lb break="yes"/>angle, cannot be greatly depended on. The conclusions come to<lb break="yes"/>(not to speak of older estimates) vary between several miles and<lb break="yes"/>three or four thousand feet. It is not improbable that the northern<lb break="yes"/>light is at very different distances at different times. The latest<lb break="yes"/>observers are disposed to connect the phenomenon, not with the<lb break="yes"/>outer limits of the atmosphere, but with the region of the clouds<lb break="yes"/>itself; they even believe that the northern streamers may be<lb break="yes"/>moved by winds and currents of air, if the luminous phenomenon,<lb break="yes"/>by which alone the existence of the electro-magnetic emanations<lb break="yes"/>becomes obvious to us, be actually connected with material collec-<lb break="no"/>tions of vesicular vapour, or, to speak more correctly, penetrates<lb break="yes"/>these collections, darting over from one vesicle to another. Cap-<lb break="no"/>tain Franklin saw a streaming Aurora on Bear lake, which he<lb break="yes"/>believed illuminated the under side of the stratum of cloud; whilst<lb break="yes" />Kendal, who had the watch through the whole of the night, and<lb break="yes" />never lost sight of the heavens for a minute from his sight, at the<lb break="yes"/>distance of but 4&#x00BD; geographical miles, observed no luminous pheno-<lb break="no"/>menon whatsoever. The statement, repeated several times of late,<lb break="yes"/>to the effect that streamers of the northern light have been ob-<lb break="no"/>served close to the ground, and between the observer and a neigh-<lb break="no"/>bouring height, is one of those points, which, like lightning and<lb break="yes"/>the fall of fire-balls, is exposed to the manifold dangers of optical<lb break="yes"/>deception.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Whether or not the magnetic storm, of which we have just<lb break="yes"/>quoted a remarkable example of local circumscription within very<lb break="yes"/>narrow bounds, has the noise, besides the light, in common with<lb break="yes"/>the electrical storm, is now rendered extremely doubtful, since the<lb break="yes" />testimony of the Greenland sledgers, and the Siberian fox-hunters,<lb break="yes"/>is no longer taken unconditionally. The northern lights have be-<lb break="no"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1">erior strata of the atmosphere. They arise when the air is extremely calm<lb break="yes"/>and the heaven is particularly serene, and under the tropics are far more<lb break="yes"/>common than in the temperate and frigid zones. I have observed the phe-<lb break="no"/>nomenon among the Andes, when I was at the height of 14,000 feet above<lb break="yes"/>the level of the sea, as well as in Northern Asia, in the plains of Krasnojarski,<lb break="yes"/>southward from Buchtarminsk, and in both instances so much alike, that<lb break="yes" />the natural process in virtue of which it takes place must be regarded as<lb break="yes"/>one of very extensive prevalence. In an exhibition of south polar streaks<lb break="yes"/>of very delicate clouds, which Arago observed by day on the 23d of June,<lb break="yes"/>1845, at Paris, dark rays shot upwards from an arch which was directed from<lb break="yes"/>east to west.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> come more silent since they have been examined more carefully<lb break="yes"/>with the eye and the ear. Parry, Franklin, and Richardson, near<lb break="yes"/>the north pole; Thienemann, in Iceland; Gieseke, in Greenland;<lb break="yes"/>Lottin and Bravais, at the North Cape; Wrangel and Anjou, on<lb break="yes"/>the shores of the icy sea, have, altogether, looked at thousands of<lb break="yes"/>northern lights, yet never heard any noises. If this negative tes-<lb break="no"/>timony be not admitted against two positive witnesses, Hearne, at<lb break="yes"/>the mouth of the Coppermine river, and Henderson, in Iceland, it<lb break="yes"/>must still be remembered that Hood heard the same noises&#x2014;as of<lb break="yes"/>musket balls shaken rapidly together, and slight cracklings, during<lb break="yes"/>the occurrence of the northern lights, indeed, but also on the fol-<lb break="no"/>lowing day, when there was no Aurora in the heavens; and then<lb break="yes"/>it must not be forgotten, that Wrangel and Gieske were firmly<lb break="yes"/>convinced that the noises heard, were owing to contractions of the<lb break="yes"/>ice and crust of snow, in consequence of a sudden cooling of the<lb break="yes"/>air. The belief in a cracking noise did not exist among the people,<lb break="yes" />but with learned travellers, and in this way:&#x2014;the flashing of<lb break="yes"/>electricity in attenuated atmospheres having been known from an<lb break="yes"/>early period, the northern light was forthwith declared to be an<lb break="yes"/>effect of atmospheric electricity, and then the noises were heard<lb break="yes"/>that ought to have been heard. Recent experiments with the<lb break="yes"/>most delicate electrometers, however, contrary to all expectation,<lb break="yes"/>have given merely negative results: the state of the aerial elec-<lb break="no"/>tricity has not been found altered during the prevalence of the<lb break="yes"/>most brilliant Aurora.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>All the three manifestations of force of the terrestrial magnetism<lb break="yes" />&#x2014;Declination, Inclination, and Intensity, on the contrary, are<lb break="yes"/>affected at once by the northern lights. In one and the same night,<lb break="yes"/>and from hour to hour, the Aurora affects the same end of the<lb break="yes"/>needle differently, now attracting it, now repelling it. The asser-<lb break="no"/>tion that the facts collected by Parry at Melville Island, near the<lb break="yes"/>magnetic pole, lead to the conclusion that the northern lights do<lb break="yes"/>not disturb the needle, but rather have a &#x201C;calming effect&#x201D; upon<lb break="yes"/>it, is completely contradicted by a more careful perusal of Parry&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>own Journal, by the beautiful observations of Richardson, Hood,<lb break="yes"/>and Franklin, in North Canada, and, more lately still, by Bravais<lb break="yes" />and Lotten in Lapland. The process in the northern lights is, as<lb break="yes"/>we have above observed, the act of an equilibrium disturbed. The<lb break="yes"/>effect upon the needle varies according to the measure of force in<lb break="yes"/>the explosion. It was only unobservable at the nocturnal winter<lb break="yes"/>station at Bosekop, when the luminous phenomenon showed itself<lb break="yes"/>very feebly and deep on the horizon. The upshooting radiate<lb break="yes"/>cylinders of the northern light have been aptly compared to the<lb break="yes"/>flame which, in the closed circuit of the Voltaic pile, arises be-<lb break="no"/>tween two charcoal points at a distance from one another, or,<lb break="yes"/>according to Fizeau, between a silver and a charcoal point, and to<lb break="yes"/>that which is drawn or thrown off from the magnet. This analogy<lb break="yes"/>at all events renders superfluous the assumption of those metallic<lb break="yes"/>vapours in the atmosphere which some natural philosophers have<lb break="yes"/>imagined as the substrate of the northern lights.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If the luminous phenomenon which we ascribe to a galvanic cur-<lb break="no" />rent, <hi rendition="#i">i. e.</hi> a motion of electricity in a circuit returning into itself,<lb break="yes"/>be designated by the indefinite name of the Northern light, or the<lb break="yes"/>Polar light, nothing more is thereby implied than the local direc-<lb break="no"/>tion in which the beginning of a certain luminous phenomenon is<lb break="yes"/>most generally, but by no means invariably, seen. What gives<lb break="yes"/>this phenomenon its greatest importance is the fact which it re-<lb break="no"/>veals, viz., that the <hi rendition="#k">Earth is luminous</hi>; that our planet, beside<lb break="yes"/>the light which it receives from the central body, the sun, shows<lb break="yes"/>itself capable of a proper luminous act or process. The intensity<lb break="yes"/>of the Earth-light, or rather the degree of luminosity which it dif-<lb break="no"/>fuses, exceeds by a little, in the case of the brightest coloured rays<lb break="yes"/>that shoot up to the zenith, the light of the moon in her first quar-<lb break="no"/>ter. Occasionally, as on the 7th of January, 1831, a printed page<lb break="yes"/>can be read without straining the sight. This light-process of the<lb break="yes"/>earth, which the Polar regions exhibit almost incessantly, leads us<lb break="yes"/>by analogy to the remarkable phenomenon which the planet Venus<lb break="yes"/>presents. The portion of this planet which is not illuminated by<lb break="yes"/>the sun, glows occasionally with a proper phosphorescent gleam.<lb break="yes"/>It is not improbable that the Moon, Jupiter, and Comets, besides<lb break="yes"/>the reflected sun-light recognisable by the polariscope, also emit<lb break="yes" />light produced by themselves. Without insisting on the proble-<lb break="no" />matical but very common phenomenon of <hi rendition="#i">sheet-lightning</hi>, in which<lb break="yes"/>the whole of a deep massy cloud is flickeringly illuminated for several<lb break="yes"/>minutes at a time, we find other examples of terrestrial evolutions<lb break="yes"/>of light. To this head belong the celebrated <hi rendition="#i">dry-fogs</hi> of 1783 and<lb break="yes" />1831, which were luminous by night; the steady luminousness of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="66" facs="#f0003"/> large clouds, perfectly free from all flickering, observed by Rosier<lb break="yes"/>and Beccaria; and even the pale, diffused light, as Arago has well<lb break="yes"/>observed, which seems to guide us in the open air, in thinly clouded<lb break="yes"/>autumn and wintry nights, when there is neither moon nor star in<lb break="yes"/>the firmament, nor snow upon the ground. As in the phenomenon<lb break="yes"/>of the Polar lights occurring in high northern latitudes, in other<lb break="yes"/>words, in electro-magnetic storms floods, of flickering and often<lb break="yes"/>parti-coloured light stream through the air, so, in the hotter zones<lb break="yes"/>of the earth, between the tropics, are there many square miles of<lb break="yes"/>ocean which are similarly light-engendering. Here, however, the<lb break="yes"/>magic of the light belongs to the organic forces of nature. Light-<lb break="no"/>foaming flashes of the bursting wave, the wide level glows with<lb break="yes"/>lustrous sparks, and every spark is the vital motion of an invisible<lb break="yes" />animal world. So manifold is the source of terrestrial light. And<lb break="yes"/>shall we conceive it latent, not yet set free in vapours, as a means<lb break="yes"/>of explaining Moser&#x2019;s <hi rendition="#i" >pictures</hi>&#x2014;a discovery in which reality still<lb break="yes" />presents itself to us a vision shrouded in mystery?&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i" >Cosmos.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 