<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/111602781X">
                        <surname>Müller-Tamm</surname>
                        <forename>Jutta</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-22" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-10-21" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="390" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>2. <hi rendition="#i">On the Height of the Snow-Line in India.</hi>
                </head>
                <p>&#x2014;Whilst the most<lb break="yes"/>learned and experienced travellers in India,&#x2014;Colebrooke, Webb,<lb break="yes"/>Hodgson, Victor Jacquemont, Forbes Royle, C. Von Hügel, and<lb break="yes"/>Vigne, who are all familiar with the Himalaya, from personal exa-<lb break="no"/>mination, are agreed as to the higher elevation of the snow-limit on<lb break="yes"/>the Thibetic declivities of the range, the fact is called in question by<lb break="yes"/>Gerard, M&#x2019;Clelland (the editor of the Calcutta Journal), and Lieut.<lb break="yes"/>Thomas Hutton (assistant surveyor of the Agra division). The ap-<lb break="no"/>pearance of my work on Central Asia excited the controversy on the<lb break="yes"/>subject anew. A number of M&#x2019;Clelland and Griffith&#x2019;s Calcutta<lb break="yes"/>Journal of Natural History, vol. iv., 1844, January, however, con-<lb break="no"/>tains a very remarkable and decisive notice of the snow-limit of the<lb break="yes"/>Himalaya. Mr Batten (Bengal service), writes from the camp of Sem-<lb break="no"/>ulka, on the Cosillah river, in the province of Kumaon, as follows:&#x2014;<lb break="yes" />&#x201C;I have only, but with surprise, heard of the statements of Mr Thomas<lb break="yes"/>Hutton, respecting the limits of perpetual snow. I feel the more<lb break="yes"/>called upon to contradict such statements, as Mr M&#x2019;Clelland goes<lb break="yes"/>so far as to speak (Hutton, Journal of the Asiatic Society of Bengal,<lb break="yes"/>vol. ix., Calcutta, 1840, p. 575, 578, and 580), of the honour which<lb break="yes"/>Mr Hutton has done himself in detecting a wide-spread error. It is<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="391" facs="#f0002"/> very erroneously stated, that every one who ascends the Himalaya<lb break="yes"/>must share in Mr Hutton&#x2019;s doubts. I am myself one of those who<lb break="yes"/>have visited the western portion of our mighty mountain chain most<lb break="yes"/>frequently. I came through the Borendo pass into the Buspa valley,<lb break="yes"/>and the inferior Kunawur-land, returning through the lofty Rupin<lb break="yes"/>pass into the Rewaian mountains of Gurwal. I penetrated to the<lb break="yes"/>springs of the Jumna, as far as Jumnotri, and then turned to the tri-<lb break="no"/>butaries of the Ganges of Mundakni and Wischnu-Aluknunda, towards<lb break="yes" />Kadarnath, and the celebrated snowy summit of Nundidevi. I several<lb break="yes"/>times crossed over the Niti pass to the high lands of Thibet. I myself<lb break="yes"/>founded the settlement of Bhote-Mehals. My continued residence<lb break="yes"/>of six years among the mountains brought me into contact with many<lb break="yes"/>native and European travellers, from whom I could obtain the most<lb break="yes"/>accurate information concerning the country. From all my experi-<lb break="no"/>ence gathered in this way, I have arrived at the conclusion, and am<lb break="yes"/>ready to maintain it, that in the Himalaya the limit of eternal snow<lb break="yes"/>lies higher on the northern, or Thibetic, than on the southern, or In-<lb break="no"/>dian declivities. Mr Hutton alters the terms of the proposition, when<lb break="yes" />he thinks he disproves Humboldt&#x2019;s general view of the phenomenon;<lb break="yes"/>he fights against a creation of his own fancy, when he seeks to prove,<lb break="yes"/>that in some single mountains of the Himalaya the snow lies longer<lb break="yes"/>on the northern than on the southern slopes; a proposition which we<lb break="yes"/>readily grant him.&#x201D; <hi rendition="#i">Vide</hi> also Note 5 (Notes, p. 45). If the<lb break="yes" />mean height of the Thibetic high lands be 10,800 feet, they may<lb break="yes" />then be compared with the delightful and fertile Peruvian plateau of<lb break="yes"/>Caxamarca. But on this estimate still they would be 1200 feet<lb break="yes"/>lower than the plateau of Bolivia, the lake of Titicaca, and the cause-<lb break="no"/>way of the town of Potosi. Ladak, from Vigne&#x2019;s measurement by<lb break="yes"/>the boiling point of water, is 1563 toises high. This is probably<lb break="yes"/>also the height of H&#x2019;Lassa (Yul-jung), a town of monks, which<lb break="yes"/>Chinese writers speak of as the &#x201C;realm of pleasure,&#x201D; and which is<lb break="yes"/>surrounded by vineyards. Must not these lie in deeply cut valleys?<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Cosmos</hi>, No. 4, p. 473. <hi rendition="#i">By Alexander Von Humboldt.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 