<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<dateline>8 NOVEMBER, 1845.</dateline><lb/><pb n="251" facs="#f0001" />
<cb/>
<div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#i">Carbonic Acid and Sulphureous Acid Springs&#x2014;<lb/>Cold
                        Springs&#x2014;Hot Springs&#x2014;Mud Volcanoes&#x2014;<lb/>Volcanoes.</hi>
                    By Baron <hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Hum-<lb/>boldt.</hi><note place="foot"
                        n="*">This extract from Cosmos, (English edition by Bail-<lb/>liere,) at
                        present in course of publication, is slightly<lb/>altered and
                        enlarged.</note></head>
                <lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Having</hi> now taken a general survey of the<lb/>activity,
                    that is, of the internal life of the globe,<lb/>in its heat, in its
                    electro-magnetic tension, in its<lb/>luminous emanations at the poles, in its
                    irregu-<lb/>larly-recurring phenomenon of motion, we come to<lb/>chemical
                    changes in the crust of the earth, and in<lb/>the composition of the atmosphere,
                    which are, in<lb/>like manner, the consequence of planetary vital<lb/>activity.
                    From the ground we see effusions of<lb/>watery vapor and of gaseous carbonic
                    acid, mostly<lb/>free from all admixture of azote; of carburetted<lb/>hydrogen
                    gas, in the Chinese province of Sse-<lb/>tschuan, for thousands of years, and in
                    the state<lb/>of New York, where, in the village of Fredonia,<lb/>it has lately
                    been employed for economical pur-<lb/>poses in heating and lighting;<note
                        place="foot" n="&#x2020;"><hi rendition="#i">Carburetted Hydrogen Spring at
                            Fredonia.</hi> &#x2014; Sailed<lb/>in a steamboat to Fredonia, a town of
                        1200 inhabitants,<lb/>with neat white houses, and six churches. The
                        streets<lb/>are lighted up with <hi rendition="#i">natural gas,</hi> which
                        bubbles out of the<lb/>ground, and is received into a gasometer, which I
                        visited.<lb/>This gas consists of <hi rendition="#i">carburetted
                            hydrogen,</hi> and issues<lb/>from a black bituminous slate, one of the
                        beds of the<lb/>Hamilton group of the New York geologists, or part
                        of<lb/>the Devonian formation of Europe. The lighthouse-<lb/>keeper at
                        Fredonia told me, that, near the shore, at a con-<lb/>siderable distance
                        from the gasometer, he bored a hole<lb/>through this black slate, and the
                        gas soon collected in<lb/>sufficient quantity to explode, when ignited.
                        &#x2014; <hi rendition="#i">Travels in<lb/>North America.</hi> By Charles
                        Lyell. Vol. ii., p. 89.<hi rendition="#i">
                            <lb/>
                        </hi><p/><hi rendition="#i">Burning Spring of Niagara.</hi> &#x2014; At the
                        falls of Niag-<lb/>ara, where we next spent a week, residing in a hotel
                        on<lb/>the Canada side, I resumed my geological explorations<lb/>of last
                        summer. Every part of the scenery, from Grand<lb/>Island above the falls, to
                        the ferry at Queenstown, seven<lb/>miles below, deserves to be studied at
                        leisure.<p/><lb/>We visited the &#x201C;burning spring&#x201D; at the edge
                        of the<lb/>river above the rapids, where carburetted hydrogen, or,
                        in<lb/>the modern chemical phraseology, a light hydro-carbon,<lb/>similar to
                        that before mentioned at Fredonia, rises from<lb/>beneath the water out of
                        the limestone rock. The bitu-<lb/>minous matter supplying this gas is
                        probably of animal<lb/>origin, as this limestone is full of marine mollusca,
                        crus-<lb/>tacea, and corals, without vegetable remains, unless
                        some<lb/>fucoids may have decomposed in the same strata. The<lb/>invisible
                        gas makes its way in countless bubbles through<lb/>the clear transparent
                        waters of the Niagara. On the<lb/>application of a lighted candle, it takes
                        fire, and plays<lb/>about with a lambent flickering flame, which
                        seldom<lb/>touches the water, the gas being, at first, too pure to
                        be<lb/>inflammable, and only obtaining sufficient oxygen after<lb/>mingling
                        with the atmosphere at the height of several<lb/>inches above the surface of
                        the stream. &#x2014; <hi rendition="#i">Lyell&#x2019;s Travels<lb/>in North
                            America,</hi> vol. ii., p. 90. &#x2014; <hi rendition="#i">Edit. of
                            Phil. Journal.</hi></note> of sulphuretted<lb/>hydrogen gas, of sulphur
                    fumes, and, more rarely,<lb/>of sulphureous and hydro-chloric acid
                    vapors.<lb/>Such emanations from fissures in the ground, do<lb/>not only
                    indicate the dominion of volcanoes long<lb/>extinct or still burning; they are
                    farther observed<lb/>exceptionally in districts in which neither
                    trachyte<lb/>nor any other volcanic rock appears at the surface.<lb/>In the
                    Andes of Quindiu, I have seen sulphur pre-<lb/>cipitated from hot sulphureous
                    vapors issuing out<lb/>of mica-slate, at a height of 6410 feet above
                    the<lb/>level of the sea; whilst the same, and, as it used<lb/>to be regarded,
                    primitive rock, in Cerra Cuelo,<lb/>near Ticsan, south of Quito, exhibits an
                    enormous<lb/>bed of sulphur in pure quartz.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Of all the gaseous springs which the earth<lb/><cb/>pours forth, those of
                    carbonic acid (mofetten) are<lb/>still, at the present time, the most important,
                    both<lb/>in number and extent. Germany, in her deeply-<lb break="maybe"/>cut valleys of the
                    Eifel, in the neighborhood of<lb/>Lake Lach, in the Kesselthal of Wehr, and
                    in<lb/>Western Bohemia, as also in the burning foci of<lb/>the primeval world,
                    or their vicinity, shows as<lb/>these effusions of carbonic acid as a kind of
                    last<lb/>effort of volcanic activity. In former epochs,<lb/>where, with a higher
                    temperature of the earth,<lb/>and the frequency of fissures yet unfilled,
                    the<lb/>processes which we are here describing proceeded<lb/>more actively where
                    carbonic acid gas and watery<lb/>vapors were mingled with the atmosphere
                    in<lb/>larger quantities than at present, the youthful<lb/>vegetable world, as
                    Adolph Brongniart has acutely<lb/>observed, must have attained almost
                    everywhere,<lb/>and independently of geographical position, to the<lb/>most rank
                    luxuriance and evolution of its organs.<lb/>In the ever hot, ever moist
                    atmosphere, surcharged<lb/>with carbonic acid, vegetables must have
                    found<lb/>such vital excitement, such superfluity of nourish-<lb/>ment, as
                    enabled them to supply the material of<lb/>those beds of coal and lignite, the
                    exhaustion of<lb/>which it is difficult to conceive, and which now<lb/>serve as
                    foundations for the physical strength and<lb/>the welfare of nations.
                        <note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn1-1">In Lyell&#x2019;s interesting Travels in North
                            America,<lb/>already quoted, we meet with the following remarks
                            on<lb/>the quantity of carbonic acid in the atmosphere, in which<lb/>the
                            plants of the coal formation flourished: &#x2014;
                            &#x201C;Before<lb/>concluding the remarks, which are naturally
                            suggested<lb/>by a visit to the Great Dismal, I shall say a few words
                            on<lb/>a popular doctrine, favored by some geologists, respecting<lb/>an
                            atmosphere highly charged with carbonic acid, in<lb/>which the coal
                            plants are supposed to have flourished.<lb/>Some imagine the air to have
                            been so full of choke damp<lb/>during the ancient era alluded to, that
                            it was unfitted for<lb/>the respiration of warm-blooded quadrupeds and
                            birds, or<lb/>even reptiles, which require a more rapid oxygenation
                            of<lb/>their blood than creatures lower in the scale of
                            organiza-<lb/>tion, such as have alone been met with hitherto in
                            the<lb/>carboniferous and older strata. It is assumed, that
                            an<lb/>excess of oxygen was set free when the plants
                            which<lb/>elaborated the coal subtracted many hundred million<lb/>tons
                            of carbon from the carbonic acid gas which previ-<lb/>ously loaded the
                            air. All this carbon was then perma-<lb/>nently locked up in the solid
                            seams of coal, and the<lb/>chemical composition of the earth&#x2019;s
                            atmosphere essen-<lb/>tially altered.<p/><lb/>But they who reason thus
                            are bound to inform us what<lb/>may have been the duration of the period
                            in the course of<lb/>which so much carbon was secreted by the powers
                            of<lb/>vegetable life; and, secondly, what accession of
                            fresh<lb/>carbonic acid did the air receive in the same. We
                            know<lb/>that, in the present state of the globe, the air is
                            continu-<lb/>ally supplied with carbonic acid from several sources,
                            of<lb/>which the principal are, <hi rendition="#i">first,</hi> The daily
                            putrefaction of<lb/>dead animal and vegetable substances; <hi
                                rendition="#i">secondly,</hi> The<lb/>disintegration of rocks
                            charged with carbonic acid and<lb/>organic matter; and, <hi
                                rendition="#i">thirdly,</hi> The copious evolution of<lb/>this gas
                            from mineral springs and the earth, especially in<lb/>volcanic
                            countries. By that law, which causes two gases<lb/>of different specific
                            gravity, when brought into contact, to<lb/>become uniformly diffused and
                            mutually absorbed through<lb/>the whole space which they occupy, the
                            heavy carbonic<lb/>acid finds its way upwards through all parts of
                            the<lb/>atmosphere, and the solid materials of large forests
                            are<lb/>given out from the earth in an invisible form, or in
                            bub-<lb/>bles rising through the water of springs. Peat mosses of<lb/>no
                            slight depth, and covering thousands of square miles,<lb/>are thus fed
                            with their mineral constituents, without<lb/>materially deranging the
                            constituents of the atmosphere<lb/>breathed by man. Thousands of trees
                            grow up, float<lb/>down to the delta of the Mississippi and other
                            rivers, and<lb/>are buried, and yet the air, at the end of many
                            centuries,<lb/>may be as much impregnated with carbonic acid
                            as<lb/>before.<p/><lb/>Coral reefs are, year after year, growing in the
                            ocean;<lb/>springs and rivers feed the same occan with carbonic
                            acid<lb/>and lime; but we have no reason to infer, that
                            when<lb/>mountain masses of calcareous rock have thus been grad-</note>
                     Such beds are princi-</p><lb/>
                    <pb n="252" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <p>
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1">ually formed in the sea, any essential change in
                            the<lb/>chemical composition of its waters has been brought<lb/>about.
                            We have no accurate data, as yet, for measuring,<lb/>whether in our own
                            time, or at any remote geological era,<lb/>the relative supply and
                            consumption of carbon in the air<lb/>or the ocean, causes the amount of
                            those elements to vary<lb/>greatly; but the variation, if admitted,
                            would not have<lb/>caused an excess, but rather a deficit, of carbon, in
                            the<lb/>periods most productive of coal or peat, as compared to<lb/>any
                            subsequent or antecedent epochs. In fact, a climate<lb/>favoring the
                            rank and luxurious growth of plants, and, at<lb/>the same time, checking
                            their decay, and giving rise to<lb/>peat or accumulations of vegetable
                            matter, might, for the<lb/>time, diminish the average amount of carbonic
                            acid in the<lb/>atmosphere&#x2014;a state of things precisely the
                            reverse of<lb/>that assumed by those to whose views I am now
                            object-<lb/>ing.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Travels in North
                                America.</hi> By Charles Lyell.<lb/>Vol. i., p. 150.&#x2014;<hi
                                    rendition="#i">Edit. of Phil. Journal.</hi></note>
                        pally contained in basins, and are peculiar to cer-<lb/>tain parts of
                    Europe. They are abundant in the<lb/>British Isles, in Belgium, in France, on
                    the Lower<lb/>Rhine, and in Upper Silesia. In the same prime-<lb/>val times of
                    all-pervading volcanic action, too,<lb/>must those enormous quantities of
                    carbonaceous<lb/>matter have issued from the bowels of the earth,<lb/>which all
                    the limestone rocks contain, and which,<lb/>separated from oxygen, and
                    represented in the<lb/>solid form, composes about an eighth part of
                    the<lb/>absolute bulk of those mountain masses. The<lb/>carbonic acid which the
                    atmosphere still contained,<lb/>and which was not absorbed by the
                    alkaline<lb/>earths, was gradually consumed by the vegetation<lb/>of the
                    primeval world; so that the atmosphere,<lb/>purified by the processes of
                    vegetable life, by and<lb/>by contained no more of the gas than was
                    uninju-<lb/>rious to the organization of such animals as people<lb/>the earth at
                    the present time. Sulphurous or sul-<lb/>phuric acid vapors, too, occurring more
                    frequently,<lb/>and much more abundantly, then than now, occa-<lb/>sioned the
                    destruction of the inhabitants of the<lb/>inland waters&#x2014;mollusca and
                    numerous genera of<lb/>fishes, as well as the formation of the
                    strangely<lb/>contorted beds of gypsum, which have often, appa-<lb/>rently, been
                    shaken by earthquakes.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Under precisely similar physical relations, there<lb/>were further thrown out
                    from the bosom of the<lb/>earth various gases and liquids, mud, and,
                    from<lb/>the eruption cones of volcanoes, which are but a<lb/>species of
                    intermitting springs, streams of molten<lb/>earths. All these matters owe their
                    temperature,<lb/>and the nature of their chemical constitution, to<lb/>the place
                    of their origin. The mean temperature<lb/>of ordinary springs is lower than that
                    of the<lb/>atmosphere where they appear, when the water<lb/>is derived from high
                    levels; their temperature<lb/>increases with the depth of the strata with
                    which<lb/>they come in contact at their origin. The numer-<lb/>ical law of this
                    increase has been stated above.<lb/>The mixture of the waters, which come from
                    the<lb/>mountain elevations, or from the depths of the<lb/>earth, renders the
                    position of the isogeothermal<lb/>lines, or lines of equal internal heat of
                    the<lb/>earth, difficult of determination, when the conclu-<lb/>sion has to be
                    come to from the temperature of<lb/>springs as they rise. So, at least, did I
                    and my<lb/>friends find it in some experiments which we<lb/>made in Northern
                    Asia. The temperature of<lb/>springs, which has been so constant an object
                    of<lb/>physical investigation for the last half century,<lb/>depends, like the
                    height of the line of perpetual<lb/>snow, on numerous and highly complex
                    causes.<lb/>It is a function of the temperature of the stratum<lb/>in which they
                    have their origin, of the capacity<lb/>for heat of the ground, and of the
                    quantity and<lb/>temperature of the atmospheric or meteoric water<lb/>
                    <cb/>
                    that falls; which last, again, according to the<lb/>mode of its
                    origin, differs in its temperature from<lb/>that of the lower strata of the
                    atmosphere.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Cold springs, as they are called, can only give<lb/>the mean temperature of the
                    air, if unmixed with<lb/>water that is rising from great depths, or that
                    is<lb/>descending from considerable heights, and when<lb/>they have flowed for a
                    very long way under the<lb/>surface&#x2014;in our latitudes from 40 to 60 feet,
                    in the<lb/>equinoctial zone, according to Boussingault, one<lb/>foot. These
                    depths are those, in fact, of the<lb/>stratum of rock in which, in the temperate
                    and<lb/>torrid zone respectively, the point of invariable<lb/>temperature
                    begins, in which the hourly, diurnal,<lb/>or monthly variations in temperature
                    of the air are<lb/>no longer perceived.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Hot springs burst out of the most diversified<lb/>mineral strata; the hottest of
                    all the permanent<lb/>springs which have yet been observed, and which<lb/>I
                    myself discovered, flow remote from all vol-<lb/>canoes. I here refer to the
                    Aguas calientes de<lb/>Las Trincheras between Porto Cabello and
                    New<lb/>Valencia, in South America, and to the Aguas de<lb/>Comangillas, near
                    Guanaxuato, in Mexico. The<lb/>first spring issuing from granite, indicated
                    90&#x00B7;3°<lb/>C.; the second, which issues from basalt,
                    showed<lb/>96&#x00B7;4° C. The depth of the source of water of<lb/>these
                    temperatures, from what we know of the<lb/>law of increase of temperature in the
                    interior of<lb/>the earth, must probably be about 6700 feet (more<lb/>than half
                    a geographical mile.) If the cause of<lb/>the heat of thermal springs, as well
                    as of active<lb/>volcanoes, be the universally diffused heat of the<lb/>earth,
                    then would rocks produce an effect only<lb/>through their capacity for, and
                    their power of, con-<lb/>ducting heat. The hottest of all the
                    permanent<lb/>springs, those, namely, from 95° to 97° C. (204°<lb/>to
                    207&#x00B7;6° F.,) it is remarkable, are the purest, are<lb/>those that contain
                    the smallest quantity of mineral<lb/>matter in solution. Their temperature
                    appears,<lb/>on the whole, to be less permanent than that of<lb/>springs between
                    50° and 74° C., the invariableness<lb/>of which, both in regard to temperature
                    and mine-<lb/>ral impregnation, has been maintained so wonder-<lb/>fully, within
                    the confines of Europe at least, during<lb/>the last fifty or sixty years, <hi
                        rendition="#i">i. e.</hi> since accurate<lb/>thermometrical observations and
                    chemical analyses<lb/>were made. Boussingault found that the thermal<lb/>springs
                    of Las Trincheras had risen in tempera-<lb/>ture, in the course of twenty-three
                    years (from<lb/>1800, when my journey was performed, to 1823,)<lb/>from
                    93&#x00B7;3° to 97° C. This very smoothly-flowing<lb/>spring is, consequently,
                    at this time 7° C. higher<lb/>in temperature than the intermitting Geyser
                    and<lb/>Strokr, the temperature of which has been lately<lb/>more carefully
                    ascertained by Krug of Nidda.<lb/>One of the most remarkable proofs of the
                    origin of<lb/>these hot springs being due to the percolation of<lb/>cold
                    meteoric water into the interior of the earth,<lb/>and its contact there with a
                    volcanic focus, was<lb/>presented in the preceding century, in
                    connection<lb/>with the volcano of Jorullo in Mexico, which was<lb/>unknown to
                    geography till after my South Ameri-<lb/>can journey. When this mountain
                    suddenly made<lb/>its appearance in September, 1759, rising to a<lb/>height of
                    1580 feet above the surrounding level,<lb/>the two small streams Rios de
                    Cuitimba y de San<lb/>Pedro disappeared; but some time afterwards<lb/>they made
                    their appearance again, under the<lb/>dreadful shocks of an earthquake, as hot
                    springs.<lb/>In 1803, I found their temperature 65°8 C.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The springs of Greece still flow apparently in<lb/>the same places as they did in
                    the times of Helle-<lb/><pb n="253" facs="#f0003"/><cb/>nic antiquity. The
                    spring of Erosinos, two leagues<lb/>south of Argos, in the declivity of Chaon,
                    is even<lb/>mentioned by Herodotus. At Delphi, the Cassotis<lb/>(the so-called
                    Wells of St. Nicholas) still rises to<lb/>the south of the Lesche, and flows
                    under the<lb/>Temple of Apollo; the Castalia, too, at the foot<lb/>of
                    Ph&#x00E6;driad&#x00E6;, and the Pirene at Acrocorinth, are<lb/>there, as well
                    as the hot baths of &#x00C6;depsos in<lb/>Cub&#x00E6;a, in which Sulla bathed at
                    the time of the<lb/>Mithridatic war. I gladly adduce these particu-<lb/>lars,
                    because they forcibly remind us how, in a<lb/>country exposed to earthquakes so
                    frequent and so<lb/>violent, the interior of our planet has been able
                    to<lb/>preserve its spring canals unaltered for 2000 years<lb/>at least. The
                    Fontaine Jaillissante of Lillers, in<lb/>the department of the Pas de Calais,
                    was bored in<lb/>the year 1126, and ever since then has the water<lb/>flowed
                    uninterruptedly to the same height, and in<lb/>the same quantity. The excellent
                    geographer of<lb/>the Caramanian coasts, Captain Reaufort, more-<lb/>over,
                    observed the same flame, fed by a stream of<lb/>infiammable gas, which flows out
                    in the district of<lb/>Phaselis, which Pliny describes as the flame
                    of<lb/>Chim&#x00E6;ra in Lycia.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The observations made by Arago in 1821, that<lb/>the deeper Artesian wells are
                    the warmer, was the<lb/>first means of throwing a great light upon
                    the<lb/>origin of thermal springs, and led to the discovery<lb/>of the law of
                    the increase of the temperature of<lb/>the earth according to the depth. It is
                    remarkable,<lb/>and only noticed in very recent times, that St.<lb/>Patricius,
                    probably Bishop of Pertusa, was led to a<lb/>very correct view of the phenomenon
                    which pre-<lb/>sented itself in the appearance of hot springs near<lb/>Carthage,
                    at the end of the third century. When<lb/>questioned as to the cause of the
                    boiling-hot water<lb/>which poured out from the earth, he answered:
                    &#x2014;<lb/>&#x201C;Fire is nourished in the clouds, and in the in-<lb/>terior
                    of the earth, as Etna, and another mountain<lb/>in the neighborhood of Naples,
                    inform you. The<lb/>subterranean waters rise as through syphons; and<lb/>the
                    cause of the heat of hot springs is this: the<lb/>waters that are more remote
                    from the subterrane-<lb/>ous fire show themselves colder; those that flow<lb/>in
                    closer proximity to the fire, warmed by it, bring<lb/>an insupportable heat to
                    the surface which we<lb/>inhabit.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>As earthquakes are frequently accompanied by<lb/>eruptions of water and watery
                    vapor, so do we per-<lb/>ceive in the salses, or the small mud-volcanoes,
                    a<lb/>transition from the alternating phenomena pre-<lb/>sented by jets of vapor
                    and thermal springs to the<lb/>great and frightful activity of hills that vomit
                    forth<lb/>lava. If these, as springs of melted mineral mat-<lb/>ter, produce
                    volcanic rocks, so do the thermal<lb/>springs that are charged with carbonic
                    acid and<lb/>sulphurous gas, (and earthy matters,) produce, by<lb/>incessant
                    precipitation, either horizontal beds of<lb/>limestone, (travertin,) or they
                    form conical hillocks,<lb/>as in the north of Africa, (Algeira,) and the
                    Banos<lb/>of Caxamarca, on the western declivity of the<lb/>Peruvian Andes. In
                    the travertin of Van Die-<lb/>man&#x2019;s Land, not far from Hobart Town, there
                    are<lb/>contained, according to Mr. Charles Darwin, the<lb/>remains of an
                    extinct flora. By lava and travertin,<lb/>two species of rock, the production of
                    which goes<lb/>on under our eyes, we here indicate the grand an-<lb/>tithesis in
                    geognostical relations.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Mud-volcanoes (salsen) deserve a greater share<lb/>of attention than geologists
                    have hitherto bestowed<lb/>upon them. The extent of the phenomena has<lb/>been
                    overlooked, because in the two states in<lb/>which it presents itself to us, the
                    one of repose is<lb/>that which has been principally dwelt upon; and<lb/><cb/>in
                    this state of repose mud-volcanoes often continue<lb/>for centuries. The
                    production of mud-vocanoes is<lb/>accompanied by earthquakes, subterranean
                    thun-<lb/>der, the elevation of a whole district of country,<lb/>and the
                    eruption of flames, which rise high, but<lb/>last only for a short time. When
                    the mud-volcano<lb/>of Iokmali made its appearance in the peninsula
                    of<lb/>Abscheron, eastward from Baku, on the Caspian<lb/>Sea, (on the 27th of
                    November, 1827,) flames burst<lb/>forth, and blazed up to an extraordinary
                    height for<lb/>a period of three hours; for the next succeeding<lb/>twenty hours
                    they scarcely rose three feet above<lb/>the surface of the crater that
                    discharged the mud.<lb/>The column of flame mounted to such a height<lb/>near
                    the village of Baklichi, westward from Baku,<lb/>that it was seen at the
                    distance of six (German)<lb/>miles. Great blocks of stone, torn from their
                    foun-<lb/>dations beneath, were scattered widely around.<lb/>Similar blocks are
                    observed about the now slum-<lb/>bering mud-volcanoes of Monte Zibio, near
                    Sassu-<lb/>olo, in the north of Italy. The second state, or<lb/>that of
                    activity, has continued for 1500 years in the<lb/>mud volcano of Girgenti,
                    (Macalubi,) in Sicily,<lb/>which is described by the ancients. Many
                    conical<lb/>hillocks, of eight, ten, and even thirty feet high,<lb/>though the
                    height, as well as the form, of these<lb/>varies at different times, are there
                    seen arranged<lb/>near one another. From the superior very small<lb/>basin,
                    which is full of water, along with the peri-<lb/>odic escapes of gas, there are
                    periodic streams of<lb/>clayey mud discharged. The mud of these vol-<lb/>canoes
                    is generally cold, but occasionally, as at<lb/>Damak, in the province of
                    Samarang, island of<lb/>Java, it is of high temperature. The gases,<lb/>which
                    escape with a rushing noise, are also of<lb/>different kinds&#x2014;hydrogen
                    gas, mixed with naph-<lb/>tha; carbonic acid; and, as Parrot and I
                    ascer-<lb/>tained, (in the peninsula of Taman and the South<lb/>American
                    Volcancitos de Turbaco,) almost pure<lb/>nitrogen gas.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Mud-volcanoes, after the first forcible outburst<lb/>of flame, which perhaps is
                    not common to all in<lb/>the same measure, present the observer with
                    a<lb/>picture of an activity of the interior of the earth,<lb/>that proceeds
                    incessantly but feebly. The com-<lb/>munication with the deep strata, in which a
                    high<lb/>temperature prevails, is speedily interrupted again;<lb/>and the cold
                    discharges of mud-volcanoes seem to<lb/>indicate that the seat of the
                    phenomenon, in its<lb/>state of continuance, cannot be very remote from<lb/>the
                    surface. The reäction of the interior of the<lb/>earth upon its outer crust is
                    exhibited in a very<lb/>different degree of force in the proper
                    volcanoes,<lb/>or burning mountains; in other words, in those<lb/>points of the
                    earth where a permanent communi-<lb/>cation, or, at all events, a communication
                    that is<lb/>renewed from time to time, is established between<lb/>the surface
                    and the deep focus of ignition. We<lb/>must carefully distinguish between more
                    or less<lb/>exaggerated volcanic phenomena, such as earth-<lb/>quakes, hot
                    springs and jets of steam, mud-volca-<lb/>noes, the rising up of bell and
                    dome-shaped un-<lb/>opened trachytic mountains, the opening of
                    these<lb/>mountains, or the upheaval of basaltic beds as cra-<lb/>ters of
                    elevation, lastly, the rise of a permanent<lb/>volcano within the crater of
                    elevation itself, or<lb/>amongst the fragments of its previous
                    constitution.<lb/>At different times, along with different degrees
                    of<lb/>activity and force, permanent volcanoes throw out<lb/>jets of aqueous
                    vapor, acids, glowing ashes and<lb/>scori&#x00E6;, and, when the resistance can
                    be over-<lb/>come, ribbon-shaped small fiery streams of melted<lb/>earthy
                    matter.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>As a consequence of a great but local manifes-<lb/><pb n="254" facs="#f0004"
                    /><cb/> tation of force in the interior of our planet, elastic<lb/>vapors raise
                    either single parts of the crust of the<lb/>earth into dome-shaped, unopened
                    masses of fels-<lb/>pathic trachyte and dolerite, (Puy de D&#x00F4;me
                    and<lb/>Chimborazo,) or the upheaved strata are broken<lb/>through, and inclined
                    outwards, in such wise, that<lb/>upon the opposite inner aspect a steep rocky
                    edge<lb/>is produced. This edge then becomes the boundary<lb/>of a crater of
                    elevation. When this has risen from<lb/>the bottom of the sea, which does not,
                    by any<lb/>means, happen in every case, it then determines<lb/>the whole of the
                    characteristic physiognomy of the<lb/>upheaved island. This is the origin of the
                    circular<lb/>form of Palma, which Leopold von Buch has de-<lb/>scribed so
                    carefully and so ably, as well as of<lb/>Nisyros, in the &#x00C6;gean Sea.
                    Occasionally, one-<lb break="maybe"/>half the ring-like edge is destroyed: and in the<lb/>bay
                    which the sea that has flowed in then forms,<lb/>the social coral polypi
                    establish themselves, and<lb/>produce their cellular dwellings. Craters of
                    ele-<lb/>vation on continents are also frequently found<lb/>filled with water,
                    when they contribute to beautify<lb/>the landscape in a peculiar manner.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Their origin is not connected with any particu-<lb/>lar mountain rock; they break
                    out in basalt, tra-<lb/>chyte, leucitic porphyry, (Somma,) or in
                    doleritic<lb/>aggregates of augite and Labrador. Hence the<lb/>very dissimilar
                    natures and external forms of this<lb/>kind of crater edge. &#x201C;No eruptive
                    phenomena<lb/>take place from such boundaries. Through them<lb/>there is no
                    permanent channel of communication<lb/>established with the interior; and it is
                    only very<lb/>rarely that traces of still active volcanic power
                    are<lb/>discovered in the precincts, or within the circuit of<lb/>such craters.
                    The force competent to bring about<lb/>such important effects, must long have
                    accumu-<lb/>lated, and gained strength in the interior, before it<lb/>could have
                    overcome the resistance of the superin-<lb/>cumbent masses. On the formation of
                    new islands,<lb/>it raises up granular rocky masses and conglome-<lb/>rates
                    (layers of tufa full of marine plants) above<lb/>the level of the sea.
                    Compressed gases escape<lb/>through the crater of elevation; but a mass
                    of<lb/>such magnitude, thus upheaved, sinks down again,<lb/>and closes forthwith
                    the openings, which are only<lb/>formed for such manifestations of force. No
                    vol-<lb/>cano is produced.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>A proper valcano only arises where a perma-<lb/>nent connection is established
                    between the interior<lb/>of the earth and the atmosphere. Here the
                    reac-<lb/>tion of the interior upon the exterior proceeds for<lb/>lengthened
                    periods. It may, as in the case of<lb/>Vesuvius, (Fisove,) be interrupted for
                    centuries,<lb/>and exhibit itself anew with renovated vigor. In<lb/>the time of
                    Nero, it was already customary, in<lb/>Rome, to rank &#x00C6;tna among the
                    number of the<lb/>gradually expiring volcanic mountains;
                    &#x00C6;lian,<lb/>indeed, at a later period, maintained that the sea-<lb/>men
                    began to see the sinking summit at a less dis-<lb/>tance on the high seas than
                    formerly. Where the<lb/>evidence of the eruption&#x2014;I might say the old
                    scaf-<lb/>folding&#x2014;has been perfectly preserved, the volcano<lb/>shows
                    itself rising from a crater of elevation; there<lb/>a high rocky wall, a rampart
                    of greatly inclined<lb/>strata, surrounds the isolated cone in the manner<lb/>of
                    a circus. Sometimes there is not a trace of this<lb/>circus-like enclosure
                    visible; and the volcano, not<lb/>always conical in figure, then arises as an
                    elon-<lb/>gated ridge immediately from the elevated plat-<lb/>form. This is the
                    case with Pichincha, at the<lb/>foot of which stands the city of Quito.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>As the nature of mountain rocks, in other<lb/>words, the combination or grouping
                    of simple min-<lb/><cb/>erals into granite, gneiss, and mica-slate,
                    into<lb/>trachyte, basalt, and dolerite, independently of<lb/>present climates,
                    and under the most dissimilar<lb/>zones, is still the same; so do we
                    everywhere<lb/>observe the same laws of formation proclaiming<lb/>themselves in
                    the realm of inorganic nature, laws<lb/>according to which the strata of the
                    crust of the<lb/>earth stand in a certain relationship to one another,<lb/>and
                    under the influence of elastic forces, break<lb/>through one another as dikes.
                    This recurrence<lb/>of the same phenomena is particularly striking
                    in<lb/>volcanoes. When the navigator, among the isl-<lb/>ands of distant seas,
                    finding himself surrounded<lb/>by palms and strange forms of vegetation, and
                    no<lb/>longer sees the same stars, in the individualities<lb/>of the landscape,
                    he still traces the characters of<lb/>Vesuvius, the dome-shaped summit of
                    Auvergne,<lb/>the crater of elevation of the Canaries and Azores,<lb/>the
                    fissures of eruption of Iceland repeated and<lb/>reflected. A glance at the
                    attendant of our planet,<lb/>the moon, generalizes still farther the analogy
                    of<lb/>formation here adverted to. In maps of the moon,<lb/>we observe in our
                    satellite, without atmosphere<lb/>and without water, vast craters of elevation,
                    which<lb/>surround conical mountains, or support them on<lb/>their circular
                    walls; unquestionable effects of the<lb/>reaction of the interior of the moon
                    upon her exte-<lb/>rior, aided by the influence of diminished gravity.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>If, in many languages, volcanoes are properly<lb/>designated Burning Mountains,
                    it would still be a<lb/>great mistake to suppose that they were produced<lb/>by
                    any gradual accumulation of the streams of<lb/>lava that have flowed from them:
                    their origin<lb/>appears to be much more generally the conse-<lb/>quence of a
                    sudden upheaval of tenacious masses<lb/>of trachyte, or augitic rock, including
                    polychroma-<lb/>tic [Labrador] felspar. The measure of the up-<lb/>heaving force
                    reveals itself in the height of the<lb/>volcano; and this is so different, that
                    in one case<lb/>it is a mere hillock (as in Cosima, one of the<lb/>Japanese
                        Kuriles;<note place="foot" n="*"><hi rendition="#i">Vide</hi>
                        Jameson&#x2019;s Edin. Phil. Journal for an interest-<lb/>ing account of
                        Cosima, communicated by Tilesius.</note>) in another, it is a cone
                    that<lb/>rises to an elevation of 18,000 feet. It has seemed<lb/>to me as if the
                    relative height had a great influence<lb/>upon the frequency of the eruptions;
                    as if these<lb/>were much more common in the lower than the<lb/>loftier
                    volcanoes. I will call attention to the fol-<lb/>lowing series: &#x2014;
                    Stromboli, (2175 feet high,) Gua-<lb/>camayo, in the province of Quiros, which
                    thunders<lb/>almost every day, (I have frequently heard it in<lb/>Chilo, near
                    Quito, at a distance of 22 German<lb/>miles,) Vesuvius, (3637 feet high,)
                    &#x00C6;tna, (10,200<lb/>feet high,) the Peak of Teneriffe, (11,424
                    feet<lb/>high,) and Cotopaxi (17,892 feet high)<choice><sic> </sic><corr type="editorial">.</corr></choice> If the<lb/>focus of these
                    several volcanoes be at the same<lb/>depth below the surface, a greater force
                    will be<lb/>required to raise the molten masses to a six or<lb/>eight times
                    higher level. Whilst the low Strom-<lb/>boli (Strongyle) has labored
                    incessantly, at least<lb/>since the times of the Homeric traditions,
                    and<lb/>serves as a light-house to the Tyrrhenian Sea,<lb/>guiding the seaman
                    with its fiery signal on his<lb/>course, the more lofty volcanoes are
                    characterized<lb/>by lengthened periods of repose. The eruptions<lb/>of the
                    greater number of the colossal volcanoes<lb/>that crown the Andes, occur at
                    intervals almost of<lb/>a century apart; where exceptions to this rule<lb/>have
                    been observed&#x2014;and I long ago directed<lb/>attention to them&#x2014;they
                    may probably be connected<lb/>with the circumstance, that the
                    communication<lb/>between the volcanic focus and the crater of
                        erup-<cb/><lb/><pb n="255" facs="#f0005"/> tion is not, and cannot be
                    conceived to be, equally<lb/>or permanently free in every volcano at all
                    times.<lb/>In the less elevated volcanoes the channel of com-<lb/>munication may
                    be closed for a season; so that<lb/>their eruptions become rarer, without their
                    being,<lb/>on this account, any nearer to extinction.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>With the consideration of the relation between<lb/>the absolute height of
                    volcanoes, and the frequency<lb/>of their activity, in so far as this is
                    externally visi-<lb/>ble, the place at which the lava flows out is
                    closely<lb/>connected. Eruptions from the crater are ex-<lb/>tremely rare in the
                    case of many volcanoes; they<lb/>generally proceed from the lateral fissures,
                    (as no-<lb/>ticed by the celebrated historian, Bembo, in the<lb/>sixteenth
                    century, whilst yet a youth,) at places<lb/>where the flanks of the uplifted
                    mountain, in con-<lb/>sequence of their shape and position, offer the
                    least<lb/>amount of resistance. Upon these fissures cones<lb/>of eruption are
                    occasionally raised. The larger of<lb/>these are of such dimensions that they
                    are often<lb/>erroneously designated by the title of new volca-<lb/>noes. Ranked
                    side by side, they show the direc-<lb/>tion of a fissure which has again become
                    closed:<lb/>the smaller ones frequently occur in groups, close-<lb/>ly set
                    together, and cover whole districts, as it<lb/>were, with bell-shaped, or
                    beehive-like, elevations.<lb/>To the latter class belong the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >hornitos</hi> of Jorullo,<lb/>and the cone of the eruption of Vesuvius of
                    Octo-<lb/>ber, 1822, of the volcano of Awatscha, according<lb/>to Postels, and
                    of the lava field near the Baidare<lb/>mountains, in the peninsula of
                    Kamtschatka, ac-<lb/>cording to Erman.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>When volcanoes do not rise free and isolated<lb/>from a plain, when, on the
                    contrary, they are sur-<lb/>rounded by table-lands from 9,000 to 12,000
                        feet<note place="foot" n="*"><hi rendition="#i">French</hi> feet in this and
                        every other instance in the<lb/>present paper.</note><lb/>high, as in the
                    double chain of the Andes of Quito,<lb/>this circumstance may very well give
                    rise to the<lb/>fact that the most violent eruptions, when red-hot<lb/>ashes and
                    scori&#x00E6; are thrown out with detonations<lb/>that are heard for hundreds of
                    miles around, are<lb/>never accompanied with <hi rendition="#i">streams of
                        lava.</hi> This is<lb/>the case with the volcanoes of Popayan, of
                    the<lb/>lofty plains of Los Pastos, and of the Andes of<lb/>Quito; the single
                    volcano of Antisana, among the<lb/>latter, perhaps excepted.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The height of the <hi rendition="#i">cone of ashes,</hi> and the dimen-<lb/>sions
                    and form of the <hi rendition="#i">crater,</hi> are the elements in<lb/>the
                    figure of volcanoes which more particularly im-<lb/>press upon each of them an
                    individual character;<lb/>but of these elements, both the cone and the
                    crater<lb/>are perfectly independent of the magnitude of the<lb/>whole mountain.
                    Vesuvius is not one third of the<lb/>height of the Peak of Teneriffe, yet its
                    cone of<lb/>ashes forms one third of the whole height of the<lb/>mountain,
                    whilst the cone of ashes of the peak is<lb/>only one twenty-second of the entire
                    elevation. In<lb/>the case of another volcano of much greater height<lb/>than
                    the peak, that of Rucu-Pinchincha, namely,<lb/>the relations come nearer to
                    those of Vesuvius.<lb/>Of all the volcanoes I have seen in either
                    hemi-<lb/>sphere, Cotopaxi is that of which the conical form<lb/>is the most
                    regular and beautiful. A sudden melt-<lb/>ing of the snow of its cone of ashes
                    indicates the<lb/>proximity of an eruption. Before there is even<lb/>any smoke
                    visible in the attenuated strata of the<lb/>atmosphere that surround the summit
                    of the cra-<lb/>ter&#x2019;s mouth, the walls of the ash-cone are
                    some-<lb/>times heated through, when the entire mountain<lb/>presents the most
                    threatening and ill-omened as-<lb/>pect.</p>
                <cb/>
                <lb/>
                <p>The crater which, except in very rare cases, oc-<lb/>cupies the summit of the
                    volcano, forms a deep,<lb/>and often accessible, basin-shaped valley,
                    whose<lb/>bottom is subject to incessant changes. The<lb/>greater or less depth
                    of the crater is, in many vol-<lb/>canoes, an indication of the proximity or
                    remote-<lb/>ness of an eruption. In the basin-shaped crater,<lb/>extensive
                    fissures open and close again alternately,<lb/>through which vapors of various
                    kinds find vent,<lb/>or small, rounded, and fiery openings, filled
                    with<lb/>molten matters are seen. The floor rises and falls,<lb/>and in it are
                    formed hillocks of ashes and cones of<lb/>eruption, which occasionally rise high
                    above the<lb/>edges of the crater, and give the volcano its char-<lb/>acteristic
                    physiognomy for years; but, on the oc-<lb/>currence of fresh eruptions, they
                    sink suddenly<lb/>down and disappear. The openings of these cones<lb/>of
                    eruption, which rise from the floor of the crater,<lb/>must not, as is too
                    frequently done, be confounded<lb/>with the crater itself, which encircles them.
                    When<lb/>the crater is inaccessible, from its vast depth, and<lb/>the
                    perpendicular inward slope of its sides, as<lb/>in the case of Rucu-Pichincha,
                    (14,946 feet high,)<lb/>one can still look down from the edges upon
                    the<lb/>summits of the monticules which rise within the<lb/>cauldron-like
                    crater, partially filled with sulphure-<lb/>ous vapor. A more wonderful or
                    grander natural<lb/>prospect I have never enjoyed. In the interval be-<lb/>tween
                    two eruptions, the crater of a volcano may<lb/>exhibit no luminous phenomenon,
                    but merely open<lb/>fissures and jets of watery vapor; or hillocks of<lb/>ashes,
                    that can be approached without danger, are<lb/>found upon its scarcely-heated
                    bottom. These<lb/>often gratify the wandering geognost, without<lb/>making him
                    run any risk, by casting out glowing<lb/>masses, which fall on the edges of the
                    cone of sco-<lb/>ri&#x00E6;, their appearance being regularly announced
                    by<lb/>slight, and entirely local, shocks&#x2014;earthquakes on<lb/>a small
                    scale. Lava occasionally flows from open<lb/>fissures, or small fiery gorges,
                    into the crater itself,<lb/>without bursting through its walls, or
                    overflowing<lb/>its edges. But if it does break through, the mol-<lb/>ten spring
                    generally flows smoothly, and in such a<lb/>determinate direction, that the
                    great cauldron-like<lb/>valley, called the crater, can still be visited
                    during<lb/>the period of the eruption. Without a particular<lb/>description of
                    the form, and also of the normal<lb/>structure of burning mountains, phenomena
                    cannot<lb/>be rightly comprehended which have been distorted<lb/>by fantastical
                    descriptions, and the various signifi-<lb/>cations attached to the words, <hi
                        rendition="#i">Crater, Cone of<lb/>eruption,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Volcano;</hi> or rather, to the indefinite<lb/>and indeterminate use of
                    these words. The edges<lb/>of the crater sometimes show themselves much
                    less<lb/>liable to change than might be expected. A com-<lb/>parison of De
                    Saussure&#x2019;s measurements with my<lb/>own, yields the remarkable result, in
                    connection<lb/>with Vesuvius at least, that the northwest edge of<lb/>the
                    volcano, the Rocca del Palo, may be regarded<lb/>as having remained for
                    forty-nine years (1773&#x2014;<lb/>1822) almost without change in its elevation
                    above<lb/>the level of the sea. Any difference that appears<lb/>may be looked on
                    as within the possible errors of<lb/>measurement.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Volcanoes whose summits reach far above the<lb/>limits of perpetual snow, like
                    those of the Andes,<lb/>present a variety of peculiar features. The sud-<lb/>den
                    melting of the snow in the course of an erup-<lb/>tion, not only occasions
                    destructive floods, tor-<lb/>rents in which heaps of smoking ashes are
                    floated<lb/>away on blocks of ice; but the accumulation of ice<lb/>and snow goes
                    on producing its influence uninter-<lb/>ruptedly, and by filtration, into the
                    trachytic rocks,<cb/><lb/><pb n="256" facs="#f0006"/>even whilst the volcano is perfectly
                    quiescent.<lb/>Caverns are thus gradually formed on the declivi-<lb/>ties or at
                    the foot of the burning mountain, and<lb/>these become subterraneous reservoirs
                    of water,<lb/>which communicate in various ways, by narrow<lb/>mouths, with the
                    alpine rivulets of Quito. The<lb/>fishes of these alpine streams multiply
                    greatly,<lb/>particularly in the gloom of the caverns; and then,<lb/>when the
                    earthquakes come, which precede all<lb/>eruptions of volcanoes in the Andes, and
                    the whole<lb/>mass of the mountain is shaken, the subterraneous<lb/>caverns at
                    once give way, and pour out a deluge<lb/>of water, fishes, and tufaceous mud.
                    This is the<lb/>singular phenomenon which the presence of the<lb/>Pimelodes
                    Cyclopum, the Prenadilla of the inhab-<lb/>itants of the lofty plains of Quito,
                    attests. When,<lb/>in the night between the 19th and 20th of June,<lb/>1698, the
                    summit of Carguairazo, a burning moun-<lb/>tain 18,000 feet high, crumbled
                    together, so that<lb/>no more than two enormous rocky horns of the
                    cra-<lb/>ter&#x2019;s edge remained, the country, for nearly two<lb/>square
                    miles, was desolated with liquid tuff and<lb/>argillaceous mud, (lodazales,)
                    enclosing dead fishes.<lb/>In like manner the putrid fever of the
                    mountain<lb/>town, Ibarra, to the north of Quito, which occurred<lb/>seven years
                    before, was ascribed to an eruption of<lb/>fish from the volcano Imbaburnu.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Water and mud, which, in the volcanoes of the<lb/>Andes, do not pour down from
                    the crater itself,<lb/>but from cavities in the trachytic mass of
                    the<lb/>mountains, ought not, consequently, in the strict<lb/>sense of the
                    phrase, to be reckoned among the<lb/>number of proper volcanic phenomena. They
                    are<lb/>only mediately connected with the activity of vol-<lb/>canoes, nearly in
                    the same measure as the irregu-<lb/>lar meteorological process, which, in my
                    early<lb/>writings, I have spoken of under the title of the<lb/><hi
                        rendition="#i">Volcano Storm.</hi> The hot watery vapor which<lb/>rises from
                    the crater, and mingles with the atmos-<lb/>phere during the eruption, forms a
                    cloud as it<lb/>cools, with which the column of ashes and fire,<lb/>many
                    thousand feet in height, is surrounded. So<lb/>sudden a condensation of vapor,
                    and the produc-<lb/>tion of a cloud of enormous superficial
                    dimensions,<lb/>increase the electrical tension, as Gay Lussac has<lb/>shown.
                    Forked lightnings dart from the column<lb/>of ashes, and the rolling thunder of
                    the volcanic<lb/>storm is then plainly distinguished from the rum-<lb/>bling in
                    the interior of the mountain. This was<lb/>well observed towards the end of the
                    eruption of<lb/>Vesuvius, in the month of October, 1822. The<lb/>lightning,
                    which proceeded from the volcanic<lb/>steam-cloud of the Katlagia burning
                    mountain in<lb/>the island of Iceland, according to Olafsen&#x2019;s
                    ac-<lb/>count, upon one occasion, (17th October 1775)<lb/>killed eleven horses
                    and two men.</p>
            </div><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
