<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-21" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="327" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Cosmos: Sketch of a Physical Description of the<lb break="yes"/>Universe.</hi> By <hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von Humboldt.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Vol. 1. Translated under the superintendence<lb break="yes"/>of Lieut.-Col. <hi rendition="#k">Edward Sabine,</hi> R. A., For. Sec.<lb break="yes"/>R. S. Longman and Co. and John Murray.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">This</hi> is the kind of work for which the genius of<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt is best adapted. It is impossible to over-<lb break="no"/>rate the impulse he has given to physical and natu-<lb break="no"/>ral inquiry. With the apt and amiable sentiment<lb break="yes" />of a St. Pierre, he has combined the graphic power<lb break="yes"/>of a Dampier. To these qualifications he has added<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> taste for the pursuits of accurate science, with<lb break="yes"/>patience to master, and power to estimate, the value<lb break="yes"/>of its driest formul&#x00E6;.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From youth until now, Humboldt has been a<lb break="yes"/>wanderer on the face of the earth. An overmaster-<lb break="no"/>ing instinct had taught him that actual observation<lb break="yes"/>alone could be relied upon. He was among the<lb break="yes"/>first to penetrate regions which have since become<lb break="yes"/>familiar to us. The Andes are the only limits of<lb break="yes" />his travels in the west; the confines of Russia and<lb break="yes"/>China in the east. No kind of knowledge has been<lb break="yes"/>unacceptable to him. He studied the statistics of<lb break="yes"/>Mexico and its antiquities; the mineralogy, meteo-<lb break="no"/>rology, and botany of South America, have equally<lb break="yes"/>engaged his attention. Man; all nature, animate<lb break="yes"/>and inanimate; whatever could be known; had<lb break="yes" />attractions for his inquiring spirit. Nor was this<lb break="yes"/>mere desultory curiosity. He regarded the uni-<lb break="no"/>verse as a whole. He recognized the unity and<lb break="yes"/>inter-dependence of all the multifarious objects of<lb break="yes"/>knowledge he had garnered into his mind.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But an intellect so ambitious of grasping all,<lb break="yes"/>could not be expected to find time to master the<lb break="yes"/>details of each. Humboldt has thus been driven to<lb break="yes"/>delegate much to assistants. Yet in this respect,<lb break="yes"/>even more than by his self-labor, he has also been<lb break="yes"/>useful. He has given an impulse to many minds<lb break="yes"/>that without him might have remained inert. At<lb break="yes" />the same time it may be admitted, that to his own<lb break="yes"/>works this method has been unfavorable. They<lb break="yes"/>are often fragmentary, being full of references to<lb break="yes"/>what his coadjutors are doing. They are often<lb break="yes"/>inaccurate when calculations have to be made.<lb break="yes"/>Still pushing onward, he takes little pains to ensure<lb break="yes"/>correctness in others by his own inspection. Lat-<lb break="no" />terly, too, the immense number and variety of his<lb break="yes"/>pursuits must have rendered it impossible for him<lb break="yes"/>to gain time for condensation. And this has some-<lb break="no"/>times impressed a character of diffuseness on his<lb break="yes"/>labors. They are new material, rather than fin-<lb break="no"/>ished works. He is, with all his genius, a &#x201C;grand<lb break="yes"/>baron&#x201D; in science: patronizing, and sometimes<lb break="yes"/>appropriating. He has a strong dash of the<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">philosophe des salons.</hi>&#x201D; Gratified to find his con-<lb break="no"/>versational attractions acknowledged, he indulges<lb break="yes"/>in gossip and compliments.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Still, from the share he has had in communicating<lb break="yes"/>form, impetus, and direction to modern science; for<lb break="yes"/>the universality of his sympathy with every effort<lb break="yes"/>of the intellect and imagination; from the skill and<lb break="yes"/>perseverance with which he has made himself the<lb break="yes"/>connecting link between the patrons and the pro-<lb break="no"/>fessional followers of science;&#x2014;Humboldt must be<lb break="yes"/>regarded as one of the most influential minds of an<lb break="yes"/>age fertile in great intellects. He belongs to the<lb break="yes"/>same class in these respects as Goethe and Vol-<lb break="no" />taire. Fragmentary and often desultory though his<lb break="yes"/>writings may be, they are full of passages of deep<lb break="yes"/>and pregnant thought, and intense poetical beauty.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Cosmos,</hi> the first volume of which is before us,<lb break="yes"/>has more of condensation than his other recent pub-<lb break="no"/>lications. It is the result of the observations,<lb break="yes" />inferences, and conjectures which have occupied his<lb break="yes"/>life; it is a condensed statement of the appearance<lb break="yes"/>which the universe presents to him who bas looked<lb break="yes"/>at it from so many points of view; and the manner,<lb break="yes"/>and all the details of the work, are informed with<lb break="yes"/>that fine artistic touch, that delicate perception, and<lb break="yes"/>exquisite enjoyment of the beautiful, which are the<lb break="yes"/>predominating features of his mind.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We give a few extracts, with the intention of<lb break="yes"/>simply indicating, for the present, the style of the<lb break="yes"/>work.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="328" facs="#f0002"/>
                <cb/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>STUDY OF THE EXTERNAL WORLD.</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Nature is the domain of liberty; and to give a<lb break="yes"/>lively picture of those ideas and those delights<lb break="yes"/>which a true and profound feeling in her contempla-<lb break="no"/>tion inspires, it is needful that thought should<lb break="yes"/>clothe itself freely and without constraint in such<lb break="yes"/>forms and with such elevation of language, as may<lb break="yes"/>be least unworthy of the grandeur and majesty of<lb break="yes"/>creation.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;If the study of physical phenomena is regarded<lb break="yes"/>in its bearings, not on the material wants of man,<lb break="yes"/>but on his general intellectual progress, its highest<lb break="yes"/>result is found in the knowledge of those mutual<lb break="yes"/>relations which link together the various forces of<lb break="yes"/>nature. It is the intuitive and intimate persuasion<lb break="yes"/>of the existence of these relations which at once<lb break="yes"/>enlarges and elevates our views, and enhances our<lb break="yes"/>enjoyment. Such extended views are the growth<lb break="yes"/>of observation, of meditation, and of the spirit of the<lb break="yes"/>age which is ever reflected in the operations of the<lb break="yes"/>human mind whatever may be their direction.<lb break="yes" />Those who by the light of history should trace<lb break="yes"/>back through past ages the progress of physical<lb break="yes"/>knowledge to its early and remote sources, would<lb break="yes"/>learn how for thousands of years the human mind<lb break="yes"/>has labored to lay hold of the sure thread of the<lb break="yes"/>invariability of natural laws, amid the perplexities<lb break="yes"/>of ceaseless change; and in so doing has gradually<lb break="yes"/>conquered, so to speak, great part of the physical<lb break="yes"/>universe. In following back this mysterious track,<lb break="yes"/>still the same image of the <hi rendition="#i" >Cosmos</hi> <choice><sic>reäppears</sic><corr type="editorial">reappears</corr></choice>,<lb break="yes"/>which, in its earlier revelation, showed itself as a<lb break="yes"/>presentiment of the true harmony and order of the<lb break="yes"/>universe, and which, in our days, presents itself as<lb break="yes"/>the fruit of long-continued and laborious observation.<lb break="yes"/>Each of these two epochs of the contemplation of<lb break="yes"/>the external world has its own proper enjoyment:<lb break="yes"/>that belonging to the first awakening of such reflec-<lb break="no"/>tions is well suited to the simplicity of the earlier<lb break="yes"/>ages of the world; to them the undisturbed suc-<lb break="no"/>cession of the planetary movements, and the pro-<lb break="no"/>gressive development of animal and vegetable life,<lb break="yes"/>were pledges of an order yet undiscovered in other<lb break="yes"/>relations, but of which they instinctively divined<lb break="yes"/>the existence. To us in an advanced civilization<lb break="yes"/>belongs the enjoyment of the precise knowledge of<lb break="yes"/>phenomena. From the time when man in interro-<lb break="no" />gating nature began to experiment, or to produce<lb break="yes"/>phenomena under definite conditions, and to collect<lb break="yes"/>and record the fruits of experience, so that investi-<lb break="no"/>gation might no longer be restricted by the short<lb break="yes"/>limits of a single life, the <hi rendition="#i">philosophy of nature</hi> laid<lb break="yes"/>aside the vague and poetic forms with which she<lb break="yes"/>had at first been clothed, and has adopted a more<lb break="yes"/>severe character;&#x2014;she now weighs the value of<lb break="yes"/>observations, and no longer divines, but combines<lb break="yes"/>and reasons. Exploded errors may survive par-<lb break="no"/>tially among the uneducated, aided in some instan-<lb break="no"/>ces by an obscure and mystic phraseology; they<lb break="yes"/>have also left behind them many expressions by<lb break="yes"/>which our nomenclature is more or less disfigured;<lb break="yes"/>while a few of happier, though figurative origin,<lb break="yes"/>have gradually received more accurate definition,<lb break="yes"/>and have been found worthy of preservation in our<lb break="yes"/>scientific language.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The aspect of external nature, as it presents<lb break="yes"/>itself in its generality to thoughtful contemplation,<lb break="yes"/>is that of unity in diversity, and of connection, re-<lb break="no"/>semblance and order, among created things most<lb break="yes"/>dissimilar in their form:&#x2014;one fair harmonious<lb break="yes"/>whole. To seize this unity and this harmony,<lb break="yes"/>amid such an immense assemblage of objects and<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> forces&#x2014;to embrace alike the discoveries of the ear-<lb break="no"/>liest ages and those of our own time&#x2014;and to ana-<lb break="no"/>lyze the details of phenomena without sinking under<lb break="yes"/>their mass&#x2014;are efforts of human reason, in the path<lb break="yes"/>wherein it is given to man to press towards the full<lb break="yes"/>comprehension of nature, to unveil a portion of her<lb break="yes"/>secrets, and, by the force of thought, to subject, so<lb break="yes"/>to speak, to his intellectual dominion, the rough<lb break="yes"/>materials which he collects by observation.&#x201D;</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>KNOWLEDGE HELPS IMAGINATION.</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;It is true that, properly speaking, the forces of<lb break="yes" />nature can only exert over us a magical power, by<lb break="yes"/>their action being to our minds enveloped in obscu-<lb break="no"/>rity, and beyond the conditions of our experience.<lb break="yes"/>Even supposing that they would thus be the better<lb break="yes"/>fitted to excite our imagination, that assuredly is<lb break="yes"/>not the faculty which we should prefer to evoke,<lb break="yes"/>whilst engaged in those laborious subsidiary obser-<lb break="no"/>vations which have for their ultimate object the<lb break="yes"/>knowledge of the grandest and most admirable<lb break="yes"/>laws of the universe. The astronomer occupied in<lb break="yes"/>determining, by the aid of the heliometer, or of the<lb break="yes"/>doubly refracting prism, the diameter of planetary<lb break="yes"/>bodies; or patiently engaged for years in measuring<lb break="yes"/>the meridian altitudes of certain stars and their dis-<lb break="no"/>tances apart&#x2014;or, searching for a telescopic comet<lb break="yes"/>among a crowded group of nebul&#x00E6;, does not feel<lb break="yes"/>his imagination more excited, (and this is the very<lb break="yes"/>warrant of the accuracy of his work,) than the bot-<lb break="no"/>anist who is intent on counting the divisions of the<lb break="yes"/>calix, the number of stamens, or the sometimes<lb break="yes"/>connected, and sometimes independent, teeth of the<lb break="yes"/>capsule of a moss. And yet it is these precise an-<lb break="no"/>gular measurements, and minute organic relations,<lb break="yes"/>which prepare and open the way to the higher<lb break="yes" />knowledge of nature and of the laws of the uni-<lb break="no"/>verse. The physical philosopher (as Thomas<lb break="yes"/>Young, Arago, and Fresnel) measures with ad-<lb break="no"/>mirable sagacity the waves of light of unequal<lb break="yes"/>length, which by their interferences reinforce or<lb break="yes"/>destroy each other, even in respect to their chemi-<lb break="no"/>cal action; the astronomer, armed with powerful<lb break="yes"/>telescopes, penetrates space, and contemplates the<lb break="yes"/>satellites of Uranus at the extreme confines of our<lb break="yes"/>solar system, or (like Herschel, South, and Struve)<lb break="yes"/>decomposes faintly sparkling points into double<lb break="yes"/>stars, differing in color and revolving round a com-<lb break="no"/>mon centre of gravity; the botanist discovers the<lb break="yes"/>constancy of the gyratory motion of the chara in<lb break="yes"/>the greater number of vegetable cells, and recog-<lb break="no"/>nizes the intimate relations of organic forms in<lb break="yes"/>genera, and in natural families. Surely the heaven<lb break="yes"/>studded with stars and nebul&#x00E6;, and the rich vege-<lb break="no"/>table covering which mantles the earth in the cli-<lb break="no"/>mate of palms, can scarcely fail to produce on<lb break="yes"/>these laborious observers impressions more imposing<lb break="yes"/>and more worthy of the majesty of creation, than on<lb break="yes"/>minds unaccustomed to lay hold of the great mutual<lb break="yes"/>relations of phenomena. I cannot therefore agree<lb break="yes"/>with Burke when he says, that our ignorance of<lb break="yes"/>natural things is the principal source of our admira-<lb break="no"/>tion and of the feeling of the sublime. The illusion<lb break="yes"/>of the senses, for example, would have nailed the<lb break="yes"/>stars to the chrystalline dome of the sky; but as-<lb break="no"/>tronomy has assigned to space an indefinite extent;<lb break="yes"/>and if she has set limits to the great nebula to<lb break="yes"/>which our solar system belongs, it has been to<lb break="yes"/>show us further and further beyond its bounds (as<lb break="yes"/>our optic powers are increased) island after island<lb break="yes"/>of scattered nebul&#x00E6;. The feeling of the sublime,<lb break="yes"/>so far as it arises from the contemplation of physi-<lb break="no"/>cal extent, reflects itself in the feeling of the infi-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="329" facs="#f0003"/>
                        <cb/> nite which belongs to another sphere of ideas. That<lb break="yes" />which it offers of solemn and imposing it owes to<lb break="yes"/>the connection just indicated; and hence the anal-<lb break="no"/>ogy of the emotions and of the pleasure excited in<lb break="yes"/>us in the midst of the wide sea; or on some lonely<lb break="yes"/>mountain summit, surrounded by semi-transparent<lb break="yes"/>vaporous clouds; or, when placed before one of<lb break="yes"/>those powerful telescopes which resolve the remoter<lb break="yes"/>nebul&#x00E6; into stars, the imagination soars into the<lb break="yes"/>boundless regions of universal space.&#x201D;</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>SCIENTIFIC INQUIRY AND NATIONAL PROSPERITY.</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;An equal appreciation of all parts of natural<lb break="yes" />knowledge is an especial requirement of the present<lb break="yes"/>epoch, in which the material wealth and the in-<lb break="no"/>creasing prosperity of nations are in great measure<lb break="yes"/>based on a more enlightened employment of natu-<lb break="no"/>ral products and forces. The most superficial<lb break="yes"/>glance at the present condition of European states<lb break="yes"/>shows, that those which linger in the race cannot<lb break="yes"/>hope to escape the partial diminution, and perhaps<lb break="yes"/>the final annihilation, of their resources. It is with<lb break="yes"/>nations as with nature, which, according to a happy<lb break="yes"/>expression of Goethe, knows no pause in unceasing<lb break="yes"/>movement, development, and production, and has<lb break="yes"/>attached a curse to standing still. The danger to<lb break="yes"/>which I have alluded must be averted by the ear-<lb break="no"/>nest cultivation of natural knowledge. Man can<lb break="yes"/>only act upon nature, and appropriate her forces to<lb break="yes"/>his use, by comprehending her laws, and knowing<lb break="yes"/>those forces in relative value and measure. Bacon<lb break="yes"/>has said that, in human societies, knowledge is<lb break="yes"/>power&#x2014;both must rise or sink together. Knowledge<lb break="yes"/>and thought are at once the delight and the prerog-<lb break="no"/>ative of man; and they are also a part of the<lb break="yes" />wealth of nations, and often afford to them an<lb break="yes"/>abundant indemnification for the more sparing be-<lb break="no"/>stowal of natural riches. Those states which<lb break="yes"/>remain behind in general industrial activity, in the<lb break="yes"/>selection and preparation of natural substances, in<lb break="yes"/>the application of mechanics and chemistry&#x2014;and<lb break="yes"/>where a due appreciation of such activity fails to<lb break="yes"/>pervade all classes&#x2014;must see their prosperity<lb break="yes"/>diminish; and that the more rapidly as neighboring<lb break="yes"/>states are meanwhile advancing, both in science<lb break="yes"/>and in the industrial arts, with, as it were, renewed<lb break="yes"/>and youthful vigor.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The improvement of agriculture in the hands<lb break="yes"/>of freemen, and on properties of moderate extent&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>the flourishing state of the mechanical arts freed<lb break="yes"/>from the trammels of the spirit of corporation&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>commerce augmented and animated by the multi-<lb break="no"/>plied contact of nations with each other&#x2014;are bril-<lb break="no"/>liant results of the general progress of intelli-<lb break="no"/>gence, and of the amelioration of political and civil<lb break="yes"/>institutions in which that progress is reflected.<lb break="yes"/>The picture presented by modern history ought to<lb break="yes"/>convince those who seem tardy in apprehending the<lb break="yes"/>instruction which it is fitted to convey. Nor let it<lb break="yes"/>be feared that the predilection for industrial pro-<lb break="no"/>gress, and for those branches of natural science<lb break="yes"/>most immediately connected with it, which charac-<lb break="no"/>terise the age in which we live, has any necessary<lb break="yes"/>tendency to check intellectual exertion in the fair<lb break="yes"/>fields of classical antiquity, history, and philosophy;<lb break="yes"/>or to deprive of the life-giving breath of imagina-<lb break="no"/>tion, the arts and the literature which embellish<lb break="yes"/>life. Where all the blossoms of civilization unfold<lb break="yes"/>themselves with vigor under the shelter of wise<lb break="yes"/>laws and free institutions, there is no danger of the<lb break="yes"/>development of the human mind in any one direc-<lb break="no"/>tion proving prejudicial to it in others. Each offers<lb break="yes"/>to the nation precious fruits&#x2014;those which furnish<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> necessary subsistence and comfort, and are the<lb break="yes" />foundation of material wealth&#x2014;and those fruits of<lb break="yes" />creative fancy which, far more enduring than that<lb break="yes"/>wealth, transmit the glory of the nation to the<lb break="yes"/>remotest posterity. The Spartans, in spite of the<lb break="yes"/>Doric severity of their mode of thought, &#x2018;prayed<lb break="yes"/>the gods to grant them the beautiful with the<lb break="yes"/>good.&#x2019;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;As in that higher sphere of thought and feeling<lb break="yes"/>to which I have just alluded, in philosophy, poetry,<lb break="yes"/>and the fine arts, the primary aim of every study<lb break="yes"/>ought to be an inward one, that of enlarging and<lb break="yes"/>fertilizing the intellect; so the direct aim of science<lb break="yes"/>should ever be the discovery of laws, and of the<lb break="yes"/>principles of unity, order, and connection, which<lb break="yes"/>everywhere reveal themselves in the universal life<lb break="yes"/>of nature. But by that happy connection, whereby<lb break="yes"/>the useful is ever linked with the true, the exalted,<lb break="yes"/>and the beautiful, science thus followed for her<lb break="yes"/>own sake will pour forth abundant, overflowing<lb break="yes"/>streams, to enrich and fertilize that industrial pros-<lb break="no"/>perity, which is a conquest of the intelligence of<lb break="yes"/>man over matter.&#x201D;</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>WORDS AND THOUGHTS.</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Thought and language are of old intimately<lb break="yes"/>allied; if the language employed lends to the<lb break="yes"/>presentation grace and clearness; if by its organic<lb break="yes"/>structure, its richness, and happy flexibility, it fa-<lb break="no"/>vors the attempt to delineate the phenomena of na-<lb break="no"/>ture, it at the same time reacts almost insensibly<lb break="yes"/>on thought itself, and breathes over it an animating<lb break="yes"/>influence. <hi rendition="#i">Words</hi>, therefore, are more than signs<lb break="yes"/>and forms; and their mysterious and beneficient in-<lb break="no"/>fluence is there most powerfully manifested, where<lb break="yes"/>the language has sprung spontaneously from the<lb break="yes"/>minds of the people, and on its own native soil.<lb break="yes"/>Proud of my country, whose intellectual unity is the<lb break="yes"/>firm foundation of every manifestation of her<lb break="yes"/>power, I look with joy to these privileges of my<lb break="yes"/>native land. Highly favored, indeed, is he, who, in<lb break="yes"/>attempting an animated representation of the phe-<lb break="no"/>nomena of the universe, is permitted to draw from<lb break="yes"/>the depths of a language, which through the eleva-<lb break="no"/>tion and free exercise of powerful thought, in the<lb break="yes"/>domain of creative fancy no less than in that of<lb break="yes"/>searching reason, has for centuries exerted so pow-<lb break="no"/>erful an influence over the minds and the destinies<lb break="yes"/>of men.&#x201D;</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>THE IGNORANCE OF KNOWLEDGE.</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Doubtless, a considerable portion of the proper-<lb break="no"/>ties of matter are still unknown to us; entire<lb break="yes"/>series of phenomena dependent on forces and qual-<lb break="no"/>ities of which we are ignorant, remain to be discov-<lb break="no"/>ered; and were it for this reason only, we must<lb break="yes"/>fail of the perfect attainment of unity in totality.<lb break="yes"/>By the side of the pleasure derived from knowledge<lb break="yes"/>already attained, there subsists, not unmixed with<lb break="yes"/>melancholy, the longing of the aspiring spirit, still<lb break="yes"/>unsatisfied with the present, after regions yet un-<lb break="no"/>discovered and unopened. Such longing draws<lb break="yes"/>still closer the link which, by ancient and deep-<lb break="no"/>seated laws of the world of thought, connects the<lb break="yes"/>material with the immaterial, and quickens the in-<lb break="no"/>terchange between that which the mind receives<lb break="yes"/>from without, and that which it gives back from its<lb break="yes"/>own depths.&#x201D;</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>METEORIC MASSES.</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The largest meteoric masses yet known to us<lb break="yes"/>are those of Bahia in Brazil, and of Otumpa, de-<lb break="no"/>scribed by Rubin de Celis; these are seven and<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="330" facs="#f0004"/>
                        <cb/> seven and a half feet in length. The meteoric<lb break="yes"/>stone of &#x00C6;gos Potamos, celebrated in antiquity, and<lb break="yes"/>mentioned in the Chronicle of the Parian Marbles,<lb break="yes"/>and which fell about the year of the birth of Socrates,<lb break="yes"/>has been described as being of the size of two mill-<lb break="no"/>stones, and equal in weight to a full wagon load.<lb break="yes"/>Notwithstanding the failure of the efforts of the<lb break="yes"/>African traveller, Browne, I have not given up the<lb break="yes"/>hope that this Thracian meteoric mass, which must<lb break="yes"/>have been so difficult to destroy, may be found,<lb break="yes"/>after the lapse of more than 2,300 years, by some<lb break="yes"/>of the European visitors to countries which have<lb break="yes"/>now become so easy of access. We learn by a<lb break="yes" />document lately discovered by Pertz, that the enor-<lb break="no"/>mous aerolite which, in the beginning of the tenth<lb break="yes"/>century, fell into the river near Narni, projected<lb break="yes"/>nearly four feet above the surface of the water. It<lb break="yes"/>must be remarked that these meteoric stones,<lb break="yes"/>whether ancient or modern, cannot be regarded as<lb break="yes"/>more than principal fragments of the mass which<lb break="yes"/>exploded in the fire-ball, or descended from the<lb break="yes"/>dark cloud.&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A more detailed estimate of the work we reserve<lb break="yes"/>until its completion. The translation has been well<lb break="yes"/>executed by Mrs. Sabine; and Col. Sabine has dis-<lb break="no"/>charged the functions of editor with care and judg-<lb break="no"/>ment.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 