<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="172" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">man&#x2014;races&#x2014;language.</hi></head><lb/><p>The present races of animals have been produced by<lb/>the combined action of many different internal, as well as<lb/>external conditions, the nature of which cannot in all cases<lb/>be defined, the most striking varieties being found in those<lb/>families which are capable of the greatest distribution over<lb/>the surface of the earth. The different races of mankind<lb/>are forms of one sole species, by the union of two of whose<lb/>members descendants are propagated. They are not dif-<lb/>ferent species of a genus, since in that case their hybrid<lb/>descendants would remain unfruitful. But whether the<lb/>human races have descended from several primitive races of<lb/>men, or from one alone, is a question that cannot be deter-<lb/>mined from experience.</p><lb/><p>Languages, as intellectual creations of man, and as closely<lb/>interwoven with the development of mind, are, indepen-<lb/>dently of the <hi rendition="#i">national</hi> form which they exhibit, of the<lb/>greatest importance in the recognition of similarities or<lb/>differences in races. This importance is especially owing<lb/>to the clue which a community of descent affords in treading<lb/>that mysterious labyrinth in which the connection of physical<lb/>powers and intellectual forces manifests itself in a thousand<lb/>different forms. The brilliant progress made within the last<lb/>half century, in Germany, in philosophical philology, has<lb/>greatly facilitated our investigations into the <hi rendition="#i">national</hi> cha-<lb/><pb n="173" facs="#f0002" />
racter of languages, and the influence exercised by descent.<lb/>But here, as in all domains of ideal speculation, the dangers<lb/>of deception are closely linked to the rich and certain profit<lb/>to be derived.</p><lb/><p>Positive ethnographical studies, based on a thorough<lb/>knowledge of history, teach us that much caution should<lb/>be applied in entering into these comparisons of nations,<lb/>and of the languages employed by them at certain epochs.<lb/>Subjection, long association, the influence of a foreign re-<lb/>ligion, the blending of races, even when only including a<lb/>small number of the more influential and cultivated of the<lb/>immigrating tribes, have produced, in both continents, simi-<lb/>larly recurring phenomena; as, for instance, in introducing<lb/>totally different families of languages amongst one and the<lb/>same race, and idioms, having one common root, amongst<lb/>nations of the most different origin. Great Asiatic con-<lb/>querors have exercised the most powerful influence on phe-<lb/>nomena of this kind.</p><lb/><p>But language is a part and parcel of the history of the<lb/>development of mind; and, however happily the human<lb/>intellect, under the most dissimilar physical conditions, may<lb/>unfettered pursue a self-chosen track, and strive to free<lb/>itself from the dominion of terrestrial influences, this eman-<lb/>cipation is never perfect. There ever remains, in the natural<lb/>capacities of the mind, a trace of something that has been<lb/>derived from the influences of race or of climate, whether<lb/>they be associated with a land gladdened by cloudless azure<lb/>skies, or with the vapoury atmosphere of an insular region.<lb/>As, therefore, richness and grace of language are unfolded<lb/>from the most luxuriant depths of thought, we have been<lb/>unwilling wholly to disregard the bond which so closely<lb/>links together the physical world with the sphere of intellect<lb/>and of the feelings, by depriving this general picture of<lb/>nature of those brighter lights and tints, which may be bor-<lb/>rowed from considerations, however slightly indicated, of<lb/>the relations existing between races and languages.</p><lb/><p>Whilst we maintain the unity of the human species, we<lb/>at the same time repel the depressing assumption of superior<lb/>and inferior races of men. There are nations more suscep-<lb/>tible of cultivation, more highly civilised, more ennobled by<lb/>mental cultivation than others&#x2014;but none in themselves<lb/>nobler than others. All are in like degree designed for<lb/>freedom &#x2014; a freedom which in the ruder conditions of<lb/><pb n="174" facs="#f0003" />
society belongs only to the individual, but which in social<lb/>states enjoying political institutions appertains as a right to<lb/>the whole body of the community. If we would indicate<lb/>an idea which throughout the whole course of history has<lb/>ever more and more widely extended its empire&#x2014;or which,<lb/>more than any other, testifies to the much contested and<lb/>still more decidedly misunderstood perfectibility of the whole<lb/>human race&#x2014;it is that of establishing our common hu-<lb/>manity&#x2014;of striving to remove the barriers which prejudice<lb/>and limited views of every kind have erected amongst men,<lb/>and to treat all mankind without reference to religion, na-<lb/>tion, or colour, as one fraternity, one great community,<lb/>fitted for the attainment of one object, the unrestrained<lb/>development of the moral faculties. This is the ultimate<lb/>and highest aim of society, identical with the direction im-<lb/>planted by nature in the mind of man towards the indefinite<lb/>extension of his existence. He regards the earth in all its<lb/>limits, and the heavens, as far as his eye can scan their<lb/>bright and starry depths, as inwardly his own, given to him<lb/>as the objects of his contemplation, and as a field for the<lb/>development of his energies. Even the child longs to pass<lb/>the hills or the seas which enclose his narrow home; yet<lb/>when his eager steps have borne him beyond those limits,<lb/>he pines, like the plant, for his native soil; and it is by this<lb/>touching and beautiful attribute of man&#x2014;this longing for<lb/>that which is unknown, and this fond remembrance of that<lb/>which is lost&#x2014;that he is spared from an exclusive attach-<lb/>ment to the present. Thus deeply rooted in the innermost<lb/>nature of man, and even enjoined upon him by his highest<lb/>tendencies, the recognition of the bond of humanity be-<lb/>comes one of the noblest leading principles in the history<lb/>of mankind.</p><lb/><p>With these words, which draw their charm from the depths<lb/>of feeling, let a brother be permitted to close this general<lb/>description of the natural phenomena of the universe. From<lb/>the remotest nebul&#x00E6;, and from the revolving double stars,<lb/>we have descended to the minutest organisms of animal<lb/>creation, whether manifested in the depths of ocean or on<lb/>the surface of our globe, and to the delicate vegetable germs<lb/>which clothe the naked declivity of the ice-crowned moun-<lb/>tain summit; and here we have been able to arrange these<lb/>phenomena according to partially known laws; but other<lb/>laws of a more mysterious nature rule the higher spheres of<lb/><pb n="175" facs="#f0004" />
the organic world, in which is comprised the human species<lb/>in all its varied conformation, its creative intellectual power,<lb/>and the languages to which it has given existence. A<lb/>physical delineation of nature terminates at the point where<lb/>the sphere of intellect begins, and a new world of mind is<lb/>opened to our view. It marks the limit, but does not pass<lb/>it.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi>.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
