<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="82" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#b">The Planetary System, as it is now Un-<lb/>derstood.</hi></head><lb/><p>Sir J. Herschel has lately expressed his opin-<lb/>ion, that it is impossible any longer to attempt<lb/>the explanations of the movements of all the<lb/>heavenly bodies by simple gravitation, as un-<lb/>derstood in the Newtonian theory&#x2014;these com-<lb/>ets, with their trains perversely turned from<lb/>the sun, deranging sadly our systematic views.<lb/>Nor are there (writes Humboldt) any constant<lb/>relations between the distances of the planets<lb/>from the central body round which they re-<lb/>volve, and their absolute magnitudes, densi-<lb/>ties, times of rotation, eccentricities, and in-<lb/>clinations of orbit or axis. We find Mars,<lb/>though more distant from the sun than either<lb/>the earth or Venus, inferior to them in magni-<lb/>tude; Saturn is less than Jupiter, and yet<lb/>much larger than Uranus. The zone of the<lb/>telescopic planets, which are so inconsiderable<lb/>in point of volume, viewed in the series of dis-<lb/>tances commencing from the sun, comes next<lb/>before Jupiter, the greatest in size of all the<lb/>planetary bodies. Remarkable as is the small<lb/>density of all the colossal planets which are<lb/>farthest from the sun, yet neither in this res-<lb/>pect can we recognize any regular succession.<lb/>Uranus appears to be denser than Saturn, and<lb/>(though the inner group of planets differ but<lb/>little from each other in this particular) we find<lb/>both Venus and Mars less dense than the<lb/>earth, which is situated between them. The<lb/>time of rotation increases, on the whole, with<lb/>increasing solar distance, but yet it is greater<lb/>in Mars than in the earth, and in Saturn than<lb/>in Jupiter. After other remarks of the same<lb/>character, he adds, &#x201C;The planetary system, in<lb/>its relation of absolute magnitude, relative<lb/>position of the axis, density, time of rotation,<lb/>and different degrees of eccentricity of the or-<lb/>bits, has, to our apprehension, nothing more<lb/>of natural necessity than the relative distribu-<lb/>tion of land and water on the surface of our<lb/>globe, the configuration continents, or the ele-<lb/>vation of mountain chains. No general law,<lb/>in these respects, is discoverable either in the<lb/>regions of space or in the irregularities of the<lb/>crust of the earth.<choice><sic></sic><corr type="editorial">&#x201D;</corr></choice></p><lb/><p>[We have endeavored to find out the place<lb/>where, and when, Sir John expressed himself,<lb/>as stated in the above extract, taken from an<lb/>exchange, but have not been able. It is en-<lb/>tirely opposed to the opinions of other eminent<lb/>astronomers, and especially to Dr. Nichols,<lb/>whose lectures in this country, are printed and<lb/>cheap, and should be read by every person.<choice><sic></sic><corr type="editorial">]</corr></choice></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
