<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="594" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#b">The Planetary System.</hi></head><lb/><p>Sir J. Herschel has lately expressed his opinion<lb/>that it is impossible any longer to attempt the expla-<lb/>nation of the movements of all the heavenly bodies<lb/>by simple attraction, as understood in the Newtoni-<lb/>an theory, these comets<choice><sic>.</sic><corr type="editorial">,</corr></choice> with their trains perversely<lb/>turned from the sun, deranging sadly our systema-<lb/>tic views. Nor are there [writes Humboldt] any<lb/>constant relations between the distances of the<lb/>planets from the central body round which they re-<lb/>volve and their absolute <choice><sic>magnituder</sic><corr type="editorial">magnitudes</corr></choice>, densities, times<lb/>of rotation, eceentricities, and inclinations of orbit<lb/>or axis. We find Mars, though more distant from<lb/>the sun than either the Earth or Venus, inferior to<lb/>them in magnitude; Saturn is less than Jupiter,<lb/>and yet much larger than Uranus. The zone of the<lb/>telescopic planets, which are so inconsiderable in<lb/>point of volume viewed in the series of distances<lb/>commencing from the sun, comes next before Jupi-<lb/>ter, the greatest in size of all the planetary bodies.<lb/>Remarkable as is the small density of all the colos-<lb/>sal planets which are farthest from the sun, yet nei-<lb/>ther in this respect can we recognize any regular<lb/>succession. Uranus appears to be denser than Sa-<lb/>turn, and [though the inner group of planets differ<lb/>but little from each other in this particular] we find<lb/>both Venus and Mars less dense than the Earth,<lb/>which is situated between them. The time of rota-<lb/>tion increases, on the whole, with increasing solar<lb/>distance; but yet it is greater in Mars than in the<lb/>Earth, and in Saturn than in Jupiter. After other<lb/>remarks of the same character, he adds: &#x201C;The<lb/>planetary system, in its relation of absolute magni-<lb/>tude, relative position of the axis, density, time of<lb/>rotation, and different degrees of eccentricity of the<lb/>orbits, has, to our apprehension, nothing more of<lb/>natural necessity than the relative distribution of<lb/>land and water on the surface of our globe, the con-<lb/>figuration of continents, or the elevation of moun-<lb/>tain chains. No general law, in these respects, is<lb/>discoverable either in the regions of space or in the<lb/>irregularities of the crust of the earth.<choice><sic></sic><corr type="editorial">&#x201D;</corr></choice></p></div><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
