<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Depth of Coal and other Mines</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:11</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VI.62</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1845-On_the_known-8-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-1-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-7-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-8-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-9-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Depth of Coal and other Mines</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1851</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Mining Manual and Almanack for 1851, Being a Yearly Compendium of Information on General Science, with Tabular and Other Statistical Details Relating to the Mining Interests&lt;/i&gt; (1851), S. 329–330.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="329" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Depth of Coal and other Mines.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;In speaking of the greatest<lb/>depths within the earth reached by human labour, we must recollect that<lb/>there is a difference between the <hi rendition="#i">absolute</hi> depth (that is the depth below<lb/>the earth&#x2019;s surface at that point) and the <hi rendition="#i">relative</hi> depth (or that beneath<lb/>the level of the sea). The greatest relative depth that man has hitherto<lb/>reached, is probably the bore at the new salt-works at Minden, in Prussia.<lb/>In June, 1844, it was exactly 1,993 feet, the absolute depth being 2,231 feet.<lb/>The temperature of the water at the bottom was 91° Fahr., which, assuming<lb/>the mean temperature of the air at 49&#x00B7;3, gives an augmentation of tem-<lb/>perature of a degree for every 54 feet. [At this rate of increase of heat, a<lb/><pb n="330" facs="#f0002" />
    stratum of granite would be in a state of fusion at a depth of nearly twenty-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>one geographical miles, or between four and five times the elevation of the<lb/>highest summit of the Himalaya.] The absolute depth of the Artesian<lb/>well of Grenelle, near Paris, is only 1,795 feet. The wells sunk by the<lb/>Chinese, for the purpose of obtaining carburetted hydrogen gas for salt-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>boiling, commonly exceed 2,000 feet, whilst one is said to be of the depth<lb/>of 3,197 feet. The relative depth reached at Mount Massi, in Tuscany,<lb/>south of Volterra, amounts to only 1,253 feet. The boring at the new salt-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>works at Minden is probably of about the same relative depth as the coal-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>mine at Apendale, near Newcastle-under-Lyne, where men work 2,175<lb/>feet below the surface of the earth. Unfortunately, I do not know the<lb/>exact height of its mouth above the level of the sea. The relative depth of<lb/>the Monkwearmouth mine (Sunderland) is only 1,496 feet. That of the<lb/>Liege coal-mine, <hi rendition="#i">L&#x2019;Espérance</hi>, at Seraing, is 1,355 feet; and the old mine<lb/>of Marihaye, in the valley of the Maes, is 1,233 feet in depth. The works<lb/>of greatest absolute depth that have ever been formed, are for the most<lb/>part situated in such elevated plains or valleys that they either do not<lb/>descend so low as the level of the sea, or, at most, reach very little below<lb/>it. Thus at Eselschacht, in Bohemia, a mine, which cannot now be worked,<lb/>had the enormous absolute depth of 3,778 feet; also, at St. Daniel, and at<lb/>Geish, on the Rörerbühel, there were, in the sixteenth century, excavations<lb/>of 3,107 feet&#x2014;the plans of the works being still preserved. The absolute<lb/>depth of the mines in the Saxon Erzgebirge, near Frieburg, are, in the<lb/>Thurmofer Mine, 1,944 feet; in the Honenbirker Mines, 1,827 feet; the<lb/>relative depths being, however, only 677 and 277 feet. The absolute depth<lb/>of the celebrated mine of Joachimstal, in Bohemia, is full 2,120 feet. In the<lb/>Harz the Samson Mine, at Andreasberg, has an absolute depth of 2,197 feet.<lb/>In what was formerly Spanish America, I know of no mine deeper than the<lb/>Valenciana (Mexico), where I found the absolute depth of the Planes de<lb/>San Bernando to be 1,686 feet; but these planes are 5,960 feet above the<lb/>level of the sea. If we compare the depth of the old Kultenburger Mine<lb/>(a depth greater than the height of the Brocken, and only 200 feet less than<lb/>that of Vesuvius) with the loftiest structures that the hands of man have<lb/>erected (with the pyramid of Cheops, and with the cathedral of Strasburg),<lb/>we find that they stand in the ratio of eight to one. In this notice I have<lb/>collected all the certain information I could find regarding the greatest<lb/>absolute and relative depths of mines and borings. In descending east-<lb/>ward from Jerusalem towards the Dead Sea, a view presents itself to the<lb/>eye which, according to our present hypsometrical knowledge of the surface<lb/>of our planet, is unrivalled in any country. As we approach the open<lb/>ravine through which the Jordan takes its course, we tread, with the open<lb/>skies above us, on rocks which, according to the barometric measurements<lb/>of Berton and Russegger, are 1,385 feet below the level of the Mediterranean.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
