<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="6" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1">
    <p><hi rendition="#k">The Universal Brotherhood of Man.</hi>&#x2014;While we<lb/>maintain the unity of the human species, we, at the same<lb/>time, repel the distressing assumption of superior and<lb/>inferior races of men. There are nations more suscep-<lb/>tible of cultivation, more highly civilized, more ennobled<lb/>by mental cultivation than others&#x2014;but none in them-<lb/>selves nobler than others. All are in like degree designed<lb/>for freedom; a freedom which, in the ruder conditions<lb/>of society, belongs only to the individual; but which, in<lb/>social states, enjoying political institutions, appertains<lb/>as a right to the whole body of the community. If we<lb/>would indicate an idea which, throughout the whole<lb/>course of history, has ever more and more widely ex-<lb/>tended its empire&#x2014;or which, more than any other, tes-<lb/>tifies to the much contested and more misunderstood<lb/>perfectibility of the whole human race&#x2014;it is that of es-<lb/>tablishing our common humanity&#x2014;of striving to remove<lb/>the barriers which prejudice and limited views of every<lb/>kind have erected among men, and to treat all mankind,<lb/>without reference to religion, nation, or colour, as one<lb/>fraternity, one great community, fitted for the attainment<lb/>of one object&#x2014;the unrestrained development of the phy-<lb/>sical powers. This is the ultimate and highest aim of<lb/>society, identical with the direction implanted by nature<lb/>in the mind of man towards the indefinite extension of<lb/>his existence. He regards the earth in all its limits, and<lb/>the heavens, as far as his eye can scan their bright and<lb/>starry depths, as inwardly his own; given to him as ob-<lb/>jects for contemplation, and as a field for the develop-<lb/>ment of his energies. Even the child longs to pass the<lb/>hills or the seas which enclose his narrow home; yet when<lb/>his eager steps have borne him beyond those limits, he<lb/>pines, like the plant, for his native soil; and it is by this</p>
    <cb/>
    <p>touching and beautiful attribute of man&#x2014;this longing for<lb/>that which is unknown,
                    and this fond remembrance of<lb/>that which is lost&#x2014;that he is spared
                    from an exclusive<lb/>attachment to the present. Thus deeply rooted in
                    the<lb/>innermost nature of man, and even enjoined upon him by<lb/>his highest
                    tendencies, the recognition of the bond of<lb/>humanity becomes one of the
                    noblest leading principles<lb/>in the history of mankind.&#x2014;<hi
                        rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Cosmos.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
