<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="134" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">THE VOLCANIC STORM.</hi></head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">Water</hi> and mud, which, in the volcanoes of the Andes, do not<lb/>pour down from the crater itself, but from cavities in the trachytic<lb/>mass of the mountains, ought not, consequently, in the strict sense<lb/>of the phrase, to be reckoned among the number of proper volcanic<lb/><pb n="135" facs="#f0002" />
phenomena. They are only mediately connected with the activity of<lb/>volcanoes, nearly in the same manner as the irregular meteorological<lb/>process, which, in my early writings, I have spoken of under the title<lb/>of <hi rendition="#i">Volcano Storm</hi>. The hot watery vapour which rises from the<lb/>crater, and mingles with the atmosphere during the eruption, forms a<lb/>cloud as it cools, with which the column of ashes and fire, many<lb/>thousand feet in height, is surrounded. So sudden a condensation of<lb/>vapour, and the production of a cloud of enormous superficial dimen-<lb/>sions, increase the electrical tension, as Gay Lussac has shewn.<lb/>Forked lightnings dart from the column of ashes, and the rolling<lb/>thunder of the volcanic storm is then plainly distinguished from the<lb/>rumbling in the interior of the mountain. This was well observed<lb/>towards the end of the eruption of Vesuvius, in the month of October<lb/>1822. The lightning which proceeded from the volcanic steam-cloud<lb/>of the Katlagia burning mountain in the island of Iceland, according<lb/>to Olafsen&#x2019;s account, upon one occasion (17th October, 1755) killed<lb/>eleven horses and two men. &#x2014; <hi rendition="#i">From Baron Humboldt&#x2019;s Kosmos.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
