<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1">
        <head>
            <hi rendition="#k">First Impression of an Earthquake.</hi>
        </head>
        <p>&#x2014;Before we<lb/>quit this great phenomenon, we must advert to that in-<lb/>describable, deep, and peculiar impression which the first<lb/>earthquake that we experience makes upon us, even when<lb/>unaccompanied with subterranean noises. The impression<lb/>is not, I believe, the consequence of any recollection of<lb/>destructive catastrophes presented to our imagination by<lb/>historical narratives. That which seizes upon us so won-<lb/>derfully is the disabuse of our innate faith in the firmness<lb/>of the solid and sure-set foundations of the earth. From<lb/>infancy, we are accustomed to the contrast between the<lb/>moveable element of water, and the immutability of the<lb/>soil on which we stand&#x2014;a belief confirmed by the evi-<lb/>dences of our senses. But, when the ground suddenly rocks<lb/>beneath us, the feeling of an unknown mysterious power in<lb/>nature coming into action, and shaking the solid globe,<lb/>arises in the mind. The illusion of our early life is in-<lb/>stantaneously annihilated. We are undeceived as to the<lb/>repose of nature; we feel ourselves transported to the<lb/>realm, and subjected to the empire of destructive, unknown<lb/>powers. Every sound&#x2014;the slightest rustle in the air&#x2014;sets<lb/>attention on the rack, and we no longer trust the earth on<lb/>which we stand. The unusualness of the phenomenon<lb/>throws the same anxious unrest and alarm over the lower<lb/>animals. Swine and dogs are particularly affected by it;<lb/>and the very crocodiles of the Orinoco, otherwise as dumb<lb/>as our lizards, leave the trembling bed of the stream, and<lb/>rush bellowing into the woods. To man, the earthquake is<lb/>something unlimited and all-pervading. We can remove<lb/>from the active crater of a volcano; we can escape from<lb/>the flood of lava that is pouring down upon our dwelling;<lb/>but with the earthquake we feel that, whithersoever we fly,<lb/>we are still over the hearth of destruction.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s<lb/>Kosmos.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
