<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Hot springs</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:10</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VI.51</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-4-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-1-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-4-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-7-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos: A General Survey of the physical phenomena of the universe&lt;/i&gt;, Bd. 1, London: Hippolyte Baillière 1845, S. 232–235.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos. Entwurf einer physischen Weltbeschreibung&lt;/i&gt;, Stuttgart/Tübingen: Cotta 1845, Bd. 1, 229–232.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Hot springs</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1846</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Year-Book of Facts in Science and Art&lt;/i&gt; (1846), S. 135–136.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="135" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">HOT SPRINGS, BY HUMBOLDT.</hi></head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">Hot Springs,</hi> burst out of the most diversified mineral strata;<lb/>the hottest of all the permanent springs which have yet been ob-<lb/>served, and which I myself discovered, flow remote from all volcanoes.<lb/>I here refer to the Aguas calientes des Las Trincheras between Porto<lb/>Cabello and New Valencia, in South America, and to the Aguas de<lb/>Comangillas, near Guanaxuato, in Mexico. The first spring, issuing<lb/>from granite, indicated 90&#x00B7;3° C.; the second, which issues from<lb/>basalt, shewed 96&#x00B7;4° C. The depth of the source of water of these<lb/>temperatures, from what we know of the law of increase of tempera-<lb/>ture in the interior of the earth, must probably be about 6700 feet<lb/>(more than half a geographical mile). If the cause of the heat of<lb/>thermal springs, as well as of active volcanoes, be the universally dif-<lb/>fused heat of the earth, then would rocks produce an effect only<lb/>through their capacity for, and their power of conducting, heat.<lb/>The hottest of all the permanent springs, those, namely, from 95° to<lb/>97° C. (204° to 207&#x00B7;6° F.), it is remarkable, are the purest, are<lb/>those that contain the smallest quantity of mineral matter in solution.<lb/>Their temperature appears, on the whole, to be less permanent than<lb/>that of springs between 50° and 74° C., the invariableness of which,<lb/>both in regard to temperature and mineral impregnation, has been<lb/>maintained so wonderfully, within the confines of Europe at least,<lb/>during the last fifty or sixty years, <hi rendition="#i">i. e.</hi> since accurate thermometrical<lb/>observation and chemical analyses were made. Boussingault found<lb/>that the thermal springs of Las Trincheras had risen in temperature,<lb/>in the course of twenty-three years (from 1800, when my journey was<lb/>performed, to 1823), from 93&#x00B7;3° to 97° C. This very smoothly-<lb break="maybe"/>flowing spring is, consequently, at this time 7° C. higher in tempera-<lb/>ture than the intermitting Geyser and Strokr, the temperature of<lb/>which has been lately more carefully ascertained by Krug of Nidda.<lb/>One of the most remarkable proofs of the origin of these hot springs<lb/><pb n="136" facs="#f0002" />
    being due to the percolation of cold meteoric water into the interior<lb/>of the earth, and its contact there with a volcanic focus, was presented<lb/>in the preceding century, in connexion with the volcano of Jorullo in<lb/>Mexico, which was unknown to geography till after my South Ameri-<lb/>can journey. When this mountain suddenly made its appearance in<lb/>September 1759, rising to a height of 1580 feet above the surround-<lb/>ing level, the two small streams Rios de Cuitimba y de San Pedro dis-<lb/>appeared; but some time afterwards they made their appearance<lb/>again, under the dreadful shocks of an earthquake, as hot springs.<lb/>In 1803, I found their temperature <choice><sic>658</sic><corr type="editorial">65&#x00B7;8</corr></choice>° C.</p><lb/><p>The observations made by Arago in 1821, that the deeper Artesian<lb/>wells are the warmer, was the first means of throwing a great light<lb/>upon the origin of thermal springs, and led to the discovery of the<lb/>law of the increase of the temperature of the earth according to the<lb/>depth. It is remarkable, and only noticed in very recent times, that<lb/>St. Patricius, probably Bishop of Pertusa, was led to a very correct<lb/>view of the phenomenon which presented itself in the appearance of<lb/>hot springs near Carthage, at the end of the third century. When<lb/>questioned as to the cause of the boiling-hot water which poured out<lb/>from the earth, he answered:&#x2014;&#x201C;Fire is nourished in the clouds, and<lb/>in the interior of the earth, as Etna, and another mountain in the<lb/>neighbourhood of Naples, inform you. The subterranean waters rise<lb/>as through syphons; and the cause of the heat of hot springs is this:<lb/>the waters that are remote from the subterraneous fires show them-<lb/>selves colder; those that flow in closer proximity to the fire,<lb/>warmed by it, bring an insupportable heat to the surface which we<lb/>inhabit.&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">From Baron Humboldt&#x2019;s Cosmos.</hi></p></div><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
