<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="132" facs="#f0001" />
<milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
    
    <div n="1">
        <head>
            PHYSIOGNOMY OF THE EARTH&#x2019;S SURFACE.
        </head><lb/>
        <p><hi rendition="#k">One</hi> of the most valuable contributions to physical science, during<lb/><pb n="133" facs="#f0002" /> the past year, has been the publication of Baron von Humboldt&#x2019;s<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Kosmos</hi>, Vol. I., whence we extract a few striking passages: &#x2014; In the<lb/>present state of the surface of our planet, the area of the solid land<lb/>bears to that of the sea the proportion of 1 to 2&#x2158; (according to Rigaud<note place="foot" n="*">Transactions of the Cambridge Philosophical Society, vol. vi., p. 2, 1837,<lb/>p. 297. According to other authorities the proportion is as 100 : 284.</note><lb/>of 100 to 270.) The islands form scarcely <hi rendition="#sup">1</hi>/<hi rendition="#sub">23</hi> of the continental<lb/>masses. The latter are so unequally distributed, that they form three<lb/>times as much land in the northern hemisphere as in the southern.<lb/>The southern hemisphere, therefore, is peculiarly and predominantly<lb/>oceanic. From 40° S.L. to the antarctic pole, the crust of the earth<lb/>is almost entirely covered with water. The liquid element is just as<lb/>predominant, and is only interrupted by widely-scattered groups of<lb/>islands, between the east coast of the old and the west coast of the new<lb/>world. The learned hydrographer, Fleurieu, has very properly dis-<lb/>tinguished this vast basin of the sea by the name of the <hi rendition="#i">great ocean</hi>.<lb/>Within the tropics, it includes a space of 145° of longitude. The<lb/>southern and western hemispheres (reckoning westward from the<lb/>meridian of Teneriffe) are, therefore, the regions containing the most<lb/>water of the whole surface of the globe.
        </p><lb/>
        <p>These, then, are the principal facts regarding the relative <hi rendition="#i">quantity</hi><lb/>of the solid land and the sea, a relation which so powerfully influences<lb/>the distribution of temperature, the variations in the pressure of the<lb/>air, the direction of the winds, and the amount of moisture in the at-<lb/>mosphere, &#x2014; the last being a feature which acts very essentially on<lb/>vegetation. When we reflect that an extent of nearly three-fourths of<lb/>the surface<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">During the middle ages an opinion prevailed that sea covered only the<lb/>one-seventh part of the surface of the earth; an idea which Cardinal D&#x2019;Ailly<lb/>(<hi rendition="#i">Imago Mundi, cap.</hi> 8) founded on a passage in the Apocrypha. Columbus,<lb/>who always drew his cosmological knowledge from the works of the Cardinal,<lb/>had a great interest in defending this opinion as to the smallness of the sea,<lb/>to which, no doubt, the misunderstood expression of the &#x201C;River Ocean&#x201D; had<lb/>led. <hi rendition="#i">Vide Humboldt, Exam. Critique de l&#x2019;Hist. de la Géographie</hi>, t. i., p. 186.</note> of our planet is covered with water, we are the less sur-<lb/>prised at the imperfect state of meteorology up to the present century:<lb/>an epoch in which, for the first time, a considerable number of accurate<lb/>observations on the temperature of the sea in different latitudes, and<lb/>in different seasons, were obtained, and numerically compared with<lb/>one another.
        </p><lb/>
        <p>We can, to a certain extent, determine, from the estimated amounts,<lb/>where the plutonic force of the interior of the globe has operated with<lb/>greatest power in elevating continental masses.</p><lb/>
        <p>The following, on plutonic agency, is striking: &#x2014; There is nothing<lb/>to assure us that the same plutonic forces may not, in the course of<lb/>future ages, make additions to the systems of mountains of different<lb/>degrees of antiquity, and having different directions, as they are<lb/>enumerated by Elie de Beaumont. Why should the crust of the<lb/>earth have already lost the property of becoming elevated or folded?<lb/>The mountain-systems of the Alps and of the Andes, which were<lb/>almost the last that made their appearance, have elevated colossal<lb/><pb n="134" facs="#f0003"/> masses in Mont Blanc and Monte Rosa, in Sorata, Illimani, and<lb/>Chimborazo, masses which do not at all lead to the conclusion that<lb/>there had been a diminution in the intensity of subterranean power.<lb/>All the phenomena of geognosy indicate a periodical alternation of<lb/>activity and tranquillity.<note place="foot" n="*"><hi rendition="#i">Vide</hi> the Second Geological Letter from Elie de Beaumont to Alexander<lb/>von Humboldt, in <hi rendition="#i">Poggendorff&#x2019;s Annalen</hi>, vol. xxv. pp. 1-58.</note> The repose which we now enjoy is only<lb/>apparent. Earthquakes, which agitate the surface of the earth in<lb/>every region under heaven, and in every kind of rock&#x2014;the rising of<lb/>Sweden, and the production of new volcanic islands, do not give<lb/>evidence in favour of the tranquillity of the earth.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">From <hi rendition="#i">Kosmos Entwurf einer Physischen Weltbeschreibung von Alexander<lb/>von Humboldt,</hi> vol. i., p. 301. 1845.</note>&#x2014;(Translated in<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Jameson&#x2019;s Journal</hi>, No. 77.)
        </p>
    </div><lb/>
</body>
    <back/>
</text>
</TEI>
