<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="105" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">On the Physiognomy of the Surface of the Earth.</hi> By <hi rendition="#k">Baron<lb/>Alexander von Humboldt.</hi></head><lb/><p>The recent progress of geognosy, or, in other words, the<lb/>extended knowledge of those <hi rendition="#i">geognostical epochs</hi> which are<lb/>characterised by mineralogical differences in the rock-forma-<lb/>tions, by the peculiarity and succession of the organisms they<lb/>include, and by relative position (the elevation, or the undis-<lb/>turbed horizontality of the strata), leads us, in following the<lb/>causal connection of the phenomena, to the consideration of<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">distribution of the solid and the liquid portions,</hi> that is to<lb/>say, of the continents and the seas which form the surface of<lb/>our planet. We here refer to a point of connection between<lb/>historical and geographical geognosy, to the whole consider-<lb/>ation of the conformation and horizontal configuration of con-<lb/>tinents. The boundary of the solid by the liquid parts, or the<lb/>areal relation of the one to the other, has been very various<lb/>during the course of the long succession of geognostical<lb/>epochs; according as the strata of the coal formation were<lb/>deposited on the elevated strata of the mountain limestone<lb/>and the old red sandstone; the Lias and Jura formations on<lb/>the shores of the <hi rendition="#i">Keuper</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Muschelkalk;</hi> or the chalk on<lb/>the declivities of the Greensand and the Jura limestone. If,<lb/>following Elie de Beaumont, we designate by the term <hi rendition="#i">Jura</hi><lb/>and <hi rendition="#i">Chalk seas,</hi> the waters under which the Jura limestone<lb/><pb n="106" facs="#f0002" />
and chalk were precipitated in a muddy condition, then the<lb/>outlines of these two formations indicate, for two epochs, the<lb/>boundary between the still stone-producing ocean and the solid<lb/>land which had previously been laid dry. The ingenious idea<lb/>has been suggested, of preparing maps of this physical portion<lb/>of <hi rendition="#i">ancient geography;</hi> maps which, perhaps, are more trust-<lb/>worthy than those of the wanderings of Io or those of the<lb/>Homeric geography. The latter exhibit opinions and mytho-<lb/>logical representations; the former present the earliest facts<lb/>of the positive doctrine of formations.</p><lb/><p>The result of investigations regarding the superficial rela-<lb/>tions of dry land is, that in the earliest periods, viz. in the<lb/>Silurian and Devonian transition-epoch, as well as in the first<lb/>floetz period, including the trias, the uncovered surface which<lb/>was clothed by land plants, was limited to detached islands;<lb/>that afterwards these islands were united with one another,<lb/>and included many lakes along the deeply penetrating bays<lb/>of the sea; and, lastly, that when the mountain chains of the<lb/>Pyrenees, the Apennines, and the Carpathians were elevated,<lb/>therefore at the period of the deposition of the older tertiary<lb/>strata, vast continents, having nearly their present size,<lb/>made their appearance. In the Silurian world, as well as<lb/>during the period characterised by a profusion of Cycade&#x00E6;<lb/>and by gigantic Saurians, the amount of dry land from pole<lb/>to pole was probably less than it is at present in the South<lb/>Sea and the Indian Sea. I shall afterwards explain how this<lb/>excessive prevalence of water, in combination with other<lb/>causes, contributed to the elevation of temperature, and to<lb/>the greater uniformity of climate. At present it is only<lb/>necessary to remark, in considering the gradual enlargement<lb/>(agglutination) of the elevated dry tracts of land, that shortly<lb/>before the revolutions which, after shorter or longer pauses,<lb/>produced, during the <hi rendition="#i">diluvial period,</hi> the sudden destruction<lb/>of so many gigantic vertebrate animals, portions of the now<lb/>existing continental masses were then completely separated<lb/>from one another. Great similarity prevails in South Ame-<lb/>rica and Australia between the living and the extinct ani-<lb/>mals. In New Holland, fossil remains of kangaroos have<lb/>been discovered; and in New Zealand, semifossil bones have<lb/><pb n="107" facs="#f0003" />
been found of an enormous ostrich-like bird (Owen&#x2019;s Dinor-<lb/>nis), which is nearly related to the Apteryx of the present<lb/>day, and is but little connected with the Dodo of the island<lb/>of Rodriguez, so lately become extinct.</p><lb/><p>The present configuration of the continents probably owes<lb/>its elevation above the surrounding seas chiefly to the erup-<lb/>tion of quartziferous porphyries; an eruption which affected<lb/>so powerfully the first great terrestrial flora,&#x2014;that flora which<lb/>afforded the material for coal. What we term the plains of<lb/>continents, are only the broad ridges of hills and mountains,<lb/>whose bases are situated at the bottom of the sea. Every<lb/><hi rendition="#i">plain</hi> is, according to its submarine relations, a <hi rendition="#i">table-land,</hi><lb/>whose inequalities are concealed by new sedimentary for-<lb/>mations deposited in a horizontal position, and by alluvial<lb/>matter.</p><lb/><p>Among the general considerations belonging to the extended<lb/>view we are now taking of our globe, the first rank is to be<lb/>assigned to the <hi rendition="#i">quantity</hi> of elevated solid land which projects<lb/>above the sea; and to this determination of the amount, there<lb/>then succeeds the consideration of the individual <hi rendition="#i">configuration<lb/>with reference to the horizontal extension</hi> (the relations of the<lb/>division of parts: <hi rendition="#i">Gliederungs-Verhältnisse</hi>), or <hi rendition="#i">with reference<lb/>to the perpendicular elevation</hi> (the hypsometrical relations of<lb/>mountain-chains.) Our planet has two envelopes, a general<lb/>one, the atmosphere, an elastic fluid; and a particular one,<lb/>only locally distributed, which bounds the solid land and<lb/>thus affects its form, viz., the sea. Both envelopes of our<lb/>planet, the air and the sea, form <hi rendition="#i">a natural whole</hi>, which gives<lb/>rise to the diversity of climate of the earth&#x2019;s surface: accord-<lb/>ing to the amount of the relative extent of sea and land, the<lb/>horizontal division (<hi rendition="#i">Gliederung</hi>) and position of the solid land,<lb/>and the direction and height of the mountain chains. It re-<lb/>sults from this knowledge of the mutual action of the <hi rendition="#i">air</hi>,<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">sea</hi>, and the <hi rendition="#i">land</hi>, that great meteorological phenomena<lb/>cannot be understood, if separated from geognostical consi-<lb/>derations. Meteorology, like the geography of plants and<lb/>animals, has only begun to make progress since observers<lb/>became convinced of the mutual dependence of the funda-<lb/>mental phenomena. The word <hi rendition="#i">climate</hi> no doubt means, in<lb/><pb n="108" facs="#f0004" />
    the first instance, a particular state of the atmosphere; but<lb/>this condition of the atmosphere is dependent on the con-<lb/>tinual <hi rendition="#i">combined action</hi> of <hi rendition="#i">the sea</hi>, which is everywhere agi-<lb/>tated to a great depth, and is traversed by currents having<lb/>entirely different temperatures, and of <hi rendition="#i">the dry land</hi>, which<lb/>radiates heat, exhibits all varieties of horizontal configura-<lb/>tion, elevation, and colour, and is either bare or covered with<lb/>woods and plants.</p><lb/><p>In the present state of the surface of our planet, the area<lb/>of the solid land bears to that of the sea the proportion of 1<lb/>to 2<formula notation="TeX">\frac{4}{5}</formula> (according to Rigaud <note place="foot" n="*">Transactions of the Cambridge Philosophical Society, vol. vi. P. 2,<lb/>1837, p. 297. According to other authorities the proportion is as<lb/>100: 284.</note> of 100 to 270.) The islands<lb/>form scarcely <formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{23}</formula> of the continental masses. The latter are<lb/>so unequally distributed, that they form three times as much<lb/>land in the northern hemisphere as in the southern. The<lb/>southern hemisphere, therefore, is peculiarly and predomi-<lb/>nantly oceanic. From 40° S. L. to the antarctic pole, the<lb/>crust of the earth is almost entirely covered with water. The<lb/>liquid element is just as predominant, and is only interrupted<lb/>by widely-scattered groups of islands, between the east coast<lb/>of the old and the west coast of the new world. The learned<lb/>hydrographer, Fleurieu, has very properly distinguished this<lb/>vast basin of the sea by the name of the <hi rendition="#i">great ocean</hi>. Within<lb/>the tropics, it includes a space of 145° of longitude. The<lb/>southern and western hemispheres (reckoning westward from<lb/>the meridian of Teneriffe) are, therefore, the regions con-<lb/>taining the most water of the whole surface of the globe.</p><lb/><p>These, then, are the principal facts regarding the relative<lb/><hi rendition="#i">quantity</hi> of the solid land and the sea, a relation which so<lb/>powerfully influences the distribution of temperature, the vari-<lb/>ations in the pressure of the air, the direction of the winds,<lb/>and the amount of moisture in the atmosphere,&#x2014;the last being<lb/>a feature which acts very essentially on vegetation. When we<lb/>reflect that an extent of nearly three-fourths of the surface<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;" xml:id="fn1-1" next="#fn1-2">During the middle ages an opinion prevailed that the sea covered only<lb/>the one-seventh part of the surface of the earth; an idea which Cardinal</note><lb/><pb n="109" facs="#f0005" />
        of our planet is covered with water, we are the less sur-<lb/>prised at the imperfect state of meteorology up to the pre-<lb/>sent century: an epoch in which, for the first time, a consi-<lb/>derable number of accurate observations on the temperature<lb/>of the sea in different latitudes, and in different seasons, were<lb/>obtained, and numerically compared with one another.</p><lb/><p>The horizontal configuration of the solid land, considered<lb/>with regard to the most general relations of its extension,<lb/>was a subject of ingenious investigation in the early periods of<lb/>Grecian antiquity. The maximum of its extension from west<lb/>to east was investigated, and Dicearchus, according to the<lb/>testimony of Agathemerus, determined it to be in the latitude<lb/>of Rhodes, in a direction running from the Pillars of Hercules<lb/>to Thin&#x00E6;. This is the line which has been termed <hi rendition="#i">the pa-<lb/>rallel of the diaphragm of Dicearchus</hi>, and the astronomical<lb/>accuracy of whose position (investigated by me elsewhere)<lb/>must be regarded with astonishment.<note place="foot" n="*">Agathemerus in Hudson, <hi rendition="#i">Geographi Minores</hi>, t. 2, p. 4. <hi rendition="#i">Vide Hum-<lb/>boldt, Asie Centr</hi>., t. i., pp. 120, 125.</note> Strabo, guided pro-<lb/>bably by Eratosthenos, seems to have been so convinced that<lb/>this parallel of 36°, regarded as the maximum of the exten-<lb/>sion of the world known to him, had an internal cause of con-<lb/>figuration, that he predicted the existence, in the same lati-<lb/>tude, of the solid land whose presence he prophetically con-<lb/>jectured in the northern hemisphere between Iberia and the<lb/>coast of Thin&#x00E6;.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;"><hi rendition="#i">Strabo</hi>, lib. i., p. 65. <hi rendition="#i">Casaub. Vide Humboldt, Examen Crit.,</hi> t. i.,<lb/>p. 152.</note></p><lb/><p>While, as we have already remarked, a considerably larger<lb/>portion of land has been elevated above the level of the sea<lb/>in the one hemisphere of the earth than in the opposite (whe-<lb/>ther the globe be halved through the equator, or through the<lb/>meridian of Teneriffe); both the great masses of land, which<lb/><note place="foot" n="&#x2020;" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1">D&#x2019;Ailly (<hi rendition="#i">Imago Mundi, cap.</hi> 8) founded on a passage in the Apocrypha.<lb/>Columbus, who always drew his cosmological knowledge from the works<lb/>of the Cardinal, had a great interest in defending this opinion as to the<lb/>smallness of the sea, to which, no doubt, the misunderstood expression<lb/>of the &#x201C;River Ocean&#x201D; had led. <hi rendition="#i">Vide Humboldt, Examen Critique de l&#x2019;Hist.<lb/>de la Géographie,</hi> t. i. p. 186.</note><lb/><pb n="110" facs="#f0006" />
are, in fact, true islands, surrounded by the ocean on all sides,<lb/>and which we term the <hi rendition="#i">eastern</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">western</hi> or the <hi rendition="#i">old and new<lb/>continents</hi>, exhibit, along with the most striking contrasts in<lb/>their total configuration, or rather in the <hi rendition="#i">position of their<lb/>larger axes</hi>, considerable resemblance in the details of their<lb/>arrangement, and more especially in the superficial relations<lb/>between the coasts which stand opposite to one another. In the<lb/>eastern continent, the prevailing direction, or the position of<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">long axis</hi>, is from east to west (more correctly from SW. to<lb/>NE.); whereas, in the western continent, it is from S. to N.,<lb/>like that of meridians, (more exactly from SSE. to NNW.).<lb/>Both masses of land are cut off to the north in the direction<lb/>of a parallel of latitude (chiefly in that of 70°), and to the<lb/>south they project in pyramidal points, for the most part with a<lb/>submarine continuation of islands and reefs. This is exhibited<lb/>in the archipelago of Terra del Fuego; in the Lagullas-Bank,<lb/>south of the Cape of Good Hope; and in Van Diemen&#x2019;s Land,<lb/>which is separated from New Holland by Bass&#x2019;s Strait. The<lb/>Northern Asiatic coast projects beyond the above mentioned<lb/>latitude at Cape Taimura (78° 16&#x2032; according to Krusenstern);<lb/>while, from the mouth of the great river Tschukotschja east-<lb/>ward towards Behring&#x2019;s Straits, it reaches only latitude<lb/>66° 3&#x2032;, according to Beechy, at the most eastern promontory<lb/>of Asia, the East Cape of Cook.<note place="foot" n="*">On the subject of the mean latitude of the North Asiatic Coast, and<lb/>the correct designation of Cape Taimura (Cape Siewero&#x2014;Wostotschnoi)<lb/>and North-east Cape (Schalagskoi Mys), <hi rendition="#i">vide Humboldt, Asie Centrale,</hi><lb/>t. iii., pp. 35, 37.</note> The northern coast of the<lb/>New Continent follows pretty exactly the parallel of 70°,<lb/>because southward and northward from Barrow&#x2019;s Straits,<lb/>from Boothia Felix and Victoria Land, all the land consists<lb/>only of detached islands.</p><lb/><p>The pyramidal form of all the southern terminations of<lb/>the continents is one of the <hi rendition="#i">similitudines physic&#x0153; in configura-<lb/>tione mundi</hi> to which Bacon (Lord Verulam) directed atten-<lb/>tion in his <hi rendition="#i">Novum Organum,</hi> and with which Reinhold For-<lb/>ster, the companion of Cook on his second voyage round the<lb/>world, connected some ingenious views. If we proceed east-<lb/>ward from the meridian of Teneriffe, we find that the termi-<lb/><pb n="111" facs="#f0007" />
    nations of the three continents, viz., the southern termina-<lb/>tions of Africa (the extremity of the whole ancient world), of<lb/>Australia, and of South America, gradually approach the<lb/>South Pole. New Zealand, which is fully 12° of latitude in<lb/>length, forms, with great regularity, an intermediate link<lb/>between Australia and South America, ending also with an<lb/>island (New Leinster). It is a remarkable fact, that almost<lb/>precisely in the same meridians in which the terrestrial mass<lb/>of the old continent attains its greatest extension to the south,<lb/>the northern coast also advances most nearly to the North<lb/>Pole. This is a result of the comparison of the Cape of Good<lb/>Hope and the Lagullas Bank with the European North Cape,<lb/>and of the Peninsula of Molucca with the Siberian Cape<lb/>Taimura.<note place="foot" n="*"><hi rendition="#i">Asie Centrale,</hi> t. i., pp. 198-200. The southern extremity of America<lb/>also, together with the Archipelago of Tierra del Fuego, is situated in<lb/>the meridian of the most northern portion of Baffin&#x2019;s Bay and of the<lb/>Great Polar Land, which probably belongs to West Greenland.</note> Whether the two poles of the globe are sur-<lb/>rounded by a zone of solid land, or only by an icy sea covered<lb/>with floetz beds of ice, is unknown to us. Towards the<lb/>North Pole, latitude 82° 55&#x2032; has been reached; and towards<lb/>the South Pole, only that of 78° 10&#x2032;.</p><lb/><p>Just as the great masses of land terminate pyramidally, so<lb/>the same configuration is repeated, and with great variety,<lb/>on the small scale, not only in the Indian Ocean (in the<lb/>peninsulas of Arabia, Hindostan, and Malacca), but also, as<lb/>was pointed out by Eratosthenes and Polybius, in the Medi-<lb/>terranean, where the Iberian, Italian, and Hellenic Penin-<lb/>sulas, were judiciously compared by these ancient authors. <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;"><hi rendition="#i">Strabo,</hi> lib, ii., pp. 92, 108, <hi rendition="#i">Casaub.</hi></note><lb/>Europe, with an area five times smaller than that of Asia,<lb/>is also only a western and much divided peninsula of the<lb/>Asiatic undivided continent; and the climatological relations<lb/>of Europe prove, that it occupies the same position in regard<lb/>to Asia, which Peninsular Brittany does in regard to the<lb/>rest of France.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;" xml:id="fn2-1" next="#fn2-2">Humboldt, <hi rendition="#i">Asie Centrale,</hi> t. iii., p. 25. So early as 1817, in my<lb/>work, <hi rendition="#i">De Distributione Geographica Plantarum secundum C&#x0153;li Temperiem et<lb/>Altitudinen Montium,</hi> I directed attention to the distinction which is so</note> Strabo had already remarked the manner<lb/><pb n="112" facs="#f0008" />
        in which the horizontal division of a continent, or the higher<lb/>development of its form, operates as well on the civilization<lb/>as on the whole state of cultivation of nations; for he ascribes<lb/>peculiar advantages to the very varied configuration of our<lb/>small continent.<note place="foot" n="*">Strabo, lib. ii., p. 126, <hi rendition="#i">Casaub.</hi></note> Africa<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Pliny, (v. i.) says of Africa&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Nec alia pars terrarum pauciores recipit<lb/>sinus.</hi> The small Indian peninsula on this side of the Ganges, with its<lb/>triangular shape, also presents a third very analogous form. In the ancient<lb/>literature of Greece, opinions prevailed of a <hi rendition="#i">regular</hi> configuration of the<lb/>solid land. It was said that there were four gulfs, of which the Persian<lb/>was placed opposite to the Hyrcanian (<hi rendition="#i">i. e.</hi> to the Caspian Sea)&#x2014;(Arrian,<lb/>vii., 16; Plut. <hi rendition="#i">in Vita Alexandri,</hi> cap. 44; Dionys. Perieg., v., 48, and<lb/>630, pp. 11 and 38, <hi rendition="#i">Bernh.</hi>) The four gulfs and the isthmuses were<lb/>even alleged, according to the optical fancies of Agesianarus, to be re-<lb/>flected on the disc of the moon (<hi rendition="#i">Plut. de Facie in Orbe Lun&#x00E6;,</hi> pp. 921, 19.)<lb/>Regarding the <hi rendition="#i">terra quadrifida,</hi> or the four solid lands, of which two were<lb/>said to lie to the north, and two to the south, of the equator, see Ma-<lb/>crobius, <hi rendition="#i">Comm. in Somnium Scipionis,</hi> ii., 9. I have subjected this portion<lb/>of ancient geography, as to which much perplexity prevails, to a new<lb/>and careful examination, in my <hi rendition="#i">Examen Crit. de l&#x2019;Hist. de la Geogr.</hi> t. i.,<lb/>p. 119, 145, 180-185; and also my <hi rendition="#i">Asie Centrale,</hi> t. ii., pp. 172-178.</note> and South America, which, in<lb/>other respects also, exhibit so close a resemblance in their con-<lb/>figuration, have, of all the great masses of land, the simplest<lb/>form of coasts. It is only the eastern coast of Asia which,<lb/>being, as it were, broken up by the eastern currents of the<lb/>sea<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Fleurieu in the <hi rendition="#i">Voyage de Marchand <choice><sic>Antour</sic><corr type="editorial">Autour</corr></choice> du Monde,</hi> t. iv.,<lb/>pp. 38-42.</note> (<hi rendition="#i">fractus ex &#x0153;quore terras</hi>), presents a configuration of a<lb/>very varied nature. There we have peninsulas and neigh-<lb/>bouring islands alternating with one another from the equa-<lb/>tor to lat. 60°.</p><lb/><p>The Atlantic ocean presents all the characters of a <hi rendition="#i">great</hi><lb/><note place="foot" n="&#x2020;" xml:id="fn2-2" prev="#fn2-1">important to climatology and human civilization, of continents having<lb/>uniform, and those having indented coasts:&#x2014;&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Regiones vel per sinus luna-<lb/>tos in longa cornua porrect&#x0153;, angulosis littorum recessibus quasi membratim<lb/>discerpt&#x0153;, vel spatia patentia in immensum, quorum littora nullis incisa angulis<lb/>ambit sine anfractu Oceanus</hi>&#x201D; (pp. 81 and 182.) With regard to the relation<lb/>of the extent of coasts to the area of the continent (which is, at the same<lb/>time, the measure of the accessibility of the interior), see my investiga-<lb/>tions in <hi rendition="#i">Berghaus Annalen der Erdkunde,</hi> vol. xii., 1835, p. 490, and <hi rendition="#i">Phy-<lb/>sikal. Atlas,</hi> 1839, No. 3. p. 69.</note><lb/><pb n="113" facs="#f0009" />
<hi rendition="#i">valley.</hi> It would seem as if, in its case, a flood of water had<lb/>directed its violence, first towards the north-east, then to-<lb/>wards the north-west, and then again towards the north-east.<lb/>The parallelism of the coasts to the north of 10° of south lat.,<lb/>the salient and re-entering angles, the convexity of Brazil<lb/>opposite the Gulf of Guinea, and the convexity of Africa in<lb/>the same latitude with the Gulf of the Antilles, are all in<lb/>favour of this apparently bold idea.<note place="foot" n="*">Humboldt in the <hi rendition="#i">Journal de Physique,</hi> t. liii., 1799, p. 33, and <hi rendition="#i">Rel.<lb/>Hist.,</hi> t. ii., p. 19; t. iii., pp. 189 and 198.</note> In the Atlantic valley,<lb/>as is the case almost everywhere with the configuration of<lb/>great masses of land, coasts which are indented and abound<lb/>in islands are placed opposite to those which are of a uni-<lb/>form character. I have long since directed attention to the<lb/>geographical interest of a comparison of the west coasts of<lb/>Africa and South America in the tropical zone. The gulf-<lb/>like indentation of the African shore at Fernando Po (north<lb/>lat. 4<formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{2}</formula>°), is repeated on the shore of the South Sea, in south<lb/>lat. 18<formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{4}</formula>°, near Arica, where (between the Valle de Arica and<lb/>the Morro de Juan Diaz) the Peruvian coast suddenly alters<lb/>its direction from a south and north one to a north-western<lb/>one. This change of direction extends, in an equal degree,<lb/>to the two parallel ranges of the chain of the Andes: not<lb/>only in the littoral<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Humboldt in <hi rendition="#i">Poggendorff&#x2019;s Annalen der Physik,</hi> vol. xl., p. 171. As<lb/>to the remarkable Fiords of the south-east extremity of America, see<lb/>Darwin&#x2019;s Journal (Narrative of the Voyages of the Adventure and Beagle,<lb/>vol. iii.), 1839, p. 266. The parallelism of the two mountain-chains con-<lb/>tinues from 5° south lat. to 5° north lat. The change of the direction of<lb/>the coast near Arica appears to be the consequence of the <hi rendition="#i">altered strike</hi> of<lb/>the fissure through which the <hi rendition="#i">Cordillera de los Andes</hi> has been elevated.</note> high land, but also in the eastern, which<lb/>was the earliest seat of human cultivation in South America,<lb/>and where the alpine Lake of Titicaca is bounded by the<lb/>colossal mountains of Sorata and Illimani. Further to the<lb/>south, from Valdivia and Chil&#x0153; (south lat. 40° to 42°), through<lb/>the Archipelago <hi rendition="#i">de los Chonos,</hi> as far as Tierra del Fuego, we<lb/>find again repeated the peculiar <hi rendition="#i">fiord-</hi>arrangement (the<lb/>complication of narrow and long indentations) which, in the<lb/>northern hemisphere, is characteristic of the west coasts of<lb/>Norway and Scotland.</p><lb/><pb n="114" facs="#f0010" />
<p>The preceding are the most general considerations regard-<lb/>ing the present configuration of Continents (the extension of<lb/>the solid land in a horizontal direction), which result from a<lb/>survey of the surface of our planet. We have placed to-<lb/>gether the facts on this subject, and the analogies of the form<lb/>of remote portions of the earth, which, however, we do not<lb/>venture to term <hi rendition="#i">laws of the form.</hi> When we observe on the<lb/>slope of an active volcano, as, for example, on Vesuvius, the<lb/>not unfrequent phenomenon of partial elevations, in which<lb/>small portions of the surface, previous to or during an erup-<lb/>tion, have their level changed to the amount of several feet,<lb/>and give rise to roof-like ridges, or to flat eminences; we<lb/>perceive that the elevated portions assume this or that form<lb/>and direction, in consequence of trifling accidental differ-<lb/>ences in the intensity of the subterranean action of the va-<lb/>pours, and of the extent of resistance to be overcome. In<lb/>the same manner, inconsiderable disturbances in the equili-<lb/>brium of the interior of our planet may have caused the ele-<lb/>vating elastic forces to have acted more towards the northern<lb/>than towards the southern half of the earth, and to have<lb/>forced up the solid land in the <hi rendition="#i">eastern</hi> hemisphere in the<lb/>form of a broad connected mass, having its principal axis<lb/>nearly parallel to the equator, and in the <hi rendition="#i">western</hi> and more<lb/>oceanic half of the earth in the form of a narrow mass, having<lb/>the direction of meridians.</p><lb/><p>But little can be ascertained empirically respecting the<lb/>causal connection of these leading points in the formation of<lb/>the dryland&#x2014;of the resemblances and contrasts of its configu-<lb/>ration. We know only this much: that the operating cause<lb/>is subterranean; that the present form of the land was not<lb/>produced at once, but that, from the epoch of the forma-<lb/>tion of the Silurian rocks, up to that of the deposition of the<lb/>Tertiary strata, the land was gradually increased and united<lb/>together by the blending of individual and smaller conti-<lb/>nents, after the occurrence of a variety of oscillating eleva-<lb/>tions and sinkings of the surface. The present configuration<lb/>is the result of two causes, which have operated consecu-<lb/>tively,&#x2014;in the <hi rendition="#i">first</hi> place, a subterranean manifestation of<lb/>power, whose amount and direction we term <hi rendition="#i">accidental,</hi> be-<lb/><pb n="115" facs="#f0011" />
    cause we are not able to determine them, and because, in so<lb/>far as our comprehension is concerned, they are removed<lb/>from the sphere of <hi rendition="#i">necessity;</hi> and, in the <hi rendition="#i">second</hi> place, the<lb/>forces acting at the surface, of which volcanic eruptions,<lb/>earthquakes, and the production of mountain-chains and ma-<lb/>rine currents, have performed the chief part. How entirely<lb/>different would the condition of the temperature of the earth,<lb/>and with it that of vegetation, of agriculture, and of human<lb/>society, have been, if the principal axis of the new Continent<lb/>had been placed in the same position as that of the old,&#x2014;if<lb/>the chain of the Andes, instead of having a meridian-like di-<lb/>rection, had risen up from the east towards the west,&#x2014;if to<lb/>the south of Europe there had been no tropical land (Africa) ra-<lb/>diating heat,&#x2014;if the Mediterranean Sea, which, at one period<lb/>stood in connection with the Caspian and Red Seas, and exer-<lb/>cised so powerful an influence on the progress of human civi-<lb/>lization, had not existed,&#x2014;and if the bottom of that sea had<lb/>been elevated to the same height as the plains of Lombardy<lb/>and Cyrene!</p><lb/><p>The changes in the relative heights of the liquid and<lb/>solid portions of the surface of the earth (changes which,<lb/>while they determine the outlines of the continents, lay dry<lb/>or submerge the low lands) are to be ascribed to the action<lb/>of many non-contemporaneous causes. The most power-<lb/>ful of these have undoubtedly been the force of the elastic<lb/>vapours which are contained in the interior of the earth; the<lb/>sudden <hi rendition="#i">alteration of the temperature</hi><note place="foot" n="*">De la Beche&#x2019;s Sections and Views, 1830, Plate xl.; and Babbage&#x2019;s<lb/>Observation on the Temple of Serapis, 1834. &#x201C;A mass of sandstone,<lb/>five English miles in thickness, when heated to 100° Fahr., would have<lb/>its surface raised to an extent of 25 feet. Heated strata of clay, on the<lb/>other hand, must, by contraction, produce a sinking of the surface.&#x201D;<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Vide</hi> the calculations as to the secular rising of Sweden, on the supposi-<lb/>tion of the small increase of 3°. R., in a mass of rock 140,000 French<lb/>feet thick, heated to the melting point, in Bischof&#x2019;s <hi rendition="#i">Wärmelehre <choice><sic>der</sic><corr type="editorial">des</corr></choice> In-<lb/>nern unseres Erdkörpers,</hi> p. 303.</note> of immense beds of<lb/>rock; the unequal secular loss of heat of the crust and nu-<lb/>cleus of the earth, produced by an elevation (literally folding<lb/>or wrinkling&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Faltung</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">Runzelung</hi>) of the solid surface; and<lb/><pb n="116" facs="#f0012" />
local modifications of the power of attraction,<note place="foot" n="*">Vide <hi rendition="#i">Bessel über Maass und Gewicht,</hi> in <hi rendition="#i">Schumacher&#x2019;s Jahrbuch</hi> for 1840,<lb/>p. 134.</note> and the result-<lb/>ing altered curvature of a portion of the liquid element. It<lb/>appears, according to the opinion now generally entertained<lb/>by geologists, and which is founded on the long-continued<lb/>observation of connected facts, as well as on the important<lb/>analogy of volcanic phenomena, that the <hi rendition="#i">elevation of continents</hi><lb/>is a <hi rendition="#i">real,</hi> and not merely an apparent, elevation. The merit<lb/>of this view belongs to Leopold von Buch, who stated it, and<lb/>first introduced it into science, in the narrative of his im-<lb/>portant journey through Norway and Sweden, performed in the<lb/>years 1806 and 1807.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Vol. ii. (1810), p. 39. See also Hallström, in <hi rendition="#i">Kongl. Vetenskaps&#x2014;Academiens<lb/>Handlingar</hi> (Stockholm), 1823, p. 30; Lyell, in Philosophical<lb/>Transactions for 1835, p. 1; and Blom&#x2019;s <hi rendition="#i">Statistische Beschreibung von<lb/>Norwegen,</hi> 1843, pp. 89&#x2014;116. Although in 1802, Playfair, in his Illus-<lb/>trations of the Huttonian Theory, § 393, and, as Keilhau reminds us (<hi rendition="#i">Om<lb/>Landjordens Stigning in Norge,</hi> in the <hi rendition="#i">Nyt Magazin for Naturvidenskaberne</hi>),<lb/>Jessen the Dane, previously to Playfair, both expressed the conjecture<lb/>that the sea does not sink, but that the solid land of Sweden rises; yet<lb/>these suggestions were entirely unknown to our great geologist Von<lb/>Buch, and exercised no influence on the progress of physical geography.<lb/>Jessen, in his work, entitled <hi rendition="#i">Kongeriget Norge fremstillet efter dets naturlige<lb/>og borgerlige Tilstand; Kjöbenh.</hi> 1763, supported his idea of the causes of<lb/>the change of the relative level of the sea and coasts by the old state-<lb/>ments of Celsius, Kalm, and Dalin. He also advances some confused<lb/>notions regarding the possibility of an internal growth and increase of<lb/>stones (of the rocky surface); but at last declares himself to be in favour<lb/>of the elevation of the land being a consequence of earthquakes. He<lb/>says,&#x2014;&#x201C; Although, immediately after the earthquake (at Egersund), no<lb/>such elevation was remarked, yet other causes may thus have been<lb/>afforded for producing it.&#x201D;</note> Although the whole coast of Sweden<lb/>and Finland is rising (upwards of four English feet in a<lb/>century) from the boundary of northern Schonen (Sölvits-<lb/>borg) to Gefle, and thence as far as Torneo, and from Torneo<lb/>to Abo, yet, on the other hand, according to Nilson, southern<lb/>Sweden is sinking.<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;"><hi rendition="#i">Berzelius&#x2019; Jahresbericht über die Fortschritte der physichen Wissenschaften,</hi><lb/>No. 18, p. 686. The islands of Saltholm, opposite Copenhagen, and<lb/>Bornholm, are rising very slightly; Bornholm scarcely one foot in a<lb/>century. See Forchhammer in the Phil. Mag., series 3, vol. ii., p. 309.</note> The maximum of the elevating force<lb/><pb n="117" facs="#f0013" />
seems to be in northern Lapland. The rising gradually di-<lb/>minishes towards the south as far as Calmar and Sölvitsborg.<lb/>Lines marking the ancient level of the sea, in pre-historical<lb/>periods, are indicated by beds of shells belonging to the sea of<lb/>the present day throughout the whole of Norway,<note place="foot" n="*">Keilhau in the <hi rendition="#i">Nyt. Mag. for Naturvid.</hi> 1832, vol. i., pp. 105&#x2014;254;<lb/>and vol. ii., p. 57; Bravais <hi rendition="#i">sur les lignes d&#x2019;ancien niveau de la Mer,</hi> 1843,<lb/>pp. 15&#x2014;40; and also Darwin on the Parallel roads of Glen-Roy, in the<lb/>Phil. Transactions for 1839, p. 60.</note> from Cape<lb/>Lindesnäs to the North Cape; and very recently their height<lb/>has been accurately measured by Bravais, during a long winter<lb/>residence in Bosekop. They are placed 640 English feet above<lb/>the present mean level of the sea; and they also occur, accord-<lb/>ing to Keilhau and Eugene Robert, on the coasts of Spitzber-<lb/>gen, opposite the North Cape (to the NNW.) Leopold von<lb/>Buch, who was the first to direct attention to the high bed<lb/>of shells at Tromsoe (lat. 69° 40&#x2032;), has shewn that the more<lb/>ancient elevations on the North Sea belong to a different<lb/>class of phenomena from the gentle (not sudden or jerking)<lb/>rising of the Swedish coast in the Bothnian Gulf. Nor must<lb/>the latter phenomenon, so well established by historical evi-<lb/>dence, be confounded with the change of level produced by<lb/>earthquakes (such as is observed on the coasts of Chili and<lb/>Cutch). Very lately the Swedish phenomenon has given<lb/>rise to analogous observations in other countries. A per-<lb/>ceptible <hi rendition="#i">sinking</hi> is sometimes met with, corresponding to the<lb/>rising, as a consequence of the folding or plaiting (<hi rendition="#i">Faltung</hi>)<lb/>of the strata; this is the case in West Greenland (according<lb/>to Pingel and Graah), in Dalmatia, and in Schonen.</p><lb/><p>Since it must be considered as extremely probable, that in<lb/>the early periods of our planet, the oscillating movements,<lb/>that is to say, the rising and sinking, of the surface, were<lb/>more intense than they are at present, we should feel the<lb/>less surprised at finding, in the interior of continents, de-<lb/>tached portions of the earth&#x2019;s surface which occupy a lower<lb/>position than the present general level of the sea. Examples<lb/>of this kind are afforded by the Natron Lakes described by<lb/><pb n="118" facs="#f0014" />
General Andreossy, by the small bitter lakes in the Isthmus<lb/>of Suez, by the Lake of Tiberias, and, above all, by the Dead<lb/>Sea.<note place="foot" n="*"><hi rendition="#i">Humboldt, Asie Centrale,</hi> t. 2, pp. 319-324; t. 3, pp. 549-551. The<lb/>depression of the Dead Sea has been gradually ascertained through<lb/>means of the barometrical measurements of Count Bertou, the much<lb/>more careful measurements of Russegger, and the trigonometrical<lb/>measurement of Lieutenant Symonds of the English navy. The last<lb/>mentioned observer, in a letter addressed by Mr Alderson to the Geo-<lb/>graphical Society of London, and communicated to me by my friend<lb/>Captain Washington, has stated that the difference of level of the surface<lb/>of the Dead Sea and of the highest house in Jaffa is 1605 English feet.<lb/>Mr Alderson believed at that time (November 28, 1841), that the Dead<lb/>Sea was about 1400 English feet below the level of the Mediterranean. In<lb/>a more recent communication by Lieutenant Symonds (Jameson&#x2019;s Jour-<lb/>nal, vol. xxxiv. p. 178), the amount of 1312 English feet is given as the<lb/>final result of two trigonometrical operations agreeing very nearly<lb/>with each other.</note> The level of the waters of the two last mentioned<lb/>lakes is 666 and 1312 English feet lower than the surface of<lb/>the Mediterranean Sea. If we could suddenly remove the<lb/>alluvial matter which covers the strata of rock in so many<lb/>level parts of the earth, it would become manifest how many<lb/>portions of the solid surface of the globe at present occupy<lb/>a lower level than the surface of the ocean. The periodical,<lb/>although irregularly alternating, rise and fall of the Caspian<lb/>Sea, of which I have myself seen distinct traces in the north-<lb/>ern portion of that basin, appears to prove<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;"><hi rendition="#i">Sur la Mobilité du fond de la Mer Caspienne</hi> in my <hi rendition="#i">Asie Centrale,</hi> t.<lb/>ii., pp. 283-294. At my request, the Imperial Academy of Sciences of<lb/>St Petersburg, in 1830, caused the learned natural philosopher Lenz to<lb/>cut fixed marks at particular points (indications shewing the mean level<lb/>of the water at a certain epoch) at Baku, in the Peninsula of Abscheron.<lb/>In 1839 also, in a supplement to the instructions given to Captain Ross<lb/>for the Antarctic expedition, I urged that marks should be cut in the<lb/>rocks of the southern hemisphere, wherever there was an opportunity,<lb/>in the same manner as in Sweden and on the shores of the Caspian Sea.<lb/>If this had been done in the early voyages of Bougainville and Cook,<lb/>we should now know if the secular alteration of the relative heights of<lb/>the sea and land is to be regarded as a general, or only as a local, natural<lb/>phenomenon; and if a law can be recognized as to the direction of the<lb/>points which rise and sink simultaneously.</note> (as is also shewn<lb/><pb n="119" facs="#f0015" />
by the observations made by Darwin in the coral seas),<note place="foot" n="*">As to the sinking and rising of the bottom of the South Sea, and the<lb/>various areas of alternate movements, <hi rendition="#i">vide</hi> Darwin&#x2019;s Journal, pp. 557 and<lb/>561-566.</note><lb/>that, without the occurrence of any actual earthquake, the<lb/>surface of the earth is still subjected to the same gentle and<lb/>progressive oscillations, which were of such general occur-<lb/>rence in early periods, when the thickness of the indurated<lb/>crust of the earth was less considerable.</p><lb/><p>The phenomena on which I have now endeavoured to fix<lb/>attention, remind us of the mutability of the present order<lb/>of things, and of the changes which the outline and configu-<lb/>ration of continents have probably undergone in the course<lb/>of long intervals of time. That which is hardly perceptible<lb/>to immediately following generations, becomes accumulated<lb/>in periods, of the length of whose duration a measure is af-<lb/>forded to us by the movement of the heavenly bodies. The<lb/>eastern coast of the Scandinavian Peninsula has probably<lb/>risen upwards of 340 English feet in eight thousand years;<lb/>and if the movement should prove to be uniform, portions of<lb/>the bottom of the sea, which lie near the coast of the penin-<lb/>sula, and are at present still covered by a stratum of water<lb/>50 fathoms (Brassen) in thickness, will make their appearance<lb/>at the surface, and begin to be laid dry in twelve thousand<lb/>years. But what is the shortness of these intervals of time,<lb/>when compared with the duration of geognostical periods,<lb/>which display to us the succession of formations, and the<lb/>hosts of entirely different extinct organisms! In the same<lb/>manner as we have now been contemplating the phenomenon<lb/>of elevation, we may also, supported by the analogies of ob-<lb/>served facts, assume the possibility of a similar amount of<lb/>sinking, or, in other words, of the depression of whole tracts<lb/>of land. The <hi rendition="#i">mean</hi> height of the non-mountainous portion of<lb/>France does not quite amount to 480 French (511<formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{2}</formula> English)<lb/>feet. When compared with ancient <hi rendition="#i">geognostical periods,</hi> dur-<lb/>ing which greater changes took place in the interior of the<lb/>globe, a very long time would not therefore be requisite for<lb/><pb n="120" facs="#f0016" />
the submersion of a considerable portion of the north-west<lb/>of Europe, and for the outlines of its coast presenting an<lb/>entirely different configuration from their present one. The<lb/>sinking and rising of the solid and liquid portions of the<lb/>surface of the earth, which are so opposed to each other in<lb/>their individual operations, that the rising of the one pro-<lb/>duces the apparent sinking of the other, are the cause of<lb/>all the changes of the form of continents. In a general<lb/>view of physical facts, and in an unbiassed and not one-<lb/>sided statement of natural phenomena, the <hi rendition="#i">possibility</hi> at<lb/>least of a diminution of water, or of an actual sinking of<lb/>the level of the sea, must be mentioned. It cannot be<lb/>doubted, that, during the former elevated temperature of the<lb/>surface of the earth; during the existence of the power of<lb/>engulphing water, which must have been the consequence of<lb/>the occurrence of a larger amount of open fissures; and dur-<lb/>ing the continuance of an entirely different constitution of<lb/>the atmosphere; great changes must at one time have taken<lb/>place in the level of the sea,&#x2014;changes which were dependent<lb/>on the increase or diminution of the liquid on the earth. In<lb/>the present state of our planet, however, there has hitherto<lb/>been an entire absence of direct proofs of a real continued<lb/>diminution or increase of the sea; and there is also an ab-<lb/>sence of evidence of gradual changes in the <hi rendition="#i">mean</hi> height of<lb/>the barometer, at the level of the sea, at the same points of<lb/>observation. According to the observations of Daussy and<lb/>Antonio Nobile, an increase of the height of the barometer<lb/>would of itself produce a lowering of the level of the water.<lb/>As, however, the mean pressure of the atmosphere at the<lb/>level of the ocean is not the same in all latitudes, owing to<lb/>meteorological causes arising from the direction of the wind<lb/>and from moisture, the barometer alone would not afford<lb/>sure evidence of an alteration of the level of the sea. The<lb/>important observations, according to which some sea ports<lb/>in the Mediterranean were, at the beginning of this century<lb/>repeatedly laid dry for periods of many hours, seem to prove<lb/>that a <hi rendition="#i">local</hi> retirement of the sea, and a permanent drying<lb/>up of a small portion of the coast, <hi rendition="#i">can</hi> be produced by a<lb/><pb n="121" facs="#f0017" />
change in the direction and strength of currents of the sea,<lb/>without an actual diminution of water, and without a gene-<lb/>ral depression of the whole ocean. We must be very care-<lb/>ful in our interpretation of the information which has re-<lb/>cently been obtained respecting these complicated pheno-<lb/>mena; for it is easy to ascribe to water, one of the &#x201C;an-<lb/>cient elements,&#x201D; what belongs to two others, viz., earth and<lb/>air.</p><lb/><p>In the same manner as the configuration of continents,<lb/>which we have hitherto been delineating in its <hi rendition="#i">horizontal</hi><lb/>extension, exercises, by means of the <hi rendition="#i">varied form of its out-<lb/>line,</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">äussere Gliederung,</hi>) i.e., by the indentations and pro-<lb/>jections of its coasts, a beneficial influence on climate, com-<lb/>merce, and the progress of cultivation; so there is also a<lb/>kind of <hi rendition="#i">internal division of parts,</hi> by means of perpendicular<lb/>elevation of the surface, (mountain chains and table-lands,)<lb/>which has produced not less important results.</p><lb/><p>Every thing which has produced alternation of forms and<lb/><hi rendition="#i">variety of physiognomy</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">Polymorphy</hi>) on the surface of our<lb/>planet (in addition to mountain chains, we here refer also<lb/>to great lakes, grassy steppes, and even to deserts surround-<lb/>ed by woody regions which may be compared to coasts), im-<lb/>presses a peculiar character on the social condition of the<lb/>population. Elevated tracts of country, covered by snow,<lb/>prevent intercourse; but a mixture of lower <hi rendition="#i">detached moun-<lb/>tain masses</hi><note place="foot" n="*">Humboldt, <hi rendition="#i">Rel. Hist.,</hi> t. iii. p. 233-234. Compare also the acute<lb/>observations on the configuration and position of mountain chains,<lb/>in Albrecht von Roon&#x2019;s <hi rendition="#i">Grundzügen der Erd-Völker-und-Staatenkunde,</hi><lb/>vol. i., 1837, pp. 158, 270, and 276.</note> and low lands, as we see exemplified in so<lb/>favourable a manner in the south of Europe, multiplies<lb/>meteorological processes, as well as the productions of the<lb/>vegetable kingdom; and, as different degrees of cultivation<lb/>then belong to each tract of country, even in the same lati-<lb/>tude, necessities are created, in order to satisfy which, the<lb/>activity of the inhabitants is stimulated. Thus, the dread-<lb/>ful convulsions, which, in consequence of the action of the<lb/><hi rendition="#i">interior</hi> on the exterior, have caused the rising up of vast<lb/><pb n="122" facs="#f0018" />
mountain chains, by means of the sudden elevation of a por-<lb/>tion of the oxidised crust of the earth, have, after the restor-<lb/>ation of tranquillity, and the resuscitation of slumbering or-<lb/>ganisms, imparted to the solid land of both hemispheres a rich<lb/>variety of individual forms, and removed, in a great measure,<lb/>the barren uniformity which operates, with an impoverishing<lb/>effect, on the physical and intellectual powers of the human<lb/>race.</p><lb/><p>To each system<note place="foot" n="*">Leopold von Buch, <hi rendition="#i">Ueber die Geognostischen Systeme von Deutschland,</hi><lb/>in his Geognostical Letters to Alexander von Humboldt, 1824, pp. 265-<lb/>271; and Elie de Beaumont, <hi rendition="#i">Récherches sur les Revolutions de la Surface<lb/>du Globe,</hi> 1829, pp. 297-307.</note> of these mountain chains, a relative age<lb/>has been assigned by the splendid views of Elie de Beau-<lb/>mont, who has shewn that the elevation of a mountain chain<lb/>must necessarily have taken place between the period of de-<lb/>position of the inclined strata, and that of the deposition of<lb/>the horizontal strata extending to the foot of the mountains.<lb/>The <hi rendition="#i">foldings</hi> of the crust of the earth (elevations of the<lb/>strata), which are of the same geognostical age, appear also<lb/>to have one and the same direction. The line of strike of<lb/>the elevated strata is not always parallel to the axis of the<lb/>chains, but sometimes cuts across it; so that, according to<lb/>my opinion,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Humboldt, <hi rendition="#i">Asie Centrale,</hi> t. i. p. 277-283. See also my <hi rendition="#i">Essai sur le<lb/>Gisement des Roches,</hi> 1822, p. 57; and <hi rendition="#i">Relat. Hist.,</hi> t. iii. pp. 244-250.</note> the phenomenon of the inclination of the beds,<lb/>which is found repeated in the neighbouring plain itself,<lb/>must be more ancient than the elevation of the chain. The<lb/>principal direction of the whole solid land of Europe (SW.<lb/>to NE.) is the opposite of that of the great terrestrial fissures,<lb/>(NW. to SE.,) which extend from the mouths of the Rhine<lb/>and the Elbe, through the Adriatic and Red Seas, and also<lb/>through the system of mountains of the Puschti-Koh in<lb/>Luristan, to the Persian Gulf and the Indian Ocean. Such<lb/>a crossing of geodesical lines at nearly right angles, has<lb/>exercised a vast influence on the commercial relations of<lb/>Europe with Asia and North-Western Africa; and also on<lb/><pb n="123" facs="#f0019" />
the progress of civilization on the formerly more prosperous<lb/>shores of the Mediterranean Sea.<note place="foot" n="*"><hi rendition="#i">Asie Centrale,</hi> t. i., pp. 284-286. The Adriatic Sea has also a SE.-<lb/>NW. direction.</note></p><lb/><p>Since immense and lofty chains of mountains occupy our<lb/>imaginations, by presenting themselves as evidences of vast<lb/>terrestrial revolutions, as the boundaries of climates, as great<lb/>water-sheds, or as the bearers of different vegetable worlds;<lb/>it becomes so much the more necessary to shew, by a correct<lb/>numerical estimate of their volume, how small the whole<lb/>quantity of the elevated masses is in comparison with the<lb/>area of entire countries. The mass of the Pyrenees, for ex-<lb/>ample&#x2014;a chain, the mean height of whose summits, and the<lb/>superficial extent of whose base, are known by accurate mea-<lb/>surements&#x2014;would, if distributed over the area of France, in-<lb/>crease the height of that country only 115 English feet.<lb/>The mass of the eastern and western chains of the Alps<lb/>would, in the same manner, raise the height of the flat country<lb/>of Europe by only 21&#x00B7;3 English feet. By means of a laborious<lb/>investigation,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;"><hi rendition="#i">De la Hauteur Moyenne des Continents</hi> in <hi rendition="#i">Asie Centrale,</hi> t. i., pp. 82-90<lb/>and 165-189. The results which I obtained are to be regarded as<lb/><hi rendition="#i">nombres-limites.</hi> Laplace estimated the mean height of continents at<lb/>3280 English feet, which was at least three times too high. That immor-<lb/>tal geometrician (<hi rendition="#i">Mécanique Céleste,</hi> t. v., p. 14) was led to this conclu-<lb/>sion by hypotheses regarding the mean depth of the sea. I have shewn<lb/>(<hi rendition="#i">Asie Centrale,</hi> t. i., p. 93) that the Alexandrine mathematicians, accord-<lb/>ing to the testimony of Plutarch (<hi rendition="#i">in &#x00C6;milio Paulo,</hi> cap. 15.), believed<lb/>that the depth of the sea was dependent on the height of the mountains.<lb/>The height of the centre of gravity of the volume of the continental<lb/>masses has probably been subjected to small changes in the course of<lb/>thousands of years.</note> which, from its very nature, only gives the<lb/>upper limit, <hi rendition="#i">i. e.,</hi> a number which may be smaller, but cannot<lb/>be larger, I have ascertained that the centre of gravity of<lb/>the volume of the land which rises above the present level of<lb/>the sea, is situated at a height of 671 and 748 English feet<lb/>in Europe and North America, and 1131&#x00B7;8 and 1151 English<lb/>feet in Asia and South America. These calculations indicate<lb/>the lowness of the northern regions: the great steppes of the<lb/><pb n="124" facs="#f0020" />
plains of Siberia are counter-balanced by the enormous swel-<lb/>ling of the surface of Asia between lat. 28<formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{2}</formula>° and 40°, be-<lb/>tween the Himalaya, the northern Thibetian Kuen-Lun, and<lb/>the Sky Mountains. We can, to a certain extent, determine,<lb/>from the estimated amounts, where the plutonic force of the<lb/>interior of the globe has operated with greatest power in<lb/>elevating continental masses.</p><lb/><p>There is nothing to assure us, that the same plutonic<lb/>forces may not, in the course of future ages, make additions<lb/>to the systems of mountains of different degrees of antiquity,<lb/>and having different directions, as they are enumerated by<lb/>Elie de Beaumont. Why should the crust of the earth have<lb/>already lost the property of becoming elevated or folded?<lb/>The mountain-systems of the Alps and of the Andes, which<lb/>were almost the last that made their appearance, have ele-<lb/>vated colossal masses in Mont Blanc and Monte Rosa, in<lb/>Sorata, Illimani, and Chimborazo, masses which do not at all<lb/>lead to the conclusion that there had been a diminution in<lb/>the intensity of subterranean power. All the phenomena of<lb/>geognosy indicate a periodical alternation of activity and<lb/>tranquillity.<note place="foot" n="*"><hi rendition="#i">Vide</hi> the Second Geological Letter from Elie de Beaumont to Alex-<lb/>ander von Humboldt, in <hi rendition="#i">Poggendorff&#x2019;s Annalen,</hi> vol. xxv., pp. 1-58.</note> The repose which we now enjoy is only appa-<lb/>rent. Earthquakes, which agitate the surface of the earth in<lb/>every region under heaven, and in every kind of rock,&#x2014;the<lb/>rising of Sweden,&#x2014;and the production of new volcanic islands,<lb/>&#x2014;do not give evidence in favour of a continuance of the<lb/>tranquillity of the earth.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">From <hi rendition="#i">Kosmos. Entwurf einer Physischen Weltbeschreibung von Alexan-<lb/>der von Humboldt,</hi> vol. i., p. 301. 1845.</note></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
