<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-21" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="170" facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <p><hi rendition="#i">Earthquakes</hi>.&#x2014;We must advert to the cause of the<lb/>indescribable, deep, and quite peculiar impression<lb/>which the first earthquake we experience makes upon<lb/>us, even when it is unaccompanied by subterranean<lb/>noises. The impression here is not, I believe, the con-<lb/>sequence of any recollection of destructive catastrophes<lb/>presented to our imagination by narratives of histori-<lb/>cal events: what seizes upon us se wonderfully is the<lb/>disabuse of that innate faith in the fixity of the solid<lb/>and sure-set foundations of the earth. From early<lb/>childhood we are habituated to the contrast between<lb/>the mobile element, water, and the immobility of the<lb/>soil on which we stand. All the evidence of our senses<lb/>have confirmed this belief. But when suddenly the<lb/>ground begins to rock beneath us, the feeling of an<lb/>unknown mysterious power in nature coming into ac-<lb/>tion, and shaking the solid globe, arises in the mind.<lb/>The illusion of the whole of our earlier life is annihi-<lb/>lated in an instant. We are undeceived as to the re-<lb/>pose of nature, we feel ourselves transported to the<lb/>realm, and made subject to the empire, of destructive<lb/>unknown powers. Every sound&#x2014;the slightest rustle<lb/>in the air&#x2014;sets attention on the stretch. We no longer<lb/>trust the earth upon which we stand. The unusual in<lb/>the phenomenon throws the same anxious unrest and<lb/>alarm over the lower animals. Swine and dogs are<lb/>particularly affected by it; and the very crocodiles of<lb/>the Oronoco, otherwise as dumb as our little lizards,<lb/>leave the shaken bed of the stream, and run bellowing<lb/>into the woods. To man the earthquake presents it-<lb/>self as an all-prevading unlimited something. We can<lb/>remove from an active crater, from the stream of lava<lb/>that is pouring down upon our dwelling we can escape;<lb/>with the earthquake we feel that, whithersoever we fly,<lb/>we are still on the hearth of destruction. Such a men-<lb/>tal condition, though evoked in our very innermost<lb/>nature, is not, however, of long duration. When a<lb/>series of slighter shocks occur in a district one after<lb/>another, every trace of alarm soon vanishes among the<lb/>inhabitants. On the rainless coasts of Peru, nothing<lb/>is known of hail, nor of explosions of lightning and<lb/>rolling thunder in the bosom of the atmosphere. The<lb/>subterraneous noise that accompanies the earthquake,<lb/>there comes in lien of the thunder of the clouds. Use<lb/>and wont for a series of years, and the very prevalent<lb/>opinion that dangerous earthquakes are only to be<lb/>apprehended two or three times in the course of a cen-<lb/>tury, lead the inhabitants of Lima scarcely to think<lb/>more of a slight shock of an earthquake that is thought<lb/>of a hail-storm in the temperate zone.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">From &#x201C;Cosmos,&#x201D;<lb/>a new work by Humboldt.</hi></p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>