<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Aerolites, or meteoric stones</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:11</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VI.64</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1845-Ueber_Sternschnuppen_und-7-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Ueber_Sternschnuppen_und-1-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Ueber_Sternschnuppen_und-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Ueber_Sternschnuppen_und-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Ueber_Sternschnuppen_und-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Ueber_Sternschnuppen_und-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Ueber_Sternschnuppen_und-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Ueber_Sternschnuppen_und-7-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Ueber_Sternschnuppen_und-8-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Ueber_Sternschnuppen_und-9-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos. Entwurf einer physischen Weltbeschreibung&lt;/i&gt;, Band 1, Stuttgart und Tübingen: J. G. Cotta 1845 S. 120-130, 131-142.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Aerolites, or meteoric stones</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1852</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Youth’s Instructer and Guardian&lt;/i&gt; 16 [= 36] (Oktober 1852), S. 451–458; 16 [= 36] (November 1852), S. 491–499.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Fußnoten mit Asterisken; Schmuck: Kapitälchen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="451" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head>AEROLITES, OR METEORIC STONES.</head><note place="foot" n="*">Those of our readers who possess the &#x201C;Cosmos&#x201D; of Alexander Von<lb/>Humboldt will forgive this reprint of the pages which relate to this difficult,<lb/>yet intensely interesting, subject, for the sake of those who possess it not. &#x2014;<lb/><hi rendition="#k">Editors.</hi></note><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">Shooting-stars</hi>, fire-balls, and meteoric stones are, with<lb/>great probability, regarded as small bodies moving with planet-<lb/>ary velocity, and revolving in obedience to the laws of general<lb/>gravity in conic sections round the sun. When these masses<lb/>meet the earth in their course, and are attracted by it, they<lb/>enter within the limits of our atmosphere in a luminous con-<lb/>dition, and frequently let fall more or less strongly heated<lb/>stony fragments, covered with a shining black crust. When<lb/>we enter into a careful investigation of the facts observed at<lb/>those epochs when showers of shooting-stars fell periodically<lb/>in Cumana, in 1799, and in North America, during the years<lb/>1833 and 1834, we shall find that <hi rendition="#i">fire-balls</hi> cannot be con-<lb/>sidered separately from shooting-stars. Both these phenomena<lb/>are frequently not only simultaneous and blended together,<lb/>but they likewise are often found to merge into one another,<lb/>the one phenomenon gradually assuming the character of the<lb/>other alike with respect to the size of their discs, the emana-<lb/>tion of sparks, and the velocities of their motion. Although<lb/>exploding smoking luminous fire-balls are sometimes seen,<lb/>even in the brightness of tropical daylight, equalling in size<lb/>the apparent diameter of the moon, innumerable quantities of<lb/>shooting-stars have, on the other hand, been observed to fall<lb/>in forms of such extremely small dimensions, that they appear<lb/>only as moving points, or <hi rendition="#i">phosphorescent lines.</hi></p><lb/><p>It still remains undetermined whether the many luminous<lb/>bodies that shoot across the sky may not vary in their nature.<lb/>On my return from the equinoctial zones, I was impressed<lb/>with an idea that in the torrid regions of the tropics I had<lb/>more frequently than in our colder latitudes seen shooting-<lb/>stars fall as if from a height of twelve or fifteen thousand feet,<lb/>that they were of brighter colours, and left a more brilliant<lb/>line of light in their track; but this impression was no doubt<lb/>owing to the greater transparency of the tropical atmosphere,<lb/><pb n="452" facs="#f0002" />
which enables the eye to penetrate further into distance.<lb/>Sir Alexander Burnes likewise extols, as a consequence of the<lb/>purity of the atmosphere in Bokhara, the enchanting and<lb/>constantly recurring spectacle of variously-coloured shooting-<lb/>stars.</p><lb/><p>The connection of meteoric stones with the grander phe-<lb/>nomenon of fire-balls&#x2014;the former being known to be projected<lb/>from the latter with such force as to penetrate from ten to<lb/>fifteen feet into the earth&#x2014;has been proved, among many<lb/>other instances, in the falls of aerolites at Barbotan, in the<lb/>Department des Landes, (24th of July, 1790,) at Siena, (16th<lb/>of June, 1794,) at Weston, in Connecticut, U. S., (14th of<lb/>December, 1807,) and at Juvenas, in the Department of<lb/>Ardèche. (15th of June, 1821.) Meteoric stones are in some<lb/>instances thrown from dark clouds suddenly formed in a clear<lb/>sky, and fall with a noise resembling thunder. Whole dis-<lb/>tricts have thus occasionally been covered with thousands of<lb/>fragmentary masses, of uniform character, but unequal magni-<lb/>tudes, that have been hurled from one of these moving clouds.<lb/>In less frequent cases, as in that which occurred on the 16th<lb/>of September, 1843, at Kleinwenden, near Mühlhausen, a<lb/>large aerolite fell with a thundering crash, while the sky was<lb/>clear and cloudless. The infinite affinity between fire-balls<lb/>and shooting-stars is further proved by the fact that fire-balls,<lb/>from which meteoric stones have been thrown, have occasion-<lb/>ally been found, as at Angers, on the 9th of June, 1822, having<lb/>a diameter scarcely equal to that of the small fireworks, called<lb/>Roman candles.</p><lb/><p>The formative power, and the nature of the physical and<lb/>chemical processes involved in these phenomena, are questions<lb/>all equally shrouded in mystery, and we are as yet ignorant,<lb/>whether the particles composing the dense mass of meteoric<lb/>stones are originally, as in comets, separated from one another<lb/>in the form of vapour, and only condensed within the fiery<lb/>ball when they become luminous to our sight; or whether in<lb/>the case of smaller shooting-stars any compact substance<lb/>actually falls; or, finally, whether a meteor is composed only<lb/>of a smoke-like dust, containing iron and nickel; whilst we<lb/>are wholly ignorant of what takes place within the dark cloud<lb/><pb n="453" facs="#f0003" />
from which a noise like thunder is often heard for many<lb/>minutes before the stones fall.</p><lb/><p>We can ascertain by measurement the enormous, wonder-<lb/>ful, and wholly planetary velocity of shooting-stars, fire-balls,<lb/>and meteoric stones, and we can gain a knowledge of what is<lb/>the general and uniform character of the phenomenon, but not<lb/>of the genetically cosmical process and the results of the meta-<lb/>morphoses. If meteoric stones while revolving in space are<lb/>already consolidated into dense masses, less dense, however,<lb/>than the mean density of the earth, they must be very small<lb/>nuclei, which, surrounded by inflammable vapour or gas, form<lb/>the innermost part of fire-balls, from the height and apparent<lb/>diameter of which we may, in the case of the largest, estimate<lb/>that the actual diameter varies from five hundred to about<lb/>two thousand eight hundred feet. The largest meteoric masses<lb/>as yet known, are those of Otumpa, in Chaco, and of Bahia,<lb/>in Brazil, described by Rubi de Celis as being from seven to<lb/>seven and a half feet in length. The meteoric stone of &#x00C6;gos<lb/>Potamos, celebrated in antiquity, and even mentioned in the<lb/>Chronicle of the Parian Marbles, which fell about the year in<lb/>which Socrates was born, has been described as of the size of<lb/>two millstones, and equal in weight to a full waggon-load.<lb/>Notwithstanding the failure that has attended the efforts of the<lb/>African traveller, Brown, I do not wholly relinquish the hope<lb/>that, even after a lapse of two thousand three hundred and<lb/>twelve years, this Thracian meteoric mass, which it would be<lb/>so difficult to destroy, may be found, since the region in which<lb/>it fell is now become so easy of access to European travellers.<lb/>The huge aerolite which in the beginning of the tenth century<lb/>fell into the river at Narni, projected between three and four<lb/>feet above the surface of the water, as we learn from a docu-<lb/>ment lately discovered by Pertz. It must be remarked that<lb/>these meteoric bodies, whether in ancient or modern times,<lb/>can only be regarded as the principal fragments of masses that<lb/>have been broken up by the explosion either of a fire-ball or a<lb/>dark cloud.</p><lb/><p>On considering the enormous velocity with which, as has<lb/>been mathematically proved, meteoric stones reach the earth<lb/>from the extremest confines of the atmosphere, and the<lb/><pb n="454" facs="#f0004" />
lengthened course traversed by fire-balls through the denser<lb/>strata of the air, it seems more than improbable that these<lb/>metalliferous stony masses, containing perfectly-formed crys-<lb/>tals of olivine, labradorite, and pyroxene, should in so short<lb/>a period of time have been converted from a vaporous con-<lb/>dition to a solid nucleus. Moreover, that which falls from<lb/>meteoric masses, even where the internal composition is<lb/>chemically different, exhibits almost always the peculiar cha-<lb/>racter of a fragment, being of a prismatic or truncated pyra-<lb/>midal form, with broad somewhat curved faces, and rounded<lb/>angles. But whence comes this form, which was first recog-<lb/>nised by Schreiber, as characteristic of the <hi rendition="#i">severed</hi> part of a<lb/>rotating planetary body? Here, as in the sphere of organic<lb/>life, all that appertains to the history of development remains<lb/>hidden in obscurity. Meteoric masses become luminous, and<lb/>kindle, at heights which must be regarded as almost devoid of<lb/>air, or occupied by an atmosphere that does not even contain<lb/>one hundred thousandth part of oxygen. The recent in-<lb/>vestigations of Biot, on the important phenomenon of twilight,<lb/>have considerably lowered the lines which had, perhaps with<lb/>some degree of temerity, been usually termed the boundaries<lb/>of the atmosphere; but processes of light may be evolved inde-<lb/>pendently of the presence of oxygen, and Poisson conjectured<lb/>that aerolites were ignited far beyond the range of our atmo-<lb/>sphere. Numerical calculation, and geometrical measurement,<lb/>are the only means by which, as in the case of the larger bodies<lb/>of our solar system, we are enabled to impart a firm and safe<lb/>basis to our investigations of meteoric stones. Although<lb/>Halley pronounced the great fire-ball of 1686, whose motion<lb/>was opposite to that of the earth in its orbit, to be a cosmical<lb/>body; Chladni, in 1794, first recognised, with ready acute-<lb/>ness of mind, the connection between fire-balls and the stones<lb/>projected from the atmosphere, and the motions of the former<lb/>bodies in space. A brilliant confirmation of the cosmical<lb/>origin of these phenomena has been afforded by Denison<lb/>Olmsted, at Newhaven, Connecticut, who has shown, on the<lb/>concurrent authority of all eye-witnesses, that during the<lb/>celebrated fall of shooting-stars, on the night between the<lb/>12th and 13th of November, 1833, the fire-balls and shooting-<lb/><pb n="455" facs="#f0005" />
stars all emerged from one and the same quarter of the<lb/>heavens, namely, in the vicinity of the star &#x03B3; in the con-<lb/>stellation Leo, and did not deviate from this point, although<lb/>the star changed its apparent height and azimuth during the<lb/>time of the observation. Such an independence of the earth&#x2019;s<lb/>rotation shows that the luminous body must have reached our<lb/>atmosphere from <hi rendition="#i">without</hi>. According to Encke&#x2019;s computation<lb/>of the whole number of the observations made in the United<lb/>States of North America, between 35° and 42° lat., it would<lb/>appear that all these meteors came from the same point of<lb/>space in the direction in which the earth was moving at the<lb/>time. On the recurrence of falls of shooting-stars in North<lb/>America, in the month of November of the years 1834 and<lb/>1837, and in the analogous falls observed at Bremen in 1838,<lb/>a like general parallelism of the orbits, and the same direction<lb/>of the meteors from the constellation Leo, were again noticed.<lb/>It has been supposed that a greater parallelism was observable<lb/>in the direction of periodic falls of shooting-stars, than in<lb/>those of sporadic occurrence; and it has further been re-<lb/>marked, that in the periodically-recurring falls in the month<lb/>of August, as, for instance, in the year 1839, the meteors<lb/>came principally from one point between Perseus and Taurus,<lb/>towards the latter of which constellations the earth was then<lb/>moving. This peculiarity of the phenomenon, manifested in<lb/>the retrograde direction of the orbits in November and August,<lb/>should be thoroughly investigated by accurate observations, in<lb/>order that it may either be fully confirmed or refuted.</p><lb/><p>The heights of shooting-stars, that is to say, the heights of<lb/>the points at which they begin and cease to be visible, vary<lb/>exceedingly, fluctuating between 16 and 140 miles. This<lb/>important result and the enormous velocity of these pro-<lb/>blematical asteroids were first ascertained by Benzenberg and<lb/>Brandes, by simultaneous observations and determinations of<lb/>parallax, at the extremities of a base-line of 49,020 feet in<lb/>length. The relative velocity of motion is from 18 to 36<lb/>miles in a second, and consequently equal to planetary<lb/>velocity. This planetary velocity, as well as the direction of<lb/>the orbits of fire-balls and shooting-stars, which has frequently<lb/>been observed to be opposite to that of the earth, may be<lb/><pb n="456" facs="#f0006" />
considered as conclusive arguments against the hypothesis<lb/>that aerolites derive their origin from the so called active lunar<lb/>volcanoes. Numerical views regarding a greater or lesser<lb/>volcanic force on a small cosmical body, not surrounded by<lb/>any atmosphere, must from their nature be wholly arbitrary.<lb/>We may imagine the reaction of the interior of a planet on<lb/>its crust, ten or even a hundred times greater than that of our<lb/>present terrestrial volcanoes; the direction of masses pro-<lb/>jected from a satellite revolving from west to east might<lb/>appear retrogressive, owing to the earth in its orbit subse-<lb/>quently reaching that point of space at which these bodies<lb/>fall. If we examine the whole sphere of relations which I<lb/>have touched upon in this work, in order to escape the charge<lb/>of having made improved assertions, we shall find that the<lb/>hypothesis of the selenic origin of meteoric stones depends<lb/>upon a number of conditions, whose accidental coincidence<lb/>could alone convert a possible into an actual fact. The view<lb/>of the original existence of small planetary masses in space is<lb/>simpler, and at the same time more analogous with those<lb/>entertained concerning the formation of other portions of the<lb/>solar system.</p><lb/><p>It is very probable that a large number of these cosmical<lb/>bodies traverse space undestroyed by the vicinity of our<lb/>atmosphere, and revolve round the sun without experiencing<lb/>any alteration but a slight increase in the eccentricity of their<lb/>orbits, occasioned by the attraction of the earth&#x2019;s mass. We<lb/>may, consequently, suppose the possibility of these bodies<lb/>remaining invisible to us during many years and frequent<lb/>revolutions. The supposed phenomenon of ascending shoot-<lb/>ing-stars and fire-balls, which Chladni has unsuccessfully<lb/>endeavoured to explain on the hypothesis of the <hi rendition="#i">reflection</hi> of<lb/>strongly compressed air, appears at first sight as the con-<lb/>sequence of some unknown tangential force, propelling bodies<lb/>from the earth; but Bessel has shown by theoretical<lb/>deductions, confirmed by Feldt&#x2019;s carefully conducted calcula-<lb/>tions, that owing to the absence of any proofs of the simul-<lb/>taneous occurrence of the observed disappearances, the<lb/>assumption of an ascent of shooting-stars was rendered wholly<lb/>improbable, and inadmissible as a result of observation. The<lb/><pb n="457" facs="#f0007" />
opinion advanced by Olbers, that the explosion of shooting-<lb/>stars and ignited fire-balls not moving in straight lines, may<lb/>impel meteors upwards in the manner of rockets, and influence<lb/>the direction of their orbits, must be made the subject of<lb/>future researches.</p><lb/><p>Shooting-stars fall either separately and in inconsiderable<lb/>numbers, that is, sporadically, or in swarms of many thousands.<lb/>The latter, which are compared by Arabian authors to swarms<lb/>of locusts, are periodic in their occurrence, and move in<lb/>streams, generally in a parallel direction. Amongst periodic<lb/>falls, the most celebrated are that known as the November<lb/>phenomenon, occurring from about the 12th to the 14th of<lb/>November, and that of the festival of St. Lawrence, (the 10th<lb/>of August,) whose &#x201C;fiery tears&#x201D; were noticed in former times<lb/>in a church-calendar of England, no less than in old traditionary<lb/>legends, as a meteorological event of constant recurrence.<lb/>Notwithstanding the great quantity of shooting-stars and fire-<lb/>balls of the most various dimensions, which, according to<lb/>Klöden, were seen to fall at Potsdam, on the night between<lb/>the 12th and 13th of November, 1822, and on the same night<lb/>of the year in 1832, throughout the whole of Europe, from<lb/>Portsmouth to Orenburg on the Ural River, and even in the<lb/>southern hemisphere, as in the Isle of France, no attention<lb/>was directed to the <hi rendition="#i">periodicity</hi> of the phenomenon, and no<lb/>idea seems to have been entertained of the connexion existing<lb/>between the fall of shooting-stars and the recurrence of certain<lb/>days, until the prodigious swarm of shooting-stars which<lb/>occurred in North America between the 12th and 13th of<lb/>November, 1833, and was observed by Olmsted and Palmer.<lb/>The stars fell on this occasion like flakes of snow, and it was<lb/>calculated that at least 240,000 had fallen during a period of<lb/>nine hours. Palmer, of New-Haven, Connecticut, was led, in<lb/>consequence of this splendid phenomenon, to the recollection<lb/>of the fall of meteoric stones in 1799, first described by Ellicot<lb/>and myself, and which, by a comparison of the facts I had<lb/>adduced, showed that the phenomenon had been simul-<lb/>taneously seen in the New Continent, from the equator to<lb/>New-Herrnhut in Greenland, (64° 14&#x2032; lat.,) and between<lb/>46° and 82° long. The identity of the epochs was recognised<lb/><pb n="458" facs="#f0008" />
with astonishment. The stream, which had been seen from<lb/>Jamaica to Boston, (40° 21&#x2032; lat.,) to traverse the whole vault<lb/>of heaven on the 12th and 13th of November, 1833, was again<lb/>observed in the United States in 1834, on the night between<lb/>the 13th and 14th of November, although on this latter<lb/>occasion it showed itself with somewhat less intensity. In<lb/>Europe the periodicity of the phenomenon has since been<lb/>manifested with great regularity. Another and a like<lb/>regularly-recurring phenomenon, is that noticed in the month<lb/>of August, the meteoric stream of St. Lawrence, appearing<lb/>between the 9th and 14th of August. Muschenbroek, as early<lb/>as in the middle of the last century, drew attention to the<lb/>frequency of meteors in the month of August; but their<lb/>certain periodic return about the time of St. Lawrence&#x2019;s day<lb/>was first shown by Quetelet, Olbers, and Benzenberg. We<lb/>shall, no doubt, in time discover other periodically appearing<lb/>streams, probably about the 22d to the 25th of April,<lb/>between the 6th and 12th of December; and, to judge by the<lb/>number of true falls of aerolites enumerated by Capocci, also<lb/>between the 27th and 29th of November, or about the 17th<lb/>of July.</p></div><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<pb n="491" facs="#f0009" />
<div n="1"><head>AEROLITES, OR METEORIC STONES.</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#c">(<hi rendition="#i">Concluded from page</hi> 458.)</hi></p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">The</hi> different meteoric streams, each of which is composed<lb/>of myriads of small cosmical bodies, probably intersect our<lb/>earth&#x2019;s orbit in the same manner as Biela&#x2019;s comet. According<lb/>to this hypothesis, we may represent to ourselves these<lb/>asteroid-meteors as composing a closed ring or zone, within<lb/>which they all pursue one common orbit. The smaller planets<lb/>between Mars and Jupiter present us, if we except Pallas,<lb/>with an analogous relation in their constantly-intersecting<lb/>orbits. As yet, however, we have no certain knowledge as to<lb/>whether changes in the periods at which the stream becomes<lb/>visible, or the <hi rendition="#i">retardations</hi> of the phenomena of which I have<lb/>already spoken, indicate a regular precession or oscillation of<lb/>the nodes; that is to say, of the points of intersection of the<lb/>earth&#x2019;s orbit and of that of the ring; or whether this ring or<lb/>zone attains so considerable a degree of breadth from the<lb/>irregular grouping and distances apart of the small bodies,<lb/>that it requires several days for the earth to traverse it. The<lb/>system of Saturn&#x2019;s satellites shows us likewise a group of<lb/>immense width, composed of most intimately-connected cos-<lb/>mical bodies. In this system, the orbit of the outermost (the<lb/>seventh) satellite has such a vast diameter, that the earth, in<lb/>her revolution round the sun, requires three days to traverse<lb/>an extent of space equal to this diameter. If, therefore, in<lb/>one of these rings, which we regard as the orbit of a periodical<lb/>stream, the asteroids should be so irregularly distributed as to<lb/>consist of but few groups sufficiently dense to give rise to these<lb/>phenomena, we may easily understand why we so seldom<lb/>witness such glorious spectacles as those exhibited in the<lb/>November months of 1799 and 1833. The acute mind of<lb/>Olbers led him almost to predict that the next appearance of<lb/>the phenomenon of shooting-stars and fire-balls intermixed,<lb/>falling like flakes of snow, would not recur until between the<lb/>12th and 14th of November, 1867.</p><lb/><p>The stream of the November asteroids has occasionally only<lb/>been visible in a small section of the earth. Thus, for instance,<lb/>a very splendid <hi rendition="#i">meteoric shower</hi> was seen in England in the<lb/>year 1837, whilst a most attentive and skilful observer at<lb/><pb n="492" facs="#f0010" />
    Braunsberg, in Prussia, only saw on the same night, which<lb/>was there uninterruptedly clear, a few sporadic shooting-stars<lb/>fall, between seven o&#x2019;clock in the evening and sunrise the<lb/>next morning. Bessel concluded from this, &#x201C;that a dense<lb/>group of the bodies composing the great ring, may have<lb/>reached that part of the earth in which England is situated,<lb/>whilst the more eastern districts of the earth might be passing<lb/>at the time through a part of the meteoric ring proportionally<lb/>less densely studded with bodies.&#x201D; If the hypothesis of a<lb/>regular progression or oscillation of the nodes should acquire<lb/>greater weight, special interest will be attached to the inves-<lb/>tigation of older observations. The Chinese annals, in which<lb/>great falls of shooting-stars, as well as the phenomena of<lb/>comets, are recorded, go back beyond the age of Tyrt&#x00E6;us, or<lb/>the second Messenian war. They give a description of two<lb/>streams in the month of March, one of which is 687 years<lb/>anterior to the Christian era. Edward Biot has observed<lb/>that, amongst the fifty-two phenomena which he has collected<lb/>from the Chinese annals, those that were of most frequent<lb/>recurrence are recorded at periods nearly corresponding with<lb/>the 20th and 22d of July, O.S., and might consequently be<lb/>identical with the stream of St. Lawrence&#x2019;s day, taking into<lb/>account that it has advanced since the epochs indicated. If<lb/>the fall of shooting-stars of the 21st of October, 1366, O.S.<lb/>(a notice of which was found by the younger Von Boguslawski,<lb/>in Benessius de Horowic&#x2019;s <hi rendition="#i">Chronicon <choice><sic>Ecclesi&#x0153;</sic><corr type="editorial">Ecclesi&#x00E6;</corr></choice> Pragensis</hi>,) be<lb/>identical with our November phenomenon, although the<lb/>occurrence in the fourteenth century was seen in broad day-<lb/>light, we find by the precession in 477 years, that this system<lb/>of meteors, or rather its common centre of gravity, must<lb/>describe a retrograde orbit round the sun. It also follows,<lb/>from the views thus developed, that the non-appearance,<lb/>during certain years, in any portion of the earth, of the two<lb/>streams hitherto observed in November and about the time<lb/>of St. Lawrence&#x2019;s day, must be ascribed either to an inter-<lb/>ruption in the meteoric ring, that is to say, to intervals<lb/>occurring between the asteroid groups; or, according to<lb/>Poisson, to the action of the larger planets on the form and<lb/>position of this annulus.</p><lb/><pb n="493" facs="#f0011" />
<p>The solid masses which are observed by night to fall to the<lb/>earth from fire-balls, and by day generally when the sky is<lb/>clear, from a dark small cloud, are accompanied by much<lb/>noise, and, although heated, are not in an actual state of<lb/>incandescence. They undeniably exhibit a great degree of<lb/>general identity with respect to their external form, the<lb/>character of their crust, and the chemical composition of their<lb/>principal constituents. These characteristics of identity have<lb/>been observed at all the different epochs and in the most<lb/>various parts of the earth in which these meteoric stones have<lb/>been found. This striking and early-observed analogy of<lb/>physiognomy in the denser meteoric masses is, however, met<lb/>by many exceptions regarding individual points. What<lb/>differences, for instance, do we not find between the malleable<lb/>masses of iron of Hradschina in the district of Agram, those<lb/>from the shores of the Sisim in the government of Jeniseisk,<lb/>rendered so celebrated by Pallas, or those which I brought<lb/>from Mexico, all of which contain ninety-six per cent. of iron,<lb/>from the a&#x00EB;rolites of Siena, in which the iron scarcely amounts<lb/>to two per cent.; or the earthy a&#x00EB;rolite of Alais, (in the<lb/>Department du Gard,) which broke up in water; or lastly,<lb/>from those of Jonzac and Juvenas, which contained no<lb/>metallic iron, but presented a mixture of oryctognostically<lb/>distinct crystalline components! These differences have led<lb/>mineralogists to separate these cosmical masses into two<lb/>classes; namely, those containing nickelliferous meteoric iron,<lb/>and those consisting of fine or coarsely-granular meteoric<lb/>dust. The crust or rind of a&#x00EB;rolites is peculiarly characteristic<lb/>of these bodies, being only a few tenths of a line in thickness,<lb/>often glossy and pitch-like, and occasionally veined. There<lb/>is only one instance on record, as far as I am aware, (the<lb/>a&#x00EB;rolite of Chantonnay, in La Vendée,) in which the rind<lb/>was absent; and this meteor, like that of Juvenas, presented<lb/>likewise the peculiarity of having pores and vesicular cavities.<lb/>In all other cases the black crust is divided from the inner<lb/>light-grey mass by as sharply-defined a line of separation as<lb/>is the black leaden-coloured investment of the white granite<lb/>blocks which I brought from the cataracts of the Orinoco,<lb/>and which are also associated with many other cataracts, as,<lb/><pb n="494" facs="#f0012" />
for instance, those of the Nile and of the Congo River. The<lb/>greatest heat employed in our porcelain-ovens would be<lb/>insufficient to produce anything similar to the crust of<lb/>meteoric stones, whose interior remains wholly unchanged.<lb/>Here and there, facts have been observed which would seem<lb/>to indicate a fusion together of the meteoric fragments; but<lb/>in general, the character of the aggregate mass, the absence<lb/>of compression by the fall, and the inconsiderable degree of<lb/>heat possessed by these bodies when they reach the earth, are<lb/>all opposed to the hypothesis of the interior being in a state<lb/>of fusion during their short passage from the boundary of the<lb/>atmosphere to our earth.</p><lb/><p>The chemical elements of which these meteoric masses<lb/>consist, and on which Berzelius has thrown so much light,<lb/>are the same as those distributed throughout the earth&#x2019;s crust,<lb/>and are fifteen in number; namely, iron, nickel, cobalt,<lb/>manganese, chromium, copper, arsenic, zinc, potash, soda,<lb/>sulphur, phosphorus, and carbon; constituting altogether<lb/>nearly one-third of all the known simple bodies. Notwith-<lb/>standing this similarity with the primary elements into which<lb/>inorganic bodies are chemically reducible, the aspect of<lb/>a&#x00EB;rolites, owing to the mode in which their constituent parts<lb/>are compounded, presents, generally, some features foreign to<lb/>our telluric rocks and minerals. The pure native iron, which<lb/>is almost always found incorporated with a&#x00EB;rolites, imparts to<lb/>them a peculiar but not consequently a <hi rendition="#i">selenic</hi> character; for<lb/>in other regions of space, and in other cosmical bodies besides<lb/>our moon, water may be wholly absent, and processes of<lb/>oxidation of rare occurrence.</p><lb/><p>Cosmical gelatinous vesicles, similar to the organic <hi rendition="#i">nostoc</hi>,<lb/>(masses which have been supposed since the middle ages to<lb/>be connected with shooting-stars,) and those pyrites of<lb/>Sterlitamak, west of the Uralian Mountains, which are said<lb/>to have constituted the interior of hailstones, must both be<lb/>classed amongst the mythical fables of meteorology. Some<lb/>few a&#x00EB;rolites, as those composed of a finely-granular tissue of<lb/>olivine, augite, and labradorite blended together, (as the<lb/>meteoric stone found at Juvenas, in the Department de<lb/>l&#x2019;Ardèche, which resembled dolorite,) are the only ones, as<lb/><pb n="495" facs="#f0013" />
Gustave Rose has remarked, which have a more familiar<lb/>aspect. These bodies contain, for instance, crystalline sub-<lb/>stances, perfectly similar to those of our earth&#x2019;s crust; and in<lb/>the Siberian mass of meteoric iron investigated by Pallas, the<lb/>olivine only differs from common olivine by the absence of<lb/>nickel, which is replaced by oxide of tin. As meteoric olivine,<lb/>like our basalt, contains from forty-seven to forty-nine per<lb/>cent. of magnesia, constituting, according to Berzelius, almost<lb/>the half of the earthy components of meteoric stones, we<lb/>cannot be surprised at the great quantity of silicate of<lb/>magnesia found in these cosmical bodies. If the a&#x00EB;rolite of<lb/>Juvenas contain separable crystals of augite and labradorite,<lb/>the numerical relation of the constituents renders it at least<lb/>probable that the meteoric masses of Chateau-Renard may<lb/>be a compound of diorite, consisting of hornblende and albite,<lb/>and those of Blansko and Chantonnay compounds of horn-<lb/>blende and labradorite. The proofs of the telluric and<lb/>atmospheric origin of a&#x00EB;rolites, which it is attempted to base<lb/>upon the oryctognostic analogies presented by these bodies, do<lb/>not appear to me to possess any great weight.</p><lb/><p>Recalling to mind the remarkable interview between Newton<lb/>and Conduit at Kensington, I would ask why the elementary<lb/>substances that compose one group of cosmical bodies, or one<lb/>planetary system, may not in a great measure be identical?<lb/>Why should we not adopt this view, since we may conjecture<lb/>that these planetary bodies, like all the larger or smaller<lb/>agglomerated masses revolving round the sun, have been<lb/>thrown off from the once far more expanded solar atmosphere,<lb/>and been formed from vaporous rings describing their orbits<lb/>round the central body? We are not, it appears to me, more<lb/>justified in applying the term telluric to the nickel and iron,<lb/>the olivine and pyroxene (augite), found in meteoric stones,<lb/>than in indicating the German plants which I found beyond<lb/>the Obi as European species of the flora of Northern Asia.<lb/>If the elementary substances composing a group of cosmical<lb/>bodies of different magnitudes be identical, why should they<lb/>not likewise, in obeying the laws of mutual attraction, blend<lb/>together under definite relations of mixture, composing the<lb/>white glittering snow and ice in the polar zones of the planet<lb/><pb n="496" facs="#f0014" />
Mars, or constituting in the smaller cosmical masses mineral<lb/>bodies enclosing crystals of olivine, augite, and labradorite?<lb/>Even in the domain of pure conjecture we should not suffer<lb/>ourselves to be led away by unphilosophical and arbitrary<lb/>views devoid of the support of inductive reasoning.</p><lb/><p>Remarkable obscurations of the sun&#x2019;s disc, during which<lb/>the stars have been seen at mid-day, (as, for instance, in the<lb/>obscuration of 1547, which continued for three days, and<lb/>occurred about the time of the eventful battle of Mühlberg,)<lb/>cannot be explained as arising from volcanic ashes or mists,<lb/>and were regarded by Kepler as owing either to a <hi rendition="#i">materia<lb/>cometica</hi>, or to a black cloud formed by the sooty exhalations<lb/>of the solar body. The shorter obscurations of 1090 and<lb/>1203, which continued the one only three and the other six<lb/>hours, were supposed by Chladni and Schnurrer to be occa-<lb/>sioned by the passage of meteoric masses before the sun&#x2019;s<lb/>disc. Since the period that streams of meteoric shooting-<lb/>stars were first considered with reference to the direction of<lb/>their orbit as a closed ring, the epochs of these mysterious<lb/>celestial phenomena have been observed to present a remark-<lb/>able connection with the regular recurrence of swarms of<lb/>shooting-stars. Adolph Erman has evinced great acuteness<lb/>of mind in his accurate investigation of the facts hitherto<lb/>observed on this subject, and his researches have enabled him<lb/>to discover the connection of the sun&#x2019;s conjunction with the<lb/>August asteroids on the 7th of February, and with the November<lb/>asteroids on the 12th of May, the latter period corresponding<lb/>with the days of St. Mamert, (May 11th,) St. Pancras,<lb/>(May 12th,) and St. Servatius, (May 13th,) which, according<lb/>to popular belief, were accounted &#x201C;cold days.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>The Greek natural philosophers, who were but little disposed<lb/>to pursue observations, but evinced inexhaustible fertility of<lb/>imagination in giving the most various interpretation of half-<lb/>perceived facts, have, however, left some hypotheses regarding<lb/>shooting-stars and meteoric stones, which strikingly accord<lb/>with the views now almost universally admitted of the cosmical<lb/>process of these phenomena. &#x201C;Falling stars,&#x201D; says Plutarch,<lb/>in his life of Lysander, &#x201C;are, according to the opinion of some<lb/>physicists, not eruptions of the etherial fire extinguished in<lb/><pb n="497" facs="#f0015" />
the air immediately after its ignition, nor yet an inflammatory<lb/>combustion of the air, which is dissolved in large quantities in<lb/>the upper regions of space; but these meteors are rather a<lb/>fall of celestial bodies, which, in consequence of a certain<lb/>intermission in the rotatory force, and by the impulse of some<lb/>irregular movement, have been hurled down not only to the<lb/>inhabited portions of the earth, but also beyond it into the<lb/>great ocean, where we cannot find them.&#x201D; Diogenes of<lb/>Apollonia expresses himself still more explicitly. According<lb/>to his views, &#x201C;Stars that are <hi rendition="#i">invisible</hi>, and consequently have<lb/>no name, move in space together with those that are visible.<lb/>These invisible stars frequently fall to the earth, and are<lb/>extinguished, as the <hi rendition="#i">stony star</hi> which fell burning at &#x00C6;gos<lb/>Potamos.&#x201D; The Apollonian, who held all other stellar bodies<lb/>when luminous to be of a pumice-like nature, probably<lb/>grounded his opinions regarding shooting-stars and meteoric<lb/>masses on the doctrine of Anaxagoras the Clazomenian, who<lb/>regarded all the bodies in the universe &#x201C;as fragments of<lb/>rocks, which the fiery ether in the force of its gyratory motion<lb/>had torn from the earth, and converted into stars.&#x201D; In the<lb/>Ionian school, therefore, according to the testimony transmitted<lb/>to us in the views of Diogenes of Apollonia, a&#x00EB;rolites and<lb/>stars were ranged in one and the same class: both, when<lb/>considered with reference to their primary origin, being<lb/>equally telluric, this being understood only so far as the earth<lb/>was then regarded as a central body, forming all things<lb/>around it in the same manner as we, according to our present<lb/>views, suppose the planets of our system to have originated<lb/>in the expanded atmosphere of another central body&#x2014;the<lb/>sun. These views must not, therefore, be confounded with<lb/>what is commonly termed the telluric or atmospheric origin<lb/>of meteoric stones, nor yet with the singular opinion of<lb/>Aristotle, which supposed the enormous mass of &#x00C6;gos Potamos<lb/>to have been raised by a hurricane. That arrogant spirit of<lb/>incredulity, which rejects facts without attempting to investigate<lb/>them, is in some cases almost more injurious than an<lb/>unquestioning credulity. Both are alike detrimental to the<lb/>force of investigation. Notwithstanding that for more than<lb/>two thousand years the annals of different nations had recorded<lb/><pb n="498" facs="#f0016" />
falls of meteoric stones, many of which had been attested<lb/>beyond all doubt by the evidence of irreproachable eye-<lb/>witnesses,&#x2014;notwithstanding the important part enacted by<lb/>the B&#x00E6;tylia in the meteor-worship of the ancients,&#x2014;notwith-<lb/>standing the fact of the companions of Cortes having seen an<lb/>a&#x00EB;rolite at Cholula which had fallen on the neighbouring<lb/>pyramid,&#x2014;notwithstanding that Caliphs and Mongolian chiefs<lb/>had caused swords to be forged from recently-fallen meteoric<lb/>stones,&#x2014;nay, notwithstanding that several persons had been<lb/>struck dead by stones falling from heaven, as, for instance, a<lb/>Monk at Crema on the 4th of September, 1511, another Monk<lb/>at Milan in 1650, and two Swedish sailors on board ship in<lb/>1674,&#x2014;yet this great cosmical phenomenon remained almost<lb/>wholly unheeded, and its intimate connection with other<lb/>planetary systems unknown, until attention was drawn to the<lb/>subject by Chladni, who had already gained immortal renown<lb/>by his discovery of the sound-figures. He who is penetrated<lb/>with a sense of this mysterious connection, and whose mind<lb/>is open to deep impressions of nature, will feel himself<lb/>moved by the deepest and most solemn emotion at the sight<lb/>of every star that shoots across the vault of heaven, no less<lb/>than at the glorious spectacle of meteoric swarms in<lb/>the November phenomenon, or on St. Lawrence&#x2019;s day.<lb/>Here motion is suddenly revealed in the midst of nocturnal<lb/>rest. The still radiance of the vault of heaven is for<lb/>a moment animated with life and movement. In the mild<lb/>radiance left on the track of the shooting-star imagination<lb/>pictures the lengthened path of the meteor through the<lb/>vault of heaven; whilst, everywhere around, the luminous<lb/>asteroids proclaim the existence of one common material<lb/>universe.</p><lb/><p>If we compare the volume of the innermost of Saturn&#x2019;s<lb/>satellites, or that of Ceres, with the immense volume of the<lb/>sun, all relations of magnitude vanish from our minds. The<lb/>extinction of suddenly-resplendent stars in Cassiopea, Cygnus,<lb/>and Serpentarius, have already led to the assumption of other<lb/>and non-luminous cosmical bodies. We now know that the<lb/>meteoric asteroids, spherically agglomerated into small masses,<lb/>revolve round the sun, intersect like comets the orbits of the<lb/><pb n="499" facs="#f0017" />
luminous larger planets, and become ignited either in the<lb/>vicinity of our atmosphere or in its upper strata.</p><lb/><p>The only media by which we are brought in connection<lb/>with other planetary bodies, and with all portions of the<lb/>universe beyond our atmosphere, are light and heat, (the latter<lb/>of which can scarcely be separated from the former,) and those<lb/>mysterious powers of attraction exercised by remote masses<lb/>according to the quantity of their constituents, upon our globe,<lb/>the ocean, and the strata of our atmosphere. Another and<lb/>different kind of cosmical or rather material mode of contact<lb/>is, however, opened to us, if we admit falling-stars and<lb/>meteoric stones to be planetary asteroids. They not only act<lb/>upon us merely from a distance by the excitement of luminous<lb/>or calorific vibrations, or in obedience to the laws of mutual<lb/>attraction, but they acquire an actual material existence for<lb/>us, reaching our atmosphere from the remoter regions of<lb/>universal space, and remaining on the earth itself. Meteoric<lb/>stones are the only means by which we can be brought in<lb/>possible contact with that which is foreign to our own planet.<lb/>Accustomed to gain our knowledge of what is not telluric<lb/>solely through measurement, calculations, and the deductions<lb/>of reason, we experience a sentiment of astonishment at<lb/>finding that we may examine, weigh, and analyse bodies that<lb/>appertain to the outer world. This awakens, by the power<lb/>of the imagination, a meditative spiritual train of thought,<lb/>where the untutored mind perceives only scintillations of<lb/>light in the firmament, and sees in the blackened stone that<lb/>falls from the exploded cloud nothing beyond the rough<lb/>product of a powerful natural force.</p><lb/><p>Although the asteroid-swarms, on which we have been led<lb/>from special predilection to dwell somewhat at length, approxi-<lb/>mate, to a certain degree, in their inconsiderable mass and<lb/>the diversity of their orbits, to comets, they present this<lb/>essential difference from the latter bodies, that our knowledge<lb/>of their existence is almost entirely limited to the moment of<lb/>their destruction, that is, to the period when, drawn within<lb/>the sphere of the earth&#x2019;s attraction, they become luminous<lb/>and ignite.</p></div><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
