<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="48" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">FIRST IMPRESSION MADE BY AN EARTHQUAKE.</hi></head><lb/><p>Before we quit this great phenomenon, we must advert<lb/>to that indescribable, deep, and peculiar impression which<lb/>the first earthquake that we experience makes upon us,<lb/>even when unaccompanied with subterranean noises. The<lb/>impression is not, I believe, the consequence of any recol-<lb/>lection of destructive catastrophes presented to our imagi-<lb/>nation by historical narratives. That which seizes upon us<lb/>so wonderfully is the disabuse of our innate faith in the<lb/>firmness of the solid and sure-set foundations of the earth.<lb/>From infancy, we are accustomed to the contrast between<lb/>the moveable element of water, and the immutability of<lb/>the soil on which we stand&#x2014;a belief confirmed by the<lb/>evidences of our senses. But, when the ground suddenly<lb/>rocks beneath us, the feeling of an unknown mysterious<lb/>power in nature coming into action, and shaking the solid<lb/>globe, arises in the mind. The illusion of our early life is<lb/>instantaneously annihilated. We are undeceived as to the<lb/>repose of nature&#x2014;we feel ourselves transported to the<lb/>realm, and subjected to the empire, of destructive, unknown<lb/>powers. Every sound&#x2014;the slightest rustle in the air&#x2014;<lb/>sets attention on the rack, and we no longer trust the earth<lb/>on which we stand. The unusualness of the phenomenon<lb/>throws the same anxious unrest and alarm over the lower<lb/>animals. Swine and dogs are particularly affected by it;<lb/>and the very crocodiles of the Orinoco, otherwise as dumb<lb/>as our lizards, leave the trembling bed of the stream, and<lb/>rush bellowing into the woods. To man, the earthquake<lb/>is something unlimited and all-pervading. We can remove<lb/>from the active crater of a volcano; we can escape from<lb/>the flood of lava that is pouring down upon our dwelling;<lb/>but with the earthquake we feel that whithersoever we fly<lb/>we are still over the hearth of destruction. &#x2014; <hi rendition="#i">Baron Hum-<lb/>boldt&#x2019;s Kosmos.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
