<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">On the known thickness of the crust of the earth</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:11</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VI.62</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1845-On_the_known-2-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-1-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-2-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-7-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-8-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-On_the_known-9-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos: A General Survey of the physical phenomena of the universe&lt;/i&gt;, Bd. 1, London: Hippolyte Baillière 1845, S. 418–420.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Cosmos: A sketch of a physical description of the universe&lt;/i&gt;, übersetzt von Elise C. Otté, London: Henry G. Bohn 1849, S. 148–150.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos. Entwurf einer physischen Weltbeschreibung&lt;/i&gt;, Band 1, Stuttgart und Tübingen: J. G. Cotta 1845, S. 416–419.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">On the known thickness of the crust of the earth</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1845</date>
          <pubPlace>Boston, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
          <pubPlace>New York City, New York</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;Littell’s Living Age&lt;/i&gt; 7:78 (8. November 1845), S. 258–259.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Schmuck: Kapitälchen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="258" facs="#f0001" />
<cb/>
<cb/>
    <div n="1"><head>ON THE KNOWN THICKNESS OF THE CRUST<lb/>OF THE EARTH.</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">It</hi> is proper to distinguish between the <hi rendition="#i">absolute</hi><lb/>depth to which man has penetrated in his mining<lb/>operations, or the depth from the surface of the<lb/>earth at the place where the operations are carried<lb/>on, and the <hi rendition="#i">relative</hi> depth, <hi rendition="#i">i. e.,</hi> the depth below<lb/>the level of the sea. The greatest relative depth<lb/>that has been reached is, perhaps, the bore at Mew<lb/>Salzwerk, Minden, in Prussia. In June, 1844, it<lb/>was exactly 1844&#x0BD; Parisian feet; the absolute<lb/>depth was, however, 2094&#x0BD; Par. feet. The tem-<lb/>perature of the water in the deepest bore was<lb/>32&#x00B7;7° C. (90&#x00B7;8° F.) which assuming 9&#x00B7;6° C. as<lb/>the mean temperature of the air, gives a rise of<lb/>1&#x00B7;6° for 29&#x00B7;6 metres (upwards of 97&#x00B7;6 feet Eng-<lb/>lish.) The Artesian well of Grenelle, at Paris, is<lb/>only 1683 feet in absolute depth. From the ac-<lb/>counts of the missionary Imbert from China, the<lb/>depth of our Artesian wells is far surpassed by<lb/>that of the fire-spring, Ho-tsing, which yields<lb/>inflammable gas, employed in salt boiling. In the<lb/>Chinese province Szü-tschuan, these fire-springs<lb/>are said very commonly to reach a depth of from<lb/><pb n="259" facs="#f0002" />
<cb/>
        1800 to 2000 feet; and at Tseu-lieu-tsing (place<lb/>of perpetual flux) a Ho-tsing bored with the rod in<lb/>the year 1812, is reported to extend to the depth<lb/>of 3000 feet (Humboldt, Asie Centrale, t. ii., p.<lb/>521 and 525; Annales de l&#x2019;Association de la Pro-<lb/>pagation de la Foi, 1829, No. 16, p. 369.) The<lb/>relative depth attained at Monte Massi, in Tus-<lb/>cany, south from Volterra, according to Matteucci,<lb/>is about 1175 feet. The bore at New Salzwerk<lb/>approaches very nearly in relative depth the coal<lb/>pit at Apendale, Newcastle-under-Lyme (Staf-<lb/>fordshire.) There the works are carried on 725<lb/>yards, or 2045 French feet, under the surface.<lb/>(Th. Smith, The Miner&#x2019;s Guide, 1836, p. 160.)<lb/>Unfortunately, the height of the ground above the<lb/>level of the sea is not accurately ascertained. The<lb/>relative depth of the Monkwearmouth pit, near<lb/>Newcastle-on-Tyne, is only 1404 feet (Philips,<lb/>Philos. Mag., vol. v., 1834, p. 446;) that of the<lb/>Esperance pit, at Liege, 1271; and that of the<lb/>lately-worked pit Marihaye, at Val St. Lambert, is<lb/>1127 feet. The greatest absolute depths to which<lb/>man has penetrated are in mines that are either<lb/>among lofty mountains or in mountain-valleys, so<lb/>much raised above the sea level, that this has<lb/>either not been reached at all, or has only been<lb/>surpassed by a very small quantity.</p><lb/><p>The Eselschacht at Kuttenberg, Bohemia,<lb/>before it was abandoned, had reached the enor-<lb/>mous depth of 3545 feet (Schmidt, Berggesetze,<lb/>Bd. 1. S. 32.) At St. Daniel, and at Geist, on<lb/>the Röhrerbühel, the works, in the 16th century,<lb/>were 2916 feet deep. A drawing of these work-<lb/>ings of the year 1539 is still preserved. (Joseph<lb/>Von Sperges, Tyroler Bergwerks-Geschichte, S.<lb/>121. See also Humboldt, Gutachten über Heran-<lb/>treibung des Meissner Stollens in die Freiberger<lb/>Erzrevier, published in Herder über den jetzt<lb/>begonnenen Erbstollen, 1838, S. 124.) It may<lb/>be imagined that information of the extraordinary<lb/>depth of the workings at Röhrerbühel had reached<lb/>England at an early period, for in Gilbert&#x2019;s work,<lb/>De Magnete, I find the statement that man had<lb/>penetrated from 2400 to 3000 feet into the bowels<lb/>of the earth.</p><lb/><p>The absolute depth of the mines in the Saxon<lb/>Erzgebirge are 1824 and 1714 feet; the relative<lb/>depths of these respectively are only 626 and 260.<lb/>The absolute depth of the rich workings in Joa-<lb/>chimsthal, Bohemia, is 1919 feet; but taking the<lb/>height of the surface upon Dechen&#x2019;s estimate at<lb/>2250 feet above the level of the sea, it is obvious<lb/>that there the sea level has not even been attained.<lb/>In the Harz, the workings in the Samson pit, at<lb/>Andreasberg, are carried on at the absolute depth<lb/>of 2062 feet. In Old Spanish America, I know<lb/>of no deeper mines than those of Valenciana, near<lb/>Guanaxuato, Mexico; I found the Planes de San<lb/>Bernard 1582 feet deep; but this mine does not<lb/>reach the level of the sea by 5592 feet. If we<lb/>compare the depth of the old Kuttenberg works<lb/>(a depth which exceeds the height of the Brocken,<lb/>and only falls short of that of Etna by 200 feet)<lb/>with the heights of the loftiest buildings that have<lb/>been reared by man (the Pyramid of Cheops and<lb/>the Minster at Strasburg,) we find that the mines<lb/>are to these in proportion of 3 to 1.</p><lb/><p>Basin-shaped curved strata, which dip down on<lb/>one hand and rise at a measureable distance,<lb/>although not penetrated by mines or shafts, still<lb/>suffice to give us accurate information of the con-<lb/>stitution of the crust of the earth at great depths<lb/>from the surface. I have to thank the excellent<lb/><cb/>
            geologist M. Von Dechen for the following:&#x2014;He<lb/>writes to me. &#x201C;The depth of the coal measures at<lb/>Mont St. Gilles, Liege, which our friend M. Von<lb/>Oeynhausen has estimated at 3650 feet below the<lb/>surface, must lie at the depth of 3250 feet below<lb/>the sea level, inasmuch as Mont St. Gilles is cer-<lb/>tainly not 400 feet high; and the coal basin at<lb/>Mons lies fully 1750 feet deeper. These depres-<lb/>sions, however, are trifling when compared with<lb/>that of the coal strata of the Saar-Revier (Saar-<lb/>brücken). After repeated trials, have found that<lb/>the lowest coal strata known in the country of<lb/>Duttweiler near Bettingen, north-eastward from<lb/>Saarlouis, dip 19,406, and 20,656 feet under the<lb/>level of the sea.&#x201D; This conclusion exceeds by<lb/>8000 feet the estimate which I have given in the<lb/>text of Cosmos for the basin of Devonian strata.<lb/>These Belgian coal measures, therefore, lie as far<lb/>below the level of the sea as Chimborazo rises<lb/>above it, at a depth where the temperature of the<lb/>earth must be 224° C. (435° F.) From the<lb/>highest summit of the Himalaya to the bottom of<lb/>this basin, containing vegetable remains of the<lb/>primeval world, we have a perpendicular depth of<lb/>45,000 feet, <hi rendition="#i">i. e.,</hi> <formula notation="TeX">\left( \frac{1}{435} \right)</formula> of the semi-diameter of the<lb/>earth.</p><lb/><p>I have thought it important thus to bring together<lb/>these data in relation to the absolute and relative<lb/>depths that have been reached by man, a subject in<lb/>connection with which many errors have been<lb/>constantly committed, principally, as it seems,<lb/>through faulty reductions of the measurements<lb/>from one standard to another. On proceeding<lb/>eastward from Jerusalem toward the Dead Sea, a<lb/>prospect is gained which, according to our present<lb/>hypsometrical knowledge, is unparalleled on the<lb/>face of the earth. There, on approaching the<lb/>chasm in which the Jordan flows, we advance,<lb/>in open day, along beds of rock, which, accord-<lb/>ing to Bertou&#x2019;s and Russegger&#x2019;s barometrical<lb/>levellings, lie 1300 feet in perpendicular depth<lb/>below the level of the Mediterranean Sea. (<hi rendition="#i">Vide</hi><lb/>Humboldt, Asie Centrale, t. ii., p. 323.)&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Cosmos,</hi><lb/>No. iv., p. 418. <hi rendition="#i">By Alex. Von Humboldt.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
