<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-22" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="339" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On the Luminousness of the Earth.</hi> By <hi rendition="#k" >Baron Von<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If the luminous phenomenon which we ascribe to a galvanic<lb break="yes" />current, <hi rendition="#i">i.e.,</hi> a movement of electricity in a circuit returning into<lb break="yes"/>itself, be designated by the indefinite name of the Northern<lb break="yes"/>light, or the Polar light, nothing more is thereby implied than<lb break="yes"/>the local direction in which the beginning of a certain luminous<lb break="yes"/>phenomenon is most generally, but by no means invariably,<lb break="yes"/>seen. What gives this phenomenon its greatest im portance, is<lb break="yes"/>the fact which it reveals, viz., that <hi rendition="#i">the earth is luminous;</hi> that<lb break="yes"/>our planet, besides the light which it receives from the central<lb break="yes"/>body, the sun, shews itself capable of a proper luminous act or<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="340" facs="#f0002"/> process. The intensity of the earth-light, or rather the degree<lb break="yes"/>of luminosity which it diffuses, exceeds by a little, in the case<lb break="yes"/>of the brightest coloured rays that shoot up to the zenith, the<lb break="yes"/>light of the moon in her first quarter. Occasionally, as on the<lb break="yes"/>7th of January 1831, a printed page can be read without<lb break="yes"/>straining the sight. This light-process of the earth, which the<lb break="yes"/>Polar regions exhibit almost incessantly, leads us by analogy<lb break="yes"/>to the remarkable phenomenon which the planet Venus pre-<lb break="no"/>sents. The portion of this planet which is not illuminated by<lb break="yes"/>the sun, glows occasionally with a proper phosphorescent gleam.<lb break="yes"/>It is not improbable that the moon, Jupiter, and comets, be-<lb break="no"/>sides the reflected sun-light recognisable by the polariscope,<lb break="yes"/>also emit light produced by themselves. Without insisting<lb break="yes"/>on the problematical, but very common phenomenon of <hi rendition="#i">sheet-<lb break="no"/>lightning,</hi> in which the whole of a deep massy cloud is flicker-<lb break="no"/>ingly illuminated for several minutes at a time, we find other<lb break="yes" />examples of terrestrial evolutions of light. To this head be-<lb break="no" />long the celebrated <hi rendition="#i">dry-fogs</hi> of 1783 and 1831, which were lu-<lb break="no"/>minous by night; the steady luminousness of large clouds,<lb break="yes"/>perfectly free from all flickering, observed by Rozier and Bec-<lb break="no"/>caria; and even the pale diffused light, as Arago has well ob-<lb break="no"/>served, which serves to guide us in the open air, in thick-<lb break="no"/>ly clouded autumn and wintry nights, when there is neither<lb break="yes"/>moon nor star in the firmament, nor snow upon the ground.<lb break="yes"/>As in the phenomenon of the Polar light occurring in high<lb break="yes"/>northern latitudes, in other words, in electro-magnetic storms,<lb break="yes"/>floods of flickering, and often party-coloured light stream<lb break="yes"/>through the air; so in the hotter zones of the earth, between<lb break="yes"/>the tropics, are there many thousand square miles of ocean<lb break="yes"/>which are similarly light-engendering. Here, however, the<lb break="yes"/>magic of the light belongs to the organic forces of nature.<lb break="yes"/>Light-foaming flashes the bursting wave, the wide level glows<lb break="yes"/>with lustrous sparks, and every spark is the vital motion of an<lb break="yes"/>invisible animal world. So manifold is the source of terrestrial<lb break="yes"/>light. And shall we conceive it latent, not yet set free in va-<lb break="no"/>pours, as a means of explaining Moser&#x2019;s <hi rendition="#i">pictures,</hi>&#x2014;a discovery in<lb break="yes" />which reality still presents itself to us as a vision shrouded in<lb break="yes"/>mystery?&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Kosmos,</hi> s. 206, and <hi rendition="#i">Cosmos,</hi> English edition, p. 209.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 