<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="369" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">The Planetary System.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;As one of the signs of the pro-<lb/>gress of science, which we feel bound to chronicle, is the opinion<lb/>lately expressed by Sir J. Herschell, that it is impossible any longer<lb/>to attempt the explanation of the movements of all the heavenly<lb/>bodies by simple attraction, as understood in the Newtonian theory,<lb/>these comets, with their trains, perversely turned <hi rendition="#i">from</hi> the sun, de-<lb/>ranging sadly our systematic views. Nor are there (writes Hum-<lb/>boldt,) any constant relations between the distances of the planets<lb/>from the central body round which they revolve and their absolute<lb/>magnitudes, densities, times of rotation, eccentricities, and inclina-<lb/>tions of orbit or axis. We find Mars, though more distant from the<lb/>sun than either the Earth or Venus, inferior to them in magnitude;<lb/>Saturn is less than Jupiter, and yet much larger than Uranus. The<lb/>zone of the telescopic planets, which are so inconsiderable in point<lb/>of volume viewed in the series of distances commencing from the<lb/>sun, comes next before Jupiter, the greatest in size of all the pla-<lb/>netary bodies. Remarkable as is the small density of all the colossal<lb/>planets which are farthest from the sun, yet neither in this respect<lb/>can we recognise any regular succession. Uranus appears to be<lb/>denser than Saturn, and, though the inner group of planets differ<lb/>but little from each other in this particular, we find both Venus and<lb/>Mars less dense than the Earth, which is situated between them.<lb/>The time of rotation increases, on the whole, with increasing solar<lb/>distance; but yet it is greater in Mars than in the Earth, and in<lb/>Saturn than in Jupiter. After other remarks of the same character,<lb/>he adds: &#x201C;The planetary system, in its relation of absolute magni-<lb/>tude, relative position of the axis, density, time of rotation, and dif-<lb/>ferent degrees of eccentricity of the orbits, has, to our apprehension,<lb/><pb n="370" facs="#f0002" />
nothing more of natural necessity than the relative distribution of<lb/>land and water on the surface of our globe, the configuration of con-<lb/>tinents, or the elevation of mountain chains. No general law, in<lb/>these respects, is discoverable either in the regions of space or in<lb/>the irregularities of the crust of the earth.&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
