<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Internal temperature of the earth</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:10</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VI.57</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1845-Internal_temperature_of-1-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Internal_temperature_of-1-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Internal_temperature_of-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Internal_temperature_of-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos: A General Survey of the physical phenomena of the universe&lt;/i&gt;, Bd. 1, London: Hippolyte Baillière 1845, S. 181–187.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos. Entwurf einer physischen Weltbeschreibung&lt;/i&gt;, Bd. 1, Stuttgart/Tübingen: J. G. Cotta 1845, S. 178–184.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Internal temperature of the earth</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1845</date>
          <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Practical Mechanic and Engineer’s Magazine&lt;/i&gt; 1 (22. November 1845), S. 42–44.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Fußnoten mit Asterisken und Kreuzen; Schmuck: Kapitälchen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="42" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>INTERNAL TEMPERATURE OF THE EARTH.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#i">(From Humboldt&#x2019;s Cosmos.)</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> figure of the earth, and the degree of solidity or density<lb break="yes"/>which it possesses, stand in intimate connection with the forces<lb break="yes"/>which animate our globe, in so far, namely, as these forces are not<lb break="yes"/>excited or awakened from without by our planetary position oppo-<lb break="no"/>site to a self-luminous central body. The oblateness, a conse-<lb break="no"/>quence of the operation of the centrifugal force upon a rotating<lb break="yes"/>mass, reveals the pristine or former state of fluidity of our planet.<lb break="yes"/>On the setting or solidification of this fluid, which we are accus-<lb break="no"/>tomed to conjecture as existing in the shape of a vaporiform mat-<lb break="no"/>ter, originally heated to a very high temperature, an enormous<lb break="yes"/>amount of latent caloric became free. If the process of consolida-<lb break="no"/>tion began in the way Fourier will have it, by radiation from the<lb break="yes" />surface into celestial space, the parts of the earth which are<lb break="yes" />situated towards the centre must still be hot and molten. While,<lb break="yes"/>after long radiation of the heat of the central parts towards the<lb break="yes"/>surface, a state of stability in the temperature of the earth is finally<lb break="yes"/>attained, it is at the same time assumed that, with an increase in<lb break="yes"/>depth, there will also be a regular progressive increase of tempera-<lb break="no"/>ture. The temperature of the water which flows from bores of<lb break="yes"/>great depth into the bowels of the earth (Artesian wells), imme-<lb break="no"/>diate experiments on the temperature of the rocks in mines, above<lb break="yes"/>all, however, the volcanic activity of the earth, in other words, the<lb break="yes"/>discharge of molten mineral streams through fissures in the surface,<lb break="yes"/>bear testimony in the most incontestible manner to this increase<lb break="yes"/>of temperature in the upper strata of the earth at considerable<lb break="yes" />depths. From conclusions which, it is true, are only founded on<lb break="yes" />analogy, it is more than probable that the temperature goes on in-<lb break="no"/>creasing in a still greater degree towards the centre.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The conclusions which have been presented to us by an ingenious,<lb break="yes" />and, for this class of inquiries, singularly perfect analytical calculus,<lb break="yes"/>on the motion of heat in homogeneous metallic spheroids,<note place="foot" n="*">Poisson has developed an hypothesis totally different from the<lb break="yes"/>view advocated by Fourier (Theorie<choice><sic>.</sic><corr type="editorial"></corr></choice> analyt. de la Chaleur). He<lb break="yes"/>denies the present fluid state of the centre of the earth; he be-<lb break="no"/>lieves &#x201C;that in cooling by radiation to the medium surrounding<lb break="yes"/>the earth, the parts first consolidated on the surface sunk down-<lb break="no"/>wards, and that by a double upward and downward current, the<lb break="yes"/>great inequality was lessened which would have taken place in a<lb break="yes"/>solid body cooling from the surface.&#x201D; The great geometrician<lb break="yes" />thinks it more probable that the consolidation commenced in the<lb break="yes"/>parts lying nearer to the centre; &#x201C;the phenomenon of the increase<lb break="yes"/>of heat with the depth does not extend to the whole mass of the<lb break="yes"/>earth, and is a mere consequence of the motion of our planet in<lb break="yes"/>universal space, the several parts of which, by reason of their <choice><sic>steller</sic><corr type="editorial">stellar</corr></choice><lb break="yes"/>heat (chaleur stellaire) have very different temperatures.&#x201D; The<lb break="yes" />heat of the water of our Artisian wells, according to Poisson, is<lb break="yes"/>therefore heat which bas penetrated the body of the earth from<lb break="yes"/>without; the earth may be viewed as we should a mass of rock<lb break="yes"/>transported from the equator to the pole in so short a time, that it<lb break="yes"/>could not cool completely. The increase of temperature in this<lb break="yes"/>block would not extend completely to its centre. The physical<lb break="yes"/>doubts which may reasonably be raised against this extraordinary<lb break="yes"/>cosmical hypothesis (an hypothesis which ascribes to heavenly space<lb break="yes" />what must rather belong to matter in its first transition from the<lb break="yes"/>gaseous to the solid state), may be found collected in Poggen-<lb break="no"/>dorff&#x2019;s Annalen, Bd. xxxix. <choice><sic>s.</sic><corr type="editorial">S.</corr></choice> 93&#x2014;100.</note> can<lb break="yes"/>only be applied, with many precautions, to the actual constitution<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="43" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/> of our planet, in consequence of our ignorance of the matter of<lb break="yes"/>which the earth is composed, of the various capacities for heat and<lb break="yes"/>powers of conduction inherent in the superimposed masses, and of<lb break="yes"/>the chemical transformations which solid and fluid bodies undergo<lb break="yes"/>under enormous pressures. Most difficult of all, for our powers of<lb break="yes"/>comprehension, is the conception of the boundary line betwixt the<lb break="yes"/>fluid mass of the interior and the concrete mineral species of the<lb break="yes"/>outer crust of the earth, of the gradual increase of solidity in the<lb break="yes"/>strata, and the state of tenacious semi-fluidity of earthy matters,<lb break="yes"/>to which the known laws of hydraulics can only apply under con-<lb break="no"/>siderable modifications. The sun and moon, which keep the<lb break="yes"/>ocean in a state of alternate ebb and flow, act in all likelihood<lb break="yes"/>even down to these depths. Beneath a vault of already consoli-<lb break="no"/>dated mineral strata, periodical rises and falls of a molten mass<lb break="yes"/>may, indeed, be readily enough conceived as taking place, and<lb break="yes"/>occasioning inequalities in the pressure exerted against the vault.<lb break="yes"/>The amount and the influence of such oscillations can, however, be<lb break="yes" />but small; and if the relative position of the attracting heavenly<lb break="yes"/>bodies must here also produce spring tides, it is still certain that<lb break="yes"/>the concussions of the earth&#x2019;s surface which take place, are not to<lb break="yes"/>be ascribed to these, but to other more powerful internal forces.<lb break="yes"/>There are groups of phenomena, the existence of which it is still<lb break="yes"/>useful to adduce in illustration of the universality of the attrac-<lb break="no"/>tive influences of the sun and moon upon the external and internal<lb break="yes"/>life of the globe, however little we may feel ourselves in a condition<lb break="yes"/>to determine numerically their amount.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From experiments on Artesian wells, which agree pretty closely,<lb break="yes" />the temperature of the upper crust of the earth appears, on an<lb break="yes" />average, to increase 1° of the centigrade thermometer for each 92<lb break="yes"/>Paris feet in perpendicular depth.<note place="foot" n="*">The degree of the centigrade thermometer = 1&#x00B7;8° of Fahrenheit.<lb break="yes"/>The Parisian foot = 1<formula notation="TeX" >\frac{1}{13}</formula> Eng. ft. very nearly.</note> Did this increase go on in<lb break="yes"/>arithmetical progression, then, as I have already had occasion to<lb break="yes"/>observe,<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">The increase in temperature is found in the Puits de Greneille,<lb break="yes"/>from 98&#x00B7;4 feet; in the bore of New-Salzwerk, Minden, almost 91<lb break="yes"/>feet; at Pregny, Geneva, also 91 feet, although there the outlet is<lb break="yes"/>1510 feet above the level of the sea. This agreement of results, from<lb break="yes"/>bores that are severally 1683, 2094, and 680 feet in absolute depth,<lb break="yes"/>by a method first suggested in 1821 by Arago (Annuaire, 1835, p.<lb break="yes"/>234), is very striking. The two points of the earth at a short per-<lb break="no" />pendicular distance from one another, whose annual temperature is<lb break="yes"/>ascertained with the greatest precision, are probably the external<lb break="yes"/>atmosphere of the Observatory of Paris and of the cellar under the Ob-<lb break="no"/>servatory. The former is 10°&#x00B7;822, the latter 11°&#x00B7;834 C.; difference<lb break="yes" />1°&#x00B7;012 C. for 86 feet of depth (Poisson, Theorie, &#x0026;c., p. 415 and<lb break="yes"/>462). In the course of the last 17 years, from causes which have<lb break="yes"/>not been ascertained, the thermometer of the <hi rendition="#i">Caves</hi> has risen 0°&#x00B7;220<lb break="yes"/>C. If the penetration of waters from lateral channels into the<lb break="yes" />main bore of Artesian wells produces some disturbance, it must be<lb break="yes"/>admitted that in reference to mines there are many more perturb-<lb break="no"/>ing causes at work, and that interfere with the accuracy of conclu-<lb break="no"/>sions in reference to their temperature at different depths. The<lb break="yes"/>general result of Reich&#x2019;s great work on the temperature of the<lb break="yes"/>mines of the Saxon Erzgebirge is the somewhat slow increase of 1°<lb break="yes"/>C. for 128&#x2153; feet of descent. Yet Phillips (Poggend. Ann. B. 34, S.<lb break="yes"/>191), in a shaft of the Monkwearmouth coal-pit, found an increase of<lb break="yes"/>1° C. for 99<formula notation="TeX" >\frac{6}{10}</formula> feet of descent, exactly what Arago found in the<lb break="yes"/>Puits de <choice><sic>Grenelle</sic><corr type="editorial">Greneille</corr></choice>.</note> would a granitic stratum at the depth of 5<formula notation="TeX">\frac{2}{10}</formula> geographi-<lb break="no"/>cal miles<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">That is German miles of 15 to a degree of the equator, and con-<lb break="no"/>sequently each = to 4 Eng. Geo. miles of 60 to a degree, or to 4&#x00B7;603<lb break="yes" />statute miles of 69&#x00B7;038 to a degree of the equator.</note> (from four to five times the depth of the highest peak in<lb break="yes"/>Himalaya range) be in a molten state.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In the body of the earth there are three kinds of motion of heat<lb break="yes" />to be distinguished: the first is periodical, and, according to the<lb break="yes"/>position of the sun and the season of the year, alters the tempera-<lb break="no"/>ture of the earth&#x2019;s strata according as the heat penetrates from<lb break="yes"/>above downwards, or as it passes in the same way from below up-<lb break="no"/>wards. The second kind of motion is likewise an effect of the sun,<lb break="yes"/>and is of extraordinary slowness: part of the heat which has pene-<lb break="no"/>trated the equatorial regions is propagated along the interior of the<lb break="yes"/>crust of the earth towards the poles, and there escapes into the<lb break="yes"/>atmosphere and distant space. The third kind of motion is the<lb break="yes"/>slowest of all: it consists in the secular cooling of the body of the<lb break="yes"/>earth, in the dissipation of the small amount of the primitive heat<lb break="yes"/>of the planet which at the present time is still given off from its<lb break="yes" />surface. This loss which the central heat suffers was very con-<lb break="no" />siderable at the epochs of the oldest revolutions of the globe; since<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> the commencement of the historical period, however, it is scarcely<lb break="yes"/>mensurable by our instruments. The surface of the earth, from the<lb break="yes"/>foregoing view, is intermediate between the red heat of the interior<lb break="yes"/>strata, and the temperature of space, which is probably below the<lb break="yes"/>congealing point of mercury.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The periodical variations of temperature which the altitude of the<lb break="yes" />sun and the meteorological processes of the atmosphere occasion,<lb break="yes"/>are propagated in the interior of the earth, but only to very small<lb break="yes"/>depths. This slow conduction of heat by the ground, however,<lb break="yes"/>lessens the loss of warmth in the winter, and is favourable to<lb break="yes"/>deeply-rooted trees. Points which lie at different depths in a ver-<lb break="no"/>tical line come to the maximum and minimum of the communicated<lb break="yes"/>temperature in very different times. The more distant they are<lb break="yes"/>from the surface, the smaller are the differences of these extremes.<lb break="yes"/>On the continent of Europe, between the parallels of 48° and 52°,<lb break="yes"/>the stratum of invariable temperature occurs at from 55 to 60 feet<lb break="yes"/>deep; even at half this depth the oscillations of the thermometer,<lb break="yes"/>in consequence of the influence of the seasons, scarcely amount to<lb break="yes"/>half a degree. In tropical climates, on the contrary, the stratum<lb break="yes"/>of invariable temperature is met with at no more than a foot below<lb break="yes"/>the surface; and this fact has been used by Boussingault, in an<lb break="yes"/>able manner, as a convenient and, in his opinion, accurate way of<lb break="yes" />determining the mean temperature of the air of a place. This<lb break="yes" />mean temperature of the air at a determinate point, or in a<lb break="yes" />group of points of the surface lying near to one another, is, in a<lb break="yes"/>certain measure, the fundamental element of the climatic relations,<lb break="yes"/>and also of the relations in reference to civilization of a country;<lb break="yes"/>but the mean temperature of the whole surface is very different<lb break="yes"/>from that of the earth itself. The oft-repeated questions, whether,<lb break="yes"/>in the course of centuries, this has suffered any considerable change?<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;whether the climate of a country has become deteriorated?&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>whether the winters have not become milder, and the summers<lb break="yes"/>in the same proportion colder?&#x2014;can only be decided by the ther-<lb break="no" />mometer; and the discovery of this instrument scarcely dates<lb break="yes" />three half-centuries back? its rational application no more than<lb break="yes"/>about 120 years. The nature and novelty of the means, therefore,<lb break="yes"/>prescribe very narrow bounds to inquiries into the tempera-<lb break="no"/>ture of the air. It is quite otherwise with the solution of the<lb break="yes"/>great problem of the internal heat of the whole globe. In the<lb break="yes"/>same way as from the unaltered rate of a pendulum we can con-<lb break="no"/>clude on the unchanged preservation of its temperature, so does<lb break="yes"/>the unaltered velocity of rotation of the earth on its axis inform<lb break="yes"/>us of the degree of stability of its mean temperature. This per-<lb break="no"/>ception of the relations between the length of the day and the<lb break="yes"/>earth&#x2019;s temperature, is one of the most brilliant applications of a<lb break="yes"/>long knowledge of the heavenly motions to the thermal condition<lb break="yes"/>of our planet. The velocity of rotation of the earth, to wit, de-<lb break="no"/>pends on its volume: precisely as the axis of rotation of the mass<lb break="yes"/>that was cooling gradually by radiation would become shorter, so<lb break="yes"/>through diminution in temperature must the velocity of rotation be<lb break="yes" />increased, and the length of the day be abridged. Now, by a com-<lb break="no" />parison of the secular inequalities of the moon&#x2019;s motions with the<lb break="yes"/>eclipses that have been observed in the more ancient times, it ap-<lb break="no"/>pears that since the age of Hipparchus, for full 2000 years, there-<lb break="no"/>fore the length of the day has not varied by the one-hundredth part<lb break="yes"/>of a second. From this, again, and within the utmost limits of<lb break="yes"/>the decrease<note place="foot" n="*">It is to be observed that the fraction <formula notation="TeX" >\frac{1}{170}</formula> of a centigrade degree<lb break="yes"/>of mercurial thermometer, which is given in text as the limit of<lb break="yes" />stability of the heat of the earth since Hipparchus&#x2019;s time, rests on<lb break="yes"/>the assumption that the dilitation of the <choice><sic>meterials</sic><corr type="editorial">materials</corr></choice> of which the body<lb break="yes"/>of the earth consists is the same as that of glass = <formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{100000}</formula> for 1° C.<lb break="yes"/>of heat.</note> the mean temperature of the body of the earth is<lb break="yes"/>discovered not to have altered, in the course of 2000 years, by<lb break="yes"/>the <formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{170}</formula>th part of a thermometrical degree.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This invariableness of form farther implies great invariabilty in<lb break="yes" />the distribution of density in the interior of the earth. The trans-<lb break="no"/>latory movements effected by the eruptions of our present volcanoes,<lb break="yes"/>the outbursts of ferruginous lavas, and the filling up of empty<lb break="yes"/>chasms and hollows with dense masses of rock, are therefore to be<lb break="yes"/>regarded as mere superficial phenomena, as peculiarities of parts<lb break="yes"/>of the earth&#x2019;s crust, which, in point of magnitude, when contrasted<lb break="yes"/>with the semi-diameter of the earth, are utterly insignificant.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The internal heat of the planet, in its course and distribution,<lb break="yes" />I have described almost exclusively from the results and beautiful<lb break="yes"/>experiments of Fourier. Poisson, however, doubts the uninter-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="44" facs="#f0003"/> rupted increase of the terrestrial heat from the surface to the<lb break="yes"/>centre. He believes that all the heat has penetrated from without,<lb break="yes"/>inwards, and that the temperature of the interior of the earth de-<lb break="no"/>pends on the very high or very low temperature of the universal<lb break="yes"/>space through which the solar system has moved. This hypothesis,<lb break="yes"/>devised by one of the most profound mathematicians of the age,<lb break="yes"/>has satisfied himself only; it has met with little countenance from<lb break="yes"/>other natural philosophers and geologists.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 