<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head>On the Races of Man.</head><lb/>
    <p>While we maintain the unity of the human<lb/>species, we at the same time repel the depress-<lb/>ing assumption of superior and inferior races<lb/>of men. There are nations more susceptible<lb/>of cultivation, more highly civilized, more en-<lb/>nobled by mental cultivation than theirs; but<lb/>none in themselves nobler than others. All<lb/>are, in like degree, designed for freedom&#x2014;a<lb/>freedom which, in the ruder conditions of so-<lb/>ciety, belongs only to the individual, but which,<lb/>in social states, enjoying political institutions,<lb/>appertains as a right to the whole body of the<lb/>community. If we would indicate an idea<lb/>which, throughout the whole course of history,<lb/>has ever more and more widely extended its<lb/>empire, or which, more than any other, testi-<lb/>fies to the much contested and still more deci-<lb/>dedly misunderstood perfectibility of the<lb/>whole human race, it is that of establishing<lb/>our common humanity&#x2014;of striving to remove<lb/>the barriers which prejudice and limited views<lb/>of every kind have erected among men, and<lb/>to treat all mankind, without reference to re-<lb/>ligion, nation, or color, as one fraternity, one<lb/>great community, fitted for the attainment of<lb/>one object&#x2014;the unrestrained development of<lb/>the physical powers. This is the ultimate and<lb/>highest aim of society, identical with the di-<lb/>rection implanted by nature in the mind of<lb/>man, toward the indefinite duration of his ex-<lb/>istence. He regards the earth, in all its lim-<lb/>its, and the heavens, as far as his eye can scan,<lb/>their bright and starry depths, as inwardly his<lb/>own, given to him as the objects of his contem-<lb/>plation, and as a <choice><sic>fiend</sic><corr type="editorial">field</corr></choice> for the development of<lb/>his energies. Even the child longs to pass the<lb/>hills or the seas which enclose his narrow<lb/>home; yet when his eager steps have borne<lb/>him beyond those limits, he pines, like the<lb/>plant, for his native soil; and it is by this<lb/>touching and beautiful attribute of man&#x2014;this<lb/>longing for that which is unknown, and this<lb/>fond remembrance of that which is lost, that<lb/>he is spared from an exclusive attachment to<lb/>the present. Thus deeply rooted in the inner-<lb/>most nature of man, and even enjoined upon<lb/>him by his highest tendencies, the recognition<lb/>of the bond of humanity becomes one of the<lb/>noblest leading principles in the history of man-<lb/>kind.</p>
    <p>With these words, which draw their charm<lb/>from the depths of feeling, let a brother be<lb/>permitted to close this general description of<lb/>the natural phenomena of the universe. From<lb/>the remotest nebul&#x00E6;, and from the revolving<lb/>double stars, we have descended to the minu-<lb/>test organisms of animal creation, whether<lb/>manifested in the depths of ocean, or on the sur-<lb/>face of our globe, and to the delicate vegeta-<lb/>ble germs which clothe the naked declivity of<lb/>the ice crowned mountain summit; and here<lb/>we have been able to arrange these phenome-<lb/>na according to partially known laws: but oth-<lb/>er laws, of a more mysterious nature, rule the<lb/>higher spheres of the organic world, in which<lb/>is comprised the human species in all its varied<lb/>conformation, its creative intellectual power,<lb/>and the languages to which it has given exist-<lb/>ence. A physical delineation of nature termi-<lb/>nates at the point where the sphere of intellect<lb/>begins, and a new world of mind is opened to<lb/>our view. It marks the limits, it does not pass<lb/>it.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i" >Humboldt</hi>.</p>
</div><lb/>
</body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
