<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-22" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="8" facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Heights and Depths.</hi>
                </head>
                <p>
                    &#x2014;In speaking of the greatest<lb/>depth within the earth reached by human labour, we<lb/>must recollect that there is a difference between the <hi rendition="#i">ab-<lb/>solute depth</hi> (that is to say, the depth below the earth&#x2019;s<lb/>surface at that point), and the <hi rendition="#i">relative depth</hi> (or that<lb/>below the level of the sea). The greatest relative depth<lb/>that man has hitherto reached is probably the bore at<lb/>the new salt works at Minden, in Prussia; in June, 1844,<lb/>it was exactly 1,993 feet, the absolute depth being 2,231<lb/>feet. The temperature of the water at the bottom was<lb/>91 degrees Fahrenheit, which, assuming the mean tem-<lb/>perature of the air at 49 degrees 3 seconds, gives an aug-<lb/>mentation of temperature of 1 degree for every 54 feet.<lb/>If we compare the depth of the old Kuttenberger mine<lb/>(a depth greater than the height of the Brocken, and<lb/>only 200 feet less than that of Vesuvius), with the<lb/>loftiest structure that the hands of man have erected<lb/>(with the Pyramid of Cheops, and the Cathedral of Stras-<lb/>burg), we find that they stand in the ratio of eight to one.<lb/>In descending eastward from Jerusalem, towards the<lb/>Dead Sea, a view presents itself to the eye which, accord-<lb/>ing to our present hypsometrical knowledge of our planet,<lb/>is unrivalled in any country; as we approach the open<lb/>ravine through which the Jordan takes its course, we<lb/>tread, with the open sky above us, on rocks which,<lb/>according to the barometric measurements of Burton<lb/>and Russegger, are 1,385 feet below the level of the<lb/>Mediterranean. Poisson endeavoured, in a singular<lb/>manner, to solve the difficulty attending an assumption<lb/>of the spontaneous ignition of meteoric stones at an<lb/>elevation above the earth where the density of the atmos-<lb/>phere is almost null. These are his words:&#x2014;&#x201C;It is diffi-<lb/>cult to attribute, as is usually done, the incandescence of<lb/>aerolites to friction against the molecules of the atmos-<lb/>phere, at an elevation above the earth where the density<lb/>of the air is almost null. May we not suppose that the<lb/>electric fluid, in a neutral condition, forms a kind of at-<lb/>mosphere, extending far beyond the mass of our atmos-<lb/>phere, yet subject to terrestrial attraction, although phy-<lb/>sically imponderable, and consequently following our<lb/>globe in its motion? According to this hypothesis, the<lb/>bodies of which we are speaking would, on entering this<lb/>imponderable atmosphere, decompose the natural fluid<lb/>by their unequal action on the two electricities, and they<lb/>would then be heated, and in a state of incandescence by<lb/>becoming electrified.&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Cosmos.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>