<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="93" facs="#f0001" />
<cb/>
<div n="1"><head>ON THE RACES OF MAN.</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">Whilst</hi> we maintain the unity of the<lb/>human species, we at the same
                    time<lb/>repel the depressing assumption of<lb/>superior and inferior races of
                    men.<lb/>There are nations more susceptible of<lb/>cultivation, more
                    highly-civilized, more<lb/>ennobled by mental cultivation than<lb/>others: but
                    none in themselves nobler<lb/>than others. All are, in like degree,<lb/>designed
                    for freedom&#x2014;a freedom which,<lb/>in the ruder conditions of society,
                    be-<lb/>longs only to the individual, but which,<lb/>in social states, enjoying
                    political insti-<lb/>tations, appertains as a right to the<lb/>whole body of the
                    community. If we<lb/>would indicate an idea which, through-<lb/>out the whole
                    course of history, has<lb/>ever more and more widely extended<lb/>its empire, or
                    which, more than any<lb/>other, testifies to the much-contested<lb/>and still
                    more decidedly misunderstood<lb/>perfectibility of the whole human race,<lb/>it
                    is that of establishing our common<lb/>humanity&#x2014;of striving to remove
                    the<lb/>barriers which prejudice and limited<lb/>views of every kind have
                    erected<lb/>amongst men, and to treat all man-<lb/>kind, without reference to
                    religion,<lb/>nation, or colour, as one fraternity,<lb/>one great community,
                    fitted for the<lb/>attainment of one object&#x2014;the unre-<lb/>strained
                    development of the physical<lb/>powers. This is the ultimate and high-<lb/><cb/>
                    est aim of society, identical with the<lb/>direction implanted by nature in
                    the<lb/>mind of man, towards the indefinite<lb/>duration of his existence. He
                    regards<lb/>the earth, in all its limits, and the<lb/>heavens, as far as his eye
                    can scan<lb/>their bright and starry depths, as in-<lb/>wardly his own, given to
                    him as the<lb/>objects of his contemplation, and as a<lb/>field for the
                    development of his ener-<lb/>gies. Even the child longs to pass the<lb/>hills or
                    the seas which enclose his nar-<lb/>row home; yet when his eager steps<lb/>have
                    borne him beyond those limits,<lb/>he pines, like the plant, for his
                    native<lb/>soil; and it is by this touching and<lb/>beautiful attribute of
                    man&#x2014;this long-<lb/>ing for that which is unknown, and<lb/>this fond
                    remembrance of that which<lb/>is lost, that he is spared from an ex-<lb/>clusive
                    attachment to the present.<lb/>Thus deeply-rooted in the innermost<lb/>nature of
                    man, and even enjoined upon<lb/>him by his highest tendencies, the
                    re-<lb/>cognition of the bond of humanity be-<lb/>comes one of the noblest
                    leading prin-<lb/>ciples in the history of mankind.</p><lb/><p>With these words, which draw their<lb/>charm from the depths of feeling, let a<lb/>brother be
                    permitted to close this gene-<lb/>ral description of the natural pheno-<lb/>mena
                    of the universe. From the re-<lb/>motest nebul&#x00E6;, and from the
                    revolving<lb/>double stars, we have descended to the<lb/>minutest organisms of
                    animal creation,<lb/>whether manifested in the depths of<lb/>ocean, or on the
                    surface of our globe,<lb/>and to the delicate vegetable germs<lb/>which clothe
                    the naked declivity of the<lb/>ice-crowned mountain summit; and<lb/>here we have
                    been able to arrange<lb/>these phenomena according to partially<lb/>known laws:
                    but other laws, of a more<lb/>mysterious nature, rule the higher<lb/>spheres of
                    the organic world, in which<lb/>is comprised the human species in all<lb/>its
                    varied conformation, its creative<lb/>intellectual power, and the
                    languages<lb/>to which it has given existence. A<lb/>physical delineation of
                    nature termi-<lb/>nates at the point where the sphere of<lb/>intellect begins,
                    and a new world of<lb/>mind is opened to our view. It marks<lb/>the limit, but
                    does not pass it. &#x2014; <hi rendition="#i">Hum-<lb/>boldt</hi>.</p></div><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
