<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-22" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="3" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">WIND AND CURRENT CHARTS.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                </head>
                <p>The great demand for these charts among seamen, and the interest which they have excited among phi-<lb break="no"/>losophers, make it proper that I should give a more detailed account than I have yet given as to the progress<lb break="yes" />of the work, the objects in view, and the prospects ahead.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This is the more proper because I hope thereby to impress seafaring men and others, who have it in their<lb break="yes"/>power to facilitate or retard the work, with the importance of the undertaking.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In the present condition of the surface of our planet,&#x201D; says the most celebrated traveller and philoso-<lb break="no"/>pher of the age, &#x201C;the area of the solid is to that of the fluid parts as 1 to 2&#x2158;, (according to Rigaud, as 100 to<lb break="yes"/>270.) The islands form scarcely <hi rendition="#sup">1</hi>/<hi rendition="#sub">22</hi> of the continental masses, which are so unequally divided that they con-<lb break="no"/>sist of three times more land in the northern than in the southern hemisphere; the latter being, therefore, pre-<lb break="no"/>eminently oceanic. From 40° South Latitude, to the Antartic Pole, the Earth is almost entirely covered with<lb break="yes"/>water. The fluid element predominates in like manner between the eastern shores of the old, and the western<lb break="yes"/>shores of the new continent, being only interspersed with some few insular groups. The learned hydrographer,<lb break="yes"/>Fleurieu, has very justly named this vast oceanic basin which, under the tropics, extends over 145° of Lon-<lb break="no"/>gitude, the Great Ocean, in contradistinction to all other seas. The southern and western hemispheres (reckon-<lb break="no"/>ing the latter from the meridian of Teneriffe) are, therefore, more rich in water than any other region of the<lb break="yes"/>whole earth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;These are the main points involved in the consideration of the relative quantity of land and sea, a relation<lb break="yes"/>which exercises so important an influence on the distribution of temperature, the variation in atmospheric pres-<lb break="no"/>sure, the direction of the winds, and the quantity of moisture contained in the air, with which the development<lb break="yes"/>of vegetation is so essentially connected. When we consider that nearly three-fourths of the upper surface<lb break="yes"/>of our planet are covered with water, we shall be less surprised at the imperfect condition of meteorology<lb break="yes"/>before the beginning of the present century; since it is only during the subsequent period that numerous ac-<lb break="no" />curate observations on the temperature of the sea at different latitudes, and at different seasons, have been made<lb break="yes"/>and numerically compared together.&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Cosmos.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;I beg you to express to Lieut. Maury, the author of the beautiful Charts of the Winds and Currents,<lb break="yes"/>prepared with so much care and profound learning, my hearty gratitude and esteem. It is a great underta-<lb break="no"/>king, equally important to the practical navigator and for the advance of meteorology in general. It has been<lb break="yes"/>viewed in this light in Germany by all persons who have a taste for physical geography. In an analogous<lb break="yes"/>way anything of isothermal countries (countries of equal annual temperature,) has for the first time become really<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="4" facs="#f0002"/> fruitful, since Dove has taught us the isotherms of the several months chiefly on the land; since two-thirds of<lb break="yes"/>the atmosphere rests upon the sea, Maury&#x2019;s work is so much the more welcome and valuable because it<lb break="yes"/>includes at the same time the oceanic currents, the course of the winds and the temperature. How remark-<lb break="no" />able are the relations of temperatures, in Sheet No. 2, South Atlantic, East and West of Longitude 40;<lb break="yes"/>how much would this department of meteorology gain if it were filled up according to Maury&#x2019;s proposition<lb break="yes"/>in Commodore Lewis Warrington&#x2019;s Log Book. The shortening of the voyage from the United States to the<lb break="yes"/>Equator, is a beautiful result of this undertaking. The bountiful manner in which these Charts are distributed<lb break="yes"/>raises our expectations still higher.&#x201D;</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Baron Von Humboldt to Dr. Flügel, U. S. Consul, Leipsic.</hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 