<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-21" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-12-12" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="625" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>GENERAL VIEW OF THE SOLAR SYSTEM.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>89. We shall conclude this treatise with a general view<lb break="yes"/>of the Solar System, compiled from Humboldt&#x2019;s <hi rendition="#i">Cosmos</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>(Sabine&#x2019;s translation), a work of most extraordinary learning<lb break="yes"/>and scientific value, to which we would gladly direct the<lb break="yes"/>student&#x2019;s attention.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The Solar System consists, according to our present<lb break="yes" />knowledge<note place="foot" n="*">Neptune and forty asteroids have been discovered since this was written.</note>, of eleven principal planets, eighteen moons or<lb break="yes"/>satellites, and myriads of comets, three of which (called pla-<lb break="no"/>netary comets) do not pass beyond the orbits of the prin-<lb break="no"/>cipal planets. We may, with considerable probability, include<lb break="yes"/>within the dominion of our sun, a revolving ring of finely<lb break="yes"/>divided or nebulous matter, situated perhaps between the<lb break="yes"/>orbits of Venus and Mars, but certainly extending beyond<lb break="yes"/>that of the earth, which we call the Zodiacal Light; and a<lb break="yes"/>host of extremely small asteroids, the paths of which inter-<lb break="no"/>sect, or very nearly approach, that of the earth, and which<lb break="yes"/>present to us the ph&#x00E6;nomena of aerolites or shooting stars.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;It has been proposed to consider the telescopic planets,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="626" facs="#f0002"/> Vesta, Juno, Ceres, and Pallas, with their more excentric<lb break="yes"/>intersecting and greatly inclined orbits, as forming a middle<lb break="yes"/>zone, or group, in our planetary system; and if we follow<lb break="yes"/>out this view, we shall find that the comparison of the inner<lb break="yes"/>group of planets, comprising Mercury, Venus, the Earth, and<lb break="yes"/>Mars, with the outer group consisting of Jupiter, Saturn,<lb break="yes"/>and Uranus, presents several striking contrasts. The planets<lb break="yes"/>of the inner group, which are nearer the sun, are of more<lb break="yes"/>moderate size, are denser, revolve about their respective<lb break="yes"/>axes more slowly in nearly equal periods, which differ little<lb break="yes"/>from twenty-four hours, are less compressed at the poles,<lb break="yes"/>and with one exception are without satellites. The external<lb break="yes"/>planets, more distant from the sun, are of much greater<lb break="yes"/>magnitude, five times less dense, more than twice as rapid<lb break="yes"/>in their rotation round their axes, more compressed at their<lb break="yes"/>poles, and richer in moons in the proportion of 17 to 1, if<lb break="yes"/>Uranus really has the six satellites ascribed to it.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In viewing these general characteristics of the two<lb break="yes" />groups, we must admit however that they cannot be strictly<lb break="yes" />applied to each of the planets in particular; nor are there<lb break="yes" />any constant relations between the distances of the planets<lb break="yes" />from the sun, their absolute magnitudes, densities, times of<lb break="yes" />rotation, excentricities, and inclinations of orbits and of<lb break="yes" />axis. We find Mars, though more distant from the sun<lb break="yes"/>than either the Earth or Venus, inferior to them in magni-<lb break="no"/>tude. Saturn is less than Jupiter, and yet much larger than<lb break="yes"/>Uranus. The zone of the telescopic planets comes next<lb break="yes"/>before Jupiter, the greatest of all the planetary bodies; and<lb break="yes"/>yet the disks of these small planets are less than twice the<lb break="yes"/>size of France. Remarkable as is the small density of the<lb break="yes"/>planets which are furthest from the sun, yet neither in this<lb break="yes"/>respect can we recognise any regular succession. Uranus<lb break="yes"/>appears to be denser than Saturn; and we find both Venus<lb break="yes"/>and Mars less dense than the earth, which is situated be-<lb break="no"/>tween them. The time of rotation decreases on the whole<lb break="yes"/>with increasing solar distance, but yet it is greater in Mars<lb break="yes"/>than in the earth, and in Saturn than in Jupiter. Among<lb break="yes"/>all the planets, the orbits of Juno, Pallas, and Mercury, have<lb break="yes"/>the greatest excentricity; and Venus and the Earth which<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="627" facs="#f0003"/> immediately follow each other have the least; while Mercury<lb break="yes"/>and Venus (which are likewise neighbours) present, in this<lb break="yes"/>respect, the same contrast as do the four smaller planets,<lb break="yes"/>whose paths are so closely interwoven. The excentricities<lb break="yes"/>of Juno and Pallas are nearly equal, but are each three<lb break="yes"/>times as great as those of Ceres and Vesta. Nor is there<lb break="yes"/>more regularity in the inclination of the planes of the orbits<lb break="yes"/>of the planets to that of the ecliptic, or in the position of<lb break="yes"/>their axes of rotation relatively to their orbits; on which<lb break="yes"/>latter position the relations of climate, seasons, and length<lb break="yes"/>of days depend, more than on the excentricity. It is in the<lb break="yes"/>planets which have the most elongated ellipses, Juno, Pallas,<lb break="yes"/>and Mercury, that we find, though not in equal proportion,<lb break="yes"/>the greatest inclination of the orbits to the ecliptic. Nei-<lb break="no"/>ther do we find a regular order of succession in the position<lb break="yes"/>of the axes of the few planets, (four or five,) of the planes<lb break="yes"/>of rotation of which we have at present any certain know-<lb break="no"/>ledge. Judging by the position of the satellites of Uranus,<lb break="yes"/>the axis is inclined barely 11° to the plane of its orbit;<lb break="yes"/>and Saturn is placed intermediately between this planet, in<lb break="yes"/>which the axis of rotation almost coincides with the plane<lb break="yes"/>of its orbit, and Jupiter, whose axis is almost perpendicular<lb break="yes"/>to it.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Among the fourteen satellites, concerning which investi-<lb break="no" />gation has arrived at some degree of certainty, the system of<lb break="yes" />the seven satellites of Saturn offers the greatest contrasts,<lb break="yes" />both of absolute magnitude, and of distance from the planet.<lb break="yes" />The sixth satellite is probably but little smaller than Mars<lb break="yes" />(whose diameter is twice that of our moon), while, on the<lb break="yes" />other hand, the two innermost satellites belong to the smallest<lb break="yes" />cosmical bodies of our system. After the sixth and seventh<lb break="yes"/>of the satellites of Saturn comes, in order of volume, the third<lb break="yes" />and brightest of Jupiter&#x2019;s.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The twelve moons attendant on Saturn, Jupiter, and the<lb break="yes" />Earth, all move, as do their primary planets, from West to<lb break="yes" />East, and in elliptical orbits differing little from circles. The<lb break="yes"/>satellites of Uranus exhibit some remarkable differences from<lb break="yes"/>the movements of other satellites and planets. In all other<lb break="yes"/>cases, the orbits are but little inclined to the ecliptic, and the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="628" facs="#f0004"/> movements are from West to East, including Saturn&#x2019;s rings,<lb break="yes"/>which may be regarded as belts formed of an aggregation of<lb break="yes"/>satellites; but the satellites of Uranus move in planes almost<lb break="yes"/>perpendicular to the ecliptic, and the direction of their motion<lb break="yes"/>is from East to West.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;It appears highly probable, that the times of rotation of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">all</hi> secondary planets, or satellites, are the same as their times<lb break="yes"/>of revolution round their primaries; so that they always pre-<lb break="no"/>sent to the latter the same face. In the case of the moon,<lb break="yes"/>owing to certain disturbing causes, rather more than half the<lb break="yes"/>surface is visible to us at different times; but as much as<lb break="yes"/>three-sevenths of the whole surface is always invisible.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Of all planetary bodies, comets,&#x2014;though their mean<lb break="yes" />mass is probably much less than the five-thousandth part of<lb break="yes" />the earth,&#x2014;are those which occupy the greatest space, their<lb break="yes"/>wide-spreading tails often extending over many millions of<lb break="yes"/>miles. The cone of light-reflecting vapour, which radiates<lb break="yes"/>from them has been found in some instances to equal in<lb break="yes"/>length the distance of the earth from the sun. It is even<lb break="yes"/>probable that the vapour of the tails of the comets of 1819<lb break="yes"/>and 1823 mixed with our atmosphere.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Comets shew such diversities of form, that the descrip-<lb break="no" />tion given of one of them cannot be applied without much<lb break="yes" />caution to another. The fainter telescopic comets are for<lb break="yes"/>the most part without tails. We can distinguish in the larger<lb break="yes"/>comets the <hi rendition="#i">head</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">nucleus</hi>, and the <hi rendition="#i">tail.</hi> The intensity of<lb break="yes"/>light in the nucleus of a comet does not increase in a uniform<lb break="yes"/>manner towards the centre, but bright zones alternate with<lb break="yes"/>concentric nebulous envelopes. The tail appears sometimes<lb break="yes"/>single, more rarely double; in the comet of 1744, the tail had<lb break="yes"/>six branches. The tails are sometimes straight, sometimes<lb break="yes"/>curved, and sometimes inflected like a flame in motion; they<lb break="yes"/>are always turned from the sun, and so directed that the<lb break="yes"/>prolongation of the axis would pass through the centre of that<lb break="yes"/>body.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Amongst the countless host of uncalculated or still un-<lb break="no" />discovered comets, it is highly probable that there are many,<lb break="yes" />the major axes of whose orbits may far exceed even that<lb break="yes"/>of the comet of 1680, to which Encke assigns a period of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="629" facs="#f0005"/> upwards of 8800 years. In order to afford some notion of<lb break="yes"/>the distance in space of a fixed star or other sun from the<lb break="yes"/>aphelion of this comet, (the one of the bodies of our solar<lb break="yes"/>system, which, according to our present knowledge, attains<lb break="yes"/>the greatest degree of remoteness,) it may be mentioned, that,<lb break="yes"/>according to the most recent determinations of parallax, even<lb break="yes"/>the nearest fixed star is at least 250 times more distant from<lb break="yes"/>our sun than this comet at its aphelion.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Another class of bodies remains to be considered; namely,<lb break="yes" />those minute asteroids, which, when they arrive in a fragmen-<lb break="no" />tary state within our atmosphere, we designate by the name<lb break="yes"/>of <hi rendition="#i">aerolites</hi>, or meteoric stones.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Shooting stars, fireballs, and meteoric stones, are with<lb break="yes" />great probability regarded as small masses moving with<lb break="yes" />planetary velocities in space, and revolving in conic sections<lb break="yes" />round the sun, in accordance with the laws of universal gravi-<lb break="no" />tation. These masses approach the Earth in their path, are<lb break="yes" />attracted by it, and enter our atmosphere, becoming luminous<lb break="yes" />at its limits, when they frequently let fall stony fragments,<lb break="yes" />heated in a greater or less degree, and covered with a shining<lb break="yes" />black crust. While there are exploding and smoke-emitting<lb break="yes" />balls of fire, which are luminous even in the bright sunshine<lb break="yes" />of a tropical day, and sometimes exceed in size the apparent<lb break="yes" />diameter of the moon, there are on the other hand shooting<lb break="yes" />stars which fall in immense numbers, and are of such small<lb break="yes" />dimensions, that they exhibit themselves only as moving<lb break="yes" />points, or as phosphorescent lines. Whether among the many<lb break="yes" />luminous bodies which shoot across the sky, there may not<lb break="yes"/>be some of a different nature from others, still remains un-<lb break="no" />certain.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The connection of meteoric stones with the more splendid<lb break="yes" />ph&#x00E6;nomenon of fireballs, and the fact that meteoric stones<lb break="yes"/>sometimes fall from fireballs with a force which causes them<lb break="yes"/>to sink to a depth of from ten to fifteen feet into the earth,<lb break="yes"/>have been proved by a variety of observations. In some<lb break="yes"/>instances a small and very dark cloud forms suddenly in a<lb break="yes"/>perfectly clear sky, and the stones are hurled from it with a<lb break="yes"/>noise resembling repeated discharges of cannon. Such a<lb break="yes"/>cloud, moving over a whole district of country, has sometimes<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="630" facs="#f0006"/> covered it with thousands of fragments, very various in size,<lb break="yes"/>but similar in quality.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;We have as yet scarcely any knowledge in regard to<lb break="yes"/>the physical and chemical processes which contribute to the<lb break="yes" />formation of these ph&#x00E6;nomena. We know by measurement<lb break="yes" />the astonishing and quite planetary velocity of shooting stars,<lb break="yes" />fireballs, and meteoric stones; in this respect therefore we<lb break="yes" />are able to recognise what is general and uniform in the ph&#x00E6;-<lb break="no"/>nomena; but the successive transformations undergone are<lb break="yes"/>not known to us. The largest meteoric masses yet known<lb break="yes"/>to us are seven and seven and a half feet in length; the<lb break="yes"/>meteoric stone of &#x00C6;gos Potamos, celebrated in antiquity,<lb break="yes"/>and mentioned in the chronicle of the Parian Marbles, and<lb break="yes"/>which fell about the year of the birth of Socrates, has been<lb break="yes"/>described as being of the size of two millstones and equal in<lb break="yes"/>weight to a waggon load.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Shooting stars fall either singly or sporadically, or in<lb break="yes" />groups of many thousands which are compared by Arabian<lb break="yes"/>writers to flights of locusts. The latter cases are periodical,<lb break="yes"/>and the meteors are then seen in streams, moving for the<lb break="yes"/>most part in parallel directions. Of the periodic groups<lb break="yes"/>those hitherto best known are the ph&#x00E6;nomena of the 12th to<lb break="yes"/>the 14th of November, and on the 10th of August or day of<lb break="yes"/>St Lawrence, whose &#x201C;fiery tears&#x201D; were long since recognised<lb break="yes"/>in England as a recurring meteorological ph&#x00E6;nomenon.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;It is probable that the different streams of meteors,<lb break="yes" />each consisting of myriads of small bodies, intersect the orbit<lb break="yes" />of the earth in the same way that Biela&#x2019;s Comet does; accord-<lb break="no"/>ing to this view, we may imagine that they form a continuous<lb break="yes"/>ring, each pursuing its course in a common direction. We<lb break="yes"/>cannot yet determine whether the variations in the epochs<lb break="yes"/>at which the stream becomes visible to us, and the observed<lb break="yes"/>retardations of the ph&#x00E6;nomena, indicate a regular progression<lb break="yes"/>of the points of intersection of the ring with the earth&#x2019;s orbit,<lb break="yes"/>or whether they are to be explained by the irregular grouping<lb break="yes"/>of these very small bodies, and by the supposition that the<lb break="yes"/>zone formed by them has a width which the earth requires<lb break="yes"/>several days to traverse. Should increased probability be<lb break="yes"/>given to the former of these hypotheses, the discovery of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="631" facs="#f0007"/> older observations of these ph&#x00E6;nomena will acquire a special<lb break="yes"/>interest.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;To complete our view of all that belongs to the solar<lb break="yes" />system, which now, since the discovery of the small planets,<lb break="yes" />of the comets of short period, and of the meteoric asteroids,<lb break="yes" />appears so complex and so rich in forms, we have yet to con-<lb break="no" />sider the <hi rendition="#i">Zodiacal Light.</hi> Those who have dwelt long in the<lb break="yes"/>zone of Palms, must retain a pleasing remembrance of the<lb break="yes"/>mild radiance of the ph&#x00E6;nomenon, which rising pyramidally<lb break="yes"/>illumines a portion of the unvarying length of the tropical<lb break="yes"/>nights. In the obscurer sky and thicker atmosphere of the<lb break="yes"/>temperate zone, the Zodiacal Light is only distinctly visible<lb break="yes"/>in the beginning of Spring, when it may be seen after evening<lb break="yes"/>twilight above the Western horizon, and at the end of Autumn,<lb break="yes"/>before the commencement of morning twilight above the<lb break="yes"/>Eastern horizon.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;We may with great probability attribute the Zodiacal<lb break="yes" />Light to the existence of an extremely oblate ring of nebulous<lb break="yes" />matter, revolving freely in space between the orbits of Venus<lb break="yes" />and Mars. We can indeed at present form no certain judg-<lb break="no"/>ment concerning the true dimensions of the supposed ring;<lb break="yes"/>its possible augmentation by emanations from the tails of<lb break="yes"/>many millions of comets when at their perihelia; the singular<lb break="yes" />variability of its extent, which seems sometimes not to exceed<lb break="yes" />that of our own orbit; or concerning its not improbable inti-<lb break="no" />mate connection with the more condensed cosmical vapour in<lb break="yes"/>the vicinity of the sun. The nebulous particles of which the<lb break="yes"/>ring consists, and which revolve round the sun according to<lb break="yes"/>the same laws as the planets, may be either self-luminous, or<lb break="yes"/>may reflect the light of the sun.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">
                        <hi rendition="#k">the end.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 