<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="354" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1">
    <head>
        <hi rendition="#k">Heights and Depths.</hi>
    </head>
    <p>In speaking of the greatest depth<lb/>within the earth reached by human<lb/>labour, we must recollect that there<lb/>is a difference between the <hi rendition="#i">absolute<lb/>depth</hi> (that is to say, the depth be-<lb/>low the earth&#x2019;s surface at that<lb/>point), and the <hi rendition="#i">relative depth</hi> (or<lb/>that below the level of the sea).<lb/>The greatest relative depth that<lb/>man has hitherto reached is pro-<lb/>bably the bore at the new salt<lb/>works at Minden, in Prussia; in<lb/>June 1844, it was exactly 1993<lb/>feet, the absolute depth being 2231<lb/>feet. The temperature of the water<lb/>at the bottom was 91 degrees<lb/>Fahrenheit, which, assuming the<lb/>mean temperature of the air at 49<lb/>degrees 3 seconds, gives an aug-<lb/>mentation of temperature of 1<lb/>degree for every 54 feet. If we<lb/>compare the depth of the old Kut-<lb/>tenberger mine (a depth greater<lb/>than the height of the Brocken,<lb/>and only 200 feet less than that of<lb/>Vesuvius), with the loftiest struc-<lb/>ture that the hands of man have<lb/>erected (with the Pyramid of<lb/>Cheops, and the Cathedral of Stras-<lb/>burg), we find that they stand in<lb/>the ratio of eight to one. In de-<lb/>scending eastward from Jerusalem<lb/>towards the Dead Sea, a view pre-<lb/>sents itself to the eye which, accord-<lb/>ing to our present hypsometrical<lb/>knowledge of our planet, is un-<lb/>rivalled in any country; as we<lb/>approach the open ravine through<lb/>which the Jordan takes its course,<lb/>we tread, with the open sky above<lb/>us, on rocks which, according to<lb/>the barometric measurements of<lb/>Burton and <choice><sic>Russeseggar</sic><corr type="editorial">Russegger</corr></choice>, are 1385<lb/>feet below the level of the Mediter-<lb/>ranean. Poisson endeavoured, in<lb/>a singular manner to solve the diffi-<lb/><pb n="355" facs="#f0002" />
culty attending an assumption of<lb/>the spontaneous ignition of meteoric<lb/>stones at an elevation above the<lb/>earth where the density of the at-<lb/>mosphere is almost null. These<lb/>are his words:&#x2014;&#x201C;It is difficult to<lb/>attribute, as is usually done, the<lb/>incandescence of aerolites to fric-<lb/>tion against the molecules of the<lb/>atmosphere, at an elevation above<lb/>the earth where the density of the<lb/>air is almost null. May we not<lb/>suppose that the electric fluid, in a<lb/>neutral condition, forms a kind of<lb/>atmosphere, extending far beyond<lb/>the mass of our atmosphere, yet<lb/>subject to terrestrial attraction,<lb/>although physically imponderable,<lb/>and consequently following our<lb/>globe in its motion? According<lb/>to this hypothesis, the bodies of<lb/>which we are speaking would, on<lb/>entering this imponderable atmo-<lb/>sphere, decompose the natural fluid<lb/>by their unequal action on the two<lb/>electricities, and they would then<lb/>be heated, and in a state of incan-<lb/>descence by becoming electrified.<lb/>&#x2014;(Humboldt&#x2019;s Cosmos.)
</p>
</div><lb/></body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
