<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-22" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-11-30" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="545" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>From the Daily Advertiser.<lb break="yes"/>EXTRACT FROM A LETTER FROM BARON VON<lb break="yes"/>HUMBOLDT.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <dateline>
                    <hi rendition="#et">Potsdam, June 19th, 1850.</hi>
                </dateline>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>You can hardly doubt the great respect, nay, I<lb break="yes"/>may say the amazement, which I feel at the rapid<lb break="yes"/>progress which has been made in the United States<lb break="yes"/>during the last eight or ten years. I refer to the<lb break="yes"/>works in history and literature of Prescott and<lb break="yes"/>Ticknor;<note place="foot" n="*">George Ticknor&#x2019;s History of Spanish Literature, in<lb break="yes"/>three volumes, is a masterly work; besides, Europe has<lb break="yes"/>scarcely a single historian that can compare with William<lb break="yes"/>Prescott in purity and dignity of style. Several years<lb break="yes"/>ago I was present and saw with what high respect the<lb break="yes"/>first appearance of Prescott&#x2019;s Ferdinand and Isabella was<lb break="yes"/>welcomed in Holland House.</note> on geography, by Fremont and Emory;<lb break="yes" />and the discoveries in practical astronomy, made<lb break="yes"/>with princely instruments, by Maury, Gillis, Bond<lb break="yes"/>and Gould. You can scarcely doubt the lively<lb break="yes"/>interest I feel in this matter, when you remember<lb break="yes"/>that my great age furnishes me with points of com-<lb break="no"/>parison from the time of Jefferson. At that time I<lb break="yes"/>found those great statesmen of imperishable glory,<lb break="yes"/>the founders of the free constitution. But anything<lb break="yes"/>of a scientific nature, which we now see developed<lb break="yes"/>there, was then only in the embryonie state. Yes,<lb break="yes"/>one was inclined to doubt, and certainly not with-<lb break="no"/>out reason, whether republican governments from<lb break="yes" />their very nature were not hostile to the active<lb break="yes"/>promotion of scientific undertakings. The interest-<lb break="no"/>ing expedition of the meritorious Lieut. Gillis to<lb break="yes"/>Chili, shows in the object aimed at, what protection<lb break="yes"/>the government affords to science, even when it<lb break="yes"/>does not immediately offer results with any direct<lb break="yes"/>practical value. The settlements of the western<lb break="yes" />coasts, though brought about by circumstances<lb break="yes"/>which often, alas, remind one of the old Spanish<lb break="yes"/>Conquista, will lead to consequences of great im-<lb break="no"/>portance on the affairs of the world.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>For a long time I have maintained, on account<lb break="yes"/>of the situation of the waters, the course of the<lb break="yes"/>winds, the configuration of the land, and the an-<lb break="no"/>tiquity of civilization, that the proper strength of<lb break="yes"/>the tropical part of America lay, not in the eastern<lb break="yes"/>coasts, but on the side towards Asia. But may the<lb break="yes"/>States which are constantly being formed to the<lb break="yes" />west of the Rocky Mountains be free from the evil<lb break="yes"/>[<hi rendition="#i">Unheil</hi>] of Slavery.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>I beg you to express to Lient. Maury, the author<lb break="yes"/>of the beautiful chart of the winds and currents,<lb break="yes"/>prepared with so much care and profound learning,<lb break="yes"/>my hearty gratitude and esteem. It is a great<lb break="yes"/>undertaking, equally important to the practical<lb break="yes"/>navigator and for the advance of meteorology in<lb break="yes" />general. It has been viewed in this light, in Ger-<lb break="no"/>many, by all persons who have a taste for physical<lb break="yes"/>geography. In an analogous way, anything of<lb break="yes"/>isothermal countries (countries of equal annual<lb break="yes"/>temperature) has for the first time become really<lb break="yes"/>fruitful. Since Dove has taught us the isotherms<lb break="yes" />of the several months, chiefly on the land; since<lb break="yes"/>two thirds of the atmosphere rests upon the sea,<lb break="yes"/>Maury&#x2019;s work is so much the more welcome and<lb break="yes"/>valuable, because it includes at the same time the<lb break="yes"/>oceanie currents, the course of the winds and the<lb break="yes"/>temperature. How remarkable are the relations<lb break="yes"/>of temperature, (temperatur verhaltoitze,) in sheet<lb break="yes"/>No. E. South Atlantic. East and West of Lon. 40;<lb break="yes" />how much would this department of meteorology<lb break="yes"/>gain if it were filled up according to Maury&#x2019;s prop-<lb break="no"/>osition, in Commodore Lewis Harrington&#x2019;s Log-<lb break="no"/>book. The shortening of the voyage from the<lb break="yes"/>United States to the Equator is a beautiful result<lb break="yes"/>of this undertaking. The bountiful manner in<lb break="yes" />which these charts are distributed, raises our ex-<lb break="no"/>pectations still higher. You see that I do not<lb break="yes"/>belong to the unthankful.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Lieut. Gillis&#x2019; letter to you, (of Feb. 25th,) the<lb break="yes"/>latest account of the variable star in the ship,<lb break="yes"/>(Argus,) the description of the observatory at<lb break="yes"/>Cambridge by Mr. Cranch Bond, to whom we are<lb break="yes"/>indebted for the important discoveries of the new<lb break="yes"/>rings of Saturn, and the revolutions of the <hi rendition="#i">nebula</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>in Andromeda, (in Gould&#x2019;s Astronomical Journal,)<lb break="yes"/>have given me much pleasure. I had the pleasure<lb break="yes" />to become acquainted with Mr. Gould here (in<lb break="yes"/>Berlin.) He holds a distinguished reputation<lb break="yes"/>amongst our German observers. The settlement<lb break="yes"/>of my talented and amiable friend, Agassiz, in North<lb break="yes"/>America, must have an important influence in all<lb break="yes"/>departments of Natural History.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 