<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Carbonic Acid and Sulphureous Acid Springs – Cold Springs – Hot Springs – Mud Volcanoes – Volcanoes</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:10</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VI.51</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-1-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-1-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-4-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1845-Carbonic_Acid_and-7-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos: A General Survey of the physical phenomena of the universe&lt;/i&gt;, Bd. 1, London: Hippolyte Baillière 1845, S. 228–247.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos. Entwurf einer physischen Weltbeschreibung&lt;/i&gt;, Stuttgart/Tübingen: Cotta 1845, Bd. 1, 225–244.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Carbonic Acid and Sulphureous Acid Springs – Cold Springs – Hot Springs – Mud Volcanoes – Volcanoes</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1845</date>
          <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal&lt;/i&gt; 39:78 (Oktober 1845), S. 277–293.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="277" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Carbonic Acid and Sulphureous Acid Springs&#x2014;Cold Springs&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Hot Springs&#x2014;Mud Volcanoes&#x2014;Volcanoes.</hi> By Baron <hi rendition="#k">Alex-<lb break="no"/>ander von Humboldt.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" n="*">This extract from Cosmos (English edition by Bailliere) at present<lb break="yes"/>in course of publication, is slightly altered and enlarged.</note>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Having now taken a general survey of the activity, that<lb break="yes"/>is, of the internal life of the globe, in its heat, in its electro-<lb break="no" />magnetic tension, in its luminous emanations at the poles, in<lb break="yes" />its irregularly-recurring phenomenon of motion, we come to<lb break="yes" />chemical changes in the crust of the earth, and in the compo-<lb break="no" />sition of the atmosphere, which are, in like manner, the conse-<lb break="no" />quence of planetary vital activity. From the ground we see<lb break="yes" />effusions of watery vapour and of gaseous carbonic acid, mostly<lb break="yes" />free from all admixture of azote; of carburetted hydrogen gas,<lb break="yes" />in the Chinese province of Sse-tschuan, for thousands of years,<lb break="yes" />and in the state of New York, where, in the village of Fre-<lb break="no" />donia, it has lately been employed for economical purposes in<lb break="yes" />heating and lighting;<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;" xml:id="fn1-1" next="#fn1-2">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Carburetted Hydrogen Spring at Fredonia.</hi>&#x2014;Sailed in a steam-boat<lb break="yes"/>to Fredonia, a town of 1200 inhabitants, with neat white houses, and<lb break="yes"/>six churches. The streets are lighted up with <hi rendition="#i">natural gas,</hi> which bubbles<lb break="yes"/>out of the ground, and is received into a gasometer, which I visited.<lb break="yes"/>This gas consists of <hi rendition="#i">carburetted hydrogen,</hi> and issues from a black bitumi-<lb break="no"/>nous slate, one of the beds of the Hamilton group of the New York<lb break="yes"/>geologists, or part of the Devonian formation of Europe. The lighthouse-<lb break="no"/>keeper at Fredonia told me, that, near the shore, at a considerable dis-<lb break="no"/>tance from the gasometer, he bored a hole through this black slate, and<lb break="yes" />the gas soon collected in sufficient quantity to explode, when ignited.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Travels in North America.</hi> By Charles Lyell. Vol. ii., p. 89.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Burning Spring of Niagara.</hi>&#x2014;At the Falls of Niagara, where we next<lb break="yes"/>spent a week, residing in a hotel on the Canada side, I resumed my<lb break="yes"/>geological explorations of last summer. Every part of the scenery,<lb break="yes"/>from Grand Island above the Falls, to the ferry at Queenstown, seven<lb break="yes"/>miles below, deserves to be studied at leisure.<lb break="yes"/>We visited the &#x201C;burning spring&#x201D; at the edge of the river above the<lb break="yes"/>rapids, where carburetted hydrogen, or, in the modern chemical phrase-<lb break="no"/>ology, a light hydro-carbon, similar to that before mentioned at Fredo-<lb break="no"/>nia, rises from beneath the water out of the limestone rock. The<lb break="yes"/>bituminous matter supplying this gas is probably of animal origin, as<lb break="yes"/>this limestone is full of marine mollusca, crustacea, and corals, without</note> of sulphuretted hydrogen gas, of sul-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="278" facs="#f0002"/> phur fumes, and, more rarely, of sulphureous and hydro-chloric<lb break="yes"/>acid vapours. Such emanations from fissures in the ground,<lb break="yes"/>do not only indicate the dominion of volcanoes long extinct<lb break="yes"/>or still burning; they are farther observed exceptionally in<lb break="yes"/>districts in which neither trachyte nor any other volcanic rock<lb break="yes"/>appears at the surface. In the Andes of Quindiu, I have seen<lb break="yes"/>sulphur precipitated from hot sulphureous vapours issuing out<lb break="yes"/>of mica-slate, at a height of 6410 feet above the level of the<lb break="yes"/>sea; whilst the same, and, as it used to be regarded, primitive<lb break="yes"/>rock, in Cerra Cuelo, near Ticsan, south of Quito, exhibits an<lb break="yes"/>enormous bed of sulphur in pure quartz.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Of all the gaseous springs which the earth pours forth, those<lb break="yes"/>of carbonic acid (mofetten) are still, at the present time, the<lb break="yes" />most important, both in number and extent. Germany, in<lb break="yes"/>her deeply-cut valleys of the Eifel, in the neighbourhood of<lb break="yes"/>Lake Lach, in the Kesselthal of Wehr, and in Western Bohe-<lb break="no"/>mia, as also in the burning foci of the primeval world, or their<lb break="yes" />vicinity, shews us these effusions of carbonic acid as a kind of<lb break="yes"/>last effort of volcanic activity. In former epochs, where, with<lb break="yes"/>a higher temperature of the earth, and the frequency of fissures<lb break="yes"/>yet unfilled, the processes which we are here describing pro-<lb break="no"/>ceeded more actively where carbonic acid gas and watery<lb break="yes"/>vapours were mingled with the atmosphere in larger quantities<lb break="yes"/>than at present, the youthful vegetable world, as Adolph<lb break="yes"/>Brongniart has acutely observed, must have attained almost<lb break="yes"/>everywhere, and independently of geographical position, to<lb break="yes"/>the most rank luxuriance and evolution of its organs. In<lb break="yes"/>the ever hot, ever moist atmosphere, surcharged with carbonic<lb break="yes"/>acid, vegetables must have found such vital excitement, such<lb break="yes"/>superfluity of nourishment, as enabled them to supply the<lb break="yes"/>material of those beds of coal and lignite, the exhaustion of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="&#x2020;" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1">vegetable remains, unless some fucoids may have decomposed in the<lb break="yes"/>same strata. The invisible gas makes its way in countless bubbles<lb break="yes"/>through the clear transparent waters of the Niagara. On the applica-<lb break="no" />tion of a lighted candle, it takes fire, and plays about with a lambent<lb break="yes"/>flickering flame, which seldom touches the water, the gas being, at first,<lb break="yes"/>too pure to be inflammable, and only obtaining sufficient oxygen after<lb break="yes"/>mingling with the atmosphere at the height of several inches above the<lb break="yes"/>surface of the stream.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Lyell&#x2019;s Travels in North America,</hi> vol. ii., p. 90.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Edit. of Phil. Journal.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="279" facs="#f0003"/> which it is difficult to conceive, and which now serve as foun-<lb break="no"/>dations for the physical strength and the welfare of nations.<note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn2-1" next="#fn2-2">In Lyell&#x2019;s interesting Travels in North America, already quoted, we<lb break="yes"/>meet with the following remarks on the quantity of carbonic acid in the<lb break="yes"/>atmosphere, in which the plants of the coal formation flourished:&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Before concluding the remarks, which are naturally suggested by a<lb break="yes"/>visit to the Great Dismal, I shall say a few words on a popular doctrine,<lb break="yes" />favoured by some geologists, respecting an atmosphere highly charged<lb break="yes"/>with carbonic acid, in which the coal plants are supposed to have<lb break="yes"/>flourished. Some imagine the air to have been so full of choke damp<lb break="yes"/>during the ancient era alluded to, that it was unfitted for the respiration<lb break="yes"/>of warm-blooded quadrupeds and birds, or even reptiles, which require<lb break="yes"/>a more rapid oxygenation of their blood than creatures lower in the scale<lb break="yes"/>of organization, such as have alone been met with hitherto in the car-<lb break="no"/>boniferous and older strata. It is assumed, that an excess of oxygen<lb break="yes"/>was set free when the plants which elaborated the coal subtracted many<lb break="yes"/>hundred million tons of carbon from the carbonic acid gas which pre-<lb break="no"/>viously loaded the air. All this carbon was then permanently locked up<lb break="yes"/>in the solid seams of coal, and the chemical composition of the earth&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>atmosphere essentially altered.<lb break="yes"/>But they who reason thus are bound to inform us what may have<lb break="yes"/>been the duration of the period in the course of which so much carbon<lb break="yes"/>was secreted by the powers of vegetable life; and, secondly, what<lb break="yes"/>accession of fresh carbonic acid did the air receive in the same. We<lb break="yes"/>know that, in the present state of the globe, the air is continually sup-<lb break="no"/>plied with carbonic acid from several sources, of which the three prin-<lb break="no"/>cipal are, <hi rendition="#i">first,</hi> The daily putrefaction of dead animal and vegetable sub-<lb break="no"/>stances; <hi rendition="#i">secondly,</hi> The disintegration of rocks charged with carbonic acid<lb break="yes"/>and organic matter; and, <hi rendition="#i" >thirdly,</hi> The copious evolution of this gas from<lb break="yes" />mineral springs and the earth, especially in volcanic countries. By that<lb break="yes"/>law, which causes two gases of different specific gravity, when brought<lb break="yes"/>into contact, to become uniformly diffused and mutually absorbed<lb break="yes"/>through the whole space which they occupy, the heavy carbonic acid<lb break="yes"/>finds its way upwards through all parts of the atmosphere, and the solid<lb break="yes"/>materials of large forests are given out from the earth in an invisible<lb break="yes" />form, or in bubbles rising through the water of springs. Peat mosses of<lb break="yes"/>no slight depth, and covering thousands of square miles, are thus fed<lb break="yes"/>with their mineral constituents, without materially deranging the con-<lb break="no"/>stituents of the atmosphere breathed by man. Thousands of trees grow<lb break="yes"/>up, float down to the delta of the Mississippi and other rivers, and are<lb break="yes" />buried, and yet the air, at the end of many centuries, may be as much<lb break="yes"/>impregnated with carbonic acid as before.<lb break="yes" />Coral reefs are, year after year, growing in the ocean; springs and</note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Such beds are principally contained in basins, and are peculiar<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="280" facs="#f0004"/> to certain parts of Europe. They are abundant in the British<lb break="yes"/>Isles, in Belgium, in France, on the Lower Rhine, and in<lb break="yes"/>Upper Silesia. In the same primeval times of all-pervading<lb break="yes"/>volcanic action, too, must those enormous quantities of carbo-<lb break="no"/>naceous matter have issued from the bowels of the earth, which<lb break="yes"/>all the limestone rocks contain, and which, separated from<lb break="yes"/>oxygen, and represented in the solid form, composes about an<lb break="yes"/>eighth part of the absolute bulk of those mountain masses.<lb break="yes"/>The carbonic acid which the atmosphere still contained, and<lb break="yes"/>which was not absorbed by the alkaline earths, was gradually<lb break="yes"/>consumed by the vegetation of the primeval world; so that<lb break="yes"/>the atmosphere, purified by the processes of vegetable life,<lb break="yes"/>by and by contained no more of the gas than was uninjurious<lb break="yes"/>to the organization of such animals as people the earth at the<lb break="yes"/>present time. Sulphurous or sulphuric acid vapours, too,<lb break="yes"/>occurring more frequently, and much more abundantly, then<lb break="yes"/>than now, occasioned the destruction of the inhabitants of the<lb break="yes"/>inland waters&#x2014;mollusca and numerous genera of fishes, as<lb break="yes"/>well as the formation of the strangely contorted beds of gypsum,<lb break="yes"/>which have often, apparently, been shaken by earthquakes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Under precisely similar physical relations, there were fur-<lb break="no"/>ther thrown out from the bosom of the earth various gases<lb break="yes"/>and liquids, mud, and, from the eruption cones of volcanoes,<lb break="yes"/>which are but a species of intermitting springs, streams of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn2-2" prev="#fn2-1">rivers feed the same ocean with carbonic acid and lime; but we have no<lb break="yes"/>reason to infer, that when mountain masses of calcareous rock have thus<lb break="yes"/>been gradually formed in the sea, any essential change in the chemical<lb break="yes"/>composition of its waters has been brought about. We have no accu-<lb break="no"/>rate data, as yet, for measuring, whether in our own time, or at any<lb break="yes"/>remote geological era, the relative supply and consumption of carbon in<lb break="yes"/>the air or the ocean, causes the amount of those elements to vary greatly;<lb break="yes"/>but the variation, if admitted, would not have caused an excess, but<lb break="yes" />rather a deficit, of carbon, in the periods most productive of coal or peat,<lb break="yes"/>as compared to any subsequent or antecedent epochs. In fact, a climate<lb break="yes"/>favouring the rank and luxurious growth of plants, and, at the same<lb break="yes"/>time, checking their decay, and giving rise to peat or accumulations of<lb break="yes"/>vegetable matter, might, for the time, diminish the average amount of<lb break="yes" />carbonic acid in the atmosphere&#x2014;a state of things precisely the reverse<lb break="yes"/>of that assumed by those to whose views I am now objecting.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Travels<lb break="yes"/>in North America.</hi> By Charles Lyell. Vol. i., p. 150.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Edit. of Phil.<lb break="yes"/>Journal.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="281" facs="#f0005"/> molten earths. All these matters owe their temperature, and<lb break="yes"/>the nature of their chemical constitution, to the place of their<lb break="yes"/>origin. The mean temperature of ordinary springs is lower<lb break="yes"/>than that of the atmosphere where they appear, when the<lb break="yes"/>water is derived from high levels; their temperature increases<lb break="yes"/>with the depth of the strata with which they come in con-<lb break="no"/>tact at their origin. The numerical law of this increase has<lb break="yes"/>been stated above. The mixture of the waters, which come<lb break="yes"/>from the mountain elevations, or from the depths of the<lb break="yes"/>earth, renders the position of the isogeothermal lines, or<lb break="yes"/>lines of equal internal heat of the earth, difficult of determina-<lb break="no"/>tion, when the conclusion has to be come to from the tempe-<lb break="no"/>rature of springs as they rise. So, at least, did I and my<lb break="yes"/>friends find it in some experiments which we made in Nor-<lb break="no"/>thern Asia. The temperature of springs, which has been so<lb break="yes"/>constant an object of physical investigation for the last half<lb break="yes"/>century, depends, like the height of the line of perpetual<lb break="yes"/>snow, on numerous and highly complex causes. It is a func-<lb break="no"/>tion of the temperature of the stratum in which they have<lb break="yes"/>their origin, of the capacity for heat of the ground, and of the<lb break="yes"/>quantity and temperature of the atmospheric or meteoric<lb break="yes"/>water that falls; which last, again, according to the mode of<lb break="yes"/>its origin, differs in its temperature from that of the lower<lb break="yes"/>strata of the atmosphere.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Cold springs, as they are called, can only give the mean<lb break="yes" />temperature of the air, if unmixed with water that is rising<lb break="yes" />from great depths, or that is descending from considerable<lb break="yes" />heights, and when they have flowed for a very long way under<lb break="yes" />the surface&#x2014;in our latitudes from 40 to 60 feet, in the equi-<lb break="no"/>noctial zone, according to Boussingault, one foot. These<lb break="yes"/>depths are those, in fact, of the stratum of rock in which, in<lb break="yes"/>the temperate and torrid zone respectively, the point of in-<lb break="no"/>variable temperature begins, in which the hourly, diurnal, or<lb break="yes"/>monthly variations in temperature of the air are no longer per-<lb break="no"/>ceived.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Hot springs burst out of the most diversified mineral strata;<lb break="yes"/>the hottest of all the permanent springs which have yet been<lb break="yes" />observed, and which I myself discovered, flow remote from all<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="282" facs="#f0006"/> volcanoes. I here refer to the Aguas calientes de Las Trin-<lb break="no"/>cheras between Porto Cabello and New Valencia, in South<lb break="yes"/>America, and to the Aguas de Comangillas, near Guanaxuato,<lb break="yes"/>in Mexico. The first spring, issuing from granite, indicated<lb break="yes"/>90&#x00B7;3° C.; the second, which issues from basalt, shewed 96&#x00B7;4° C.<lb break="yes"/>The depth of the source of water of these temperatures, from<lb break="yes"/>what we know of the law of increase of temperature in the inte-<lb break="no"/>rior of the earth, must probably be about 6700 feet (more than<lb break="yes"/>half a geographical mile). If the cause of the heat of thermal<lb break="yes"/>springs, as well as of active volcanoes, be the universally diffused<lb break="yes"/>heat of the earth, then would rocks produce an effect only<lb break="yes"/>through their capacity for, and their power of, conducting heat.<lb break="yes"/>The hottest of all the permanent springs, those, namely, from<lb break="yes"/>95° to 97° C. (204° to 207&#x00B7;6° F.), it is remarkable, are the<lb break="yes"/>purest, are those that contain the smallest quantity of mineral<lb break="yes"/>matter in solution. Their temperature appears, on the whole,<lb break="yes"/>to be less permanent than that of springs between 50° and 74°<lb break="yes"/>C., the invariableness of which, both in regard to temperature<lb break="yes"/>and mineral impregnation, has been maintained so wonderfully,<lb break="yes"/>within the confines of Europe at least, during the last fifty or<lb break="yes"/>sixty years, <hi rendition="#i">i. e.,</hi> since accurate thermometrical observations<lb break="yes"/>and chemical analyses were made. Boussingault found that<lb break="yes"/>the thermal springs of Las Trincheras had risen in temperature,<lb break="yes"/>in the course of twenty-three years (from 1800, when my<lb break="yes"/>journey was performed, to 1823), from 93&#x00B7;3° to 97° C. This<lb break="yes"/>very smoothly-flowing spring is, consequently, at this time 7°<lb break="yes"/>C. higher in temperature than the intermitting Geyser and<lb break="yes"/>Strokr, the temperature of which has been lately more carefully<lb break="yes"/>ascertained by Krug of Nidda. One of the most remarkable<lb break="yes"/>proofs of the origin of these hot springs being due to the per-<lb break="no"/>colation of cold meteoric water into the interior of the earth,<lb break="yes"/>and its contact there with a volcanic focus, was presented in<lb break="yes"/>the preceding century, in connexion with the volcano of Jo-<lb break="no"/>rullo in Mexico, which was unknown to geography till after<lb break="yes"/>my South American journey. When this mountain suddenly<lb break="yes"/>made its appearance in September 1759, rising to a height of<lb break="yes"/>1580 feet above the surrounding level, the two small streams<lb break="yes"/>Rios de Cuitimba y de San Pedro disappeared; but some time<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="283" facs="#f0007"/> afterwards they made their appearance again, under the dread-<lb break="no"/>ful shocks of an earthquake, as hot springs. In 1803, I found<lb break="yes"/>their temperature 65°8 C.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The springs of Greece still flow apparently in the same<lb break="yes"/>places as they did in the times of Hellenic antiquity. The<lb break="yes"/>spring of Erasinos, two leagues south of Argos, in the decli-<lb break="no"/>vity of Chaon, is even mentioned by Herodotus. At Delphi,<lb break="yes"/>the Cassotis (the so-called Wells of St Nicholas) still rises<lb break="yes"/>to the south of the Lesche, and flows under the Temple of<lb break="yes"/>Apollo; the Castalia, too, at the foot of Ph&#x00E6;driad&#x00E6;, and the<lb break="yes"/>Pirene at Acrocorinth, are there, as well as the hot baths of<lb break="yes" />&#x00C6;depsos in Cub&#x00E6;a, in which Sulla bathed at the time of<lb break="yes"/>the Mithridatic war. I gladly adduce these particulars, be-<lb break="no"/>cause they forcibly remind us how, in a country exposed to<lb break="yes"/>earthquakes so frequent and so violent, the interior of our<lb break="yes"/>planet has been able to preserve its spring canals unaltered for<lb break="yes"/>2000 years at least. The Fontaine Jaillissante of Lillers, in<lb break="yes"/>the department of the Pas de Calais, was bored in the year<lb break="yes"/>1126, and ever since then has the water flowed uninterruptedly<lb break="yes"/>to the same height, and in the same quantity. The excellent<lb break="yes"/>geographer of the Caramanian coasts, Captain Beaufort, more-<lb break="no"/>over, observed the same flame, fed by a stream of inflammable<lb break="yes"/>gas, which flows out in the district of Phaselis, which Pliny<lb break="yes"/>describes as the flame of Chim&#x00E6;ra in Lycia.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The observations made by Arago in 1821, that the deeper<lb break="yes"/>Artesian wells are the warmer, was the first means of throw-<lb break="no"/>ing a great light upon the origin of thermal springs, and<lb break="yes"/>led to the discovery of the law of the increase of the temper-<lb break="no"/>ature of the earth according to the depth. It is remarkable,<lb break="yes"/>and only noticed in very recent times, that St <choice><sic>Patricius</sic><corr type="editorial">Patricius,</corr></choice> pro-<lb break="no"/>bably Bishop of Pertusa, was led to a very correct view of<lb break="yes"/>the phenomenon which presented itself in the appearance of<lb break="yes"/>hot springs near Carthage, at the end of the third century.<lb break="yes"/>When questioned as to the cause of the boiling-hot water<lb break="yes"/>which poured out from the earth, he answered:&#x2014;&#x201C;Fire is<lb break="yes"/>nourished in the clouds, and in the interior of the earth, as<lb break="yes"/>Etna, and another mountain in the neighbourhood of Naples,<lb break="yes"/>inform you. The subterranean waters rise as through syphons;<lb break="yes"/>and the cause of the heat of hot springs is this: the waters<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="284" facs="#f0008"/> that are more remote from the subterraneous fire shew them-<lb break="no"/>selves colder; those that flow in closer proximity to the fire,<lb break="yes"/>warmed by it, bring an insupportable heat to the surface which<lb break="yes"/>we inhabit.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As earthquakes are frequently accompanied by eruptions of<lb break="yes"/>water and watery vapour, so do we perceive in the salses, or<lb break="yes"/>the small mud-volcanoes, a transition from the alternating phe-<lb break="no"/>nomena presented by jets of vapour and thermal springs to the<lb break="yes"/>great and frightful activity of hills that vomit forth lava. If<lb break="yes"/>these, as springs of melted mineral matter, produce volcanic<lb break="yes"/>rocks, so do the thermal springs that are charged with car-<lb break="no"/>bonic acid and sulphurous gas (and earthy matters), pro-<lb break="no"/>duce, by incessant precipitation, either horizontal beds of<lb break="yes"/>limestone (travertin), or they form conical hillocks, as in the<lb break="yes"/>north of Africa (Algeira), and the Banos of Caxamarca, on<lb break="yes"/>the western declivity of the Peruvian Andes. In the tra-<lb break="no"/>vertin of Van Dieman&#x2019;s Land, not far from Hobart Town,<lb break="yes"/>there are contained, according to Mr Charles Darwin, the re-<lb break="no"/>mains of an extinct flora. By lava and travertin, two species<lb break="yes"/>of rock, the production of which goes on under our eyes, we<lb break="yes"/>here indicate the grand antithesis in geognostical relations.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mud-volcanoes (salsen) deserve a greater share of attention<lb break="yes"/>than geologists have hitherto bestowed upon them. The ex-<lb break="no"/>tent of the phenomena has been overlooked, because in the<lb break="yes"/>two states in which it presents itself to us, the one of repose<lb break="yes"/>is that which has been principally dwelt upon; and in this<lb break="yes"/>state of repose mud-volcanoes often continue for centuries.<lb break="yes"/>The production of mud-volcanoes is accompanied by earth-<lb break="no"/>quakes, subterranean thunder, the elevation of a whole district<lb break="yes"/>of country, and the eruption of flames, which rise high, but<lb break="yes"/>last only for a short time. When the mud-volcano of Iok-<lb break="no"/>mali made its appearance in the peninsula of Abscheron, east-<lb break="no"/>ward from Baku, on the Caspian Sea (on the 27th of Novem-<lb break="no"/>ber 1827), flames burst forth, and blazed up to an extraordinary<lb break="yes"/>height for a period of three hours; for the next succeeding<lb break="yes"/>twenty hours they scarcely rose three feet above the surface<lb break="yes"/>of the crater that discharged the mud. The column of flame<lb break="yes"/>mounted to such a height near the village of Baklichi, west-<lb break="no"/>ward from Baku, that it was seen at the distance of six (Ger-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="285" facs="#f0009"/> man) miles. Great blocks of stone, torn from their foundations<lb break="yes"/>beneath, were scattered widely around. Similar blocks are<lb break="yes"/>observed about the now slumbering mud-volcanoes of Monte<lb break="yes"/>Zibio, near Sassuolo, in the north of Italy. The second state,<lb break="yes"/>or that of activity, has continued for 1500 years in the mud<lb break="yes"/>volcano of Girgenti (Macalubi), in Sicily, which is described<lb break="yes"/>by the ancients. Many conical hillocks, of eight, ten, and<lb break="yes"/>even thirty feet high, though the height, as well as the form, of<lb break="yes"/>these varies at different times, are there seen arranged near<lb break="yes"/>one another. From the superior very small basin, which is<lb break="yes"/>full of water, along with the periodic escapes of gas, there are<lb break="yes"/>periodic streams of clayey mud discharged. The mud of these<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes is generally cold, but occasionally, as at Damak, in<lb break="yes"/>the province of Samarang, island of Java, it is of high tem-<lb break="no"/>perature. The gases, which escape with a rushing noise, are<lb break="yes"/>also of different kinds&#x2014;hydrogen gas, mixed with naphtha;<lb break="yes"/>carbonic acid; and, as Parrot and I ascertained, (in the penin-<lb break="no"/>sula of Taman and the South American Volcancitos de Tur-<lb break="no"/>baco), almost pure nitrogen gas.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mud-volcanoes, after the first forcible outburst of flame,<lb break="yes"/>which perhaps is not common to all in the same measure, pre-<lb break="no"/>sent the observer with a picture of an activity of the interior<lb break="yes"/>of the earth, that proceeds incessantly but feebly. The com-<lb break="no"/>munication with the deep strata, in which a high temperature<lb break="yes"/>prevails, is speedily interrupted again; and the cold discharges<lb break="yes"/>of mud-volcanoes seem to indicate that the seat of the pheno-<lb break="no"/>menon, in its state of continuance, cannot be very remote from<lb break="yes"/>the surface. The re-action of the interior of the earth upon<lb break="yes"/>its outer crust is exhibited in a very different degree of force<lb break="yes"/>in the proper volcanoes, or burning mountains; in other words,<lb break="yes"/>in those points of the earth where a permanent communication,<lb break="yes"/>or, at all events, a communication that is renewed from time<lb break="yes"/>to time, is established between the surface and the deep<lb break="yes"/>focus of ignition. We must carefully distinguish between<lb break="yes"/>more or less exaggerated volcanic phenomena, such as earth-<lb break="no"/>quakes, hot springs and jets of steam, mud-volcanoes, the<lb break="yes"/>rising up of bell and dome-shaped unopened trachytic moun-<lb break="no"/>tains, the opening of these mountains, or the upheaval of<lb break="yes"/>basaltic beds as craters of elevation, lastly, the rise of a per-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="286" facs="#f0010"/> manent volcano within the crater of elevation itself, or amongst<lb break="yes"/>the fragments of its previous constitution. At different times,<lb break="yes"/>along with different degrees of activity and force, permanent<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes throw out jets of aqueous vapour, acids, glowing<lb break="yes"/>ashes and scoriae, and, when the resistance can be overcome,<lb break="yes"/>ribbon-shaped small fiery streams of melted earthy matter.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As a consequence of a great but local manifestation of force<lb break="yes"/>in the interior of our planet, elastic vapours raise either single<lb break="yes" />parts of the crust of the earth into dome-shaped, unopened<lb break="yes" />masses of felspathic trachyte and dolerite (Puy de D&#x00F4;me and<lb break="yes"/>Chimborazo), or the upheaved strata are broken through, and<lb break="yes"/>inclined outwards, in such wise, that upon the opposite inner<lb break="yes"/>aspect a steep rocky edge is produced. This edge then be-<lb break="no"/>comes the boundary of a crater of elevation. When this<lb break="yes"/>has risen from the bottom of the sea, which does not, by any<lb break="yes"/>means, happen in every case, it then determines the whole of<lb break="yes"/>the characteristic physiognomy of the upheaved island. This<lb break="yes"/>is the origin of the circular form of Palma, which Leopold<lb break="yes"/>von Buch has described so carefully and so ably, as well as<lb break="yes"/>of Nisyros, in the &#x00C6;gean Sea. Occasionally, one-half the<lb break="yes"/>ring-like edge is destroyed; and in the bay which the sea that<lb break="yes"/>has flowed in then forms, the social coral polypi establish<lb break="yes"/>themselves, and produce their cellular dwellings. Craters of<lb break="yes"/>elevation on continents are also frequently found filled with<lb break="yes"/>water, when they contribute to beautify the landscape in a<lb break="yes"/>peculiar manner.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Their origin is not connected with any particular moun-<lb break="no"/>tain rock; they break out in basalt, trachyte, leucitic por-<lb break="no"/>phyry (Somma), or in doleritic aggregates of augite and Lab-<lb break="no"/>rador. Hence the very dissimilar natures and external forms<lb break="yes"/>of this kind of crater edge. &#x201C;No eruptive phenomena<lb break="yes"/>take place from such boundaries. Through them there is no<lb break="yes"/>permanent channel of communication established with the<lb break="yes"/>interior; and it is only very rarely that traces of still active<lb break="yes"/>volcanic power are discovered in the precincts, or within the<lb break="yes"/>circuit of such craters. The force competent to bring about<lb break="yes"/>such important effects, must long have accumulated, and<lb break="yes"/>gained strength in the interior, before it could have over-<lb break="no"/>come the resistance of the superincumbent masses. On the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="287" facs="#f0011"/> formation of new islands, it raises up granular rocky masses<lb break="yes"/>and conglomerates (layers of tufa full of marine plants) above<lb break="yes"/>the level of the sea. Compressed gases escape through the<lb break="yes"/>crater of elevation; but a mass of such magnitude, thus up-<lb break="no"/>heaved, sinks down again, and closes forthwith the openings,<lb break="yes"/>which are only formed for such manifestations of force. No<lb break="yes"/>volcano is produced.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A proper volcano only arises where a permanent connection<lb break="yes"/>is established between the interior of the earth and the atmo-<lb break="no" />sphere. Here the reaction of the interior upon the exterior<lb break="yes" />proceed for lengthened periods. It may, as in the case of<lb break="yes" />Vesuvius (Fisove), be interrupted for centuries, and exhibit<lb break="yes" />itself anew with renovated vigour. In the time of Nero,<lb break="yes"/>it was already customary, in Rome, to rank &#x00C6;tna among<lb break="yes"/>the number of the gradually expiring volcanic mountains;<lb break="yes"/>&#x00C6;lian, indeed, at a later period, maintained that the seamen<lb break="yes"/>began to see the sinking summit at a less distance on the<lb break="yes"/>high seas than formerly. Where the evidence of the erup-<lb break="no"/>tion&#x2014;I might say the old scaffolding&#x2014;has been perfectly pre-<lb break="no"/>served, the volcano shews itself rising from a crater of ele-<lb break="no"/>vation; there a high rocky wall, a rampart of greatly inclined<lb break="yes"/>strata, surrounds the isolated cone in the manner of a circus.<lb break="yes"/>Sometimes there is not a trace of this circus-like enclosure<lb break="yes"/>visible; and the volcano, not always conical in figure, then<lb break="yes"/>arises as an elongated ridge immediately from the elevated<lb break="yes"/>platform. This is the case with Pichincha, at the foot of<lb break="yes"/>which stands the city of Quito.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As the nature of mountain rocks, in other words, the<lb break="yes"/>combination or grouping of simple minerals into granite,<lb break="yes"/>gneiss, and mica-slate, into trachyte, basalt, and dolerite, in-<lb break="no"/>dependently of present climates, and under the most dissimilar<lb break="yes"/>zones, is still the same; so do we everywhere observe the<lb break="yes"/>same laws of formation proclaiming themselves in the realm<lb break="yes"/>of inorganic nature, laws according to which the strata of the<lb break="yes"/>crust of the earth stand in a certain relationship to one ano-<lb break="no"/>ther, and under the influence of elastic forces, break through<lb break="yes"/>one another as dikes. This recurrence of the same pheno-<lb break="no"/>mena is particularly striking in volcanoes. When the naviga-<lb break="no"/>tor, among the islands of distant seas, finds himself surrounded<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="288" facs="#f0012"/> by palms and strange forms of vegetation, and no longer sees<lb break="yes"/>the same stars, in the individualities of the landscape, he still<lb break="yes"/>traces the characters of Vesuvius, the dome-shaped summit of<lb break="yes"/>Auvergne, the crater of elevation of the Canaries and Azores,<lb break="yes"/>the fissures of eruption of Iceland repeated and reflected. A<lb break="yes"/>glance at the attendant of our planet, the moon, generalizes still<lb break="yes"/>farther the analogy of formation here adverted to. In maps<lb break="yes"/>of the moon, we observe in our satellite, without atmosphere<lb break="yes"/>and without water, vast craters of elevation, which surround<lb break="yes"/>conical mountains, or support them on their circular walls;<lb break="yes"/>unquestionable effects of the reaction of the interior of the<lb break="yes"/>moon upon her exterior, aided by the influence of diminished<lb break="yes"/>gravity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If, in many languages, volcanoes are properly designated<lb break="yes"/>Burning Mountains, it would still be a great mistake to sup-<lb break="no"/>pose that they were produced by any gradual accumulation of<lb break="yes"/>the streams of lava that have flowed from them: their origin<lb break="yes"/>appears to be much more generally the consequence of a sud-<lb break="no"/>den upheaval of tenacious masses of trachyte or augitic rock,<lb break="yes"/>including polychromatic [Labrador] felspar. The measure of<lb break="yes"/>the upheaving force reveals itself in the height of the volcano;<lb break="yes"/>and this is so different, that in one case it is a mere hillock (as<lb break="yes"/>in Cosima, one of the Japanese Kuriles<note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">Vide</hi> Jameson&#x2019;s Edin. Phil. Journal for an interesting account of<lb break="yes"/>Cosima, communicated by Tilesius.</note>); in another, it is a<lb break="yes"/>cone that rises to an elevation of 18,000 feet. It has seemed<lb break="yes"/>to me as if the relative height had a great influence upon the<lb break="yes"/>frequency of the eruptions; as if these were much more com-<lb break="no"/>mon in the lower than the loftier volcanoes. I will call atten-<lb break="no"/>tion to the following series:&#x2014;Stromboli (2175 feet high),<lb break="yes"/>Guacamayo, in the province of Quiros, which thunders almost<lb break="yes"/>every day (I have frequently heard it in Chilo, near Quito, at a<lb break="yes"/>distance of 22 German miles), Vesuvius (3637 feet high), &#x00C6;tna<lb break="yes"/>(10,200 feet high), the Peak of Teneriffe (11,424 feet high),<lb break="yes"/>and Cotopaxi (17,892 feet high). If the focus of these several<lb break="yes" />volcanoes be at the same depth below the surface, a greater<lb break="yes" />force will be required to raise the molten masses to a six or<lb break="yes" />eight times higher level. Whilst the low Stromboli (Strongyle)<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="289" facs="#f0013"/> has laboured incessantly, at least since the times of the Ho-<lb break="no"/>meric traditions, and serves as a light-house to the Tyrrhenian<lb break="yes"/>Sea, guiding the seaman with its fiery signal on his course, the<lb break="yes"/>more lofty volcanoes are characterized by lengthened periods<lb break="yes"/>of repose. The eruptions of the greater number of the colossal<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes that crown the Andes, occur at intervals almost of a<lb break="yes"/>century apart: where exceptions to this rule have been ob-<lb break="no"/>served,&#x2014;and I long ago directed attention to them,&#x2014;they may<lb break="yes"/>probably be connected with the circumstance, that the com-<lb break="no"/>munication between the volcanic focus and the crater of erup-<lb break="no"/>tion is not, and cannot be conceived to be, equally or perma-<lb break="no"/>nently free in every volcano at all times. In the less elevated<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes the channel of communication may be closed for a<lb break="yes"/>season; so that their eruptions become rarer, without their<lb break="yes"/>being, on this account, any nearer to extinction.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>With the consideration of the relation between the absolute<lb break="yes" />height of volcanoes, and the frequency of their activity, in so<lb break="yes" />far as this is externally visible, the place at which the lava<lb break="yes" />flows out is closely connected. Eruptions from the crater are<lb break="yes" />extremely rare in the case of many volcanoes; they generally<lb break="yes" />proceed from the lateral fissures (as noticed by the celebrated<lb break="yes" />historian Bembo, in the 16th century, whilst yet a youth), at<lb break="yes" />places where the flanks of the uplifted mountain, in conse-<lb break="no" />quence of their shape and position, offer the least amount<lb break="yes"/>of resistance. Upon these fissures cones of eruption are occa-<lb break="no" />sionally raised. The larger of these are of such dimensions<lb break="yes" />that they are often erroneously designated by the title of new<lb break="yes" />volcanoes. Ranked side by side, they shew the direction of a<lb break="yes" />fissure which has again become closed: the smaller ones fre-<lb break="no" />quently occur in groups, closely set together, and cover whole<lb break="yes" />districts, as it were, with bell-shaped, or beehive-like, eleva-<lb break="no" />tions. To the latter class belong the <hi rendition="#i">hornitos</hi> of Jorullo, and<lb break="yes"/>the cone of the eruption of Vesuvius of October 1822, of the<lb break="yes"/>volcano of Awatscha, according to Postels, and of the lava field<lb break="yes"/>near the Baidare mountains, in the peninsula of Kamtschatka,<lb break="yes"/>according to Erman.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When volcanoes do not rise free and isolated from a plain,<lb break="yes"/>when, on the contrary, they are surrounded by table-lands<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">
                        <hi rendition="#k">vol. xxxix. no. lxxviii.&#x2014;october</hi> 1845. <hi rendition="#k">t</hi>
                    </fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="290" facs="#f0014"/> from 9000 to 12,000 feet<note place="foot" n="*">
                        <hi rendition="#i">French</hi> feet in this and every other instance in the present paper.</note> high, as in the double chain of the<lb break="yes" />Andes of Quito, this circumstance may very well give rise to<lb break="yes" />the fact, that the most violent eruptions, when red-hot ashes<lb break="yes" />and scori&#x00E6; are thrown out with detonations that are heard for<lb break="yes"/>hundreds of miles around, are never accompanied with <hi rendition="#i">streams<lb break="yes"/>of lava.</hi> This is the case with the volcanoes of Popayan, of<lb break="yes"/>the lofty plains of Los Pastos, and of the Andes of Quito; the<lb break="yes"/>single volcano of Antisana, among the latter, perhaps excepted.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The height of the <hi rendition="#i">cone of ashes,</hi> and the dimensions and<lb break="yes"/>form of the <hi rendition="#i">crater,</hi> are the elements in the figure of volcanoes<lb break="yes"/>which more particularly impress upon each of them an indi-<lb break="no"/>vidual character; but of these elements, both the cone and the<lb break="yes"/>crater are perfectly independent of the magnitude of the whole<lb break="yes"/>mountain. Vesuvius is not one-third of the height of the Peak<lb break="yes"/>of Teneriffe, yet its cone of ashes forms one-third of the whole<lb break="yes"/>height of the mountain, whilst the cone of ashes of the Peak<lb break="yes"/>is only one-twenty-second of the entire elevation. In the case<lb break="yes"/>of another volcano of much greater height than the Peak, that<lb break="yes"/>of Rucu-Pinchincha, namely, the relations come nearer to<lb break="yes"/>those of Vesuvius. Of all the volcanoes I have seen in either<lb break="yes"/>hemisphere, Cotopaxi is that of which the conical form is the<lb break="yes"/>most regular and beautiful. A sudden melting of the snow of<lb break="yes"/>its cone of ashes indicates the proximity of an eruption. Be-<lb break="no"/>fore there is even any smoke visible in the attenuated strata<lb break="yes"/>of the atmosphere that surround the summit of the crater&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>mouth, the walls of the ash-cone are sometimes heated through,<lb break="yes"/>when the entire mountain presents the most threatening and<lb break="yes"/>ill-omened aspect.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The crater which, except in very rare cases, occupies the<lb break="yes"/>summit of the volcano, forms a deep, and often accessible,<lb break="yes"/>basin-shaped valley, whose bottom is subject to incessant<lb break="yes"/>changes. The greater or less depth of the crater is, in many<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes, an indication of the proximity or remoteness of an<lb break="yes"/>eruption. In the basin-shaped crater, extensive fissures open<lb break="yes"/>and close again alternately, through which, vapours of various<lb break="yes"/>kinds find vent, or small, rounded, and fiery openings, filled<lb break="yes"/>with molten matters are seen. The floor rises and falls,<lb break="yes"/>and in it are formed hillocks of ashes and cones of erup-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="291" facs="#f0015"/> tion, which occasionally rise high above the edges of the crater,<lb break="yes"/>and give the volcano its characteristic physiognomy for years;<lb break="yes"/>but, on the occurrence of fresh eruptions, they sink suddenly<lb break="yes"/>down, and disappear. The openings of these cones of erup-<lb break="no"/>tion, which rise from the floor of the crater, must not, as is too<lb break="yes"/>frequently done, be confounded with the crater itself, which<lb break="yes"/>encircles them. When the crater is inaccessible, from its vast<lb break="yes"/>depth, and the perpendicular inward slope of its sides, as in<lb break="yes"/>the case of Rucu-Pichincha (14,946 feet high), one can still<lb break="yes"/>look down from the edges upon the summits of the monticules<lb break="yes"/>which rise within the cauldron-like crater, partially filled with<lb break="yes"/>sulphureous vapour. A more wonderful or grander natural<lb break="yes"/>prospect I have never enjoyed. In the interval between two<lb break="yes"/>eruptions, the crater of a volcano may exhibit no luminous<lb break="yes"/>phenomenon, but merely open fissures and jets of watery<lb break="yes"/>vapour; or hillocks of ashes, that can be approached without<lb break="yes"/>danger, are found upon its scarcely heated bottom. These<lb break="yes"/>often gratify the wandering geognost, without making him<lb break="yes"/>run any risk, by casting out glowing masses, which fall on the<lb break="yes"/>edges of the cone of scori&#x00E6;, their appearance being regularly<lb break="yes"/>announced by slight, and entirely local, shocks&#x2014;earthquakes<lb break="yes"/>on a small scale. Lava occasionally flows from open fissures,<lb break="yes"/>or small fiery gorges, into the crater itself, without bursting<lb break="yes"/>through its walls, or overflowing its edges. But if it does<lb break="yes"/>break through, the molten spring generally flows smoothly,<lb break="yes"/>and in such a determinate direction, that the great cauldron-<lb break="no"/>like valley, called the crater, can still be visited during the<lb break="yes"/>period of the eruption. Without a particular description of<lb break="yes"/>the form, and also of the normal structure of burning moun-<lb break="no"/>tains, phenomena cannot be rightly comprehended which have<lb break="yes"/>been distorted by fantastical descriptions, and the various signi-<lb break="no"/>fications attached to the words <hi rendition="#i">Crater, Cone of eruption,</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Volcano;</hi> or rather, to the indefinite and indeterminate use of<lb break="yes"/>these words. The edges of the crater sometimes shew them-<lb break="no"/>selves much less liable to change than might be expected. A<lb break="yes"/>comparison of De Saussure&#x2019;s measurements with my own, yields<lb break="yes"/>the remarkable result, in connection with Vesuvius at least,<lb break="yes"/>that the north-west edge of the volcano, the Rocca del Palo,<lb break="yes"/>may be regarded as having remained for forty-nine years<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="292" facs="#f0016"/> (1773-1822) almost without change in its elevation above the<lb break="yes"/>level of the sea. Any difference that appears may be looked<lb break="yes"/>on as within the possible errors of measurement.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Volcanoes whose summits reach far above the limits of per-<lb break="no"/>petual snow, like those of the Andes, present a variety of<lb break="yes"/>peculiar features. The sudden melting of the snow in the<lb break="yes"/>course of an eruption, not only occasions destructive floods,<lb break="yes"/>torrents in which heaps of smoking ashes are floated away on<lb break="yes"/>blocks of ice; but the accumulation of ice and snow goes on<lb break="yes"/>producing its influence uninterruptedly, and by filtration, into<lb break="yes"/>the trachytic rocks, even whilst the volcano is perfectly qui-<lb break="no"/>escent. Caverns are thus gradually formed on the declivities<lb break="yes"/>or at the foot of the burning mountain, and these become sub-<lb break="no"/>terraneous reservoirs of water, which communicate in various<lb break="yes"/>ways, by narrow mouths, with the alpine rivulets of Quito.<lb break="yes"/>The fishes of these alpine streams multiply greatly, particu-<lb break="no"/>larly in the gloom of the caverns; and then, when the earth-<lb break="no"/>quakes come, which precede all eruptions of volcanoes in the<lb break="yes"/>Andes, and the whole mass of the mountain is shaken, the<lb break="yes"/>subterraneous caverns at once give way, and pour out a deluge<lb break="yes"/>of water, fishes, and tufaceous mud. This is the singular<lb break="yes"/>phenomenon which the presence of the Pimelodes Cyclopum,<lb break="yes"/>the Prenadilla of the inhabitants of the lofty plains of Quito,<lb break="yes"/>attests. When, in the night between the 19th and 20th of<lb break="yes"/>June 1698, the summit of Carguairazo, a burning mountain<lb break="yes"/>18,000 feet high, crumbled together, so that no more than two<lb break="yes"/>enormous rocky horns of the crater&#x2019;s edge remained, the<lb break="yes"/>country, for nearly two square miles, was desolated with liquid<lb break="yes"/>tuff, and argillaceous mud (lodazales), enclosing dead fishes.<lb break="yes"/>In like manner the putrid fever of the mountain town, Ibarra,<lb break="yes"/>to the north of Quito, which occurred seven years before, was<lb break="yes"/>ascribed to an eruption of fish from the volcano Imbaburnu.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Water and mud, which, in the volcanoes of the Andes, do<lb break="yes"/>not pour down from the crater itself, but from cavities in the<lb break="yes"/>trachytic mass of the mountains, ought not, consequently, in<lb break="yes"/>the strict sense of the phrase, to be reckoned among the num-<lb break="no"/>ber of proper volcanic phenomena. They are only mediately<lb break="yes"/>connected with the activity of volcanoes, nearly in the same<lb break="yes"/>measure as the irregular meteorological process, which, in my<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="293" facs="#f0017"/> early writings, I have spoken of under the title of the <hi rendition="#i">Volcano<lb break="yes"/>Storm.</hi> The hot watery vapour which rises from the crater,<lb break="yes"/>and mingles with the atmosphere during the eruption, forms a<lb break="yes"/>cloud as it cools, with which the column of ashes and fire,<lb break="yes"/>many thousand feet in height, is surrounded. So sudden a<lb break="yes"/>condensation of vapour, and the production of a cloud of enor-<lb break="no"/>mous superficial dimensions, increase the electrical tension, as<lb break="yes"/>Gay Lussac has shewn. Forked lightnings dart from the<lb break="yes"/>column of ashes, and the rolling thunder of the volcanic storm<lb break="yes"/>is then plainly distinguished from the rumbling in the interior<lb break="yes"/>of the mountain. This was well observed towards the end of<lb break="yes"/>the eruption of Vesuvius, in the month of October 1822. The<lb break="yes"/>lightning, which proceeded from the volcanic steam-cloud of<lb break="yes"/>the Katlagia burning mountain in the island of Iceland, accor-<lb break="no"/>ding to Olafsen&#x2019;s account, upon one occasion (17th October<lb break="yes"/>1755) killed eleven horses and two men.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 