<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="417" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">all the universe in motion.</hi></head><lb/><p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">If</hi>, for a moment, we imagine the acuteness of<lb/>our senses preternaturally heightened to the ex-<lb/>treme limits of telescopic vision, and bring together<lb/>events separated by wide intervals of time, the ap-<lb/>parent repose which reigns in space will suddenly<lb/>vanish, countless stars will be seen moving in<lb/>groups in various directions; nebul&#x00E6; wandering,<lb/>condensing, are dissolving, like cosmical clouds;<lb/><pb n="418" facs="#f0002" />
the milky way breaking up in parts, and its veil<lb/>rent asunder. In every point of the celestial vault,<lb/>we should recognize the dominion of progressive<lb/>movement, as on the surface of the earth, where<lb/>vegetation is constantly putting forth its leaves and<lb/>buds, and unfolding its blossoms. The celebrated<lb/>Spanish botanist, Cavanilles, first conceived the<lb/>possibility of &#x2018;seeing grass grow,&#x2019; by placing the<lb/>horizontal micrometer wire of a telescope, with a<lb/>high magnifying power, at one time on the point of<lb/>a bamboo-shoot, and at another on the rapidly un-<lb/>folding flowering stem of an American aloe; pre-<lb/>cisely as the astronomer places the cross wires on a<lb/>culminating star. Throughout the whole life of<lb/>physical nature&#x2014;in the organic as in the sidereal<lb/>world&#x2014;existence, preservation, production, and de-<lb/>velopment, are alike associated with motion as their<lb/>essential condition.&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s &#x201C;Cosmos.&#x201D;</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
