<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Physical description of the universe</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:11</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VI.71</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1846-Physical_Description_of-01-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-01-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Physical_Description_of-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Substance and Light of Comets: Alexander von Humboldt,&lt;i&gt; Kosmos. Entwurf einer physischen Weltbeschreibung&lt;/i&gt;, Band 1, Stuttgart und Tübingen: J. G. Cotta 1845, S. 110-111.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Earthquakes: Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos. Entwurf einer physischen Weltbeschreibung&lt;/i&gt;, Band 1, Stuttgart und Tübingen: J. G. Cotta 1845, S. 212</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Subterranean Noises: Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos. Entwurf einer physischen Weltbeschreibung&lt;/i&gt;, Band 1, Stuttgart und Tübingen: J. G. Cotta 1845, S. 216-217</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Growth of the Dry Land: Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos. Entwurf einer physischen Weltbeschreibung&lt;/i&gt;, Band 1, Stuttgart und Tübingen: J. G. Cotta 1845, S. 302-303.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Universal Diffusion of Life: Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos. Entwurf einer physischen Weltbeschreibung&lt;/i&gt;, Band 1, Stuttgart und Tübingen: J. G. Cotta 1845, S. 369-370, 372-373.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Physical description of the universe</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1846</date>
          <pubPlace>Durham</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;Durham Chronicle, Sunderland Times, and Darlington and Stockton Gazette&lt;/i&gt; 1403 (25. September 1846), S. 6.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="6" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION <hi rendition="#k">of the</hi> UNIVERSE.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Extracts from Humboldt&#x2019;s &#x201C;Cosmos.&#x201D;</hi>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>SUBSTANCE AND LIGHT OF COMETS.<lb break="yes"/>There is no doubt that the light of a star of the<lb break="yes"/>tenth magnitude passed through very dense nebulous<lb break="yes"/>matter on the 29th of September, 1835, at a distance<lb break="yes"/>of 7&#x2032;&#x2032;.78 from the centre of the nucleus of Halley&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>comet, according to Bessel&#x2019;s most careful <choice><sic>mensure-<lb break="no"/>ment</sic><corr type="editorial">measure-<lb break="no"/>ment</corr></choice>, without experiencing any deflection in its rec-<lb break="no"/>tilinear course at any moment of its passage. Such<lb break="yes"/>an absence of refracting power, if actually extending<lb break="yes"/>to the centre of the nucleus, makes it difficult to<lb break="yes"/>regard the substance of comets as of a gaseous nature;<lb break="yes"/>or is the absence of refracting power a consequence<lb break="yes"/>of the almost infinite rarity of a fluid of that descrip-<lb break="no"/>tion ? or does the comet consist of &#x201C;detached par-<lb break="no"/>ticles,&#x201D; forming a <hi rendition="#i">cosmical cloud,</hi> which no more<lb break="yes"/>affects the ray of light passing through it than do<lb break="yes"/>the clouds of our atmosphere, which in like manner<lb break="yes"/>have no influence on the zenith distances of the<lb break="yes"/>heavenly bodies! In the passage of a comet over a<lb break="yes"/>star, there has often been noticed a greater or less<lb break="yes"/>diminution of the light of the star; but this has been<lb break="yes"/>justly ascribed to the brightness of the ground on<lb break="yes"/>which, during the coincidence, the star is seen.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We are indebted to Arago&#x2019;s polarisation experi-<lb break="no"/>ments for the most important and decisive observa-<lb break="no"/>tions on the nature of the light of comets. His<lb break="yes"/>polariscope instructs us concerning the physical con-<lb break="no"/>stitution of the Sun, as well as that of the comets;<lb break="yes"/>it informs us whether a luminous ray, which reaches<lb break="yes"/>us from a distance of many millions of miles, is a<lb break="yes"/>direct, or a reflected or refracted ray; and, if direct,<lb break="yes"/>whether the source of light is a solid, a liquid, or a<lb break="yes"/>gaseous body. The light of Capella, and that of the<lb break="yes"/>great comet of 1819, were examined at the Paris<lb break="yes" />Observatory with the same apparatus. The comet<lb break="yes"/>shewed polarized, and therefore reflected light;<lb break="yes"/>whilst, as was to be expected, the fixed star was<lb break="yes"/>proved to be a self-luminous sun. The existence of<lb break="yes"/>polarized cometary light announced itself not only<lb break="yes"/>by the inequality of the images, but was shown with<lb break="yes"/>still greater certainty at the reappearance of Halley&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>comet in 1835, by the more striking contrast of com-<lb break="no"/>plementary colours, in accordance with the laws of<lb break="yes"/>chromatic polarization discovered by Arago in 1811.<lb break="yes"/>These fine experiments leave it, however, still unde-<lb break="no"/>cided, whether, besides this reflected solar light,<lb break="yes"/>comets may not have a proper light of their own.<lb break="yes" />Even in planets, in Venus for example, an evolution<lb break="yes"/>of independent light appears very probable.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>EARTHQUAKES.<lb break="yes"/>Natives of those countries who have experienced<lb break="yes"/>many hundred earthquakes believe the difference to<lb break="yes"/>be less in the greater or less duration of the shocks,<lb break="yes"/>or the slowness or rapidity of the horizontal oscilla-<lb break="no"/>tion, than in the alteration of motion in opposite<lb break="yes"/>directions. The circular (or giratory) earthquakes<lb break="yes"/>are the most rare, and at the same time the most<lb break="yes" />dangerous. In the great earthquake of Riobamba,<lb break="yes"/>in the province of Quito (4th February, 1797), and in<lb break="yes"/>that of Calabria (5th February and 28th March,<lb break="yes"/>1783), walls were changed in direction without being<lb break="yes"/>overthrown, straight and parallel rows of trees were<lb break="yes"/>inflected, and in fiels having two sorts of cultiva-<lb break="no"/>tion, one crop even took the place before occupied<lb break="yes"/>by the other: the latter ph&#x00E6;nomenon allowing either<lb break="yes"/>a movement of translation, or a mutual penetration<lb break="yes"/>of the different strata. When making a plan of the<lb break="yes"/>ruined city of Riobamba, I was shown a place where<lb break="yes"/>the whole furniture of one house had been found<lb break="yes" />under the remains of another; the earth had evi-<lb break="no"/>dently moved like a fluid in streams or currents, of<lb break="yes"/>which we must assume that the direction was first<lb break="yes"/>downward, then horizontal, and lastly, again upward.<lb break="yes"/>Disputes concerning the ownership of objects which<lb break="yes"/>had been thus carried to distances of many hundred<lb break="yes"/>yards, were decided by the Audiencia or court of justice.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>SUBTERRANEAN NOISES.<lb break="yes"/>The most striking instance of uninterrupted sub-<lb break="no"/>terranean noise unaccompanied by any trace of<lb break="yes"/>earthquake, is the ph&#x00E6;nomenon which is known in<lb break="yes"/>the Mexican territory by the name of &#x201C;the subter-<lb break="no"/>ranean roaring and thundering (bramidos y truenos<lb break="yes" />subterraneos) of Guanaxuato.&#x201D; This rich and cele-<lb break="no"/>brated mountain-city is situated at a distance from<lb break="yes"/>any active volcano. The noise began on the 9th of<lb break="yes"/>January, 1784, at midnight, and lasted above a<lb break="yes"/>month. I have been enabled to give a circumstan-<lb break="no"/>tial description of the ph&#x00E6;nomonon from the report<lb break="yes"/>of many witnesses, and from the documents of the<lb break="yes"/>municipality which I was permitted to make use of.<lb break="yes"/>From the 13th to the 16th of January, it was as if<lb break="yes"/>there were heavy storm-clouds under the feet of the<lb break="yes"/>inhabitants, in which slow rolling thunder alternated<lb break="yes"/>with short thunder-claps. The noise ceased gra-<lb break="no" />dually, as it had commenced; it was confined to a<lb break="yes"/>small space, for it was not heard in a basaltic dis-<lb break="no"/>trict at the distance of only a few miles. Almost all<lb break="yes"/>the inhabitants were terrified and quitted the city,<lb break="yes"/>in which large masses of silver were stored; but the<lb break="yes"/>most courageous, when they had become somewhat<lb break="yes"/>accustomed to the subterranean thunder, returned<lb break="yes" />and fought with the bands of robbers who had taken<lb break="yes"/>possession of the treasure. Neither at the surface,<lb break="yes"/>nor in mines 1,598 English feet in depth, could the<lb break="yes"/>slightest trembling of the ground be perceived. In<lb break="yes"/>no part of the whole mountainous country of Mexico<lb break="yes"/>had anything similar ever been known before; nor<lb break="yes"/>has this awful ph&#x00E6;nomenon been since repeated.<lb break="yes"/>Thus, as chasms in the interior of the earth close or<lb break="yes"/>open, the propagation of the waves of sound is either<lb break="yes"/>arrested in its progress or continued until it reaches<lb break="yes"/>the ear.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>GROWTH OF THE DRY LAND.<lb break="yes"/>The following are the results of the investigations<lb break="yes"/>which have had for their object the determination of<lb break="yes"/>the extent of the dry land at different epochs. In<lb break="yes"/>the most ancient times&#x2014;during the silurian, de-<lb break="no"/>vonian, and carboniferous epochs, and even as lately<lb break="yes"/>as the triassic period&#x2014;the portion of the surface<lb break="yes"/>supporting land vegetation was exclusively insular.<lb break="yes"/>At a subsequent epoch, these islands became con-<lb break="no" />nected with each other, forming numerous lakes and<lb break="yes"/>deeply indented bays. Finally, when the mountain<lb break="yes"/>chains of the Pyrenees, the Appenines, and the<lb break="yes"/>Carpathians, were elevated&#x2014;about the epoch, there-<lb break="no"/>fore, of the older tertiary formations&#x2014;the great<lb break="yes"/>continents possessed nearly their present form and<lb break="yes"/>extent. During the silurian epoch, when the cycade&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>were in the greatest abundance, and the gigantic<lb break="yes"/>saurians were living, the whole surface of dry land<lb break="yes"/>from pole to pole must have been less than it now is<lb break="yes"/>in the Pacific and Indian oceans. We shall see pre-<lb break="yes"/>sently how this great preponderance of oceanic sur-<lb break="yes"/>face must have contributed, together with other<lb break="yes" />causes, to equalize climates, and to maintain a high<lb break="yes" />temperature. It is only necessary to add here, in<lb break="yes"/>reference to the progressive extension of dry land,<lb break="yes"/>that a short time before the cataclysms which, at<lb break="yes"/>longer or shorter intervals, caused the destruction<lb break="yes"/>of so many gigantic vertebrated animals, part of the<lb break="yes"/>continental masses presented the same divisions as<lb break="yes"/>at present. There prevails, both in South America<lb break="yes"/>and in Australia, a great analogy between the living<lb break="yes"/>animals and the extinct species of those countries.<lb break="yes"/>Fossil species of kangaroo have been discovered in<lb break="yes"/>New Holland; and in New Zealand, the semi-fossi-<lb break="no" />lized bones of a gigantic struthious bird, the dinornis<lb break="yes"/>of Owen, closely allied to the present apteryx, of the<lb break="yes"/>same islands, and remotely so to the recently extinct<lb break="yes"/>dodo of the island of Rodriguez.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>UNIVERSAL DIFFUSION OF LIFE.<lb break="yes"/>Since the time when, in an earlier work, (&#x201C;Ansich-<lb break="no"/>ten der Natur,&#x201D; &#x201C;Tableaux de la Nature&#x201D;), I at-<lb break="no"/>tempted to describe the universal diffusion of organic<lb break="yes"/>life on the surface of the globe, and its distribution<lb break="yes"/>in height and in depth, our knowledge has been won-<lb break="yes"/>derfully augmented by Ehrenberg&#x2019;s brilliant dis-<lb break="yes"/>coveries, (&#x201C;Über das Verhalten des kleinsten Lebens<lb break="yes"/>in dem Weltmeere wie in dem Eise der Polar län-<lb break="no"/>der&#x201D;) which rest not on ingenious combinations and<lb break="yes"/>inferences, but on direct and exact observation. By<lb break="yes"/>these discoveries the sphere of animated existence<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;we may say the horizon of life&#x2014;has expanded be-<lb break="yes"/>fore our view. &#x201C;Not only is there no interruption<lb break="yes"/>of minute microscopic forms of animal life in the<lb break="yes"/>vicinity of either Pole, where larger animals cannot<lb break="yes"/>maintain themselves, but we find among the micro-<lb break="yes"/>scopic animals of the South Polar Seas, collected<lb break="yes"/>in the Antarctic expedition of Captain James Ross,<lb break="yes"/>a remarkable abundance of new forms, which are<lb break="yes" />often of great elegance. Even in the residuum ob-<lb break="yes"/>tained from melted ice which floats in rounded frag-<lb break="yes"/>ments in latitude 78&#x00B0; 10&#x2019; 8., there have been found<lb break="yes"/>above fifty species of siliceous-shelled polygastrica,<lb break="yes"/>and even coscinodisc&#x00E6; with green ovaries, which<lb break="yes"/>were therefore certainly living and able to resist the<lb break="yes"/>extreme severity of the cold.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>It is not only in particular localities, in inland<lb break="yes"/>waters, or in the vicinity of coasts, that the ocean is<lb break="yes"/>thus thickly peopled with living atoms invisible to<lb break="yes"/>the naked eye. Samples of water taken up by<lb break="yes"/>Schayer in 57&#x00B0; 8. latitude, on his return from Van<lb break="yes"/>Diemen Island, as well as those taken between the<lb break="yes"/>Tropics in the middle of the Atlantic, show that the<lb break="yes"/>ocean-water in its ordinary condition, without any<lb break="yes"/>appearance of discolouration, contains innumerable<lb break="yes"/>microscopic organisms, quite distinct from the sili-<lb break="no"/>ceous filaments of the genus ch&#x00E6;toceros, floating in<lb break="yes"/>a fragmentary state like the oscillatoria of our fresh<lb break="yes"/>waters. Some polygastrica which have been found<lb break="yes" />mixed with sand and excrements of penguins in the<lb break="yes"/>Cockburn Islands, appear to be generally distributed<lb break="yes"/>over the globe; other species belong to both the<lb break="yes"/>Artic and Antarctic Polar regions. Thus we see<lb break="yes"/>that animal life reigns in the perpetual night of the<lb break="yes"/>depths of the ocean; while on continents, vege-<lb break="yes"/>table life, stimulated by the periodical action of the<lb break="yes"/>solar rays, chiefly predominates.</p>
                <p>Not only are earth, air, and water, filled with life,<lb break="yes"/>and that at the most different temperatures, but also<lb break="yes"/>the interior of the various parts of animal bodies:<lb break="yes"/>there are animalcula in the blood of frogs and of<lb break="yes"/>salmon: according to Nordmann, the fluids of the<cb/>eyes of fishes are often filled with a worm which<lb break="yes" />lives by suction (diplostomum); and the same natu-<lb break="no"/>ralist has even discovered in the gills of the bleak an<lb break="yes"/>extraordinary double animal (diplozon paradoxon)<lb break="yes"/>having two heads and two caudal extremities dis-<lb break="yes"/>posed in rectangular directions.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 
