<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Egyptian Antiquities</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:11</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VI.69</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1846-Extrait_d_une-4-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Extrait_d_une-1-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Extrait_d_une-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Extrait_d_une-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1846-Extrait_d_une-4-neu.xml" type="self"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Egyptian Antiquities</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1846</date>
          <pubPlace>New York City, New York</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">&lt;i&gt;in: The Evening Post&lt;/i&gt; 44 (21. November 1846), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<pb facs="#f0002" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Egyptian Antiquities</hi>.</head><p>&#x2014;The reader will find on<lb/>the outside a pleasant account of the doings of the<lb/>Prussian Scientific Expedition in Atrica. Mr. Lep-<lb/>sius, the leader of it, reported to Berlin early in the<lb/>summer, and Humboldt, in a letter to Mons. Jornald,<lb/>gives the following statement of the results of the<lb/>expedition:</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Thirteen hundred magnificent drawings, from<lb/>thousands of sketches taken on the spot, and all the<lb/>manuscripts, have already arrived here. Two ves-<lb/>sels, laden with the monuments themselves, were to<lb/>sail (from Egypt) in April. M. Lepsius brings with<lb/>him fragments of monuments of all dynasties, from<lb/>the fourth of Manetho down to the Ptolemies, and of<lb/>the Roman Emperors below Caracalla down to De-<lb/>cius. These original monuments, with the names of<lb/>the fourth, fifth and sixth dynasties, from two thou-<lb/>sand to three thousand years before our era, will be<lb/>of great importance in our new Egyptian Museum,<lb/>for everything before the invasion of the Hykshos is<lb/>very rare, even at Turin, at Paris, and at London. I<lb/>say nothing to you of the two bilingual decrees, co-<lb/>pied at Phil&#x00E6;, because I believe M. Ampere has sent<lb/>copies to you.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;The collection of images and inscriptions, found<lb/>in the country of the ancient copper mines of the<lb/>peninsula of Sinai, bearing the name of Cheops, is<lb/>of the greatest importance. Plaster casts from Wadi<lb/>&#x2014;Megara&#x2014;the illustrations and complete plans of<lb/>the Labyrinth&#x2014;a colossal ram from Mount Bargal,<lb/>with the image and inscription of Amenophis&#x2014;Mem-<lb/>non&#x2014;the large stones of the Nilemetre of Senneh,<lb/>with the emblem of Amenemha-Moris, (proving that<lb/>4,000 years ago the mean height of the river in those<lb/>countries was 22 feet higher than it is now;) four<lb/>sepulchral chambers from the plateau of Gizeh, be-<lb/>longing as far back as the fourth dynasty; a colos-<lb/>sal bust of Horus, of the eighteenth dynasty; pro-<lb/>files of Amenophis and of Ahmes Nefanari; hun-<lb/>dreds of bricks with dates; and five large historical<lb/>papyri, like those of the British Museum, are trea-<lb/>sures which ought to bring you among us.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;M. Lepsius, before beginning his preparatory<lb/>Egyptian studies at Turin, at Pisa, at Rome, at Pa-<lb/>ris, and at London, had occupied himself wholly<lb/>with the study of Sanscrit, Greek, the Eugubian ta-<lb/>bles, and the philosophy of languages. Such philo-<lb/>sophical tastes have induced him in this journey to<lb/>collect complete materials&#x2014;1st, on the Congara lan-<lb/>guage of the blacks of the interior; 2d, the Nuba<lb/>language of two dialects. Of this language, which<lb/>has never before been <choice><sic>w itten</sic><corr type="editorial">written</corr></choice>, he has brought home<lb/>twenty or more songs and translations from the fa-<lb/>bles of Lokman, (known to English readers as Pil-<lb/>pay&#x2019;s fables,) and some translations from a Thousand<lb/>and one Nights, which a Nubian had translated from<lb/>Arabic into the Nuba language; and 3d, the Bega<lb/>language, spoken between the Nubian Nile and the<lb/>Red Sea by the Bischari tribes. This is a branch of<lb/>the great family of Caucaso-Asiatic languages, al-<lb/>lied to the present form of the Ethiopian idiom of<lb/>Meroe.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;M. Lepsius has also, besides the Greek and Sinaitic<lb/>inscriptions, some ancient Ethiopian inscriptions,<lb/>found even in the pyramids of Meroe. These are an<lb/>unknown alphabet, sometimes a little analogous to<lb/>Greek characters. The knowledge of the Bega lan-<lb/>guage will facilitate the interpretation of them. The<lb/>study of this department of languages, so important<lb/>for the history of our race, is allied to the curious re-<lb/>searches of M. Roses, now a dragoman at Constan-<lb/>tinople, whom the King of Prussia sent to reside for<lb/>two years in the valleys of Caucasus, that he might<lb/>seek there in the language of the Ossetes, the origin<lb/>of the Indo-germanic branch, and in the Laze or<lb/>Mingrelien, the origin of the Iberian or Grusian<lb/>branch, to which belonged the language of ancient<lb/>Colchis. M. Roses is a brother of the great Indianist<lb/>who lately died at London. He will make his bro-<lb/>ther&#x2019;s place perfectly good by the extent of his philo-<lb/>logical acquisitions and the vivacity of his genius.&#x201D;&#x2014;<lb/>[National Intelligencer.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
