<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="422" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">All the Universe in Motion.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;If, for a mo-<lb/>ment, we imagine the acuteness of our senses<lb/>preternaturally heightened to the extreme limits<lb/>of telescopic vision, and bring together events<lb/>separated by wide intervals of time, the apparent<lb/>repose which reigns in space will suddenly vanish,<lb/>countless stars will be seen moving in groups in<lb/><choice><sic>varions</sic><corr type="editorial">various</corr></choice> directions; nebul&#x00E6; wandering, condensing<lb/>are dissolving, like cosmical clouds; the milky<lb/>way breaking up in parts, and its veil rent asun-<lb/>der. In every point of the celestial vault, we<lb/>should recognize the dominion of progressive<lb/>movement as on the surface of the earth, where<lb/>vegetation is constantly putting forth its leaves<lb/>and buds, and unfolding its blossoms. The cele-<lb/>brated Spanish botanist, Cavanilles, first conceiv-<lb/>ed the possibility of &#x201C;seeing grass grow,&#x201D; by<lb/>placing the horizontal micrometer wire of a tele-<lb/>scope, with a high magnifying power, at one time<lb/>on the point of the bamboo-shoot, and at another<lb/>on the rapidly unfolding flowering stem of an<lb/>American aloe; precisely as the astronomer places<lb/>the cross wires on a culminating star. Through-<lb/>out the whole life of physical nature&#x2014;in the or-<lb/>ganic as in the sidereal world&#x2014;existence, preser-<lb/>vation, production, and developement, are alike<lb/>associated with motion as their essential condition.<lb/>&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Cosmos.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
