<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="128" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">the sublime character of hebrew poetry.</hi></head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">It</hi> is characteristic of Hebrew poetry in reference to nature, that, as a
                    reflex of mo-<lb/>notheism, it always embraces the whole world in its unity,
                    comprehending the life of the<lb/>terrestrial globe, as well as the shining
                    regions of space. It dwells less on details of<lb/>phenomena, and loves to
                    contemplate great masses. Nature is pourtrayed, not as self-<lb/>subsisting, or
                    glorious in her own beauty, but ever in relation to a higher, an
                    over-ruling,<lb/>a spiritual power. The Hebrew bard ever sees in her the living
                    expression of the om-<lb/>nipresence of God in the works of the visible
                    creation. Thus, the lyrical poetry of the<lb/>Hebrews, in its descriptions of
                    nature, is essentially, in its very subject, grand and solemn:<lb/>and, when
                    touching on the earthly condition of man, full of a yearning pensiveness. It
                    is<lb/>deserving of notice, that notwithstanding its grand character, and even
                    in its highest lyrical<lb/>flights, elevated by the charm of music, the Hebrew
                    poetry, unlike that of the Hindoos,<lb/>scarcely ever appears unrestrained by
                    law and measure. Devoted to the pure contemplation<lb/>of the divinity,
                    figurative in language, but clear and simple in thought, it delights in
                    com-<lb/>parisons, which recur continually and almost rhythmically. As
                    descriptions of natural<lb/>scenery, the writings of the Old Testament show, as
                    in a mirror, the nature of the country<lb/>in which the people of Israel moved
                    and dwelt, with its alternations of desert, fruitful land,<lb/>forest, and
                    mountain. They pourtray the variations of the climate of Palestine, the
                    suc-<lb/>cession of the seasons, the pastoral manners of the people, and their
                    innate disinclination<lb/>to agriculture. The epic, or historical and narrative,
                    portions are of the utmost simplicity,<lb/>almost more unadorned even than the
                    Herodotus; and from the small alteration which has<lb/>taken place in the
                    manners, and in the usages and circumstances of a nomade life,
                    modern<lb/>travellers have been enabled to testify unanimously to their truth to
                    nature. The Hebrew<lb/>lyrical poetry is more adorned, and unfolds rich and
                    animated views of the life of nature.<lb/>A single psalm, the 104th, may be said
                    to present a picture of the entire cosmos.&#x2014;<lb/><hi rendition="#i"
                        >Humboldt&#x2019;s Cosmos.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
