<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="144" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head>THE SUBLIME CHARACTER OF HEBREW POETRY</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">It</hi> is characteristic of Hebrew poetry in reference to nature,<lb/>that,
                    as a reflex of monotheism, it always embraces the<lb/>whole world in its unity,
                    comprehending the life of the<lb/>terrestrial globe, as well as the shining
                    regions of space.<lb/>It dwells less on details of phenomena, and loves to
                    contem-<lb/>plate great masses. Nature is pourtrayed, not as
                    self-sub<lb/>sisting, or glorious in her own beauty, but ever in relation<lb/>to
                    a higher, an over-ruling, a spiritual power. The Hebrew<lb/>bard ever sees in
                    her the living expression of the omni-<lb/>presence of God in the works of the
                    visible creation. Thus,<lb/>the lyrical poetry of the Hebrews, in its
                    descriptions of<lb/>nature, is essentially, in its very subject, grand and
                    solemn;<lb/>and, when touching on the earthly condition of man, full<lb/>of a
                    yearning pensiveness. It is deserving of notice, that<lb/>notwithstanding its
                    grand character, and even in its highest<lb/>lyrical flights, elevated by the
                    charm of music, the Hebrew<lb/>poetry, unlike that of the Hindoos, scarcely ever
                    appears<lb/>unrestrained by law and measure. Devoted to the
                    pure<lb/>contemplation of the Divinity, figurative in language, but<lb/>clear
                    and simple in thought, it delights in comparisons<lb/>which recur continually
                    and almost rhythmically. As de-<lb/>scriptions of natural scenery, the writings
                    of the Old Testa-<lb/>ment show, as in a mirror, the nature of the country
                    in<lb/>which the people of Israel moved and dwelt, with its alter-<lb/>nations
                    of desert, fruitful land, forest, and mountain. They<lb/>pourtray the variations
                    of the climate of Palestine, the suc-<lb/>cession of the seasons, the pastoral
                    manners of the people,<lb/>and their innate disinclination to agriculture. The
                    epic,<lb/>or historical and narrative, portions are of the utmost
                    sim-<lb/>plicity, almost more unadorned even than Herodotus; and<lb/>from the
                    small alteration which has taken place in the<lb/>manners, and in the usages and
                    circumstances of a nomade<lb/>life, modern travellers have been enabled to
                    testify unani-<lb/>mously to their truth to nature. The Hebrew
                    lyrical<lb/>poetry is more adorned, and unfolds rich and animated views<lb/>of
                    the life of nature. A single psalm, the 104th, may be<lb/>said to present a
                    picture of the entire cosmos.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
