<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Beautiful Extract.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;Humboldt&#x2019;s Kosmos<lb/>contains the following beautiful passage:</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;We possess a genuine fragment which Cicero<lb/>has preserved to us from a lost work of
                    Aristotle.<lb/>It runs thus:&#x2014;&#x201C;If there were beings who lived
                    in<lb/>the depths of the earth, in dwellings adorned with<lb/>statues and
                    paintings, and everything which is pos-<lb/>sessed <choice>
                        <sic>iu r ch</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">in rich</corr>
                    </choice> abundance by those whom we es-<lb/>teem fortunate, and if these beings
                    could receive<lb/>tidings of the power and might of the Gods, and<lb/>could then
                    emerge from their hidden dwellings<lb/>through the open fissures of the earth,
                    to the pla-<lb/>ces which we inhabit&#x2014;if they could suddenly be-<lb/>hold
                    the earth, and the sea, and the vault of heav-<lb/>en, could recognise the
                    expanse of the cloudy firm-<lb/>ament and the might of the winds of heaven,
                    and<lb/>admire the sun in its majesty, beauty, and radiant<lb/>effulgence; and
                    lastly, when night veiled the earth<lb/>in darkness, they could behold the
                    starry heavens,<lb/>the changing moon and the stars rising and setting<lb/>in
                    the unvarying course ordained from eternity&#x2014;<lb/>they would surely
                    exclaim, <hi rendition="#i">there are Gods, and<lb/>such great things must be
                        the work of their hands.</hi>&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>It has been justly observed that this passage is<lb/>alone sufficient to corroborate Cicero&#x2019;s opinion of<lb/>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">the golden flow of Aristotle&#x2019;s eloquence,</hi>&#x201D; and<lb/>that his works are pervaded by something of the<lb/>inspired force of Plato&#x2019;s genius. Such a testimo-<lb/>ny to the existence of the heavenly powers, drawn<lb/>from the beauty and stupendous greatness of the<lb/>works of creation, is rarely to be met with in the<lb/>works of antiquity.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
