<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="4" facs="#f0001"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#b">The Diffusion of Life.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We find from the most recent observations that animal<lb break="yes"/>life predominates amid the eternal night of the depths of<lb break="yes"/>ocean, whilst vegetable life, which is so dependent on<lb break="yes"/>the periodic action of the solar rays, is most prevalent on<lb break="yes"/>continents. The mass of vegetation on the earth very<lb break="yes"/>far exceeds that of animal organisms. For what is the<lb break="yes"/>volume of all the large living cetacea and pachyderma-<lb break="no"/>ta, when compared with the thickly crowded colossal<lb break="yes"/>trunks of trees of from eight to twelve feet in diameter,<lb break="yes"/>which fill the vast forests covering the tropical region of<lb break="yes"/>South America, between the Orinoco, the Amazon, and<lb break="yes"/>the Rio da Maderia? And although the character of dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent portions of the earth depends on the combination<lb break="yes"/>of external phenomena, as the outlines of mountains&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>the physiognomy of plants and animals&#x2014;the azure of<lb break="yes"/>the sky&#x2014;the forms of the clouds&#x2014;and the transparency<lb break="yes"/>of the atmosphere&#x2014;it must still be admitted that the veg-<lb break="no"/>etable mantle with which the earth is decked, consti-<lb break="no"/>tutes the main feature of the picture. Animal forms are<lb break="yes"/>inferior in mass, and their powers of motion often with-<lb break="no"/>draw them from our sight. The vegetable kingdom, on<lb break="yes"/>the contrary, acts upon our imagination by its continued<lb break="yes"/>presence, and by the magnitude of its form; for the<lb break="yes"/>size of a tree indicates its age, and here alone age is as-<lb break="no"/>sociated with the expression of a constantly renewed<lb break="yes"/>vigor. In the animal kingdom (and this knowledge is<lb break="yes"/>also the result of Ehrenberg&#x2019;s discoveries) the forms<lb break="yes"/>which we term microscopic occupy the largest space, in<lb break="yes"/>consequence of their rapid propagation. The minutest<lb break="yes"/>of the infusoria, the monadid&#x00E6;, have a diameter which<lb break="yes"/>does not exceed 1&#x00B7;3000th of a line, and yet these sili-<lb break="no"/>ceous shelled organisms form in humid districts subter-<lb break="no"/>ranean strata of many fathoms in depth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The strong and beneficial influence exercised on the<lb break="yes"/>feelings of mankind by the consideration of the diffusion<lb break="yes"/>of life throughout the realms of nature, is common to<lb break="yes"/>every zone, but the impression thus produced is most<lb break="yes"/>powerful in the equatorial regions, in the land of palms,<lb break="yes"/>bamboos, and arborescent ferns&#x2014;where the ground rises<lb break="yes"/>from the shore of seas rich in mollusea and corals, to the<lb break="yes"/>limits of perpetual snow. The local distribution of plants<lb break="yes"/>embraces almost all heights and all depths. Organic<lb break="yes"/>forms not only descend into the interior of the earth,<lb break="yes"/>where the industry of the miner has laid open extensive<lb break="yes"/>excavations, and sprung deep shafts, but I have also<lb break="yes"/>found snow-white stalactitic columns encircled by the<lb break="yes"/>delicate web of an Usnea, in caves where meteoric wa-<lb break="no"/>ter could alone penetrate through fissures. Podurell&#x00E6;<lb break="yes"/>penetrate into the icy crevices of the glaciers on Mount<lb break="yes"/>Rosa, the Grindelwald, and the Upper Aar; the Chron&#x00E6;a<lb break="yes"/>araneoides described by Dalman, and the microscopic<lb break="yes"/>Discerea nivalis (formerly known as Protococous,) exist<lb break="yes"/>in the polar snow as well as in that of our high moun-<lb break="no"/>tains. The redness assumed by the snow after lying on<lb break="yes"/>the ground for some time, was known to Aristotle, and<lb break="yes"/>was probably observed by him on the mountains of Ma-<lb break="no"/>cedonia. Whilst on the loftiest summits of the Alps,<lb break="yes"/>only Lecide&#x00E6;, Parmeli&#x00E6;, and Umbilicari&#x00E6;, cast their<lb break="yes"/>colored but scanty covering over the rocks, exposed by<lb break="yes"/>the melted snow, beautiful phanerogamic plants, as the<lb break="yes"/>Culcitum rufescens, Sida pinchinchensis, and Saxifraga<lb break="yes"/>boussingaulti, are still found to flourish in the tropical<lb break="yes"/>region of the chain of the Andes, at an elevation of more<lb break="yes"/>than 15,000 feet. Thermal springs contain small insects<lb break="yes"/>(Hydroporus thermalis,) gallionell&#x00E6;, oscillatoria, and<lb break="yes"/>conferv&#x00E6;e, whilst the waters bathe the root-fibres of<lb break="yes"/>phanerogamic plants. As air and water are animated<lb break="yes"/>at different temperatures by the presence of vital organ-<lb break="no"/>isms, so likewise is the interior of the different portions<lb break="yes"/>of animal bodies. Animaleules have been found in the<lb break="yes"/>blood of the frog and the salmon; according to Nord-<lb break="no"/>man, the fluids in the eyes of fishes are often filled with<lb break="yes"/>a worm that lives by suction (Diplostomum,) whilst in the<lb break="yes"/>gills of the bleak the same observer has discovered a<lb break="yes"/>remarkable double animalcule, (Diplozoon paradoxam,)<lb break="yes"/>having a cross shaped form, with two heads and two<lb break="yes"/>cautal extremities.&#x2014;</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>[Humboldt&#x2019;s &#x201C;Cosmos.&#x201D;</salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 