<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>

<pb n="188" facs="#f0001" />

    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">The Book of Job.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;The Book of Job is ge-<lb/>nerally regarded as the most perfect specimen of<lb/>the poetry of the Hebrews. It is alike pictur-<lb/>esque in the delineation of individual phenomena,<lb/>and artistically skillful in the didactic arrange-<lb/>ment of the whole work. In all the modern lan-<lb/>guages into which the Book of Job has been<lb/>translated, its images, drawn from the natural<lb/>scenery of the East, leaves a deep impression on<lb/>the mind. The Lord walketh on the heights of<lb/>the waters, on the ridges of the waves towering<lb/>high beneath the force of the wind. The morn-<lb/>ing <choice><sic>read</sic><corr type="editorial">red</corr></choice> has colored the margins of the earth,<lb/>and variously formed the covering of the clouds,<lb/>as the hand of man moulds the yielding clay.&#x2014;<lb/>The habits of animals are described, as, for in-<lb/>stance, those of the wild ass, the horse, the buf-<lb/>falo, the rhinoceros and the crocodile, the eagle<lb/>and the ostrich. We see the pure ether spread,<lb/>during the scorching heat of the south wind, as<lb/>a melted mirror over the parched desert.</p><lb/><p>The poetic literature of the Hebrews is not<lb/>deficient in variety of form; for while the He-<lb/>brew poetry breathes a tone of warlike enthusi-<lb/>asm, from Joshua to Samuel, the little Book of<lb/>the gleaner Ruth presents us with a charming<lb/>and exquisite picture of nature. Goethe, at the<lb/>period of his enthusiasm for the East, spoke of<lb/>it as the loveliest specimen of epic and idyl poe-<lb/>try which we possess.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Cosmos.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
