<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>

<pb n="35" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head>The Book of Job.</head><lb/><p>&#x201C;The Book of Job is generally regarded as the<lb/>most perfect specimen of the poetry of
                    the Hebrews.<lb/>It is alike picturesque in the delineation of indi-<lb/>vidual
                    phenomena, and artistically skilful in the<lb/>didactic arrangement of the whole
                    work. In all<lb/>the modern languages into which the Book of Job<lb/>has been
                    translated, its images, drawn from the<lb/>natural scenery of the East, leave a
                    deep impres-<lb/>sion on the mind. &#x2018;The Lord walketh on the<lb/>heights
                    of the waters, on the ridges of the waves<lb/>towering high beneath the force of
                    the wind.&#x2019;<lb/>&#x2018;The morning red has coloured the margins of
                    the<lb/>earth, and variously formed the covering of the<lb/>clouds, as the hand
                    of man moulds the yielding<lb/>clay.&#x2019; The habits of animals are
                    described, as, for<lb/>instance, those of the wild ass, the horse, the
                    buf-<lb/>falo, the rhinoceros and the crocodile, the eagle<lb/>and the ostrich.
                    We see &#x2018;the pure ether spread,<lb/>during the scorching heat of the south
                    wind, as a<lb/>melted mirror over the parched desert.&#x2019;</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;The poetic literature of the Hebrews is not<lb/>deficient in variety of form; for while the Hebrew<lb/>poetry breathes a tone of warlike enthusiasm, from<lb/>Joshua to Samuel, the little Book of the gleaner<lb/>Ruth presents us with a charming and exquisite<lb/>picture of nature. Göethe, at the period of his en-<lb/>thusiasm for the East, spoke of it &#x2018;as the loveliest<lb/>specimen of epic and idyl poetry which we pos-<lb/>sess.&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Cosmos, vol. II., p.</hi> 60.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
