<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/111602781X">
                        <surname>Müller-Tamm</surname>
                        <forename>Jutta</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-10-25" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="575" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>TO THE EDITOR OF THE LAUNCESTON<lb break="yes"/>EXAMINER.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <div n="2">
                            <p>
                                <hi rendition="#k">Sir,</hi>&#x2014;In your paper of the 19th instant, you<lb break="yes"/>have favored us with a review of the <hi rendition="#i">Tasmanian<lb break="yes"/>Journal,</hi> No. 5, vol. 3, and I regret to observe<lb break="yes"/>that the <choice><sic>transalation</sic><corr type="editorial">translation</corr></choice> you have given of Humboldt&#x2019;s<lb break="yes" />letter is very incorrect. It has been well said,<lb break="yes" />&#x201C;everything suffers by translation but a bishop,&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>and your ingenious <hi rendition="#i" >traducteur</hi> has so contrived to<lb break="yes"/>
                                <hi rendition="#i">trans-mogrify</hi> the letter in question, that I fear the<lb break="yes"/>venerable author himself would not recognise it.<lb break="yes"/>It reminds one of the exclamation made by a<lb break="yes"/>person on seeing the portrait of his friend&#x2014;&#x201C;it is<lb break="yes"/>so like you would not know it!&#x201D;&#x2014;I therefore send<lb break="yes"/>you a more correct, and, I hope, more intelligible<lb break="yes" />version.&#x2014;I am, Sir,</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>A <hi rendition="#k">Member of the Tasmanian Society.</hi>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <hi rendition="#i">Launceston.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;How rejoiced I am to learn, my excellent<lb break="yes" />friend, that you are about to penetrate those beau-<lb break="no" />tiful vallies of the Himalayah, and even beyond,<lb break="yes" />towards Ladak and the plateaux of Thibet; the<lb break="yes"/>mean elevation of which, apart from that of the<lb break="yes"/>peaks which rise from the table-land itself, is an<lb break="yes"/>object worthy of research! How I appreciate that<lb break="yes"/>noble ardor which induces you to undertake ano-<lb break="no"/>ther hazardous expedition, after having been in<lb break="yes"/>that to the South Pole, which was so gloriously<lb break="yes"/>conducted. Your agreeable letter of the 5th<lb break="yes"/>September, found me rather indisposed. I have<lb break="yes"/>been living at the park Sans Souci during the<lb break="yes"/>absence of the King, and the excessive cold has<lb break="yes"/>compelled me to return to town. My depar-<lb break="no"/>ture for Paris has been deferred, and I have<lb break="yes"/>thus corrected here the last sheets of the second<lb break="yes"/>volume of <hi rendition="#i">Cosmos,</hi> which will shortly appear. I<lb break="yes"/>expect the King and Queen will return to-morrow,<lb break="yes"/>and I shall be able to set out about the 4th Oct.,<lb break="yes"/>so as to pass two or three months in Paris. I<lb break="yes"/>begin to console myself for the injustice they did<lb break="yes"/>you in not giving you the chair of Edinburgh;<lb break="yes"/>for, from the extent and variety of information<lb break="yes"/>which you possess, you are called upon to render<lb break="yes"/>eminent services not only to the geography of<lb break="yes"/>plants, but also to all branches of meteorology, as<lb break="yes"/>well as to geology. You have the advantage that<lb break="yes"/>your views are enlarged, and you have a taste (a<lb break="yes"/>feeling) for exactness.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;I congratulate the &#x2018;Board of Admiralty&#x2019; and<lb break="yes"/>the &#x2018;Commissioners of Woods and Forests,&#x2019; in<lb break="yes"/>the name of that department of the physical sci-<lb break="no"/>ences to which all my life has been devoted, upon<lb break="yes"/>the choice which they have made, in extending to<lb break="yes"/>you their patronage, and of which you are so<lb break="yes"/>worthy, &#x2014;by your acquirements,&#x2014; by the vivacity<lb break="yes"/>and ardor of your character,&#x2014;and by the constancy<lb break="yes"/>of a devotedness so disinterested! I look back with<lb break="yes" />pleasure to the remembrance of those conversa-<lb break="no" />tions, to me so instructive, during the time I lived<lb break="yes"/>in the same house with you in Paris: I took<lb break="yes"/>notes of them almost from your dictation, and it<lb break="yes"/>gives me pleasure to find them among my papers;<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;happy advantage of old age which has so few!<lb break="yes"/>Your excellent father has undertaken the publi-<lb break="no"/>cation of my Cryptogamic plants of the Cordil-<lb break="no"/>leras; and here is his son, whom I have the<lb break="yes"/>pleasure of calling my young friend, has seen<lb break="yes"/>the eruptions of Mount Erebus, and is about to see<lb break="yes"/>that which has been the dream of my life, now<lb break="yes"/>near its close.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;Do not forget, my dear friend, to write to me<lb break="yes" />at Paris, before setting out on this magnificent<lb break="yes" />expedition. I am delighted with your (paper on<lb break="yes" />the) Gallipagos, but would be very glad if you<lb break="yes" />would draw up for my information a few geogra-<lb break="no"/>phic notes, merely specifying such European or<lb break="yes"/>American <hi rendition="#i">Phanerogamic</hi> plants, as are without<lb break="yes"/>doubt indigenous to the southern hemisphere,<lb break="yes"/>
                                <hi rendition="#i">not American.</hi> Tell me also something about your<lb break="yes"/>
                                <cb/>
                                <hi rendition="#i">C&#x00E6;lebogyne ilicifolia,</hi> which Jussieu places among<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i" >Euphorbiace&#x00E6;.</hi> Is the idea of fertile seeds<lb break="yes"/>without stamina still entertained?&#x2014;what do you<lb break="yes"/>think of it?</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;I need scarcely call your attention to specific<lb break="yes"/>objects, acquainted as you are with the problems<lb break="yes"/>which they involve.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;The altitudes at which certain families of<lb break="yes" />plants cease.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;Do the characteristics of the Siberian Flora<lb break="yes" />extend so far into Cashmere and Ladak, as has<lb break="yes"/>been supposed?</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;To what altitude are fish found in the lakes?<lb break="yes" />Compare their species and determine their <choice><sic>affini-<lb break="no" />nities</sic><corr type="editorial">affini-<lb break="no" />ties</corr></choice>.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;Be particularly attentive to the temperature<lb break="yes" />of the soil at different altitudes.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;As a test for this purpose, compare the<lb break="yes" />temperature of the soil within the tropics at from<lb break="yes" />18 inches, to 2 feet below the surface, (Boussin-<lb break="no" />gault) with the depth of 20 or 30 feet (and repeat<lb break="yes" />these observations as you advance) northwards.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;Clear up the problem about the height of per-<lb break="no" />petual snow on the southern and northern slopes<lb break="yes"/>of the Himalayah, bearing in mind the data which<lb break="yes"/>I have brought together in the 3rd vol. of my work<lb break="yes"/>on Central Asia.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;I cannot believe in the uniformity and un-<lb break="no" />broken continuity of the Gneiss, Mica schists, or<lb break="yes" />Silurian formations of the Himalayah.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;Observe particularly the Porphyritic forma-<lb break="no" />tions&#x2014;the Greenstone, the Amygdaloids(?), the<lb break="yes"/>Basalts(?) of the chain.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;If you are fortunate enough to cross the grand<lb break="yes" />Cordillera of Kouenlun in order to reach Yark-<lb break="no"/>and, in ascending towards the sources of the<lb break="yes"/>Cajouh, a tributary of the Indus, observe atten-<lb break="no"/>tively the <hi rendition="#i">lowest point</hi> of elevation of the plain<lb break="yes"/>which sends its waters to the east, by the (River)<lb break="yes"/>Tarem to Lake Lop.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;It would be most desirable to determine the<lb break="yes" />height of the plain to the east of Yarkand by<lb break="yes" />barometric observation, or, if you can manage it,<lb break="yes"/>
                                <hi rendition="#i">by the boiling point of water.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;The horary variations of the barometer on the<lb break="yes" />plateaux, and on the Himalayah itself.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;Psychrometric observations, so as to compare<lb break="yes" />their results with the excessive dryness which I<lb break="yes" />experienced on the Steppes of Siberia.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;The temperature of caverns at their further<lb break="yes" />extremities.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;Do insects live at a less height than plants?</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;I must cease, lest I tire you with what you<lb break="yes" />know better than myself.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;Accept the renewed expression of my deep<lb break="yes"/>and affectionate esteem both for yourself, my<lb break="yes"/>excellent friend, and your respected father, Sir<lb break="yes"/>William.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;My compliments to your talented friend, Mr.<lb break="yes" />Darwin, all whose works delight me.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <closer>
                                <salute>
                                    <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Alexander Humboldt.</hi>
                                    </hi>
                                </salute>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <dateline>&#x201C;Berlin, 30th Sept. 1847.</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <div n="2">
                            <p>&#x201C;I have no time to read over my scrawl. I<lb break="yes"/>am going to see how many Nos. of your beautiful<lb break="yes"/>Flora I possess.&#x201D;</p>
                        </div>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>[We are not displeased to have another transla-<lb break="no"/>tion of this interesting communication; but the<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Member,&#x201D; or the Editor of the <hi rendition="#i">Tasmanian Jour-<lb break="no"/>nal,</hi> ought to have saved us from giving <hi rendition="#i">two</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>versions by publishing it in English.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k" >Ed.</hi> L. E.]</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 