<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>

<pb n="266" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head>HEBRAIC POETRY.</head><lb/><div n="2"><head>BY HUMBOLDT.</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">The</hi> Hebraic poetry, besides all its innate, exalted sublimity,<lb/>presents the nations of the West with the special attraction<lb/>of being interwoven with numerous reminiscences connected<lb/>with the local seat of the religion professed by the followers<lb/>of the three most widely diffused forms of belief, Judaism,<lb/>Christianity, and Mahomedanism. Thus missions, favoured<lb/>by the spirit of commerce, and thirst for conquest, evinced by<lb/>maritime nations, have combined to bear the geographical<lb/>names and natural descriptions of the East, as they are pre-<lb/>served to us in the books of the Old Testament, far into the<lb/>forests of the New World, and to the remote islands of the<lb/>Pacific. It is characteristic of the poetry of the Hebrews,<lb/>that as a reflex of monotheism it always embraces the uni-<lb/>verse in its unity, comprising both terrestrial life, and the<lb/>luminous realms of space. It dwells but rarely on the indivi-<lb/>duality of phenomena, preferring the contemplation of great<lb/>masses. The Hebrew poet does not depict nature as a self-<lb/>dependent object, glorious in its individual beauty, but always<lb/>as in relation and subjection to a higher spiritual power.<lb/>Nature is to him a work of creation and order, the living<lb/>expression of the omnipresence of the Deity, in the visible<lb/>world; hence the lyrical poetry of the Hebrews, from the very<lb/>nature of its subject, is grand and solemn, and when it treats<lb/>of the earthly condition of mankind is full of sad and pensive<lb/>longing. It is worthy of remark, that Hebrew poetry, not-<lb/>withstanding its grandeur, and the lofty tone of exaltation to<lb/>which it is often elevated by the charm of music, scarcely<lb/>ever loses the restraint of measure, as does the poetry of India.<lb/>Devoted to the pure contemplation of the Divinity, it remains<lb/>clear and simple in the midst of the most figurative forms of<lb/>expression; delighting in comparisons which recur with almost<lb/>rhythmical regularity, as descriptions of nature. The writings<lb/>of the Old Testament are a faithful reflection of the character<lb/>of the country in which they were composed, of the alterna-<lb/>tions of barrenness and fruitfulness, and of the Alpine forests by<lb/>which the land of Palestine was characterised. They describe,<lb/>in their regular succession, the relations of the climate, the<lb/><pb n="267" facs="#f0002" />
manners of this people of herdsmen, and their hereditary aversion<lb/>to agricultural pursuits. The epic or historical narratives are<lb/>marked by a graceful simplicity, much more unadorned than<lb/>those of Herodotus, and most true to nature, a point on which<lb/>the unanimous testimony of modern travellers may be received<lb/>as conclusive, owing to the inconsiderable changes effected in<lb/>the course of ages in the habits and manners of a nomadic<lb/>people. Their lyrical poetry is more adorned, and develops a<lb/>rich and animated conception of the life of nature. It might<lb/>almost be said that that one single glorious Psalm, the 104th,<lb/>represents the image of the whole world&#x2014;&#x201C;Who coverest<lb/>thyself with light as with a garment: who stretchest out the<lb/>heavens like a curtain: who layeth the beams of his chambers<lb/>in the waters: who walketh upon the wings of the wind:<lb/>who laid the foundations of the earth, that it should not be<lb/>removed for ever. He sendeth the springs into the valleys,<lb/>which run among the hills. They give drink to every beast<lb/>of the field: the wild asses quench their thirst,&#x201D; &#x0026;c. The<lb/>great and wide sea is then described, &#x201C;wherein are things<lb/>creeping, innumerable, both small and great beasts,&#x201D; &#x0026;c. The<lb/>description of the heavenly bodies renders this picture of na-<lb/>ture complete. We are astonished to find in a lyrical poem<lb/>of such a limited compass the whole universe&#x2014;the heavens<lb/>and the earth&#x2014;sketched with a few bold touches. The calm<lb/>and toilsome labour of man, from the rising of the sun to the<lb/>setting of the same, when his daily work is done, is here con-<lb/>trasted with the moving life of the elements of nature. This<lb/>contrast and generalisation in the conception of the mutual<lb/>action of natural phenomena, and this retrospection of an<lb/>omnipresent invisible power, which can renew the earth, or<lb/>crumble it to dust, constitute a solemn and exalted, rather<lb/>than a glowing and gentle, form of poetic creation.</p><lb/><p>Similar views occur repeatedly in the Psalms, and most fully,<lb/>perhaps, in the ancient, if not ante-Mosaic, book of Job. The<lb/>meteorological processes, which take place in the atmosphere,<lb/>the formation and solution of vapour, according to the chang-<lb/>ing direction of the wind, &#x0026;c., are described with individual-<lb/>ising accuracy; and many questions are propounded which <hi rendition="#i">we</hi><lb/>in the present state of <hi rendition="#i">our</hi> physical knowledge may indeed be<lb/>able <hi rendition="#i">to express</hi> under more scientific definitions, but scarcely <hi rendition="#i">to<lb/>answer</hi> satisfactorily. The Book of Job is regarded as the<lb/>most perfect specimen of the poetry of the Hebrews. It is<lb/>alike picturesque in the delineation of individual phenomena,<lb/>and artistically skilful in the didactic arrangement of the<lb/>whole work. In all the modern languages into which the<lb/><pb n="268" facs="#f0003" />
Book of Job has been translated, its images drawn from the<lb/>natural scenery of the East, leave a deep impression on the<lb/>mind.</p><lb/><p>Where nature has but sparingly bestowed her gifts, the<lb/>senses of man are sharpened, and he marks every change in<lb/>the moving clouds of the atmosphere around him, tracing in<lb/>the solitude of the dreary desert, as on the face of the deep<lb/>and moving sea, every phenomenon through its varied changes,<lb/>back to the signs by which its coming was proclaimed.</p><lb/><p>The climate of Palestine, especially in the arid and rocky<lb/>portions of the country, is peculiarly adapted to give rise to<lb/>such observations.</p><lb/><p>The poetic literature of the Hebrews is not deficient in<lb/>variety of form; for whilst the Hebrew poetry breathes a<lb/>tone of warlike enthusiasm, from Joshua to Samuel; the little<lb/>book of the gleaner Ruth presents us with a charming and<lb/>exquisitely simple picture of nature. Goethe spoke of it &#x201C;as<lb/>the loveliest specimen of epic and idyl poetry which we pos-<lb/>sess.&#x201D; (<hi rendition="#i">Cosmos: Bohn&#x2019;s ed., vol.</hi> ii.)</p></div></div><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
