<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="189" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Arabian Scientific Researches.&#x2014;</hi></head><p>Besides the tribute of praise which we<lb/>have here paid to the advances made by<lb/>the
                    Arabians in the knowledge of nature,<lb/>both in the terrestrial and
                    celestial<lb/>spheres, we have still to allude to the<lb/>additions which, in
                    the solitary paths of<lb/>the development of ideas, they made to<lb/>the
                    treasury of pure mathematical know-<lb/>ledge. According to the most
                    recent<lb/>works written in England, France, and<lb/>Germany, on the history of
                    mathematics,<lb/>the algebra of the Arabians is to be<lb/>regarded as
                    &#x201C;having originated from the<lb/>confluence of two streams which
                    had<lb/>long flowed independently of each other,<lb/>one Indian and one
                    Greek.&#x201D; The com-<lb/>pendium of algebra written by the com-<lb/>mand of
                    the Caliph Al-Mamun, by the<lb/>Arabian mathematician, Mahommed Ben-<lb
                        break="maybe"/>Musa (the Chowarezmian), is based, as<lb/>my deceased learned
                    friend Friedrich<lb/>Rosen has shown, not on the works of<lb/>Diophantus, but on
                    Indian knowledge;<lb/>and even as early as under Almansor, at<lb/>the end of the
                    eighth century, Indian<lb/>astronomers were called to the brilliant<lb/>court of
                    the Abassides. According to<lb/>Castri and to Colebrooke, Diophantus<lb/>was not
                    translated into Arabic until the<lb/>end of the tenth century by
                    Abul-Wefa<lb/>Buzjani. The Arabians were indebted to<lb/>the Alexandrian school
                    for that which we<lb/>miss in the old Indian algebraists, namely,<lb/>the
                    establishment of a conclusion by the<lb/>successive advance from proposition
                    to<lb/>proposition. This fair inheritance, yet<lb/>farther increased by their
                    own exertions,<lb/>passed in the twelfth century from the<lb/>Arabs to the
                    European literature of the<lb/>middle ages through Johannes Hispalensis<lb/>and
                    Gerard of Cremona. &#x201C;In the alge-<lb/>braical works of the Indians we find
                    the<lb/>general solution of indeterminate equa-<lb/>tions of the first degree,
                    and a far more<lb/>highly finished treatment of those of the<lb/>second degree,
                    than in the writings of the<lb/>Alexandrian school which have come<lb/><pb
                        n="190" facs="#f0002"/> down to us; there is therefore no doubt,<lb/>that if
                    the works of the Indian writers<lb/>had been made known to Europeans
                    two<lb/>centuries earlier, instead of only in our<lb/>own time, they must have
                    aided the<lb/>development of modern analysis.&#x201D; The<lb/>Arabs in Persia
                    and on the Euphrates, as<lb/>well as in Arabia, received in the
                    ninth<lb/>century the knowledge of the Indian<lb/>numerical characters, through
                    channels<lb/>similar to those which had led to their<lb/>acquaintance with
                    Indian algebra. Per-<lb/>sians were employed at that period as<lb/>revenue
                    collectors on the Indus; and the<lb/>use of Indian numbers became
                    general<lb/>among the Arab revenue officers, and ex-<lb/>tended to Northern
                    Africa, opposite to<lb/>the coast of Sicily. Nevertheless, the<lb/>profound and
                    historical investigations to<lb/>which a distinguished mathematician,<lb/>M.
                    Chasles, was led, by his correct inter-<lb/>pretation of the so-called
                    Pythagorean<lb/>table in the geometry of Boethius, render<lb/>it more than
                    probable that the Christians<lb/>in the West were acquainted even
                    earlier<lb/>than the Arabians, with the Indian sys-<lb/>tem of numeration; the
                    use of the nine<lb/>figures, having their values determined<lb/>by position,
                    being known by them under<lb/>the name of the system of the Abacus.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
