<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/111602781X">
                        <surname>Müller-Tamm</surname>
                        <forename>Jutta</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-10-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="v" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>INTRODUCTION<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">by</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/> (<hi rendition="#i">Extract from a Letter to</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Sir Robert H. Schomburgk.</hi>)</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Nearly</hi> eight years have now passed, my dear Sir<lb break="yes"/>Robert, since I wrote a Preface to the German transla-<lb break="no"/>tion of your interesting &#x201C;Travels in Guiana and on the<lb break="yes"/>Orinoco.&#x201D; Proceeding from east to west through the<lb break="yes"/>mountain-group of the Parime, after encountering many<lb break="yes"/>perils you arrived at the lonely little village of Esmeralda,<lb break="yes"/>one of the last missionary-stations on the Upper Orinoco,<lb break="yes"/>which I had succeeded in reaching with my astronomical<lb break="yes"/>instruments thirty-nine years before, from the opposite<lb break="yes"/>side of the globe. Your labours have materially en-<lb break="no"/>larged our knowledge of the Geography and Natural<lb break="yes"/>History of the eastern part of South America, of the<lb break="yes"/>mountain-systems, and the great net of rivers between<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="vi" facs="#f0002"/> the sea-coast of Guiana, the Rio Branco, and the basin<lb break="yes"/>of the Amazon. If human civilization, which is making<lb break="yes"/>such giant strides in North America, should ever pene-<lb break="no"/>trate into these fastnesses (a hope which St. Basil calls<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;day-dreams of man&#x201D;), the structure of this great net<lb break="yes"/>of rivers, from north to south, may open channels of<lb break="yes"/>communication such as are unknown in any other part<lb break="yes"/>of the world. An insignificant canal, in the vicinity<lb break="yes"/>of the Brazilian Villa Bella, connecting the basin of the<lb break="yes"/>Guapore (a tributary of the Rio da Madeira) with the<lb break="yes"/>basin of the Paraguay, would effect the possibility of an<lb break="yes"/>unbroken navigation throughout the whole continent,<lb break="yes"/>from Buenos Ayres to the mouth of the Orinoco, op-<lb break="no"/>posite the island of Trinidad. These hydrographical<lb break="yes"/>contemplations impart a permanent interest to all that<lb break="yes"/>relates to any single portion of the world of rivers<lb break="yes"/>in South America, a country which at the same time<lb break="yes"/>presents the charms of magnificent tropical vegetation,<lb break="yes"/>and the aspect of life in its freest and wildest forms.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>With these brief considerations I may connect the<lb break="yes"/>gratification derived from this interesting Work, which,<lb break="yes"/>in conjunction with Mr. Taylor, you have undertaken<lb break="yes"/>to translate. It conducts us through Brazil to the<lb break="yes"/>mouth of the Amazon River, and through this into<lb break="yes"/>one of its important tributaries, the Xingú, the course<lb break="yes"/>of which is now explored for the first time. Prince<lb break="yes"/>Adalbert of Prussia, whose younger brother shared in<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="vii" facs="#f0003"/> the glorious deeds of the British army during the<lb break="yes"/>last war in India, had previously visited the Crimea,<lb break="yes"/>Constantinople, and Greece. A youthful passion for<lb break="yes"/>the sea early awakened in him; and a noble thirst for<lb break="yes"/>knowledge, the desire to enrich life by the acquisi-<lb break="no"/>tion of new and enlarged ideas, subsequently led him<lb break="yes"/>to travel through Sicily, along the Spanish coast, to<lb break="yes"/>Teneriffe, and Rio de Janeiro. The Journal of his<lb break="yes"/>Travels, printed originally only for the perusal of his<lb break="yes"/>friends, and enriched with sketches made from nature<lb break="yes"/>by the Author himself, is not in the strict sense of the<lb break="yes"/>word a scientific book; nevertheless it contains observa-<lb break="no"/>tions and views of nature and customs which reflect a<lb break="yes"/>vivid picture of the scenes which the Prince witnessed<lb break="yes"/>and passed through. Instruction is imparted in the<lb break="yes"/>most pleasing manner, when an unaffected simplicity<lb break="yes"/>and an absence of all pretension pervade a work like<lb break="yes"/>this.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <dateline>Sans Souci, October, 1848.</dateline>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 