<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#b">EXTRACTS FROM NEW WORKS.</hi><lb/>THE FOREST AT MIDNIGHT.
                </head>
                <p>Below the mission of Santa Barbara de Arichuna we passed<lb/>
                    the night as usual, under the open sky, on a sandy flat on the<lb/>
                    bank of the Rio Apure closely bordered by the impenetrable<lb/>
                    forest. It was not without difficulty that we succeeded in finding<lb/>
                    dry wood to kindle the fires with which it is here customary<lb/>
                    in that country to surround the bivouac, in order to guard <lb/>
                    the attacks of the jaguar. The night was humid, mild, and<lb/>
                    moonlight. Several crocodiles approached the shore; I think<lb/>
                    I have observed these animals to be attracted by fire, like our<lb/>
                    cray-fish and many other inhabitants of the water. The oars of<lb/>
                    our boat were placed upright and carefully driven into the<lb/>
                    ground, to form poles from which our hammocks could be sus-<lb/>
                    pended. Deep stillness prevailed; only from time to time we<lb/>
                    heard blowing of the fresh-water dolphins which are peculiar<lb/>
                    to the Orinoco net-work of rivers (and, according to Colebroke,<lb/>
                    to the Ganges as far as Benares), which followed each other in<lb/>
                    long lines.</p>
                <p>Soon after eleven o&#x2019;clock such a disturbance began to be<lb/>
                    heard in the adjoining forest, that for the remainder of the night<lb/>
                    all sleep was impossible. The wild cries of animals appeared<lb/>
                    to rage throughout the forest. Among the many voices which<lb/>
                    resounded together, the Indians could only recognise those<lb/>
                    which, after short pauses in the general uproar, were first heard<lb/>
                    singly. There was the monotonous howling of the aloates (the<lb/>
                    howling monkeys); the plaintive, soft, and almost flute-like<lb/>
                    tones of the small sapajous; the snorting grumblings of the<lb/>
                    striped nocturnal monkey(the Nyetipithicus trivirgatus, which<lb/>
                    I was the first to describe); the interrupted cries of the great<lb/>
                    tiger, the cuguar or maneless American lion, the peccary, the<lb/>
                    sloth, and a host of parrots, parraquas, and other pheasant-<lb/>
                    like birds. When the tigers came near the edge of the forest,<lb/>
                    our dog, which had before barked incessantly, came howling to<lb/>
                    seek refuge under our hammocks. Sometimes the cry of the<lb/>
                    tiger was heard to proceed from amidst the high branches of a<lb/>
                    tree, and was in such case always accompanied by the plaintive<lb/>
                    piping of the monkeys, who were seeking to escape from the<lb/>
                    unwonted pursuit.</p>
                <p>If one asks the Indians why this incessant noise and distur-<lb/>
                    bance arises on particular nights, they answer, with a smile,<lb/>
                    that &#x201C;the animals are rejoicing in the bright moonlight, and<lb/>
                    keeping the feast of the full moon.&#x201D; To me it appeared that<lb/>
                    the scene had probably originated in some accidental combat,<lb/>
                    and that hence the disturbance had spread to other animals, and<lb/>
                    thus the noise had increased more and more. The jaguar pur-<lb/>
                    sues the peccaries and tapirs, and these, pressing against each<lb/>
                    other in their flight break thorugh the interwoven tree-like<lb/>
                    shrubs which impede their escape; the apes on the tops of the<lb/>
                    trees, being frightened by the crash, join their cries to those of<lb/>
                    the larger animals; this arouses the tribes of birds, who build<lb/>
                    their nests in communities, and thus the whole animal world<lb/>
                    becomes in a state of commotion. Longer experience taught<lb/>
                    us that it is by no means always the celebration of the bright-<lb/>
                    ness of the moon which disturbs the repose of the woods: we<lb/>
                    witnessed the same occurrence repeatedly, and found that the<lb/>
                    voices were loudest during violent falls of rain, or when, with<lb/>
                    loud peals of thunder, the flashing lightning illuminated the<lb/>
                    deep recesses of the forest. The good-natured Franciscan<lb/>
                    monk, who, although he had been suffering for several months<lb/>
                    from fever, accompanied us through the Cataracts of Atures<lb/>
                    and Maypures to San Carlos on the Rio Negro, and to the Bra-<lb/>
                    zilian boundary, used to say, when fearful on the closing in of<lb/>
                    night that there might be a thunder-storm, &#x201C;May Heaven<lb/>
                    grant a quiet night both to us and to the wild beasts of the<lb/>
                    forest!&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Aspects of Nature.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 