<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Descendants of the Peruvian Incas</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:13</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VI.117</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1849-Das_Hochland_von-4-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_Hochland_von-1-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_Hochland_von-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_Hochland_von-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_Hochland_von-4-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_Hochland_von-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_Hochland_von-6.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Aspects of Nature&lt;/i&gt;, übersetzt von Sabine, 2 Bände, London: Longman, Brown, Green and Longmans, John Murray 1849, Band 2, S. 292–295.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Ansichten der Natur&lt;/i&gt;, Dritte verbesserte und vermehrte Ausgabe, 2 Bände, Stuttgart und Tübingen: Cotta 1849, Band 2, S. 352–358.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Descendants of the Peruvian Incas</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1849</date>
          <pubPlace>Nottingham</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Nottinghamshire Guardian and Midland Advertiser&lt;/i&gt; 4:186 (8. November 1849), S. 4.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="4" facs="#f0001" />
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#k">Decendants of the Peruvian Incas.</hi>&#x2014;We<lb/>found descendants of the monarch, the family of the<lb/>Indian Cacique Astorpilco, dwelling in Caxamarca,<lb/>among the meancholy ruins of ancient departed<lb/>splendour, and living in great poverty and privation;<lb/>but patient and uncomplaining. Their descent from<lb/>Atahuallpa through the female line has never been<lb/>doubted in Caxamarca, but traces of beard may<lb/>perhaps indicate some admixture of Spanish blood.<lb/>Of the sons of the Great (but for a child of the sun<lb/>somewhat free thinking) Huayna Capac, neither of the<lb/>two who swayed the sceptre before the arrival of the<lb/>Spaniards, Huascar and Atahuallpa, left behind them<lb/>acknowledged sons. Huascar became the prisoner of<lb/>Atahuallpa in the plains of Quipaypan, and was soon<lb/>afterwards secretly murdered by his order. Neither<lb/>were there any surviving male descendants of the two<lb/>remaining brothers of Atahuallpa, the insignificant<lb/>youth Toparca, whom Pizarro caused to be crowned<lb/>as Inca in the autumn of 1553, and the enterprising<lb/>Manco Capao, similarly crowned, but who afterwards<lb/>rebelled again. Atahuallpa left indeed a son, whose<lb/>Christian name was Don Francisco (but who died very<lb/>young), and a daughter, Donna Angelina, by whom<lb/>Francisco Pizarro (with whom she led a wild and war-<lb/>like life), had a son whom he loved fondly, grandchild<lb/>of the slaughtered monarch. Besides the family of<lb/>the Cacique Astorpilco, with whom I was acquainted<lb/>at Caxamarca, the Carguraicos and Titu Buscamayty<lb/>were pointed out at the period of my visit as belonging<lb/>to the Inca dynasty; but the Buscamayta family has<lb/>since become extinct. The son of the Cacique Astor-<lb/>pilco, a pleasing and friendly youth of 17, who accom-<lb/>panied me over the ruins of the palace of his ancestor,<lb/>while living in extreme poverty, had filled his imagina-<lb/>tion with images of buried splendour and golden<lb/>treasures hidden beneath the masses of rubbish<lb/>upon which we trod. He related to me that one of his<lb/>more immediate forefathers had bound his wife&#x2019;s eyes,<lb/>and then coaducted her through many labyrinths cut<lb/>in the rock into the subterranean garden of the Incas.<lb/>There she saw, skilfully and elaborately imitated, and<lb/>formed of the purest gold, artificial trees, with leaves<lb/>and fruit, and birds sitting on the branches; and there,<lb/>too, was the much sought for golden travelling chair<lb/>(una de las andas) of Atahuallpa. The man commanded<lb/>his wife not to touch any of these enchanted riches,<lb/>because the long foretold period of the restoration of<lb/>the empire had not yet arrived, and that whoever should<lb/>attempt before that time to appropriate aught of them<lb/>should die that very night. These golden dreams and<lb/>fancies of the youth were founded on recollections and<lb/>traditions of former days. The artificial &#x201C;golden gar-<lb/>dens&#x201D; (Jardines o Huertas de ora) were often described<lb/>by actual eye-witnesses, Cieza de Leon Sarmiento,<lb/>Garcilaso, and other early historians of the conquest.<lb/>They were found beneath the temple of the sun at<lb/>Cuzco, in Caxamarca, and in the pleasant valley of<lb/>Yucav, a favorite residence of the monarch&#x2019;s family.<lb/>Where the golden Huertas were not below ground,<lb/>living plants grew by the side of the artificial ones;<lb/>among the latter, tall plants and ears of maize (mazor-<lb/>cas) are mentioned as particularly well executed. The<lb/>morbid confidence with which the young Astorpilco<lb/>assured me that below our feet, a little to the right of<lb/>the spot on which I stood at the moment, there was an<lb/>artificial large flowered Datura tree (Guanto), formed<lb/>of gold wire and gold plates, which spread its branches<lb/>over the Inca&#x2019;s chair, impressed me deeply but pain-<lb/>fully, for it seemed as if these illusive and baseless<lb/>visions were cherished as consolations in present suf-<lb/>fering. I asked the lad&#x2014;&#x201C;Since you and your parents<lb/>believed so firmly in the existence of this garden, are<lb/>not you sometimes tempted in your necessities to dig<lb/>in search of treasures so close at hand?&#x201D; The boy&#x2019;s<lb/>answer was simple, and expressed so fully the quiet<lb/>resignation characteristic of the aboriginal inhabitants<lb/>of the country, that I noted it in Spanish in my journal.<lb/>&#x201C;Such a desire (tal antojo) does not come to us; fa-<lb/>ther says it would be sinful (que fuese pecado). If<lb/>we had the golden branches with all their golden<lb/>fruits our white neighbours would hate and injure us.<lb/>We have a small field and good wheat (buen trigo).&#x201D;<lb/>Few of my readers, I think, will blame me for recall-<lb/>ing here the words of the young Astorpilco and his<lb/>golden visions. The belief, so widely current among<lb/>the natives, that to take possession of buried treasures<lb/>which belonged to the Incas would be wrong, and<lb/>would incur punishment and bring misfortune on his<lb/>entire race, is connected with another belief which<lb/>prevailed, especially in the 16th and 17th centuries,<lb/><hi rendition="#i">i. e.</hi>, the future restoration of a kingdom of the Incas.<lb/>Every suppressed nationality looks forward to a day<lb/>of change, and to a renewal of the old Government.<lb/>The flight of Manco Inca, the brother of Atahuallpa,<lb/>into the forests of Vilcapampa on the declivity of the<lb/>eastern Cordillera, and the sojourn of Sayri Tupas and<lb/>Inca Tupas Amaru in those wildernesses, have left<lb/>permanent recollections. It was believed that the<lb/>dethroned dynasty had settled between the rivers<lb/>Apurimac and Beni, or still farther to the east in<lb/>Guiana. The myth of el Dorado and the golden<lb/>city of Manoa, travelling from the west to the east,<lb/>increased these dreams, and Raleigh&#x2019;s imagination<lb/>was so inflamed by them that he founded an expedi-<lb/>tion on the hope of &#x201C;conquering the &#x2018;imperial and<lb/>golden city,&#x2019; placing in it a garrison of 3,000 or 4,000<lb/>English, and levying from the &#x2018;Emperor of Guiana,&#x2019;<lb/>a descendent of Huayna Capac, and who holds his<lb/>court with the same magnificence, an annual tribute<lb/>of &#163;300,000 sterling, as the price of his promised re-<lb/>storation to the throne in Cuzco and Caxamarca.&#x201D;<lb/>Wherever the Peruvian Quichua language has ex-<lb/>tended, some traces of such expectations of the return<lb/>of the Inca&#x2019;s sovereignty continues to exist in the<lb/>minds of many among those of the natives who are<lb/>possessed of some knowledge of the history of their<lb/>country.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt.</hi>
            </p>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>