<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">  
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Nocturnal Life of Animals.&#x2014;A night on the<lb/>
                    Apure.</hi>&#x2014;Below the mission of Santa Barbara de Arichuna we passed<lb/>
                    the night as usual, in the open air, on a sandy flat, on the banks of the<lb/>
                    Apure, skirted by the impenetrable forest. We had some difficulty in<lb/>
                    finding dry wood to kindle the fires with which it is here customary to<lb/>
                    surround the bivouac, as a safeguard against the attacks of the jaguar.<lb/>
                    The air was bland and soft, and the moon shone brightly. Several cro-<lb/>
                    codiles approached the bank, and I have observed that fire attracts<lb/>
                    these creatures as it does our crabs and many other aquatic animals.&#x2014;<lb/>
                    The oars of our boats were fixed upright in the ground to support our<lb/>
                    hammocks. Deep stillness prevailed, only broken at intervals by the<lb/>
                    blowing of the fresh-water dolphins. After eleven o&#x2019;clock, such<lb/>
                    a noise began in the contiguous forest, that for the remainder<lb/>
                    of the night all sleep was impossible. The wild cries of animals rung<lb/>
                    through the woods. Among the many voices which resounded toge-<lb/>
                    ther the Indians could only recognise those which, after short pauses,<lb/>
                    were heard singly. There was the monotonous plaintive cry of the<lb/>
                    aluates (howling monkeys), the whining, flute-like notes of the small<lb/>
                    sapajous, the grunting murmur of the striped nocturnal ape (<hi rendition="#i">Nyctipithe-<lb/>
                    cus trivirgatus,</hi> which I was the first to describe), the fitful roar of the<lb/>
                    great tiger, the cuguar or maneless American lion, the peccary, the<lb/>
                    sloth, and a host of parrots, perraquas (<hi rendition="#i">Ortalides</hi>), and other pheasant-<lb/>
                    like birds. Whenever the tigers approached the edge of the forest, our<lb/>
                    dog, who before had barked incessantly, came howling to seek protec-<lb/>
                    tion under the hammocks. Sometimes the cry of the tiger resounded<lb/>
                    from the branches of a tree, and was then always accompanied by the<lb/>
                    plaintive piping tones of the apes, who were endeavouring to escape<lb/>
                    from the unwonted pursuit. If one asks the Indians why such a conti-<lb/>
                    nuous noise is heard on certain nights, they answer, with a smile, that<lb/>
                    &#x201C;the animals are rejoicing in the beautiful moonlight, and celebrating<lb/>
                    the return of the full moon.&#x201D; To me, the scene appears rather to be<lb/>
                    owing to an accidental, long-continued, and gradually increasing con-<lb/>
                    flict among the animals. Thus, for instance, the jaguar will pursue the<lb/>
                    peccaries and the tapirs, which, densely crowded together, burst<lb/>
                    through the barrier of tree-like shrubs which opposes their flight.&#x2014;<lb/>
                    Terrified at the confusion, the monkeys on the tops of the trees join<lb/>
                    their cries with those of the larger animals. This arouses the tribes of<lb/>
                    birds who build their nests in communities, and suddenly the whole<lb/>
                    animal world is in a state of commotion. Further experience taught<lb/>
                    us that it was by no means always the festival of moonlight that dis-<lb/>
                    turbed the stillness of the forest, for we observed that the voices were<lb/>
                    loudest during violent storms of rain, or when the thunder echoed and<lb/>
                    the lightning flashed through the depths of the woods. The good natured<lb/>
                    Franciscan monk, who (notwithstanding the fever from which he had<lb/>
                    been suffering for many months) accompanied us through the cataracts<lb/>
                    of Atures and Maypures to San Carlos, on the Rio Negro, and to the<lb/>
                    Brazilian coast, used to say, when apprehensive of a storm at night,<lb/>
                    &#x201C;May Heaven grant a quiet night both to us and to the wild beasts of<lb/>
                    the forest!&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Views of Nature.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 