<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/111602781X">
                        <surname>Müller-Tamm</surname>
                        <forename>Jutta</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-10-25" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Junction of the Pacific and the Atlantic<lb/>Ocean.</hi>&#x2014;Having for more than<lb/>forty years been occupied with the subject of the means of<lb/>communication between the two seas, I have constantly,<lb/>both in my printed works and in the different memoirs<lb/>which with honourable confidence the Free States of Spanish<lb/>America have requested me to furnish, urged that the Isth-<lb/>mus should be examined hypsometrically throughout its<lb/>entire length, and more especially where, in Darien and<lb/>the inhospitable former Provincia de Biruquete, it joins the<lb/>continent of South America; and where, between the Atrato<lb/>and the Bay of Cupica (on the shore of the Pacific), the<lb/>mountain chain of the Isthmus almost entirely disappears.<lb/>Gen. Bolivar, at my request, caused an exact levelling of<lb/>the Isthmus between Panama and the mouth of the Rio<lb/>Chagres to be made in 1828 and 1829, by Lloyd and Fal-<lb/>mare. (Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of<lb/>London for the year 1830, p. <choice><sic>59 68</sic><corr type="editorial">59&#x2015;68</corr></choice>.) Other measurements<lb/>have since been executed by accomplished and experienced<lb/>French engineers, and projects have been formed for canals<lb/>and railways, with locks and tunnels, but always in the di-<lb/>rection of a meridian between Portobello and Panama&#x2014;or<lb/>more to the west, towards Chagres and Cruces. Thus the<lb/>most important points of the eastern and south-eastern part<lb/>of the Isthmus have remained unexamined on both shores!<lb/>So long as this part is not examined geographically by<lb/>means of exact but easily obtained determinations of lati-<lb/>tude and longitude by chronometers, as well as hypsome-<lb/>trically in the conformation of the surface by barometric<lb/>measurements of elevation, so long I consider that the state-<lb/>ment I have repeatedly made, and which I now repeat in<lb/>1849, will still be true&#x2014;viz. that it is as yet unproved and<lb/>quite premature to pronounce that the Isthmus does not<lb/>admit of the formation of an oceanic canal (that is, a canal<lb/>with fewer locks than the Caledonian Canal), permitting<lb/>at all seasons the passage of the same sea-going ships be-<lb/>tween New York and Liverpool on the one hand, and Chili<lb/>and California on the other. On the Atlantic side (accord-<lb/>ing to examinations which the Directions of the Deposito<lb/>Hidrografico of Madrid have entered on their maps since<lb/>1809), the Ensenada de Mandinga penetrates so deeply to-<lb/>wards the south, that it appears to be only four or five Ger-<lb/>man geographical miles, fifteen to an equatorial degree<lb/>(that is, sixteen or twenty English geographical miles) from<lb/>the coast of the Pacific on the east of Panama. On the<lb/>Pacific side the Isthmus is almost equally indented by the<lb/>deep Golfo de San Miguel, into which the Rio Tuyra falls,<lb/>with its tributary river the Chuchunque (Chuchunaque).<lb/>This last-named stream in the upper part of its course ap-<lb/>proaches within sixteen English geographical miles of the<lb/>Atlantic side of the Isthmus to the west of Cape Tiburon.<lb/>For more than twenty years I have had inquiries made from<lb/>me on the subject of the problem of the Isthmus of Panama,<lb/>by associations desirous of employing considerable pecuniary<lb/>means; but the simple advice which I have given has never<lb/>been followed. Every scientifically educated engineer<lb/>knows that between the Tropics (even without corresponding<lb/>observations) good barometric measurements (the horary<lb/>variations being taken into account) afford results which<lb/>are assured to be less than from seventy to ninety French,<lb/>or seventy five to ninety six English feet. It would besides<lb/>be easy to establish for a few months, on the two shores, two<lb/>fixed <choice><sic>corrresponding</sic><corr type="editorial">corresponding</corr></choice> barometric stations, and to compare<lb/>repeatedly the portable instruments employed in preliminary<lb/>levelling, with each other and with those at the fixed sta-<lb/>tions. Let that part be particulary examined where, near<lb/>the continent of South America, the separating mountain<lb/>ridge sinks into hills. Seeing the importance of the subject<lb/>to the great commerce of the world, the research ought not,<lb/>as hitherto, to be restricted to a limited field.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s<lb/>Aspects of Nature.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 