<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="18" facs="#f0001" />
<cb/>
<p><hi rendition="#et">Selected for &#x201C;The Friend.&#x201D;</hi></p><lb/><p>On leaving the Island del Diamante, in which<lb/>Zambos, who speak Spanish, cultivate sugar-canes,<lb/>we entered on scenes of nature characterized by<lb/>wildness and grandeur. The air was filled with<lb/>countless flocks of flamingoes and other water birds,<lb/>which appeared against the blue sky like a dark<lb/>cloud with continually varying outlines. The river<lb/>had here narrowed to between 900 and 1000 feet,<lb/>and flowing in a perfectly straight line, formed a<lb/>kind of canal, enclosed on either side by dense<lb/>wood. The margin of the forest presents at this<lb/>part a singular appearance. In front of the almost<lb/>impenetrable wall of giant trunks of C&#x00E6;salpinia,<lb/>Cedrela, and Desmanthus, there rises from the<lb/>sandy river beach, with the greatest regularity, a<lb/>low hedge of Sauso, only four feet high, consisting<lb/>of a small shrub, Hermesia castaneifolia. Some<lb/>slender thorny palms stand next; and the whole re-<lb/>sembles a close, well-pruned garden hedge, having<lb/>only occasional openings at considerable distances<lb/>from each other, which have doubtless been made<lb/>by the larger four-footed beasts of the forest, to gain<lb/>easy access to the river. One sees, more especially<lb/>in the early morning and at sunset, the American<lb/>tiger or jaguar, the tapir, and the peccary, lead<lb/>their young through these openings to the river to<lb/>drink. When startled by the passing canoe, they<lb/>do not attempt to regain the forest by breaking<lb/>forcibly through the hedge which has been de-<lb/>scribed, but one has the pleasure of seeing these wild<lb/>animals stalk leisurely along between the river and<lb/>the hedge for four or five hundred paces, until they<lb/>have reached the nearest opening, when they dis-<lb/>appear through it. In the course of an almost<lb/>uninterrupted river navigation of 1520 miles on<lb/>the Orinoco to near its sources, on the Cassi-<lb/>quiare, and on the Rio Negro&#x2014;and during which<lb/>we were confined for seventy-four days to a small<lb/>canoe&#x2014;we enjoyed the repetition of the same<lb/>spectacle at several different points, and, I may add,<lb/>always with new delight. There came down to-<lb/>gether, to drink, to bathe, or to fish, groups con-<lb/>sisting of the most different classes of animals, the<lb/>larger mammalia being associated with many co-<lb/>loured herons, palamedeas, and proudly-stepping<lb/>curassow and cashew birds. &#x201C;Es como en el<lb/>Paraise&#x201D;&#x2014;it is here as in Paradise&#x2014;said, with a<lb/>pious air, our steersman, an old Indian, who had<lb/><cb/>
    been brought up in the house of an ecclesiastic.<lb/>The peace of the golden age was, however, far from<lb/>prevailing among the animals of this American<lb/>paradise, which carefully watched and avoided<lb/>each other. The capybara is devoured in the ri-<lb/>ver by crocodiles and on shore by the tiger. It<lb/>runs so indifferently that we were several times<lb/>able to catch individuals from among the nume-<lb/>rous herds which presented themselves.</p><lb/><p>Below the mission of Santa Barbara de Arichuna,<lb/>we passed the night, as usual, under the open sky,<lb/>on a sandy flat on the bank of the Rio Apure,<lb/>closely bordered by the impenetrable forest. It<lb/>was not without difficulty that we succeeded in<lb/>finding dry wood to kindle the fire with which it is<lb/>always customary in that country to surround a<lb/>bivouac, in order to guard against the attacks of<lb/>the jaguar. The night was humid, mild and moon-<lb/>light. Several crocodiles approached the shore; I<lb/>think I have observed these animals to be attracted<lb/>by fire, like our cray-fish and many other inhabit-<lb/>ants of the water. The oars of our boat were<lb/>placed upright, and carefully driven into the<lb/>ground, to form poles from which our hammocks<lb/>could be suspended. Deep stillness prevailed; only<lb/>from time to time we heard the blowing of the<lb/>fresh water dolphins, which are peculiar to the<lb/>Orinoco net-work of rivers, (and, according to<lb/>Colebrooke, to the Ganges as far as Benares,) which<lb/>followed each other in long lines. Soon after 11<lb/>o&#x2019;clock, such a disturbance began to be heard in<lb/>the adjoining forest, that for the remainder of the<lb/>night all sleep was impossible. The wild cries of<lb/>animals appeared to rage throughout the forest.<lb/>Among the many voices which resounded together,<lb/>the Indians could only recognise those which, after<lb/>short pauses in the general uproar, were first heard<lb/>singly. There was the monotonous howling of the<lb/><choice><sic>alnates</sic><corr type="editorial">aluates</corr></choice>, (the howling monkeys;) the plaintive, soft,<lb/>and almost flute like tones of the small sapajous;<lb/>the snorting grumblings of the striped nocturnal<lb/>monkey; the interrupted cries of the great tiger,<lb/>the cuguar or maneless American lion, the pec-<lb/>cary, the sloth, and a host of parrots, of parraquas,<lb/>and other pheasant-like birds. When the tigers<lb/>came near the edge of the forest, our dog, which<lb/>before had barked incessantly, came howling to<lb/>seek refuge under our hammocks. Sometimes the<lb/>cry of the tiger was heard to proceed from amidst<lb/>the high branches of a tree, and was in such case<lb/>always accompanied by the plaintive piping of the<lb/>monkeys, who were seeking to escape from the<lb/>unwonted pursuit.</p><lb/><p>If one asks the Indians why this incessant noise<lb/>and disturbance arises on particular nights, they<lb/>answer, with a smile, that &#x201C;the animals are re-<lb/>joicing in the bright moonlight, and keeping the<lb/>feast of the full moon.&#x201D; To me it appeared that<lb/>the scene had probably originated in some acci-<lb/>dental combat, and that hence the disturbance had<lb/>spread to other animals, and thus the noise had<lb/>increased more and more. The jaguar pursues the<lb/>peccaries and tapirs, and these pressing against<lb/>each other in their flight, break through the inter-<lb/>woven tree-like shrubs which impede their escape;<lb/>the apes on the tops of the trees, being frightened<lb/>by the crash, join their cries to those of the larger<lb/>animals; this arouses the tribes of birds, who build<lb/>their nests in communities, and thus the whole ani-<lb/>mal world becomes in a state of commotion. Longer<lb/>experience taught us that it is by no means always<lb/>the celebration of the brightness of the moon which<lb/>disturbs the repose of the woods; we witnessed the<lb/>same occurrence repeatedly, and found that the<lb/>voices were loudest during violent falls of rain, or<lb/>when, with loud peals of thunder, the flashing<lb/>lightning illuminated the deep recesses of the<lb/><cb/>
        forest. The good-natured Franciscan monk who,<lb/>although he had been suffering for several months<lb/>from fever, accompanied us through the Cataracts<lb/>of Atures and Maypures to San Carlos on the Rio<lb/>Negro, and to the Brazilian boundary, used to say<lb/>when fearful on the closing in of night that there<lb/>might be a thunder storm, &#x201C;May heaven grant a<lb/>quiet night both to us and to the wild beasts of the<lb/>forest.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>Scenes, such as those I have just described, were<lb/>wonderfully contrasted with the stillness which<lb/>prevails within the tropics during the noontide<lb/>hours of a day of more than usual heat. I borrow<lb/>from the same journal the recollections of a day<lb/>at the Narrows of Baragnan. At this part of<lb/>its course, the Orinoco forces for itself a passage<lb/>through the western portion of the Parime moun-<lb/>tains. What is called at this remarkable pass a<lb/>&#x201C;Narrow,&#x201D; is still a bed or water-basin of 5690<lb/>feet in breadth. On the naked rocks which formed<lb/>the shores we saw only, besides an old withered<lb/>stem Aubletia and a new Apocinea (Allamanda<lb/>salicifolia,) a few silvery croton shrubs. A ther-<lb/>mometer in the shade, but brought within a few<lb/>inches of the towering mass of granite rock, rose to<lb/>above 122° Fahr. All distant objects had wave-<lb break="maybe"/>like, undulating outlines, the effect of mirage; not<lb/>a breath of air stirred the fine, dust-like sand. The<lb/>sun was in the zenith, and the flood of light which<lb/>he poured down upon the river, and which, from<lb/>a slight rippling movement of the waters, flashed<lb/>sparkling back, rendered still more sensible the<lb/>red haze which veiled the distance. All the naked<lb/>rocks and boulders around were covered with a<lb/>countless number of large thick-scaled iguanas,<lb/>gecko-lizards, and variously spotted salamanders.<lb/>Motionless, with uplifted heads and open months,<lb/>they appeared to inhale the burning air with ecs-<lb/>tasy. At such times the larger animals seek shel-<lb/>ter in the recesses of the forest, and the birds hide<lb/>themselves under the thick foliage of the trees, or<lb/>in the clefts of the rocks; but if in this apparent<lb/>entire stillness of nature, one listens for the faint-<lb/>est tones which an attentive ear can seize, there is<lb/>perceived an all-pervading rustling sound, a hum-<lb/>ming and fluttering of insects close to the ground,<lb/>and in the lower strata of the atmosphere. Every-<lb/>thing announces a world of organic activity and<lb/>life. In every bush, in the cracked bark of the<lb/>trees, in the earth undermined by lymenopterous<lb/>insects, life stirs audibly. It is, as it were, one of<lb/>the many voices of Nature, heard only by the sen-<lb/>sitive and reverent ear of her true votaries.&#x2014;<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Aspects of Nature.</hi></p><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
