<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#b">The Junction of the Pacific and the At-<lb break="no"/>lantic Oceans.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Having for more than forty years been<lb break="yes"/>occupied with the subject of the means of<lb break="yes"/>communication between the two sens, I<lb break="yes"/>have constantly, both in my printed works<lb break="yes"/>and in the different memoirs which with<lb break="yes"/>honorable confidence the Free States of<lb break="yes"/>Spanish America have requested me to<lb break="yes"/>furnish, urged that the Isthmus should be<lb break="yes" />examined hypsometrically throughout its<lb break="yes"/>entire length, and more especially where,<lb break="yes"/>in Darien and the inhospitabl@ former<lb break="yes"/>Provincia de Biruquete, it joins the conti-<lb break="no"/>nent of South Amerien; and where, be-<lb break="no"/>tween the Atrato and the Bay of Cupica<lb break="yes"/>(on the shores of the Pacific,) the mountain<lb break="yes"/>chain of the Isthmus almost entirely dis-<lb break="no" />appenrs. Gen. Bolivar, at my request.<lb break="yes"/>caused an exact levelling of the Isthmus<lb break="yes"/>between Panama and the mouth of the Rio<lb break="yes"/>Chagres to be made in 1828 and 1829,<lb break="yes"/>by Lloyd und Falmare. (Philosophical<lb break="yes"/>Transactions of the Royal Society of Lon-<lb break="no"/>don, for the year 1830, p. 59-68.) Other<lb break="yes"/>measurements have since been executed<lb break="yes"/>by accomplished and experienced French<lb break="yes"/>engineers, and projects have been formed<lb break="yes"/>for canals and railways, with locks and<lb break="yes"/>tunnels, but always in the direction of a<lb break="yes" />meridian between Portobello and Panama<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;or more to the west, towards Chagres<lb break="yes"/>and Cruces. Thus the most important<lb break="yes"/>points of the eastern and south-eastern part<lb break="yes"/>of the Isthmus have remained unexamined<lb break="yes"/>on both shores! So long as this part is<lb break="yes"/>not examined geographically, by means of<lb break="yes"/>exact but easily obtained determinations of<lb break="yes" />latitude and longitude by chronometers, as<lb break="yes"/>well as hypsometrically in the conforma-<lb break="no"/>tion of the surface by barometric measure-<lb break="no"/>ments of elevation, so long I consider that<lb break="yes"/>the statements I have repeatedly made,<lb break="yes" />and which I now repeat in 1849, will still<lb break="yes"/>be true, viz: that it is as yet unproved and<lb break="yes"/>quite premature to pronounce that the<lb break="yes"/>Isthmus does not admit of the formation of<lb break="yes"/>an occanic canal (that is, a canal with<lb break="yes"/>fewer locks than the Caledonian Canal,)<lb break="yes"/>permitting at all seasons the passage of<lb break="yes"/>the same sea-going ships between New<lb break="yes" />York and Liverpool on the one hand, und<lb break="yes"/>Chili and California on the other.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On the Atlantic side (according to ex-<lb break="no"/>aminations which the Directors of the De-<lb break="no"/>posito Hidrografico of Madrid have en-<lb break="no"/>tered upon their maps since 1809), the<lb break="yes"/>Ensenada de Mandinga penetrates so<lb break="yes"/>deeply towards the South, that it appears<lb break="yes"/>to be only four or five German geographi-<lb break="no"/>cal miles, fifteen to an equatorial degree,<lb break="yes" />(that is, sixteen or twenty English geo-<lb break="no"/>graphical miles,) from the coast of the<lb break="yes"/>Pacific to the east of Panarna. On the<lb break="yes"/>Pacific side the Isthmus is almost equally<lb break="yes" />indented by the deep Golfo de San Miguel,<lb break="yes"/>into which the Rio Tuyra falls, with its<lb break="yes"/>tributary river the Chuchunque (Chu-<lb break="no"/>chunaque.) This last named stream in<lb break="yes"/>the upper part of its course approaches<lb break="yes"/>within sixteen English geographical miles<lb break="yes"/>of the Atlantic side of the Isthmus to the<lb break="yes"/>west of Cape Tiburon. For more than<lb break="yes"/>twenty years I have had inquiries made<lb break="yes"/>from me on the subject of the problem of<lb break="yes"/>the Isthmus of Panama, by associations<lb break="yes" />desirous of employing considerable pecu-<lb break="no"/>niary means; but the simple advice which<lb break="yes"/>I have given has never been followed.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Every scientifically educated engineer<lb break="yes"/>knows that between the tropics (even with-<lb break="no"/>out corresponding observations) good ba-<lb break="no"/>rometric measurements (the horary varia-<lb break="no"/>tions being taken into account) afford<lb break="yes"/>results which are assured to be less than<lb break="yes"/>from seventy to ninety French, or seventy-<lb break="no"/>five to ninety-six English feet. It would,<lb break="yes"/>besides, be easy to establish for a few<lb break="yes"/>months, on the two shores, two correspon-<lb break="no"/>ding barometric stations, and to compare<lb break="yes"/>repeatedly the portable instruments em-<lb break="no"/>ployed in preliminary levelling, with each<lb break="yes"/>other and those at the fixed stations. Let<lb break="yes"/>that part be particularly examined where,<lb break="yes"/>near the continent of South America, the<lb break="yes"/>separating mountain ridge sinks into hills.<lb break="yes"/>Seeing the importance of the subject to the<lb break="yes" />great commerce of the world, the research<lb break="yes"/>ought not, as hitherto, be restricted to a<lb break="yes"/>limited field.&#x2014;</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Aspect of Na-<lb break="no"/>ture.</hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 