<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="613" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><p><hi rendition="#k">Subterranean Golden Gardens</hi>.&#x2014;The son of<lb/>the Cacique Astorpilco, a pleasing and friendly youth<lb/>of seventeen, who accompanied me over the ruins of<lb/>the palace of his ancestor, while living in extreme po-<lb/>verty, had filled his imagination with images of buried<lb/>splendour and golden treasures hidden beneath the<lb/>masses of rubbish upon which we trod. He related to<lb/>me that one of his more immediate forefathers had<lb/>bound his wife&#x2019;s eyes, and then conducted her through<lb/>many labyrinths cut in the rock into the subterranean<lb/>garden of the Incas. There she saw, skilfully and<lb/>elaborately imitated, and formed of the purest gold,<lb/>artificial trees, with leaves and fruit, and birds sitting<lb/>on the branches; and there too was the much sought<lb/>for golden travelling chair (<hi rendition="#i">una de las andas</hi>) of Ata-<lb/>huallpa. The man commanded his wife not to touch<lb/>any of these enchanted riches, because the long foretold<lb/>period of the restoration of the empire had not yet<lb/>arrived, and that whoever should attempt before that<lb/>time to appropriate aught of them would die that very<lb/>night. These golden dreams and fancies of the youth<lb/>were founded on recollections and traditions of former<lb/>days. The artificial &#x201C;golden gardens&#x201D; (Jardines o<lb/>Huertas de oro) were often described by actual eye-<lb/>witnesses, Cieza de Leon<choice><sic></sic><corr type="editorial">,</corr></choice> Sarmiento, Garcilaso, and<lb/>other early historians of the conquest. They were<lb/>found beneath the temple of the sun at Cuzco, in<lb/>Caxamarca, and in the pleasant valley of Yucay, a fa-<lb/>vourite residence of the monarch&#x2019;s family. Where the<lb/>golden Huertas were now below ground, living plants<lb/>grew by the side of the artificial ones; among the latter,<lb/>tall plants and ears of maize (mazorcas) are mentioned<lb/>as particularly well executed. The morbid confidence<lb/>with which the young Astorpilco assured me that<lb/>below our feet, a little to the right of the spot on which<lb/>I stood at that moment, there was an artificial large-<lb/>flowered Datura tree (Guanto) formed of gold wire<lb/>and gold plates, which spread its branches over the<lb/>Inca&#x2019;s chair, impressed me deeply but painfully, for it<lb/>seemed as if these illusive and baseless visions were<lb/>cherished as consolations in present sufferings. I asked<lb/>the lad&#x2014;&#x201C;Since you and your parents believe so firmly<lb/>in the existence of this garden, are not you sometimes<lb/>tempted in your necessities to dig in search of trea-<lb/>sures so close at hand?&#x201D; The boy&#x2019;s answer was so sim-<lb/>ple, and expressed so fully the quiet resignation char-<lb/>acteristic of the aboriginal inhabitants of the country,<lb/>that I noted it in Spanish in my journal. &#x201C;Such a de-<lb/>sire (tal antojo) does not come to us; father says it<lb/>would be sinful (que fuese pecado). If we had the<lb/>golden branches with all their golden fruits our white<lb/>neighbours would hate and injure us. We have a small<lb/>field and good wheat (buen trigo).&#x201D; Few of my read-<lb/>ers, I think, will blame me for recalling here the words<lb/>of the young Astropilco and his golden visions.&#x2014;The<lb/>belief, so widely current among the natives, that to<lb/>take possession of buried treasures which belonged to<lb/>the Incas would be wrong, and would incur punish-<lb/>ment and bring misfortune on the entire race, is con-<lb/>nected with another belief which prevailed, especially<lb/>in the 16th and 17th centuries, i.e. the future restora-<lb/>tion of a kingdom of the Incas.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Aspects<lb/>of Nature</hi>.</p></div>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
