<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="62" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">The Northern Desert of Africa.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;Moun-<lb/>tains and forests resound with the thunder of the fall-<lb/>ing waters, with the roar of the tiger-like jaguar, and<lb/>with the melancholy rain, announcing howlings of<lb/>the bearded apes. In the midst of this grand and<lb/>savage nature live many tribes of men, isolated from<lb/>each other by the extraordinary diversity of their<lb/>languages: some are nomadic, wholly unacquainted<lb/>with agriculture, and using ants, gums, and earth as<lb/>food. These, as the Otomacs and Jarures, seem a<lb/>kind of outcasts from humanity: others, like the Mar-<lb/>quiritares and Macas, are settled, more intelligent and<lb/>of milder manners, and live on fruits which they<lb/>have themselves reared. Large spaces between the<lb/>Cassiquiare and the Atabapo are only inhabited by<lb/>the tapir and the social apes, and are wholly destitute<lb/>of human beings. Figures graven on the rocks show<lb/>that even these deserts were once the seat of some de-<lb/>gree of intellectual cultivation. They bear witness to<lb/>the changeful destinies of man, as de the unequally<lb/>developed flexible languages; which latter belong to<lb/>the oldest and most imperishable class of historic<lb/>memorials. But, as in the Steppe, tigers and croco-<lb/>diles fight with horses and cattle, so in the forests on<lb/>its borders, in the wildernesses of Guiana, man is ever<lb/>armed against man. Some tribes drink with unna-<lb/>tural thirst the blood of their enemies; others appa-<lb/>rently weaponless and yet prepared for murder, kill<lb/>with a poisoned thumb-nail. The weaker hordes,<lb/>when they have to pass along the sandy margin of<lb/>the rivers, carefully efface with their hands the traces<lb/>of their timid footsteps. Thus man, in the lowest stage<lb/>of almost animal rudeness, as well as amidst the ap-<lb/>parent brilliancy of our higher cultivation, prepares<lb/>for himself and his fellow men increased toil and<lb/>danger. The traveller wandering over the wide globe<lb/>by sea and land, as well as the historic inquirer,<lb/>searching the records of past ages, finds every where<lb/>the uniform and saddening spectacle of man at variance<lb/>with man. He, therefore, who, amidst the unrecon-<lb/>ciled discord of nations, seeks for intellectual calm,<lb/>gladly turns to contemplate the silent life of vegetation,<lb/>and the hidden activities of forces and powers operat-<lb/>ing in the sanctuaries of nature, or, obedient to the<lb/>inborn impulse which for thousands of years has<lb/>glowed in the human breast, gases upwards in medi-<lb/>tative contemplation on those celestial orbe, which are<lb/>ever pursuing, in undisturbed harmony, their ancient<lb/>and unchanging course.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s &#x201C;Cosmos.&#x201D;</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
