<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="183" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Nocturnal Life of Animals&#x2014;A Night on<lb/>
                    the Apure.</hi>&#x2014;Below the mission of Santa Barbara<lb/>
                    de Arichuna we passed the night as usual, in the open<lb/>
                    air, on a sandy flat, on the banks of the Apure, skirted<lb/>
                    by the impenetrable forest. We had some difficulty<lb/>
                    in finding dry wood to kindle the fires with which it<lb/>
                    is here customary to surround the bivouac, as a safe-<lb/>
                    guard against the attacks of the jaguar. The air was<lb/>
                    bland and soft, and the moon shone brightly. Several<lb/>
                    crocodiles approached the bank, and I have observed<lb/>
                    that fire attracts these creatures as it does our crabs<lb/>
                    and many other aquatic animals. The oars of our<lb/>
                    boats were fixed upright in the ground to support our<lb/>
                    hammocks. Deep stillness prevailed, only broken at<lb/>
                    intervals by the blowing of the fresh-water dolphins.<lb/>
                    After eleven o&#x2019;clock such a noise began in the con-<lb/>
                    tiguous forest, that for the remainder of the night all<lb/>
                    sleep was impossible. The wild cries of animals rang<lb/>
                    through the woods. Among the many voices which<lb/>
                    resounded together the Indians could only recognise<lb/>
                    those which, after short pauses, were heard singly.<lb/>
                    There was the monotonous plaintive cry of the aluates<lb/>
                    (howling monkeys), the whining, flute-like notes of<lb/>
                    the small sapajous, the grunting murmur of the striped<lb/>
                    nocturnal ape (<hi rendition="#i">Nyctipithecus trivirgatus,</hi> which I was<lb/>
                    the first to describe) the fitful roar of the great tiger,<lb/>
                    the cuguar or maneless American lion, the peccary, the<lb/>
                    sloth, and a host of parrots, perraquas (<hi rendition="#i">Ortalides</hi>),<lb/>
                    and other pheasant-like birds. Whenever the tigers<lb/>
                    approached the edge of the forest, our dog, who be-<lb/>
                    fore had barked incessantly, came howling to seek pro-<lb/>
                    tection under the hammocks. Sometimes the cry of a<lb/>
                    tiger resounded from the branches of a tree, and was<lb/>
                    then always accompanied by the plaintive piping tones<lb/>
                    of the apes, who were endeavouring to escape from<lb/>
                    the unwonted pursuit. If one asks the Indians why<lb/>
                    such a continuous noise is heard on certain nights, they<lb/>
                    answer, with a smile, that &#x201C;the animals are rejoicing<lb/>
                    in the beautiful moonlight, and celebrating the return<lb/>
                    of the full moon.&#x201D; To me, the scene appeared rather<lb/>
                    to be owing to an accidental, long-continued, and<lb/>
                    gradually-increasing conflict among the animals. Thus,<lb/>
                    for instance, the jaguar will pursue the peccaries and<lb/>
                    the tapirs, which, densely crowded together, burst<lb/>
                    through the barrier of tree-like shrubs which opposes<lb/>
                    their flight. Terrified at the confusion, the monkeys<lb/>
                    on the tops of the trees join their cries with those of<lb/>
                    the larger animals. This arouses the tribes of birds<lb/>
                    who build their nests in communities, and suddenly the<lb/>
                    whole animal world is in a state of commotion. Fur-<lb/>
                    ther experience taught us that it was by no means<lb/>
                    always the festival of moonlight that disturbed the<lb/>
                    stillness of the forest, for we observed that the voices<lb/>
                    were loudest during violent storms of rain, or when<lb/>
                    the thunder echoed and the lightning flashed through<lb/>
                    the depths of the woods. The good-natured Fran-<lb/>
                    ciscan monk who (notwithstanding the fever from<lb/>
                    which he had been suffering for many months) accom-<lb/>
                    panied us through the cataracts of Atures and May-<lb/>
                    pures to San Carlos, on the Rio Negro, and to the<lb/>
                    Brazilian coast, used to say, when apprehensive of a<lb/>
                    storm at night, &#x201C;May Heaven grant a quiet night<lb/>
                    both to us and to the wild beasts of the forest!&#x201D;&#x2014;<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i" >Humboldt&#x2019;s Views of Nature.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 