<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-11-30" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="4" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Junction of the Atlantic and<lb break="yes" />Pacific.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p>&#x2014; As the taking possession of a<lb break="yes"/>considerable part of the west coast of the<lb break="yes"/>new continent by the United States of<lb break="yes"/>North America, and the report of the abund-<lb break="no"/>ance of gold in California, have rendered<lb break="yes"/>more and more urgent than ever the form-<lb break="no"/>ation of a communication between the At-<lb break="no"/>lantic States and the regions of the west,<lb break="yes" />through the Isthmus of Panama, I feel it<lb break="yes"/>my duty to call the attention, once again, to<lb break="yes"/>the circumstance that the shortest way to<lb break="yes"/>the shores of the Pacific, which was shown<lb break="yes" />by the natives to Alonzo Martin de Benito,<lb break="yes"/>is in the eastern part of the isthmus, and<lb break="yes"/>led to the Golfo de San Miguel. We know<lb break="yes"/>that Columbus sought for an &#x201C;<choice>
                        <sic>estrecko</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">estrecho</corr>
                    </choice> de<lb break="yes"/>terra firme,&#x201D; and in the official documents<lb break="yes"/>of 1505 and 1507, and especially 1514,<lb break="yes"/>mention is made of the desired opening<lb break="yes"/>which should lead directly to &#x201C;the Indian<lb break="yes"/>Land of Spices.&#x201D; Having for more than<lb break="yes"/>40 years been occupied with the subject of<lb break="yes"/>the means of communication between the<lb break="yes"/>two seas, I have constantly urged that the<lb break="yes" />isthmus should be examined hypsometrically<lb break="yes"/>through its whole length, and more espe-<lb break="no"/>cially where in Darien, and the inhospitable<lb break="yes"/>former province de Birnquete, it joins the<lb break="yes"/>continent of South America, and where<lb break="yes"/>between the Atrato and Bay of Cupica (on<lb break="yes"/>the shore of the Pacific); the mountain chain<lb break="yes"/>of the isthmus almost entirely disappears.<lb break="yes"/>General Bolivar, at my request, caused the<lb break="yes" />exact <choice>
                        <sic>levelliug</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">levelling</corr>
                    </choice> of the isthmus, between Pa-<lb break="no"/>nama and the mouth of the Rio Chagres, to<lb break="yes"/>be made in 1828 and &#x2019;29, by Lloyd and<lb break="yes"/>Fulmare. Other measurements have been<lb break="yes"/>made by experienced French engineers, and<lb break="yes"/>projects have been formed for canals and<lb break="yes"/>railways, with locks and tunnels, but always<lb break="yes"/>in the direction of a meridian between Porto-<lb break="no" />bello and Panama; or more to the west,<lb break="yes"/>towards Chagres and Cruces. Thus the<lb break="yes"/>most important points of the eastern and<lb break="yes"/>south-eastern part of the isthmus have re-<lb break="no" />mained unexamined on both shores! So<lb break="yes"/>long as this part is not examined geogra-<lb break="no"/>phically by means of exact but easily ob-<lb break="no"/>tained determinations of latitude and longi-<lb break="no" />tude, by chronometers, as well as hypso-<lb break="no"/>metrically by barometric measurements of<lb break="yes"/>elevation, so long do I consider that the<lb break="yes"/>statement I have repeatedly made, and<lb break="yes" />which I now repeat in 1849, will still be<lb break="yes"/>true, viz., &#x201C;that it is yet unproved, and<lb break="yes"/>quite premature to pronounce that the<lb break="yes"/>isthmus does not admit of the formation of<lb break="yes"/>an oceanic canal (i. e., a canal with fewer<lb break="yes" />locks than the Caledonian Canal), permit-<lb break="no"/>ting, at all seasons, the passage of the same<lb break="yes"/>sea-going ships between New York and<lb break="yes"/>Liverpool, on the one hand, and Chili and<lb break="yes" />California on the other. On the Atlantic<lb break="yes"/>side the Eusenada de Mandinga penetrates<lb break="yes"/>so deeply to the south that it appears to be<lb break="yes"/>only 4 or 5 German geographical miles (16<lb break="yes" />or 20 English geographical miles) from the<lb break="yes"/>coast of the Pacific on the east of Panama.<lb break="yes"/>On the Pacific side, the isthmus is almost<lb break="yes"/>equally indented by the Golfo de San Mi-<lb break="no" />guel, into which the Rio Fuyra falls, with<lb break="yes"/>its tributary the Chuchunque<choice>
                        <sic/>
                        <corr type="editorial">.</corr>
                    </choice> The last-<lb break="no"/>named stream in the upper part of its course<lb break="yes"/>approaches within 16 English geographical<lb break="yes"/>miles of the Atlantic side of the isthmus<lb break="yes"/>west of Cape Tiburon. For more than 20<lb break="yes"/>years I have had inquiries made from me<lb break="yes"/>by associations desirous of employing con-<lb break="no"/>siderable pecuniary means, but my simple<lb break="yes"/>advice has never been followed. Every<lb break="yes"/>scientific engineer knows that between the<lb break="yes"/>tropics good barometric measurements afford<lb break="yes"/>results well assured to less than from seventy-<lb break="no" />five to ninety-five English feet. It would<lb break="yes"/>be easy to establish for a few months, on<lb break="yes"/>the two shores, two fixed corresponding<lb break="yes"/>barometric stations, and compare repeatedly<lb break="yes"/>the portable instruments for the preliminary<lb break="yes" />levelling, with each other, and with those<lb break="yes"/>at the stations. Let that part be particu-<lb break="no"/>larly examined where, near the continent of<lb break="yes"/>South America, the separating mountain<lb break="yes"/>ridge sinks into hills. Seeing the import-<lb break="no"/>ance of the object, the research ought not<lb break="yes"/>to be restricted to a limited field; a great<lb break="yes"/>and comprehensive work, which shall in-<lb break="no"/>clude the whole eastern part of the Isthmus,<lb break="yes"/>and be equally useful for canal as for rail-<lb break="no" />way, can alone decide the problem. That<lb break="yes"/>will be done at last, which should, and had<lb break="yes"/>my advice been taken, would have been<lb break="yes"/>done in the first instance.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i" >Humboldt&#x2019;s As-<lb break="no"/>pects of Nature, translated by Mrs. Sabine.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 