<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Junction of the Pacific and the Atlantic Oceans</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:13</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VI.114</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1849-Baron_Humboldt_on-4-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Baron_Humboldt_on-1-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Baron_Humboldt_on-2-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Baron_Humboldt_on-3-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Baron_Humboldt_on-4-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Baron_Humboldt_on-5-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Baron_Humboldt_on-6-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Baron_Humboldt_on-7-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Baron_Humboldt_on-8-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Baron_Humboldt_on-9-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Ansichten der Natur&lt;/i&gt;, Dritte verbesserte und vermehrte Ausgabe, 2 Bände, Stuttgart und Tübingen: Cotta 1849, Band 2, S. 389–392.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Junction of the Pacific and the Atlantic Oceans</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1850</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Morning Post&lt;/i&gt; 23814 (6. April 1850), S. 3.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="3" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Junction of the Pacific and the Atlantic<lb/>Oceans.</hi>&#x2014; Having for more than forty years been occupied<lb/>with the subject of the means of communication between<lb/>the two seas, I have constantly, both in my printed works<lb/>and memoirs, which, with honourable confidence, the Free<lb/>States of Spanish America have requested me to furnish,<lb/>urged that the isthmus should be examined hypsometri-<lb/>cally throughout its entire length, and more especially<lb/>where, in Darien and the inhospitable former Provincia de<lb/>Biruquete, it joins the continent of South America; and<lb/>where between the Atrato and the Bay of Cupica (on the<lb/>shore of the Pacific), the mountain chain of the isthmus<lb/>almost entirely disappears. General Bolivar, at my request,<lb/>caused an exact levelling of the isthmus between Panama<lb/>and the mouth of the Rio Chagres to be made in 1822,<lb/>and 1829, by Lloyd and Falmare. (Philosophical Transac-<lb/>tions of the Royal Society of London for the year 1839, p.<lb/>52-68). Other measurements have since been executed by<lb/>accomplished and experienced French engineers, and pro-<lb/>jects have been formed for canals and railways, with<lb/>locks and tunnels, but always in the direction of a meridian<lb/>between Portobello and Panama&#x2014;or more to the west<lb/>towards Chagres and Cruces. Thus the most important<lb/>points of the eastern and south-eastern part of the isthmus<lb/>have remained unexamined on both shores! So long as<lb/>this part is not examined geographically by means of exact<lb/>but easily obtained determinations of latitude and longitude<lb/>by chronometers, as well as hypsometrically in the confor-<lb/>mation of the surface by barometric measurements of eleva-<lb/>tion, so long I consider that the statement I have repeatedly<lb/>made, and which I now repeat in 1849, will still be true,<lb/>viz., that it is as yet unproved and quite premature to pro-<lb/>nounce that the isthmus does not admit of the formation of<lb/>an oceanic canal (that is, a canal with fewer locks than the<lb/>Caledonian Canal), permitting at all seasons the passage of<lb/>the same seagoing ships between New York and Liverpool<lb/>on the one hand, and Chili and California on the other.<lb/>On the Atlantic side (according to examination which the<lb/>directors of the Deposito Hydrographico of Madrid have<lb/>entered on their maps since 1849) the Ensenda de Man-<lb/>dinga penetrates so deeply towards the south that it appears<lb/>to be only four or five German geographical miles, fifteen to<lb/>an equatorial degree (that is, sixteen or twenty English<lb/>geographical miles) from the coast of the Pacific on the east<lb/>of Panama. On the Pacific side the isthmus is almost<lb/>equally indented by the deep Golfo de San Miguel, into which<lb/>the Rio Tuyra falls with its tributary river, the Chucunque<lb/>(Chuchunaque). The last named stream in the upper part of<lb/>its course approaches within sixteen English geographical<lb/>miles of the Atlantic side of the isthmus to the west of Cape<lb/>Tiburon. For more than twenty years I have had inquiries<lb/>made from me on the subject of the problem of the Isthmus<lb/>of Panama, by associations desirous of employing consider-<lb/>able pecuniary means; but the simple advice which I have<lb/>given has never been followed. Every scientifically educated<lb/>engineer knows that between the tropics (even without cor-<lb/>responding observations) good barometric measurement<lb/>(the horary variations being taken into account) afford re-<lb/>sults which are assured to be less than from seventy to<lb/>ninety French, or seventy-five to ninety six English feet. It<lb/>would, beside, be easy to establish for a few months, on the<lb/>two shores, two fixed corresponding barometric stations,<lb/>and to compare repeatedly the portable instruments em-<lb/>ployed in preliminary levelling with each other and with<lb/>those at the fixed stations. Let that part be particulary<lb/>examined where, near the continent of South America, the<lb/>separating mountain ridge sinks into hills. Seeing the<lb/>importance of the subject to the great commerce of the world,<lb/>the research ought not, as hitherto, to be restricted to a<lb/>limited field.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Aspect of Nature.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 