<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Nocturnal Life of Animals.&#x2014;A Night on the<lb break="yes"/>Apure.</hi>
                </head>
                <p>&#x2014;Below the mission of Santa Barbara de Arich@<lb break="yes"/>we passed the night as usual, in the open air, on a sandy flat,<lb break="yes"/>on the banks of the Apure, skirted by the impenetrable<lb break="yes"/>forest. We had some difficulty in finding dry wood to kindle<lb break="yes"/>the fires with which it is here customary to surround the<lb break="yes"/>bivouac, as a safeguard against the attacks of the jaguar.<lb break="yes"/>The @ir was bland and soft, and the moon shone brightly.<lb break="yes"/>Several crocodiles approached the bank, and I have observed<lb break="yes"/>that fire attracts these creatures as it does our crabs and<lb break="yes"/>many other aquatic animals. The oars of our boats were<lb break="yes"/>fixed upright in the ground to support our hammocks.<lb break="yes"/>Deep stillness prevailed, only broken at intervals by<lb break="yes"/>the blowing of the fresh-water dolphins. After eleven<lb break="yes"/>o&#x2019;clock, such a noise began in the contiguous forest, that<lb break="yes"/>for the remainder of the night all sleep was impossible. The<lb break="yes"/>wild cries of animals rung through the woods. Among the<lb break="yes"/>many voices which resounded together the Indians could only<lb break="yes"/>recognise those which, after short pauses, were heard singly.<lb break="yes"/>There was the monotonous plaintive cry of the aluates (howling<lb break="yes"/>monkeys), the whining, flute-like notes of the small sapajous,<lb break="yes"/>the grunting murmur of the striped nocturnal ape(<hi rendition="#i">Ny@-<lb break="no"/>cus trivirgatus,</hi> which I was the first to describe), the fi@ful<lb break="yes"/>roar of the great tiger, the cuguar or maneless American<lb break="yes"/>lion, the peccary, the sloth, and a host of parrots, perraquas<lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">Ortalides</hi>), and other pheasant-like birds. Whenever the<lb break="yes"/>tigers approached the edge of the forest, our dog, who before<lb break="yes"/>had barked incessantly, came howling to seek protection<lb break="yes"/>under the hammocks. Sometimes the cry of the tiger re-<lb break="no"/>sounded from the branches of a tree, and was then always<lb break="yes"/>accompanied by the plaintiff piping tones of the apes, wh@<lb break="yes"/>were endeavouring to escape from the unwonted pursuit.<lb break="yes"/>If one asks the Indians why such a continuous noise is<lb break="yes"/>heard on certain nights, they answer, with a smile, that &#x201C;the<lb break="yes"/>animals are rejoicing in the beautiful moonlight, and cele-<lb break="no"/>brating the return of the full moon.&#x201D; To me, the scene ap-<lb break="no"/>peared rather to be owing to an accidental, lon@<lb break="yes"/>continued, and gradually increasing conflict amo@<lb break="yes"/>the animals. Thus, for instance, the jaguar will purs@<lb break="yes"/>the peccaries and the tapirs, which, densely crowded<lb break="yes"/>together, burst through the barrier of tree-like shrub@<lb break="yes"/>which opposes their flight. Terrified at the confusion,<lb break="yes"/>the monkeys on the tops of the trees join their cries<lb break="yes"/>with those of the larger animals. This arouses the tribes of<lb break="yes"/>birds who build their nests in communities, and suddenly the<lb break="yes"/>whole animal world is in a state of commotion. Further<lb break="yes"/>experience taught us that it was by no means always the<lb break="yes"/>festival of moonlight that disturbed the stillness of the forest,<lb break="yes"/>for we observed that the voices were loudest during violent<lb break="yes"/>storms of rain, or when the thunder echoed and the light-<lb break="no"/>ning flashed through the depths of the woods. The good-<lb break="no"/>natured Franciscan monk who (notwithstanding the fever<lb break="yes"/>from which he had been suffering for many months) accom-<lb break="no"/>panied us through the cataracts of Ature@ and Maypur@ to<lb break="yes"/>San Carlos, on the Rio Negro, and to the Brazilian coast,<lb break="yes"/>used to say, when apprehensive of a storm at night, &#x201C;May<lb break="yes"/>Heaven grant a quiet night both to us and to the wild beasts<lb break="yes"/>of the forest!&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i" >Humboldt&#x2019;s Views of Nature.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 