<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-13" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001" />
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#i">The Subterranean Garden of the Incas in Quito.</hi>&#x2014;The<lb/>son of the Cacique Astorpilco, a pleasing and friendly youth<lb/>of seventeen, who accompanied me over the ruins of the<lb/>palace of his ancestor, while living in extreme poverty, had<lb/>filled his imagination with images of buried splendour and<lb/>golden treasures hidden beneath the masses of rubbish upon<lb/>which we trod. He related to me that one of his more imme-<lb/>diate forefathers had bound his wife&#x2019;s eyes, and then con-<lb/>ducted her through many labyrinths cut in the rock into the<lb/>subterranean garden of the Incas. There she saw, skilfully<lb/>and elaborately imitated, and formed of the purest gold, arti-<lb/>ficial trees, with leaves and fruit, and birds sitting on the<lb/>branches; and there, too, was the much sought-for golden<lb/>travelling chair (una de las andas) of Atahualpa. The man<lb/>commanded his wife not to touch any of these enchanted<lb/>riches, because the long-foretold period of the restoration of<lb/>the empire had not yet arrived, and that whoever should<lb/>attempt before that time to appropriate aught of them would<lb/>die that very night. These golden dreams and fancies of the<lb/>youth were founded on recollections and traditions of former<lb/>days. The artificial &#x201C;golden gardens&#x201D; (Jardines o Huertas<lb/>de oro) were often described by actual eye-witnesses, Cieza<lb/>de Leon Sarmiento, Garcilaso, and other early historians of<lb/>the conquest. They were found beneath the Temple of the<lb/>Sun at Cuzco, in Caxamarca, and in the pleasant valley of<lb/>Yucay, a favorite residence of the monarch&#x2019;s family. Where<lb/>the golden Huertas were not below ground, living plants<lb/>grew by the side of the artificial ones; among the latter tall<lb/>plants and ears of maize (mazoacas) are mentioned as parti-<lb/>cularly well executed. The morbid confidence with which<lb/>the young Astorpilco assured me that below our feet, a little<lb/>to the right of the spot on which I stood at the moment, there<lb/>was an artificial large-flowered datura tree (Guanto), formed<lb/>of gold wire and gold plates, which spread its branches over<lb/>the Inca&#x2019;s chair, impressed me deeply but painfully, for it<lb/>seemed as if these illusive and baseless visions were cherished<lb/>as consolations in present sufferings. I asked the lad,&#x201C;Since<lb/>you and your parents believe so firmly in the existence of this<lb/>garden, are not you sometimes tempted in your necessities to<lb/>dig in search of treasures so close at hand?&#x201D; The boy&#x2019;s<lb/>answer was so simple, and expressed so fully the quiet resig-<lb/>nation characteristic of the aboriginal inhabitants of the<lb/>country, that I noted it in Spanish in my journal. &#x201C;Such a<lb/>desire (tal antojo) does not come to us; father says it would<lb/>be sinful (que fuese pecado). If we had the golden branches<lb/>with all their golden fruits our white neighbours would hate<lb/>and injure us. We have a small field and good wheat (buen<lb/>trigo).&#x201D; Few of my readers, I think, will blame me for re-<lb/>calling the words of the young Astorpilco and his golden<lb/>visions.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Aspects of Nature.</hi>
            </p>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>