<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/111602781X">
                        <surname>Müller-Tamm</surname>
                        <forename>Jutta</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Stobl</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-10-25" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Humboldt, on the Junction of the Pacific and<lb/>
                the Atlantic Oceans.</hi>&#x2014;Having for more than<lb/>
                    forty years been occupied with the subject of<lb/>
                    the means of communication between the two<lb/>
                    seas, I have constantly, both in my printed works<lb/>
                    and in the different memoirs which with honor-<lb/>
                    able confidence the Free States of Spanish<lb/>
                    America have requested me to furnish, urged<lb/>
                    that the Isthmus should be examined hypsomet-<lb/>
                    rically throughout its entire length, and more<lb/>
                    especially where, in Darien and the inhospitable<lb/>
                    former Provincia de Biruquete, it joins the conti-<lb/>
                    nent of South America; and where, between the<lb/>
                    Atrato and the Bay of Cupica (on the shore of<lb/>
                    the Pacific,) the mountain chain of the Isthmus<lb/>
                    almost entirely disappears. Gen. Bolivar, at my<lb/>
                    request, caused an exact levelling of the Isth-<lb/>
                    mus between Panama and the mouth of the Rio<lb/>
                    Chagres to be made in 1828 and 1829, by Lloyd<lb/>
                    and Falmare. (Philosophical Transactions of<lb/>
                    the Royal Society of London, for the year 1830,<lb/>
                    p. 59-68.) Other measurements have since been<lb/>
                    executed by accomplished and experienced<lb/>
                    French engineers, and projects have been formed<lb/>
                    for canals and railways, with locks and tunnels,<lb/>
                    but always in the direction of a meridian between<lb/>
                    Portobello and Panama&#x2014;or more to the west,<lb/>
                    towards Chagres and Cruces. Thus the most<lb/>
                    important points of the eastern and south-eastern<lb/>
                    part of the Isthmus have remained unexamined<lb/>
                    on both shores! So long as this part is not ex-<lb/>
                    amined geographically, by means of exact but<lb/>
                    easily obtained determinations of latitude and<lb/>
                    longitude by chronometers, as well as hypsomet-<lb/>
                    rically in the conformation of the surface by ba-<lb/>
                    rometric measurements of elevation, so long I<lb/>
                    consider that the statement I have repeatedly<lb/>
                    made, and which I now repeat in 1849, will still<lb/>
                    be true, viz; that it is as yet unproved and quite<lb/>
                    premature to pronounce that the Isthmus does<lb/>
                    not admit of the formation of an oceanic canal<lb/>
                    (that is, a canal with fewer locks than the Cale-<lb/>
                    donian Canal,) permitting at all seasons the pas-<lb/>
                    sage of the same sea-going ships between New<lb/>
                    York and Liverpool on the one hand, and Chili<lb/>
                    and California on the other.</p>
                <p>On the Atlantic side (according to examina-<lb/>
                    tions which the Direction of the Deposito Hidro-<lb/>
                    grafico of Madrid have entered on their maps<lb/>
                    since 1809), the Ensenada de Mandinga penetrates<lb/>
                    so deeply towards the South, that it appears to be<lb/>
                    only four or five German geographical miles,<lb/>
                    fifteen to an equatorial degree, (that is, sixteen or<lb/>
                    twenty English geographical miles,) from the<lb/>
                    coast of the Pacific on the east of Panama. On<lb/>
                    the Pacific side the Isthmus is almost equally<lb/>
                    indented by the deep Golfo de San Miguel, into<lb/>
                    which the Rio Tuyra falls, with its tributary<lb/>
                    river the Chuchunque (Chuchunaque). This<lb/>
                    last named stream in the upper part of its course<lb/>
                    approaches within sixteen English geographical<lb/>
                    miles of the Atlantic side of the Isthmus to the<lb/>
                    west of Cape Tiburon. Vor more than twenty<lb/>
                    years I have had inquiries made from me on the<lb/>
                    subject of the problem of the Isthmus of Panama,<lb/>
                    by associations desirous of employing conside-<lb/>
                    rable pecuniary means; but the simple advice<lb/>
                    which I have given has never been followed.<lb/>
                    Every scientifically educated engineer knows that<lb/>
                    between the tropics (even without correspond-<lb/>
                    ing observations) good barometric measurements<lb/>
                    (the horary variations being taken into account)<lb/>
                    afford results which are assured to be less<lb/>
                    than from seventy to ninety French, or seventy-<lb/>
                    five to ninety-six English feet. It would, be-<lb/>
                    sides, be easy to establish for a few months, on the<lb/>
                    two shores, two corresponding barometric stations,<lb/>
                    and to compare repeatedly the portable instru-<lb/>
                    ments employed in preliminary levelling, with<lb/>
                    each other and with those at the fixed stations. Let<lb/>
                    that part be particulary examined where, near<lb/>
                    the continent of South America, the separating<lb/>
                    mountain ridge sinks into hills. Seeing the im-<lb/>
                    portance of the subject to the great commerce<lb/>
                    of the world, the research ought not, as hitherto,<lb/>
                    to be restricted to a limited field.<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#et">[<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Aspect of Nature.</hi></hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 