<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="3" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>A NIGHT ON THE BANKS OF A SOUTH AMERICAN<lb break="yes"/>RIVER.<lb break="yes" />(From Humboldt&#x2019;s &#x201C;Aspects of Nature.&#x201D;)</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Below the mission of Santa Barbara de Arichuna, we passed<lb break="yes"/>the
                    night, as usual, under the open sky, on a sandy flat on the<lb break="yes"/>bank
                    of the Rio Apure, closely bordered by the impenetrable<lb break="yes"/>forest.
                    It was not without difficulty that we succeeded in find-<lb break="no"/>ing dry
                    wood to kindle the fire with which it is always custom-<lb break="no"/>ary in
                    that country to surround a bivouac, in order to guard<lb break="yes"/>against
                    the attacks of the jaguar. The night was humid, mild,<lb break="yes"/>and
                    moonlight. Several crocodiles approached the shore. I<lb break="yes"/>think I
                    have observed these animals to be attracted by fire, like<lb break="yes"/>our
                    cray fish, and many other inhabitants of the water. The<lb break="yes"/>oars of
                    our boat were placed upright, and carefully driven into<lb break="yes"/>the
                    ground, to form poles from which our hammocks could be<lb break="yes"
                    />suspended. Deep stillness prevailed. Only from time to time<lb break="yes"/>we
                    heard the blowing of the fresh-water dolphins which are<lb break="yes"/>peculiar
                    to the Orinoco net-work of rivers (and, according to<lb break="yes"/>Colebrooke,
                    to the Ganges as far as Benares), which followed<lb break="yes"/>each other in
                    long lines. Soon after eleven o&#x2019;clock such a dis-<lb break="no"/>turbance
                    began to be heard in the adjoining forest, that for the<lb break="yes"
                    />remainder of the night all sleep was impossible. The wild cries<lb break="yes"
                    />of animals appeared to rage throughout the forest. Among the<lb break="yes"
                    />many voices which resounded together, the Indians could only<lb break="yes"
                    />recognise those which, after short pauses in the general uproar,<lb
                        break="yes"/>were first heard singly. There was the monotonous howling of<lb
                        break="yes"/>the aluates (the howling monkeys); the plaintive, soft, and
                        al-<lb break="no"/>most flute-like tones of the small sapajous; the snorting
                        grumb-<lb break="no"/>lings of the striped nocturnal monkey (the
                    Nyctipithicus trivir-<lb break="no"/>gatus, which I was the first to describe);
                    the interrupted cries<lb break="yes"/>of the great tiger, the cuguar or maneless
                    American lion, the<lb break="yes"/>peccary, the sloth, and a host of parrots, of
                    parraquas, and other<lb break="yes"/>pheasant-like birds. When the tigers came
                    near the edge of the<lb break="yes"/>forest, our dog, which had before barked
                    incessantly, came<lb break="yes"/>howling to seek refuge under our hammocks.
                        Sometimes<lb break="yes"/>the cry of the tiger was heard to proceed from
                    amidst the high<lb break="yes"/>branches of a tree, and was in such case always
                    accompanied by<lb break="yes"/>the plaintive piping of the monkeys, who were
                    seeking to escape<lb break="yes"/>from the unwonted pursuit. If one asks the
                    Indians why this<lb break="yes"/>incessant noise and disturbance arises on
                    particular nights, they<lb break="yes"/>answer, with a smile, that &#x201C;the
                    animals are rejoicing in the<lb break="yes"/>bright moonlight, and keeping the
                    feast of the full moon.&#x201D; To<lb break="yes"/>me it appeared that the scene
                    had probably originated in some<lb break="yes"/>accidental combat, and that
                    hence the disturbance had spread to<lb break="yes"/>other animals, and thus the
                    noise had increased more and more.<lb break="yes"/>The jaguar pursues the
                    peccaries and tapirs, and these pressing<lb break="yes"/>against each other in
                    their flight, break through the interwoven<lb break="yes"/>tree-like shrubs
                    which impede their escape; the apes on the<lb break="yes"/>tops of the trees,
                    being frightened by the crash, join their cries<lb break="yes"/>to those of the
                    larger animals; this arouses the tribes of birds,<lb break="yes"/>who build
                    their nests in communities, and thus the whole ani-<lb break="no"/>mal world
                    becomes in a state of commotion. Longer experi-<lb break="no"/>ence taught us
                    that it is by no meams always the celebration of<lb break="yes"/>the brightness
                    of the moon which disturbs the repose of the<lb break="yes"/>woods: we witnessed
                    the same occurrence repeatedly, and found<lb break="yes"/>that the voices were
                    loudest during violent falls of rain, or when,<lb break="yes"/>with loud peals
                    of thunder, the flashing lightning illuminated<lb break="yes"/>the deep recesses
                    of the forest. The good-natured Franciscan<lb break="yes"/>monk, who, although
                    he had been suffering for several months<lb break="yes"/>from fever, accompanied
                    us through the cataracts of Atures and<lb break="yes"/>Maypures to San Carlos on
                    the Rio Negro, and to the Brazilian<lb break="yes"/>boundary, used to say, when
                    fearful on the closing in of night<lb break="yes"/>that there might be a
                    thunderstorm, &#x201C;May heaven grant a<lb break="yes"/>quiet night both to us
                    and to the wild beasts of the forest.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 