<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Junction of the Pacific and the Atlantic<lb break="yes" />Oceans.</hi></head>
                <p>&#x2014;Having for more than forty years been oc-<lb break="no"/>cupied with the
                    subject of the means of communica-<lb break="no"/>tion between the two seas, I
                    have constantly, both in<lb break="yes"/>my printed works and memoirs, which,
                    with honourable<lb break="yes"/>confidence, the Free States of Spanish America
                        have<lb break="yes"/>requested me to furnish, urged that the isthmus<lb
                        break="yes"/>should be examined hypsometrically throughout its<lb
                        break="yes"/>entire length, and more especially where, in Darien<lb
                        break="yes"/>and the inhospitable former Provincia de Biruquete, it<lb
                        break="yes"/>joins the continent of South America; and where<lb break="yes"
                    />between the Atrato and the Bay of Cupica (on the<lb break="yes"/>shore of the
                    Pacific), the mountain chain of the isthmus<lb break="yes"/>almost entirely
                    disappears. General Bolivar, at my<lb break="yes"/>request, caused an exact
                    levelling of the isthmus be-<lb break="no"/>tween Panama and the mouth of the
                    Rio Chagres to<lb break="yes"/>be made in 1822, and 1829, by Lloyd and
                    <choice><sic>Falmarc</sic><corr type="editorial">Falmare</corr></choice>.<lb break="yes"/>(Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society
                        of<lb break="yes"/>London for the year 1839, p. 52-68). Other
                        measurements<lb break="yes"/>have since been executed by accomplished and
                        experi-<lb break="no"/>enced French engineers, and projects have been
                        formed<lb break="yes"/>for canals and railways, with locks and tunnels,
                        but<lb break="yes"/>always in the direction of a meridian between Porto-<lb
                        break="no"/>bello and Panama&#x2014;or more to the west towards Chagres<lb
                        break="yes"/>and Cruces. Thus the most important points of the<lb
                        break="yes"/>eastern and south-eastern part of the isthmus have<lb
                        break="yes"/>remained unexamined on both shores! So long as this<lb
                        break="yes"/>part is not examined geographically by means of exact<lb
                        break="yes"/>but easily obtained determinations of latitude and<lb
                        break="yes"/>longitude by chronometers, as well as hypsometrically<lb
                        break="yes"/>in the conformation of the surface by barometric<lb break="yes"
                    />measurements of elevation, so long I consider that the<lb break="yes"
                    />statement I have repeatedly made, and which I now<lb break="yes"/>repeat in
                    1849, will still be true, viz., that it is as yet<lb break="yes"/>unproved and
                    quite premature to pronounce that the<lb break="yes"/>isthmus does not admit of
                    the formation of an oceanic<lb break="yes"/>canal (that is, a canal with fewer
                    locks than the Cale-<lb break="no"/>donian canal), permitting at all seasons the
                    passage of<lb break="yes"/>the same seagoing ships between New York and
                                <choice><sic>Liver<lb break="yes"/>pool</sic><corr type="editorial"
                                >Liver-<lb break="no"/>pool</corr></choice> on the one hand, and
                    Chili and California on the<lb break="yes"/>other. On the Atlantic side
                    (according to examina-<lb break="no"/>tion which the directors of the Deposito
                        Hydrogra-<lb break="no"/>phico of Madrid have entered on their maps since<lb
                        break="yes"/><choice><sic>1849</sic><corr type="editorial"
                        >1809</corr></choice>) the Ensenda de Mandinga penetrates so deeply<lb
                        break="yes"/>towards the south that it appears to be only four or<lb
                        break="yes"/>five German geographical miles, 15 to an equatorial<lb
                        break="yes"/>degree (that is, 16 or 20 English geographical miles)<lb
                        break="yes"/>from the coast of the Pacific on the coast of<lb break="yes"
                    />Panama. On the Pacific side the isthmus is almost<lb break="yes"/>equally
                    indented by the deep Golfade San Miguel, into<lb break="yes"/>which the Rio
                    Tuyra falls with its tributary river,<lb break="yes"/>the Chucunque
                    (Chuchunaque). The last named<lb break="yes"/>stream in the upper part of its
                    course approaches<lb break="yes"/>within sixteen English geographical miles of
                        the<lb break="yes"/>Atlantic side of the isthmus in the west of Cape<lb
                        break="yes"/>Tiburon. For more than twenty years I have had<lb break="yes"
                    />inquiries made from me on the subject of the problem<lb break="yes"/>of the
                    Isthmus of Panama, by associations desirous of<lb break="yes"/>employing
                    considerable pecuniary means; but the<lb break="yes"/>simple advice which I have
                    given has never been fol-<lb break="no"/>lowed. Every scientifically educated
                    engineer knows<lb break="yes"/>that between the tropics (even without
                        corresponding<lb break="yes"/>observations) good barometic measurement (the
                        ho-<lb break="no"/>rary variations being taken into account) afford re-<lb
                        break="no"/>sults which are assured to be less than from 70<lb break="yes"
                    />to 90 French or 75 to 96 English feet. It would,<lb break="yes"/>beside, be
                    easy to establish for a few months, on<lb break="yes"/>the two shores, two fixed
                    corresponding barometric<lb break="yes"/>stations, and to compare repeatedly the
                    portable in-<lb break="no"/>struments employed in preliminary levelling with
                        each<lb break="yes"/>other and with those at the fixed stations. Let that<lb
                        break="yes"/>part be particularly examined where, near the conti-<lb
                        break="no"/>nent of South America, the separating mountain<lb break="yes"
                    />ridge sinks into hills. Seeing the importance of the<lb break="yes"/>subject
                    to the great commerce of the world, the re-<lb break="no"/>search ought not, as
                    hitherto, to be restricted to a<lb break="yes"/>limited field.&#x2014;<hi
                        rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Aspect of Nature.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 