<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Nocturnal life of animals in the primeval forest</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:13</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VI.118</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-17-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-17-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-21-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-22-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1849-Das_naechtliche_Leben-23-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Nocturnal life of animals in the primeval forest</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1851</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Monthly Packet of Evening Readings for Younger Members of the English Church&lt;/i&gt; 1:5 (Mai 1851), S. 360–365.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Schmuck: Kapitälchen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="360" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head>NOCTURNAL LIFE OF ANIMALS IN THE<lb/>PRIMEVAL FOREST.</head><lb/><p>&#x2018;<hi rendition="#k">If</hi> we comprehend in one general view the wooded region<lb/>which includes the whole of the interior of South America,<lb/>from the grassy steppes of Venezuela to the Pampas of<lb/>Buenos Ayres, or from 8° north to 19° south latitude, we<lb/>shall perceive that this connected forest of the tropical zone<lb/>has an extent unequalled in any other portion of the<lb/>earth&#x2019;s surface. Its area is about twelve times that of<lb/>Germany. Traversed in all directions by systems of<lb/>rivers, in which the minor and tributary streams exceed<lb/>our Rhine or our Danube in the abundance of their<lb/>waters, it owes the wonderful luxuriance of the growth<lb/>of its trees to the combined influence of great moisture<lb/>and high temperature.</p><lb/><p>&#x2018;The rivers, with their countless lateral arms, afford the<lb/>only routes by which the country can be traversed. Be-<lb/>tween the Orinoco, the Cassiquiare, and the Rio Negro,<lb/><pb n="361" facs="#f0002" />
astronomical observations, and, where these were want-<lb/>ing, determinations by compass of the directions of the<lb/>rivers, respectively showed us that two lonely mission<lb/>villages might be only a few miles apart, and yet that the<lb/>monks, when they wished to visit each other, could only<lb/>do so by spending a day and a half in following the wind-<lb/>ings of small streams, in canoes hollowed out of the<lb/>trunks of trees. A striking evidence of the impenetra-<lb/>bility of particular parts of the forest is afforded by a<lb/>trait related by an Indian, of the habits of the large<lb/>American tiger, or panther-like jaguar. These creatures<lb/>are often led, by their love of wandering and by their<lb/>rapacity, to lose themselves in such impenetrable parts of<lb/>the forest that they can no longer hunt along the ground,<lb/>and live instead in the trees, where they are the terror<lb/>of the families of monkeys and of the prehensile-tailed<lb/>viverra, the cercoleptes.</p><lb/><p>&#x2018;On leaving the Island del Diamante, in which Zambos,<lb/>who speak Spanish, cultivate sugar-canes, we entered on<lb/>scenes of nature characterized by wildness and grandeur.<lb/>The air was filled with countless flocks of flamingoes and<lb/>other water-birds, which appeared against the blue sky<lb/>like a dark cloud with continually varying outlines. The<lb/>river had here narrowed to between 900 and 1000 feet,<lb/>and, flowing in a perfectly straight line, formed a kind of<lb/>canal enclosed on either side by dense wood. The margin<lb/>of the forest presents at this part a singular appearance.<lb/>In front of the almost impenetrable wall of giant trunks of<lb/>C&#x00E6;salpinia, Cedrela, and Desmanthus, there rises from the<lb/>sandy river beach, with the greatest regularity, a low hedge<lb/>of sanso, only four feet high, consisting of a small shrub,<lb/>which forms a new genus of the family of Euphorbiace&#x00E6;.<lb/>Some slender thorny palms stand next; and the whole re-<lb/>sembles a close, well-pruned garden hedge, having only occa-<lb/>sional openings at considerable distances from each other,<lb/>which have doubtless been made by the larger four-footed<lb/><pb n="362" facs="#f0003" />
beasts of the forest to gain easy access to the river. One<lb/>sees, more especially in the early morning and at sunset, the<lb/>American tiger or jaguar, the tapir, and the peccary, lead<lb/>their young through these openings to the river to drink.<lb/>When startled by the passing canoe, they do not attempt<lb/>to regain the forest by breaking forcibly through the hedge<lb/>which has been described, but one has the pleasure of seeing<lb/>these wild animals stalk leisurely along, between the river<lb/>and the hedge, for four or five hundred paces, until they<lb/>have reached the nearest opening, when they disappear<lb/>through it. In the course of an almost uninterrupted<lb/>river navigation of 1520 geographical miles on the Ori-<lb/>noco to near its sources, on the Cassiquiare, and on the<lb/>Rio Negro&#x2014;and during which we were confined for<lb/>seventy-four days to a small canoe&#x2014;we enjoyed the repe-<lb/>tition of the same spectacle at several different points,<lb/>and, I may add, always with new delight. There came<lb/>down together, to drink, to bathe, or to fish, groups con-<lb/>sisting of the most different classes of animals, the larger<lb/>mammalia being associated with many coloured herons,<lb/>palamedeas, and proudly-stepping curassow and cashew<lb/>birds. &#x201C;Es como en el Paraiso,&#x201D; it is here as in Paradise<lb/>said, with a pious air, our steersman, an old Indian who<lb/>had been brought up in the house of an ecclesiastic. The<lb/>peace of the golden age was, however, far from prevailing<lb/>among the animals of this American paradise, which<lb/>carefully watched and avoided each other. The capybara,<lb/>a cang, three or four feet long, is devoured in the rivers<lb/>by the crocodiles, and on shore by the tiger. It runs so<lb/>indifferently, that we were several times able to catch<lb/>individuals from among the numerous herds which pre-<lb/>sented themselves.</p><lb/><p>&#x2018;Below the Mission of Santa Barbara de Wuchuna we<lb/>passed the night as usual, under the open sky, on a sandy<lb/>flat on the banks of the Rio Apure, closely bordered by<lb/>the impenetrable forest. It was not without difficulty<lb/><pb n="363" facs="#f0004" />
that we succeeded in finding dry wood to kindle the fire,<lb/>with which it is always customary in that country to sur-<lb/>round a bivouac, in order to guard against the attacks of<lb/>the jaguar. The night was humid, mild, and moonlight.<lb/>Several crocodiles approached the shore; I think I have<lb/>observed these animals to be attracted by fire, like our<lb/>cray-fish, and many other inhabitants of the water. The<lb/>oars of our boat were placed upright and carefully driven<lb/>into the ground, to form poles from which our hammocks<lb/>could be suspended. Deep stillness prevailed; only from<lb/>time to time we heard the blowing of the fresh-water<lb/>dolphins, which are peculiar to the Orinoco network of<lb/>rivers, which followed each other in long lines.</p><lb/><p>&#x2018;Soon after 11 o&#x2019;clock such a disturbance began to be<lb/>heard in the adjoining forest, that for the remainder of the<lb/>night all sleep was impossible. The wild cries of the<lb/>animals appeared to rage throughout the forest. Among<lb/>the many voices which resounded together, the Indians<lb/>could only recognise those which, after short pauses in<lb/>the general uproar, were first heard singly. There was<lb/>the monstrous howling of the aluates (the howling<lb/>monkey); the plaintive, soft, and almost flute-like tones<lb/>of the small sapajous; the snorting grumblings of the<lb/>striped nocturnal monkey; the interrupted cries of the<lb/>great tiger, the cuquar or maneless American lion, the<lb/>peccary, the sloth, and a host of parrots, of parraquas,<lb/>and other pheasant-like birds. When the tigers came<lb/>near the edge of the forest, our dog, which had before<lb/>barked incessantly, came howling to seek refuge under<lb/>our hammocks. Sometimes the cry of the tiger was<lb/>heard to proceed from amidst the high branches of a tree,<lb/>and was in such case always accompanied by the plaintive<lb/>piping of the monkeys, who were seeking to escape from<lb/>the unwonted pursuit.</p><lb/><p>&#x2018;If one asks the Indians why this incessant noise and<lb/>disturbance arises on particular nights, they answer, with<lb/><pb n="364" facs="#f0005" />
a smile, that &#x201C;the animals are rejoicing in the bright<lb/>moonlight, and keeping the feast of the full moon.&#x201D; To<lb/>me it appeared that the scene had probably originated in<lb/>some accidental combat, and that hence the disturbance<lb/>had spread to other animals, and thus the noise had<lb/>increased more and more. The jaguar pursues the pec-<lb/>caries and tapirs, and these, pressing against each other<lb/>in their flight, break through the interwoven tree-like<lb/>shrubs which impede their escape; the apes on the tops<lb/>of the trees, being frightened by the crash, join their<lb/>cries to those of the larger animals; this arouses the<lb/>tribes of birds, who build their nests in communities, and<lb/>thus the whole animal world becomes in a state of com-<lb/>motion. Longer experience taught us that it is by no<lb/>means always the celebration of the brightness of the<lb/>moon which disturbs the repose of the woods: we wit-<lb/>nessed the same occurrence repeatedly, and found that<lb/>the voices were loudest during violent falls of rain, or<lb/>when, with loud peals of thunder, the flashing lightning<lb/>illuminated the deep recesses of the forest. The good-<lb/>natured Franciscan Monk, who, although he had been<lb/>suffering several months from fever, accompanied us,<lb/>used to say, when fearful on the closing in of night that<lb/>there might be a thunder-storm, &#x201C;May heaven grant a<lb/>quiet night both to us and to the wild beasts of the<lb/>forest.&#x201D;&#x2019;</p><lb/><p>Scenes, such as those I have just described, were won-<lb/>derfully contrasted with the stillness which prevails within<lb/>the tropics during the noontide hours of a day of more<lb/>than usual heat. I borrow from the same journal the<lb/>recollections of a day at the Narrows of Baraguan:&#x2014;</p><lb/><p>&#x2018;On the naked rock which formed the shores, we saw<lb/>only, besides an old withered stem of aubletia, and a new<lb/>apocinea, a few silvery croton shrubs. A thermometer<lb/>rose to 122° Fahrenheit. All distant objects had wave-<lb/>like undulating outlines, the effect of mirage; not a breath<lb/><pb n="365" facs="#f0006" />
of air stirred the fine dust-like sand. The sun was in<lb/>the zenith, and the flood of light which he poured down<lb/>upon the river, and which, from a slight rippling move-<lb/>ment of the waters, flashed sparkling back, rendered still<lb/>more sensible the red haze which veiled the distance.<lb/>All the naked rocks and boulders around were covered<lb/>with a countless number of large thick-scaled iguanas,<lb/>gecko-lizards, and variously-spotted salamanders. Mo-<lb/>tionless, with uplifted heads and open mouths, they ap-<lb/>peared to inhale the burning air with ecstasy. At such<lb/>times the larger animals seek shelter in the recesses of<lb/>the forest, and the herds hide themselves under the thick<lb/>foliage of the trees, or in the clefts of the rocks; but if,<lb/>in this apparent entire stillness of nature, one listens for<lb/>the faintest tones which an attentive ear can seize, there<lb/>is perceived an all-pervading rustling sound, a humming<lb/>and fluttering of insects close to the ground, and in the<lb/>lowest strata of the atmosphere. Everything announces<lb/>a world of organic activity and life. In every bush, in<lb/>the cracked bark of the trees, in the earth undermined by<lb/>hymenopterous insects, life stirs audibly. It is, as it<lb/>were, one of the many voices of nature, heard only by<lb/>the sensitive and reverent ear of her true votaries.&#x2019;&#x2014;<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Aspects of Nature.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
