<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Extract of a Letter From Baron Alexander de Humboldt to Dr. T. G. Flugel, at Leipsic</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:14</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VII.5</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1850-Letter_from_Humboldt-2-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1850-Letter_from_Humboldt-1-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1850-Letter_from_Humboldt-2-neu.xml" type="self"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Extract of a Letter From Baron Alexander de Humboldt to Dr. T. G. Flugel, at Leipsic</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1850</date>
          <pubPlace>Washington, District of Columbia</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;Weekly National Intelligencer&lt;/i&gt; 470 (Juni 1850), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>EXTRACT OF A LETTER<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">From Baron</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Alexander de Humboldt</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">to</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Dr.<lb break="yes"/>T. G. Flugel,</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#i">at Leipsic.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>[<hi rendition="#k">translated from the serman.</hi>]</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <p>I hasten, my respected Doctor, to express to<lb break="yes"/>you my best thanks, in a few lines only, (being en-<lb break="no"/>gaged since yesterday in all the horrors of a remo-<lb break="no"/>val from Potsdam to Berlin,) for the very interest-<lb break="no"/>ing journey of <hi rendition="#k" >Emory,</hi> and for <hi rendition="#k">Gilliss&#x2019;s</hi> notices on<lb break="yes"/>the determination of the parallax in Chili and on<lb break="yes"/>the astronomical longitude of Washington. I had<lb break="yes"/>already written specially to New York for Emory&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>report.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>For an antediluvian like me, who is attached<lb break="yes"/>with his whole soul to the New Continent, through<lb break="yes"/>the color of his opinions and his knowledge of the<lb break="yes"/>beautiful country, *********<lb break="yes"/>it is refreshing and gratifying to follow the rapid<lb break="yes"/>and magnificent development of scientific spirit<lb break="yes"/>in the United States, and to have to acknowledge<lb break="yes"/>the participation of the Government in a three years&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>expedition to Chili, undertaken because a Professor<lb break="yes"/>in Marburg desires it, and nobody listens to him in<lb break="yes"/>Europe.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We are indebted for excellent labors in hypso-<lb break="no"/>metry, astronomy, botany, and geognosy, to <hi rendition="#k">Fre-<lb break="no" />mont, Emory, Wislizenus,</hi> Lieuts. <hi rendition="#k">Abert</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#k">Bache,</hi> of the fine coast survey, and to the circum-<lb break="no"/>navigation of <hi rendition="#k">Charles Wilkes.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>In my &#x201C;Aspects of Nature,&#x201D; vol. 11, pp. 388-392,<lb break="yes" />I have used <hi rendition="#i">earnest</hi> language on the possibility of an<lb break="yes"/>oceanic canal over the Isthmus of Panama. May<lb break="yes"/>those words at last find an echo in North America,<lb break="yes"/>and be diffused <hi rendition="#i">through the newspapers.</hi> They<lb break="yes"/>can be read in English in Mrs. Sabine&#x2019;s transla-<lb break="no"/>tion of Humboldt&#x2019;s &#x201C;Aspects of Nature,&#x201D; vol. 11,<lb break="yes"/>p. 319, &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Points in which the examination has<lb break="yes"/>been neglected.</hi>&#x201D; *********</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>With great respect, I am your most obedient,</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <closer>
                        <salute>
                            <hi rendition="#et">A. HUMBOLDT.</hi>
                        </salute>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <dateline>
                            <hi rendition="#k">Berlin, Dec.</hi> 22, 1849.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#k">from the &#x201C;aspects of nature,&#x201D; vol. 11, p.</hi> 319.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>As the taking possession of a considerable part of-the west<lb break="yes" />cosst of the New Continent by the United States of North<lb break="yes" />America, and the report of the abundance of gold in New<lb break="yes" />California, (now called Upper California,) have rendered<lb break="yes" />more urgent than ever the formation of a communication be-<lb break="no" />tween the Atlantic States and the regions of the West<lb break="yes" />through the Isthmus of Panama, I feel it my duty to call at-<lb break="no" />tention once again to the circumstance that the shortest way<lb break="yes"/>to the shores of the Pacific, which was shown by the natives<lb break="yes"/>to Alonso Martin de Don Berito, is in the eastern part of the<lb break="yes"/>Isthmus, and led to the Golfo de San Miguel. We know<lb break="yes"/>that Culumbus (Vida del Amirante por Don Fernando Colon,<lb break="yes"/>cap. 90) sought for an &#x201C;estrecho de tierra firm&#x00EB;;&#x201D; and in<lb break="yes"/>the official documents which we possess of the years 1505<lb break="yes"/>and 1507, and especially 1514, mention is made of the de-<lb break="no"/>sired &#x201C;opening&#x201D; (abertura) and of the pass (passo) which<lb break="yes"/>should lead directly to the &#x201C;Indian land of spices.&#x201D; Having<lb break="yes"/>for more than forty years been occupied with the subject of<lb break="yes"/>the means of communication between the two seas, I have<lb break="yes"/>constantly, both in my printed works and in the different<lb break="yes"/>memoirs which with honorable confidence the Free States of<lb break="yes"/>Spanish America have requested me to furnish, urged that the<lb break="yes"/>Isthmus should be examined hypsometrically throughout its<lb break="yes"/>entire length, and more especially where in Darien and in the<lb break="yes"/>inhospitable former Provincia de Biruguete, it joins the con-<lb break="no"/>tinent of South America, and where, between the Atrato and<lb break="yes"/>the Bay of Cupica, (on the shore of the Pacific,) the mountain<lb break="yes"/>chain of the Isthmus almost entirely disappears. (See in my<lb break="yes"/>Atlas geographique et physique de la Nouvelle Espagne,<lb break="yes"/>pl. <hi rendition="#k">iv.</hi>; in the Atlas de la Relation historique, pl. <hi rendition="#k">xxii</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#k">xxiii</hi>; Voyage aux Régions équinoniales du Nouveau<lb break="yes"/>Continent, T. <hi rendition="#k">iii,</hi> p. 117-154; and Essai politique sur le<lb break="yes"/>Ragaume de la Nouvelle Espagne, T. 1, 2d edit. 1825, p.<lb break="yes"/>202-248.)</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>General Bolivar, at my request, caused an exact levelling<lb break="yes"/>of the Isthmus between Panama and the mouth of the Rio<lb break="yes"/>Chagres to be made in 1828 and 1829, by Lloyd and Fal-<lb break="no"/>marc. (Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of Lon-<lb break="no"/>don for the year 1830, p. 59-68.) Other measurements have<lb break="yes"/>since been executed by accomplished and experienced French<lb break="yes" />engineers, and projects have been formed for canals and rail-<lb break="no"/>ways with locks and tunnels, but always in the direction of a<lb break="yes"/>meridian between Porto Bello and Panama, or more to the<lb break="yes"/>west, towards Chagres and Cruces. Thus the <hi rendition="#i">most impor-<lb break="no"/>tant</hi> points of the <hi rendition="#i">eastern</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">southeastern</hi> part of the Isthmus<lb break="yes"/>have remained unexamined on both shores! So long as this<lb break="yes"/>part is not examined geographically, by means of exact but<lb break="yes"/>easily attained determinations of latitude and longitude, by<lb break="yes"/>chronometers as well as hypsometrically, in the confirmation<lb break="yes"/>of the surface by barometric measurements of elevation; so<lb break="yes"/>long I consider that the statement I have repeatedly made, and<lb break="yes"/>which I now repeat in 1849, will still be true, viz: &#x201C;That it<lb break="yes"/>is as yet unproved and <hi rendition="#i">quite premature</hi> to pronounce that the<lb break="yes"/>Isthmus does not admit of the formation of an Oceanic Canal,<lb break="yes"/>(i. e. a canal with fewer locks than the Caledonian Canal,)<lb break="yes"/>permitting at all seasons the passage of the same sea-going<lb break="yes"/>ships between New York and Liverpool, on the one hand, and<lb break="yes"/>Chili and California on the other.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>On the Atlantic side (according to examinations which the<lb break="yes" />Direccion of the Deposito hidrogrefico of Madrid have enter-<lb break="no" />ed on their maps since 1809) the Ensenada de Mandinga<lb break="yes" />penetrated so deeply towards the south that it appears to be<lb break="yes"/>only four or five German geographical miles, fifteen to an<lb break="yes"/>equatorial degree, (i. e. 16 or 20 English geographical miles,)<lb break="yes"/>from the coast of the Pacific on the <hi rendition="#i">east</hi> of Panama. On<lb break="yes"/>the Pacific side the Isthmus is almost equally indented by<lb break="yes"/>the deep Golfo de San Miguel, into which the Rio Tuyra falls,<lb break="yes"/>with its tributary river the Chuchungue, (Churhurnague.)<lb break="yes"/>This last named stream, in the upper part of its course, ap-<lb break="no" />proaches within 16 English geographical miles of the Atlan-<lb break="no" />tic side of the Isthmus to the west of Cape Tiburon. For<lb break="yes" />more than twenty years I have had inquiries made from me<lb break="yes" />on the subject of the problem of the Isthmus of Panama, by<lb break="yes" />associations desirous of employing considerable pecuniary<lb break="yes" />means, but the simple advice which I have given has never<lb break="yes" />been followed. Every scientifically educated engineer knows<lb break="yes" />that between the tropics, (even without corresponding observa-<lb break="no"/>tions,) good barometric measurements (the horary variations<lb break="yes"/>being taken into account) afford results which are well as-<lb break="no"/>sured to be less than from 70 to 90 French or 75 to 96 Eng-<lb break="no"/>lish feet. It would besides be easy to establish for a few<lb break="yes"/>months on the two shores two fixed corresponding barometric<lb break="yes"/>stations, and to compare repeatedly the portable instruments<lb break="yes"/>employed in preliminary levelling with each other, and with<lb break="yes"/>those at the fixed stations. Let that part be particularly ex-<lb break="no"/>amined where, near the continent of South America, the<lb break="yes"/>separating mountain ridge sinks into hills. Seeing the im-<lb break="no"/>portance of the subject to the great commerce of the world,<lb break="yes"/>the research ought not, as hitherto, to be restricted to a limited<lb break="yes"/>field. A great and comprehensive work, which shall include the<lb break="yes"/>whole eastern part of the Isthmus, and which will be equally<lb break="yes"/>useful for every possible kind of operation, for canal or for<lb break="yes"/>railway, can alone decide the much-discussed problem either<lb break="yes" />affirmatively or negatively. That will be done at last, which<lb break="yes"/>should, and had my advice been taken, would have been done<lb break="yes"/>in the first instance.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 