<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#b">HUMBOLDT</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#k">and the</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#b">PEACE CONGRESS.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The Times, in publishing the subjoined<lb break="yes"/>letter of Humboldt to the Peace Congress<lb break="yes"/>of Frankfort, remarks:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Another voice has been added to those<lb break="yes"/>of the Frankfort peace-makers, and it is<lb break="yes"/>the voice of a great man. Indisposed to<lb break="yes"/>participate in the overt realities of the<lb break="yes" />platform, Baron Alexander Von Humboldt<lb break="yes"/>compounded, after a fashion not uncommon<lb break="yes"/>among ourselves, between approbation of a<lb break="yes"/>principle and dislike of a demonstration,<lb break="yes" />by despatching an epistle of adherence and<lb break="yes"/>sympathy to be read at the projected meet-<lb break="no"/>ing. Unfortunately the letter arrived too<lb break="yes"/>late to be put in evidence, but that the<lb break="yes" />moral might not be lost, it was forwarded<lb break="yes"/>to us for publication, and found in due<lb break="yes"/>course, a place in our columns of Satur-<lb break="no"/>day. The idealization of a subject in Ger-<lb break="no"/>man hands is apt to transcend the ordinary<lb break="yes" />comprehension of Englishmen, nor is the<lb break="yes"/>difficulty in any degree lessoned when the<lb break="yes"/>result is communicated through the imper-<lb break="no"/>feet medium of a translation. If, there-<lb break="no" />fore, the practical suggestions contained in<lb break="yes"/>the Baron&#x2019;s letter appear of less impor-<lb break="no"/>tance than might be expected, some allow-<lb break="no"/>ance must be made for the peculiar form of<lb break="yes"/>his contribution.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <opener>
                        <salute>
                            <hi rendition="#c">TO THE PRESIDENT AND MEMBERS OF THE<lb break="yes" />PEACE CONGRESS.</hi>
                        </salute>
                    </opener>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I regret so much the more that my per-<lb break="no"/>sonal position and advanced age, which<lb break="yes"/>warns me to complete what work I have<lb break="yes"/>commenced, should hinder me from assist-<lb break="no"/>ing at a meeting having so noble an aim in<lb break="yes"/>view, as it would have afforded me the gra-<lb break="no"/>tification of coming into close contact with<lb break="yes"/>so many men distinguished for talent and<lb break="yes"/>humanity. I have already verbally express-<lb break="no" />ed this regret a few weeks ago, when I had<lb break="yes"/>the pleasure to see Messrs. Henry Richard<lb break="yes"/>and Elihu Burritt and Visschers, and to<lb break="yes"/>converse with them on the probable influ-<lb break="no"/>ence which your Society may hope to exer-<lb break="no" />cise.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The general peace which our Continent<lb break="yes"/>has now so long enjoyed, and the praise-<lb break="no"/>worthy efforts of many governments, to<lb break="yes"/>avert the oft-threatening dangers of gene-<lb break="no"/>ral European war, proved that the ideas<lb break="yes" />which so prominently occupied your minds<lb break="yes"/>are in accordance with the sentiments call-<lb break="no"/>ed forth and diffused by the inereased cul-<lb break="no"/>ture of humanity. It is a useful enterprise<lb break="yes"/>to inspire such sentiments in the common-<lb break="no" />wealth by public conferences, and at the<lb break="yes"/>same time to point out some way through<lb break="yes"/>which wise and sincere governments may,<lb break="yes"/>by fostering the progressive and legitimate<lb break="yes"/>development and perfectibility of free in-<lb break="no"/>stitutions, weaken the long accumulated<lb break="yes" />elements of animosity.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>How much mildness of manners and an<lb break="yes"/>improved order in the organization of<lb break="yes"/>States have confined within narrower limits<lb break="yes"/>the wild outbursts of physical violence,<lb break="yes"/>may be seen by comparing the first and<lb break="yes" />middle ages with modern times. The whole<lb break="yes"/>history of the past shows that, under the<lb break="yes"/>protection of a superior power, a long<lb break="yes"/>nourished yearning after a nobler aim, in<lb break="yes"/>the life of nations, will at length find its<lb break="yes" />consumation. Has not a disgraceful legis-<lb break="no"/>lation conniving at&#x2014;yea encouraging, the<lb break="yes"/>infamous system of slavery and the traffic<lb break="yes"/>in human beings, at least on our continent<lb break="yes"/>and in the independent States of former<lb break="yes"/>Spanish America, yielded to the united ef-<lb break="no" />forts of the better part of mankind?</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We must not, then, relinquish the hope<lb break="yes"/>that a path will open by which all hostile<lb break="yes"/>divisions and contracting jealousies will<lb break="yes"/>gradually disappear. The whole history of<lb break="yes"/>the world teaches, to use the expression of<lb break="yes" />a statesman long departed, &#x201C;that the idea<lb break="yes"/>of humanity becomes in the course of cen-<lb break="no"/>turies even more visible, in a more enlarged<lb break="yes"/>acceptation, and proclaims its animating<lb break="yes"/>power.&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Inspired with these hopes and wishes,<lb break="yes"/>honored men, I beg to commend myself to<lb break="yes"/>your kind remembrance, &#x0026;c.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <closer>
                        <salute>
                            <hi rendition="#et">
                                <hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von Humboldt.</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </salute>
                    </closer>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <dateline>Potsdam, Aug. 20th.</dateline>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 