<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="2" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#c">BARON HUMBOLDT AND THE PEACE<lb/>CONGRESS.</hi></head>
                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> following letter from Baron Von Humboldt to the<lb/>Peace Congress at Frankfort, which did not arrive in time to<lb/>be read at the meeting, has now been forwarded to us by the<lb/>Committee for publication:&#x2014;</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">to the president and members of the peace<lb/>congress.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p>&#x201C;I regret so much the more that my personal position and ad-<lb/>vanced age, which warns me to complete what work I have com-<lb/>menced, should hinder me from assisting at a meeting having so<lb/>noble an aim in view, as it would have afforded me the gratifica-<lb/>tion of coming into close contact with so many men distinguished<lb/>for talent and humanity. I have already verbally expressed this<lb/>regret a few weeks ago, when I had the pleasure to see Messrs.<lb/>Henry Richard, and Elihu Burritt and Visscheres, and to converse<lb/>with them on the probable influence which your society may hope<lb/>to exercise.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;The general peace which our continent has now so long en-<lb/>joyed, and the praiseworthy efforts of many governments to avert<lb/>the oft-threatening dangers of a general European war, prove that<lb/>the ideas which so prominently occupy our minds are in accord-<lb/>ance with the sentiments called forth and diffused by the increased<lb/>culture of humanity. It is a useful enterprise to inspire such sen-<lb/>timents in the commonwealth by public conferences, and at the<lb/>same time to point out the way through which wise and sincere<lb/>governments may, by fostering the progressive and legitimate de-<lb/>velopment and perfectibility of free institutions, weaken the long-<lb/>accumulated elements of animosity.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;How much mildness of manners and an improved order in the<lb/>organization of States have confined within narrower limits the<lb/>wild outbursts of physical violence may be seen by comparing the<lb/>first middle ages with modern times. The whole history of the<lb/>past shows that, under the protection of a superior power, a long-<lb/>nourished yearning after a noble aim, in the life of nations, will at<lb/>length find its consummation. Has not a disgraceful legislation,<lb/>conniving at&#x2014;yes, encouraging the infamous system of slavery<lb/>and the traffic in human beings, at least on our continent, and in<lb/>the independent States of former Spanish America, yielded to the<lb/>united efforts of the better part of mankind?</p>
                <p>&#x201C;We must not, then, relinquish the hope that a path will open<lb/>by which all hostile divisions and contracting jealousies will gradu-<lb/>ally disappear. The whole history of the world teaches, to use<lb/>the expression of a statesman long departed, &#x2018;that the idea of<lb/>humanity becomes in the course of centuries ever more visible, in<lb/>a more enlarged acceptation, and proclaims its animating power.&#x2019;</p>
                <p>&#x201C;Inspired with these hopes and wishes, honoured men, I beg to<lb/>commend myself to your kind remembrance, &#x0026;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        (Signed) ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT.
                    </salute>
                </closer>
                <dateline><hi rendition="#i">Potsdam, August</hi> 20, 1850.</dateline>
            </div>
            <lb/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 