<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="71" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head>I.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">From Baron Von Humboldt.</hi></head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#c">To the President and Members of the Peace Congress.</hi></p><lb/><p>I regret so much the more, that my personal position and advanced age,<lb/>which warn me to complete what work I have commenced, should hinder<lb/>me from assisting at a meeting having so noble an aim in view, as it would<lb/>have afforded me the gratification of coming into closer contact with so<lb/>many men distinguished for talent and humanity. I have already verbally<lb/>expressed this regret a few weeks ago, when I had the pleasure to see<lb/>Messrs. Henry Richard, Elihu Burritt, and Visschers, and to converse with<lb/>them on the probable influence which your Society may hope to exercise.</p><lb/><p>The general Peace which our Continent has now so long enjoyed, and<lb/>the praiseworthy efforts of many Governments to avert the oft-threatening<lb/>dangers of a general European war, prove that the ideas which so promi-<lb/>nently occupy your minds are in accordance with the sentiments called<lb/>forth and diffused by the increased culture of humanity. It is a useful<lb/>enterprise to inspire such sentiments in the commonwealth by public con-<lb/>ferences, and, at the same time, to point out the way through which wise<lb/>and sincere Governments may, by fostering the progressive and legitimate<lb/>development and perfectibility of free institutions, weaken the long-accu-<lb/>mulated elements of animosity.</p><lb/><p>How much mildness of manners, and an improved order in the orga-<lb/>nisation of states, have confined within narrower limits the wild outbursts<lb/>of physical violence, may be seen by comparing the first middle ages with<lb/>modern times. The whole history of the past shows, that, under the<lb/>protection of a superior power, a long-nourished yearning after a noble<lb/>aim, in the life of nations, will at length find its consummation. Has not<lb/>a disgraceful legislation, conniving at, yea, even encouraging, the infamous<lb/>system of slavery, and the traffic in human beings, at least on our Continent,<lb/>and in the independent States of former Spanish America, yielded to the<lb/>united efforts of the better part of mankind?</p><lb/><p>We must not, then, relinquish the hope that a path will open, by which<lb/>all hostile divisions and contracting jealousies will gradually disappear.<lb/>The whole history of the world teaches, to use the expression of a states-<lb/>man long departed, &#x201C;that the idea of humanity becomes, in the course of<lb/>centuries, ever more visible, in a more enlarged acceptation, and proclaims<lb/>its animating power.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>Inspired with these hopes and wishes, honoured men, I beg to commend<lb/>myself to your kind
                    remembrance, &amp;c.</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#et">(Signed)</hi></p><closer><salute><hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von Humboldt.</hi></salute></closer><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#i">Potsdam,</hi> 20<hi rendition="#i">th August,</hi> 1850.</dateline></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
