<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="740" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>THE PEACE CONGRESS AT FRANKFORT.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following letters from eminent men, with the<lb break="yes"/>exception of the last, from Baron Humboldt, were<lb break="yes"/>read at the sittings of the Peace Congress at Frank-<lb break="no"/>fort, but were not included in our report of the<lb break="yes"/>proceedings. We have now great pleasure in pub-<lb break="no"/>lishing them <hi rendition="#i">in extenso:</hi>&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#et">Paris, August 21.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">To the President of the Congress of Peace at Frankfort.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Monsieur le President&#x2014;I beg to acknowledge the visit<lb break="yes"/>paid me by the delegates of the Peace Congress, assem-<lb break="no"/>bling at Frankfort. I have expressed to them my<lb break="yes"/>opinion on these solemn public meetings, and on the<lb break="yes"/>object which they propose to attain.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These gentlemen desired to have my thoughts on this<lb break="yes"/>subject in writing. I hasten, therefore, to express to<lb break="yes"/>you, as well as to them, this proof of my sympathies and<lb break="yes"/>my good will.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Myself, a man of peace, minister of a God who has<lb break="yes"/>said of himself that he was &#x201C;meek and lowly of heart,&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>I applaud these efforts of the friends of peace to esta-<lb break="no"/>blish concord on the earth, and to banish wars and divi-<lb break="no"/>sions. This is a grand object; an object essentially<lb break="yes"/>Christian. We cannot yet attain it, but there is a strong<lb break="yes"/>tendency towards its attainment. These public mani-<lb break="no"/>festations, expressed by these Congresses, prepare and<lb break="yes"/>form opinion, which is always the queen of the world.<lb break="yes"/>When public opinion shall be decidedly pronounced<lb break="yes"/>against violence and brute force, to terminate the dif-<lb break="no"/>ferences which arise among nations, their rulers will be<lb break="yes"/>obliged to consider among themselves what to do, and<lb break="yes"/>wars will become more and more rare.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But, above all, by the development of this Christian<lb break="yes"/>spirit among men of peace, when it shall be solidly es-<lb break="no"/>tablished on the earth, when humanity shall form only<lb break="yes"/>one family, when men shall look upon one another as<lb break="yes"/>brothers, when the Church shall have only faithful chil-<lb break="no"/>dren, and the passions be subdued, when feelings of sel-<lb break="no"/>fishness shall give place to those of justice and charity,<lb break="yes"/>then will peace descend to the earth; there shall be<lb break="yes"/>peace on earth and good-will among men.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We shall, in vain, Monsieur le Président, seek for<lb break="yes"/>combinations founded on reason and on material inte-<lb break="no"/>rests of men. They are impotent. It is the heart of the<lb break="yes"/>people which must be changed. This great and salutary<lb break="yes"/>revolution on the earth cannot be effected except by the<lb break="yes"/>aid of a fulcrum taken from heaven. May all the friends<lb break="yes"/>of peace, therefore, be, above all, the friends of Christi-<lb break="no"/>anity! Let them promote its operation on and among<lb break="yes"/>themselves. It is the sole means of real efficacy to at-<lb break="no"/>tain the end proposed, and which we are all engaged to<lb break="yes"/>promote.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>May God supremely bless our common efforts, and in-<lb break="no"/>cline the hearts of the people towards gentleness and<lb break="yes"/>love, which are, indeed, at the foundation of all<lb break="yes"/>religion.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Receive, Monsieur le Président, the assurance of my<lb break="yes"/>very distinguished and devoted sentiments.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#et">M. D. <hi rendition="#k">Auguste,</hi> Archbishop of Paris.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#et">Tronville-sur-Mer, August 19, 1850.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>My dear and honourable Friend,&#x2014;I regret very deeply<lb break="yes"/>that family reasons prevent my taking part with you in<lb break="yes"/>this new demonstration in favour of peace, and the union<lb break="yes"/>of the peoples.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>You know with what ardour of sentiment I partake<lb break="yes"/>all your convictions, and associate myself with all your<lb break="yes"/>ideas on this subject. The more the people are enlight-<lb break="no"/>ened, the more they comprehend political economy, the<lb break="yes"/>more will they learn to know the true nature of things,<lb break="yes"/>and the more they will be led cheerfully to obey the will<lb break="yes"/>of God, in loving one another.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We have yet much to do, and our pacific mission is<lb break="yes"/>far from being terminated, for the governments and the<lb break="yes"/>peoples appear, until now, quite sunk in the old ruts.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It was not without a feeling of shame, that I read the<lb break="yes"/>other day, in our official journal, the terms of a treaty of<lb break="yes"/>amity and commerce between France and the Republic<lb break="yes"/>of Guatemala. It is said in that treaty that the citizens<lb break="yes"/>of the two countries shall be freely admitted from one to<lb break="yes"/>the other; that, if they conform with the laws, they can<lb break="yes"/>freely reside in the one country or the other, enjoy their<lb break="yes"/>personal liberty, and carry on commerce, in wholesale<lb break="yes"/>or in retail!&#x2014;As if all things ought not, in our day, to<lb break="yes"/>be accorded to all men, and everywhere!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is really curious that, in the middle of the nine-<lb break="no"/>teenth century, the people who are called diplomatists<lb break="yes"/>succeed in persuading the nations that, without their in-<lb break="no"/>tervention, men would eat each other.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Tell our friends, I pray you, the mortification I feel at<lb break="yes"/>not finding myself among them. And receive, my dear<lb break="yes"/>and honourable friend, the fresh assurances of my entire<lb break="yes"/>devotedness. <hi rendition="#et">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Horace Say.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Richard Cobden, Esq.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#et">Paris, August 17, 1850.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mr. President,&#x2014;An affection of the throat, under<lb break="yes"/>which I am suffering, would not have sufficed to have<lb break="yes"/>kept me away from the Congress, because my part would<lb break="yes"/>have been rather to hear than to speak, if I had not<lb break="yes"/>submitted myself to a treatment which obliges me to<lb break="yes"/>remain at Paris. Penetrated with a sense of what is<lb break="yes"/>great and novel in this spectacle of men of all races and<lb break="yes"/>all languages, coming together from every point of the<lb break="yes"/>globe, to labour in common for the triumph of universal<lb break="yes"/>peace, it is with zeal, with enthusiasm, that I would<lb break="yes"/>have joined my efforts to yours in so holy a cause.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In truth, universal peace is considered by many as a<lb break="yes"/>chimera, and consequently the Congress, as an effort,<lb break="yes"/>honourable, indeed, but impracticable. This feeling<lb break="yes"/>reigns, perhaps, more in France than anywhere, because<lb break="yes"/>it is the country which has been most wearied with<lb break="yes"/>Utopianisms, and where ridicule is most dreaded. If I<lb break="yes"/>could have spoken to the Congress, I should have ad-<lb break="no"/>dressed myself to rectify this false appreciation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Without doubt, there has been a time when a congress<lb break="yes"/>of peace would have had no chance of success. When<lb break="yes"/>men made war to acquire booty, or territory, or slaves,<lb break="yes"/>it would have been difficult to have arrested them by<lb break="yes"/>moral or economical considerations. Even religion itself<lb break="yes"/>has failed. But to-day, two circumstances have alto-<lb break="no"/>gether changed the question.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The first is, that war has no interest to plead, as a<lb break="yes"/>cause, or even as a pretext, being always contrary to the<lb break="yes"/>true interest of the masses.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The second is, that it is no longer dependent on the<lb break="yes"/>caprice of a chief, but on public opinion. From the<lb break="yes"/>combination of these two circumstances, it follows that<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> war must become more and more rare, and finally dis-<lb break="no" />appear, by the mere force of events, even independently<lb break="yes"/>of all intervention of the Congress; for a fact which in-<lb break="no"/>jures the public, and is yet dependent on the public,<lb break="yes"/>must necessarily cease.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>What, then, is the work of the Congress? It is to<lb break="yes"/>hasten a conclusion already inevitable, in showing, to<lb break="yes"/>those who have not yet seen it, in what way, and to<lb break="yes"/>what extent, war and great armaments injure the gene-<lb break="no"/>ral interests. And is there anything Utopian in such a<lb break="yes"/>mission?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>During the last few years, the world has passed<lb break="yes"/>through circumstances which, certainly, at another<lb break="yes"/>epoch, would have produced long and cruel wars. Why<lb break="yes"/>have they been avoided? Because, if there be in Europe<lb break="yes"/>a war party, there are also the friends of peace. If there<lb break="yes"/>are men always ready to fight, whom a stupid education<lb break="yes"/>has imbued with antique ideas, and barbarous prejudices,<lb break="yes"/>which attach honour only to animal courage, and see no<lb break="yes"/>glory except in military achievements; there are, hap-<lb break="no"/>pily, other men at the same time more religious, more<lb break="yes"/>moral, more wise and provident calculators. Is it not<lb break="yes"/>very natural that the latter should endeavour to make<lb break="yes"/>proselytes among the former? How many times has<lb break="yes" />civilization, as in 1830, in 1840, in 1848, been suspended,<lb break="yes"/>so to speak, on this question, Who shall prevail, the<lb break="yes"/>party of war, or the party of peace? Hitherto the peace<lb break="yes"/>party has triumphed; and it must be acknowledged, not<lb break="yes"/>perhaps by its numbers or its ardour, but because it had<lb break="yes"/>the political influence. Thus peace and war are dependent<lb break="yes"/>upon opinion, and opinion is divided. And thus there<lb break="yes"/>is a danger always imminent. In these circumstances,<lb break="yes"/>does not the Congress undertake a work which is useful,<lb break="yes"/>sober, efficacious&#x2014;I will even dare to say, easy, when<lb break="yes"/>it strives to strengthen the pacific opinion, so as, in the<lb break="yes"/>end, to give it a decisive preponderance? What is there<lb break="yes"/>chimerical in this? If we had said to mankind, &#x201C;We<lb break="yes"/>come to summon you to trample your own interests<lb break="yes"/>under foot, to act henceforth on a mere principle of<lb break="yes"/>duty, of sacrifice, of self-denial,&#x201D; I fear, alas! that<lb break="yes"/>the enterprise would have been very doubtful.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But we come, on the contrary, to say to them, &#x201C;Con-<lb break="no"/>sult not only the interest of another life, but even of<lb break="yes"/>this. Examine the effects of war. See if they are not<lb break="yes"/>most disastrous. See if war, and great standing arma-<lb break="no"/>ments, do not produce interruption of labour, paralysis<lb break="yes"/>of industry, waste of resources, crushing debts, heavy<lb break="yes"/>taxation, financial impossibilities, discontents and revo-<lb break="no"/>lutions, without taking into account the deplorable<lb break="yes"/>moral habits they produce, and the culpable violation of<lb break="yes"/>the laws of religion.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>May we not be permitted to hope that this language<lb break="yes"/>will be listened to? Courage, then, men of faith and<lb break="yes"/>devotion! Courage and confidence! Those who can-<lb break="no"/>not, to-day, mingle with your ranks, follow you with<lb break="yes"/>their eyes and their hearts.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Receive, Mr. President, the assurance of my respect-<lb break="no"/>ful and devoted sentiments.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#et">
                        <hi rendition="#k">Frederic Bastiat.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following letter from Baron Von Humboldt to<lb break="yes"/>the Peace Congress at Frankfort did not arrive in<lb break="yes"/>time to be read at the meeting:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>
                        <hi rendition="#k">To the President and Members of the Peace<lb break="yes" />Congress.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I regret so much the more that my personal position<lb break="yes"/>and advanced age, which warns me to complete what<lb break="yes"/>work I have commenced, should hinder me from assist-<lb break="no"/>ing at a meeting having so noble an aim in view, as it<lb break="yes"/>would have afforded me the gratification of coming into<lb break="yes"/>close contact with so many men distinguished for talent<lb break="yes"/>and humanity. I have already verbally expressed this<lb break="yes"/>regret a few weeks ago, when I had the pleasure to see<lb break="yes"/>Messrs. Henry Richard, and Elihu Burritt and Viss-<lb break="no"/>chers, and to converse with them on the probable in-<lb break="no"/>fluence which your society may hope to exercise.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The general peace which our continent has now so<lb break="yes"/>long enjoyed, and the praiseworthy efforts of many<lb break="yes"/>governments to avert the oft-threatening dangers of a<lb break="yes"/>general European war, prove that the ideas which so<lb break="yes"/>prominently occupy your minds are in accordance with<lb break="yes"/>the sentiments called forth and diffused by the increased<lb break="yes"/>culture of humanity. It is a useful enterprise to inspire<lb break="yes"/>such sentiments in the commonwealth by public con-<lb break="no"/>ferences, and at the same time to point out the way<lb break="yes"/>through which wise and sincere governments may, by<lb break="yes"/>fostering the progressive and legitimate development<lb break="yes"/>and perfectibility of free institutions, weaken the long-<lb break="no"/>accumulated elements of animosity.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>How much mildness of manners and an improved<lb break="yes"/>order in the organization of states have confined within<lb break="yes"/>narrower limits the wild outbursts of physical violence<lb break="yes"/>may be seen by comparing the first middle ages with<lb break="yes"/>modern times. The whole history of the past shows<lb break="yes"/>that, under the protection of a superior Power, a long-<lb break="no"/>nourished yearning after a noble aim, in the life of<lb break="yes"/>nations, will at length find its consummation. Has not<lb break="yes"/>a disgraceful legislation, conniving at&#x2014;yea, encouraging<lb break="yes"/>the infamous system of slavery and the traffic in human<lb break="yes"/>beings, at least on our continent, and in the independent<lb break="yes"/>states of former Spanish America; yielded to the united<lb break="yes"/>efforts of the better part of mankind?</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We must not, then, relinquish the hope that a path<lb break="yes"/>will open by which all hostile divisions and contracting<lb break="yes"/>jealousies will gradually disappear. The whole history<lb break="yes"/>of the world teaches, to use the expression of a states-<lb break="no"/>man long-departed, &#x201C;that the idea of humanity becomes<lb break="yes"/>in the course of centuries ever more visible, in a more<lb break="yes" />enlarged acceptation, and proclaims its animating<lb break="yes" />power.&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Inspired with these hopes and wishes, honoured men,<lb break="yes"/>I beg to commend myself to your kind remembrance, &#x0026;c.:</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <closer>
                        <salute>
                            <hi rendition="#et">
                                <hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von Humboldt.</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </salute>
                    </closer>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <dateline>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Potsdam, August</hi> 20.</dateline>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 