<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.1" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision" >Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.1" when="2018-12-12" who="#wernicke_nd">Mark-up. <note type="remarkRevision" >Auszeichnungsfehler bereinigt.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-11-30" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision" >Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <p><hi rendition="#right">From the St. Louis Union, May 2.</hi></p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#b"><hi rendition="#c">Colonel Fremont.</hi></hi>
                </p>
                <lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">Col. Frémont, Man and Boy.&#x2014;The Early Promise,<lb/>
                    and the Ripe Performance.</hi></hi></p>
                <lb/>
                <p>There have come to our hands at the same time two no-<lb/>
                    tices of Colonel Frémont: one in relation to his early<lb/>
                    age and schoolboy days, the other in relation to his great<lb/>
                    explorations, and both honorable to him, and from per-<lb/>
                    sons whose testimony is most honorable&#x2014;his teacher<lb/>
                    and the Baron Humboldt. In the preface to a school<lb/>
                    edition of Xenophon&#x2019;s Anabasis for a Greek class, by Dr.<lb/>
                    Roberton, now of Philadelphia, there is an account<lb/>
                    of the young Frémont as he first appeared at the gram-<lb/>
                    mar school of the Doctor, at Charleston, (South Caro-<lb/>
                    lina,) and of his diligence, and progress, and moral de-<lb/>
                    portment, and early promise of distinguished life; which<lb/>
                    is given, as the preface states, as an example and en-<lb/>
                    couragement to all his scholars. The other is a letter<lb/>
                    from the great Baron Humboldt, and, besides expressing<lb/>
                    his own admiration of the labors of Frémont, communi-<lb/>
                    cates to him the grand golden medal of the King of<lb/>
                    Prussia for progress in the sciences, and makes known<lb/>
                    to him his election as an honorary member of the Geo-<lb/>
                    graphical Society at Berlin.</p>
                <p>The following is the notice of the old teacher:</p>
                <lb/>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <p>&#x201C;For your further encouragement, I will here relate a<lb/>
                            very remarkable instance of patient diligence and indom-<lb/>
                            itable perseverance.</p>
                        <p>&#x201C;In the year 1827, after I had returned to Charleston<lb/>
                            from Scotland, and my classes were going on, a very re-<lb/>
                            spectable lawyer came to my school&#x2014;I think some time<lb/>
                            in the month of October&#x2014;with a youth apparently about<lb/>
                            sixteen, or perhaps not so much, (14,) of middle size,<lb/>
                            graceful in manners, rather slender, but well formed, and,<lb/>
                            upon the whole, what I would call handsome; of a keen,<lb/>
                            piercing eye, and a noble forehead, seemingly the very<lb/>
                            seat of genius. The gentleman stated that he found him<lb/>
                            given to study; that he had been about three weeks<lb/>
                            learning the Latin rudiments, and (hoping, I suppose, to<lb/>
                            turn the youth&#x2019;s attention from the law to the ministry)<lb/>
                            had resolved to place him under my care for the purpose<lb/>
                            of learning Greek, Latin, and mathematics sufficient to<lb/>
                            enter Charleston College. I very gladly received him;<lb/>
                            for I immediately perceived he was no common youth, as<lb/>
                            intelligence beamed in his dark eye and shone brightly<lb/>
                            on his countenance, indicating great ability, and an as-<lb/>
                            surance of his future progress. I at once put him in the<lb/>
                            highest class, just beginning to read C&#x00E6;sar&#x2019;s Commenta-<lb/>
                            ries, and, although at first inferior, his prodigious mem-<lb/>
                            ory and enthusiastic application soon enabled him to<lb/>
                            surpass the best. He began Greek at the same time, and<lb/>
                            read with some who had been long at it, in which he also<lb/>
                            soon excelled. In short, in the space of one year he had<lb/>
                            with the class, and at odd hours with myself, read four<lb/>
                            books of C&#x00E6;sar, Cornelius Nepos, Sallust, six books<lb/>
                            of Virgil, nearly all Horace, and two books of Livy;<lb/>
                            and in Greek, all Gr&#x00E6;ca Minora, about the half of the<lb/>
                            first volume of Gr&#x00E6;ca Majora, and four books of Homer&#x2019;s<lb/>
                            Iliad. And whatever he read he retained. It seemed<lb/>
                            to me, in fact, as if he learned by mere intuition. I<lb/>
                            was myself utterly astonished, and at the same time de-<lb/>
                            lighted with his progress. I have hinted above that he<lb/>
                            was designed for the church; but when I contemplated<lb/>
                            his bold, fearless disposition, his powerful inventive ge-<lb/>
                            nius, his admiration of warlike exploits, and his love of<lb/>
                            heroic and adventurous deeds, I did not think it likely he<lb/>
                            would be a minister of the Gospel. He had not, how-<lb/>
                            ever, the least appearance of any vice whatever. On the<lb/>
                            contrary, he was always the very pattern of virtue and<lb/>
                            modesty. I could not help loving him, so much did he<lb/>
                            captivate me by his gentlemanly conduct and extraordi-<lb/>
                            nary progress. It was easy to see that he would one day<lb/>
                            raise himself to eminence. Whilst under my instruction,<lb/>
                            I discovered his early genius for poetic composition in the<lb/>
                            following manner: When the Greek class read the ac-<lb/>
                            count that Herodotus gives of the battle of Marathon,<lb/>
                            the bravery of Miltiades and his ten thousand Greeks<lb/>
                            raised his patriotic feelings to enthusiasm, and drew from<lb/>
                            him expressions which I thought were imbodied in a few<lb/>
                            days afterwards in some well-written verses in a Charles-<lb/>
                            ton paper, on that far-famed unequal but successful con-<lb/>
                            flict against tyranny and oppression; and, suspecting my<lb/>
                            talented scholar to be the author, I went to his desk and<lb/>
                            asked him if he did not write them, and, hesitating at<lb/>
                            first, he rather blushingly confessed he did. I then said,<lb/>
                            &#x2018;I knew you could do such things, and I suppose you<lb/>
                            have some such pieces by you, which I should like to see.<lb/>
                            Do bring them to me.&#x2019; He consented, and in a day or two<lb/>
                            brought me a number, which I read with pleasure and<lb/>
                            admiration at the strong marks of genius stamped on all,<lb/>
                            but here and there requiring, as I thought, a very slight<lb/>
                            amendment.</p>
                        <p>&#x201C;I had hired a mathematician to teach both him and my-<lb/>
                            self, (for I could not then teach that science,) and in this he<lb/>
                            also made such wonderful progress that at the end of one<lb/>
                            year he entered the junior class in Charleston College<lb/>
                            triumphantly, whilst others who had been studying four<lb/>
                            years and more were obliged to take the Sophomore<lb/>
                            class. About the end of the year 1828 I left Charleston,<lb/>
                            but I heard that he highly distinguished himself, and<lb/>
                            graduated in 1830. After that he taught mathematics for<lb/>
                            some time. His career afterwards has been one of heroic<lb/>
                            adventure, of hair-breadth escapes by flood and field, and<lb/>
                            of scientific explorations, which have made him world-<lb/>
                            wide renowned. In a letter I received from him very<lb/>
                            lately, he expresses his gratitude to me in the following<lb/>
                            words: <hi rendition="#i">&#x2018;I am very far from either forgetting you or<lb/>
                                neglecting you, or in any way losing the old regard I had<lb/>
                                for you. There is no time to which I go back with more<lb/>
                                pleasure than that spent with you, for there was no time<lb/>
                                so thoroughly well spent; and of anything I may have<lb/>
                                learned, I remember nothing so well and so distinctly as<lb/>
                                what I acquired with you.&#x2019;</hi> Here I cannot help saying<lb/>
                            that the merit was almost all his own. It is true that I<lb/>
                            encouraged and cheered him on; but if the soil into which<lb/>
                            I put the seeds of learning had not been of the richest<lb/>
                            quality, they never would have sprung up to a hundred-<lb/>
                            fold in the full year.</p>
                        <p>&#x201C;Such, my young friends, is but an imperfect sketch<lb/>
                            of my once beloved and favorite pupil, now a senator,<lb/>
                            and who may yet rise to be at the head of this great<lb/>
                            and growing republic. My prayer is, that he may<lb/>
                            ever be opposed to war, injustice, and oppression of<lb/>
                            every kind, a blessing to his country, and an example of<lb/>
                            every noble virtue to the whole world.&#x201D;</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>As many of our readers understand French, and might<lb/>
                    like to see the letters of the great Humboldt, the patriarch<lb/>
                    of science, and for fifty years at the head of the scientific<lb/>
                    world, and now in the eighty-second year of his age, we<lb/>
                    here give it in French, as copied from the original:</p>
                <lb/>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                            <p><hi rendition="#k">&#x201C;Monsieur le Senateur:</hi> Il m&#x2019;est bien doux, Mon-<lb/>
                                sieur, de vous adresser ces lignes par mon excellent ami,<lb/>
                                notre ministre aux Etats-Unis, M. de Gerolt. Après vou<lb/>
                                avoir donné dans la nouvelle édition de mes <hi rendition="#i">Tableaux de<lb/>
                                    la Nature</hi> le témoignage publique de l&#x2019;admiration qui est<lb/>
                                due à vos gigantesques travaux entre St. Louis du Mis-<lb/>
                                souri et les c&#x00F4;tes de la mer du Sud, je me sens heureux<lb/>
                                de vous offrir, dans ce petit signe de vie, l&#x2019;hommage de<lb/>
                                ma vive reconnaisance. Vous avez déployé un noble<lb/>
                                courage dans des expéditions lointaines, bravé tous les<lb/>
                                dangers des frimas et du manque de nouriture, enrichi<lb/>
                                toutes les parties de sciences naturelles, illustré un vaste<lb/>
                                pays qui nous était presque entièrement enconnu. Un<lb/>
                                mérite si rare a eté reconnu par un souverain, vivement<lb/>
                                interessé aux progrès de la géographie physique: le Roi<lb/>
                                m&#x2019;ordonne de vous offrir lagrande médaille d&#x2019;or, destinée<lb/>
                                à ceux qui ont travaillé à des progrès scientifiques.<lb/>
                                J&#x2019;éspère que cette marque de la bienveillance royale vous<lb/>
                                sera agréable dans un moment, ou sur la proposition de<lb/>
                                l&#x2019;illustre géographe Charles Ritter, la société de géographie<lb/>
                                résidant à Berlin vous a mommé pour membre hon-<lb/>
                                noraire. Quant à moi je dois vous remercier particulièr-<lb/>
                                ement aussi de l&#x2019;honneur que vous m&#x2019;avez fait d&#x2019;attacher<lb/>
                                mon nom et celui de mon collaborateur et ami intime M.<lb/>
                                Bonpland à des contrées voisines de celles qui ont été<lb/>
                                l&#x2019;objet de nos travaux. La Californie qui a <hi rendition="#i">noblement</hi><lb/>
                                résisté à l&#x2019;introduction de l&#x2019;esclavage sera dignement rep-<lb/>
                                résentée par un ami de la liberté et des progrès de l&#x2019;in-<lb/>
                                telligence.</p>
                            <p>&#x201C;Agreez, je vous prie, Monsieur le Sénateur, l&#x2019;ex-<lb/>
                                pression de ma haute et affectueuse consideration.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <salute>
                                    <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Votre t. h. et t. o. serviteur,</hi><lb/>
                                        <hi rendition="#right">&#x201C;A. V. HUMBOLDT.</hi>
                                </salute>
                                <dateline>&#x201C;A <hi rendition="#k">Sans Souci</hi>, le 7 Octobre 1850.&#x201D;</dateline>
                            </closer>
                            <lb/>
                            <closer>On the envelope thus addressed:<lb/>
                                <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;A Monsieur,<lb/>
                                    &#x201C;Monsieur le Colonel Frémont, Senateur.<lb/>
                                    &#x201C;Avec la grade médaille d&#x2019;or<lb/>
                                    &#x201C;Pour les progrès dans les sciences.<lb/>
                                    &#x201C;Baron HUMBOLDT.&#x201D;</hi>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <lb/>
                <p>The following is the English translation of Baron<lb/>
                    Humboldt&#x2019;s letter:<lb/>
                    &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">To Col. Fremont, Senator:</hi>
                </p>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                            <p>&#x201C;It is very agreeable to me, sir, to address you these<lb/>
                                lines by my excellent friend, our Minister to the United<lb/>
                                States, Mr. de Gerolt. After having given you in the<lb/>
                                new edition of my &#x2018;Aspects of Nature,&#x2019; the public testi-<lb/>
                                mony of the admiration which is due to your gigantic<lb/>
                                labors between St. Louis, of Missouri, and the coasts of<lb/>
                                the South Sea, I feel happy to offer you, in this living<lb/>
                                token, (dans ce petit signe de vie,) the homage of my<lb/>
                                warm acknowledgment. You have displayed a noble<lb/>
                                courage in distant expeditions, braved all the dangers of<lb/>
                                cold and famine, enriched all the branches of the natural<lb/>
                                sciences, illustrated a vast country which was almost en-<lb/>
                                tirely unknown to us. A merit so rare has been ac-<lb/>
                                knowledged by a sovereign warmly interested in the pro-<lb/>
                                gress of physical geography; the King orders me to offer<lb/>
                                you the grand golden medal destined to those who have<lb/>
                                labored at scientific progress. I hope that this mark of<lb/>
                                the royal good-will will be agreeable to you at a time<lb/>
                                when, upon the proposition of the illustrious geographer,<lb/>
                                (Chas. Ritter,) the Geographical Society at Berlin has<lb/>
                                named you an honorary member. For myself, I must<lb/>
                                thank you particularly, also, for the honor which you<lb/>
                                have done in attaching my name and that of my fellow-<lb/>
                                laborer and intimate friend, Mr. Bonpland, to countries<lb/>
                                neighboring to those which have been the object of our<lb/>
                                labors. California, which has so nobly resisted the in-<cb/>
                                troduction of slavery, will be worthily represented by a<lb/>
                                friend of liberty and of the progress of intelligence.</p>
                            <p>&#x201C;Accept, I pray you, sir, the expression of my high<lb/>and affectionate consideration.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <salute>
                                    <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Your most humble and most obedient servant,</hi><lb/>
                                        <hi rendition="#right">&#x201C;A. V. HUMBOLDT.</hi>
                                </salute>
                                <dateline>
                                    &#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Sans Souci</hi>, October 7, 1850.&#x201D;
                                </dateline>
                            </closer>
                            <lb/>
                            <closer>On the envelope thus addressed:<lb/>
                                <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;To Colonel Frémont, Senator.<lb/>
                                    &#x201C;With the great Golden Medal<note place="foot" n="*">The following is the description of the medal: Of fine<lb/>gold, massive, more than double the size of the American<lb/>double eagle, and of exquisite workmanship. On the face<lb/>is the medallion head of the King, Frederick William the<lb/>Fourth, surrounded by figures emblematical of Religion,<lb/>Jurisprudence, Medicine, and the Arts. On the reverse,<lb/>Apollo, in the chariot of the sun, drawn by four high-<lb/>mettled plunging horses, traversing the zodiac, and darting<lb/>rays of light from his head.</note>
                                    <lb/>&#x201C;For progress in the sciences.<lb/>
                                    &#x201C;Baron HUMBOLDT.&#x201D;</hi>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <lb/>
                <p>The following is the public testimony of the Baron&#x2019;s<lb/>
                    admiration of the gigantic labors of Frémont, referred to<lb/>
                    in the letter, as contained in the new or third edition of<lb/>
                    his Aspects of Nature, and which, as a reference, be-<lb/>
                    comes a natural appendant to the letter:</p>
                <p>&#x201C;Fremont&#x2019;s map and geographical investigations com-<lb/>
                    prehend the extensive region from the junction of the<lb/>
                    Kanzas river with the Missouri to the falls of the Co-<lb/>
                    lumbia, and to the missions of Santa Barbara and Puebla<lb/>
                    de los Angeles, in New California, or a space of 28 de-<lb/>
                    grees of longitude, and from the 34th to the 45th parallel<lb/>
                    of latitude. Four hundred points have been determined<lb/>
                    hyposometrically by barometric observations, and, for<lb/>
                    the most part, geographically by astronomical observa-<lb/>
                    tions; so that a district which, with the windings of the<lb/>
                    route, amounts to 3,600 geographical miles from the<lb/>
                    mouth of the Kanzas to Fort Vancouver and the shores<lb/>
                    of the Pacific, (almost 720 miles more than the distance<lb/>
                    from Madrid to Tobolsk,) has been represented in profile,<lb/>
                    showing the relative heights above the level of the sea.<lb/>
                    As I was, I believe, the first person who undertook to rep-<lb/>
                    resent, in geognostic profile, the form of entire countries&#x2014;<lb/>
                    such as the Iberian peninsula, the high lands of Mexico,<lb/>
                    and the Cordilleras of South America, (the semi-perspec-<lb/>
                    tive projections of a Siberian traveller, the Abbe<lb/>
                    Chappe, were founded on mere and generally ill-judged<lb/>
                    estimations of the fall of rivers)&#x2014;it has given me pecu-<lb/>
                    liar pleasure to see the geographical method of represent-<lb/>
                    ing the form of the earth in a vertical direction, or the<lb/>
                    elevations of the solid portion of our planet above its<lb/>
                    watery covering, applied on so grand a scale as has been<lb/>
                    done in Frémont&#x2019;s map.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 