<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-01-05" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>An Interview with Humboldt&#x2015;His Letter to<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Heine.<lb break="yes"/>Mr. <hi rendition="#k">Heine</hi>, a talented German artist, who has<lb break="yes"/>been for some time residing in this city, is about<lb break="yes"/>to accompany Mr. <hi rendition="#k">E. G. Squier</hi> on his scientific<lb break="yes"/>exploration of the antiquities of Central Ameri-<lb break="no"/>ca. In order that he might overlook no advantage<lb break="yes"/>to be derived from such a journey, he recently<lb break="yes"/>wrote to his father, in Berlin, enclosing a <choice><sic>letter</sic><corr type="editorial">letter to</corr></choice><lb break="yes"/>Humboldt, in which he asked of that philosopher<lb break="yes"/><choice><sic>to some</sic><corr type="editorial">some</corr></choice> information in regard to the subjects<lb break="yes"/>most worthy of notice, to be met with in his pro-<lb break="no" />jected tour. Mr. Heine has kindly furnished us<lb break="yes"/>with an extract from his father&#x2019;s letter, describing<lb break="yes"/>his interview with Humboldt, together with a<lb break="yes"/>copy of Humboldt&#x2019;s letter to himself. We trans-<lb break="no"/>late from the former the following passages,<lb break="yes"/>which contain an interesting description of the<lb break="yes" />Nestor of scientific men.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;I found this great philosopher the most amia-<lb break="no"/>ble old man whom I have ever met&#x2015;in one word,<lb break="yes"/>the friend of Man, as of Nature. The mild, clear<lb break="yes"/>eye, the friendly features surrounded with a halo<lb break="yes"/>of silver hair, made a powerful impression on me,<lb break="yes" />and I cannot now decide whether reverence or an<lb break="yes"/>instant affection for him, was the prevailing feel-<lb break="no"/>ing in my mind. He speaks very fast, yet dis-<lb break="no"/>tinctly; his voice is soft and winning, and his<lb break="yes"/>slightly bent stature scarcely betrays the veteran<lb break="yes" />of 81 years. He invited me to sit with your<lb break="yes"/>mother on the sofa, and drew a cane chair famil-<lb break="no"/>iarly toward me. In answer to a movement of<lb break="yes"/>mine he said he &#x201C;never sat on sofas.&#x201D; I will en-<lb break="no"/>deavor to recall his own words, as near as possi-<lb break="no"/>ble:</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;&#x2018;Pray do not interrupt me, for my time is<lb break="yes"/>very limited; only answer me. Your son has<lb break="yes"/>written me a charming letter, which has given<lb break="yes"/>me great pleasure and fully informs me about his<lb break="yes"/>plans. I know Mr. Squier and am already ac-<lb break="no"/>quainted with his undertaking. I have also<lb break="yes"/>spoken to the King about it, and he is pleased<lb break="yes"/>that a young German artist will be Mr. Squier&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>companion. The King has much respect for Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Squier; but was at first a little astounded con-<lb break="no" />cerning his reports of the monstrous dimensions<lb break="yes"/>of the ancient American monuments. It is<lb break="yes"/>therefore agreeable to His Majesty to find those<lb break="yes"/>reports so thoroughly confirmed, and he takes no<lb break="yes"/>less interest in the undertaking, than myself.<lb break="yes"/>You cannot think how keenly everything inter-<lb break="no"/>ests me, which is going on in the great distance,<lb break="yes"/>to discover for us new truths and beauties,&#x2019;&#x2015;and<lb break="yes"/>here Humboldt&#x2019;s clear eyes said plainly that he<lb break="yes"/>would willingly be young again, to do as he has<lb break="yes"/>done, as if he did not already wear enough of<lb break="yes" />well earned hours. I wish I could better des-<lb break="no"/>cribe his dignified and yet unpretending expres-<lb break="no"/>sion, which impressed me strongly with the pre-<lb break="no"/>sence of a great man. &#x2018;The highest degree of<lb break="yes"/>perfection which Man can reach,&#x2019; said he, &#x2018;is<lb break="yes"/>the knowledge of what still remains for him<lb break="yes"/>to achieve. I have arranged for your son,&#x2019; he<lb break="yes"/>continued, &#x2018;what I wish him to do for me. But<lb break="yes"/>wait a moment, I must write something more.&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>With that he went into an adjoining room, and<lb break="yes"/>soon returned with two volumes, smiling as he<lb break="yes"/>said: &#x2018;If I want to write well, I must write very<lb break="yes"/>slowly&#x2015;yes yes, these 81 years!&#x2019;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;I asked whether he desired I should give him<lb break="yes"/>further details, when I should again hear from<lb break="yes"/>you. &#x2018;It will give me pleasure,&#x2019; he answered,<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;to hear them from your own lips, but don&#x2019;t<lb break="yes"/>write, for then I should very likely hear nothing.<lb break="yes"/>I receive 5,000 letters a year; how should I read<lb break="yes"/>them all? Many must necessarily lie unread,<lb break="yes"/>though this troubles me. You cannot think how<lb break="yes"/>many claims are made upon me, all of which I<lb break="yes"/>am expected to answer. See, here are notes<lb break="yes"/>which I got up at 5 o&#x2019;clock this morning to write.<lb break="yes"/>This very day I was obliged to pay a large amount<lb break="yes" />of postage, and for what? A piece of embroidery,<lb break="yes"/>which I was expected to set up as a lottery for a<lb break="yes"/>charitable purpose. Now the design of this is<lb break="yes"/>praiseworthy, and therefore one most do the fa-<lb break="no"/>vor&#x2015;But I shall keep my promise and send to-<lb break="no" />morrow a friendly letter to your son. I most<lb break="yes"/>heartily wish him a fortunate result in whatever<lb break="yes"/>he undertakes.&#x2019; I reminded him of your promise<lb break="yes"/>concerning the palm-blossoms, &#x2018;Ah,&#x2019; said he,<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;how can I describe them more minutely? If I<lb break="yes"/>could go myself, I would be better able to do it,&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>and again the longing for new activity and new<lb break="yes" />discovery shone in his eyes. I then left him; but<lb break="yes"/>the half hour I spent in his company will always<lb break="yes"/>remain one of the most delightful reminiscences<lb break="yes"/>of my life.&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>We also translate the following letter from<lb break="yes"/>
                <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi> to Mr. Heine:</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C; At a season when I am unusually active and<lb break="yes"/>preoccupied, my dear Herr Heine, I can only<lb break="yes"/>thank you in a few words for your very friendly<lb break="yes"/>letter. I consider you fortunate that your talents<lb break="yes"/>have met with a favorable opportunity to repre-<lb break="no"/>sent the grand scenes of the tropic world and the<lb break="yes"/>venerable remains of ancient culture. I recom-<lb break="no"/>mend to you the correct illustration of the vol-<lb break="no"/>canic peaks as much more important than that of<lb break="yes"/>the physiognomy of the vegetable world, which<lb break="yes"/>has already been enriched by the extensive and<lb break="yes"/>faithful sketches of Rugendas, Edward, Hilde-<lb break="no"/>brandt and Bellermann. Still, those great lakes,<lb break="yes"/>filled with islands, must present many new fea-<lb break="no"/>tures of landscape painting. As regards the mon-<lb break="no" />uments, (in Yucatan, Guatemala and Nicaragua,)<lb break="yes"/>there is a great lack of illustrations which pre-<lb break="no"/>serve the correct proportions. Your architectural<lb break="yes"/>knowledge will enable you to supply this defi-<lb break="no"/>ciency.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;The eighth edition of my folio work in three<lb break="yes"/>parts, <hi rendition="#i">Vue des Cordillères</hi>, will, I think, be of<lb break="yes" />most service to you. You will find in it a multi-<lb break="no"/>tude of views which may throw some light upon<lb break="yes"/>what discoveries you make in the department of<lb break="yes"/>ornamental sculpture, with which all the ancient<lb break="yes"/>edifices of the Aztecs the inhabitants of Yucatan<lb break="yes" />and the southern region adjoining the Isthmus,<lb break="yes"/>are richly covered. In Yucatan there is a species<lb break="yes"/>of pointed arch to be found, constructed, however,<lb break="yes"/>from a series of overlapping stones, as in the old<lb break="yes"/>Egyptian monuments. You may there be able to<lb break="yes" />find sculptures of the Aztec calendar, traditions<lb break="yes"/>of the four ages of the world, or the name <hi rendition="#i">Wotun</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>which seems to have some connection with that<lb break="yes"/>of Odin, and stands as authority for our division<lb break="yes"/>of the year.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;I rejoice at your connection with Mr. <hi rendition="#k">Squier</hi>,<lb break="yes"/>whom I beg you to assure of my particular re-<lb break="no"/>gard, since I have to thank him for his admirable<lb break="yes"/>researches among the enigmatical monuments of<lb break="yes"/>the United States. May you find that enjoyment<lb break="yes"/>which must certainly crown your laudable spirit<lb break="yes"/>of enterprise! <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi>&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>
            </p>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 