<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-11-30" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="256" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Velocity of Light.</hi> By Humboldt.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On the subject of the velocity of light, and the probability that<lb break="yes" />it requires a certain time for its propagation, we find the earliest<lb break="yes"/>view expressed by Francis Bacon, in the second book of the No-<lb break="no"/>vum Organum. He speaks of the time required by a ray of light to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="257" facs="#f0002"/> traverse the immensity of space, and throws out the question whether<lb break="yes"/>the stars still exist which we now see sparkle. One is astonished at<lb break="yes"/>finding so happy a conjecture in a work whose celebrated author was<lb break="yes"/>so far below some of his <choice>
                        <sic>cotemporaries</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">contemporaries</corr>
                    </choice> in mathematical, astronomical,<lb break="yes"/>and physical knowledge. The velocity of the reflected solar light<lb break="yes"/>was measured by Römer (November 1675) by comparison of the<lb break="yes"/>times of occultation of Jupiter&#x2019;s satellites; and the velocity of the<lb break="yes"/>direct light of the fixed stars by Bradley&#x2019;s great discovery of the<lb break="yes"/>aberration of light (made in the autumn of 1727),&#x2014;that demon-<lb break="no"/>stration to our senses of the earth&#x2019;s movement of translation in its<lb break="yes"/>orbit; viz. of the truth of the Copernican system. In very recent<lb break="yes"/>times a third method of measurement has been proposed by Arago,<lb break="yes"/>by the phenomena of the light of a variable star; for example, Algol<lb break="yes"/>in Perseus. We have to add to these astronomical methods a ter-<lb break="no"/>restrial measurement, which has very recently been executed with<lb break="yes"/>great ingenuity and success by M. Fizeau, in the neighbourhood of<lb break="yes"/>Paris. It recalls to recollection an attempt of Galileo&#x2019;s with two<lb break="yes"/>lanterns, which did not lead to any result.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From Römer&#x2019;s first observations of Jupiter&#x2019;s satellites, Horrebow<lb break="yes"/>and Du Hamel estimated the time occupied in the passage of light<lb break="yes"/>from the sun to the earth, at their mean distance apart, at 14&#x2032; 7&#x2033;;<lb break="yes"/>Carsini, at 14&#x2032; 10&#x2033;; Newton, which is very striking, much nearer<lb break="yes"/>to the truth, at 7&#x2032; 30&#x2033;. Delambre, by taking into account, among<lb break="yes"/>the observations of his time, only those of the first satellite, found<lb break="yes"/>8&#x2032; 13&#x2033; &#x00B7;2. Encke has very justly remarked how important it would<lb break="yes"/>be, with the certainty of obtaining the more accordant results which<lb break="yes"/>the present perfection of telescopes would afford, to undertake a series<lb break="yes"/>of occultations of Jupiter&#x2019;s satellites, for the express purpose of de-<lb break="no"/>ducing the velocity of light.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>From Bradley&#x2019;s observations of aberration, recently discovered by<lb break="yes"/>Rigaud of Oxford, there follows, according to the investigation of Dr<lb break="yes"/>Busch of Königsberg, for the passage of light from the sun to the<lb break="yes"/>earth, 8&#x2032; 12&#x2033; &#x00B7;14; for the velocity of the light of the stars 167,976<lb break="yes"/>geographical miles in a second; and for the constant of aberration, 20&#x2033;<lb break="yes"/>&#x00B7;2116<choice>
                        <sic>:</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">;</corr>
                    </choice> but, from the more recent aberration observations of Struve,<lb break="yes"/>made for eighteen months with the large transit instrument at Pulkowa,<lb break="yes"/>it appears that the first of these numbers must be considerably in-<lb break="no"/>creased. The result of Struve&#x2019;s great investigation is 8&#x2032; 17&#x2033; &#x00B7;78;<lb break="yes"/>whence with the aberration-constant, 20&#x2033; &#x00B7;4451, with Encke&#x2019;s correc-<lb break="no"/>tion of the sun&#x2019;s parallax made in 1835, and with the value of the<lb break="yes"/>earth&#x2019;s semi-diameter given by him in the Jahrbuch for 1852, we<lb break="yes"/>have for the velocity of light 166,196 geographical miles in a second.<lb break="yes"/>The probable error of the velocity scarcely amounts to eight geogra-<lb break="no"/>phical miles. Struve&#x2019;s result for the time which light requires to<lb break="yes" />reach the earth from the sun differs <formula notation="TeX" >\frac{1}{110}</formula> from that of Delambre<lb break="yes"/>(8&#x2032; 13&#x2033; &#x00B7;2), which latter was employed by Bessel in the Tabul&#x00E6; Re-<lb break="no"/>giomontan&#x00E6;, and has been used hitherto in the Berlin Astronomical<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">
                        <hi rendition="#k">vol. l. no. c.&#x2014;april 1851. r</hi>
                    </fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="258" facs="#f0003"/> Almanac. The discussion of this subject cannot be regarded as<lb break="yes"/>completely terminated; but the earlier entertained supposition, that<lb break="yes"/>the velocity of the light of the Pole-star was less than that of its<lb break="yes"/>companion in the ratio of 133:134, remains subject to great doubts.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A physicist distinguished for his knowledge as well as for his great<lb break="yes"/>delicacy in experimenting, M. Fizeau, has succeeded in executing a<lb break="yes"/>terrestrial measurement of the velocity of light, by means of an inge-<lb break="no"/>niously devised apparatus, in which the artificial star-like light of<lb break="yes"/>oxygen and hydrogen is returned to the point from whence it came,<lb break="yes"/>by a mirror placed at a distance of 8633 metres (28,324 English<lb break="yes"/>feet), between Suresne and La Butte Montmartre. A disc, fur-<lb break="no"/>nished with 720 teeth, which made 12&#x00B7;6 revolutions in a second,<lb break="yes"/>alternately stopped the ray of light, and allowed it to pass freely be-<lb break="no"/>tween the teeth of the limb. From the indications of a counter<lb break="yes"/>(compteur) it was inferred, that the artificial light traversed 17,266<lb break="yes"/>metres (56,648 English feet), or twice the distance between the sta-<lb break="no" />tions, in <formula notation="TeX">\frac{1}{18000}</formula> of a second of time; whence there results a velocity<lb break="yes"/>of 167,528 geographical miles in a second. This result comes nearest<lb break="yes"/>to that of Delambre derived from Jupiter&#x2019;s satellites, which is 167,976<lb break="yes" />geographical miles in a second.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Direct observations, and ingenious considerations on the absence of<lb break="yes"/>any alteration of colour during the change of light of variable stars,<lb break="yes"/>(a subject to which I shall presently return), have led Arago to the<lb break="yes"/>conclusion that (in the language of the undulatory theory), rays of<lb break="yes"/>light which have different colours, and therefore very different<lb break="yes"/>lengths and rapidities of transverse vibration, move through space<lb break="yes"/>with equal velocities; but that in the interior of the different bodies<lb break="yes"/>through which the coloured rays pass, their rates of propagation and<lb break="yes"/>their refractions are different. Arago&#x2019;s observations have <choice>
                        <sic>shewn</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">shown</corr>
                    </choice>,<lb break="yes"/>that in the prism the refraction is not altered by the relation which<lb break="yes"/>the velocity of light bears to that of the earth&#x2019;s motion. All the<lb break="yes"/>measurements accord in the result, that the light of the stars towards<lb break="yes"/>which the earth is advancing, has the same index of refraction, as<lb break="yes"/>the light of the stars from which the earth is receding. Speaking in<lb break="yes"/>the language of the emission hypothesis, the celebrated observer we<lb break="yes"/>have just named said, that bodies send forth rays of all velocities,<lb break="yes"/>but that among these different velocities there is only one which can<lb break="yes" />awaken the sensation of light.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If we compare the velocities of solar, sidereal, and terrestrial light,<lb break="yes"/>which all comport themselves exactly in the same manner in the<lb break="yes"/>prism, with the velocity of the current of friction-electricity, we are<lb break="yes"/>inclined to assign to the latter, according to the experiments devised<lb break="yes"/>with admirable ingenuity by Wheatstone, a velocity superior to the<lb break="yes"/>former in the ratio of at least 3 to 2. According to the lowest results<lb break="yes"/>of Wheatstone&#x2019;s optical rotating apparatus, the electric current tra-<lb break="no"/>verses 288,000 English statute miles, or 250,000 geographical miles,<lb break="yes"/>in a second. If, then, we reckon with Struve for sidereal light in the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="259" facs="#f0004"/> aberration-observations 166,196 geographical miles in a second, we<lb break="yes"/>get a difference of 83,804 geographical miles in a second for the<lb break="yes"/>greater velocity of the electric current.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This result appears to contradict the previously mentioned view of<lb break="yes" />William Herschel, which regarded the light of the sun and of the<lb break="yes"/>fixed stars as perhaps the effect of an electro-magnetic process,&#x2014;a<lb break="yes"/>perpetual Aurora. I say appears to contradict; for it cannot be<lb break="yes"/>deemed impossible that, in the different luminous bodies of space,<lb break="yes"/>there may be several magneto-electric processes very different in kind,<lb break="yes"/>and in which the light produced by the process may have a different<lb break="yes"/>rate of propagation. To this possible conjecture must be added the<lb break="yes" />uncertainty of the numerical result obtained with Wheatstone&#x2019;s appa-<lb break="no"/>ratus, which result he himself regards as &#x201C;not sufficiently established<lb break="yes"/>and as requiring fresh confirmation,&#x201D; in order to be compared satisfac-<lb break="no"/>torily with the deductions from aberration, and satellite-observations.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Later experiments made by Walker in the United States of North<lb break="yes" />America on the velocity of the propagation of electricity, on the oc-<lb break="no"/>casion of his telegraphic determination of the longitudes of Washing-<lb break="no"/>ton, Philadelphia, New York, and Cambridge, have excited a lively<lb break="yes"/>interest in the minds of physical enquirers. According to Stein-<lb break="no"/>heil&#x2019;s description of these experiments, the astronomical clock of the<lb break="yes"/>observatory at Philadelphia was connected with Morse&#x2019;s writing ap-<lb break="no" />paratus on the line of telegraph in such a manner, that the clock&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>march noted itself by points on the endless strip of paper of the appa-<lb break="no"/>ratus. The electric telegraph carries each of these points instantane-<lb break="no"/>ously to the other stations, and gives them the Philadelphia time by<lb break="yes"/>similar points on their moving strips of paper. Arbitrary signals,<lb break="yes"/>or the instant of the passage of a star, may be noted in the same<lb break="yes"/>manner by the observer, by merely touching or pressing an index<lb break="yes"/>with his finger. The material advantage of this American method<lb break="yes"/>consists, as Steinheil expresses it, &#x201C;in its making the determination<lb break="yes"/>of time independent of the connection of the two senses, sight and<lb break="yes" />hearing; as the clock&#x2019;s march notes itself, and the instant of the star&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>passage is given direct (to within a mean error of the 70th part of a<lb break="yes"/>second, as Walker states) by the movement of the observer&#x2019;s finger.<lb break="yes"/>A constant difference between the compared clock-marks of Phila-<lb break="no"/>delphia and Cambridge is produced by the time which the electric<lb break="yes"/>current requires to traverse twice the closed circuit between the two<lb break="yes" />stations.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Measurements made with conductors 1050 English statute miles,<lb break="yes"/>or 968 geographical miles, in length, gave, from 18 equations of<lb break="yes" />condition, the rate of propagation of the hydrogalvanic current at<lb break="yes"/>only 18,700 statute or 16,240 geographical miles in a second; <hi rendition="#i">i. e.,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>fifteen times slower than the electric current in Wheatstone&#x2019;s rotating<lb break="yes"/>disc apparatus! As in Walker&#x2019;s remarkable experiments two wires<lb break="yes"/>were not used, but half the conduction, according to the common<lb break="yes"/>expression, took place through the moist body of the earth, it might<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">
                        <hi rendition="#k">r</hi> 2</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="260" facs="#f0005"/> seem a justifiable supposition that the velocity of the propagation<lb break="yes"/>of electricity is dependent on the nature as well as on the dimensions<lb break="yes"/>of the medium. In the voltaic circuit bad conductors become more<lb break="yes"/>heated than good conductors, and electric discharges are very<lb break="yes"/>variously complicated phenomena, as appears by the latest experi-<lb break="no"/>ments of Riess. The now prevailing views respecting what is com-<lb break="no"/>monly called &#x201C;connection through the earth&#x201D; are opposed to the<lb break="yes"/>view of linear molecular conduction between the two ends of the<lb break="yes"/>wire, and to the conjectures of impediments to conduction, and of<lb break="yes" />accumulation and discharges in a current; as that which was once<lb break="yes"/>regarded as intermediate conduction in the earth is now supposed to<lb break="yes"/>belong only to an equalisation or to a restoration of electric tension.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Although, according to the present limits of exactness in this kind<lb break="yes"/>of observation, it is probable that the aberration constant, and there-<lb break="no"/>fore the velocity of light, of all the fixed stars, is the same, yet the<lb break="yes"/>possibility has more than once been spoken of, that there may be<lb break="yes"/>luminous bodies in space whose light does not reach us because, from<lb break="yes"/>their enormous mass gravitation constrains the luminous particles<lb break="yes"/>to return. The emission theory gives to such fancies a scientific<lb break="yes"/>form: I only allude to them here, because I shall subsequently have<lb break="yes"/>to notice certain peculiarities of motion ascribed to the star Procyon,<lb break="yes"/>which appear to point to a perturbation by dark bodies. It is the<lb break="yes" />object of this part of my work to touch on matters which, during<lb break="yes"/>the time in which it has been in progress, have influenced the direc-<lb break="no"/>tion which science has pursued, and thus to mark the individual<lb break="yes"/>character of the epoch in regard to the study of nature, whether in<lb break="yes"/>the sidereal or the telluric sphere.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Sabine&#x2019;s Edition of Humboldt&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>Cosmos.</hi> Vol. iii., Part 1, p. 71.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 