<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1">
                <head>From the N. Y. Courier and Enquirer.<lb/><hi rendition="#b">Humboldt and
                        Fremont.</hi></head>
                <lb/>
                <p>To honor him as a pioneer of American<lb/>Discovery, the King of Prussia
                    presented to<lb/>Colonel John C. Fremont &#x201C;the Golden<lb/>Medal of
                    Progress in the sciences.&#x201D; The<lb/>medal is of fine gold, massive, more
                    than<lb/>double the size of the American double ea-<lb/>gle, and of exquisite
                    workmanship. On the<lb/>face is the medallion head of the King, Fred-<lb/>erick
                    William the Fourth, surrounded by<lb/>figures emblematical of Religion, <choice>
                        <sic>Jurlspru<lb/>dence</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Jurispru-<lb/>dence</corr>
                    </choice>, Medicine and the Arts. On the re-<lb/>verse, Apollo, in the chariot
                    of the sun,<lb/>drawn by four high-mettled, plunging hor-<lb/>ses, traversing
                    the zodiac, and darting rays<lb/>of light from his head. This beautiful
                    trib-<lb/>ute to the merit of Col. Fremont came to<lb/>him accompanied with a
                    complimentry let-<lb/>ter from Baron Humboldt, of which the fol-<lb/>lowing is a
                    translation:</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">To Col. Fremont, Senator:</hi></p>
                <lb/>
                <p>&#x201C;It is very <choice>
                        <sic>agreeabie</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">agreeable</corr>
                    </choice> to me, sir, to ad-<lb/>dress you these lines by my excellent
                    friend,<lb/>our minister to the United States, M. de<lb/>Gerolt. After having
                    given you in the new<lb/>edition of my &#x2018;<hi rendition="#i">Aspects of
                        Nature,</hi>&#x2019; the pub-<lb/>lic testimony of the admiration which is
                    due<lb/>to your gigantic labors between St. Louis,<lb/>of Missouri, and the
                    coasts of the South Sea,<lb/>I feel happy to offer you, in this living
                    to-<lb/>ken (<hi rendition="#i">dans ce petit signe de vie)</hi> the
                    homage<lb/>of my warm acknowledgment. You have<lb/>displayed a noble courage in
                    distant expedi-<lb/>tions, braved all the dangers of cold and<lb/>famine,
                    enriched all the branches of the nat-<lb/>ural sciences, and illustrated a vast
                    country<lb/>which was almost entirely unknown to us.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>A merit so rare has been acknowledged by<lb/>a sovereign warmly interested in the
                    prog-<lb/>ress of physical geography; the King orders<lb/>me to offer you the
                    grand golden medal<lb/>destined to those who have labored at sci-<lb/>entific
                    progress. I hope that this mark of<lb/>the Royal good will, will be agreeable
                    to<lb/>you at a time when, upon the proposition of<lb/>the illustrious
                    geographer, Chas. Ritter, the<lb/>Geographical Society at Berlin has
                    named<lb/>you an honorary member. For myself, I<lb/>must thank you particularly
                    also for the <choice>
                        <sic>hon-<lb/>on</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">hon-<lb/>or</corr>
                    </choice> which you have done in attaching my<lb/>name and that of my fellow
                    laborer and in-<lb/>timate friend, Mr. Bonpland, to countries<lb/>neighboring to
                    those which have been the<lb/>object of our labors. <hi rendition="#i"
                        >California, which has<lb/>so nobly resisted the introduction of
                        slavery,<lb/>will be worthily represented by a friend of<lb/>liberty, and of
                        the progress of intelligence.</hi></p>
                <lb/>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Accept, I pray you sir, the expression of<lb/>my high and affectionate
                        consideration.<lb/>Your most humble and most obedient<lb/>servant,<lb/><hi
                            rendition="#et">A. V. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute>
                </closer>
                <lb/>
                <dateline>Sans Souci, Oct. 7, 1850.&#x201D;</dateline>
            </div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
