<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="327" facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>While alluding to the estimate placed upon the<lb break="yes"/>scientific results of Col. Fremont&#x2019;s explorations, by<lb break="yes"/>some of his eminent contemporaries, we may be pardoned<lb break="yes"/>for anticipating the tributes paid two years later to<lb break="yes"/>his labors by Baron Humboldt, on behalf of the King<lb break="yes"/>of Prussia, and by the Royal Geographical Society of<lb break="yes"/>London. As a minister of the Prussian government,<lb break="yes" />Humboldt was charged to present Fremont with &#x201C;the<lb break="yes"/>
                <hi rendition="#i">great golden medal for progress in the sciences.</hi>&#x201D; He<lb break="yes"/>accompanied the medal with the following highly<lb break="yes"/>complimentary note to Fremont, in which a graceful<lb break="yes" />allusion is made to that early struggle against slavery<lb break="yes"/>with which his political career in California commenced<lb break="yes"/>and closed.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <floatingText>
                <body>
                    <div type="letter">
                        <p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Monsieur le Sénateur</hi>
                            <note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn1-1" next="#fn1-2">Fremont had just been elected to the United States Senate, from<lb break="yes" />California. The following is the English translation of Baron Humboldt&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>letter:<lb break="yes" />&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">To Col. Fremont, Senator.</hi>
                                <lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;It is very agreeable to me, sir, to address you these lines by my<lb break="yes"/>excellent friend, our minister to the United States, M. de Gerolt. After<lb break="yes"/>having given you, in the new edition of my &#x2018;Aspects of Nature,&#x2019; the<lb break="yes"/>public testimony of the admiration which is due to your gigantic labors<lb break="yes" />between St. Louis, of Missouri, and the coasts of the South Sea, I feel<lb break="yes"/>happy to offer you, in this living token, (<hi rendition="#i">dans cc petit signe de vie</hi>) the<lb break="yes"/>homage of my warm acknowledgment. You have displayed a noble<lb break="yes"/>courage in distant expeditions, braved all the dangers of cold and<lb break="yes"/>famine, enriched all the branches of the natural sciences, illustrated a<lb break="yes"/>vast country which was almost entirely unknown to us.<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;A merit so rare has been acknowledged by a sovereign warmly inte-<lb break="no"/>rested in the progress of physical geography; the king orders me to</note>
                            <hi rendition="#i">:</hi> Il m&#x2019;est bien doux, Monsieur, de<lb break="yes"/>vous addresser ces lignes par mon excellent ami, notre ministre<lb break="yes"/>
                            <pb n="328" facs="#f0002"/> aux États-Unis, M. de Gerolt. Après vous avoir donné dans la<lb break="yes"/>nouvelle édition de mes <hi rendition="#i">Tableaux de la Nature</hi> le témoignage<lb break="yes"/>public de l&#x2019;admiration qui est due à vos gigantesques travaux<lb break="yes"/>entre St. Louis du Missouri et les côtes de la mer du Sud, je me<lb break="yes"/>sens heureux de vous offrir, dans ce petit signe de vie, l&#x2019;hom-<lb break="no"/>mage de ma vive reconnaissance. Vous avez déployé un noble<lb break="yes" />courage dans des expéditions lointaines, bravé tout les dangers<lb break="yes"/>des frimas et du manque de nourriture, enrichi toutes les parties<lb break="yes"/>de sciences naturelles, illustré un vaste pays qui nous était pres-<lb break="no"/>que entièrement inconnu. Un mérite si rare a été reconnu par<lb break="yes"/>un souverain vivement interessé aux progrès de la géographie<lb break="yes"/>physique: le roi m&#x2019;ordonne de vous offrir la grande médaille<lb break="yes" />d&#x2019;or, destinée à ceux qui ont travaillé à des progrès scientifiques.<lb break="yes"/>J&#x2019;espère que cette marque de la bienveillance royale vous sera<lb break="yes"/>agréable dans un moment, où, sur la proposition de l&#x2019;illustre<lb break="yes" />géographe, Charles Ritter, la Société de Géographie, residante à<lb break="yes"/>Berlin, vous a nommé pour membre honoraire. Quant à moi,<lb break="yes"/>je dois vous remercier particulièrement aussi de l&#x2019;honneur que<lb break="yes"/>vous m&#x2019;avez fait d&#x2019;attacher mon nom et celui de mon collabora-<lb break="no"/>teur et ami intime, M. Bonpland, à des contrées voisines de<lb break="yes" />celles qui ont été l&#x2019;objet de nos travaux. La Californie, qui a<lb break="yes"/>
                            <note place="foot" n="*" xml:id="fn1-2" prev="#fn1-1">offer you the grand golden medal destined to those who have labored at<lb break="yes"/>scientific progress. I hope that this mark of the royal good will, will be<lb break="yes"/>agreeable to you at a time when, upon the proposition of the illustrious<lb break="yes" />geographer, Chas. Ritter, the Geographical Society at Berlin has named<lb break="yes"/>you an honorary member. For myself, I must thank you particularly<lb break="yes"/>also for the houor which you have done in attaching my name, and that<lb break="yes"/>of my fellow-laborer and intimate friend, Mr. Bonpland, to countries<lb break="yes"/>neighboring to those which have been the object of our labors. <hi rendition="#i">Califor-<lb break="no"/>nia, which has so nobly resisted the introduction of slavery, will be wor-<lb break="no"/>thily represented by a friend of liberty and of the progress of intelli-<lb break="no"/>gence.</hi>
                                <lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Accept, I pray you, sir, the expression of my high and affectionate<lb break="yes"/>consideration.<lb break="yes"/>
                                <hi rendition="#c">&#x201C;Your most humble and most obedient servant,</hi>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;A. v. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi>
                                </hi>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <date>
                                    <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Sans Souci,</hi> October 7, 1850.&#x201D;</hi>
                                </date>
                            </note>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <pb n="329" facs="#f0003"/>
                            <hi rendition="#i">noblement</hi> résisté à l&#x2019;introduction de l&#x2019;esclavage, sera dignement<lb break="yes"/>représentée par un ami de la liberté et des progrès de l&#x2019;intelli-<lb break="no" />gence.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>&#x201C;Agréez, je vous prie, Monsieur le Sénateur, l&#x2019;expression de<lb break="yes"/>ma haute et affectueuse considération.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rendition="#c">&#x201C;Votre très humble et très obéissant serviteur,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;A. v. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi>
                                </hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <dateline>
                            <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;A <hi rendition="#k">Sans Souci,</hi> le 7 Octobre, 1850.&#x201D;</hi>
                        </dateline>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </floatingText>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>On the envelope thus addressed:</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;À Monsieur le Colonel Frémont, Senateur,</hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Avec la grande médaille d&#x2019;or,<note place="foot" n="*">The medal is of fine gold, massive, more than double the size of the<lb break="yes"/>American double eagle, and of exquisite workmanship. On the face is<lb break="yes"/>the medallion head of the king, Frederic William the Fourth, surrounded<lb break="yes"/>by figures emblematical of Religion, Jurisprudence, Medicine and the<lb break="yes"/>Arts. On the reverse, Apollo, in the chariot of the sun, drawn by four<lb break="yes" />high mettled plunging horses, traversing the zodiac, and darting rays of<lb break="yes"/>light from his head.</note>
                </hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Pour les progrès dans les sciences.</hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <closer>
                <salute>
                    <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Baron Humboldt.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </salute>
            </closer>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI> 