<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i"><hi rendition="#g">COLONEL FREMONT AND BARON HUMBOLDT</hi></hi></head><lb/>
<p>The present electioneering contest in the United<lb/>States for a President has given a New York
                    paper an op-<lb/>portunity of publishing a very intereating letter. In
                    the<lb/>year 1850 the Prussian government awarded Colonel Fre-<lb/>mont the
                    great gold medal for his efforts in the advance-<lb/>ment of science, and in
                    transmitting it, the great German<lb/>naturalist enhanced its value by sending
                    with it the fol-<lb/>lowing document:</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;To the Senator Colonel Fremont,&#x2014;It affords me great<lb/>pleasure to forward you
                    these lines through my excellent<lb/>friend M. de Gerolt. Having, in my new
                    edition of the &#x2018;Views<lb/>of Nature,&#x2019; publicly acknowledged my
                    admiration for the<lb/>gigantic works so meritoriously completed by you
                    between<lb/>St. Louis and the South Sea, I feel happy in being able
                    once<lb/>more to give you the assurance of my warm recognition.<lb/>In your
                    distant expeditions you displayed a noble fortitude,<lb/>braved every danger of
                    cold and hunger, enriched every<lb/>branch of natural science, and opened for us
                    a great region<lb/>that was previously almost wholly unknown to us.</p><lb/><p>Such rare merit has been recognised by a sovereign who<lb/>takes such a lively interest in the
                    progress of physical geo-<lb/>graphy. The King commissions me to present you
                    with the<lb/>great gold medal that is intended for those who have sig-<lb/>nally
                    contributed to the advancement of science. I hope<lb/>this sign of recognition
                    will be doubly welcome to you at a<lb/>time that the Geographical Society of
                    Berlin, upon the mo-<lb/>tion of the celebrated geographer Charles Ritter, has
                    fur-<lb/>ther named you an honourable member. In so far as con-<lb/>cerns
                    myself, I must also especially thank you for the<lb/>honour you confer upon me
                    by having bestowed the names<lb/>of myself, as well as of my fellow-explorer and
                    friend Bon-<lb/>pland, on regions that border on those which formed
                    the<lb/>object of our scientific labours. California, that has so
                    mag-<lb/>nanimously withstood the introduction of slavery, will be<lb/>worthily
                    represented by a friend to freedom and to the pro-<lb/>gress of science.</p><lb/><closer><salute>&#x201C;Accept the assurance, &amp;c., <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;A. v. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute></closer><lb/><dateline>&#x201C;Sans-Souci, Oct. 7, 1850.&#x201D;</dateline></div>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
