<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="2" facs="#f0001" />
<p>&#x201C;To the Senator Colonel Fremont.&#x2014;It affords me<lb/>great pleasure to forward you these lines through my<lb/>excellent friend M. de Gerolt. Having, in my new edi-<lb/>tion of the &#x2018;Views of Nature,&#x2019; publicly acknowledged<lb/>my admiration for the gigantic works so meritoriously<lb/>completed by you between St. Louis and the South Sea,<lb/>I feel happy in being able once more to give you the<lb/>assurance of my warm recognition. In your distant<lb/>expeditions you displayed a noble fortitude, braved<lb/>every danger of cold and hunger, enriched every branch<lb/>of natural science, and opened for us a great region that<lb/>was previously almost unknown to us.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Such rare merit has been recognised by a sovereign<lb/>who takes such a lively interest in the progress of<lb/>physical geography. The King commissions me to<lb/>present you with the great gold medal that is intended<lb/>for those who have signally contributed to the advanco-<lb/>ment of science. I hope this sign of recognition will be<lb/>doubly welcome to you at a time that the Geographical<lb/>Society of Berlin, upon the motion of the celebrated<lb/>geographer Charles Ritter, has further named you an<lb/>honourable member. In so far as concerns myself, I<lb/>must also especially thank you for the honour you con-<lb/>fer upon me by having bestowed the names of myself, as<lb/>well as of my fellow-explorer and friend Bonland, on<lb/>regions that border on those which formed the object of<lb/>our scientific labours. California, that has so magnani-<lb/>mously withstood the introduction of slavery, will be<lb/>worthily represented by a friend to freedom and to the<lb/>progress of science.</p><lb/><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Accept the assurance, &#x0026;c.,<lb/>A. v. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute></closer><lb/><dateline>&#x201C;Sans-Souci, Oct. 7, 1850.&#x201D;</dateline><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
