<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<pb facs="#f0002" />
<div><head>Col. Fremont and Baron Humboldt.</head><lb/><p>Col. Fremont is known and honored among<lb/>learned and scientific men the world over, as<lb/>but few of our citizens are. Were he to die<lb/>to day, he would leave a name more honora-<lb/>ble and more immortal than that achieved by<lb/>either of his rivals for the Presidency, one of<lb/>whom is nearly twice bis age, and the other<lb/>a full half older. He has contributed to the<lb/>stock of knowledge of the world,&#x2014;he has<lb/>made his mark on the record which lives,&#x2014;<lb/>he has done something positive, for he is an<lb/>affirmative and positive man. Among the<lb/>notable recognitions of his labors in the field<lb/>of science, and as a pioneer of American dis-<lb/>covery, was the conferring upon him, sever-<lb/>al years ago, by the King of Prussia, of the<lb/>great &#x201C;Golden Medal of Progress in the Sci-<lb/>ences.&#x201D; It was presented through the great<lb/>European savan and traveler, Baron Hum-<lb/>boldt, with a letter most flattering in its terms.<lb/>We subjoin this, as showing in what light<lb/>Fremont is held by a man so learned, emi-<lb/>nent and noble. One sentence of Humboldt&#x2019;s<lb/>letter we have marked in italics; it was a<lb/>conscientious tribute paid to the Senator<lb/>then; it is highly significant of Fremont&#x2019;s<lb/>&#x201C;friendship to liberty and to the progress of<lb/>intelligence&#x201D; <hi rendition="#i">now.</hi></p><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">To Col. Fremont, Senator:</hi>&#x2014;It is very a-<lb/>greeable to me, sir, to address you these lines<lb/>by my excellent friend, our Minister to the Uni-<lb/>ted States, M. de Gerolt. After having giv-<lb/>en you in the new edition of my &#x201C;Aspects of<lb/>Nature&#x201D; the public testimony of the admira-<lb/>tion which is due to your gigantic labors be-<lb/>tween St. Louis of Missouri, and the coasts<lb/>of the South Sea, I feel happy to offer you.<lb/>in this living token <hi rendition="#i">(dans ce petit signe de<lb/>vie,)</hi> the homage of my warm acknowledg-<lb/>ment. You have displayed a noble courage<lb/>in distant expeditions, braved all the dangers<lb/>of cold and famine, enriched all the branches<lb/>of the natural sciences, illustrated a vast<lb/>country which was most entirely unknown to<lb/>us.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;A merit so rare has been acknowledged<lb/>by a sovereign warmly interested in the prog-<lb/>ress of physical geography; the King orders<lb/>me to offer you the grand golden medal des-<lb/>tined to those who have labored at scientific<lb/>progress. I hope that this mark of the royal<lb/>good will be agreeable to you at a time<lb/>when, upon the proposition of the illustrous<lb/>geographer, Charles Ritter, of the Geographi-<lb/>cal Society at Berlin, has named you a hon-<lb/>orarv member. For myself, I must thank<lb/>you particularly also for the honor which<lb/>you have done in attaching my name and that<lb/>of my fellow-laborer and intimate friend. Mr.<lb/>Bonpland, to countries neighboring to those<lb/>which have been the object of our labors.<lb/><hi rendition="#i">California, which has so nobly resisted the in-<lb/>troduction of slavery, will be worthily repre-<lb/>sented by a friend of liberty and of the prog-<lb/>ress of intelligence.</hi></p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Accept, I pray you, sir, the expression of<lb/>my high and affectio@te consideration.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Your mos@ hu@ble and most obedient ser-<lb/>vant.</p><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">A. V. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute></closer><lb/><dateline>&#x201C;Sans Souci, Oct. 7, 1850.&#x201D;</dateline></div><lb/><div><p><hi rendition="#et">On the envelope thus addressed:&#x2014;<lb/>&#x201C;To Colonel <hi rendition="#k">Fremont,</hi> Senator,<lb/>&#x201C;With the Golden Medal<lb/>&#x201C;For the progress of the sciences.<lb/>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Baron Humboldt.</hi>&#x201D;</hi></p><lb/><p>The following is the description of the med-<lb/>al: Of fine gold, massive, more than double<lb/>the size of the American double eagle, and of<lb/>exquisite work manship. On the face is the<lb/>medallion head of the King Frederic William<lb/>the Fourth surrounded by figures emblemat-<lb/>ical of Religion, Jurisprudence, Medicine and<lb/>the Arts. On the reverse, Apollo, in the<lb/>chariot of the sun, drawn by four high-met-<lb/>tled plunging horses, traversing the zodiac,<lb/>and darting rays of light from his head.</p><lb/><p>The following is the recognition of Fre-<lb/>mont&#x2019;s geographical and geological labors<lb/>which Baron Humboldt alludes to, as having<lb/>been embraced in one of his books:</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Fremont&#x2019;s map and geographical investi-<lb/>gations comprehend the extensive region from<lb/>the junction of the Kansas river with the<lb/>Missouri to the falls of the Columbia, and to<lb/>the missions of Santa Barbara and Pueble de<lb/>los Angeles, in New California; or a space<lb/>of 28 degrees longitude, and from the 34th to<lb/>the 45th parallel of latitude. Four hundred<lb/>points have been determined hyposometrical-<lb/>ly by barometic observations, and, for the<lb/>most part, geographically by astronomical<lb/>observations; so that a district which, with<lb/>the winding of the route, amounts to 3,600<lb/>geographical miles from the mouth of the<lb/>Kansas to Fort Van Couver and the shores<lb/>of the Pacific, (almost 720 miles more than<lb/>the distance from Madrid to Tobolsk.) has<lb/>been represented in profile, showing the rel-<lb/>ative heights above the level of the sea.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;As I was, I believe, the first person who<lb/>undertook to represent, in geognostic profile,<lb/>the form of entire countries&#x2014;such as the Ibe-<lb/>rian peninsula, the high lands of Mexico and<lb/>the Cordilleras of South America, (the semi-<lb/>perspective profections of a Siberian traveler,<lb/>Abbe Chappe, were founded on mere and<lb/>generally ill-judged estimations of the fall of<lb/>rivers) it has given me particular pleasure<lb/>to see the geographical method of represent-<lb/>ing the form of the earth in a vertical direc-<lb/>tion, or the elevations of the solid portion of<lb/>our planet above its watery covering, applied<lb/>on so grand a scale as has been done in Fre-<lb/>mont&#x2019;s map.&#x201D;</p><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#b"><hi rendition="#g">PLANING.</hi></hi></hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
