<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.1" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision" >Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.1" when="2018-12-12" who="#wernicke_nd">Mark-up. <note type="remarkRevision" >Auszeichnungsfehler bereinigt.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-11-30" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision" >Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Col. Fremont, Man and Boy.&#x2014;The Early Pro-<lb break="no"/>mise, and the Ripe Performance.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>There has come to our hands at the same time two notices<lb break="yes"/>of Col. <hi rendition="#k">Fremont,</hi> one in relation to his early age and school-<lb break="no"/>boy days, the other in relation to his great explorations, and<lb break="yes"/>both honorable to him, and from persons whose testimony is<lb break="yes"/>most honorable&#x2014;his teacher, and the Baron <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi> In<lb break="yes"/>the preface to a school edition of Xenophon&#x2019;s Anabasis for a<lb break="yes"/>Greek class, by Dr. <hi rendition="#k" >Roberton,</hi> now of Philadelphia, there<lb break="yes"/>is an account of the young <hi rendition="#k">Fremont</hi> as he first appeared at<lb break="yes"/>the grammar school of the Dr. at Charleston, (S. C.) and of<lb break="yes"/>his diligence, and progress, and moral deportment, and early<lb break="yes"/>promise of distinguished life; which is given, as the preface<lb break="yes"/>states, as an example and encouragement to all his scholars.<lb break="yes"/>The other is a letter from the great Baron <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt,</hi> and,<lb break="yes"/>besides expressing his own admiration of the labors of <hi rendition="#k" >Fre-<lb break="no"/>mont,</hi> communicates to him the grand golden medal of the<lb break="yes"/>King of Prussia for progress in the sciences, and makes known<lb break="yes"/>to him his election as an honorary member of the Geographi-<lb break="no"/>cal Society at Berlin.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following is the notice of the old teacher:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <p>&#x201C;For your further encouragement, I will here relate a<lb break="yes"/>very remarkable instance of patient diligence and indomita-<lb break="no"/>ble perseverance.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>&#x201C;In the year 1827, after I had returned to Charleston<lb break="yes"/>from Scotland, and my classes were going on, a very respec-<lb break="no"/>table lawyer came to my school, I think some time in the<lb break="yes"/>month of October, with a youth apparently about sixteen, or<lb break="yes"/>perhaps not so much, (14,) of middle size, graceful in man-<lb break="no"/>ners, rather slender, but well formed, and, upon the whole,<lb break="yes"/>what I would call handsome; of a keen, piercing eye, and a<lb break="yes"/>noble forehead, seemingly the very seat of genius. The gen-<lb break="no"/>tleman stated that he found him given to study; that he had<lb break="yes"/>been about three weeks learning the Latin rudimen&#x2019;s, and<lb break="yes"/>(hoping, I suppose, to turn the youth&#x2019;s attention from the<lb break="yes"/>law to the ministry) had resolved to place him under my care<lb break="yes"/>for the purpose of learning Greek, Latin, and Mathematics,<lb break="yes"/>sufficient to enter Charleston College. I very gladly receiv-<lb break="no"/>ed him, for I immediately perceived he was no common<lb break="yes"/>youth, as intelligence beamed in his dark eye, and shone<lb break="yes"/>brightly on his countenance, indicating great ability, and an<lb break="yes"/>assurance of his future progress. I at once put him in the<lb break="yes"/>highest class, just beginning to read C&#x00E6;sar&#x2019;s Commentaries,<lb break="yes"/>and, although at first inferior, his prodigious memory and en-<lb break="no" />thusiastic application soon enabled him to surpass the best.<lb break="yes"/>He began Greek at the same time, and read with some who<lb break="yes"/>had been long at it, in which he also soon excelled. In short,<lb break="yes"/>in the space of one year, he had with the class, and at odd<lb break="yes"/>hours with myself, read four books of C&#x00E6;sar, Cornelius Ne-<lb break="no"/>pos, Sallust, six books of Virgil, nearly all Horace, and two<lb break="yes"/>books of Livy; and in Greek, all Graeca Minora, about the<lb break="yes"/>half of the first volume of Graeca Majora, and four books of<lb break="yes"/>Homer&#x2019;s Iliad. And whatever he read, he retained. It<lb break="yes"/>seemed to me, in fact, as if he learned by mere intuition. I<lb break="yes"/>was myself utterly astonished, and at the same time delighted,<lb break="yes"/>with his progress. I have hinted above that he was designed<lb break="yes"/>for the Church, but when I contemplated his bold, fearless<lb break="yes" />disposition, his powerful inventive genius, his admiration of<lb break="yes"/>warlike exploits, and his love of heroic and adventurous<lb break="yes"/>deeds, I did not think it likely he would be a minister of the<lb break="yes"/>Gospel. He had not, however, the least appearance of any<lb break="yes"/>vice whatever. On the contrary, he was always the very<lb break="yes"/>pattern of virtue and modesty. I could not help loving him,<lb break="yes"/>so much did he captivate me by his gentlemanly conduct and<lb break="yes"/>extraordinary progress. It was easy to see that he would one<lb break="yes"/>day raise himself to eminence. Whilst under my instruction,<lb break="yes"/>I discovered his early genius for poetic composition in the fol-<lb break="no"/>lowing manner. When the Greek class read the account<lb break="yes"/>that Herodotus gives of the battle of Marathon, the bravery of<lb break="yes"/>Miltiades and his ten thousand Greeks raised his patriotic<lb break="yes" />feelings to enthusiasm, and drew from him expressions which<lb break="yes"/>I thought were embodied in a few days afterwards in some<lb break="yes"/>well-written verses in a Charleston paper, on that far-famed<lb break="yes"/>unequal but successful conflict against tyranny and oppression;<lb break="yes"/>and, suspecting my talented scholar to be the author, I went<lb break="yes"/>to his desk, and asked him if he did not write them; and,<lb break="yes" />hesitating at first, rather blushingly he confessed he did. I<lb break="yes"/>then said, &#x2018;I knew you could do such things, and I suppose<lb break="yes"/>you have some such pieces by you which I should like to see.<lb break="yes"/>Do bring them to me.&#x2019; He consented, and in a day or two<lb break="yes"/>brought me a number, which I read with pleasure and admi-<lb break="no"/>ration at the strong marks of genius stamped on all, but<lb break="yes"/>here and there requiring, as I thought, a very slight amend-<lb break="no" />ment.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>&#x201C;I had hired a mathematician to teach both him and my-<lb break="no"/>self, (for I could not then teach that science,) and in this he<lb break="yes"/>also made such wonderful progress that, at the end of one<lb break="yes"/>year, he entered the junior class in Charleston College trium-<lb break="no"/>phantly, whilst others who had been studying four years and<lb break="yes"/>more were obliged to take the Sophomore class. About the end<lb break="yes"/>of the year 1828 I left Charleston, but I heard that he highly<lb break="yes" />distinguished himself, and graduated in 1830. After that he<lb break="yes"/>taught mathematics for some time. His career afterwards has<lb break="yes"/>been one of heroic adventure, of hair-breadth escapes by flood<lb break="yes"/>and field, and of scientific explorations, which have made<lb break="yes"/>him world-wide renowned. In a letter I received from him<lb break="yes"/>very lately, he expresses his gratitude to me in the following<lb break="yes"/>words: <hi rendition="#i">&#x2018;I am very far from either forgetting you, or ne-<lb break="no"/>glecting you, or in any way losing the old regard I had for<lb break="yes"/>you. There is no time to which I go back with more plea-<lb break="no"/>sure than that spent with you, for there was no time so<lb break="yes"/>thoroughly well spent; and of any thing I may have learned<lb break="yes"/>I remember nothing so well and so distinctly as what I ac-<lb break="no"/>quired with you.&#x2019;</hi> Here I cannot help saying that the merit<lb break="yes"/>was almost all his own. It is true that I encouraged and<lb break="yes"/>cheered him on, but if the soil into which I put the seeds of<lb break="yes"/>learning had not been of the richest quality, they never would<lb break="yes" />have sprung up to a hundred fold in the full ear. Such,<lb break="yes"/>my young friends, is but an imperfect sketch of my once be-<lb break="no"/>loved and favorite pupil, now a Senator, and who may yet<lb break="yes"/>rise to be at the head of this great and growing Republic.<lb break="yes"/>My prayer is that he may ever be opposed to war, injustice,<lb break="yes"/>and oppression of every kind, a blessing to his country, and<lb break="yes"/>an example of every noble virtue to the whole world.&#x201D;</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As many of our readers understand French, and might like<lb break="yes"/>to see the letters of the great <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt,</hi> the patriarch of<lb break="yes"/>science, and for fifty years at the head of the scientific world,<lb break="yes"/>and now in the eighty-second year of his age, we here give<lb break="yes"/>it in French, as copied from the original.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                            <salute>
                                <hi rendition="#i">Monsieur le Senateur:</hi>
                            </salute>
                            <p>Il m&#x2019;est bien doux, Monsieur, de<lb break="yes"/>vous adresser ces lignes par mon excellent ami, notre ministre<lb break="yes"/>aux Etats-Unis, M. de Gerolt. Après vous avoir donné dans<lb break="yes"/>la nouvelle édition de mes <hi rendition="#i">Tableaux de la Nature</hi> le témoignage<lb break="yes"/>publique de l&#x2019;admiration qui est due à vos gigantesques<lb break="yes"/>travaux entre St. Louis du Missouri et les c&#x00F4;tes de la mer du<lb break="yes"/>Sud, je me sens heureux de vous offrir, dans ce petit signe<lb break="yes"/>de vie, l&#x2019;hommage de ma vive reconnaisance. Vous avez<lb break="yes" />déployé un noble courage dans des expéditions lointaines,<lb break="yes"/>bravé tous les dangers des frimas et du manque de <choice><sic>nouriture</sic><corr type="editorial">nourriture</corr></choice>,<lb break="yes"/>enrichi toutes les parties de sciences naturelles, illustré un<lb break="yes"/>vaste pays qui nous était presque entièrement inconnu. Un<lb break="yes"/>mérite si rare a eté reconnu par un souverain, vivement<lb break="yes"/>interessé aux progrès de la géographie physique: le Roi<lb break="yes"/>m&#x2019;ordonne de vous offrir la grande médaille d&#x2019;or, destinée à<lb break="yes"/>ceux qui ont travaillé à des progrès scientifiques. J&#x2019;éspère<lb break="yes"/>que cette marque de la bienveillance royale vous sera agréable<lb break="yes" />dans un moment, où sur la proposition de l&#x2019;illustre géographe<lb break="yes" />Charles Ritter, la société de géographie résidant à Berlin<lb break="yes"/>vous a nommé pour membre honnoraire. Quant à moi je<lb break="yes"/>dois vous remercier particulièrement aussi de l&#x2019;honneur que<lb break="yes"/>vous m&#x2019;avez fait d&#x2019;attacher mon nom et celui de mon collabo-<lb break="no"/>rateur et ami intime M. Bonpland à des contrées voisines de<lb break="yes"/>celles qui ont été l&#x2019;objet de nos travaux. La Californie qui<lb break="yes"/>a <hi rendition="#i">noblement</hi> résisté à l&#x2019;introduction de l&#x2019;esclavage sera<lb break="yes"/>dignement représentée par un ami de la liberté et des progrès<lb break="yes"/>de l&#x2019;intelligence.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>Agreez, je vous prie, Monsieur le Sénateur, l&#x2019;expression<lb break="yes"/>de ma haute et affectueuse consideration.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <closer>
                                <salute>
                                    <hi rendition="#et">Votre t. h. et t. o. serviteur.<lb break="yes"/>A. V. HUMBOLDT.</hi>
                                </salute>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <dateline>A <hi rendition="#k">Sans-Souci</hi> le 7 octobre 1850.</dateline>
                            </closer>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <closer>On the envelope thus addressed:<lb break="yes"/>
                                <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;A Monsieur,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Monsieur le Colonel Frémont, Senateur.<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Avec la grade médaille d&#x2019;or<lb break="yes" />&#x201C;Pour les progrès dans les sciences.<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Baron <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi>&#x201D;</hi>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following is the English translation of Baron <hi rendition="#k">Hum-<lb break="no" />boldt</hi>&#x2019;s letter:<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">To Col. Fremont, Senator.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                            <p>It is very agreeable to me, sir, to address you these lines<lb break="yes"/>by my excellent friend, our Minister to the United States,<lb break="yes"/>Mr. de Gerolt. After having given you in the new edition<lb break="yes"/>of my &#x201C;Aspects of Nature&#x201D; the public testimony of the ad-<lb break="no"/>miration which is due to your gigantic labors between St.<lb break="yes"/>Louis, of Missouri, and the coasts of the South Sea, I feel<lb break="yes"/>happy to offer you, in this living token (dans ce petit signe<lb break="yes" />de vie) the homage of my warm acknowledgment. You<lb break="yes"/>have displayed a noble courage in distant expeditions, braved<lb break="yes"/>all the dangers of cold and famine, enriched all the branches<lb break="yes"/>of the natural sciences, illustrated a vast country which was<lb break="yes"/>almost entirely unknown to us. A merit so rare has been<lb break="yes"/>acknowledged by a sovereign warmly interested in the pro-<lb break="no"/>gress of physical geography; the King orders me to offer you<lb break="yes"/>the grand golden medal destined to those who have labored at<lb break="yes"/>scientific progress. I hope that this mark of the royal good<lb break="yes"/>will, will be agreeable to you at a time when, upon the<lb break="yes"/>proposition of the illustrious geographer, <hi rendition="#k">Char. Ritter,</hi> the<lb break="yes"/>Geographical Society at Berlin has named you an honorary<lb break="yes"/>member. For myself, I must thank you particularly also for<lb break="yes"/>the honor which you have done in attaching my name and<lb break="yes"/>that of my fellow-laborer and intimate friend, Mr. <hi rendition="#k">Bompland,</hi>
                                <lb break="yes"/>to countries neighboring to those which have been the object<lb break="yes" />of our labors. California, which has so nobly resisted the<lb break="yes"/>introduction of slavery, will be worthily represented by a<lb break="yes"/>friend of liberty and of the progress of intelligence.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>Accept, I pray you, sir, the expression of my high and affectionate consideration.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <closer>
                                <salute>
                                    <hi rendition="#et">Your most humble and most obedient servant,<lb break="yes"/>A. V. HUMBOLDT.</hi>
                                </salute>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <dateline>
                                    <hi rendition="#k">Sans Souci, October 7, 1850.</hi>
                                </dateline>
                            </closer>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <closer>On the envelope thus addressed:<lb break="yes"/>
                                <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;To Colonel Fremont, Senator.<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;With the great Golden Medal<note place="foot" n="*)">The following is the description of the medal:<lb break="yes"/>Of fine gold, massive, more than double the size of the<lb break="yes"/>American double eagle, and of exquisite workmanship. On<lb break="yes"/>the face is the medallion head of the King, Frederic William<lb break="yes"/>the Fourth, surrounded by figures emblematical of Religion,<lb break="yes"/>Jurisprudence, Medicine, and the Arts. On the reverse,<lb break="yes"/>Apollo, in the chariot of the sun, drawn by four high-mettled<lb break="yes"/>plunging horses, traversing the zodiac, and darting rays of<lb break="yes"/>light from his head.</note>
                                    <lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;For progress in the sciences.<lb break="yes"/>
                                    <hi rendition="#k">&#x201C;Baron Humboldt.</hi>&#x201D;</hi>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>The following is the public testimony of the Baron&#x2019;s admi-<lb break="no"/>ration of the gigantic labors of <hi rendition="#k">Fremont</hi>, referred to in the<lb break="yes"/>letter, as contained in the new, or third edition of his Aspects<lb break="yes"/>of Nature, and which, as a reference, becomes a natural ap-<lb break="no" />pendant to the letter:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Fremont&#x2019;s map and geographical investigations compre-<lb break="no"/>hend the extensive region from the junction of the Kanzas<lb break="yes"/>river with the Missouri to the falls of the Columbia, and to<lb break="yes"/>the missions of Santa Barbara and Puebla de los Angeles, in<lb break="yes"/>New California; or a space of 28 degrees of longitude, and<lb break="yes"/>from the 34th to the 45th parallel of latitude. Four hundred<lb break="yes" />points have been determined hyposometrically by barometric<lb break="yes"/>observations, and, for the most part, geographically by astro-<lb break="no"/>nomical observations; so that a district which, with the wind-<lb break="no"/>ings of the route, amounts to 3,600 geographical miles, from<lb break="yes"/>the mouth of the Kanzas to Fort Vancouver and the shores<lb break="yes"/>of the Pacific, (almost 720 miles more than the distance from<lb break="yes" />Madrid to Tobolsk,) has been represented in profile, showing<lb break="yes"/>the relative heights above the level of the sea. As I was, I<lb break="yes"/>believe, the first person who undertook to represent, in geog-<lb break="no"/>nostic profile, the form of entire countries&#x2015;such as the Iberian<lb break="yes"/>peninsula, the high lands of Mexico, and the Cordilleras of<lb break="yes"/>South America, (the semi-perspective projections of a Sibe-<lb break="no"/>rian traveller, the Abbe Chappe, were founded on mere and<lb break="yes" />generally ill-judged estimations of the fall of rivers) &#x2015;it has<lb break="yes"/>given me peculiar pleasure to see the geographical method of<lb break="yes"/>representing the form of the earth in a vertical direction, or<lb break="yes"/>the elevation of the solid portion of our planet above its wa-<lb break="no"/>tery covering, applied on so grand a scale as has been done in<lb break="yes"/>Fremont&#x2019;s map.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 