<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="127" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>HUMBOLDT AND FREMONT.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/> From the New York Courier and Enquirer.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>To honor him as a Pioneer of American Dis-<lb break="no"/>covery, the King of Prussia presented to Colonel<lb break="yes"/>John C. Fremont &#x201C;the great Golden Medal of<lb break="yes"/>Progress in the Sciences.&#x201D; The Medal is of<lb break="yes"/>fine gold, massive, more than double the size<lb break="yes"/>of the American double eagle, and of exquisite<lb break="yes" />workmanship. On the face, is the medallion<lb break="yes"/>head of the King, Frederick William IV, sur-<lb break="no"/>rounded by figures emblematical of Religion,<lb break="yes"/>Jurisprudence, Medicine, and the Arts. On<lb break="yes"/>the reverse, Apollo, in the chariot of the sun,<lb break="yes" />drawn by four high-mettled, plunging horses,<lb break="yes"/>traversing the zodiac, and darting rays of light<lb break="yes"/>from his head. This beautiful tribute to the<lb break="yes"/>merit of Colonel Fremont came to him accom-<lb break="no"/>panied with a complimentary letter from Baron<lb break="yes" />Humboldt, of which the following is a transla-<lb break="no"/>tion:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <div n="2" type="letter">
                            <opener>
                                <salute>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">To Colonel Fremont, Senator:</hi>
                                </salute>
                            </opener>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;It is very agreeable to me, sir, to address<lb break="yes" />you these lines by my excellent friend, our Min-<lb break="no" />ister to the United States, M. De Gerolt. After<lb break="yes" />having given you, in the new edition of my<lb break="yes" />&#x2018;Aspects of Nature,&#x2019; the public testimony of<lb break="yes"/>the admiration which is due to your gigantic<lb break="yes"/>labors between St. Louis of Missouri, and the<lb break="yes"/>coast of the South Sea, I feel happy to offer you<lb break="yes"/>in this living token (<hi rendition="#i" >dans ce petit signe devie</hi>)<lb break="yes"/>the homage of thy warm acknowledgment.<lb break="yes"/>You have displayed a noble courage in distant<lb break="yes"/>expeditions, braved all the colds and famine,<lb break="yes"/>enriched all the branches of the natural sciences,<lb break="yes"/>illustrated a vast country which was almost en-<lb break="no"/>tirely unknown to us.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;A merit so rare has been acknowledged by<lb break="yes"/>a Sovereign warmly interested in the progress<lb break="yes"/>of physical Geography; the King orders me to<lb break="yes"/>offer you the Grand Golden Medal destined to<lb break="yes"/>those who have labored at scientific progress.<lb break="yes"/>I hope that this mark of the Royal good will<lb break="yes"/>will be agreeble to you at a time when, upon<lb break="yes"/>the proposition of the illustrious geographer,<lb break="yes"/>Charles Ritter, the Geographical Society at<lb break="yes"/>Berlin has named you an honorary member.<lb break="yes"/>For myself, I must thank you particularly also<lb break="yes"/>for the honor which you have done in attaching<lb break="yes"/>my name, and that of my fellow-laborer and in-<lb break="no"/>timate friend, Mr. Bompland, to those which<lb break="yes"/>have been the objects of our labors. California,<lb break="yes"/>which has so nobly resisted the introduction of<lb break="yes"/>Slavery, will be worthily represented by a friend<lb break="yes"/>of Liberty, of the progress of intelligence.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;Accept, I pray you, sir, the expression of<lb break="yes"/>my high and affectionate consideration.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;Yourst most humble and most obedient ser-<lb break="no" />vant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <salute>
                                    <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;A. V. <hi rendition="#k" >Humboldt.</hi>
                                    </hi>
                                </salute>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <dateline>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Sans Souci, October</hi> 7, 1850.&#x201D;</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following is the public testimony of the<lb break="yes"/>Baron&#x2019;s admiration of the gigantic labors of<lb break="yes"/>Fremont, referred to in the letter, as contained<lb break="yes"/>in a new or third edition of his &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Aspects of<lb break="yes"/>Nature,</hi>&#x201D; and which, as a reference, becomes a<lb break="yes"/>natural appendant to the letter:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Fremont&#x2019;s map and geographical investiga-<lb break="no"/>tions comprehend the extensive region from the<lb break="yes"/>junction of the Kansas river with the Missouri,<lb break="yes"/>to the falls of the Columbia, and to the missions<lb break="yes"/>of Santa Barbara and Puebla de los Angeles, in<lb break="yes"/>New California; or space of 28 degrees of lon-<lb break="no" />gitude, and from the 34th to the 45th parallel<lb break="yes"/>of latitude. Four hundred points have been<lb break="yes"/>determined hyposmeritically by barometric ob-<lb break="no"/>servations, and from the most part geographi-<lb break="no"/>cally by astronomical observations; so that a<lb break="yes" />distance which, with the windings of the route,<lb break="yes"/>amounts to 3,600 geographical miles, from the<lb break="yes"/>mouth of the Kansas to Fort Vancouver and<lb break="yes"/>the shores of the Pacific, (almost 750 miles<lb break="yes"/>more than the distance from Madrid to Tobolsk,)<lb break="yes" />has been represented in profile, showing the<lb break="yes"/>relative heights above the level of the sea.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;As I was, I believe, the first person who<lb break="yes"/>undertook to represent, in geognostic profile,<lb break="yes"/>the form of entire countries&#x2014;such as the Iberian<lb break="yes"/>Peninsula, the high lands of Mexico, and the<lb break="yes"/>Cordilleras of South America, (the semi-per-<lb break="no"/>spective projections of a Siberian traveller, the<lb break="yes"/>Abbe Chappe, were founded on mere and gen-<lb break="no" />erally ill-judged estimations to the fall of<lb break="yes"/>rivers,) it has given me peculiar pleasure to see<lb break="yes"/>the geographical method of representing the<lb break="yes"/>form of the earth in a vertical direction, or the<lb break="yes"/>elevations of the solid portion of our planet<lb break="yes"/>above its watery covering, applied on so grand<lb break="yes" />a scale as has been done in Fremont&#x2019;s map.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 