<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-12-12" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <pb facs="#f0002"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Animacul&#x00E6; in the Air</hi>.</head>
                <p>&#x2014;The celebrated Prus-<lb break="no"/>sian naturalist, M. Ehrenberg, says Humboldt, has<lb break="yes"/>discovered, by microscopic observations that the<lb break="yes"/>dust, or yellow sand which falls like rain on the<lb break="yes"/>Atlantic, near the Cape de Verde Islands, and is<lb break="yes" />sometimes transported to Italy, and even the mid-<lb break="no"/>dle of Europe, consists of a multitude of silicious,<lb break="yes"/>shelled, microscopic animals. &#x201C;Perhaps,&#x201D; says<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt, &#x201C;many of them float for years in the<lb break="yes"/>upper stratum of the atmosphere, until they are<lb break="yes"/>brought down by vertical currents of the trade-<lb break="no"/>winds, still susceptible of revivification, and mul-<lb break="no"/>tiplying their species by spontaneous division, in<lb break="yes"/>conformity with the particular laws of their organ-<lb break="no"/>ization.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>But besides creatures fully formed, continues<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt, the atmosphere contains innumerable<lb break="yes"/>germs of future life, such as the eggs of insects and<lb break="yes"/>the seeds of plants: the latter provided with light,<lb break="yes"/>hairy, and leathery appendages, by means of which<lb break="yes"/>they are wafted through the air during long autum-<lb break="no"/>nal wanderings. Even the fertilizing dust or pol-<lb break="no" />len sexes are separated, and carried over land and<lb break="yes"/>sea by winds and by the agency of winged insects<lb break="yes"/>to the solitary female plants on the opposite shores.<lb break="yes"/>Thus, wherever the glance of the inquirer into<lb break="yes"/>nature penetrates, he sees the continual dissemina-<lb break="no"/>tion of life, either fully formed or in the germ.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We do not know where life is most abundant&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>whether on the continents or in the unfathomed<lb break="yes"/>depths of ocean. Through an excellent work of<lb break="yes"/>Ehrenberg, we have seen the sphere of organic life<lb break="yes"/>extend, and its horizon widen before our eyes,<lb break="yes"/>both in the tropical parts of the ocean, and<lb break="yes"/>in the fixed or floating masses of ice in the an-<lb break="no"/>tartic seas. Silicious-shelled polygastrico, and<lb break="yes"/>even coscimodic&#x00E6;, with their green ovaries, have<lb break="yes"/>been found alive enveloped in masses of ice, only<lb break="yes"/>twelve degrees from the Pole; the small black gla-<lb break="no"/>cier flea and pondupell&#x00E6; inhabit the narrow tubular<lb break="yes"/>holes examined by Agassiz, in the Swiss glaciers.<lb break="yes"/>Ehrenberg has shown that on several microscopic<lb break="yes" />infusoria others live as parasites; and that in the<lb break="yes" />gallionell&#x00E6;, such is the prodigious power of develop-<lb break="no" />ment, or capacity of division, &#x201C;that in the space<lb break="yes"/>of four days, an animalcul&#x00E6; inviaible to the naked<lb break="yes"/>eye can form two cubic feet of the Bilin polishing<lb break="yes"/>slate!&#x201D; In the sea, gelatinous worms, living or<lb break="yes"/>dead shine like stars and by their phosphoric light,<lb break="yes"/>change the surface of the ocean into a sea of fire.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Ineffaceable is the impression made on my mind<lb break="yes"/>by the calm nights of the torrid zone on the waters<lb break="yes"/>of the Pacific. I still see the dark azure of the fir-<lb break="no"/>mament, the constellation of ships near the zenith,<lb break="yes"/>and that of the Cross declining towards the horizon,<lb break="yes"/>shedding through the perfumed air their soft and<lb break="yes"/>planetary lustre; while bright furrows of flashing<lb break="yes"/>light marked the Dolphin&#x2019;s track through the midst<lb break="yes"/>of the foaming waves. Not only the ocean, but also<lb break="yes"/>the waters of our marshes hide from us an innumer-<lb break="no"/>able multitude of strange forms. The naked eye<lb break="yes" />can with difficulty distinguish the cylindias, the<lb break="yes"/>euglenas, and the hosts of naiads, divisible by<lb break="yes"/>branches like the lemna or duckweed, of which<lb break="yes"/>they seek the shade<choice><sic></sic><corr type="editorial">.</corr></choice> Other creatures inhabit re-<lb break="no"/>ceptacles where the light cannot penetrate, and an<lb break="yes"/>atmosphere variously composed, but different from<lb break="yes"/>that which we breathe. Such are the reported<lb break="yes" />ascaris which live beneath the skin of the worm,<lb break="yes"/>the leuceptera, of a bright silvery color, in the in-<lb break="no"/>terior of the shore daiab, and a pentastoma, which<lb break="yes"/>inhabit the large pulmonary cells of the rattlesnake<lb break="yes"/>of the tropics. There are animalcul&#x00E6; in the blood<lb break="yes"/>of frogs and of salmon; and even, according to<lb break="yes"/>Noreman, in the fluid of the eyes of fishes, and in<lb break="yes"/>the gills of the bleak.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 