<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-23" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt and Fremont.</hi>
                </head>
                <p>&#x2014;To honor him as a pio-<lb break="no"/>neer of American discovery, the King of Prussia<lb break="yes"/>presented to Col. John C. Fremont &#x201C;the great Golden<lb break="yes"/>Medal of Progress in the Sciences.&#x201D; The medal is of<lb break="yes"/>fine gold, massive, more than double the size of the<lb break="yes"/>American double eagle, and of exquisite workman-<lb break="no"/>ship. On the face is the medallion head of the King,<lb break="yes"/>Frederick William the Fourth, surrounded by figures<lb break="yes"/>emblematical of religion, jurisprudence, medicine and<lb break="yes"/>the arts. On the reverse, Apollo, in the chariot of the<lb break="yes"/>sun, drawn by four high mettled, plunging horses,<lb break="yes"/>traversing the zodiac and darting rays of light from<lb break="yes"/>his head. This beautiful tribute to the merit of Col.<lb break="yes"/>Fremont came to him accompanied with a compli-<lb break="no" />mentary letter from Baron Humboldt, of which the<lb break="yes"/>following is a translation:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <div n="2" type="letter">
                            <opener>
                                <salute>
                                    <hi rendition="#i">To Colonel John C. Fremont:</hi>
                                </salute>
                            </opener>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;It is very agreeable to me, air, to address you these<lb break="yes"/>lines by my excellent friend, our minister to the<lb break="yes"/>United States, M. de Gerolt. After having given you<lb break="yes"/>in the new edition of my &#x2018;Aspects of Nature,&#x2019; the<lb break="yes"/>public testimony of the admiration which is due to<lb break="yes"/>your gigantic labors between St. Louis, of Missouri,<lb break="yes"/>and the coasts of the South Sea, I feel happy to offer<lb break="yes"/>you, in this living token (<hi rendition="#i">dans ce petit sig@ da vie</hi>)<lb break="yes"/>the homage of my warm acknowledgment. You<lb break="yes"/>have displayed a noble courage in distant expeditions,<lb break="yes"/>braved all the dangers of cold and famine, enriched<lb break="yes"/>all the branches of the natural sciences, illustrated a<lb break="yes"/>vast country which was almost entitely unknown to<lb break="yes"/>us.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;A merit so rare has been acknowledged by a sov-<lb break="no" />ereign warmly interested in the progress of physical<lb break="yes"/>geography; the King orders me to offer you the grand<lb break="yes"/>golden medal destined to those who have labored at<lb break="yes"/>scientifie progress. I hope that this mark of the<lb break="yes"/>Royal good will, will be agreeable to you at a time<lb break="yes"/>when, upon the proposition of the illustrious geo-<lb break="no"/>grapher, Charles Ritter, the Geographical Society at<lb break="yes"/>Berlin has named you as an honorary member. For<lb break="yes"/>myself, I must thank you particularly also for the<lb break="yes"/>honor which you have done in attaching my name<lb break="yes"/>and that of my fellow-laborer and intimate friend,<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Bonpland, to countries neighboring to those which<lb break="yes"/>have been the object of our labors. California, which<lb break="yes"/>has so nobly resisted the introduction of slavery, will<lb break="yes"/>be worthily represented by a friend of liberty, and of<lb break="yes"/>the progress of intelligence.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;Accept, I pray you, sir, the expression of my<lb break="yes" />high and affectionate consideration.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <p>&#x201C;Your most humble and most ob&#x2019;t serv&#x2019;t.</p>
                            <lb break="yes"/>
                            <closer>
                                <salute>
                                    <hi rendition="#et">A. V. HUMBOLDT.</hi>
                                </salute>
                                <lb break="yes"/>
                                <dateline>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Sa@s Souci,</hi> October 7, 1850.&#x201D;</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On the envelope thus addressed:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;To Colonel Fremont, Senator,<lb break="yes"/>With the great Golden Medal,<lb break="yes"/>For progress in the sciences,<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#k">Baron Humboldt.</hi>&#x201D;</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following is the public testimony of the Ba-<lb break="no"/>ron&#x2019;s admiration of the gigantic labors of Fremont,<lb break="yes"/>referred to in the letter, as contained in the new or<lb break="yes"/>third edition of his &#x201C;Aspects of Nature,&#x201D; an@,<lb break="yes"/>as a reference, becomes a natural appendant to the<lb break="yes"/>letter:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Fremont&#x2019;s map and geographical investigations<lb break="yes"/>comprehend the extensive region from the junction of<lb break="yes"/>the Kansas river with the Missouri, to the falls of the<lb break="yes"/>Columbia, and to the missions of the Santa Barbara<lb break="yes"/>and Puebla de los Angeles, in New California; or a<lb break="yes"/>space of 28 degrees of longitude, and from the 24th<lb break="yes"/>to the 43d parallel of latitude. Four hundred points<lb break="yes"/>have been determined hyposometrically by barome-<lb break="no" />tric obe&#x00EB;rvations, and, for the most part, geographi-<lb break="no" />cally by astronomical observations; so that a district<lb break="yes"/>which, with the windings of the route, amounts to<lb break="yes"/>3600 geographical miles, from the mouth of the Kan-<lb break="no"/>sas, to&#x2019; Fort Vancouver and the shores of the Pacific,<lb break="yes"/>(almost 720 miles more than the distance from Mad-<lb break="no"/>rid to Tobolsk,) has been represented in profile, show-<lb break="no"/>ing the relative heights above the level of the sea.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;As I was, I believe, the first person who under-<lb break="no"/>took to represent, in geognostic profile the form of<lb break="yes"/>entire countries&#x2014;such as the Iberian peninsula, the<lb break="yes"/>high lands of Mexico, and the Cordilleras of South<lb break="yes"/>America, (the semi-perspective projections of a Sibe-<lb break="no"/>rian traveller, the Abbe Chappe, were founded on<lb break="yes"/>mere and generally ill-judged estimations of the fall<lb break="yes"/>of rivers)&#x2014;it has given me peculiar pleasure to see<lb break="yes"/>the geographical method of representing the form of<lb break="yes"/>the earth in a virtual direction, or the elevations of<lb break="yes"/>the solid portion of our planet above its watery cover-<lb break="no"/>ing, applied on so grand a scale as has been done in<lb break="yes"/>Fremont&#x2019;s map.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 