<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>

<pb n="19" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">letter from baron humboldt.</hi></head><lb/><p>To <hi rendition="#k">Col. Fremont</hi>, <hi rendition="#i">Senator:</hi>&#x2014;It is very<lb/>agreeable to me, sir, to address you these lines<lb/>by my excellent friend, our Minister to the<lb/>United States, N. de Gerold. After having<lb/>given you, in the new edition of my &#x201C;Aspects<lb/><pb n="20" facs="#f0002" />
of Nature,&#x201D; the public testimony of the admi-<lb/>ration which is due to your gigantic labors be-<lb/>t een St. Louis, of Missouri, and the coasts<lb/>of the South Sea, I feel happy to offer you, in<lb/>this little token of my existence (<hi rendition="#i">dans ce petit<lb/>signe de vie</hi>), the homage of my warm ac-<lb/>knowledgment. You have displayed a noble<lb/>courage in distant expeditions, braved all the<lb/>dangers of cold and famine, enriched all the<lb/>branches of the natural sciences, illustrated<lb/>a vast country which was almost entirely un-<lb/>known to us.</p><lb/><p>A merit so rare has been acknowledged by<lb/>a sovereign warmly interested in the progress<lb/>of physical geography; the king orders me to<lb/>offer you the grand golden medal destined to<lb/>those who have labored at scientific progress.<lb/>I hope that this mark of the Royal good will<lb/>will be agreeable to you at a time when, upon<lb/>the proposition of the illustrious geographer,<lb/>Chas. Ritter, the Geographical Society at Ber-<lb/>lin has named you an honorary member. For<lb/>myself, I must thank you particularly also for<lb/>the honor which you have done in attaching<lb/>my name and that of my fellow-laborer and<lb/>intimate friend, Mr. Bonpland, to countries<lb/>neighboring to those which have been the ob-<lb/>ject of our labors. <hi rendition="#i">California, which has so<lb/>nobly resisted the introduction of Slavery, will<lb/>be worthily represented by a friend of liberty<lb/>and of the progress of intelligence.</hi></p><lb/><p>Accept, I pray you, sir, the expression of<lb/>my high and affectionate consideration.</p><lb/><p>Your most humble and most obedient ser-<lb/>vant,</p><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">A. VON HUMBOLDT.</hi></salute></closer><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#i">Sans Souci</hi>, October 7, 1850.</dateline></div><lb/>
    <div><p>On the envelope thus addressed:</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#et">To Colonel Fremont, Senator,<lb/>With the Great Golden Medal<lb/>For Progress in the Sciences.<lb/><hi rendition="#k">Baron Humboldt.</hi></hi></p></div><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
