<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#b">Humboldt and Fremont.</hi></head><lb/><p>Among the scientific honors paid to Col.<lb/>Fremont, as a pioneer of American discove-<lb/>ry, certainly not the least notable was that<lb/>conferred by the King of Prusia in &#x201C;the<lb/>great Golden Medal of Progress in the Sci-<lb/>ences.&#x201D; The manner of its communication<lb/>added a rare value to the gift. It was sent<lb/>with a most complimentary letter of Baron<lb/>Humboldt, who took occasion to add the<lb/>warmest expressions of his own personal re-<lb/>spect and admiration. As this letter has<lb/>apparently been overlooked in the notices<lb/>recently made of Fremont by the press, we<lb/>avail ourselves of the advance sheets of the<lb/>new biography in the course of publication<lb/>by Derby &amp; Co., of this city, to lay it before<lb/>our readers. One sentence of Humboldt&#x2019;s<lb/>letter we have marked in italics; it was a<lb/>conscientious tribute paid to the Senator<lb/>then; it is highly significant of Fremont&#x2019;s<lb/>&#x201C;friendship to liberty and to the &#x201C;progress of<lb/>intelligence&#x201D; <hi rendition="#i">now.</hi></p><lb/><p>The following <choice><sic>in</sic><corr type="editorial">is</corr></choice>the English translation of<lb/>Baron Humboldt&#x2019;s letter:</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">To Col. Fremont,</hi> <hi rendition="#i">Senator</hi>&#x2014;It is very<lb/>agreeable to me, Sir, to address you these<lb/>lines by my excellent friend, our Minister to<lb/>the United States, <choice><sic>N</sic><corr type="editorial">M</corr></choice>. de Gerolt. After hav-<lb/>ing given you, in the new edition of my &#x2018;As-<lb/>pects of Nature,&#x2019; the public testimony of the<lb/>admiration which is due to your gigantic<lb/>labors between St. Louis, of Missouri, and<lb/>the coasts of the South Sea, I feel happy to<lb/>offer you, in this living token, (<hi rendition="#i">dans ce petit<lb/>signe de vie,</hi>) the homage of my warm ac-<lb/>knowledgment. You have displayed a noble<lb/>courage in distant expeditions, braved all the<lb/>dangers of cold and famine, enriched all the<lb/>branches of the natural sciences, illustrated a<lb/>vast country which was almost entirely un-<lb/>known to us.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;As merit so rare has been acknowledged<lb/>by a sovereign warmly interested in the
                    pro-<lb/>gress of physical geography; the King orders<lb/>me to offer you the
                    grand golden medal des-<lb/>tined to those who have labored at
                    scientific<lb/>progress. I hope that this mark of the Roy-<lb/>al good will,
                    will be agreeable to you at a<lb/>time when, upon the proposition of the
                    il-<lb/>lustrious geographer, Chas. Ritter the Geo-<lb/>graphical Society at
                    Berlin has named you<lb/>an honorary member. For myself I must<lb/>thank you
                    particularly also for the honor<lb/>which you have done in attaching my
                    name<lb/>and that of my fellow laborer and intimate<lb/>friend, Mr. Bonpland, to
                    countries neighbor-<lb/>ing to those which have been the object of<lb/>our
                    labors. <hi rendition="#i">California, which has so nobly<lb/>resisted the
                        introduction of Slavery, will be<lb/>worthily represented by a friend of
                        Liberty<lb/>and of the progress of intelligence.</hi></p><lb/><closer><salute>&#x201C;Accept, I pray you, Sir the expression of<lb/>my high and affectionate
                        consideration.<lb/>&#x201C;Your most humble and most obedient
                            servant<lb/><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;A. V. HUMBOLDT.</hi></salute></closer><lb/><dateline>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Sans Souci,</hi> October 7, 1850.&#x201D;</dateline><lb/>
    </div>
    <div>
        <p><hi rendition="#et">On the envelope thus addressed:<lb/>&#x201C;To Colonel Fremont.
                        Senator.<lb/>&#x201C;With the great Golden Medal<note place="foot" n="*">The
                            following is the description of the medal:<lb/>&#x201C;Of fine gold,
                            massive, more than double the size of the<lb/>American double eagle, and
                            of exquisite workmanship.&#x2014;<lb/>On the face is the medallion head
                            of the King, Frederic-<lb break="maybe"/>William the Fourth, surrounded
                            by figures emblematical<lb/>of Religion, Jurisprudence, Medicine, and
                            the Arts. On<lb/>the <choice>
                                <sic>revese</sic>
                                <corr type="editorial">reverse</corr>
                            </choice>, <choice>
                                <sic>Appollo</sic>
                                <corr type="editorial">Apollo</corr>
                            </choice>, in the chariot of the Sun, drawn by<lb/>four high-mettled,
                            plunging horses, traversing the zodiac,<lb/>and darting rays of light
                            from his head.&#x201D;</note><lb/>&#x201C;For progress in the
                            sciences.<lb/>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Baron
                        Humboldt.</hi>&#x201D;</hi></p><lb/><p>The following is the public testimony of<lb/>the Baron&#x2019;s <choice><sic>administration</sic><corr type="editorial">admiration</corr></choice> of the gigantic<lb/>labors of Fremont, referred to in the letter,<lb/>as contained in the new or third editions of<lb/>his &#x201C;Aspects of Nature,&#x201D; and which, as a<lb/>reference, becomes a natural appendant to<lb/>the letter:</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Fremont&#x2019;s map and geographical investi-<lb/>gations comprehend the extensive
                    region<lb/>from the junction of the Kansas River with<lb/>the Missouri to the
                    Falls of the Columbia and<lb/>to the missions of Santa Barbara and Puebla<lb/>de
                    los Angeles, in New California; or a space<lb/>of 28 degrees of longitude, and
                    from the 34th<lb/>to the 45th parallel of <choice>
                        <sic>latisude</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">latitude</corr>
                    </choice>. Four hun-<lb/>dred points have been determined hyposome-<lb/>trically
                    by barometric observations, and, for<lb/>the most part, geographically by
                    astronomi-<lb/>cal observations; so that a district which,<lb/>with the winding
                    of the route, amounts to<lb/>3,600 geographical miles, from the mouth of<lb/>the
                    Kansas to Fort Van Couver and the<lb/>shores of the Pacific, (almost 720 miles
                    more<lb/>than the distance from Madrid to Tobolsk,)<lb/>has been represented in
                    profile, showing the<lb/>relative hights above the level of the sea.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;As I was, I believe, the first person who<lb/>undertook to represent, in geognostic
                    profile,<lb/>the form of entire countries&#x2014;such as the<lb/>Iberian
                    Peninsula, the high lands of Mexico,<lb/>and the Cordilleras of South America,
                    (the<lb/>semi-perspective projections of a Siberian<lb/>traveler, the Abbe
                    Chappe, were founded on<lb/>mere and generally ill-judged estimations of<lb/>the
                    fall of rivers)&#x2014;it has given me peculiar<lb/>pleasure to see the
                    geographical method of<lb/>representing the form of the earth in a
                    verti-<lb/>cal direction, on the elevations of the solid<lb/>portion of our
                    planet above its watery cover-<lb/>ing, applied on so grand a scale as has
                    been<lb/>done in Fremont&#x2019;s map.&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
