<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#b">Humboldt and Fremont.</hi></head><lb/><p>Among the scientific honors paid to Col.<lb/>Fremont, as a pioneer of American
                    discovery,<lb/>certainly not the least notable, was that con-<lb/>ferred by the
                    King of Prussia, in &#x201C;the great<lb/>Golden Medal of Progress in the
                    Sciences.&#x201D;&#x2014;<lb/>The manner of its communication added a
                    rare<lb/>value to the gift. It was sent with a most<lb/>complimentary letter to
                    Baron Humboldt, who<lb/>took occasion to add the warmest expressions<lb/>of his
                    own personal respect and admiration.&#x2014;<lb/>As this letter has apparently
                    been overlooked<lb/>in the notices recently made of Fremont by the<lb/>press, we
                    avail ourselves of the advance sheets<lb/>of the new biography in the course of
                    publica-<lb/>tion by Derby &amp; Co., of this city, to lay it be-<lb/>fore our
                    readers. One sentence of Humboldt&#x2019;s<lb/>letter we have marked in italics;
                    it was a con-<lb/>scientious tribute paid to the Senator then; it<lb/>is highly
                    significant of Fremont&#x2019;s &#x201C;friendship<lb/>to liberty,&#x201D; and
                    to the &#x201C;progress of intelligence&#x201D;<lb/><hi rendition="#i"
                        >now.</hi></p><lb/><p>The following is the English translation of<lb/>Baron Humboldt&#x2019;s letter:</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;To Col. <hi rendition="#k">Fremont,</hi> Senator&#x2014;It is very<lb/>agreeable to me, sir, to address you these lines<lb/>by my excellent friend, our Minister to the<lb/><choice><sic>Uuited</sic><corr type="editorial">United</corr></choice> States, <choice><sic>N</sic><corr type="editorial">M</corr></choice>. de Gerolt. After having<lb/>given you, in the new edition of my &#x201C;Aspects<lb/>of Nature,&#x201D; the public testimony of the admi-<lb/>ration which is due to your gigantic labors be-<lb/>tween St. Louis, Mo. and the coasts of the<lb/>South Sea, I feel happy to offer you, in this<lb/>living token, (<hi rendition="#i">dans de petit signe de vie,</hi>) the<lb/>homage of my warm acknowledgement. You<lb/>have displayed a noble courage in distant ex-<lb/>peditions, braved all the dangers of cold and<lb/>famine, enriched all the branches of the nat-<lb/>ural sciences, illustrated a vast country which<lb/>was almost entirely unknown to us.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;A merit so rare has been acknowledged by<lb/>a sovereign warmly interested in the progress<lb/>of physical geography; the King orders me to<lb/>offer you the grand golden medal destined to<lb/>those who have labored at scientific progress.<lb/>I hope that this mark of the Royal good will<lb/>be agreeable to you at a time when, upon the<lb/>proposition of the illustrious geographer, Chas.<lb/><choice><sic>Ritner</sic><corr type="editorial">Ritter</corr></choice>, the Geographical Society at Berlin has<lb/>named you an honorary member. For my-<lb/>self, I must thank you particularly also for the<lb/>honor which you have done in attaching my<lb/>name and that of my fellow laborer and inti-<lb/>mate friend, Mr. Bonpland, to countries neigh-<lb/>boring to those which have been the object<lb/>of our labors. California which has so nobly<lb/>resisted the introduction of Slavery, will be<lb/>worthily represented by <hi rendition="#i">a friend of Liberty</hi><lb/>and of the progress of intelligence.</p><lb/><closer><salute>&#x201C;Accept, I pray you, Sir, the expression of<lb/>my high and affectionate consideration:<lb/>Your most humble and obedient servant,<lb/><hi rendition="#et">A. A. HUMBOLDT.&#x201D;</hi></salute></closer><lb/><dateline>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Sans Souci,</hi> Oct. 7, 1850.</dateline><lb/>
    </div>
    <div>
    <p><hi rendition="#et">On the envelope was thus addressed:<lb/>&#x2018;To Colonel Fremont,
                        Senator.<lb/>&#x2018;With the great Golden Medal<note place="foot" n="*">The
                            following is the description of the<lb/>medal.<lb/>&#x201C;Of fine gold,
                            massive, more than double<lb/>the size of the American double eagle, and
                            of<lb/>exquisite workmanship. On the face is the<lb/>medallion head of
                            the King, Frederic William<lb/>the Fourth, surrounded by figures
                            emblemati-<lb/>cal of Religion, Jurisprudence, Medicine, and<lb/>the
                            Arts. On the reverse, <choice><sic>Appollo</sic><corr type="editorial">Apollo</corr></choice>, in the<lb/>chariot of the Sun, drawn by
                            four high-met-<lb/>taled, plunging horses, traversing the
                            zodiac,<lb/><choice><sic>add</sic><corr type="editorial">and</corr></choice> darting rays of light from his
                        head.&#x201D;</note><lb/>&#x2018;For progress in the
                            Sciences.<lb/>&#x2018;<hi rendition="#k">Baron
                        Humboldt.</hi>&#x2019;</hi></p><lb/><p>The following is the public testimony of the<lb/>Baron&#x2019;s admiration of the gigantic labors of Fre-<lb/>mont, referred to in the letter, as contained in<lb/>the new or third edition of his &#x201C;Aspects of<lb/>Nature,&#x201D; and which, as a reference, becomes<lb/>a natural appendant to the letter:</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Fremont&#x2019;s map and geographical investi-<lb/>gations comprehend the extensive
                    region from<lb/>the the junction of Kansas river with the Mis-<lb/>souri to the
                    Falls of Columbia, and to the Mis-<lb/>sions of Santa Barbara and Puebla de los
                    Ang-<lb/>elos, in New California; or a space of 28 de-<lb/>grees of longitude,
                    and from the 34th to the<lb/>45th parallel of latitude. Four hundred
                    points<lb/>have been determined hyposometrically by<lb/>barometric observation,
                    and, for the most part,<lb/>geographically by astronomical observations;<lb/>so
                    that a district which, with the windings of<lb/>the route, amounts to 3,600
                    geographical miles<lb/>from the mouth of the Kansas to Fort Van<lb/>Couver and
                    the shores of the Pacific, (almost<lb/>720 miles more than the distance from
                    Mad-<lb/>rid to Tobolsk,) has been represented in pro-<lb/>file, showing the
                            relative heights above the<lb/>level of the sea.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;As I was, I believe, the first person who<lb/>undertook to represent, in geognostic profile,<lb/>the form of entire countries&#x2014;such as the Ibe-<lb/>rian Peninsula, the highlands of Mexico, and<lb/>the Cordilleras of South America, (the semi-<lb break="maybe"/>perspective projections of a Siberian traveler<lb/>the Abbe Chappe, were founded on mere and<lb/>generally ill-judged estimations of the <choice><sic>falls</sic><corr type="editorial">fall</corr></choice> of<lb/>the rivers,)&#x2014;it has given me peculiar pleasure<lb/>to see the geographical method of representing<lb/>the form of the earth in a vertical direction, or<lb/>the elevations of the solid portion of our planet<lb/>above its watery covering, applied on so grand<lb/>a scale as has been done in Fremont&#x2019;s map.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
