<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Velocity of light</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:15</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VII.25</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1851-Velocity_of_Light-2-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1851-Velocity_of_Light-1-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1851-Velocity_of_Light-2-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem type="related">
        <bibl>&lt;i&gt;Cosmos: Sketch of a Physical Description of the Universe. &lt;/i&gt;Translated by Edward Sabine. Vol. 3, London 1851, S. 71–77.&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;Alexander von Humboldt, &lt;i&gt;Kosmos. Entwurf einer physischen Weltbeschreibung&lt;/i&gt;, Band 3, Stuttgart und Tübingen: J. G. Cotta 1850, S. 90–97.</bibl>
      </relatedItem>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Velocity of light</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1852</date>
          <pubPlace>Boston, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in:&lt;i&gt; Annual of scientific discovery, or, year-book of facts in science and art&lt;/i&gt; (1852), S. 138–141.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="138" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">velocity of light.</hi></head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">On</hi> the subject of the velocity of light, and the probability that
                    it<lb/>requires a certain time for its propagation, we find the earliest
                    view<lb/>expressed by Francis Bacon, in the second book of the Novum
                    Or-<lb/>ganum. He speaks of the time required by a ray of light to
                    traverse<lb/>the immensity of space, and throws out the question whether the
                    stars<lb/>still exist which we now see sparkle. One is astonished at finding
                    so<lb/>happy a conjecture in a work whose celebrated author was so far<lb/>below
                    some of his contemporaries in mathematical, astronomical and<lb/>physical
                    knowledge. The velocity of the reflected solar light was<lb/>measured by Römer,
                    November, 1675, by comparison of the times of<lb/>occultation of
                    Jupiter&#x2019;s satellites, and the velocity of the direct light<lb/>of the
                    fixed stars by Bradley&#x2019;s great discovery of the aberration of<lb/>light,
                    made in the autumn of 1727. In very recent times a third<lb/>method of
                    measurement has been proposed by Arago, by the phenome-<lb/>non of the light of
                    a variable star; for example, Algol in Perseus. We<lb/><pb n="139" facs="#f0002"
                    /> have to add to these astronomical methods a terrestrial
                    measurement,<lb/>which has recently been executed with great ingenuity and
                    success by<lb/>M. Fizeau, in the neighborhood of Paris.<note place="foot" n="*"
                            ><hi rendition="#i">Annual Scientific Discovery</hi>, 1850, Vol. I., pp.
                        145&#x2014;147.</note> It recalls to recollection<lb/>an attempt of
                    Galileo&#x2019;s with two lanterns, which did not lead to any<lb/>result. From
                    Römer&#x2019;s first observations of Jupiter&#x2019;s satellites, Hor-<lb/>rebow
                    and Du Hamel estimated the time occupied in the passage of<lb/>light from the
                    sun to the earth, at their mean distance apart, at 14&#x2032;
                    7&#x2033;;<lb/>Cassini at 14&#x2032; 10&#x2033;; Newton, which is very striking,
                    much nearer to<lb/>the truth, at 7&#x2032; 30&#x2033;. Delambre, by taking into
                    account, among the<lb/>observations of his time, only those of the first
                    satellite, found 8&#x2032; 13&#x2033;.2.<lb/>Encke has very justly remarked how
                    important it would be, with the<lb/>certainty of obtaining the more accordant
                    results which the present<lb/>perfection of telescopes would afford, to
                    undertake a series of occulta-<lb/>tions of Jupiter&#x2019;s satellites, for the
                    express purpose of deducing the<lb/>velocity of light. From Bradley&#x2019;s
                    observations of aberration, recently<lb/>discovered by Rigaud, of Oxford, there
                    follows, according to the inves-<lb/>tigation of Dr. Busch, of Konigsberg, for
                    the passage of light from<lb/>the sun to the earth 8&#x2032; 12&#x2033;.64; for
                    the velocity of the light of the stars<lb/>167,976 geographical miles in a
                    second; but from the more recent<lb/>aberration observations of Struve, made for
                    eighteen months with the<lb/>large transit instrument at Pulkowa, it appears
                    that the first of these<lb/>numbers must be considerably increased. The result
                    of Struve&#x2019;s great<lb/>investigation is 8&#x2032; 17&#x2033;, which gives
                    for the velocity of light 166,196<lb/>geographical miles in a second; the
                    probable error of this velocity<lb/>scarcely amounts to eight geographical
                    miles.</p><lb/><p>M. Fizeau has succeeded in executing a terrestrial measurement of<lb/>the velocity of light, by
                    means of an ingeniously devised apparatus, in<lb/>which the artificial star,
                    like the light of oxygen and hydrogen, is<lb/>returned to the point from whence
                    it came by a mirror placed at the<lb/>distance of 8633 metres (28,324 English
                    feet); a disc furnished with<lb/>720 teeth, which made 12.6 revolutions in a
                    second, alternately stopped<lb/>the ray of light and allowed it to pass freely
                    between the teeth of the<lb/>limb. From the indications of a counter, it was
                    inferred that the arti-<lb/>ficial light traversed 17,266 metres (56,648 English
                    feet), or twice the<lb/>distance between the stations, in one eighteen
                    thousandth of a second<lb/>of time; whence there results a velocity of 167,528
                    geographical<lb/>miles in a second. This result comes nearest to that of
                    Delambre,<lb/>derived from Jupiter&#x2019;s satellites, which is 167,976
                    geographical miles.<lb/>Direct observations, and ingenious considerations on the
                    absence of<lb/>any alteration of color during the change of light of variable
                    stars,<lb/>have led Arago to the conclusion that rays of light which have
                    differ-<lb/>ent colors, and therefore very different lengths and rapidities of
                    trans-<lb/>verse vibration, move through space with equal velocities; but that
                    in<lb/>the interior of the different bodies through which the colored rays
                    pass,<lb/>their rates of propagation and their refractions are different.
                    Arago&#x2019;s<lb/>observations have shown, that in the prism the refraction is
                    not altered<lb/>by the relation which the velocity of light bears to that of the
                    earth&#x2019;s<lb/>motion. All the measurements accord in the result, that the
                    light of<lb/><pb n="140" facs="#f0003"/> the stars towards which the earth is
                    advancing has the same index of<lb/>refraction as the light of the stars from
                    which the earth is receding.<lb/>The celebrated observer we have just named
                    said, that bodies send<lb/>forth rays of all velocities, but that among these
                    different velocities<lb/>there is only one which can awaken the sensation of
                    light. If we com-<lb/>pare the velocities of solar, sidereal and terrestrial
                    light, which all<lb/>comport themselves exactly in the same manner in the prism,
                    with the<lb/>velocity of the current of friction-electricity, we are inclined to
                    assign<lb/>to the latter, according to the experiments devised with
                    admirable<lb/>ingenuity by Wheatstone, a velocity superior to the former in the
                    ratio<lb/>of at least three to two. According to the lowest results of
                    Wheat-<lb/>stone&#x2019;s optical rotating apparatus, the electric current
                    traverses 288,000<lb/>English statute miles, or 250,000 geographical miles, in a
                    second. If,<lb/>then, we reckon with Struve for sidereal light in the aberration
                    observa-<lb/>tions 166,196 geographical miles in a second, we get a difference
                    of<lb/>83,804 geographical miles in a second for the greater velocity of
                    the<lb/>electric current. This result appears to contradict the
                    previously<lb/>mentioned view of William Herschel, which regarded the light of
                    the<lb/>sun and of the fixed stars as perhaps the effect of an
                    electro-magnetic<lb/>process, &#x2014; a perpetual aurora. I say appears to
                    contradict; for it can-<lb/>not be deemed impossible that, in the different
                    luminous bodies of<lb/>space, there may be several magneto-electric processes
                    very different in<lb/>kind, and in which the light produced by the process may
                    have a differ-<lb/>ent rate of propagation. To this possible conjecture must be
                    added the<lb/>uncertainty of the numerical result obtained with
                    Wheatstone&#x2019;s appa-<lb/>ratus, which result he himself regards as
                    &#x201C;not sufficiently established,<lb/>and as requiring fresh
                    confirmation,&#x201D; in order to be compared satisfac-<lb/>torily with the
                    deductions from aberrations and satellite observations.<lb/>Later experiments,
                    made by Walker, in the United States, on the veloc-<lb/>ity of the propagation
                    of electricity, on the occasion of his telegraphic<lb/>determination of the
                    longitudes of Washington, Philadelphia, New<lb/>York and Cambridge, have excited
                    a lively interest in the minds of<lb/>physical inquirers.<note place="foot"
                        n="*"><hi rendition="#i">Annual Scientific Discovery</hi>, 1850, Vol. I.,
                        pp. 124&#x2014;127.</note></p><lb/><p>Measurements made with conductors 1050 English statute miles, or<lb/>968 geographical miles, in
                    length, gave, from 18 equations of condi-<lb/>tion, the rate of propagation of
                    the hydro-galvanic current at only 18,700<lb/>statute, or 16,240 geographical
                    miles in a second, that is, fifteen times<lb/>slower than the electric current
                    in Wheatstone&#x2019;s rotating disc appa-<lb/>ratus. As in Walker&#x2019;s
                    remarkable experiments two wires were not<lb/>used, and but half the conduction
                    according to the common expression,<lb/>took place through the moist body of the
                    earth, it might seem a justi-<lb/>fiable supposition that the velocity of the
                    propagation of electricity is<lb/>dependent on the nature as well as on the
                    dimensions of the medium. In<lb/>the voltaic current bad conductors become more
                    heated than good con-<lb/>ductors, and electric discharges are very variously
                    complicated phe-<lb/>nomena, as appears by the latest experiments of Reiss. The
                    now<lb/>prevailing views of what is commonly called &#x201C;connection through
                    the<lb/>earth&#x201D; are opposed to the view of linear conduction between
                        the<lb/><pb n="141" facs="#f0004"/> two ends of the wire, and to the
                    conjectures of impediments to conduc-<lb/>tion, and of accumulation and
                    discharges in a current; as that which<lb/>was once regarded as intermediate
                    conduction in the earth is now<lb/>supposed to belong only to an equalization or
                    to a restoration of elec-<lb/>tric tension. Although, according to the present
                    limits of exactness<lb/>in this kind of observation, it is probable the
                    aberration is constant,<lb/>and, therefore, the velocity of light, of all the
                    fixed stars, is the same,<lb/>yet the possibility has more than once been spoken
                    of that there may<lb/>be luminous bodies in space whose light does not reach us
                    because,<lb/>from their enormous mass, gravitation constrains the luminous
                    par-<lb/>ticles to return. &#x2014; <hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s
                        Cosmos.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
