<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="381" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">animalcul&#x00E6; in the air.</hi></head><lb/><p>The celebrated Prussian naturalist, M. Ehren-<lb/>berg, says Humboldt, has discovered, by mi-<lb/>croscopic observations that the dust, or yellow<lb/>sand which falls like rain on the Atlantic, near<lb/>the Cape de Verde Islands, and is sometimes<lb/>transported to Italy, and even the middle of Eu-<lb/>rope, consists of a multitude of silicious, shell-<lb/>ed, microscopic animals. &#x201C;Perhaps,&#x201D; says Hum-<lb/>boldt, &#x201C;many of them float for years in the<lb/>upper stratum of the atmosphere, until they are<lb/>brought down by vertical currents of the trade-<lb/>winds, still susceptible of revivification, and<lb/>multiplying their species by spontaneous divi-<lb/>sion, in conformity with the particular laws of<lb/>their organization.</p><lb/><p>But besides creatures fully formed, continues<lb/>Humboldt, the atmosphere contains innumerable<lb/>germs of future life, such as the eggs of insects<lb/>and the seeds of plants: the latter provided with<lb/>light, hairy, and leathery appendages, by means<lb/>of which they are wafted through the air during<lb/>long autumnal wanderings. Even the fertiliz-<lb/>ing dust or pollen sexes are separated, and car-<lb/>ried over land and sea by winds and by the agen-<lb/>cy of winged insects to the solitary female plants<lb/><cb/>
on the opposite shores. Thus, wherever the<lb/>glance of the inquirer into nature penetrates, he<lb/>sees the continual dissemination of life, either<lb/>fully formed or in the germ.</p><lb/><p>We do not know where life is most abundant<lb/>&#x2014;whether on the continent or in the unfathomed<lb/>depths of ocean. Through an excellent work of<lb/>Ehrenberg, we have seen the sphere of organic<lb/>life extend, and its horizon widen before our<lb/>eyes, both in the tropical parts of the ocean, and<lb/>in the fixed or floating masses of ice in the an-<lb/>tarctic seas. Silicious shelled polygastrico, and<lb/>even coscimodic&#x00E6;, with their green ovaries, have<lb/>been found alive enveloped in masses of ice, only<lb/>twelve degrees from the Pole; the small black<lb/>glacier flea and pondupell&#x00E6; inhabit the narrow<lb/>tubular holes examined by Agassiz, in the Swiss<lb/>glaciers. Ehrenberg has shown that on several<lb/>microscopic infusoria others live as parasites;<lb/>and that in the gallionell&#x00E6;, such is the prodigious<lb/>power of development, or capacity of division,<lb/>&#x201C;that in the space of four days, an animalcul&#x00E6;<lb/>invisible to the naked eye can form two cubic<lb/>feet of the Billin polished slate!&#x201D; In the sea,<lb/>gelatinous worms, living or dead, shine like stars<lb/>and by their phosphoric light, change the sur-<lb/>face of the ocean into a sea of fire.</p><lb/><p>Ineffaceable is the impression made on my<lb/>mind by the calm nights of the torrid zone
                    on<lb/>the waters of the Pacific. I still see the dark<lb/>azure of the
                    firmament, the constellation of ships<lb/>near the zenith, and that of the Cross
                    declining<lb/>towards the horizon, shedding through the per-<lb/>fumed air their
                    soft and planetary lustre; while<lb/>bright furrows of flashing light marked the
                    Dol-<lb/>phin&#x2019;s track through the midst of the foaming<lb/>waves. Not
                    only the ocean, but also the wa-<lb/>ters of our marshes hide from us an
                    innumerable<lb/>multitude of strange forms. The naked eye can<lb/>with
                    difficulty distinguish the cylindias, the<lb/>euglenas, and the hosts of naiads,
                    divisible by<lb/>branches like the lemna or duckweed, of which<lb/>they seek the
                    shade. Other creatures inhabit<lb/>receptacles where the light cannot penetrate,
                    and<lb/>an atmosphere variously composed, but different<lb/>from that which we
                    breathe. Such are the re-<lb/>ported ascaris which live beneath the skin of
                    the<lb/>worm, the leuceptera, of a bright silvery color,<lb/>in the interior of
                    the shore daiab, and a pentas-<lb/>toma, which inhabit the large pulmonary
                    cells<lb/>of the rattlesnake of the tropics. There are ani-<lb/>macul&#x00E6; in
                    the blood of frogs and of salmon;<lb/>and even, according to <choice><sic>Noreman</sic><corr type="editorial">Nordmann</corr></choice>, in the
                    fluid of<lb/>the eyes of fishes, and in the gills of the bleak.&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
