<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Letter from Baron Alexander von Humboldt to Lionel Gisborne, Esq., M.A., C.E.</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:17</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VII.49</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1853-Junction_of_the-20-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-20-neu.xml" type="self"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Letter from Baron Alexander von Humboldt to Lionel Gisborne, Esq., M.A., C.E.</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1853</date>
          <pubPlace>Sydney</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Empire&lt;/i&gt; 913 (14. Dezember 1853), Beilage, [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Letter from Baron Alexander von Humboldt<lb/>
                    to Lionel Gisborne, Esq., M.A., C.E.</hi><lb/>
                    (Translated from the French original.)</hi></p>
                <lb/>
                <div n="2" type="letter">
                    <p>&#x201C;Sir&#x2014;I trust you will excuse the oldest among<lb/>
                        the travellers in both the tropics of America and<lb/>
                        the steppes of Siberia, for having so long delayed<lb/>
                        to thank you for the information I derived from<lb/>
                        your interesting journal, &amp;c., on the junction of<lb/>
                        the Atlantic with the Pacific. The position I<lb/>
                        occupy in this country, and the ardent desire I<lb/>
                        feel to finish, before my death, some scientific<lb/>
                        works which I had the imprudence to begin, con-<lb/>
                        siderably interrupt the even course of my corres-<lb/>
                        pondence. I therefore hope that I shall meet, on<lb/>
                        your part also, with that indulgence which your<lb/>
                        countrymen have shown me during so long a<lb/>
                        period.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;I have not been beyond the Rio Rimo, which<lb/>
                        lies east of the mouth of the Atrato, since the<lb/>
                        time when I left the island of Cuba on my way<lb/>
                        to Lima by Bogota, Quito, and the river Amazon,<lb/>
                        for the purpose of observing the passage of<lb/>
                        Mercury through the solar disc. I was then upon<lb/>
                        friendly terms with a very intelligent merchant,<lb/>
                        Don Ignacio Iombo, of Cartagena, in America,<lb/>
                        and I recollect that the <hi rendition="#i">Casso</hi> (Treasury convoy)<lb/>
                        of Guayaquil was then on its way to Europe, by<lb/>
                        the road from Cupica to the Atrato, which was first<lb/>
                        opened by the Biscayian pilot Poguerache. Know-<lb/>
                        ing, geologically, the interruption of the mountain<lb/>
                        chains, and the depression of the range in the<lb/>
                        eastern part of the Isthmus, my attention has re-<lb/>
                        mained fixed during this last half century on the<lb/>
                        Bay of San Miguel, and the route from Cupica to<lb/>
                        the Rio Napipi. Owing to my friendly relations<lb/>
                        with General Bolivar, I obtained through him<lb/>
                        the first line of levels across the Isthmus of Pa-<lb/>
                        nama. Ever since, the subject has not ceased to<lb/>
                        occupy my mind, as the various works and maps<lb/>
                        which I published since 1810, and my correspon-<lb/>
                        dence with various statesmen, will testify. But<lb/>
                        all my striving and urging only led to imperfect<lb/>
                        trials, and projects calculated for a line to the<lb/>
                        west of the meridian of Panama and Portobello,<lb/>
                        none of which ever gained my confidence. I had,<lb/>
                        however, the gratification of seeing my views<lb/>
                        honoured by an eminent member of Her Britan-<lb/>
                        nic Majesty&#x2019;s navy, Captain Fitzroy. (<hi rendition="#i">Journal<lb/>
                            of the Royal Geographical Society</hi>, vol. xx., p.<lb/>
                        20.)</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;The increase of human knowledge, and the<lb/>
                        immense progress of science, arts, and industry<lb/>
                        among the western nations, have given us powers<lb/>
                        which only call for application. Everything de-<lb/>
                        pends upon energy and perseverance. I there-<lb/>
                        fore congratulate you, Sir, and your courageous<lb/>
                        friend, Dr. Cullen, as well as Sir Charles Fox,<lb/>
                        Mr. Henderson, and Mr. Brassey, for having<lb/>
                        given your names to so noble an undertaking. I<lb/>
                        have always considered, firstly, the opening of an<lb/>
                        oceanic canal, without locks; and secondly, the<lb/>
                        cut at Huchnecoca, in the valley of Mexico (which<lb/>
                        is on a comparatively smaller scale, as may be<lb/>
                        seen by the map and section I published), as two<lb/>
                        events calculated highly to improve the relations<lb/>
                        between the different families of the human spe-<lb/>
                        cies. In fact, such a work as the one you con-<lb/>
                        template will bring Eastern Asia nearer to the<lb/>
                        nations of Europe and America. It will render<lb/>
                        the whole globe more easy to be travelled over&#x2014;<lb/>
                        this little globe, of which Christopher Columbus,<lb/>
                        in one of his letters to the Queen of Spain, said,<lb/>
                        &#x2018;<hi rendition="#i">el mundo es poco.</hi>&#x2019; It will facilitate the diffu-<lb/>
                        sion of productions, especially of precious metals,<lb/>
                        of which the relative value (1 to 15 5-6ths) would<lb/>
                        change too suddenly without this &#x2018;permeability&#x2019;<lb/>
                        of the world.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;As early as the discovery of the new conti-<lb/>
                        nent, civilisation had spread, in a direction from<lb/>
                        north to south, over those portions of America<lb/>
                        which lie opposite to Asia, those on the European<lb/>
                        side being then occupied by barbarous hunting<lb/>
                        tribes. The finest harbours, the most precious<lb/>
                        products are likewise found in the West. Even<lb/>
                        the currents of the air, by their direction, con-<lb/>
                        tribute towards the preponderance of West<lb/>
                        American power over the rich countries of Asia.<lb/>
                        The increasing importance of the west coast of<lb/>
                        America promises to balance, at some future<lb/>
                        time, the surprising progress of the Atlantic<lb/>
                        States, provided the Western States keep them-<lb/>
                        selves free from that hideous disease&#x2014;slavery of<lb/>
                        coloured people.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;Indeed, Sir, I feel the most ardent wishes for<lb/>
                        the happy success of this oceanic canal. The at-<lb/>
                        tention which the public of the two continents<lb/>
                        bestows already upon your undertaking will in-<lb/>
                        crease, as soon as you will be enabled, assisted by<lb/>
                        further explorations, and a survey extending<lb/>
                        over all details, and carried on by a great number<lb/>
                        of experienced men, to publish, on a large scale,<lb/>
                        maps and sections of the line fixed upon between<lb/>
                        Puerto Escoces and the Gulf of San Miguel. The<lb/>
                        changes which the success of the undertaking is<lb/>
                        sure to effect in the international commerce of<lb/>
                        the world will only disturb such people as in the<lb/>
                        narrowness of their own views oppose themselves<lb/>
                        to the natural and Providential course of events,<lb/>
                        and shed tears over the unfortunate discovery of<lb/>
                        America. The Rio Huaxacualco with its portage<lb/>
                        to the Rio Chimalapa (Tehuantepec), of which I<lb/>
                        published the first map after the itineraries dis-<lb/>
                        covered by me in the archives of the vice-king-<lb/>
                        dom of Mexico, will always be of great impor-<lb/>
                        tance, owing to its position opposite Louisiana,<lb/>
                        in the Gulf of Mexico, which has all the appear-<lb/>
                        ance of soon becoming a <hi rendition="#i">mare clausum</hi>&#x2014;a lake<lb/>
                        of the United States. The nature of the soil,<lb/>
                        however, does not allow great works to<lb/>
                        be carried out in that locality; be-<lb/><cb/>
                        sides, you know the difficulties impeding<lb/>
                        any canalisation or rectification of rivers of great<lb/>
                        length, and the great variations of the volume of<lb/>
                        water, as in the river San Juan; but a railway<lb/>
                        would be a great advantage to the southern States.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;The great interest which every one at the<lb/>
                        present time takes in the canalization of the<lb/>
                        Isthmus recalls a similar fact to my memory,<lb/>
                        reminding me of the sudden interest created by<lb/>
                        the discovery of guano.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;I was the first who brought guano to Europe,<lb/>
                        of which Klaproth and Vauquelin published an<lb/>
                        analysis. During 40 years I preached, but al-<lb/>
                        ways in vain, the usefulness of this substance, and<lb/>
                        in vain did I recommend its employment in ferti-<lb/>
                        lizing the fields of Europe. But it is only 15 or<lb/>
                        18 years since it has at last become a great article<lb/>
                        of commerce.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;I beg of you, my dear Sir, to present my kind<lb/>
                        remembrance to the excellent and able Mr.<lb/>
                        Peterman, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rendition="#et">
                                &#x201C;ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT.
                            </hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>&#x201C;P.S.&#x2014;I am not surprised at the difference<lb/>
                            between the level you found at Turbaco and my<lb/>
                            own statement. To this, however, I had prudently<lb/>
                            added, &#x2018;doubtful barometrical observation.&#x2019; (See<lb/>
                            my <hi rendition="#i">Recueil d&#x2019;Observations Astronomiques et de<lb/>
                                Mesures Barométriques,</hi> vol, i. p. 299.) The<lb/>
                            fact that the gas issuing from the little volcanoes<lb/>
                            at Turbaco is inflammable in its natural state has<lb/>
                            already been communicated by Colonel Acosta<lb/>
                            (<hi rendition="#i">Journal</hi>, p. 65). It appears that the gaseous<lb/>
                            fluid which issues from the &#x2018;salses&#x2019; is not the<lb/>
                            same at all times. I find in my journal that, in<lb/>
                            1801, the flame of any burning substance was<lb/>
                            suddenly extinguished on being thrown into a<lb/>
                            bottle containing air from those little volcanoes.</p>
                        <p>&#x201C;Parrot, also, in the mud volcanoes in the<lb/>
                            island of Taman, found only azote, although the<lb/>
                            gas emitted would burn at other times. (See my<lb/>
                            <hi rendition="#i">Relation Historique</hi>, vol. xii., chap. 29, p. 367&#x2014;<lb/>
                            371.)&#x201D;</p>
                    </postscript>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 