<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="3" facs="#f0001" />


<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">A CHEAPER LIGHT THAN GAS.</hi></head><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<p>On the road leading to the port, we were forcibly struck by a<lb/>spectacle which our stay of two
                    years, in the hottest part of the<lb/>tropics might have rendered familiar to
                    us, but, previously, I<lb/>had nowhere seen such an innumerable quantity of
                    phos-<lb/>phorescent insects. The grass that overspread the ground,
                    the<lb/>branches and foliage of the trees, all shone with that reddish<lb/>and
                    moveable light, which varies in its intensity at the will of<lb/>the animal by
                    which it is produced. It seemed as though the<lb/>starry firmament reposed on
                    the savannah. In the hut of the<lb/>poorest inhabitant of the country, fifteen
                    cocuyos, placed in a<lb/>calabash pierced with holes, afford sufficient light to
                    search for<lb/>anything during the night. To shake the calabash forcibly
                    is<lb/>all that is necessary to excite the animal to increase the
                    intensity<lb/>of the luminous discs situated on each side of its body.
                    The<lb/>people of the country remark, with a simple truth of
                    expression,<lb/>that calabashes filled with cocuyos are lanterns always
                    ready<lb/>lighted. They are, in fact, only extinguished by the sickness
                    or<lb/>death of the insects, which are easily fed with a little sugar<lb/>cane.
                    A young woman at Trinidad de Cuba told us, that<lb/>during a long and difficult
                    passage from the main land, she<lb/>always made use of the phosphorescence of
                    the cocuyos when<lb/>she gave suck to her child at night; the captain of the
                    ship<lb/>would allow no other light on board, for fear of the
                        corsairs.&#x2014;<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels.</hi></p></div>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
