<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="3" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>JUNCTION OF ATLANTIC AND PACIFIC OCEANS.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following is the translation of a letter on<lb break="yes"/>this subject addressed by Baron <hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von<lb break="yes" />Humboldt</hi> to Mr <hi rendition="#k">Lionel Gisborne,</hi> of London:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Sir:</hi> I trust you will excuse the oldest among the tra-<lb break="no"/>vellers in both the tropies of America and the steppes<lb break="yes"/>of Siberia for having so long delayed to thank you for<lb break="yes"/>the information I derived from your interesting journal,<lb break="yes"/>&#x0026;c. on the junction of the Atlantie with the Pacific. The<lb break="yes"/>position I occupy in this country, and the ardent desire<lb break="yes"/>I feel to finish, before my death, some scientific works<lb break="yes"/>which I had the imprudence to begin, considerably inter-<lb break="no"/>rupted the even course of my correspondence. I there-<lb break="no"/>fore hope that I shall meet, on your part also, with that<lb break="yes"/>indulgence which your countrymen have shown me dur-<lb break="no"/>ing so long a period.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have not been beyond the Rio Rimo, which lies east<lb break="yes"/>of the mouth of the Atrato. It was at the time when I<lb break="yes"/>left the island of Cuba on my way to Lima, by Bogota,<lb break="yes"/>Quito, and the River Amazon, for the purpose of observ-<lb break="no"/>ing the passage of Mercury through the solar dise. I was<lb break="yes"/>then on friendly terms with a very intelligent merchant,<lb break="yes"/>Don Tynacio Tombo, of Carthagena, in America; and I<lb break="yes"/>recollect that the Casso (treastiry convoy) of Guayaquil<lb break="yes"/>was then on its way to Europe, by the road from Capica<lb break="yes"/>to the Atrato, which was first opened by the Biscayian<lb break="yes"/>pilot Poguerache. Knowing geologically the interruption<lb break="yes"/>of the mountain chains, and the depression of the range<lb break="yes"/>in the eastern part of the Isthmus, my attention has re-<lb break="no"/>mained fixed, during this last half century, on the Bay of<lb break="yes"/>San Miguel, and the route from Cupica to the Rio<lb break="yes"/>Napipi.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Owing to my friendly relations with Gen. Bolivar, I ob-<lb break="no"/>tained through him the first line of levels across the Isth-<lb break="no"/>mus of Panama. Ever since the subject has not ceased<lb break="yes"/>to occupy my mind, as the various works and maps which<lb break="yes"/>I published since 1810 and my correspondence with va-<lb break="no"/>rious statesmen will testify. But all my striving and<lb break="yes"/>urging only led to imperfect trials and projects calcu-<lb break="no"/>lated for a line to the west of the meridian of Panama<lb break="yes"/>and Portobello, none of which ever gained my confidence.<lb break="yes"/>I had, however, the gratification of seeing my views hon-<lb break="no"/>ored by an eminent member of her Britannic Majesty&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>Navy, Capt. Fitzroy. (Journal of the Royal Georgian<lb break="yes"/>Society, vol. xx., 2.) The increase of human knowledge,<lb break="yes"/>and the immense progress of science, arts, and industry<lb break="yes"/>among the western nations, have given us powers which<lb break="yes"/>only call for application.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Every thing depends upon energy and perseverance.<lb break="yes"/>I therefore congratulate you, sir, and your courageous<lb break="yes"/>friend, Mr. Cullen, as well as Sir Charles Fox, Mr. Hen-<lb break="no"/>derson, and Mr. Brassey, for having given your names to<lb break="yes"/>so noble an undertaking. I have always considered,<lb break="yes"/>firstly, the opening of an oceanic canal without locks,<lb break="yes"/>and, secondly, the cut at Huchnecoca, in the valley of<lb break="yes"/>Mexico, (which is on a comparatively smaller scale, as<lb break="yes"/>may be seen from the map and section published,) as two<lb break="yes"/>events calculated highly to improve the relations between<lb break="yes"/>the different families of the human species. In fact, such<lb break="yes"/>a work as the one you contemplate will bring Eastern<lb break="yes"/>Asia nearer to the nations of Europe and America. It<lb break="yes"/>will render the whole globe more easy to be travelled<lb break="yes"/>over; this little globe, of which Christopher Columbus,<lb break="yes"/>in one of his letters to the Queen of Spain said, &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">El<lb break="yes"/>mundo cepoco.</hi>&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It will facilitate the diffusion of productions, especially<lb break="yes"/>of precious metals, of which the relative value (1 to 15<lb break="yes"/>5-6) would change too suddenly without this &#x201C;permea-<lb break="no"/>bility&#x201D; of the world.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As early as the discovery of the new continent, civili-<lb break="no"/>zation had spread, in a direction from north to south,<lb break="yes"/>over those portions of America which lie opposite to Asia,<lb break="yes"/>those on the European side being then occupied by bar-<lb break="no"/>barous hunting tribes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The finest harbors, the most precious products are like-<lb break="no"/>wise found in the west.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Even the currents of the air, by their direction, con-<lb break="no"/>tribute towards the preponderance of West American<lb break="yes"/>power over the rich countries of Asia. The increasing<lb break="yes"/>importance of the west coast of America promises to ba-<lb break="no"/>lance, at soxie future time, the surprising progress of the<lb break="yes"/>Atlantic States, provided the Western States keep them-<lb break="no"/>selves free from that hideous disease, slavery of colored<lb break="yes"/>pe@ple.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Indeed, sir, I feel the most ardent wishes for the happy<lb break="yes"/>success of this oceanic canal. The attention which the<lb break="yes"/>public of the two continents bestow already upon your<lb break="yes"/>undertaking will increase as soon as you will be enabled,<lb break="yes"/>assisted by forther explorations and a survey extending<lb break="yes"/>over all details, and carried on by a great number of ex-<lb break="no"/>perienced men, to publish on a large scale maps and sec-<lb break="no"/>tions of the line fixed upon between Puerto Escoces and<lb break="yes"/>the Gulf of San Miguel. The changes which the success<lb break="yes"/>of the undertaking is sure to effect in the international<lb break="yes"/>commerce of the world will only disturb such people as,<lb break="yes"/>in the narrowness of their views, oppose themselves to<lb break="yes"/>the natural and providential course of events, and shed<lb break="yes"/>tears over the unfortunate discovery of America. The<lb break="yes"/>Rio Huaxacualco, with its portage to the Rio Chimalapa,<lb break="yes"/>(Tehuantepec,) of which I published the first map after<lb break="yes"/>the itineraries discovered by me in the archives of the<lb break="yes"/>Vice Kingdom of Mexico, will always be of great im-<lb break="no"/>portance, owing to its position opposite Louisiana, in the<lb break="yes"/>Gulf of Mexico, which has all the appearance of soon<lb break="yes"/>becoming a <hi rendition="#i">mare clau@um</hi>&#x2014;a lake of the United States.<lb break="yes"/>The nature of the soil, however, does not allow great<lb break="yes"/>works to be carried out in that locality; besides, you<lb break="yes"/>know the difficulties impeding any canalization or recti-<lb break="no"/>fication of rivers of great length, and the great varia-<lb break="no"/>tions of the volume of water, as in the river San Juan.<lb break="yes"/>But a railway would be a great advantage to the Southern<lb break="yes"/>States.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The great interest which every one at the present time<lb break="yes"/>takes in the canalization of the Isthmus recalls a similar<lb break="yes"/>fact to my memory, reminding me of the sudden interest<lb break="yes"/>created by the discovery of guano. I was the first who<lb break="yes"/>brought guano to Europe, of which Klaproth and Vau-<lb break="no"/>quelin published an analysis. During forty years I<lb break="yes"/>preached, but always in vain, the usefulness of this sub-<lb break="no"/>stance, and in vain did I recommend its employment in<lb break="yes"/>fertilizing the fields in Europe; but it is only fifteen or<lb break="yes"/>eighteen years since it has at last become a great article<lb break="yes"/>of commerce.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I beg of you, my dear sir, to present my kind remem-<lb break="no"/>brances to the excellent and able Mr. Petermann, @<lb break="yes"/>to, &#x0026;c.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#et">ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT.</hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <postscript>
                    <p>P. S. I am not surprised at the difference between the<lb break="yes"/>level you found at Turbaco and my own statement. To<lb break="yes"/>this, however, I had prudently added &#x201C;doubtful barome-<lb break="no"/>trical observation.&#x201D; [See my &#x201C;Recueil d&#x2019;Observations<lb break="yes"/>Astronomiques et de Mesures Barometriques,&#x201D; vol. 1, p.<lb break="yes"/>299.] The fact that the gas issuing from the little vol-<lb break="no"/>canoes at Turbaco is inflammable in its natural state has<lb break="yes"/>already been communicated by Col. Acosta. [Journal, p.<lb break="yes"/>65.] It appears that the gaseous fluid which issues from<lb break="yes"/>the salses is not the same at all times. I find in my jour-<lb break="no"/>nal that in 1801 the flame of any burning substance was<lb break="yes"/>suddenly extinguished on being thrown into a bottle con-<lb break="no"/>taining air from those little volcanoes. Parrot also, in<lb break="yes"/>the mud volcanoes in the island of Taman, found only<lb break="yes"/>azote, although the gas emitted would burn at other<lb break="yes"/>times. [See my &#x201C;Relation Historique,&#x201D; vol. 15, chap.<lb break="yes"/>29, pp. 367-371.]</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 