<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-12-12" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="160" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">the study of nature.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In considering the study of physical phenomena, not<lb break="yes"/>merely in its bearings on the material wants of life, but in<lb break="yes"/>its general influence on the intellectual advancement of<lb break="yes"/>mankind, we find its noblest and most important result to<lb break="yes"/>be a knowledge of the chain of connection, by which all<lb break="yes"/>natural forces are linked together, and made mutually de-<lb break="no"/>pendent upon each other; and it is the perception of these<lb break="yes"/>relations that exalts our views and ennobles our enjoyments.<lb break="yes"/>Such a result can, however, only be reaped as the fruit of<lb break="yes"/>observation and intellect, combined with the spirit of the<lb break="yes"/>age, in which are reflected all the varied phases of thought.<lb break="yes"/>He who can trace, through bygone times, the stream of our<lb break="yes"/>knowledge to its primitive source, will learn from history<lb break="yes"/>how, for thousands of years, man has laboured, amid the<lb break="yes"/>ever-recurring changes of form, to recognise the invariability<lb break="yes"/>of natural laws, and has thus by the force of mind gradually<lb break="yes"/>subdued a great portion of the physical world to his do-<lb break="no"/>minion. In interrogating the history of the past, we trace<lb break="yes"/>the mysterious course of ideas yielding the first glimmering<lb break="yes"/>perception of the same image of a Cosmos, or harmoniously<lb break="yes"/>ordered whole, which, dimly shadowed forth to the human<lb break="yes"/>mind in the primitive ages of the world, is now fully re-<lb break="no"/>vealed to the maturer intellect of mankind as the result<lb break="yes"/>of long and laborious observation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Each of these epochs of the contemplation of the external<lb break="yes"/>world &#x2014; the earliest dawn of thought, and the advanced<lb break="yes"/>stage of civilization &#x2014; has its own source of enjoyment. In<lb break="yes"/>the former, this enjoyment, in accordance with the simplicity<lb break="yes"/>of the primitive ages, flowed from an intuitive feeling of<lb break="yes"/>the order that was proclaimed by the invariable and suc-<lb break="no"/>cessive reappearance of the heavenly bodies, and by the<lb break="yes"/>progressive development of organised beings; whilst in<lb break="yes"/>the latter, this sense of enjoyment springs from a definite<lb break="yes"/>knowledge of the phenomena of nature. When man began<lb break="yes"/>to interrogate nature, and, not content with observing, learnt<lb break="yes"/>to evoke phenomena under definite conditions; when once<lb break="yes"/>he sought to collect and record facts, in order that the fruit<lb break="yes"/>of his labours might aid investigation after his own brief<lb break="yes"/>existence had passed away, the <hi rendition="#i">philosophy of Nature</hi> cast<lb break="yes"/>aside the vague and poetic garb in which she had been<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="161" facs="#f0002"/> enveloped from her origin, and having assumed a severer<lb break="yes"/>aspect, she now weighs the value of observations, and sub-<lb break="no"/>stitutes induction and reasoning for conjecture and assump-<lb break="no"/>tion. The dogmas of former ages survive now only in the<lb break="yes"/>superstitions of the people and the prejudices of the<lb break="yes"/>ignorant, or are perpetuated in a few systems, which, con-<lb break="no"/>scious of their weakness, shroud themselves in a veil of<lb break="yes"/>mystery. We may also trace the same primitive intuitions<lb break="yes"/>in languages exuberant in figurative expressions; and a few<lb break="yes"/>of the best chosen symbols engendered by the happy in-<lb break="no"/>spiration of the earliest ages, having by degrees lost their<lb break="yes"/>vagueness through a better mode of interpretation, are still<lb break="yes"/>preserved amongst our scientific terms.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Nature considered <hi rendition="#i">rationally</hi>, that is to say, submitted to<lb break="yes"/>the process of thought, is a unity in diversity of phenomena;<lb break="yes"/>a harmony, blending together all created things, however<lb break="yes"/>dissimilar in form and attributes; one great whole ani-<lb break="no"/>mated by the breath of life. The most important result<lb break="yes"/>of a rational inquiry into nature is, therefore, to establish<lb break="yes"/>the unity and harmony of this stupendous mass of force and<lb break="yes"/>matter, to determine with impartial justice what is due to<lb break="yes"/>the discoveries of the past and to those of the present, and<lb break="yes"/>to analyse the individual parts of natural phenomena with-<lb break="no"/>out succumbing beneath the weight of the whole. Thus,<lb break="yes"/>and thus alone, is it permitted to man, while mindful of<lb break="yes"/>the high destiny of his race, to comprehend nature, to lift<lb break="yes"/>the veil that shrouds her phenomena, and, as it were, sub-<lb break="no"/>mit the results of observation to the test of reason and of<lb break="yes"/>intellect.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In reflecting upon the different degrees of enjoyment<lb break="yes"/>presented to us in the contemplation of nature, we find that<lb break="yes"/>the first place must be assigned to a sensation, which is<lb break="yes"/>wholly independent of an intimate acquaintance with the<lb break="yes"/>physical phenomena presented to our view, or of the peculiar<lb break="yes"/>character of the region surrounding us. In the uniform<lb break="yes"/>plain bounded only by a distant horizon, where the lowly<lb break="yes"/>heather, the cistus, or waving grasses, deck the soil; on the<lb break="yes"/>ocean shore, where the waves, softly rippling over the<lb break="yes"/>beach, leave a track, green with the weeds of the sea;<lb break="yes"/>everywhere, the mind is penetrated by the same sense of<lb break="yes"/>the grandeur and vast expanse of nature, revealing to the<lb break="yes"/>soul, by a mysterious inspiration, the existence of laws that<lb break="yes"/>regulate the forces of the universe. Mere communion with<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="162" facs="#f0003"/> nature, mere contact with the free air, exercise a soothing<lb break="yes"/>yet strengthening influence on the wearied spirit, calm the<lb break="yes"/>storm of passion, and soften the heart when shaken by<lb break="yes"/>sorrow to its inmost depths. Everywhere, in every region<lb break="yes"/>of the globe, in every stage of intellectual culture, the same<lb break="yes"/>sources of enjoyment are alike vouchsafed to man. The<lb break="yes"/>earnest and solemn thoughts awakened by a communion<lb break="yes"/>with nature intuitively arise from a presentiment of the<lb break="yes"/>order and harmony pervading the whole universe, and from<lb break="yes"/>the contrast we draw between the narrow limits of our own<lb break="yes"/>existence and the image of infinity revealed on every side,<lb break="yes"/>whether we look upwards to the starry vault of heaven, scan<lb break="yes"/>the far-stretching plain before us, or seek to trace the dim<lb break="yes"/>horizon across the vast expanse of ocean.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The contemplation of the individual characteristics of the<lb break="yes" />landscape, and of the conformation of the land in any<lb break="yes"/>definite region of the earth, gives rise to a different source<lb break="yes"/>of enjoyment, awakening impressions that are more vivid,<lb break="yes"/>better defined, and more congenial to certain phases of the<lb break="yes"/>mind, than those of which we have already spoken. At<lb break="yes"/>one time the heart is stirred by a sense of the grandeur of<lb break="yes"/>the face of nature, by the strife of the elements, or, as in<lb break="yes"/>Northern Asia, by the aspect of the dreary barrenness of<lb break="yes"/>the far-stretching steppes; at another time, softer emotions<lb break="yes"/>are excited by the contemplation of rich harvests wrested by<lb break="yes"/>the hand of man from the wild fertility of nature, or by the<lb break="yes"/>sight of human habitations raised beside some wild and<lb break="yes"/>foaming torrent. Here I regard less the degree of intensity,<lb break="yes"/>than the difference existing in the various sensations that<lb break="yes"/>derive their charm and permanence from the peculiar cha-<lb break="no"/>racter of the scene.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If I might be allowed to abandon myself to the recollec-<lb break="no"/>tions of my own distant travels, I would instance, among<lb break="yes"/>the most striking scenes of nature, the calm sublimity of a<lb break="yes"/>tropical night, when the stars, not sparkling, as in our<lb break="yes"/>northern skies, shed their soft and planetary light over the<lb break="yes"/>gently-heaving ocean;&#x2014;or I would recall the deep valleys<lb break="yes"/>of the Cordilleras, where the tall and slender palms pierce<lb break="yes"/>the leafy veil around them, and waving on high their<lb break="yes"/>feathery and arrow-like branches, form, as it were, &#x201C;a<lb break="yes"/>forest above a forest;&#x201D;&#x2014;or I would describe the summit of the<lb break="yes" />Peak of Teneriffe, when a horizontal layer of clouds, daz-<lb break="no" />zling in whiteness, has separated the cone of cinders from<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="163" facs="#f0004"/> the plain below, and suddenly the ascending current pierces<lb break="yes"/>the cloudy veil, so that the eye of the traveller may range<lb break="yes"/>from the brink of the crater, along the vine-clad slopes of<lb break="yes"/>Orotava, to the orange-gardens and banana-groves that skirt<lb break="yes"/>the shore. In scenes like these, it is not the peaceful charm<lb break="yes"/>uniformly spread over the face of nature that moves the<lb break="yes"/>heart, but rather the peculiar physiognomy and conformation<lb break="yes"/>of the land, the features of the landscape, the ever-varying<lb break="yes"/>outline of the clouds, and their blending with the horizon<lb break="yes"/>of the sea, whether it lies spread before us like a smooth and<lb break="yes"/>shining mirror, or is dimly seen through the morning mist.<lb break="yes"/>All that the senses can but imperfectly comprehend, all<lb break="yes"/>that is most awful in such romantic scenes of nature, may<lb break="yes"/>become a source of enjoyment to man, by opening a wide<lb break="yes"/>field to the creative powers of his imagination. Impressions<lb break="yes"/>change with the varying movements of the mind, and we<lb break="yes"/>are led by a happy illusion to believe that we receive from<lb break="yes"/>the external world that with which we have ourselves in-<lb break="no"/>vested it.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When, far from our native country, after a long voyage,<lb break="yes"/>we tread for the first time the soil of a tropical land, we<lb break="yes"/>experience a certain feeling of surprise and gratification in<lb break="yes"/>recognising, in the rocks that surround us, the same inclined<lb break="yes"/>schistose strata, and the same columnar basalt covered with<lb break="yes"/>cellular amygdaloids, that we had left in Europe, and whose<lb break="yes"/>identity of character, in latitudes so widely different, reminds<lb break="yes"/>us, that the solidification of the earth&#x2019;s crust is altogether<lb break="yes" />independent of climatic influences. But these rocky masses<lb break="yes"/>of schist and of basalt are covered with vegetation of a<lb break="yes"/>character with which we are unacquainted, and of a physi-<lb break="no"/>ognomy wholly unknown to us; and it is then, amid the<lb break="yes"/>colossal and majestic forms of an exotic flora, that we feel<lb break="yes"/>how wonderfully the flexibility of our nature fits us to re-<lb break="no"/>ceive new impressions, linked together by a certain secret<lb break="yes"/>analogy. We so readily perceive the affinity existing<lb break="yes"/>amongst all the forms of organic life, that although the sight<lb break="yes"/>of a vegetation similar to that of our native country might<lb break="yes"/>at first be most welcome to the eye, as the sweet familiar<lb break="yes"/>sounds of our mother tongue are to the ear, we nevertheless,<lb break="yes"/>by degrees, and almost imperceptibly, become familiarised<lb break="yes"/>with a new home and a new climate. As a true citizen of<lb break="yes"/>the world, man everywhere habituates himself to that which<lb break="yes"/>surrounds him; yet fearful, as it were, of breaking the links<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="164" facs="#f0005"/> of association that bind him to the home of his childhood,<lb break="yes"/>the colonist applies to some few plants in a far distant clime<lb break="yes"/>the names he had been familiar with in his native land;<lb break="yes"/>and by the mysterious relations existing among all types of<lb break="yes"/>organization, the forms of exotic vegetation present them-<lb break="no"/>selves to his mind as nobler and more perfect developments<lb break="yes"/>of those he had loved in earlier days. Thus do the spon-<lb break="no"/>taneous impressions of the untutored mind lead, like the<lb break="yes"/>laborious deductions of cultivated intellect, to the same<lb break="yes"/>intimate persuasion, that one sole and indissoluble chain<lb break="yes"/>binds together all nature.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k" >Humboldt.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 