<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="508" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head>THE ISTHMUS OF DARIEN<lb/>SHIP CANAL.</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">Dr. Cullen</hi> has been favoured<lb/>with the following communication<lb/>by Baron Humboldt:&#x2014;</p><lb/><p>Sir,&#x2014;I am very much to blame<lb/>for having so long delayed an<lb/>answer to the agreeable
                    and in-<lb/>teresting despatch that you have<lb/>been kind enough to forward me
                    by<lb/>the hands of Mr. Augustus Peter-<lb/>man, so estimable by his
                    character,<lb/>as well as by the solidity of his geo-<lb/>graphical labours. Dr.
                    Cullen can-<lb/>not doubt the high importance that<lb/>I would attach to the
                    merit of his<lb/>courageous and useful investigations<lb/>in the eastern part of
                    the Isthmus<lb/>of Panama; knowing my position<lb/>and my antediluvian age, he
                    will<lb/>receive with indulgence, even so<lb/>late, the expression of my
                    lively<lb/>gratitude.</p><lb/><p>After having laboured, in vain, during half a century, to prove the pos-<lb/>sibility of an <hi rendition="#i">Oceanic Canal</hi>, and to point out the Gulf of San Miguel and<lb/>Cupica as the points most worthy of attention; after having regretted,<lb/>almost with bitterness, in the last edition of my &#x201C;Aspects of Nature,&#x201D;<lb/>that the employment of the means which the present state of our<lb/>knowledge affords for obtaining precise measurements has been<lb/>so long delayed; I ought, more than any one else, to be satisfied to see,<lb/>at last, my hopes for so noble an enterprise revived. By your publica-<lb/>tions, sir, and by that of Mr. Gisborne, will be originated the great work<lb/>of changing an important part of the commerce of nations, and of render-<lb/>ing more accessible the rich countries of Eastern Asia and the Indian<lb/>Archipelago. The undertaking is by no means above the intellectual<lb/>and material power which civilised nations have attained to. The work<lb/>should be one to last for ever; it should not commence with a canal with<lb/>locks, like the magnificent Caledonian Canal; it must be a really <hi rendition="#i">oceanic</hi><lb/>canal, without locks&#x2014;a free passage from sea to sea, across which the<lb/>speed of the navigation will be modified, but not interrupted, by the differ-<lb/>ence in height and non-coincidence of the tides.</p><lb/><closer><salute>Receive, I pray you, sir, the expression of my highest consideration.<lb/><hi rendition="#c"
                        >Yours, &#x0026;c.</hi></salute><lb/><dateline>Potsdam, June 4th,
                            1853.</dateline>
                        <hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von
                        Humboldt.</hi></hi></closer></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
