<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-27" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="2" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>BARON VON HUMBOLDT.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>@</head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Baron Von Humboldt.</hi> In fulfilment of an ap-<lb break="no"/>pointment, we went at one, and were admitted by<lb break="yes"/>his faithful servant, the companion of many an ar-<lb break="no"/>duous journey. His mansion is a plain editice, situ-<lb break="no"/>ated in a retired part of the city; and he would not<lb break="yes"/>have been now at home had not the King gone to<lb break="yes"/>Konigsberg; for his residence is generally with the<lb break="yes"/>King, at Potsdam, who keeps him near his person,<lb break="yes"/>as his father did before him, not only for his society<lb break="yes"/>and conversation, but, no doubt, also as a counsellor,<lb break="yes"/>wise from his many years, and his large experience<lb break="yes"/>in the world. We passed through his library, which<lb break="yes"/>fills, on all sides, a room of considerable size; and<lb break="yes"/>he issued from a door on the remote side of the apart-<lb break="no"/>ment, opening apparently from his private room. He<lb break="yes"/>met us with great kindness and perfect frankness,<lb break="yes"/>and with a pleasant rebuke for my having hesitated<lb break="yes"/>to call on him, (I had written a note, asking permis-<lb break="no"/>sion to call,) implying that he was not ignorant of<lb break="yes"/>my position and efforts at home. I then introduced<lb break="yes"/>my son and Mr. Brush, and we were at once placed<lb break="yes"/>perfectly at our ease. His bright countenance ex-<lb break="no"/>presses great benevolence; and from the fountain of<lb break="yes"/>his immense stores of knowledge, a stream, almost<lb break="yes"/>constant, flowed for nearly an hour. He was not en-<lb break="no"/>grossing, but yielded to our promptings, whenever<lb break="yes"/>we suggested an inquiry, or alluded to any particular<lb break="yes"/>topic; for we did not wish to occupy the time with<lb break="yes"/>our own remarks any further than to draw him out.<lb break="yes"/>He has a perfect command of the best English, and<lb break="yes"/>speaks the language quite agreeably. There is no<lb break="yes"/>stateliness or reserve about him; and he is as affable<lb break="yes"/>as if he had no claims to superiority. His voice is<lb break="yes"/>exceedingly musical, and he is so animated and<lb break="yes"/>amiable that you feel at once as if he were an old<lb break="yes"/>friend. His person is not much above the middle<lb break="yes"/>size; he is not unlike in form to the late Colonel<lb break="yes"/>Trumbull. He stoops a little, but less than most men<lb break="yes"/>at the age of 82. He has no appearance of decrepi-<lb break="no"/>itude; his eyes are brilliant, his complexion light;<lb break="yes"/>his features and person are round, although not fat;<lb break="yes"/>his hair thin and white; his mind very active, and<lb break="yes"/>his language brilliant and sparkling with bright<lb break="yes"/>thoughts. He alluded in a flattering manner to our<lb break="yes"/>progress in knowledge in the United States, and to<lb break="yes"/>the effect which <hi rendition="#i">The American Journal of Science<lb break="yes"/>and Arts</hi> had produced in promoting it. He showed<lb break="yes"/>himself perfectly acquainted with the progress of<lb break="yes"/>physical science and general improvement in our<lb break="yes"/>country, and particularly commended the labors of<lb break="yes"/>Col. Fremont in the Far West, of Professor Bache<lb break="yes"/>in the coast survey, and of Lieut. Maury in naviga-<lb break="no"/>tion. Bringing out his maps, and tracing his lines<lb break="yes"/>without glasses, he pointed out a channel of commu-<lb break="no"/>nication across the Isthmus of Darien, which he had<lb break="yes"/>observed and described more than forty years ago,<lb break="yes"/>and to which his attention had been recalled by a<lb break="yes"/>paper of Capt. Fitzrov&#x2019;s in <hi rendition="#i">The Journal of the Roy-<lb break="no"/>al Geographical Society.</hi> He showed us that there<lb break="yes"/>are no mountains in the course he indicated, which<lb break="yes"/>is more southern than any of the existing routes,<lb break="yes"/>and that it possessed several important advantages.<lb break="yes"/>I alluded to his brief visit in the United States in<lb break="yes"/>1804, when he travelled no further north than Phil-<lb break="no"/>adelphia. He told us that he passed three weeks at<lb break="yes"/>Monticello with the late Mr. Jefferson, who entertain-<lb break="no"/>ed him with an extraordinary project of his inven-<lb break="no"/>tive but often visionary mind, regarding the ultimate<lb break="yes"/>division of the American continent into three great<lb break="yes"/>Republics, involving the conquest of Mexico and of<lb break="yes"/>the South American States. He discussed many to-<lb break="no"/>pics regarding the United States. The discovery of<lb break="yes"/>gold in California furnished him an abundant theme<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;our topography, climates, productions, institutions,<lb break="yes"/>and even political controversies, were all familiar<lb break="yes"/>to him.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Baron Humboldt, although associated intimately<lb break="yes"/>with Kings, is evidently a friend to human liberty,<lb break="yes"/>and rejoices in the prosperity of our country. He<lb break="yes"/>made some very interesting remarks on the present<lb break="yes"/>state of Europe, and on the impossibility of keeping<lb break="yes"/>down moral power by physical force. In his library<lb break="yes"/>hung an excellent likeness of the King, and another<lb break="yes"/>of his own brother, the late William Humboldt, the<lb break="yes"/>eminent phiologist and ethnological antiquary.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We retired greatly gratified, and the more so, as<lb break="yes"/>a man in his 83d year might soon pass away.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>When we were about leaving Berlin, I addressed<lb break="yes"/>a note to the Baron, expressing our great satisfaction<lb break="yes"/>at the interview, bidding him farewell, and asking<lb break="yes"/>for his autograph. He readily replied, but instead<lb break="yes"/>of his signature merely, he sent an interesting ori-<lb break="no"/>ginal letter, written on the occasion, from which, I<lb break="yes"/>trust, it is not improper to make an extract of senti-<lb break="no"/>ments relating to the American continents.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>After some very kind expressions of personal re-<lb break="no"/>gard, he alludes to his usual residence at Potsdam,<lb break="yes"/>where are both the rural palace of the King, and the<lb break="yes"/>tombs of some preceding monarchs: &#x201C;Compelled to<lb break="yes"/>return in the morning to the country, where are the<lb break="yes"/>tombs which I shall soon occupy, I have reserved to<lb break="yes"/>myself the perusal of certain scientific American<lb break="yes"/>papers which had been presented to me.&#x201D; He then<lb break="yes"/>adds: &#x201C;I have moral reasons to fear the immeasura-<lb break="no"/>ble aggrandizement of your confederacy&#x2014;the temp-<lb break="no"/>tations to the abuse of power, dangerous to the<lb break="yes"/>Union, (and have occasion also to fear) the distinct<lb break="yes"/>individual character of the other populations (de-<lb break="no"/>scriptions of the population) of America. I am<lb break="yes"/>not less impressed by the great advantages which<lb break="yes"/>the physical knowledge of the world, and positive<lb break="yes"/>science and intelligence, ought to derive from this<lb break="yes"/>very aggrandizement&#x2014;from that intelligence which<lb break="yes"/>by peaceable conquests, facilitates the movement<lb break="yes"/>of knowledge, and superimposes, not without vio-<lb break="no"/>lence, new classes of population upon the indigen-<lb break="no"/>ous races which are in a course of rapid extinc-<lb break="no"/>tion. However imposing this spectacle may be, which<lb break="yes"/>is being realized under our eyes, and is preparing<lb break="yes"/>another still more remarkable for the history of the<lb break="yes"/>intellectual development of our races, I already des-<lb break="no"/>cry the distinct epoch, when a high degree of civili-<lb break="no"/>zation, and institutions free, firm and peaceful, (three<lb break="yes"/>elements which are not easily associated,) shall pen-<lb break="no"/>etrate into the tropical regions where the high table<lb break="yes"/>lands of Mexico, Bogota, Quito and Potosi shall come<lb break="yes"/>to resemble (in their institutions) New York, Boston<lb break="yes"/>and Philadelphia.&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The letter concludes with warm personal good<lb break="yes"/>wishes, and a kind message to Professor Agassiz,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;equally distinguished by his vast and solid acqui-<lb break="no"/>sitions in science and the great emenity of his char-<lb break="no"/>acter.&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The signature is without a title: &#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Alexander<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt,</hi> a Berlin, 5 Juillet, (it should have been<lb break="yes"/>Aout,) 1851.&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>It is proper to add, that at the time of our visit<lb break="yes"/>Baron Von Humboldt was engaged in the prepara-<lb break="no"/>tion of a new production on the Outline Form of<lb break="yes"/>Mountain Peaks, in which he was working up ori-<lb break="no"/>ginal observations and drawings made during the<lb break="yes"/>course of his various wanderings. He assured us<lb break="yes"/>that the greater part of his literary labor was of ne-<lb break="no"/>cessity performed when others slept, as the hours of<lb break="yes"/>usual labor were with him consumed by the demands<lb break="yes"/>of the King. He added, that he early made the discov-<lb break="no"/>ery that he could get on very well with four hours of<lb break="yes"/>sleep. This, as has been often remarked, ac-<lb break="no" />counts for his prodigious performances in literary<lb break="yes" />labor.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Such are the modest and unassuming language and<lb break="yes"/>appearance of one who has, in person, explored a<lb break="yes"/>larger portion of our globe than any other living<lb break="yes"/>traveller; of a philosopher who has illustrated and<lb break="yes"/>enlarged almost every department of human knowl-<lb break="no"/>edge; general physics and chemistry, geology, nat-<lb break="no"/>ural history, philology, civil antiquities, and ethno-<lb break="no"/>graphy, have all been illustrated by him.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>He has endured the extreme vicissitudes of oppo-<lb break="no"/>site climates, and seen men, and animals, and plants,<lb break="yes"/>under every phase and aspect. His published works<lb break="yes"/>are a library. His faculties combine the enthusiasm<lb break="yes"/>of poetry with the severity of science; and from the<lb break="yes"/>culminating point of four-score years and four, he<lb break="yes"/>surveys all his vast labors, and the wide panorama<lb break="yes"/>of universal science, which, as probably his last la-<lb break="no"/>bor, he is now presenting to his fellow-men by the<lb break="yes"/>reflection of that splendid intellectual mirror, his<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#k">Kosmus</hi>&#x2014;the comprehensive <hi rendition="#i" >Hellenism,</hi> which ex-<lb break="no"/>pressed both <hi rendition="#i">the universal</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">the beautiful.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Such is the philosopher who, of all living men, be-<lb break="no"/>longs not so much to @s country as to mankind, and<lb break="yes"/>who, when he departs, will leave no one who can fill<lb break="yes"/>his place.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We dismiss him, with the hope that he may inherit<lb break="yes"/>blessings beyond the grave, and find in a higher state<lb break="yes"/>of being, that his large measure of human knowl-<lb break="no"/>edge is infinately surpassed by the spiritual illumina-<lb break="no"/>tion and revelations of that glorious world.&#x201D;</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 