<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>

<pb n="640" facs="#f0001" />

    <div n="1"><head>M. DE BUCH.</head><lb/><p>The following is a translation of an affecting<lb/>letter from the veteran Baron Alexander Hum-<lb/>boldt to Sir Roderick Murchison&#x2014;the original of<lb/>which has been kindly communicated by Sir<lb/>Roderick to the London Athen&#x00E6;um It conveys<lb/>intelligence which will be heard with great regret<lb/>in the scientific world.</p><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Berlin</hi>, March 4, 1853.</hi></dateline><lb/>
    </div>
    <div>
        <p>&#x201C;That I should be destined&#x2014;I, an old man of<lb/>eighty-three&#x2014;to announce to you, dear Sir Rode-<lb/>rick, the saddest news that I could have to con-<lb/>vey:&#x2014;to you for whom M. De Buch professed a<lb/>friendship so tender&#x2014;and to the many admirers<lb/>of his genius, his vast labors, and his noble cha-<lb/>racter! Leopold De Buch was taken from us this<lb/>morning by typhoid fever&#x2014;so violent in its attack<lb/>that two days only of danger warned us. He was<lb/>at my house so lately as the 26th (ult.,) despite<lb/>the snow and the distance between us&#x2014;talking<lb/>geology with the most lively interest. That<lb/>evening he went into society; and on Sunday and<lb/>Monday (the 27th and 28th) he complained of a<lb/>feverish attack, which he believed to be caused<lb/>by a large chilblain swelling, from which he had<lb/>suffered for years. The inflammation required<lb/>the application of leeches&#x2014;but the pain and the<lb/>fever increased. He was speechless for thirty-<lb break="maybe"/>eight hours. ** He died surrounded by his<lb/>friends&#x2014;most of whom knew nothing of his dan-<lb/>ger till Wednesday evening, the 2d of March.</p><lb/><cb/><lb/>
        <p>&#x201C;He and I were united by a friendship of sixty-<lb break="maybe"/>three years,&#x2014;a friendship which never knew in-<lb/>terruption. I found him in 1791, in Werner&#x2019;s<lb/>house in Freiberg, when I entered the School of<lb/>Mines. We were together in Italy, in Switzer-<lb/>land, in France,&#x2014;four months in Saltzburg. M.<lb/>De Buch was not only one of the great illustra-<lb/>tions of his age&#x2014;he was a man of noble soul.<lb/>His mind left a track of light wherever it passed.<lb/>Always in contact with Nature herself,&#x2014;he could<lb/>boast of having extended the limits of geological<lb/>science. I grieve for him profoundly,&#x2014;without<lb/>him I feel desolate. I consulted him as a mas-<lb/>ter: and his affection (like that of Gay Lussac<lb/>and that of Arago, who were also his friends)<lb/>sustained me in my labours. He was four years<lb/>my junior,&#x2014;and nothing forewarned me of this<lb/>misfortune. It is not at the distance of a few<lb/>hours only from such a loss, that I can say more<lb/>respecting it. Pity me&#x2014;and accept the homage<lb/>of my profound respect and affectionate devotion.</p><lb/><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Al. Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute></closer><lb/>
    </div>
    <div>
        <p>&#x201C;And my poor countryman Overweg, in Africa!<lb/>What a blessing to learn one day by means of<lb/>the astronomer Vogel the magnetic condition of<lb/>the interior of a vast continent!&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
