<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-01-04" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="2" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#c">THE ISTHMUS OF DARIEN.</hi></head>
                <p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Letter from Baron Alexander von Humboldt to<lb/>
                Lionel Gisborne, Esq., M.A., C.E.</hi></hi></p>
                <div n="2" type="letter">
                    <p>&#x201C;Sir,&#x2014;I trust you will excuse the oldest among the tra-<lb/>
                        vellers, in both the tropics of America and the steppes of Si-<lb/>
                        beria, for having so long delayed to thank you for the infor-<lb/>
                        mation I derived from your interesting journal, &amp;c., on the<lb/>
                        junction of the Atlantic with the Pacific. The position I oc-<lb/>
                        cupy in this country, and the ardent desire I feel to finish,<lb/>
                        before my death, some scientific works which I had the im-<lb/>
                        prudence to begin, considerably interrupted the even course of<lb/>
                        my correspondence. I therefore hope that I shall meet, on<lb/>
                        your part also, with that indulgence which your countrymen<lb/>
                        have shown me during so long a period.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;I have not been beyond the Rio Rimo, which lies east of<lb/>
                        the mouth of the Atrato. It was at the time when I left the island<lb/>
                        of Cuba on my way to Lima by Bogota, Quito, and the river<lb/>
                        Amazon, for the purpose of observing the passage of Mer-<lb/>
                        cury through the solar disc. I was then on friendly terms<lb/>
                        with a very intelligent merchant, Don Ignacio Iombo, of Car-<lb/>
                        tagena, in America, and I recollect that the <hi rendition="#i">Casso</hi> (Treasury<lb/>
                        convoy) of Guayaquil was then on its way to Europe, by the<lb/>
                        road from Cupicà to the Atrato, which was first opened by<lb/>
                        the Biscayian pilot Poguerache. Knowing, geologically, the<lb/>
                        interruption of the mountain chains, and the depression of<lb/>
                        the range in the eastern part of the Isthmus, my attention<lb/>
                        has remained fixed during this last half century on the bay of<lb/>
                        San Miguel and the route from Cupicà to the Rio Napipi.<lb/>
                        Owing to my friendly relations with General Bolivar, I ob-<lb/>
                        tained through him the first line of levels across the Isthmus<lb/>
                        of Panama. Ever since the subject has not ceased to occupy<lb/>
                        my mind, as the various works and maps which I published<lb/>
                        since 1810 and my correspondence with various statesmen<lb/>
                        will testify. But all my striving and urging only led to im-<lb/>
                        perfect trials and projects calculated for a line to the west of<lb/>
                        the meridian of Panama and Portobello, none of which ever<lb/>
                        gained my confidence. I had, however, the gratification of<lb/>
                        seeing my views honoured by an eminent member of her Bri-<lb/>
                        tannic Majesty&#x2019;s navy, Captain Fitzroy. (<hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Royal<lb/>
                            Geographical Society</hi>, vol. xx., p. 20.)</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;The increase of human knowledge, and the immense pro-<lb/>
                        gress of science, art, and industry among the western nations,<lb/>
                        have given us powers which only call for application. Every-<lb/>
                        thing depends upon energy and perseverance. I therefore con-<lb/>
                        gratulate you, sir, and your courageous friend, Dr. Cullen,<lb/>
                        as well as Sir Charles Eox, Mr. Henderson, and Mr. Bras-<lb/>
                        sey, for having given your names to so noble an undertaking.<lb/>
                        I have always considered, firstly, the opening of an oceanic<lb/>
                        canal, without locks; and secondly, the cut at Huchnecoca,<lb/>
                        in the valley of Mexico (which is on a comparatively smaller<lb/>
                        scale, as may be seen from the map and section I published), as<lb/>
                        two events calculated highly to improve the relations between<lb/>
                        the different families of the human species. In fact, such a<lb/>
                        work as the one you contemplate will bring Eastern Asia nearer to<lb/>
                        the nations of Europe and America. It will render the whole<lb/>
                        globe more easy to be travelled over&#x2014;this little globe, of<lb/>
                        which Christopher Columbus, in one of his letters to the<lb/>
                        Queen of Spain, said, &#x2018;<hi rendition="#i">el mundo es poco.</hi>&#x2019; It will facilitate<lb/>
                        the diffusion of productions, especially of precious metals, of<lb/>
                        which the relative value (1 to 15 5-6ths) would change too<lb/>
                        suddenly without this &#x2018;permeability&#x2019; of the world.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;As early as the discovery of the new continent, civilisa-<lb/>
                        tion had spread, in a direction from north to south, over those<lb/>
                        portions of America which lie opposite to Asia, those on the<lb/>
                        European side being then occupied by barbarous hunting<lb/>
                        tribes. The finest harbours, the most precious products, are<lb/>
                        likewise found in the West. Even the currents of the air, by<lb/>
                        their direction, contribute towards the preponderance of West<lb/>
                        American power over the rich countries of Asia. The in-<lb/>
                        creasing importance of the west coast of America promises<lb/>
                        to balance, at some future time, the surprising progress of<lb/>
                        the Atlantic States, provided the Western States keep them-<lb/>
                        selves free from that hideous disease&#x2014;slavery of coloured<lb/>
                        people.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;Indeed, sir, I feel the most ardent wishes for the happy<lb/>
                        success of this oceanic canal. The attention which the pub-<lb/>
                        lic of the two continents bestow already upon your under-<lb/>
                        taking will increase, as soon as you will be enabled, assisted by<lb/>
                        further explorations, and a survey extending over all details,<lb/>
                        and carried on by a great number of experienced men, to<lb/>
                        publish on a large scale, maps and sections of the line fixed<lb/>
                        upon between Puerto Escoces and the Gulf of San Miguel.<lb/>
                        The changes which the success of your undertaking is sure<lb/>
                        to effect in the international commerce of the world will only<lb/>
                        disturb such people as in the narrowness of their views op-<lb/>
                        pose themselves to the natural and providential course of<lb/>
                        events, and shed tears over the unfortunate discovery of<lb/>
                        America. The Rio Huaxacualco with its portage to the Rio<lb/>
                        Chimalapa (Tehuantepec,) of which I published the first map<lb/>
                        after the itineraries discovered by me in the archives of the<lb/>
                        vice-kingdom of Mexico, will always be of great importance,<lb/>
                        owing to its position opposite Louisiana, in the Gulf of Mexico,<lb/>
                        which has all the appearance of soon becoming a <hi rendition="#i">mare clau-<lb/>
                            sum</hi>&#x2014;a lake of the United States. The nature of the soil,<lb/>
                        however, does not allow of great works to be carried out in<lb/>
                        that locality; besides, you know the difficulties impeding any<lb/>
                        canalisation or rectification of rivers of great length, and the<lb/>
                        great variation of the body of water as in the river San Juan;<lb/>
                        but a railway would be a great advantage to the southern<lb/>
                        states.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;The great interest which every one at the present time<lb/>
                        takes in the canalisation of the Isthmus recalls a similar fact<lb/>
                        to my memory, reminding me of the sudden interest created<lb/>
                        by the discovery of guano.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;I was the first who brought guano to Europe, of which<lb/>
                        Klaproth and Vanquelin published an analysis. During 40<lb/>
                        years I preached, but always in vain, the usefulness of this<lb/>
                        substance, and in vain did I recommend its employment in<lb/>
                        fertilising the fields of Europe. But it is only 15 or 18 years<lb/>
                        since it has at last become a great article of commerce.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;I beg of you, my dear sir, to present my kind remem-<lb/>
                        brance to the excellent and able Mr. Petermann, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rendition="#et">
                                <hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt.</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <lb/>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>&#x201C;P.S.&#x2014;I am not surprised at the difference between the<lb/>
                            level you found at Turbaco and my own statement. To this,<lb/>
                            however, I prudently added &#x2018;doubtful barometrical observa-<lb/>
                            tion. (See my <hi rendition="#i" >Recueil d&#x2019;Observations Astronomiques et de<lb/>
                                Mesures Barométriques,</hi> vol. I., p. 299.) The fact that the<lb/>
                            gas issuing from the little volcanoes at Turbaco is inflammable<lb/>
                            in its natural state has already been communicated by Co-<lb/>
                            lonel Acosta, (<hi rendition="#i">Journal</hi>, p. 65). It appears that the gaseous<lb/>
                            fluid which issues from the &#x2018;salses&#x2019; is not the same at all times.<lb/>
                            I find in my journal, that in 1801, the flame of any burning substance<lb/>
                            was suddenly extinguished on being thrown into a bottle<lb/>
                            containing air from those little volcanoes.</p><lb/>
                        <p>&#x201C;Parrot, also, in the mud volcanoes in the island of Taman<lb/>
                            found only azote, although the gas emitted would burn at<lb/>
                            other times. (See my <hi rendition="#i">Relation Historique,</hi> xii., chap. 29, p.<lb/>
                            367&#x2014;371.&#x201D;)</p>
                    </postscript>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 