<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">The Isthmus of Darien</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:17</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VII.49</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1853-Junction_of_the-02-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-02-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">The Isthmus of Darien</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1853</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;Shipping &amp;amp; Mercantile Gazette&lt;/i&gt; 4819 (11. August 1853), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#b">THE ISTHMUS OF DARIEN.</hi></head>
                <lb/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb/>
                <p>The following is a translation from the French of a letter re-<lb/>
                    ceived from Baron Humboldt, upon inter-oceanic communica-<lb/>
                    tions across Central America :&#x2014;</p>
                <lb/>
                <div n="2" type="letter">
                    <p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">letter from baron alexander von humboldt to lionel<lb/>
                        gisborne, ESQ., M.A., C.E.</hi><lb/>
                        (Translated from the French original.)</hi></p><lb/>
                    <p>Sir,&#x2014;I trust you will excuse the oldest among the travel-<lb/>
                        lers in both the tropics of America and the steppes of Siberia,<lb/>
                        for having so long delayed to thank you for the information I<lb/>
                        derived from your interesting journal, &amp;c., on the junction of<lb/>
                        the Atlantic with the Pacific. The position I occupy in this<lb/>
                        country, and the ardent desire I feel to finish, before my death,<lb/>
                        some scientific works which I had the imprudence to begin,<lb/>
                        considerably interrupt the even course of my correspondence.<lb/>
                        I, therefore, hope that I shall meet, on your part also, with<lb/>
                        that indulgence which your countrymen have shown me dur-<lb/>
                        ing so long a period.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;I have not been beyond the Rio Rimo, which lies east of<lb/>
                        the mouth of the Atrato, since the time when I left the island<lb/>
                        of Cuba on my way to Lima by Bogota, Quito, and the river<lb/>
                        Amazon, for the purpose of observing the passage of Mercury<lb/>
                        through the solar disc. I was then on friendly terms with a<lb/>
                        very intelligent merchant, Don Ignacio Iombo, of Cartagena,<lb/>
                        in America, and I recollect that the Casso (Treasury convoy)<lb/>
                        of Guayaquil was then on its way to Europe, by the road from<lb/>
                        Cupicà to the Atrato, which was first opened by the Biscayian<lb/>
                        pilot Poguerache. Knowing, geologically, the interruption of<lb/>
                        the mountain chains, and the depression of the range in the<lb/>
                        eastern part of the Isthmus, my attention has remained fixed<lb/>
                        during this last half century on the bay of San Miguel and the<lb/>
                        route from Cupicà to the Rio Napipi. Owing to my friendly<lb/>
                        relations with General Bolivar, I obtained through him the<lb/>
                        first line of levels across the Isthmus of Panama. Ever<lb/>
                        since the subject has not ceased to occupy my mind, as the<lb/>
                        various works and maps which I published since 1810 and my<lb/>
                        correspondence with various statesmen will testify. But all<lb/>
                        my striving and urging only led to imperfect trials and projects<lb/>
                        calculated for a line to the west of the meridian of Panama<lb/>
                        and Portobello, none of which ever gained my confidence. I<lb/>
                        had, however, the gratification of seeing my views honored<lb/>
                        by an eminent member of Her Britannic Majesty&#x2019;s navy,<lb/>
                        Captain Fitzroy. (<hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Royal Geographical Society</hi>,<lb/>
                        vol. xx., p. 20)</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;The increase of human knowledge, and the immense pro-<lb/>
                        gress of science, arts, and industry among the western nations,<lb/>
                        have given us powers which only call for application. Every-<lb/>
                        thing depends upon energy and perseverance. I therefore<lb/>
                        congratulate you, Sir, and your courageous friend, Mr. Cullen,<lb/>
                        as well as Sir Charles Fox, Mr. Henderson, and Mr. Brassey,<lb/>
                        for having given your names to so noble an undertaking. I have<lb/>
                        always considered, firstly, the opening of an oceanic canal, without<lb/>
                        locks; and secondly, the cut at Huchuecoca, in the valley of Mexico<lb/>
                        (which is on a comparatively smaller scale, as may be seen by<lb/>
                        the map and section I published), as two events calculated<lb/>
                        highly to improve the relations between the different families<lb/>
                        of the human species. In fact, such a work as the one you<lb/>
                        contemplate will bring Eastern Asia nearer to the nations of<lb/>
                        Europe and America. It will render the whole globe more<lb/>
                        easy to be travelled over&#x2014;this little globe, of which Chris-<lb/>
                        topher Columbus, in one of his letters to the Queen of Spain,<lb/>
                        said, &#x2018;<hi rendition="#i">El mundo es poco</hi>.&#x2019; It will facilitate the diffusion of<lb/>
                        productions, especially of precious metals, of which the rela-<lb/>
                        tive value (1 to 15 5-6ths) would change too suddenly without<lb/>
                        this &#x2018;permeability&#x2019; of the world.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;As early as the discovery of the new continent, civilisa-<lb/>
                        tion had spread, in a direction from north to south, over<lb/>
                        those portions of America which lie opposite to Asia, those<lb/>
                        on the European side being then occupied by barbarous<lb/>
                        hunting tribes. The finest harbours, the most precious pro-<lb/>
                        ducts, are likewise found in the west. Even the currents of<lb/>
                        the air, by their direction, contribute towards the preponde-<lb/>
                        rance of West American power over the rich countries of Asia.<lb/>
                        The increasing importance of the west coast of America pro-<lb/>
                        mises to balance, at some future time, the surprising pro-<lb/>
                        gress of the Atlantic States, provided the western states keep<lb/>
                        themselves free from that hideous disease&#x2014;slavery of coloured<lb/>
                        people.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;Indeed, Sir, I feel the most ardent wishes for the happy<lb/>
                        success of this oceanic canal. The attention which the public<lb/>
                        of the two continents bestow already upon your undertaking<lb/>
                        will increase, as soon as you are enabled, assisted by<lb/>
                        further exploration and a survey extending over all details, and<lb/>
                        carried on by a great number of experienced men, to publish,<lb/>
                        on a large scale, maps and sections of the line fixed upon<lb/>
                        between Puerto Escoces and the Gulf of San Miguel. The<lb/>
                        changes which the success of your undertaking is sure to<lb/>
                        effect in the international commerce of the world will<lb/>
                        only disturb such people as in the narrowness of their<lb/>
                        views oppose themselves to the natural and providential course<lb/>
                        of events, and shed tears over the unfortunate discovery of<lb/>
                        America. The Rio Huaxacualco with its portage to the Rio<lb/>
                        Chimalapa (Tehuantepec), of which I published the first map<lb/>
                        after the itineraries discovered by me in the archives of the<lb/>
                        vice kingdom of Mexico, will always be of great importance,<lb/>
                        owing to its position opposite Louisiana, in the Gulf of Mexico,<lb/>
                        which has all the appearance of soon becoming a <hi rendition="#i">mare clausum</hi><lb/>
                        &#x2014;a lake of the United States. The nature of the soil, however,<lb/>
                        does not allow great works to be carried out in that locality;<lb/>
                        besides, you know the difficulties impeding any canalisation or<lb/>
                        rectification of rivers of great length, and the great variations<lb/>
                        of the volume of water, as in the river San Juan; but a rail-<lb/>
                        way would be a great advantage to the southern states.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;The great interest which every one at the present time<lb/>
                        takes in the canalisation of the Isthmus recals a similar fact<lb/>
                        to my memory, reminding me of the sudden interest created by<lb/>
                        the discovery of guano.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;I was the first who brought guano to Europe, of which<lb/> Klaproth
            and Vauquelin published an analysis. During 40<lb/> years I preached, but always in
            vain, the usefulness of this<lb/> substance, and in vain did I recommend its employment
            in fer-<lb/> tilising the fields in Europe. But it is only 15 or 18 years<lb/> since it
            has at last become a great article of commerce.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;I beg of you, my dear Sir, to present my kind remembrance<lb/>
                        to the excellent and able Mr. Petermann, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rendition="#et">
                                &#x201C;ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT.
                            </hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <lb/>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>&#x201C;P.S. I am not surprised at the difference between the<lb/>
                            level you found at Turbaco and my own statement. To<lb/>
                            this, however, I had prudently added, &#x2018;doubtful barome-<lb/>
                            trical observations.&#x2019; (See my <hi rendition="#i">Recueil d&#x2019;Observations Astrono-<lb/>
                            miques et de Mesures Barométriques</hi>, vol. i., p. 299). The fact<lb/>
                            that the gas issuing from the little volcanoes at Turbaco is in-<lb/>
                            flammable in its natural state has already been communicated<lb/>
                            by Colonel Acosta (<hi rendition="#i">Journal</hi>, p. 65). It appears that the<lb/>
                            gaseous fluid which issues fromm the &#x2018;salses&#x2019; is not the same at<lb/>
                            all times. I find in my journal that, in 1801, the flame of any<lb/>
                            burning substance was suddenly extinguished on being thrown<lb/>
                        into a bottle containing air from those little volcanoes.</p>
                        <p>&#x201C;Parrot, also, in the mud volcanoes in the island of Taman,<lb/>
                            found only azota, although the gas emitted would burn at<lb/>
                            other times. (See my <hi rendition="#i">Relation Historique</hi>, vol. xii., chap. 29,<lb/>
                            p. 367-371).&#x201D;</p>
                    </postscript>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 