<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>

<pb n="240" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Von Buch.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;This eminent geologist died at Berlin, on the 4th of<lb/>March, aged 79 years. The following is a letter from Humboldt to Sir<lb/>R. I. Murchison, announcing his death, (Athen&#x00E6;um, No. 1924.)</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;That I should be destined&#x2014;I, an old man of eighty-three&#x2014;to an-<lb/>nounce
                    to you, dear Sir Roderick, the saddest news that I could have<lb/>to
                    convey:&#x2014;to you for whom M. De Buch professed a friendship so<lb/>tender,
                    and to the many admirers of his genius, his vast labours, and<lb/>his noble
                    character! Leopold De Buch was taken from us this morn-<lb/>ing by typhoid
                    fever, so violent in its attack that two days only of<lb/>danger warned us. He
                    was at my house so lately as the 26th [ult.]<lb/>despite the snow and the
                    distance between us, talking geology with<lb/>the most lively interest. That
                    evening he went into society; and on<lb/>Sunday and Monday (the 27th and 28th)
                    he <choice>
                        <sic>camplained</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">complained</corr>
                    </choice> of a feverish<lb/>attack, which he believed to be caused by a large
                    chilblain swelling<lb/>from which he had suffered for years. The inflammation
                    required the<lb/>application of leeches, but the pain and the fever increased.
                    He was<lb/>speechless for <choice>
                        <sic>forty-eight</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">thirty-eight</corr>
                    </choice> hours. ** He died surrounded by his<lb/>friends,&#x2014;most of whom
                    knew nothing of his danger till Wednesday<lb/>evening, the 2nd of March.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;He and I were united by a friendship of sixty-three years,&#x2014;a<lb/>friendship which
                    never knew interruption. I found him in 1791, in<lb/>Werner&#x2019;s house in
                    Freiburgh, when I entered the School of Mines. We<lb/>were together in Italy, in
                    Switzerland, in France,&#x2014;four months in Saltz-<lb/>burg. M. De Buch was
                    not only one of the great illustrations of his<lb/>age,&#x2014;he was a man of a
                    noble soul. His mind left a track of light<lb/>wherever it passed. Always in
                    contact with Nature herself, he could<lb/>well boast of having extended the
                    limits of geological science. I grieve<lb/>for him profoundly,&#x2014;without
                    him I feel desolate. I consulted him as<lb/>a master; and his affection (like
                    that of Gay Lussac and that of Arago<lb/>who were also his friends) sustained me
                    in my labours. He was four<lb/>years my junior,&#x2014;and nothing forewarned me
                    of this misfortune. It<lb/>is not at the distance of a few hours only from such
                    a loss, that I can<lb/>say more respecting it. Pity me,&#x2014;and accept the
                    homage of my pro-<lb/>found respect and affectionate devotion.&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
