<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
    <div>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>M. <hi rendition="#k">De Buch.</hi>&#x2014;The following is a translation of
                an<lb/>affecting letter from the veteran Baron Alexander<lb/>Humboldt to Sir
                Roderick Murchison, the original of<lb/>which has been kindly communicated by Sir
                Roderick<lb/>to us (<hi rendition="#i">Athen&#x00E6;um</hi>). It conveys
                intelligence which will<lb/>be heard with great regret in the scientific world
                of<lb/>England:&#x2014;</p>
            <dateline><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Berlin, March</hi> 4,
                    1853.</hi></dateline>
            <lb/>
    </div>
    <div>
            <p>&#x201C;That I should be destined&#x2014;I, an old man of 83&#x2014;<lb/>to announce
                to you, dear Roderick, the saddest news<lb/>that I could have to convey&#x2014;to
                you for whom M. De<lb/>Buch professed a friendship so tender&#x2014;and to
                the<lb/>many admirers of his genius, his vast labours, and his<lb/>noble character!
                Leopold de Buch was taken from us<lb/>this morning, by typhoid fever&#x2014;so
                violent in its attack<lb/>that two days only of danger warned us. He was at<lb/>my
                house so lately as the 26th ult., despite the snow<lb/>and the distance between
                us&#x2014;talking geology with the<lb/>most lively interest. That evening he went
                into so-<lb/>ciety, and on Sunday and Monday (the 27th and 28th),<lb/>he complained
                of a feverish attack, which he believed<lb/>to be caused by a large chilblain
                swelling, from which he<lb/>had suffered for years. The inflammation required
                the<lb/>application of leeches; but the pain and the fever in-<lb/>creased. He was
                speechless for 38 hours. He died sur-<lb/>rounded by his friends, most of whom knew
                nothing<lb/>of his danger till Wednesday evening, the 2d of March.<lb/>He and I were
                united by a friendship of sixty-three<lb/>years&#x2014;a friendship which never knew
                interruption.<lb/>I found him, in 1791, in Werner&#x2019;s house, in
                Freiberg,<lb/>when I entered the School of Mines. We were to-<lb/>gether in Italy,
                in Switzerland, in France, four months<lb/>in Saltzburg. M. De Buch was not only one
                of the<lb/>great illustrations of his age&#x2014;he was a man of noble<lb/>soul. His
                mind left a track of light wherever it passed.<lb/>Always in contact with Nature
                herself, he could boast<lb/>of having extended the limits of geological science.
                I<lb/>grieve for him profoundly&#x2014;without him I feel desolate.<lb/>I consulted
                him as master; and his affection (like<lb/>that of Gay Lussac and that of Arago, who
                were also<lb/>his friends) sustained me in my labours. He was four<lb/>years my
                junior, and nothing forewarned me of this<lb/>misfortune. It is not at the distance
                of a few hours<lb/>only from such a loss that I can say more respecting it.<lb/>Pity
                me&#x2014;and accept the homage of my profound re-<lb/>spect and affectionate
                devotion.</p>
            <lb/>
            <closer>
                <salute><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Al.
                    Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute>
            </closer>
            <lb/>
    </div>
    <div>
            <p>&#x201C;And my poor countryman, Overweg, in Africa!<lb/>What a blessing to learn one
                day, by means of the as-<lb/>tronomer Vogel, the magnetic condition of the
                interior<lb/>of a vast continent!&#x201D;</p>
            <lb/>
    </div>
        </body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
