<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="828" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head>CULLEN&#x2019;S ISTHMUS OF DARIEN SHIP CANAL.<lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<hi rendition="#k">The</hi> following letter has been received by Dr. Cullen from Baron<lb/>Von Humboldt, and forwarded to us for publication:&#x2014;<lb/>(<hi rendition="#k">translation from the french.</hi>)</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">Dr. Edward Cullen,</hi> <hi rendition="#i">Strand, London,</hi></p><lb/><p>Sir,&#x2014;I am very much to blame for having so long delayed an answer<lb/>to the agreeable and
                    interesting dispatch that you have been kind enough<lb/>to forward me by the
                    hands of Mr. Augustus Peterman, so estimable by<lb/>his character, as well as by
                    the solidity of his geographical labours. Dr.<lb/>Cullen cannot doubt the high
                    importance that I would attach to the<lb/>merit of his courageous and useful
                    investigations in the eastern part of<lb/>the Isthmus of Panama; knowing my
                    position and my antediluvian age,<lb/>he will receive with indulgence, even so
    late, the expression of my lively<lb/>gratitude.</p><lb/><p>After having laboured, in vain, during half a century, to prove the<lb/>possibility of an <hi rendition="#i">Oceanic Canal</hi>, and to point out the Gulf of San Miguel<lb/>and Cupìca as the points most worthy of attention; after having re-<lb/>gretted, almost with bitterness, in the last edition of my &#x201C;Aspects of<lb/>Nature,&#x201D; that the employment of the means, which the present state of<lb/>our knowledge affords for obtaining precise measurements has been so<lb/>long delayed; I ought, more than any one else, be satisfied to see, at last,<lb/>my hopes for so noble an enterprise revived. By your publications, sir,<lb/>will be orignated the great work of changing an important part of the<lb/>commerce of nations, and of rendering more accessible the rich countries<lb/>of Eastern Asia and the Indian Archipelago. The undertaking is, by no<lb/>means above the <choice><sic>intetlectual</sic><corr type="editorial">intellectual</corr></choice> and material power which civilised nations<lb/>have attained to. The work should be one to last for ever; it should<lb/>not commence with a Canal with Locks, like the magnificent Caledonian<lb/>Canal; it must be a really <hi rendition="#i">Oceanic</hi> Canal, without Locks; a free passage<lb/>from sea to sea, across which the speed of the navigation will be modified,<lb/>but not interrupted by the difference in height and non-coincidence of<lb/>the tides.</p><lb/><closer><salute>Receive, I pray you, Sir, the expression of my highest consideration.<lb/><hi rendition="#et">Yours, &#x0026;c., &#x0026;c.,<lb/>(Signed) ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT.</hi></salute></closer><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#k">Potsdam</hi>, 4th June, 1853.</dateline></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
