<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="245" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Noon in the Tropics.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;The soil<lb/>(says Humboldt, in his &#x201C;Narrative,&#x201D;) ap-<lb/>peared to
                    undulate, from the effect of<lb/>mirage, without a breath of wind being
                    left.<lb/>The sun was near the zenith, and its<lb/>dazzling light, reflected
                    from the surface<lb/>of the river, contrasted with the reddish<lb/>vapours that
                    enveloped every surrounding<lb/>object. How vivid is the impression
                    pro-<lb/>duced by the calm of nature, at noon, in<lb/>these burning climates.
                    The beasts of<lb/>the forests retire to the thickets; the birds<lb/>hide
                    themselves beneath the foliage of the<lb/>trees, or in the crevices of the
                    rocks. Yet,<lb/>amidst this apparent silence, when we lend<lb/>an attentive ear
                    to the most feeble sounds<lb/>transmitted through the air, we hear a<lb/>dull
                    vibration, a continual murmur, a<lb/>hum of insects, filling, if we may use
                    the<lb/>expression, all the lower strata of the air.<lb/>Myriads of insects
                    creep upon the soil<lb/>and flutter round the plants parched by<lb/>the heat of
                    the sun. A confused noise<lb/>issues from every bush, from the
                    decayed<lb/>trunks of trees, from the clefts of rocks,<lb/>and from the ground
                    undermined by lizards, millepedes, and <hi rendition="#i"
                    >cecilias.</hi><lb/>These are so many voices proclaiming to us that all nature
                    breathes,<lb/>and that, under a thousand different forms, life is diffused
                    throughout<lb/>the cracked and dusty soil, as well as in the bosom of the
                    waters,<lb/>and in the air around us.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
