<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">The Isthmus of Darien</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:17</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VII.49</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1853-Junction_of_the-07-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-07-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">The Isthmus of Darien</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1853</date>
          <pubPlace>Dublin</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;Saunders’s News-Letter and Daily Advertiser&lt;/i&gt; 34744 (13. August 1853), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>THE ISTHMUS OF DARIEN.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following interesting letter from Baron Alexander Von<lb break="yes" />Humboldt to Lionel Gisborne, Esq., M.A., C.E., has been<lb break="yes"/>made public:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <opener>
                        <salute>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Sir</hi>
                        </salute>
                    </opener>
                    <p>&#x2014;I trust you will excuse the oldest among the travel<lb break="yes" />lers in both the tropics of America and the steppes of Siberia,<lb break="yes"/>for having so long delayed to thank you for the information I<lb break="yes"/>derived from your inter sting journal, &#x0026;c., on the junction of<lb break="yes"/>the Atlantic with the Pacific. The position I occupy in this<lb break="yes"/>country, and the ardent desire I feel to finish, beforemy death,<lb break="yes"/>some scientific works which I had the imprudence to begin,<lb break="yes"/>considerably interrupt the even course of my correspondance<lb break="yes"/>I therefore hope that I shall meet, on your part also, with that<lb break="yes"/>indulgence which your countrymen have shown me during so<lb break="yes"/>long a period.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;I have not been beyond the Rio Rimo, which lies east of<lb break="yes"/>the mouth of the Atrato, since the time when I left the island<lb break="yes"/>of Cuba on my way to Lima by Bogota, Quito, and the river<lb break="yes"/>Amazon, for the purpose of observing the passage of Mercury<lb break="yes"/>through the solar disc. I was then on friendly terms with a<lb break="yes"/>very intelligent merchant. Don Ignacio Iombo, of Cartagena,<lb break="yes"/>in America, and I recollect that the Casso (Treasury convoy)<lb break="yes"/>of Guayaquil was then on its way to Europe, by the road from<lb break="yes"/>Cupica to the Atrato, which was first opened by the Biscavan<lb break="yes"/>pilot Poguerache. Knowing, geologically the interruption of<lb break="yes"/>the mountain chains, and the depression of the range in the<lb break="yes"/>eastern part of the Isthmus, my attention has remained fixed<lb break="yes"/>during this last half century on the Bay of San Miguel and the<lb break="yes"/>route from Cupica to the Rio Napipi Owing to my friendly<lb break="yes"/>relations with Gene al Bolivar. I obtained through him the<lb break="yes"/>first line of levels across the lsthmus of Panama. Ever since<lb break="yes"/>the subject has not ceased to occupy my mind as the various<lb break="yes"/>works and maps which I published since 1810 and my cor-<lb break="no"/>respondence with various statesmen will testify. But all my<lb break="yes"/>striving and urging only led to imperfect trials and projects<lb break="yes"/>calculated for a line to the weat of the meridian of Panama<lb break="yes"/>and Portobello, none of which ever gained my confidence. I<lb break="yes"/>had, however, the gratification of seeing my views honored<lb break="yes"/>by an eminent member of her Britannic Majesty&#x2019;s navy, Capt.<lb break="yes" />Fitzroy.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Royal Geographical Society,</hi> vol. xx.,<lb break="yes"/>p. 20)</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The increase of human knowledge, and the immense pro-<lb break="no" />gress of science, arts, and industry, among the western nations,<lb break="yes"/>have given us powers which only call for application. Every-<lb break="no"/>thing depends upon energy and perseverance. I therefore con-<lb break="no"/>gratulate you, air, and your courageous friend, Dr. Cullen, as<lb break="yes"/>well as Sir Charles Fox, Mr Henderson, and Mr. Brassey, for<lb break="yes"/>having given your names to so noble an undertaking. I have<lb break="yes"/>always considered, firstly, the opening of an oceanic canal,<lb break="yes"/>without locks; and secondly, the cut at Huchuecoca, in the<lb break="yes"/>valley of Mexico (which is on a comperatively smaller scale,<lb break="yes"/>as may be seen by the map and section I published), as two<lb break="yes"/>events calculated highly to improve the reletions between the<lb break="yes"/>different families of the human species. In fact, such a work<lb break="yes"/>as the one you contemplate will bring Eastern Asia nearer to<lb break="yes"/>the nations of Europe and America. It will render the whole<lb break="yes" />globe more easy to be travelled over&#x2014;this little globe, of<lb break="yes"/>which Christopher Columbus, in one of his letters to the Quren<lb break="yes"/>of Spain, said. &#x2018;<hi rendition="#i">el mundo es poco.</hi>&#x2019; It will facilitate the dif-<lb break="no" />fusion of productions, especially of precious metals, of which<lb break="yes"/>the relative value (1 to 15 5-6ths) would change too suddenly<lb break="yes"/>without this &#x2018;permeability&#x2019; of the world.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;As early as the discovery of the new continent, civilisation<lb break="yes"/>had spread, in a direction from north to south, over those por-<lb break="no"/>tions of America which He opposite to Asia, those on the<lb break="yes"/>European side being then occupied by barbarous hunting<lb break="yes"/>tribes. The finest harhours, the most precious products, are<lb break="yes"/>likewise found in the West. Even the currents of the air, by<lb break="yes"/>their direction, contribute towards the preponderance of West<lb break="yes"/>American power over the rich countries of Asia. The increasing<lb break="yes"/>importance of the west coast of America promises to balance,<lb break="yes"/>at some future time, the surprising progress of the Atlantic<lb break="yes"/>States, provided the western States keep themselves free from<lb break="yes"/>that hideous disease&#x2014;slavery of coloured people.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Indeed, sir, I feel the most ardent wishes for the happy<lb break="yes"/>success of this oceanic canal. The attention which the public<lb break="yes"/>of the two continents be-tows already upon your undertaking<lb break="yes"/>will increase, as soon as you are enabled, assisted by further<lb break="yes"/>explorations, and a survey extending over all details, and car-<lb break="no"/>ried on by a great number of experienced men, to publish, on<lb break="yes"/>a large scale, maps and sections of the line fixed upon between<lb break="yes"/>Puerto Escoces and the Gulf of San Miguel. The changes<lb break="yes"/>which the success of your undertaking is sure to effect in the<lb break="yes"/>international commerce of the world will only disturb such<lb break="yes"/>people as in the narrowness of their views oppose themselves<lb break="yes"/>to the natural and providential course of events, and shed<lb break="yes"/>tears over the unfortunate discovery of America. The Rio<lb break="yes"/>Huaxacualco with its portage to the Rio Chimalapa (Tehuan-<lb break="no"/>tepec), of which I published the first map after the itineraries<lb break="yes"/>discovered by me in the archives of the vice-kingdom of<lb break="yes"/>Mexico, will always be of great importance, owing to its po-<lb break="no"/>sition opposite to Louisiana in the Gulf of Mexico, which has<lb break="yes"/>all the appearance of soon becoming a <hi rendition="#i">mare clanrum</hi>&#x2014;a lake<lb break="yes"/>of the United States. The nature of the soil, however, does<lb break="yes"/>not allow great works to be carried out in that locality; be-<lb break="no"/>sides you know the difficulties impeding any canalization or<lb break="yes"/>rectification of rivers of great length, and the great variations<lb break="yes"/>of the volume of water, as in the river San Juan; but a rall-<lb break="no"/>way would be a great advantage to the southern States.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The great interest which every one at the present time<lb break="yes" />takes in the canalization of the Isthmus recalls a similar fact<lb break="yes"/>to my memory, reminding me of the sudden interest created<lb break="yes"/>by the discovery of guano.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;I was the first who brought guano to Europe, of which<lb break="yes"
            />Klaproth and <choice>
              <sic>Vanquelin</sic>
              <corr type="editorial">Vauquelin</corr>
            </choice> published an analysis. During 40<lb break="yes"/>years I preached, but always
            in vain, the usefulness of this sub-<lb break="no"/>stance, and in vain did I recommend
            its employment in ferti-<lb break="no"/>lising the fields of Europe. But it is only
            fifteen or eighteen<lb break="yes"/>years since it has at last become a great article of
            commerce.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <closer>
                        <salute>&#x201C;I beg of you, my dear sir, to present my kind remem-<lb break="no"/>brance to the excellent and able Mr. Peterman, &#x0026;c.<lb break="yes"/>
                            <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von Humboldt.</hi>&#x201D;</hi>
                        </salute>
                    </closer>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 