<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="763" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>THE ISTHMUS OF DARIEN.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">letter from baron alexander von humboldt<lb break="yes"/>to lionel gisborne, esq., m. a., c. e.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Translated from the French original.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Sir</hi> &#x2014; I trust that you will excuse the oldest<lb break="yes"/>among the travellers, in both the tropics of<lb break="yes" />America and the steppes of Siberia, for hav-<lb break="no"/>ing so long delayed to thank you for the in-<lb break="no"/>formation I derived from your interesting<lb break="yes"/>journal, &#x0026;c., on the junction of the Atlantic<lb break="yes"/>with the Pacific. The position I occupy in<lb break="yes"/>this country, and the ardent desire I feel to<lb break="yes" />finish, before my death, some scientific works<lb break="yes"/>which I had the imprudence to begin, con-<lb break="no"/>siderably interrupt the even course of my<lb break="yes"/>correspondence. I therefore hope that I shall<lb break="yes"/>meet, on your part also, with that indulgence<lb break="yes" />which your countrymen have shown me dur-<lb break="no"/>ing so long a period.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have not been beyond the Rio Rimo, which<lb break="yes"/>lies east of the mouth of the Atrato, since the<lb break="yes"/>time when I left the Island of Cuba on my<lb break="yes"/>way to Lima by Bogota, Quito, and the<lb break="yes" />River Amazon, for the purpose of observing<lb break="yes"/>the passage of Mercury through the solar<lb break="yes"/>disc. I was then on friendly terms with a<lb break="yes"/>very intelligent merchant, Don Ignacio<lb break="yes" />Iombo, of Carthagena, in America; and I<lb break="yes"/>recollect that the <hi rendition="#i">Casso</hi> (treasury convoy) of<lb break="yes"/>Guayaquil, was then on its way to Europe, by<lb break="yes"/>the road from Cupicà to the Atrato, which<lb break="yes"/>was first opened by the Biscayan pilot,<lb break="yes"/>Poguerache. Knowing, geologically, the in-<lb break="no" />terruption of the mountain chains, and the<lb break="yes"/>depression of the range in the eastern part of<lb break="yes"/>the Isthmus, my attention has remained fixed<lb break="yes"/>during this last half century on the Bay of<lb break="yes"/>San Miguel and the route from Cupicà to the<lb break="yes"/>Rio Napipi. Owing to my friendly relation<lb break="yes"/>with General Bolivar, I obtained through<lb break="yes"/>him the first line of levels across the Isthmus<lb break="yes"/>of Panama. Ever since, the subject has not<lb break="yes"/>ceased to occupy my mind, as the various<lb break="yes"/>works and maps which I published since 1810,<lb break="yes"/>and my correspondence with various statesmen<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> will testify. But all my striving and urging<lb break="yes"/>only led to imperfect trials and projects, cal-<lb break="no"/>culated for a line to the west of the meridian<lb break="yes"/>of Panama and Portobello, none of which ever<lb break="yes"/>gained my confidence. I had, however, the<lb break="yes"/>gratification of seeing my views honored by an<lb break="yes" />eminent member of Her Britannic Majesty&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>Navy, Captain Fitzroy. (<hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Royal<lb break="yes"/>Geographical Society,</hi> Vol. xx., p. 30.)</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The increase of human knowledge, and the<lb break="yes"/>immense progress of science, arts, and indus-<lb break="no"/>try, among the western nations, have given<lb break="yes"/>us powers which only call for application.<lb break="yes"/>Everything depends upon energy and persever-<lb break="no" />ance. I therefore congratulate you, sir, and<lb break="yes"/>your courageous friend, Dr. Cullen, as well as<lb break="yes"/>Sir Charles Fox, Mr. Henderson, and Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Brassey, for having given your names to so<lb break="yes"/>noble an undertaking. I have always con-<lb break="no" />sidered, firstly, the opening of an oceanic<lb break="yes"/>canal, without locks; and, secondly, the cut<lb break="yes"/>at Huchuecoca, in the valley of Mexico (which<lb break="yes"/>is on a comparatively smaller scale, and may<lb break="yes"/>be seen by the map and section I published),<lb break="yes"/>as two events calculated highly to improve<lb break="yes"/>the relations between the different families of<lb break="yes"/>the human species. In fact, such a work as<lb break="yes"/>the one you contemplate will bring Eastern<lb break="yes"/>Asia nearer to the nations of Europe and<lb break="yes" />America. It will render the whole globe<lb break="yes"/>more easily travelled over &#x2014; this little globe,<lb break="yes"/>of which Christopher Columbus, in one of his<lb break="yes"/>letters to the Queen of Spain, said, &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">el mundo<lb break="yes"/>es poco.</hi>&#x201D; It will facilitate the diffusion of pro-<lb break="no"/>ductions, especially of precious mentals, of<lb break="yes"/>which the relative value (1 to 15 5-6ths)<lb break="yes"/>would change too suddenly without this<lb break="yes" />&#x201C;permeability&#x201D; of the world.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As early as the discovery of the new con-<lb break="no"/>tinent, civilization had spread, in a direction<lb break="yes"/>from north to south, over those portions of<lb break="yes"/>America which lie opposite to Asia, those on<lb break="yes"/>the European side being then occupied by<lb break="yes" />barbarous hunting tribes. The finest harbors,<lb break="yes"/>the most precious products, are likewise found<lb break="yes"/>in the West. Even the currents of the air,<lb break="yes"/>by their direction, contribute towards the<lb break="yes"/>preponderance of West American power over<lb break="yes" />the rich countries of Asia. The increasing<lb break="yes"/>importance of the west coast of America prom-<lb break="no"/>ises to balance, at some future time, the sur-<lb break="no"/>prising progress of the Atlantic States, pro-<lb break="no"/>vided the Western States keep themselves free<lb break="yes" />from that hideous disease &#x2014; slavery of colored<lb break="yes" />people.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Indeed, sir, I feel the most ardent wishes<lb break="yes"/>for the happy success of this oceanic canal.<lb break="yes"/>The attention which the public of the two<lb break="yes"/>continents bestows already upon your under-<lb break="no"/>taking will increase, as soon as you are en-<lb break="no" />abled, assisted by further explorations, and a<lb break="yes"/>survey extending over all details, and carried<lb break="yes"/>on by a great number of experienced men, to<lb break="yes"/>publish, on a large scale, maps and sections<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="764" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/> of the line fixed upon between Puerto Escoces<lb break="yes"/>and the Gulf of San Miguel. The changes<lb break="yes"/>which the success of your undertaking is sure<lb break="yes"/>to effect in the international commerce of the<lb break="yes"/>world will only disturb such people as in the<lb break="yes" />narrowness of their views oppose themselves<lb break="yes"/>to the natural and providential course of<lb break="yes"/>events, and shed tears over the unfortunate<lb break="yes"/>discovery of America. The Rio Huaxacualco,<lb break="yes"/>with its portage to the Rio Chimalapa (Te-<lb break="no" />huantepec), of which I published the first<lb break="yes"/>map after the itineraries discovered by me in<lb break="yes"/>the archives of the vice-kingdom of Mexico,<lb break="yes"/>will always be of great importance, owing to<lb break="yes"/>its position opposite Louisiana, in the Gulf of<lb break="yes" />Mexico, which has all the appearance of soon<lb break="yes"/>becoming a <hi rendition="#i">mare clausum</hi> &#x2014; a lake of the<lb break="yes" />United States. The nature of the soil, how-<lb break="no"/>ever, does not allow great works to be carried<lb break="yes"/>out in that locality; besides, you know the<lb break="yes"/>difficulties impending any canalization or<lb break="yes"/>rectification of rivers of great length, and the<lb break="yes" />great variations of the volume of water, as in<lb break="yes"/>the river San Juan; but a Railway would be<lb break="yes"/>a great advantage to the Southern States.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The great interest which every one at the<lb break="yes"/>present time takes in the canalization of the<lb break="yes"/>Isthmus, recalls a similar fact to my memory,<lb break="yes"/>reminding me of the sudden interest created<lb break="yes"/>by the discovery of guano.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I was the first who brought guano to Europe,<lb break="yes"/>of which Klaproth and Vauquelin published<lb break="yes"/>an analysis. During 40 years I preached, but<lb break="yes"/>always in vain, the usefulness of this sub-<lb break="no"/>stance, and in vain did I recommend its em-<lb break="no" />ployment in fertilizing the fields of Europe.<lb break="yes"/>But it is only 15 or 18 years since it has at<lb break="yes"/>last become a great article of commerce.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I beg of you, my dear sir, to present my<lb break="yes"/>kind remembrance to the excellent and able<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Peterman, &#x0026;c.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#et">
                            <hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von Humboldt.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 