<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-27" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="5" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#b">GERMAN SAVANTS.</hi></hi><lb/>
                <hi rendition="#k">Professor</hi> Silliman, an American gentleman well<lb/>known to the members of scientific societies, relates<lb/>the particulars of interviews which he has recently<lb/>obtained with several of the illustrious men of science<lb/>in Europe who were no strangers to his name. One<lb/>of these pleasant meetings introduces us to<lb/>
                <hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">baron von humboldt.</hi></hi>
            </p>
                <p>In fulfilment of an appointment, we went at one,<lb/>and were admitted by his faithful servant, the compa-<lb/>nion of many an arduous journey. His mansion is a<lb/>plain editice, situated in a retired part of the city; and<lb/>he would not have been now at home had not the king<lb/>gone to Konigsberg; for his residence is generally with<lb/>the king at Potsdam, who keeps him near his person,<lb/>as his father did before him, not only for his society<lb/>and conversation, but, no doubt, also as a counsellor,<lb/>wise, from his many years and his large experience in<lb/>the world. We passed through his library, which fills,<lb/>on all sides, a room of considerable size; and he issued<lb/>from a door on the remote side of the apartment, open-<lb/>ing apparently from his private room. He met us<lb/>with great kindness and perfect frankness, and with a<lb/>pleasant rebuke for my having hesitated to call on him<lb/>(I had written a note, asking permission to call), im-<lb/>plying that he was not ignorant of my position and<lb/>efforts at home. I then introduced my son and Mr.<lb/>Brush, and we were at once placed perfectly at our<lb/>ease. His bright countenance expresses great bene-<lb/>volence; and from the fountain of his immense stores<lb/>of knowledge, a stream, almost constant, flowed for<lb/>nearly an hour. He was not engrossing, but yielded<lb/>to our promptings, whenever we suggested an inquiry,<lb/>or alluded to any particular topic, for we did not wish<lb/>to occupy the time with our own remarks, any<lb/>further than to draw him out. He has<lb/>a perfect command of the best English,<lb/>and speaks the language quite agreeably. There<lb/>is no stateliness or reserve about him; and he is<lb/>as affable as if he had no claims to superiority. His<lb/>voice is exceedingly musical, and he is so animated<lb/>and amiable that you feel at once as if he were an old<lb/>friend. His person is not much above the<lb/>middle size; he is not unlike in form to the<lb/>late Colonel Trumbull. He stoops a little, but<lb/>less than most men at the age of eighty-<lb/>two. He has no appearance of decrepitude; his eyes<lb/>are brilliant, his complexion light, his features and<lb/>person are round, although not fat; his hair thin and<lb/>white; his mind very active, and his language bril-<lb/>liant, and sparkling with bright thoughts. He alluded<lb/>in a flattering manner to our progress in knowledge in<lb/>the United States, and to the effect which the <hi rendition="#i">American<lb/>Journal of Science and Arts</hi> had produced in promoting it.<lb/>He showed himself perfectly acquainted with the pro-<lb/>gress of physical science and general improvement in<lb/>our country, and particularly commended the labours<lb/>of Colonel Freemont in the far west, of Professor Baché<lb/>in the coast survey, and of Lieut. Maury in navigation.<lb/>Bringing out his maps, and tracing his lines without<lb/>glasses, he pointed out a channel of communication<lb/>across the Isthmus of Darien, which he had observed<lb/>and described more than forty years ago, and to which<lb/>his attention had been recalled by a paper of Captain<lb/>Fitzroy in the <hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Royal Geographical So-<lb/>ciety.</hi> He showed us that there are no mountains in<lb/>the course he indicated, which is more southern than<lb/>any of the existing routes, and that it possessed seve-<lb/>ral important advantages. I alluded to his brief visit<lb/>in the United States in 1804, when he travelled no fur-<lb/>ther north than Philadelphia. He told us that he<lb/>passed three weeks at Monticello with the late Mr.<lb/>Jefferson, who entertained him with an extraordinary<lb/>project of his inventive, but often visionary mind, re-<lb/>garding the ultimate division of the American conti-<lb/>nent into three great republics, involving the conquest<lb/>of Mexico and of the South American States. He dis-<lb/>cussed many topics regarding the United States. The<lb/>discovery of gold in California furnished him an abun-<lb/>dant theme&#x2014;our topography, climates, productions,<lb/>institutions, and even political controversies, were all<lb/>familiar to him.</p>
                <p>Baron Humboldt, although associated intimately<lb/>with kings, is evidently a friend to human liberty,<lb/>and rejoices in the prosperity of our country. He<lb/>made some very interesting remarks on the present<lb/>state of Europe, and on the impossibility of keeping<lb/>down moral power by physical force. In his library<lb/>hung an excellent likeness of the king, and another of<lb/>his own brother, the late William Humboldt, the emi-<lb/>nent phiologist and ethnological antiquary.</p>
                <p>We retired greatly gratified, and the more so, as a<lb/>man in his eighty-third year might soon pass away.</p>
                <p>When we were about leaving Berlin, I addressed a<lb/>note to the Baron, expressing our great satisfaction at<lb/>the interview, bidding him farewell, and asking him<lb/>for his autograph. He readily replied, but instead of<lb/>his signature merely, he sent an interesting original<lb/>letter, written on the occasion, from which, I trust, it<lb/>is not improper to make an extract of sentiments re-<lb/>lating to the American continents.</p>
                <p>After some very kind expressions of personal re-<lb/>gard, he alludes to his usual residence at Potsdam,<lb/>where are both the rural palace of the King, and the<lb/>tombs of some preceding monarchs: &#x201C;Compelled to<lb/>return in the morning to the country, where are the<lb/>tombs which I shall soon occupy, I have reserved to<lb/>myself the perusal of&#x201D;&#x2014;certain scientific American<lb/>papers which had been presented to him. He then<lb/>adds, &#x201C;I have moral reasons to fear the immeasurable<lb/>aggrandisement of your confederacy&#x2014;the temptations<lb/>to the abuse of power, dangerous to the Union (and<lb/>have occasion also to fear) the distinct individual cha-<lb/>racter of the other populations (descriptions of the popu-<lb/>lation) of America. I am not less impressed by the<lb/>great advantages which the physical knowledge of the<lb/>world, and positive science and intelligence, ought to<lb/>derive from this very aggrandisement, from that intelli-<lb/>gence which, by peaceable conquests facilitates the move-<lb/>ment of knowledge, and superimposes, not without<lb/>violence, new classes of population upon the indigen-<lb/>ous races which are in a course of rapid extinction.<lb/>However imposing this spectacle may be, which is<lb/>being realized under our eyes, and is preparing<lb/>another still more remarkable for the history of the<lb/>intellectual development of our races, I already descry<lb/>the distinct epoch, when a high degree of civilisation,<lb/>and institutions free, firm, and peaceful (three elements<lb/>which are not easily associated,) shall penetrate into<lb/>the tropical regions where the high table lands of<lb/>Mexico, Bogota, Quito and Potosi shall come to re-<lb/>semble (in their institutions) New York, Boston and<lb/>Philadelphia.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>The letter concludes with warm personal good<lb/>wishes, and a kind message to Professor Agassiz,<lb/>&#x201C;equally distinguished by his vast and solid acquisi-<lb/>tions in science, and the great amenity of his charac-<lb/>ter.&#x201D;</p>
                    <p>The signature is without a title: &#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Alexander<lb/>Humboldt,</hi> á Berlin, 5 Juillet (it should have been<lb/>Aout), 1851.</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 