<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="107" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head>JUNCTION OF THE ATLANTIC AND PACIFIC<lb/>OCEANS.</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">Extract</hi> from a letter on this subject, addressed by Baron<lb/>Alexander
                    Von Humboldt to Mr. Lionel Gisborne:&#x2014;</p><lb/><p>Everything depends upon energy and perseverance. I<lb/>therefore, congratulate you, sir, and your
                                                  courageous<lb/>friend Mr. Cullen, as well as Sir
                                                  Chailes Fox, Mr. Hen-<lb/>derson, and Mr. Brassey,
                                                  for having given your names to<lb/>so noble an
                                                  undertaking. I have always
                                                  considered,<lb/>firstly, the opening of an oceanic
                                                  canal without locks, and<lb/>secondly, the cut at
                                                  Huchnecoca, in the valley of Mexico<lb/>(which is
                                                  on a comparatively smaller scale, as may be
                                                  seen<lb/>from the map and section published), as
                                                  two events calcu-<lb/>lated highly to improve the
                                                  relations between the different<lb/>families of
                                                  the human species. In fact, such a work as<lb/>the
                                                  one you contemplate will bring Eastern Asia
                                                  nearer<lb/>to the nations of Europe and America.
                                                  It will render<lb/>the whole globe more easy to be
                                                  travelled over; this little<lb/>globe, of which
                                                  Christopher Columbus, in one of his<lb/>letters to
                                                  the Queen of Spain, said&#x2014;&#x201C;<hi
                                                                      rendition="#i">El mundo <choice><sic>espoco</sic><corr type="editorial">es poco</corr></choice>.</hi>&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>It will facilitate the diffusion of productions, especially<lb/>of precious metals, of which the relative value (1 to 15 5-6)<lb/>would change too suddenly without this &#x201C;permeability&#x201D;<lb/>of the world.</p><lb/><p>As early as the discovery of the new continent, civilisa-<lb/>tion had spread, in a direction from north to south, over<lb/>those portions of America which lie opposite to Asia,<lb/>those on the European side being then occupied by barba-<lb/>rous hunting tribes.</p><lb/><p>The finest harbours, the most precious products, are<lb/>likewise found in the west.</p><lb/><p>Even the currents of the air, by their direction, contri-<lb/>bute towards the preponderance of
                                                  West American power<lb/>over the rich countries of
                                                  Asia. The increasing impor-<lb/>tance of the west
                                                  coast of America promises to balance,<lb/>at some
                                                  future time, the surprising progress of
                                                  the<lb/>Atlantic States, provided the Western
                                                  states keep them-<lb/>selves free from that
                                                  hideous disease&#x2014;slavery of
                                                  colored<lb/>people.</p><lb/><p>Indeed, sir, I feel the most ardent wishes for the happy<lb/>success of this oceanic canal. The
                                                  attention which the<lb/>public of the two
                                                  continents bestow already upon
                                                  your<lb/>undertaking, will increase as soon as you
                                                  will be enabled,<lb/>assisted by farther
                                                  explorations, and a survey extending<lb/>over all
                                                  details, and carried on by a great number
                                                  of<lb/>experienced men, to publish, on a large
                                                  scale, maps and<lb/>sections of the line fixed
                                                  upon between Puerto Escoces<lb/>and the Gulf of
                                                  San Miguel. The changes which the<lb/>success of
                                                  the undertaking is sure to effect in the
                                                  interna-<lb/>tional commerce of the world, will
                                                  only disturb such peo-<lb/>ple, as in the
                                                  narrowness of their views, oppose
                                                  themselves<lb/>to the natural and providential
                                                  course of events, and shed<lb/>tears over the
                                                  unfortunate discovery of America. The<lb/>Rio
                                                  Huaxacualco with its portage to the Rio
                                                  Chimalapa<lb/>(Tehuantepec), of which I published
                                                  the first map after<lb/>the itineraries discovered
                                                  by me in the archives of the<lb/><pb n="108"
                                                  facs="#f0002"/> Vice Kingdom of Mexico, will
                                                  always be of great impor-<lb/>tance, owing to its
                                                  position opposite Louisiana, in the<lb/>Gulf of
                                                  Mexico, which has all the appearance of
                                                  soon<lb/>becoming a <hi rendition="#i">mare
                                                  clausum</hi>&#x2014;a lake of the United
                                                  States.<lb/>The nature of the soil, however, does
                                                  not allow great<lb/>works to be carried out in
                                                  that locality; besides, you<lb/>know the
                                                  difficulties impeding any canalisation or
                                                  rectifi-<lb/>cation of rivers of great length, and
                                                  the great variations<lb/>of the volume of water,
                                                  as in the river San Juan. But a<lb/>railway would
                                                  be of great advantage to the
                                                  southern<lb/>states.</p></div>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
