<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>THE ISTHMUS OF DARIEN.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/> LETTER FROM BARON ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT TO<lb break="yes" />LIONEL GISBORNE, ESQ., M.A., C.E.<lb break="yes"/>(Translated from the French original.)</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I trust you will excuse the oldest among the tra-<lb break="no"/>vellers, in both the tropics of America and the steppes<lb break="yes"/>of Siberia, for having so long delayed to thank you<lb break="yes"/>for the information I derived from your interesting<lb break="yes"/>journal, &#x0026;c., on the junction of the Atlantic with the<lb break="yes"/>Pacific. The position I occupy in this country, and<lb break="yes"/>the ardent desire I feel to finish, before my death, some<lb break="yes"/>scientific works which I had the imprudence to begin,<lb break="yes"/>considerably interrupt the even course of my corre-<lb break="no"/>spondence. I therefore hope that I shall meet, on your<lb break="yes"/>part also, with that indulgence which your countrymen<lb break="yes"/>have shown me during so long a period.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I have not been beyond the Rio Rimo, which lies<lb break="yes"/>east of the mouth of the Atrato, since the time when<lb break="yes"/>I left the Island of Cuba, on my way to Lima, by<lb break="yes"/>Bogota, Quito, and the river Amazon, for the purpose<lb break="yes"/>of observing the passage of Mercury through the solar<lb break="yes"/>disc. I was then on friendly terms with a very in-<lb break="no"/>telligent merchant, Don Ignacio Iombo, of Cartagena,<lb break="yes"/>in America, and I recollect that the Casso (Treasury<lb break="yes"/>Convoy) of Guayaquil was then on its way to Europe,<lb break="yes"/>by the road from Cupicà to the Atrato, which was<lb break="yes" />first opened by the Biscayan pilot Poguerache.<lb break="yes"/>Knowing, geologically, the interruption of the moun-<lb break="no"/>tain chains, and the depression of the range in the<lb break="yes"/>eastern part of the Isthmus, my attention has remained<lb break="yes"/>fixed during this half century on the Bay of San<lb break="yes"/>Miguel and the route from Cupicà to the Rio Napipi.<lb break="yes"/>Owing to my friendly relations with General Bolivar,<lb break="yes"/>I obtained, through him, the first line of levels across<lb break="yes"/>the Isthmus of Panama. Ever since, the subject has<lb break="yes"/>not ceased to occupy my mind, as the various works<lb break="yes"/>and maps which I published since 1810 and my corre-<lb break="no"/>spondence with various statesmen will testify. But all<lb break="yes"/>my striving and urging only led to imperfect trials and<lb break="yes"/>projects calculated for a line to the west of the<lb break="yes"/>meridian of Panama and Portobello, none of which<lb break="yes" />ever gained my confidence. I had, however, the<lb break="yes"/>gratification of seeing my views honoured by an emi-<lb break="no"/>nent member of Her Britannic Majesty&#x2019;s navy, Captain<lb break="yes"/>Fitzroy. (<hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Royal Geographical Society,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Vol. XX., p. 20.)</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The increase of human knowledge, and the immense<lb break="yes"/>progress of science, arts, and industry among the<lb break="yes"/>western nations, have given us powers which only call<lb break="yes"/>for application. Everything depends on energy and<lb break="yes"/>perseverance. I therefore congratulate you, Sir, and<lb break="yes"/>your courageous friend, Dr. Cullen, as well as Sir<lb break="yes"/>Charles Fox, Mr. Henderson, and Mr. Brassey, for<lb break="yes"/>having given your names to so noble an undertaking.<lb break="yes"/>I have always considered, firstly, the opening of an<lb break="yes"/>oceanic canal, without locks; and secondly, the cut<lb break="yes"/>at Huchnecoca, in the valley of Mexico (which is on<lb break="yes"/>a comparatively smaller scale, as may be seen by the<lb break="yes"/>map and section I published), as two events calcu-<lb break="no"/>lated highly to improve the relations between the<lb break="yes" />different families of the human species. In fact, such<lb break="yes"/>a work as the one you contemplate will bring Eastern<lb break="yes"/>Asia nearer to the nations of Europe and America.<lb break="yes"/>It will render the whole globe more easy to be tra-<lb break="no"/>velled over&#x2014;this little globe, of which Christopher<lb break="yes"/>Columbus, in one of his letters to the Queen of Spain,<lb break="yes"/>said, &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">el mundo es poco.</hi>&#x201D; It will facilitate the diffusion<lb break="yes"/>of productions, especially of precious metals, of which<lb break="yes"/>the relative value (1 to 15 5-6ths) would change too<lb break="yes"/>suddenly without this &#x201C;permeability&#x201D; of the world.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>As early as the discovery of the new continent,<lb break="yes"/>civilisation had spread, in a direction from north to<lb break="yes"/>south, over those portions of America which lie opposite<lb break="yes"/>to Asia, those on the European side being then occu-<lb break="no"/>pied by barbarous hunting tribes. The finest harbours,<lb break="yes"/>the most precious products, are likewise found in the<lb break="yes"/>West. Even the currents of the air, by their direction,<lb break="yes"/>contribute towards the preponderance of West Ameri-<lb break="no"/>can power over the rich countries of Asia. The in-<lb break="no"/>creasing importance of the west coast of America<lb break="yes" />promises to balance, at some future time, the surprising<lb break="yes" />progress of the Atlantic States, provided the western<lb break="yes"/>States keep themselves free from that hideous disease<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;slavery of coloured people.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Indeed, Sir, I feel the most ardent wishes for the<lb break="yes"/>happy success of this oceanic canal. The attention<lb break="yes"/>which the public of the two continents bestows already<lb break="yes"/>upon your undertaking will increase, as soon as you<lb break="yes"/>are enabled&#x2014;assisted by further explorations, and a<lb break="yes"/>survey extending over all details, and carried on by a<lb break="yes"/>great number of experienced men&#x2014;to publish on a<lb break="yes"/>large scale maps and sections of the line fixed upon be-<lb break="no"/>tween Puerto Escoces and the Gulf of San Miguel.<lb break="yes"/>The changes which the success of your undertaking is<lb break="yes"/>sure to effect in the international commerce of the<lb break="yes"/>world will only disturb such people as in the narrow-<lb break="no"/>ness of their views oppose themselves to the natural<lb break="yes"/>and Providential course of events, and shed tears over<lb break="yes"/>the unfortunate discovery of America. The Rio<lb break="yes" />Huaxacualco, with its portage to the Rio Chimalapa<lb break="yes" />(Tehuantepec), of which I published the first map after<lb break="yes"/>the itineraries discovered by me in the archives of the<lb break="yes"/>vice-kingdom of Mexico, will always be of great im-<lb break="no"/>portance, owing to its position opposite Louisiana, in<lb break="yes"/>the Gulf of Mexico, which has all the appearance of<lb break="yes"/>soon becoming a <hi rendition="#i">mare clausum</hi>&#x2014;a lake of the United<lb break="yes"/>States. The nature of the soil, however, does not<lb break="yes"/>allow great works to be carried out in that locality;<lb break="yes"/>besides, you know the difficulties impeding any<lb break="yes"/>canalisation or rectification of rivers of great length,<lb break="yes"/>and the great variations of the volume of water, as in<lb break="yes"/>the river San Juan; but a railway would be a great<lb break="yes"/>advantage to the Southern States.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 