<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><body>
<pb n="464" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Von Buch.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;This eminent geologist died at Berlin, on the 4th of<lb/>March, aged 79 years. The following is a letter from Humboldt to<lb/>Sir R. I. Murchison, announcing his death, (Athen&#x00E6;um, No 1324).</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;That I should be destined&#x2014;I, an old man of eighty-three&#x2014;to an-<lb/>nounce to you, dear Sir Roderick, the saddest news that I could have<lb/>to convey:&#x2014;to you for whom M. de Buch professed a friendship so<lb/>tender, and to the many admirers of his genius, his vast labors, and his<lb/>noble character! Leopold De Buch was taken from us this morning<lb/>by typhoid fever, so violent in its attack that two days only of danger<lb/>warned us. He was at my house so lately as the 26th [ult.], despite<lb/>the snow and the distance between us, talking geology with the most<lb/>lively interest. That evening he went into society; and on Sunday<lb/>and Monday (the 27th and 28th) he complained of a feverish attack,<lb/>which he believed to be caused by a large chilblain swelling from which<lb/>he had suffered for years. The inflammation required the application<lb/>of leeches, but the pain and the fever increased. He was speechless<lb/>for thirty-eight hours. ** He died surrounded by his friends,&#x2014;<lb/>most of whom knew nothing of his danger till Wednesday evening,<lb/>the 2d of March.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;He and I were united by a friendship of sixty-three years,&#x2014;a<lb/>friendship which
                    never knew interruption. I found him in 1791, in<lb/>Werner&#x2019;s house in
                    Freiburg, when I entered the School of Mines. We<lb/>were together in Italy, in
                    Switzerland, in France,&#x2014;four months in<lb/>Saltzburg. M. De Buch was not
                    only one of the great illustrations of<lb/>his age,&#x2014;he was a man of noble
                    soul. His mind left a track of light<lb/>wherever it passed. Always in contact
                    with Nature herself, he could<lb/>well boast of having extended the limits of
                    geological science. I grieve<lb/>for him profoundly,&#x2014;without him I feel
                    desolate. I consulted him as<lb/><pb n="465" facs="#f0002"/> a master; and his
                    affection (like that of Gay Lussac and that of Arago<lb/>who were also his
                    friends) sustained me in my labors. He was four<lb/>years my junior,&#x2014;and
                    nothing forewarned me of this misfortune. It<lb/>is not at the distance of a few
                    hours only from such a loss, that I can<lb/>say more respecting it. Pity
                    me,&#x2014;and accept the homage of my pro-<lb/>found respect and affectionate
                    devotion.&#x201D;</p></div><lb/>
</body></text>
</TEI>
