<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">The Isthmus of Darien</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:17</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VII.49</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1853-Junction_of_the-03-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-03-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1853-Junction_of_the-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">The Isthmus of Darien</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1853</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;The Globe and Traveller&lt;/i&gt; 17187 (11. August 1853), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>THE ISTHMUS OF DARIEN.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following interesting letter from Baron Alex-<lb break="no"/>ander Von Humboldt to Lionel Gisborne, Esq., M.A.,<lb break="yes"/>C. E. has been made public:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Sir&#x2014;I trust you will excuse the oldest among the<lb break="yes" />travellers in both the tropics of America and the<lb break="yes"/>steppes of Siberia, for having so long delayed to thank<lb break="yes"/>you for the information I derived from your interesting<lb break="yes"/>journal, &#x0026;c., on the junction of the Atlantic with the<lb break="yes"/>Pacific. The position I occupy in this country and the<lb break="yes"/>ardent desire I feel to finish, before my death, some<lb break="yes"/>sientific works which I had the imprudence to begin,<lb break="yes"/>considerably interrupt the even course of my corre-<lb break="no"/>spondence. I therefore hope that I shall meet, on your<lb break="yes"/>part also, with that indulgence which your countrymen<lb break="yes"/>have shown me during so long a period.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;I have not been beyond the Rio Rimo, which lies<lb break="yes"/>east of the mouth of the Atrato, since the time when I<lb break="yes"/>left the island of Cuba on my way to Lima by Bogota,<lb break="yes"/>Quito, and the river Amazon, for the purpose of ob-<lb break="no"/>serving the passage of Mercury through the solar disc.<lb break="yes"/>I was then on friendly terms with a very intelligent<lb break="yes"/>merchant, Don Ignacio Iombo, of Cartagena, in Ame-<lb break="no"/>rica, and I recollect that the Casso (Treasury convoy)<lb break="yes"/>of Guayaquil was then on its way to Europe, by the<lb break="yes"/>road from Cupica to the Atrato, which was first opened<lb break="yes"/>by the Biscayan pilot Poguerache. Knowing, geologi-<lb break="no"/>cally, the interruption of the mountain chains, and the<lb break="yes"/>depression of the range in the eastern part of the Isth-<lb break="no"/>mus, my attention has remained fixed during this last<lb break="yes"/>half century on the Bay of San Miguel and the route<lb break="yes"/>from Cupica to the Rio Napipi. Owing to my friendly<lb break="yes"/>relations with General Bolivar, I obtained through him<lb break="yes"/>the first line of levels across the Isthmus of Panama.<lb break="yes"/>Ever since the subject has not ceased to occupy my<lb break="yes"/>mind, as the various works and maps which I published<lb break="yes"/>since 1810 and my correspondence with various states-<lb break="no"/>men will testify. But all my striving and urging only<lb break="yes"/>led to imperfect trials and projects calculated for a line<lb break="yes"/>to the west of the meridian of Panama and Portobello,<lb break="yes"/>none of which ever gained my confidence. I had, how-<lb break="no"/>ever, the gratification of seeing my views honoured by<lb break="yes"/>an eminent member of Her Britannic Majesty&#x2019;s navy,<lb break="yes"/>Captain Fitzroy. (<hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Royal Geographical<lb break="yes"/>Society,</hi> vol. xx., p. 20.)</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The increase of human knwledge, and the immense<lb break="yes"/>progress of science, arts, and industry among the west-<lb break="no"/>ern nations, have given us powers which only call for<lb break="yes"/>application. Everything depends upon energy and per-<lb break="no"/>severance. I therefore congratulate you, Sir, and your<lb break="yes"/>courageous friend, Dr. Cullen, as well as Sir Charles<lb break="yes"/>Fox, Mr. Henderson, and Mr. Brassey, for having<lb break="yes"/>given your names to so noble an undertaking. I have<lb break="yes"/>always considered, firstly, the opening of an oceanic<lb break="yes"/>canal, without locks; and secondly, the cut at<lb break="yes" />Huchuecoca, in the valley of Mexico (which is on a<lb break="yes" />comparatively smaller scale, as may be seen by the<lb break="yes"/>map and section I published), as two events calculated<lb break="yes"/>highly to improve the relations between the different<lb break="yes"/>families of the human species. In fact, such a work as<lb break="yes"/>the one you contemplate will bring Eastern Asia nearer<lb break="yes"/>to the nations of Europe and America. It will render<lb break="yes"/>the whole globe more easy to be travelled over&#x2014;this<lb break="yes"/>little globe, of which Christopher Columbus, in one of<lb break="yes"/>his letters to the Queen of Spain, said, &#x2018;<hi rendition="#i">el mundo es<lb break="yes"/>poco.</hi>&#x2019; It will facilitate the diffusion of productions,<lb break="yes"/>especially of precious metals, of which the relative value<lb break="yes"/>(1 to 15 5-6ths) would change too suddenly without this<lb break="yes" />&#x2018;permeability&#x2019; of the world.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;As early as the discovery of the new Continent,<lb break="yes" />civilisation had spread, in a direction from north to<lb break="yes"/>south, over those portions of America which he op-<lb break="no"/>posite to Asia, those on the European side being then<lb break="yes"/>occupied by barharous hunting tribes. The finest<lb break="yes"/>harbours, the most precious products, are likewise<lb break="yes"/>found in the West. Even the currents of the air, by<lb break="yes"/>their direction, contribute towards the preponderance<lb break="yes"/>of West American power over the rich countries of<lb break="yes"/>Asia. The increasing importance of the west coast of<lb break="yes"/>America promises to balance, at some future time, the<lb break="yes"/>surprising progress of the Atlantic States, provided the<lb break="yes"/>western States keep themselves free from that hideous<lb break="yes"/>disease&#x2014;slavery of coloured people.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Indeed, Sir, I feel the most ardent wishes for the<lb break="yes"/>happy suceess of this oceanic canal. The attention<lb break="yes"/>which the public of the two continents bestows already<lb break="yes"/>upon your undertaking will increase, as soon as you<lb break="yes"/>are enabled, assisted by further explorations, and a<lb break="yes"/>survey extending over all details, and carried on by a<lb break="yes"/>great number of experienced men, to publish, on a<lb break="yes"/>large scale, maps and sections of the line fixed upon<lb break="yes"/>between Puerto Escoces and the Gulf of San Miguel.<lb break="yes"/>The changes which the success of your undertaking<lb break="yes"/>is sure to effect in the international commerce<lb break="yes" />of the world will only disturb such people as in<lb break="yes"/>the narrowness of their viewa oppose themselves<lb break="yes"/>to the natural and providential course of events,<lb break="yes"/>and shed tears over the unfortunate discovery of<lb break="yes"/>America. The Rio Huaxacualco with its portage<lb break="yes"/>to the Rio Chimalapa (Tchuantepee), of which I pub-<lb break="no"/>lished the first map after the itineraries discovered by<lb break="yes"/>me in the archives of the vice-kingdom of Mexico, will<lb break="yes"/>always be of great importance, owing to its position<lb break="yes"/>opposite Louisiana, in the Gulf of Mexico, which has<lb break="yes"/>all the appearance of soon becoming a <hi rendition="#i">mare clausum</hi>&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>a lake of the United States. The nature of the soil,<lb break="yes"/>however, does not allow great works to be carried out<lb break="yes"/>in that locality; besides, you know the difficulties im-<lb break="no"/>peding any canalization or rectification of rivers of<lb break="yes"/>great length, and the great variations of the volume of<lb break="yes"/>water, as in the river San Juan; but a radway would<lb break="yes"/>be a great advantage to the southern States.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The great interest which every one at the present<lb break="yes"/>time takes in the canalization of the Isthmua recalls a<lb break="yes"/>similar fact to my memory, reminding me of the sudden<lb break="yes"/>interest created by the discovery of guano.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;I was the first who brought guano to Europe, of<lb break="yes"/>which Klaproth and Vanquchn published an analysis.<lb break="yes"/>During 40 years I preached, but always in vain, the use-<lb break="no"/>fulness of this substance, and in vain did I recommend<lb break="yes"/>its employment in fertilising the fields of Europe. But it<lb break="yes"/>is only 15 or 18 years since it has at last become a great<lb break="yes"/>article of commerce.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <closer>
                    <salute>&#x201C;I beg of you, my dear Sir, to present my kind re-<lb break="no" />membrance to the excellent and able Mr. Peterman, &#x0026;c.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von Humboldt.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <postscript>
                    <p>&#x201C;P.S. I am not surprised at the difference between<lb break="yes"/>the level you found at Turbaco and my own statement.<lb break="yes"/>To this, however, I had prudently added, &#x2018;doubtful<lb break="yes" />barometrical observation.&#x2019; (See my <hi rendition="#i">Recueil d&#x2019;Obserca-<lb break="no"/>tions Astronomiques et de Mesures Barometriques,</hi> vol.<lb break="yes"/>i. p. 299.) The fact that the gas issuing from the little<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes at Turbaco is inflammable in its natural state<lb break="yes"/>has already been communicated by Colonel Acosta<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">(Journal,</hi> p. 65). It appears that the gaseons fluid<lb break="yes"/>which issues from the &#x2018;salses&#x2019; is not the same at all<lb break="yes"/>times. I find in my journal that, in 1801, the flame of<lb break="yes"/>any burning substance was suddenly extinguished on<lb break="yes"/>being thrown into a bottle containing air from those<lb break="yes"/>little volcanoes.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Parrot, also, in the mud volcanoes in the island of<lb break="yes" />Taman, found only azote, although the gas emitted<lb break="yes"/>would burn at other times. (See my <hi rendition="#i">Relation Histo-<lb break="no"/>rique,</hi> vol. xii., chap. 29, p. 367 371).&#x201D;</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 