<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>THE ISTHMUS OF DARIEN.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following interesting letter from Baron Alexander<lb break="yes"/>Von Humboldt to Lionel Gisborne, Esq., M.A., C.E., has<lb break="yes"/>been made public:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <opener>
                        <salute>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Sir,</hi>
                        </salute>
                    </opener>
                    <p>&#x2014;I trust you will excuse the oldest among the<lb break="yes"
                        />travellers in both the tropics of America and the steppes<lb break="yes"
                        />of Siberia, for having so long delayed to thank you for<lb break="yes"
                        />the information I derived from your interesting journal,<lb break="yes"
                        />&#x0026;c., on the junction of the Atlantic with the Pacific.<lb
                            break="yes"/>The position I occupy in this country, and the ardent<lb
                            break="yes"/>desire I feel to finish, before my death, some
                            scientific<lb break="yes"/>works which I had the imprudence to begin,
                            considerably<lb break="yes"/>interrupt the even course of my
                        correspondence. I<lb break="yes"/>therefore hope that I shall meet, on your
                        part also, with<lb break="yes"/>that indulgence which your countrymen have
                        shown me<lb break="yes"/>during so long a period.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;I have not been beyond the Rio Rimo, which lies<lb break="yes"/>east
                        of the mouth of the Atrato, since the time when I<lb break="yes"/>left the
                        island of Cuba on my way to Lima by Bogota,<lb break="yes"/>Quito, and the
                        river Amazon, for the purpose of ob-<lb break="no"/>serving the passage of
                        Mercury through the solar disc.<lb break="yes"/>I was then on friendly terms
                        with a very intelligent<lb break="yes"/>merchant, Don Ignacio Iombo, of
                        Cartagena, in Ame-<lb break="no"/>rica, and I recollect that the Casso
                        (Treasury convoy)<lb break="yes"/>of Guayaquil was then on its way to
                        Europe, by the<lb break="yes"/>road from Cupica to the Atrato, which was
                        first opened<lb break="yes"/>by the Biscayan pilot Poguerache. Knowing,
                            geologi-<lb break="no"/>cally, the interruption of the mountain chains,
                        and the<lb break="yes"/>depression of the range in the eastern part of the
                            Isth-<lb break="no"/>mus, my attention has remained fixed during this
                            last<lb break="yes"/>half century on the Bay of San Miguel and the
                            route<lb break="yes"/>from Cupica to the Rio Napipi. Owing to my
                            friendly<lb break="yes"/>relations with General Bolivar, I obtained
                        through him<lb break="yes"/>the first line of levels across the Isthmus of
                            Panama.<lb break="yes"/>Ever since the subject has not ceased to occupy
                            my<lb break="yes"/>mind, as the various works and maps which I
                            published<lb break="yes"/>since 1810, and my correspondence with various
                            states-<lb break="no"/>men, will testify. But all my striving and urging
                            only<lb break="yes"/>led to imperfect trials and projects calculated for
                        a line<lb break="yes"/>to the west of the meridian of Panama and
                            Portobello,<lb break="yes"/>none of which ever gained my confidence. I
                        had, how-<lb break="no"/>ever, the gratification of seeing my views honoured
                            by<lb break="yes"/>an eminent member of her Britannic Majesty&#x2019;s
                            navy,<lb break="yes"/>Captain Fitzroy. <hi rendition="#i">(Journal of
                            the Royal Geographical<lb break="yes"/>Society,</hi> vol. xx., p.
                        20.)</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The increase of human knowledge, and the immense<lb break="yes"
                        />progress of science, arts, and industry among the wes-<lb break="no"/>tern
                        nations, have given us powers which only call for<lb break="yes"
                        />application. Everything depends upon energy and per-<lb break="no"
                        />severance. I therefore congratulate you, sir, and your<lb break="yes"
                        />courageous friend, Dr. Cullen, as well as Sir Charles<lb break="yes"/>Fox,
                        Mr. Henderson, and Mr. Brassey, for having given<lb break="yes"/>your names
                        to so noble an undertaking. I have always<lb break="yes"/>considered,
                        firstly, the opening of an oceanic canal,<lb break="yes"/>without locks; and
                        secondly, the cut at Huchuecoca, in<lb break="yes"/>the valley of Mexico
                        (which is on a comparatively<lb break="yes"/>smaller scale, as may be seen
                        by the map and section I<lb break="yes"/>published), as two events
                        calculated highly to improve<lb break="yes"/>the relations between the
                        different families of the human<lb break="yes"/>species. In fact, such a
                        work as the one you contem-<lb break="no"/>plate will bring Eastern Asia
                        nearer to the nations of<lb break="yes"/>Europe and America. It will render
                        the whole globe<lb break="yes"/>more easy to be travelled over&#x2014;this
                        little globe of which<lb break="yes"/>Christopher Columbus, in one of his
                        letters to the<lb break="yes"/>Queen of Spain, said. &#x2018;<hi
                            rendition="#i">el mundo es poco.</hi>&#x2019; It will facili-<lb
                            break="no"/>tate the diffusion of productions, especially of precious<lb
                            break="yes"/>metals, of which the relative value (1 to 15 5-6ths)<lb
                            break="yes"/>would change too suddenly without this
                            &#x2018;permeability&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>of the world.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;As early as the discovery of the new continent,<lb break="yes"
                        />civilization had spread, in a direction from north to<lb break="yes"
                        />south, over those portions of America which lie oppo-<lb break="no"/>site
                        to Asia, those on the European side being then<lb break="yes"/>occupied by
                        barbarous hunting tribes. The finest har-<lb break="no"/>bours, the most
                        precious products, are likewise found in<lb break="yes"/>the west. Even the
                        currents of the air, by their direc-<lb break="no"/>tion, contribute towards
                        the preponderance of West<lb break="yes"/>American power over the rich
                        countries of Asia. The<lb break="yes"/>increasing importance of the west
                        coast of America pro-<lb break="no"/>mises to balance, at some future time,
                        the surprising<lb break="yes"/>progress of the Atlantic States, provided the
                            western<lb break="yes"/>States keep themselves free from that hideous
                            disease&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>slavery of coloured people.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Indeed, sir, I feel the most ardent wishes for the<lb break="yes"
                        />happy success of this oceanic canal. The attention<lb break="yes"/>which
                        the public of the two continents bestows already<lb break="yes"/>upon your
                        undertaking will increase, as soon as you<lb break="yes"/>are enabled,
                        assisted by further explorations, and a<lb break="yes"/>survey extending
                        over all details, and carried on by a<lb break="yes"/>great number of
                        experienced men, to publish, on a large<lb break="yes"/>scale, maps and
                        sections of the line fixed upon between<lb break="yes"/>Puerto Escoces and
                        the Gulf of San Miguel. The<lb break="yes"/>changes which the success of
                        your undertaking is sure<lb break="yes"/>to effect in the international
                        commerce of the world will<lb break="yes"/>only disturb such people as in
                        the narrowness of their<lb break="yes"/>views oppose themselves to the
                        natural and providential<lb break="yes"/>course of events, and shed tears
                        over the unfortunate<lb break="yes"/>discovery of America. The Rio
                        Huaxacualco with its<lb break="yes"/>portage to the Rio Chimalapa
                        (Tehuantepec), of which<lb break="yes"/>I published the first map after the
                        itineraries discovered<lb break="yes"/>by me in the archives of the
                        vice-kingdom of Mexico,<lb break="yes"/>will always be of great importance,
                        owing to its position<lb break="yes"/>opposite Louisiana, in the Gulf of
                        Mexico, which has<lb break="yes"/>all the appearance of soon becoming a <hi
                            rendition="#i">mare clausum</hi>&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>a lake of the
                        United States. The nature of the soil,<lb break="yes"/>however, does not
                        allow great works to be carried out<lb break="yes"/>in that locality;
                        besides, you know the difficulties im-<lb break="no"/>peding any
                        canalization or rectification of rivers of<lb break="yes"/>great length, and
                        the great variations of the volume of<lb break="yes"/>water, as in the river
                        San Juan; but a railway would be<lb break="yes"/>a great advantge to the
                        southern states.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The great interest which every one at the present<lb break="yes"
                        />time takes in the canalization of the Isthmus recalls a<lb break="yes"
                        />similar fact to my memory, reminding me of the sudden<lb break="yes"
                        />interest created by the discovery of guano.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;I was the first who brought guano to Europe, of<lb break="yes"/>which
                        Klaproth and Vanquelin published an analysis.<lb break="yes"/>During forty
                        years I preached, but always in vain,<lb break="yes"/>the usefulness of this
                        substance, and in vain did I<lb break="yes"/>recommend its employment in
                        fertilising the fields of<lb break="yes"/>Europe. But it is only fifteen or
                        eighteen years since it<lb break="yes"/>has at last become a great article
                        of commerce.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <closer>
                        <salute>&#x201C;I beg of you, my dear sir, to present my kind<lb break="yes"
                            />remembrance to the excellent and able Mr. Peter-<lb break="no"/>man,
                                &#x0026;c.<lb break="yes"/>
                            <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von
                                    Humboldt</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </salute>
                    </closer>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>&#x201C;P.S.&#x2014;I am not surprised at the difference between<lb
                                break="yes"/>the level you found at Turbaco and my own statement.<lb
                                break="yes"/>To this, however, I had prudently added,
                                &#x2018;doubtful<lb break="yes"/>barometrical observation.&#x2019;
                            (See my <hi rendition="#i">Recucil d&#x2019;Observa-<lb break="no"
                                />tions Astronomiques et de Mesures Barométriques.</hi> vol. i.<lb
                                break="yes"/>p. 299.) The fact that the gas issuing from the
                                little<lb break="yes"/>volcanoes at Turbaco is inflammable in its
                            natural state<lb break="yes"/>has already been communicated by Colonel
                                Acosta<lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">Journal,</hi> p. 65). It
                            appears that the gaseous fluid<lb break="yes"/>which issues from the
                            &#x2018;salses&#x2019; is not the same at all<lb break="yes"/>times. I
                            find in my journal that, in 1801, the flame of<lb break="yes"/>any
                            burning substance was suddenly extinguished on<lb break="yes"/>being
                            thrown into a bottle containing air from those<lb break="yes"/>little
                            volcanoes.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>&#x201C;Parrot, also, in the mud volcanoes in the island of<lb
                                break="yes"/>Taman, found only azote, although the gas emitted<lb
                                break="yes"/>would burn at other times. (See my <hi rendition="#i"
                                >Relation Histo-<lb break="no"/>rique,</hi> vol. xii., chap. 29, p.
                            367-371).&#x201D;</p>
                    </postscript>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 