<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head>The Isthmus of Darien<lb/>LETTER FROM BARON ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT<lb/>TO LIONEL GISBORNE, ESQ., M. A., C. E.<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Translated from the French original.</hi></head><lb/><p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Sir:</hi> I trust that you will excuse the old-<lb/>est among the travelers, in both the tropics of Ame-<lb/>rica and the steppes of Siberia, for having so long<lb/>delayed to thank you for the information I derived<lb/>from your interesting journal, &amp;c., on the junction<lb/>of the Atlantic with the Pacific. The position I<lb/>occupy in this country, and the ardent desire I feel<lb/>to finish, before my death, some scientific works<lb/>which I had the imprudence to begin, considerably<lb/>interrupt the even course of my correspondence. I<lb/>therefore hope that I shall meet, on your part also,<lb/>with that indulgence which your countrymen have<lb/>shown me during so long a period.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;I have not been beyond the Rio Rimo, which<lb/>lies east of the mouth of the Atrato,
                    since the time<lb/>when I left the Island of Cuba, on my way to Lima<lb/>by
                    Bogota, Quito, and the River Amazon, for the<lb/>purpose of observing the
                    passage of Mercury<lb/>through the solar disc. I was then on friendly
                    terms<lb/>with a very intelligent merchant, Don <hi rendition="#k"
                        >Ignacio<lb/>Iombo,</hi> of Carthagena, in America: and I recollect<lb/>that
                    the <hi rendition="#i">Casso</hi> (treasury convoy) of Guayaquil, was<lb/>then
                    on its way to Europe, by the road from Cupicà<lb/>to the Atrato, which was first
                    opened by the Biscay<lb/>an pilot, <hi rendition="#k">Poguerache.</hi> Knowing,
                    geologically, the<lb/>interruption of the mountain chains, and the
                    depres-<lb/>sion of the range in the eastern part of the Isthmus,<lb/>my
                    attention has remained fixed during this last half<lb/>century on the Bay of San
                    Miguel and the route<lb/>from Cupicà to the Rio Napipi. Owing to my<lb/>friendly
                    relations with General <hi rendition="#k">Bolivar,</hi> I ob-<lb/>tained through
                    him the first line of levels across the<lb/>Isthmus of Panama. Ever since, the
                    subject has<lb/>not ceased to occupy my mind, as the various works<lb/>and maps
                    which I published since 1810, and my<lb/>correspondenee with various statesmen
                    will testify.<lb/>But all my striving and urging only led to
                    imperfect<lb/>trials and projects, calculated for a line to the west<lb/>of the
                    meridian of Panama and Portobello, none of<lb/>which ever gained my confidence.
                    I had, however,<lb/>the gratification of seeing my views honored by
                    an<lb/>eminent member of Her Britannic Majesty&#x2019;s Navy,<lb/>Captain <hi
                        rendition="#k">Fitzroy.</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Royal
                        Geographi-<lb/>cal Society,</hi> Vol. xx., p. 30)</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;The increase of human knowledge, and the im-<lb/><pb facs="#f0002"/> mense progress of
                    science, arts, and industry<lb/>ameng the western nations, have given us
                    powers<lb/>which only call for application. Everything de-<lb/>pends upon energy
                    and perseverance. I therefore<lb/>congratulate you, Sir, and your courageous
                    friend,<lb/>Dr. <hi rendition="#k">Cullen,</hi> as well as Sir <hi
                        rendition="#k">Charles Fox,</hi> Mr.<lb/><hi rendition="#k">Henderson,</hi>
                    and Mr. <hi rendition="#k">Brassey,</hi> for having given<lb/>your names to so
                    noble an undertaking. I have<lb/>always considered, firstly, the opening of an
                    oceanic<lb/>canal, without locks; and secondly, the cut at<lb/>Huchuecoca, in
                    the valley of Mexico (which is on<lb/>a comparatively smaller scale, and may be
                    seen by<lb/>the map and section I published,) as two events<lb/>calculated
                    highly to improve the relations between<lb/>the different families of the human
                    species. In fact,<lb/>such a work as the one you contemplate will
                    bring<lb/>Eastern Asia nearer to the nations of Europe and<lb/>America. It will
                    render the whole globe more<lb/>easily traveled over&#x2014;this little globe,
                    of which<lb/><hi rendition="#k">Christopher Columbus,</hi> in one of his letters
                    to<lb/>the Queen of Spain, said, &#x2018;<hi rendition="#i">el mundo es
                        poco.</hi>&#x2019; It<lb/>will facilitate the diffusion of productions,
                    especial-<lb/>ly of precious metals, of which the relative value<lb/>(1 to 55
                    5.6ths) would change too suddenly without<lb/>this &#x2018;permeability&#x2019;
                    of the world.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;As early as the discovery of the new continent,<lb/>civilization had spread, in a direction from north to<lb/>south, over those portions of America which lie<lb/>opposite to Asia, those on the European side being<lb/>then occupied by barbarous hunting tribes. The<lb/>finest harbors, the most precious products, are like-<lb/>wise found in the West. Even the currents of the<lb/>air, by their direction, contribute towards the pre-<lb/>ponderance of West American power over the rich<lb/>countries of Asia. The increasing importance of<lb/>the west coast of America promises to balance, at<lb/>some future time, the surprising progress of the<lb/>Atlantic States, provided the Western States keep<lb/>themselves free from that hideous disease&#x2014;slavery<lb/>of colored people.</p><lb/><pb facs="#f0003" />
<p>&#x201C;Indeed, Sir, I feel the most ardent wishes for<lb/>the happy success of this oceanic
                    canal. The at-<lb/>tention which the public of the two continents be-<lb/>stows
                    already upon your undertaking will increase,<lb/>as soon as you are enabled,
                    assisted by further ex-<lb/>plorations, and a survey extending over all
                    details,<lb/>and carried on by a great number of experienced<lb/>men, to
                    publish, on a large scale, maps and sections<lb/>of the line fixed upon between
                    Puerto Escoces and<lb/>the Gulf of San Miguel. The changes which the<lb/>success
                    of your undertaking is sure to effect in<lb/>the international commerce of the
                    world will only<lb/>disturb such people as in the narrowness of their<lb/>views
                    oppose themselves to the natural and Provi-<lb/>dential course of events, and
                    shed tears over the<lb/>unfortunate discovery of America. The
                    Rio<lb/>Huaxacualco, with its portage to the Rio Chimala-<lb/>pa, (Tehuantepec,)
                    of which I published the first<lb/>map after the itineraries discovered by me in
                    the<lb/>archives of the vice-kingdom of Mexico, will al-<lb/>ways be of great
                    importance, owing to its position<lb/>opposite Louisiana, in the Gulf of Mexico,
                    which<lb/>has all the appearance of soon becoming a <hi rendition="#i"
                        >mare<lb/>clausum</hi>&#x2014;a lake of the United States. The nature<lb/>of
                    the soil, however, does not allow great works to<lb/>be carried out in that
                    locality; besides, you know<lb/>the difficulties impending any canalization or
                    recti-<lb/>fication of rivers of great length, and the great va-<lb/>riations of
                    the volume of water, as in the river<lb/>San Juan; but a Railway would be a
                    great advan-<lb/>tage to the Southern States.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;The great interest which every one at the<lb/>present time takes in the canalization of the Isth-<lb/>mus, recalls a similar fact to my memory, remind-<lb/>ing me of the sudden interest created by the discov-<lb/>ery of guano.</p><lb/><pb facs="#f0004" />
<p>&#x201C;I was the first who brought guano to Europe, of<lb/>which <hi rendition="#k">Klaproth</hi> and <hi rendition="#k">Vauquelin</hi> published an an-<lb/>alysis. During 40 years I preached, but always in<lb/>vain, the usefulness of this substance, and in vain<lb/>did I recommend its employment in fertilizing the<lb/>fields of Europe. But it is only 15 or 18 years<lb/>since it has at last become a great article of com-<lb/>merce.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;I beg of you, my dear Sir, to present my kind<lb/>remembrance to the excellent and able Mr. <hi rendition="#k">Peter-<lb/>man,</hi> &amp;c., <hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von Humboldt.</hi></p><lb/><p>&#x201C;P. S.&#x2014;I am not surprised at the difference be-<lb/>tween the level you found at Turbaco and my own<lb/>statement. To this, however, I had prudently<lb/>added &#x2018;doubtful barometrical observation.&#x2019; (See<lb/>my <hi rendition="#i">Recueil d&#x2019;Observations Astronomiques et de<lb/>Mesures Barométriques,</hi> vol. i. p. 299.) The fact<lb/>that the gas issuing from the little volcanoes at<lb/>Turbaco is inflammable in its natural state has al-<lb/>ready been communicated by Colonel <hi rendition="#k">Acosta.</hi><lb/>(<hi rendition="#i">Journal,</hi> p. 65). It appears that the gaseous fluid<lb/>which issues from the &#x2018;salses&#x2019; is not the same at all<lb/>times. I find in my journal that, in 1801, the flame<lb/>of any burning substance was suddenly extinguished<lb/>on being thrown into a bottle containing air from<lb/>these little volcanoes.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Parrot,</hi> also, in the mud volcanoes in the<lb/>island of Taman found only azote, although the<lb/>gas emitted would burn at other times. (See my<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Relation Historique,</hi> vol. xii, chap. 20, p. 367&#x2014;371.)&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
