<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="479" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head>HUMBOLDT AND DE BUCH.</head><lb/>
<p>Science has lost a distinguished apostle in the person of<lb/>the celebrated geologist, Baron Christian Leopold von<lb/>Buch, who died at Berlin on the 4th instant, after a few<lb/>days&#x2019; illness, in his 79th year. The melancholy event is<lb/>thus announced to Sir Richard Murchison, by von Buch&#x2019;s<lb/>venerable friend and fellow-student, Alexander von Hum-<lb/>boldt. We were unavoidably obliged, by pressure of space,<lb/>to omit this interesting document from last week&#x2019;s publica-<lb/>tion:&#x2014;</p><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#et">Berlin, March 4, 1853.</hi></dateline><lb/>
</div>
<div>
                    <p>That I should be destined&#x2014;I, an old man of 83&#x2014; to<lb/>announce to you, dear
                    Roderick, the saddest news that I<lb/>could have to convey&#x2014;to you for
                    whom M. de Buch pro-<lb/>fessed a friendship so tender&#x2014;and to the many
                    admirers of<lb/>his genius, his vast labours, and his noble
                    character!<lb/>Leopold De Buch was taken from us this morning by<lb/>typhoid
                    fever&#x2014;so violent in its attack that two days only<lb/>of danger warned
                    us. He was at my house so lately as the<lb/>26th ult., despite the snow and the
                    distance between us&#x2014;<lb/>talking geology with the most lively interest.
                    That evening<lb/>he went into society, and on Sunday and Monday (the
                    27th<lb/>and 28th) he complained of a feverish swelling from which<lb/>he had
                    suffered for years. The inflammation required the<lb/>application of
                    leeches&#x2014;but the pain and the fever in-<lb/>creased. He was speechless for
                    38 hours. ... He<lb/>died surrounded by his friends, most of whom
                    knew<lb/>nothing of his danger till Wednesday evening, the 2nd of<lb/>March. He
                    and I were united by a friendship of 63<lb/>years&#x2014;a friendship which
                    never knew interruption. I<lb/>found him in 1791, in Werner&#x2019;s house in
                    Freiberg, when I<lb/>entered the School of Mines. We were together in
                    Italy,<lb/>in Switzerland, in France, four months in Saltzburg. M.<lb/>De Buch
                    was not only one of the great illustrations of his<lb/>age&#x2014;he was a man
                    of noble soul. His mind left a track<lb/>of light&#x2014;he could boast of
                    having extended the limits of<lb/>geological science. I grieve for him
                    profoundly&#x2014;without<lb/>him I feel desolate. I consulted him as muster;
                    and his<lb/>affection (like that of Gay Lussac and that of Arago, who<lb/>were
                    also his friends) sustained me in my labours. He was<lb/>four years my
                    junior&#x2014;and nothing forewarned me of this<lb/>misfortune. It is not at the
                    distance of a few hours only<lb/>from such a loss that I can say more respecting
                    it. Pity<lb/>me&#x2014;and accept the homage of my profound respect
                    and<lb/>affectionate devotion.</p><lb/><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#k">Al. Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute></closer></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
