<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head>ISTHMUS OF DARIEN SHIP CANAL.<lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
(<hi rendition="#i">Ttanslation from the French.</hi>)</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#k">to dr. edward cullen, strand, london.</hi></hi></p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">Sir,</hi>&#x2014;I am very much to blame for having so long de-<lb/>layed an
                    answer to the agreeable and interesting dispatch<lb/>that you have been kind
                    enough to forward me by the<lb/>hands of Mr. Augustus Peterman, so estimable by
                    his cha-<lb/>racter, as well as by the solidity of his geographical
                    labours.<lb/>Dr. Cullen cannot doubt the high importance that I would<lb/>attach
                    to the merit of his courageous and useful investiga-<lb/>tions in the eastern
                    part of the Isthmus of Panama; know-<lb/>ing my position and my antediluvian
                    age, he will receive<lb/>with indulgence, even so late, the expression of my
                    lively<lb/>gratitude.</p><lb/><p>After having laboured in vain during half a century to<lb/>prove the possibility of an Oceanic
                    Canal, and to point out<lb/>the Gulf of San Miguel and Cupica as the points most
                    wor-<lb/>thy of attention&#x2014;after having regretted, almost with
                    bitter-<lb/>ness, in the last edition of my &#x201C;Aspects of Nature,&#x201D;
                    that<lb/>the employment of the means, which the present state of<lb/>our
                    knowledge affords, for obtaining precise measurements<lb/>has been so long
                    delayed&#x2014;I ought, more than any one else,<lb/>to be satisfied to see at
                    last my hopes for so noble an enter-<lb/>prise revived. By your publications,
                    sir, and by that of Mr.<lb/>Gisborne, will be originated the great work of
                    changing an<lb/>important part of the commerce of nations, and of
                    rendering<lb/>more accessible the rich countries of Eastera Asia and
                    the<lb/>Indian Archipelago. The undertaking is by no means above<lb/>the
                    intellectual and material power which civilized nations<lb/>have attained to.
                    The work should be one to last for ever;<lb/>it should not commence with a canal
                    with locks, like the<lb/>magnificent Caledonian Canal; it must be a really
                    Oceanic<lb/>Canal, without locks; a free passage from sea to sea,
                    across<lb/>which the speed of the navigation will be modified, but
                    not<lb/>interrupted, by the differences in height and non-coincidence<lb/>of the
                    tides.</p><lb/><closer><salute>Receive, I pray you, Sir, the expression of my highest<lb/>consideration.&#x2014;Yours,
                        &#x0026;c., &#x0026;c.,<lb/><hi rendition="#et">(Signed) ALEXANDER VON
                            HUMBOLDT.</hi></salute></closer><lb/><dateline>Potsdam, 4th June, 1852.</dateline></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
