<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="240" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head>THE EXTINCT AMERICAN RACE.</head><lb/><p>&#x201C;As,&#x201D; says Humboldt, &#x201C;properly speaking, only civilised na-<lb/>tions have a
                    history, the history of the Americans is necessarily<lb/>no more than that of a
                    small portion of the inhabitants of the<lb/>mountains. Profound obscurity
                    envelopes the vast country<lb/>which stretches from the eastern slope of the
                    Cordilleras towards<lb/>the Atlantic; and for this very reason, whatever in that
                    country<lb/>relates to the preponderance of one nation over others, to
                    distant<lb/>migrations, to the physiognomical features which denote a
                    foreign<lb/>race, excite our deepest<lb/>interest. Amidst the<lb/>plains of
                    North America,<lb/>some powerful nation,<lb/>which has disappeared,<lb/><hi
                        rendition="#g">constructed circular,</hi><lb/>square, and octagonal
                    for-<lb/>tifications; walls 6,000<lb/>toises in length; tumuli<lb/>from seven to
                    eight hun-<lb/>dred feet in diameter,<lb/>and an hundred and forty<lb/>feet in
                    height, sometimes<lb/>round, sometimes with<lb/>several storeys, and
                    con-<lb/>taining thousands of skele-<lb/>tons. These skeletons are<lb/>the
                    remains of men less<lb/>slender and more squat<lb/>than the present
                    inhabi-<lb/>tants of those countries.<lb/>Other bones, wrapped in<lb/>fabrics,
                    resembling those<lb/>of the Sandwich and<lb/>Feejee Islands, are found<lb/>in
                    the natural grottoes<lb/>of Kentucky. What is<lb/>become of those nations<lb/>of
                    Louisiana anterior to<lb/>the Lenni-Lenapes, the<lb/>Shawanese, and
                    perhaps<lb/>even to the Sioux (Nado-<lb/>wessess, Nahcotas) of the<lb/>Missouri,
                    who are strongly<lb/>Mongolised, and who, it<lb/>is believed, according
                    to<lb/>their own additions, came<lb/>from the coast of Asia?<lb/>In the plains
                    of South<lb/>America we find only a<lb/>very few hillocks of that<lb/>kind,
                    called cerros hechos<lb/>a mano; and no where<lb/>any works of
                    fortification<lb/>analogous to those of the<lb/>Ohio. However, on a<lb/>vast
                    space of ground, at<lb/>the Lower Orinoco, as<lb/>well as on the banks
                    of<lb/>the Cassiquiare, and be-<lb/>tween the sources of the<lb/>Essequibo and
                    the Rio<lb/>Branco, there are rocks<lb/>of granite covered with<lb/>symbolic
                    figures. These<lb/>sculptures denote that the<lb/>extinct generations
                    be-<lb/>longed to nations different<lb/>from those which now in-<lb/>habit the
                    same regions<lb/>There seems to be no<lb/>connection between the<lb/>history of
                    Mexico and<lb/>that of the Cundinamarca<lb/>and of Peru; but in the<lb/>plains
                    of the east a warlike<lb/>and long dominant nation<lb/>betrays in its features
                    and<lb/>its physical constitution traces of a foreign origin. The<lb/>Caribs
                    preserve traditions that seem to indicate ancient<lb/>communications between
    North and South America. Such<lb/>a phenomenon <choice><sic>deerves</sic><corr type="editorial">deserves</corr></choice> particular attention. If
                    it be true<lb/>that savages are for the most part degenerate races,
                    rem-<lb/>nants escaped from a common wreck, as their languages,<lb/>their
                    cosmogonic fables, and numerous other indications seem to<lb/>prove, it becomes
                    doubly important to examine the course by<lb/>which these remnants have been
                    driven from one hemisphere to<lb/>the other.&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
