<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><body><pb facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Noon in the Tropics.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;The soil appeared to un-<lb/>dulate, from the effect of mirage, without a breath<lb/>of
                    wind being felt. The sun was near the zenith,<lb/>and its dazzling light,
                    reflected from the surface of<lb/>the river, contrasted with the reddish vapors
                    that<lb/>enveloped every surrounding object. How vivid is<lb/>the impression
                    produced by the calm of nature, at<lb/>noon, in these burning climes! The beasts
                    of the<lb/>forests retire to the thickets; the birds hide them-<lb/>selves
                    beneath the foliage of the trees, or in the<lb/>crevices of the rocks. Yet,
                    amidst this apparent<lb/>silence, when we lend an attentive car to the
                    most<lb/>feeble sounds transmitted through the air, we hear a<lb/>dull
                    vibration, a continual murmur, a hum of in-<lb/>sects, filling, if we may use
                    the expression, all the<lb/>lower strata of the air. Myriads of insects creep
                    upon<lb/>the soil and flutter round the plants parched by the<lb/>heat of the
                    sun. A confused noise issues from every<lb/>bush, from the decayed trunks of
                    trees, from the<lb/>clefts of rocks, and from the ground undermined
                    by<lb/>lizards, millepedes, and <hi rendition="#i">cecilias.</hi> These are so
                    many<lb/>voices proclaiming to us that all nature breathes;<lb/>and that, under
                    a thousand different forms, life is<lb/>diffused throughout the cracked and
                    dusty soil, as<lb/>well as in the bosom of the waters, and in the air<lb/>around
                        us.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Personal Narrative.</hi></p></div><lb/>
</body></text>
</TEI>
