<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
    <div><p>M. <hi rendition="#k">De Bu@.</hi>&#x2014;The following is a translation of an affecting<lb/>letter from the veteran Baron Alexander Humboldt to Sir<lb/>Roderick Murchison, the original of which has been kindly<lb/>communicated by Sir. Roderick to us (<hi rendition="#i">Athen&#x0153;um</hi>@ It con-<lb/>vey@ intelligence which will be beard with great regret in the<lb/>scientific world of England:&#x2014;</p><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Berlin, March 4. 1853.</hi></dateline></div><lb/><div><p>&#x201C;That I should be destined&#x2014;I. an old man of 83&#x2014;to an-<lb/>nounce to you, dear Roderick the saddest news that I could<lb/>have to convey&#x2014;to you for whom M. De Buch professed a<lb/>friendship so tender&#x2014;and to the many admirers of his genius.<lb/>his vast labours, and his noble character! Leopold De Buch<lb/>was taken from us this morning by typhoid fever&#x2014;so violent<lb/>in its attack that two days only of danger warned us. He was<lb/>at my house @ lately as the 26th ult., desp@ the snow and<lb/>the distance between us&#x2014;talking geology with the most lively<lb/>interest. That evening he went into society, and on Sunday<lb/>and Monday (the 27th and 28th) he complain@ of a feverish<lb/>attack, which he believed to be caused by a @rge chilblain<lb/>swelling from which he had suffered for years. The inflam-<lb/>mation required the application of leeches&#x2014;but the pain and<lb/>the fever increased. He was speech@s for 38 hours. .</p><lb/><p>He died surrounded by his friends, most of whom knew nothing<lb/>of his danger till Wednesday evening. the 2nd of March.<lb/>He and I were united by a friendship of 63 years&#x2014;a friend-<lb/>ship which never knew interruption. I found him in 1791.<lb/>in Werner&#x2019;s house in Freiberg, when I entered the School of<lb/>Mines. We were together in Italy, in Switzerland, in France.<lb/>four months in Salt@burg. M. De Buch was not only one of<lb/>the great illustrations of his age&#x2014;he was a man of noble<lb/>soul. His mind left a track of light wherever it passed<lb/>Always in contact with Nature herself&#x2014;he could bo@t of huv<lb/>Ing extended the limits of geological science. I grieve for<lb/>him profoundly&#x2014;without him I feel desolate. I consulted<lb/>him as master; and his affection (like that of Gay Lu@sac and<lb/>that of Arago. who were also his friend@) sustained me in my<lb/>labours. He was four years my junior&#x2014;and nothing fore-<lb/>warned me ofthis misfortune. It is not at the distance of a<lb/>few hours only from such a loss that I can say more respecting<lb/>it. Pity me&#x2014;and accept the homage of my profound respect<lb/>and affectionate devotion.</p><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Al. Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute></closer></div><lb/><div><p>&#x201C;And my poor countryman Overweg, in Africa! What a<lb/>blessing to learn one day by means of the astronomer Vogel<lb/>the magnetic condition of the interior of a vast continent!&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
