<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="94" facs="#f0001" />
<cb/>
<cb/>
<div n="1"><head>THE ISTHMUS OF DARIEN.</head><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
    <p>(From the <hi rendition="#i">Times</hi>.)<lb/>Mr. Lionel Gisborne, who with Sir Charles Fox, and Messrs.<lb/>Henderson and Brassey projected a scheme for cutting a Ship<lb/>Canal through the Isthmus of Darien, has published the following<lb/>translation of a letter received from Baron Von Humboldt on that<lb/>important subject. We have already directed public attention to<lb/>the project of uniting the two great oceans of the Western hemis-<lb/>phere by means of a canal free from all obstructions; and we feel<lb/>certain, that at no distant period the commerce on the Western<lb/>coast of America, and the necessity for a more speedy passage to<lb/>Australia, will render such a means of communication imperative.</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Letter from Baron Alexander von Humboldt to Lionel<lb/>Gisborne, Esq.,</hi> M.A., C.E.<lb/>(Translated from the French original.)</hi></p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Sir,&#x2014;I trust you will excuse the oldest among the travellers, in both<lb/>the tropics of America and the steppes of Siberia, for having so long<lb/>delayed to thank you for the information I derived from your interesting<lb/>journal, &amp;c., on the junction of the Atlantic with the Pacific. The<lb/>position I occupy in this country, and the ardent desire I feel to finish,<lb/>before my death, some scientific works which I had the imprudence to<lb/>begin, considerably interrupt the even course of my correspondence. I<lb/>therefore hope that I shall meet, on your part also, with that indulgence<lb/>which your countrymen have shown me during so long a period.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;I have not been beyond the Rio Rimo, which lies east of the mouth<lb/>of the Atrato, since the <choice><sic>sime</sic><corr type="editorial">time</corr></choice> when I left the island of Cuba on my way<lb/>to Lima by Bogota, Quito, and the river Amazon, for the purpose of<lb/>observing the passage of Mercury through the solar disc. I was then<lb/>on friendly terms with a very intelligent merchant, Don Ignacio Iombo,<lb/>of Cartagena, in America, and I recollect that the <hi rendition="#i">Casso</hi> (Treasury<lb/>convoy) of Guayaquil was then on its way to Europe, by the road from<lb/>Cupicà to the Atrato, which was first opened by the Biscayan pilot<lb/>Poguerache. Knowing, geologically, the interruption of the mountain<lb/>chains, and the depression of the range in the eastern part of the<lb/><pb n="95" facs="#f0002" />
<cb/>
        Isthmus, my attention has remained fixed during this last half century<lb/>on the Bay of San Miguel and the route from Cupicà to the Rio Napipi.<lb/>Owing to my friendly relations with General Bolivar, I obtained through<lb/>him the first line of levels across the Isthmus of Panama. Ever since<lb/>the subject has not ceased to occupy my mind, as the various works and<lb/>maps which I published since 1810 and my correspondence with various<lb/>statesmen will testify. But all my striving and urging only led to im-<lb/>perfect trials and projects calculated for a line to the west of the meri-<lb/>dian of Panama and Portobello, none of which ever gained my confidence.<lb/>I had, however, the gratification of seeing my views honoured by an<lb/>eminent member of Her Britannic Majesty&#x2019;s navy, Captain Fitzroy.<lb/>(<hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Royal Geographical Society,</hi> vol. xx., p. 20.)</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;The increase of human knowledge, and the immense progress of<lb/>science, arts, and industry among the western nations, have given<lb/>us powers which only call for application. Everything depends<lb/>upon energy and perseverance. I therefore congratulate you, Sir, and<lb/>your courageous friend, Dr. Cullen, as well as Sir Charles Fox, Mr.<lb/>Henderson, and Mr. Brassey, for having given your names to so noble<lb/>an undertaking. I have always considered, firstly, the opening of an<lb/>oceanic canal, without locks; and secondly, the cut at Huchuecoca, in<lb/>the valley of Mexico (which is on a comparatively smaller scale, as may<lb/>be seen by the map and section I published), as two events calculated<lb/>highly to improve the relations between the different families of the<lb/>human species. In fact, such a work as the one you contemplate will<lb/>bring Eastern Asia nearer to the nations of Europe and America. It<lb/>will render the whole globe more easy to be travelled over&#x2014;this little<lb/>globe, of which Christopher Columbus, in one of his letters to the Queen<lb/>of Spain, said, &#x2018;<hi rendition="#i">el mundo es poco.</hi>&#x2019; It will facilitate the diffusion of pro-<lb/>ductions, especially of precious metals, of which the relative value (1 to<lb/>15 5-6ths) would change too suddenly without this &#x2018;permeability&#x2019; of the<lb/>world.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;As early as the discovery of the new continent, civilization had<lb/>spread, in a direction from north to south, over those portions of Ame-<lb/>rica which lie opposite to Asia, those on the European side being then<lb/>occupied by barbarous hunting tribes. The finest harbours, the most<lb/>precious products, are likewise found in the West. Even the currents<lb/>of the air, by their direction, contribute towards the preponderance of<lb/>West American power over the rich countries of Asia. The increasing<lb/>importance of the west coast of America promises to balance, at some<lb/>future time, the surprising progress of the Atlantic States, provided the<lb/>western States keep themselves free from that hideouse disease&#x2014;slavery<lb/>of coloured people.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Indeed, Sir, I feel the most ardent wishes for the happy success of<lb/>this oceanic canal. The attention which the public of the two continents<lb/>bestows already upon your undertaking will increase, as soon as you are<lb/>enabled, assisted by further explorations, and a survey extending over<lb/>all details, and carried on by a great number of experienced men, to<lb/>publish, on a large scale, maps and sections of the line fixed upon<lb/>between Puerto <choice><sic>Escoses</sic><corr type="editorial">Escoces</corr></choice> and the Gulf of San Miguel. The changes<lb/>which the success of your undertaking is sure to effect in the inter-<lb/>national commerce of the world will only disturb such people as in the<lb/>narrowness of their views oppose themselves to the natural and Provi-<lb/>dential course of events, and shed tears over the unfortunate discovery<lb/>of America. The Rio Huaxacualco with its portage to the Rio Chimalapa<lb/>(Tehuantepec), of which I published the first map after the itineraries<lb/>discovered by me in the archives of the vice-kingdom of Mexico, will<lb/>always be of great importance, owing to its position opposite Louisiana,<lb/>in the Gulf of Mexico which has all the appearance of soon becoming a<lb/><hi rendition="#i">mare clausum</hi>,&#x2014;a lake of the United States. The nature of the soil,<lb/>however, does not allow great works to be carried out in that locality;<lb/>besides, you know the difficulties impeding any canalization or rectifica-<lb/>tion of rivers of great length, and the great variations of the volume of<lb/>water, as in the river San Juan; but a railway would be a great advan-<lb/>tage to the southern States.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;The great interest which every one at the present time takes in the<lb/>canalization of the Isthmus recalls a similar fact to my memory, remind-<lb/>ing me of the sudden interest created by the discovery of guano.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;I was the first who brought guano to Europe, of which Klaproth<lb/>and Vauquelin published an analysis. During 40 years I preached, but<lb/>always in vain, the usefuluess of this substance, and in vain did I recom-<lb/>mend its employment in fertilizing the fields of Europe. But it is only<lb/>15 or 18 years since it has at last become a great article of commerce.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;I beg of you, my dear Sir, to present my kind remembrance to the<lb/>excellent and able Mr. Peterman, &amp;c.</p><lb/><closer><salute>&#x201C;ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT.</salute></closer><lb/>
</div>
    <div>
    <p>&#x201C;P.S. I am not surprised at the difference between the level you<lb/>found at Turbaco and
                    my own statement. To this, however, I had<lb/><cb/> prudently added,
                    &#x2018;doubtful barometrical observation.&#x2019; (See my <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Recueil<lb/>d&#x2019;Observations Astronomiques et de Mesures
                        <choice><sic>Baromètriques</sic><corr type="editorial">Barométriques</corr></choice>.</hi> vol. i.<lb/>p. 299.) The fact that the gas issuing from
                    the little volcanoes at<lb/>Turbaco is inflammable in its natural state has
                    already been communi-<lb/>cated by Colonel Acosta (<hi rendition="#i"
                        >Journal</hi>, p. 65). It appears that the gaseous<lb/>fluid which issues
                    from the &#x2018;salses&#x2019; is not the same at all times. I find<lb/>in my
                    journal, that in 1801, the flame of any burning substance was<lb/>suddenly
                    extinguished on being thrown into a bottle containing air<lb/>from those little
                    volcanoes.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Parrot, also, in the mud volcanoes in the island of Taman found<lb/>only azote, although the gas emitted would burn at other times. (See<lb/>my <hi rendition="#i">Rélation Historique</hi>, vol. xii. chap. 29, p. 367&#x2014;371.)</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
