<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="12" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head>INDIAN SANG-FROID.</head><lb/><p>The inhabitants of the banks of the Orinoco and its<lb/>tributary streams have marked the manners
                    of the croco-<lb/>dile, as the torero has studied the manners of the
                    bull.<lb/>When they are assailed they put in practice, with that<lb/>presence of
                    mind and that resignation which characterise<lb/>the Indians, the Zamboes, and
                    copper-coloured men in<lb/>general, the counsels which they have heard in
                    infancy.<lb/>In countries where nature is so powerful and so terrible,<lb/>man
                    is constantly prepared for danger. A young Indian<lb/>girl, who delivered
                    herself from the jaws of the crocodile<lb/>said: &#x201C;I knew he would let me
                    go, if I thrust my fingers<lb/>into his eyes.&#x201D; The girl belonged to the
                    indigent class of<lb/>the people, in whom the habits of physical want
                    augment<lb/>energy of character: but how can we avoid being surprised<lb/>to
                    observe, in the countries convulsed by terrible earth-<lb/>quakes, on the table
                    land of the province of Quito, women<lb/>belonging to the highest classes of
                    society display, in the<lb/>moment of peril, the same calm, the same reflecting
                    in-<lb/>trepidity? I shall mention one example only, in support<lb/>of this
                    assertion. On the 4th of February, 1797, when<lb/>35,000 Indians perished in the
                    space of a few minutes, a<lb/>young mother saved herself and children, crying
                    out to<lb/>them to extend their arms, at the moment when the<lb/>cracked ground
                    was ready to swallow them up. When<lb/>this courageous woman heard the
                    astonishment that was<lb/>expressed at a presence of mind so extraordinary,
                    she<lb/>answered, with great simplicity: &#x201C;I had been told in
                    my<lb/>infancy, if the earthquake surprise you in the house, place<lb/>yourself
                    under a doorway that communicates from one<lb/>apartment to another; if you be
                    in the open air, and feel<lb/>the ground opening beneath you, extend both your
                    arms,<lb/>and try to support yourself on the edge of the
                    crevice.&#x201D;<lb/>Thus, in savage regions, or in countries exposed to
                    frequent<lb/>convulsions, man is prepared to struggle with the beasts of<lb/>the
                    forest, to deliver himself from the jaws of the crocodile,<lb/>and to escape
                    from the conflict of the elements.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i"
                        >Humboldt&#x2019;s<lb/>Travels.</hi></p>
</div>
</body>
    <back/>
</text>
</TEI>
