<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="2" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">A Cheaper Light than Gas.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;On the road leading<lb/>to the port, we were forcibly struck by a spectacle which<lb/>our
                    stay of two years in the hottest part of the tropics<lb/>might have rendered
                    familiar to us, but, previously, I<lb/>had nowhere seen such innumerable
                    quantity of phos-<lb/><cb/>phorescent insects. The grass that overspreads
                    the<lb/>ground, the branches, and foliage of the trees, all shone<lb/>with that
                    reddish and moveable light, which varies in its<lb/>intensity at the will of the
                    animal by which it is produced.<lb/>It seemed as though the starry firmament
                    reposed on the<lb/>savannah. In the hut of the poorest inhabitant of
                    the<lb/>country, fifteen cocuyos, placed in a calabash pierced<lb/>with holes,
                    afforded sufficient light to search for anything<lb/>during the night. To shake
                    the calabash forcibly is all<lb/>that is necessary to excite the animal to
                    increase the<lb/>intensity of the luminous discs situated on each side
                    of<lb/>its body. The people of the country remark, with a<lb/>simple truth of
                    expression, that calabashes filled with<lb/>cocuyos are lanterns always ready
                    lighted. They are, in<lb/>fact, only extinguished by the sickness or death of
                    the<lb/>insects, which are easily fed with a little sugar cane. A<lb/>young
                    woman at Trinidad de Cuba told us, that during a<lb/>long and difficult passage
                    from the main land, she always<lb/>made use of the phosphorescence of the
                    cocuyos when<lb/>she gave suck to her child at night; the captain of
                    the<lb/>ship would allow no other light on board, from the fear<lb/>of
                        corsairs.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s Travels, Vol. III.:
                        Bohn&#x2019;s<lb/>Scientific Library.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
