<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">Baron Humboldt on the Darien Canal Project.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;Hum-<lb/>boldt, the celebrated traveller, has sent the following<lb/>letter to Dr. Cullen
                    of London, on the project of the<lb/>Isthmus of Darien Ship
                    Canal:&#x2014;&#x201C; Dr. Cullen cannot<lb/>doubt the high importance that I
                    would attach to the<lb/>merit of his courageous and useful investigations in
                    the<lb/>eastern part of the Isthmus of Panama; knowing my<lb/>position and my
                    antediluvian age, he will receive with<lb/>indulgence, even so late, the
                    expression of my lively<lb/>gratitude. After having laboured in vain, during
                    half a<lb/>century, to prove the possibility of an oceanic canal, and<lb/>to
                    point out the Gulf of San Miguel and Cupica as the<lb/>points most worthy of
                    attention; after having regretted,<lb/>almost with bitterness, in the last
                    edition of my Aspects<lb/>of Nature, that the employment of the means,
                    which<lb/>the present state of our knowledge affords for obtain-<lb/>ing precise
                    measurements has been so long delayed;<lb/>I ought, more than any one else, to
                    be satisfied to<lb/>see, at last, my hopes for so noble an enterprise
                    re-<lb/>vived. By your publications, Sir, and by that of Mr.<lb/>Gisborne, will
                    be originated the great work of chang-<lb/>ing an important part of the commerce
                    of nations, and<lb/>of rendering more accessible the rich countries
                    of<lb/>Eastern Asia and the Indian Archipelago. The under-<lb/>taking is by no
                    means above the intellectual and ma-<lb/>terial power which civilised nations
                    have attained to.<lb/>The work should be one to last for ever; it should<lb/>not
                    commence with a canal with locks, like the magni-<lb/>ficent Caledonian Canal;
                    it must be a really oceanic canal,<lb/>without locks; a free passage from sea to
                    sea, across<lb/>which the speed of the navigation will be modified, but
                    not<lb/>interrupted by the difference in height and non-coinci-<lb/>dence of the
                    tides.&#x201D;</p>
</div>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
