<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-06" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">THE ISTHMUS OF DARIEN.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                </head>
                <p>The following interesting letter from Baron Alexander<lb break="yes"/>Von Humboldt to Lionel Gisborne, Esq., M.A., C.E., has<lb break="yes"/>been made public:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <opener>
                        <salute>&#x201C;Sir,</salute>
                    </opener>
                    <p>&#x2014;I trust you will excuse the oldest among the<lb break="yes" />travellers in both the tropics of America and the steppes of<lb break="yes"/>Siberia, for having so long delayed to thank you for the in-<lb break="no"/>formation I derived from your interesting journal, &#x0026;c., on<lb break="yes"/>the junction of the Atlantic with the Pacific. The position<lb break="yes"/>I occupy in this country, and the ardent desire I feel to<lb break="yes"/>finish, before my death, some scientific works which I had<lb break="yes"/>the imprudence to begin, considerably interrupt the even<lb break="yes"/>course of my correspondence. I therefore hope that I shall<lb break="yes"/>meet, on your part also, with that indulgence which your<lb break="yes"/>countrymen have shown me during so long a period.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;I have not been beyond the Rio Rimo, which lies east<lb break="yes" />of the mouth of the Atrato, since the time when I left the<lb break="yes" />island of Cuba on my way to Lima by Bogota, Quito, and<lb break="yes"/>the River Amazon, for the purpose of observing the passage<lb break="yes"/>of Mercury through the solar disc. I was then on friendly<lb break="yes"/>terms with a very intelligent merchant, Don Ignacio<lb break="yes"/>Iombo, of Carthagena, in America, and I recollect that the<lb break="yes"/>Casso (Treasury convoy) of Guayaquil was then on its<lb break="yes"/>way to Europe, by the road from Cupica to the Atrato,<lb break="yes"/>which was first opened by the Biscayan pilot Poguerache.<lb break="yes"/>Knowing, geologically, the interruption of the mountain<lb break="yes"/>chains, and the depression of the range in the eastern part<lb break="yes"/>of the Isthmus, my attention has remained fixed during<lb break="yes"/>this last half century on the Bay of San Miguel and the<lb break="yes"/>route from Cupica to the Rio Napipi. Owing to my friendly<lb break="yes"/>relations with General Bolivar, I obtained through him<lb break="yes"/>the first line of levels across the Isthmus of Panama.<lb break="yes"/>Ever since the subject has not ceased to occupy my mind,<lb break="yes"/>as the various works and maps which I published since<lb break="yes"/>1810, and my correspondence with various statesmen, will<lb break="yes"/>testify. But all my striving and urging only led to im-<lb break="no"/>perfect trials and projects calculated for a line to the west<lb break="yes"/>of the meridian of Panama and Portobello, none of which<lb break="yes"/>ever gained my confidence. I had, however, the gratifica-<lb break="no"/>tion of seeing my views honoured by an eminent member<lb break="yes"/>of her Britannic Majesty&#x2019;s navy, Captain Fitzroy (Jour-<lb break="no"/>nal of the Royal Geographical Society, Vol. XX., p. 20.)</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The increase of human knowledge, and the immense<lb break="yes" />progress of science, arts, and industry among the western<lb break="yes" />nations, have given us powers which only call for<lb break="yes" />application. Everything depends upon energy and per-<lb break="no" />severance. I therefore congratulate you, sir, and your<lb break="yes" />courageous friend, Dr. Cullen, as well as Sir Charles<lb break="yes"/>Fox, Mr. Henderson, and Mr. Brassey, for having<lb break="yes"/>given your names to so noble an undertaking. I have<lb break="yes"/>
                        <cb/> always considered, firstly, the opening of the oceanic<lb break="yes" />canal, without locks; and, secondly, the cut at Huchuecoca,<lb break="yes" />in the valley of Mexico (which is on a comparatively<lb break="yes" />smaller scale, as may be seen by the map and section I<lb break="yes" />published,) as two events calculated highly to improve the<lb break="yes" />relations between the different families of the human<lb break="yes" />species. In fact, such a work as the one you contemplate<lb break="yes" />will bring Eastern Asia nearer to the nations of Europe and<lb break="yes" />America. It will render the whole globe more easy to be<lb break="yes" />travelled over&#x2014;this little globe, of which Christopher<lb break="yes"/>Columbus, in one of his letters to the Queen of Spain, said,<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;<hi rendition="#i">el mundo es poco.</hi>&#x2019; It will facilitate the diffusion of pro-<lb break="yes" />ductions, especially of precious metals, of which the rela-<lb break="yes" />tive value (1 to 15 5-6ths) would change too suddenly with<lb break="yes" />out this &#x2018;permeability&#x2019; of the world.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;As early as the discovery of the new continent, civili-<lb break="no" />sation had spread, in a direction from north to south, over<lb break="yes" />those portions of America which lie opposite to Asia, those<lb break="yes" />on the European side being then occupied by barbarous<lb break="yes" />hunting tribes. The finest harbours, the most precious pro-<lb break="no" />ducts, are likewise found in the west. Even the currents of<lb break="yes" />the air, by their direction, contributo towards the pre-<lb break="no" />ponderance of West American power over the rich countries<lb break="yes" />of Asia. The increasing importance of the west coast of<lb break="yes" />America promises to balance, at some future time, the sur-<lb break="no" />prising progress of the Atlantic States, provided the West-<lb break="no" />ern States keep themselves free from that hideous disease&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>slavery of coloured people.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Indeed, sir, I feel the most ardent wishes for the happy<lb break="yes"/>suceess of this oceanic canal. The attention which the<lb break="yes"/>public of the two continents bestows already upon your<lb break="yes"/>undertaking will increase, as soon as you are enabled,<lb break="yes"/>assisted by further explorations, and a survey extending<lb break="yes"/>over all details, and carried on by a great number of ex-<lb break="no"/>perienced men, to publish, on a large scale, maps and<lb break="yes"/>sections of the line fixed upon between Puerto Escoces<lb break="yes"/>and the Gulf of San Miguel. The changes which the<lb break="yes"/>success of your undertaking is sure to effect in the inter-<lb break="no"/>national commerce of the world will only disturb such<lb break="yes"/>people as in the narrowness of their views oppose them-<lb break="no"/>selves to the natural and providential course of events<lb break="yes"/>and shed tears over the unfortunate discovery of<lb break="yes"/>America. The Rio Huaxacualco with its portage to<lb break="yes"/>the Rio Chimalapa (Tehuantepec), of which I published<lb break="yes"/>the first map after the itineraries discovered by me<lb break="yes"/>in the archives of the vice-kingdom of Mexico, will<lb break="yes"/>always be of great importance, owing to its position<lb break="yes"/>opposite Louisiana, in the Gulf of Mexico, which has<lb break="yes"/>all the appearance of soon becoming a <hi rendition="#i" >mare clausum</hi>&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>a lake of the United States. The nature of the soil,<lb break="yes"/>however, does not allow great works to be carried out in<lb break="yes"/>that locality; besides, you know the difficulties impeding<lb break="yes"/>any canalisation or rectification of rivers of great length<lb break="yes"/>and the great variations of the volume of water, as in the<lb break="yes"/>river San Juan; but a railway would be a great advan-<lb break="yes"/>tage to the southern states.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The great interest which every one at the present<lb break="yes"/>time takes in the canalisation of the Isthmus recalls a<lb break="yes"/>similar fact to my memory, reminding me of the sudden<lb break="yes"/>interest created by the discovery of guano.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;I was the first who brought guano to Europe, of which<lb break="yes" />Klaproth and Vanquelin published an analysis. During<lb break="yes"/>40 years I preached, but always in vain, the usefulness of<lb break="yes"/>this substance, and in vain did I recommend its employ-<lb break="yes"/>ment in fertilising the fields of Europe. But it is only<lb break="yes"/>15 or 18 years since it has at last become a great article<lb break="yes"/>of commerce.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <closer>
                        <salute>&#x201C;I beg of you, my dear sir, to present my kind remem-<lb break="no"/>brances to the excellent and able Mr. Peterman, &#x0026;c.<lb break="yes"/>
                            <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von Humboldt.</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </salute>
                    </closer>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>&#x201C;P.S. I am not surprised at the difference between the<lb break="yes"/>level you found at Turbaco and my own statement. To<lb break="yes"/>this, however, I had prudently added, &#x2018;doubtful baro-<lb break="yes"/>metrical observation.&#x2019; (See my <hi rendition="#i">Recueil d&#x2019;Observations<lb break="yes" />Astronomiques et de Mesures Barometriques,</hi> vol. i. p. 299.)<lb break="yes"/>The fact that the gas issuing from the little volcanoes at<lb break="yes"/>Turbaco is inflammable in its natural state has already been<lb break="yes"/>communicated by Colonel Acosta (Journal, p. 65). It<lb break="yes"/>appears that the gascous fluid which issues from the &#x2018;salses&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>is not the same at all times. I find in my journal that, in<lb break="yes"/>1801, the flame of any burning substance was suddenly ex-<lb break="yes"/>tinguished on being thrown into a bottle containing air from<lb break="yes"/>those little volcanoes.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>&#x201C;Parrot, also, in the mud volcanoes in the island of<lb break="yes" />Taman, found only azote, although the gas emitted won&#x2019;t<lb break="yes" />burn at other times. (See my <hi rendition="#i">Relation Historique,</hi> vol. xii<lb break="yes"/>chap. 29, p. 367&#x2014;371).&#x201D;</p>
                    </postscript>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 