<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head>THE ISTHMUS OF DARIEN SHIP CANAL.<lb/><hi rendition="#k">to the editor of the express.</hi></head><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#et">Potsdam, 4th June, 1853.</hi></dateline><lb/><p>Sir&#x2014;I am very much to blame for having so long delayed<lb/>an answer to the agreeable and
                    interesting despatch that you<lb/>have been kind enough to forward me, by the
                    hands of Mr.<lb/>Augustus Peterman, so estimable by his character, as
                    well<lb/>as by the solidity of his geographical labours. Dr. Cullen<lb/>cannot
                    doubt the high importance that I would attach to<lb/>the merit of his courageous
                    and useful investigations in the<lb/>eastern part of the Isthmus of Panama;
                    knowing my posi-<lb/>tion and my antediluvian age, he will receive with
                    indul-<lb/>gence, even so late, the expression of my lively gratitude.<lb/>After
                    having laboured in vain, during half a century, to<lb/>prove the possibility of
                    an oceanic canal, and to<lb/>point out the Gulf of San Miguel and Cupica<lb/>as
                    the points most worthy of attention; after having<lb/>regretted, almost with
                    bitterness, in the last edition of my<lb/>&#x201C;Aspects of Nature,&#x201D;
                    that the employment of the means,<lb/>which the present state of our knowledge
                    affords for ob-<lb/>taining precise measurements has been so long delayed;
                    I<lb/>ought, more than any one else, to be satisfied to see, at last,<lb/>my
                    hopes for so noble an enterprise revived. By your pub-<lb/>lications, sir, and
                    by that of Mr. Gisborne, will be <choice>
                        <sic>origi.<lb/>nated</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">origi-<lb/>nated</corr>
                    </choice> the great work of changing an important part of the<lb/>commerce of
                    nations, and of rendering more accessible the<lb/>rich countries of Eastern Asia
                    and the Indian Archipelago.<lb/>The undertaking is by no means above the
                    intellectual and<lb/>material power which civilised nations have attained
                    to.<lb/>The work should be one to last for ever; it should not com-<lb/>mence
                    with a canal with locks, like the magnificent Cale-<lb/>donian Canal; it must be
                    a really oceanic canal, without<lb/>locks; a free passage from sea to sea,
                    across which the<lb/>speed of the navigation will be modified, but not
                    inter-<lb/>rupted by the difference in height and non-coincidence of<lb/>the
        tides.&#x2014;</p><closer><salute>Receive, I pray you, sir, the expression of my<lb/>highest consideration. Yours, &#x0026;c., &#x0026;c.<lb/><hi rendition="#et">(Signed) <hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute></closer><lb/>
    </div>
    <div>
        <p>Dr. Edward Cullen, Strand, London<choice><sic>,</sic><corr type="editorial">.</corr></choice></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
