<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-05-27" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="320" facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>When we were about leaving Berlin, I addressed a note to<lb break="yes"/>the Baron, expressing our great satisfaction in the interview,<lb break="yes"/>bidding him farewell, and asking for his autograph. He readily<lb break="yes"/>replied, but instead of his signature merely, he sent an interest-<lb break="no"/>ing original letter, written on the occasion, from which, I trust,<lb break="yes"/>it is not improper to make an extract of sentiments relating to<lb break="yes"/>the American continents.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>After some very kind expressions of personal regard, he<lb break="yes"/>alludes to his usual residence at Potsdam, where are both the<lb break="yes"/>rural palace of the king, and the tombs of some preceding<lb break="yes"/>monarchs: &#x201C;Compelled to return in the morning to the coun-<lb break="no"/>try, where are the tombs which I shall soon occupy, I have re-<lb break="no"/>served to myself the perusal of&#x201D;&#x2014;certain scientific American<lb break="yes"/>papers which had been presented to him. He then adds: &#x201C;I<lb break="yes"/>have moral reasons to fear the immeasurable aggrandizement of<lb break="yes"/>your confederacy&#x2014;the temptations to the abuse of power, dan-<lb break="no"/>gerous to the Union, (and have occasion also to fear) the<lb break="yes"/>distinct individual character of the other populations<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">In a marginal note, he adds: &#x201C;And the possible formation of a<lb break="yes" />powerful empire, independent of sugar, slaves, and cotton, and the<lb break="yes"/>temporizing legislation&#x2014;la douce legislation&#x2014;which accompanies this<lb break="yes"/>species of culture.</note> (descrip-<lb break="no"/>tions of population<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">The words in parenthesis are not in the original letter written<lb break="yes"/>in French, but are added to elucidate his meaning.</note>) of America. I am not less impressed by<lb break="yes"/>the great advantages which the physical knowledge of the<lb break="yes"/>world, and positive science and intelligence, ought to derive<lb break="yes"/>from this very aggrandizement&#x2014;from that intelligence which,<lb break="yes"/>by peaceable conquests, facilitates the movement of know-<lb break="no"/>ledge, and superimposes, not without violence, new classes of<lb break="yes"/>population upon the indigenous races which are in a course<lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="321" facs="#f0002"/> of rapid extinction. However imposing this spectacle may<lb break="yes"/>be, which is being realized under our eyes, and is prepar-<lb break="no"/>ing another still more remarkable for the history of the in-<lb break="no"/>tellectual development of our races; I already descry the dis-<lb break="no"/>tinct epoch, when a high degree of civilization, and institu-<lb break="no"/>tions free, firm and peaceful (three elements which are not<lb break="yes"/>easily associated), shall penetrate into the tropical regions<lb break="yes"/>where the high table lands of Mexico, Bogota, Quito, and<lb break="yes"/>Potosi shall come to resemble (in their institutions) New-York,<lb break="yes"/>Boston, and Philadelphia.&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>The letter concludes with warm personal good wishes, and<lb break="yes"/>a kind message to Professor Agassiz, &#x201C;equally distinguished by<lb break="yes"/>his vast and solid acquisitions in science and the great amenity<lb break="yes"/>of his character.&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>The signature is without a title: &#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Alexandre Humboldt,</hi>
                <lb break="yes"/>à Berlin, 5 Juillet (it should have been Aout), 1851.&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>It is proper to add, that at the time of our visit Baron Von<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt was engaged in the preparation of a new production<lb break="yes"/>on the Outline Form of Mountain Peaks, in which he was work-<lb break="no"/>ing up original observations and drawings made during the<lb break="yes"/>course of his various wanderings. He assured us that the<lb break="yes"/>greater part of his literary labor was of necessity performed<lb break="yes"/>when others slept, as the hours of usual labor were with him<lb break="yes"/>consumed by the demands of the king. He added, that he<lb break="yes"/>early made the discovery that he could get on very well with<lb break="yes"/>four hours of sleep. This, as has been often remarked, ac-<lb break="no"/>counts for his prodigious performances in literary labor.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>Such are the modest and unassuming language and appear-<lb break="no"/>ance of one who has, in person, explored a larger portion of<lb break="yes"/>our globe than any other living traveller; of a philosopher who<lb break="yes"/>has illustrated and enlarged almost every department of human<lb break="yes"/>knowledge; general physics and chemistry, geology, natural<lb break="yes"/>history, philology, civil antiquities, and ethnography, have all<lb break="yes"/>been illustrated by him.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 