<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-11-30" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <p><hi rendition="#k">The Extinct American Race.</hi>&#x2014;As, properly speak-<lb/>
                    ing, only civilised nations have a history, the history of<lb/>
                    the Americans is necessarily no more than that of a small<lb/>
                    portion of the inhabitants of the mountains. Profound<lb/>
                    obscurity envelops the vast country which stretches from<lb/>
                    the eastern slope of the Cordilleras towards the Atlantic;<lb/>
                    and for this very reason, whatever in that country relates<lb/>
                    to the preponderance of one nation over others, to dis-<lb/>
                    tant migrations, to the physiognomical features which<lb/>
                    denote a foreign race, excite our deepest interest. Amidst<lb/>
                    the plains of North America, some powerful nation, which<lb/>
                    has disappeared, constructed circular, square, and octa-<lb/>
                    gonal fortifications; walls six thousand toises in length;<lb/>
                    tumuli from seven to eight hundred feet in diameter, and<lb/>
                    an hundred and forty feet in height, sometimes round,<lb/>
                    sometimes with several storeys, and containing thousands<lb/>
                    of skeletons. These skeletons are the remains of men<lb/>
                    less slender, and more squat, than the present inhabitants<lb/>
                    of those countries. Other bones, wrapped in fabrics, re-<lb/>
                    sembling those of the Sandwich and Feejee Islands, are<lb/>
                    found in the natural grottoes of Kentucky. What is be-<lb/>
                    come of those nations of Louisiana anterior to the Lenni-<lb/>
                    Lenapes, the Shawanese, and perhaps even to the Sioux<lb/>
                    (Nadowessess, Nahcotas) of the Missouri, who are<lb/>
                    strongly mongolised, and who, it is believed, according to<lb/>
                    their own traditions, came from the coast of Asia? In<lb/>
                    the plains of South America we find only a very few<lb/>
                    hillocks of that kind, called cerros hechos a mano; and<lb/>
                    nowhere any works of fortification analogous to those of<lb/>
                    the Ohio. However, on a vast space of ground, at the<lb/>
                    Lower Orinoco, as well as on the banks of the Cassiquiare,<lb/>
                    and between the sources of the Essequibo and the Rio<lb/>
                    Branco, there are rocks of granite covered with symbolic<lb/>
                    figures. These sculptures denote that the extinct gene-<lb/>
                    rations belonged to nations different from those which<lb/>
                    now inhabit the same regions. There seems to be no<lb/>
                    connection between the history of Mexico, and that of the<lb/>
                    Cundinamarca, and of Peru; but in the plains of the east<lb/>
                    a warlike and long dominant nation betrays in its features,<lb/>
                    and its physical constitution, traces of a foreign origin.<lb/>
                    The Caribs preserve traditions that seem to indicate<lb/>
                    ancient communications between North and South Ame-<lb/>
                    rica. Such a phenomenon deserves particular attention.<lb/>
                    If it be true that savages are for the most part degenerate<lb/>
                    races, remnants escaped from a common wreck, as their<lb/>
                    languages, their cosmogonic fables, and numerous other<lb/>
                    indications seem to prove, it becomes doubly important<lb/>
                    to examine the course by which these remnants have been<lb/>
                    driven from one hemisphere to the other.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s<lb/>
                        Travels, Vol. III.: Bohn&#x2019;s Scientific Library.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 