<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="171" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Death of Leopold De Buch.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;The following is a<lb/>translation of an affecting letter from the veteran
                    Baron<lb/>Alex. Humboldt to Sir Roderick Murchison; the original<lb/>of which
                    has been kindly communicated by Sir Roderick to<lb/>us. It conveys intelligence
                    which will be heard with great<lb/>regret in the scientific world of
    England:&#x2014;</p><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Berlin. March 4, 1853.</hi></dateline><lb/>
    </div>
    <div>
        <p>&#x201C;That I should be destined&#x2014;I, an old man of eighty-<lb break="maybe"
                    />three&#x2014;to announce to you, dear Sir Roderick, the saddest<lb/>news that
                    I could have to convey&#x2014;to you for whom M. De<lb/>Buch professed a
                    friendship so tender&#x2014;and to the many<lb/>admirers of his genius, his vast
                    labours, and his noble cha-<lb/>racter! Leopold De Buch was taken from us this
                    morning<lb/>by typhoid fever&#x2014;so violent in its attack, that two
                    days<lb/>only of danger warned us. He was at my house so lately<lb/>as the 26th
                    ult., despite the snow and the distance between<lb/>us&#x2014;talking geology
                    with the most lively interest. That<lb/>evening he went into society; and on
                    Sunday and Monday<lb/>(the 27th and 28th) he complained of a feverish
                    attack,<lb/>which he believed to be caused by a large chilblain swell-<lb/>ing,
                    from which he had suffered for years. The inflamma-<lb/>tion required the
                    application of leeches&#x2014;but the pain and<lb/>the fever increased. He was
                    speechless for thirty-eight<lb/>hours. ... He died surrounded by his
                    friends&#x2014;most<lb/>of whom knew nothing of his danger till Wednesday
                    even-<lb/>ing, the 2nd of March. He and I were united by a friend-<lb/>ship of
                    sixty-three years&#x2014;a friendship which never knew<lb/>interruption. I found
                    him, in 1791, in Werner&#x2019;s house in<lb/>Freiburg, when I entered the
                    School of Mines. We were<lb/>together in Italy, in Switzerland, in
                    France&#x2014;four months<lb/>in Saltzburg. M. De Buch was not only one of the
                    great<lb/>illustrations of his age&#x2014;he was a man of noble soul.
                    His<lb/>mind left a track of light wherever it passed. Always in<lb/>contact
                    with nature herself&#x2014;he could boast of having ex-<lb/>tended the limits of
                    geological science. I grieve for him<lb/>profoundly&#x2014;without him I feel
                    desolate. I consulted him<lb/>as a master: and his affection (like that of Gay
                    Lussac and<lb/>that of Arago, who were also his friends) sustained me in<lb/>my
                    labours. He was four years my junior&#x2014;and nothing<lb/>forewarned me of
                    this misfortune. It is not at the distance<lb/>of a few hours only from such a
                    loss that I can say more<lb/>respecting it. Pity me, and accept the homage of my
                    pro-<lb/>found respect and affectionate devotion.</p><lb/><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Al. Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute></closer><lb/>
    </div>
    <div>
        <p>&#x201C;And my poor countryman Overweg, in Africa! What<lb/>a blessing to learn one day by means
                    of the Astronomer<lb/>Vogel the magnetic condition of the interior of a vast
    con-<lb/>tinent!&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">The Athen&#x00E6;um.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
