<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>

<pb n="350" facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#b">Remarkable Indian Sang-Froid.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;The inhabitants of the banks of<lb/>the Orinoco and its tributary streams discourse continually on the<lb/>dangers to which they are exposed. They have marked the manners<lb/>of the crocodile, as the torero has studied the manners of the bull. When<lb/>they are assailed they put in practice with that presence of mind and<lb/>that resignation which characterize the Indians, the Zamboes, and copper-<lb break="maybe"/>colored men in general, the counsels they have heard from their infancy.<lb/>In countries where nature is so powerful and so terrible, man is constant-<lb/>ly prepared for danger. We have mentioned before the answer of the<lb/>young Indian girl, who delivered herself from the jaws of the crocodile:&#x2014;<lb/>&#x201C;I knew he would let me go, if I thrust my fingers into his eyes.&#x201D; This<lb/>girl belonged to the indigent class of the people, in whom the habits of<lb/>physical want augment energy of character; but how can we avoid<lb/>being surprised to observe, in the countries convulsed by terrible<lb/>earthquakes, on the table-land of the province of Quito, women belong-<lb/>ing to the highest classes of society display, in the moment of peril, the<lb/>same calm, the same reflecting intrepidity? I shall mention one exam-<lb/>ple only, in support of this assertion. On the 4th of February, 1797,<lb/>when 35,000 Indians perished in the space of a few minutes, a young<lb/>mother saved herself and children, crying out to them to extend their<lb/>arms at the moment when the cracked ground was ready to swallow<lb/>them up. When this courageous woman heard the astonishment that<lb/>was expressed at a presence of mind so extraordinary, she answered,<lb/>with great simplicity: &#x201C;I had been told in my infancy, if the earth-<lb/>quake surprise you in a house, place yourself under a doorway that<lb/>communicates from one apartment to another; if you be in the open<lb/>air, and feel the ground opening beneath you, extend both your arms,<lb/>and try to support yourself on the edge of the crevice.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>Thus, in savage regions, or in countries exposed to frequent convul-<lb/>sions, man is prepared
                    to struggle with the beasts of the forest, to<lb/>deliver himself from the jaws
                    of the crocodile, and to escape from the<lb/>conflict of the elements.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
