<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="6" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">A Sensitive Murderer.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;It also frequently happens that<lb/>sentences of death, tardily pronounced by the
                    Audiencia of<lb/>Caraccas, cannot be executed for want of a hangman. In
                    these<lb/>cases the barbarous custom is observed of pardoning one<lb/>criminal
                    on condition of his hanging the others. Our guides<lb/>related to us that, a
                    short time before our arrival on the coast of<lb/>Cumana, a Zambo, known for the
                    great ferocity of his manners,<lb/>determined to screen himself from punishment
                    by turning<lb/>executioner. The preparation for the execution, however,
                    shook<lb/>his resolution; he felt a horror of himself, and, preferring
                    death<lb/>to the disgrace of thus saving his life, he called again for
                    his<lb/>irons, which had been struck off. He did not long remain in<lb/>prison,
                    and he underwent his sentence through the baseness of<lb/>one of his
                    accomplices. This awakening of a sentiment of<lb/>honour in the soul of a
                    murderer is a psychologic phenomenon<lb/>worthy of reflection. The man who had
                    so often shed the blood<lb/>of travellers in the plains recoiled at the idea of
                    becoming the<lb/>passive instrument of justice, in inflicting upon others a
                    punish-<lb/>ment which he felt that he himself deserved.&#x2014;<hi
                        rendition="#i">Humboldt&#x2019;s<lb/>Travels, Vol. III.: Bohn&#x2019;s
                        Scientific Library.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
