<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="xvii" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#b">INTRODUCTION.<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#k">by</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>BARON ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">In</hi> these few pages I fulfil, too confidently perhaps, and<lb break="yes"/>without duly considering the measure of my ability, a mourn-<lb break="no"/>ful duty. Invited by the kind regard of a family who are<lb break="yes"/>dear to me, to prefix a short introduction to the collected<lb break="yes"/>works of the illustrious man whose friendship, during nearly<lb break="yes"/>half a century, has contributed to the happiness of my life,<lb break="yes"/>some apology may seem to be required for having acceded<lb break="yes"/>to this request; I offer none, however, because I have felt<lb break="yes"/>that neither modesty, nor the claims of other literary occu-<lb break="no"/>pations, can have any place when asked to lay on this<lb break="yes"/>recently closed tomb the homage of my admiration and<lb break="yes"/>lively gratitude.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>M. Arago and I were fellow members of the Academy<lb break="yes"/>of Sciences of the French Institute; the intimate relations<lb break="yes"/>maintained between us throughout a long series of years,<lb break="yes"/>his pleasing and constant habit of conversing with me and<lb break="yes"/>writing to me concerning his labours and his scientific pro-<lb break="no"/>jects, afforded me the most favourable opportunities of ob-<lb break="no"/>serving, I will not say the development of the faculties of<lb break="yes"/>his powerful mind, but their progressive application to the<lb break="yes"/>great discoveries which we owe to him. Without intending<lb break="yes"/>to write either a Eulogium or a Biographical Notice, I pro-<lb break="no"/>pose, therefore, to avail myself of the acquaintance which I<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">a</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="xviii" facs="#f0002"/> thus possess with all the materials which have been brought<lb break="yes"/>together in the collection of M. Arago&#x2019;s works. I would<lb break="yes"/>recall the vast extent embraced by the labours of a single<lb break="yes"/>man in the different branches of human knowledge, and<lb break="yes"/>how, amidst this variety of objects, his mind tended ever<lb break="yes"/>towards the same leading aims, <hi rendition="#i" >i.e.</hi> generalisation of views,<lb break="yes"/>the connection of phenomena which had long appeared to<lb break="yes"/>stand alone, and a nearer approach to the less accessible<lb break="yes"/>regions of natural philosophy. The action of forces mani-<lb break="no"/>fested in light, heat, magnetism, and electricity, as well as<lb break="yes"/>in the combinations and decompositions of chemistry, belong<lb break="yes"/>to the series of mysterious effects on which the brilliant dis-<lb break="no"/>coveries of the 19th century have shed an unexpected illu-<lb break="no"/>mination. In the field of these glorious conquests, M.<lb break="yes"/>Arago has taken his place among the great physicists of<lb break="yes"/>our age. At once ardent in discovery and circumspect in<lb break="yes"/>regard to conclusions which might be beyond the legitimate<lb break="yes"/>reach of partial results, he especially delighted in indicating<lb break="yes"/>new paths by which the desired goal might be more and<lb break="yes"/>more nearly approached, and in recognising identity of<lb break="yes"/>cause in phenomena apparently most diverse. When we<lb break="yes"/>rise from the consideration of the method followed by M.<lb break="yes"/>Arago to that of the powerful faculties which he exercised,<lb break="yes"/>we cannot measure their extent without astonishment.<lb break="yes"/>While to scientific men he moved back the limiting bound-<lb break="no"/>aries of the study of Nature, he had, at the same time, a<lb break="yes"/>marvellous aptitude for the diffusion of knowledge already<lb break="yes"/>acquired. Thus no kind of influence was wanting to him,<lb break="yes"/>and the authority of his name equalled its popularity.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It was five years after my return from Mexico, during<lb break="yes"/>which interval I had had the inestimable advantage of work-<lb break="no"/>ing with M. Gay-Lussac, with whom I had travelled in<lb break="yes"/>Italy, Switzerland, and Germany, that I became acquainted<lb break="yes"/>with M. Arago on his arrival from Algiers in July, 1809.<lb break="yes"/>He had travelled along the coast of Africa in the month of<lb break="yes"/>August, 1808, after having been long a prisoner in a<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="xix" facs="#f0003"/> Spanish citadel at the conclusion of important trigonome-<lb break="no"/>trical operations for the connection of the Balearic Islands<lb break="yes"/>with the continent.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>My attention had long been drawn to M. Arago, not<lb break="yes"/>only from his having been distinguished by the choice<lb break="yes"/>which, on the strong representations of Laplace, the Bureau<lb break="yes"/>des Longitudes had made of him to proceed to Spain for<lb break="yes"/>the purpose of terminating, in conjunction with M. Biot,<lb break="yes"/>the French are of the meridian; but also, and more espe-<lb break="no"/>cially, by the opinion of the most illustrious of geometri-<lb break="no"/>cians, &#x2014; the author of the &#x201C;Mecanique Analytique,&#x201D; &#x2014; La-<lb break="no"/>grange, with whom I had then the honour of being on inti-<lb break="no"/>mate terms, and who, with the sagacity which characterised<lb break="yes"/>all his judgments, had recognised the great and early de-<lb break="no"/>veloped powers of the young philosopher. He had been<lb break="yes"/>struck in him from the first with that faculty of penetration<lb break="yes"/>which in complex problems discerns, and rapidly and clearly<lb break="yes"/>lays hold of, the decisive point, and had often spoken of<lb break="yes"/>him to me as a young man of extraordinary promise. This<lb break="yes"/>divination of Lagrange, who was generally so sparing of<lb break="yes"/>praise, has remained in my memory as a title of honour<lb break="yes"/>worthy of record.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When M. Arago&#x2019;s arrival on the coast of France was<lb break="yes"/>made known at Arcueil, where I was then living in the en-<lb break="no"/>joyment of the friendship of Berthollet and Laplace, I wrote<lb break="yes"/>to congratulate him before he quitted the Lazaretto at Mar-<lb break="no"/>seilles; and this was the first letter which he received in<lb break="yes"/>Europe after having been exposed to so many dangers and<lb break="yes"/>sufferings in preserving the fruits of his observations. I<lb break="yes"/>recall a fact of very little moment, &#x2014; but I do so because<lb break="yes"/>M. Arago, feeling the charm which friendship gives to life,<lb break="yes"/>preserved a long-continued and lively recollection of it, and<lb break="yes"/>dated from thence the origin of our subsequent intimacy.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In September, 1809, at the age of twenty-three, M.<lb break="yes"/>Arago was elected a member of the Academy of Sciences<lb break="yes"/>by 47 votes out of 52. He succeeded Lalande, whose rare<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">a 2</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="xx" facs="#f0004"/> merit, attacked with too much levity during his long scien-<lb break="no"/>tific career, has since his death been universally recognised.<lb break="yes"/>It was not alone M. Arago&#x2019;s arduous astronomical and geo-<lb break="no"/>desical labours which the Institute desired to recompense<lb break="yes"/>by his election: the attention of scientific men had also<lb break="yes"/>been drawn to several important optical and physical in-<lb break="no"/>vestigations. In concert with M. Biot, M. Arago had de-<lb break="no"/>termined the weight of atmospheric air relatively to that of<lb break="yes"/>mercury, and had measured the deflection undergone by a<lb break="yes"/>ray of light in the different gases. Thenceforward the<lb break="yes"/>prism and the repeating circle were capable of furnishing<lb break="yes"/>data respecting the proportions between the constituent<lb break="yes"/>parts of the atmosphere, and even of showing how little<lb break="yes"/>those proportions vary. Such is the admirable mutual con-<lb break="no"/>nection which links together different natural phenomena,<lb break="yes"/>that it has long been possible for the geometrician to prove<lb break="yes"/>to the chemist, solely by the measurement of an angle of re-<lb break="no"/>fraction, that atmospheric air contains less than twenty-seven<lb break="yes"/>or twenty-eight per cent. of oxygen.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The velocity of light had been to M. Arago the subject<lb break="yes"/>of a no less ingenious investigation in physical astronomy.<lb break="yes"/>By the application of a prism to the object-glass of a tele-<lb break="no"/>scope, he had proved not only that the same tables of re-<lb break="no"/>fraction may serve for the light which proceeds from the<lb break="yes"/>sun and that which comes from the fixed stars; but also a<lb break="yes"/>fact which was already sufficient to cast great doubts on the<lb break="yes"/>emission theory, viz. that the rays of light coming from the<lb break="yes"/>fixed stars towards which the earth is moving, and the rays<lb break="yes"/>of light coming from the fixed stars from which she is<lb break="yes"/>receding, are refracted by exactly the same quantity. In<lb break="yes"/>order to reconcile this fact (obtained from very delicate ob-<lb break="no"/>servations) with the Newtonian hypothesis, it would have<lb break="yes"/>been necessary to admit that luminous bodies emit rays of<lb break="yes"/>all velocities, and that it is only rays of a certain velocity<lb break="yes"/>which are visible, <hi rendition="#i">i.e.</hi> that they alone produce in the eye<lb break="yes"/>the sensation of light.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="xxi" facs="#f0005"/>
                <p>In considering the kind of researches to which M. Arago<lb break="yes"/>had addicted himself even before he quitted France, we may<lb break="yes"/>remark in the first instance an extreme predilection for every-<lb break="no"/>thing relating to refraction, <hi rendition="#i">i. e.,</hi> to the path of luminous rays,<lb break="yes"/>and the causes which alter their velocity. This predilection,<lb break="yes"/>as Arago himself has often told me, took its rise from<lb break="yes"/>the assiduous perusal of the works on Optics of Bouguer,<lb break="yes"/>Lambert, and Smith, which had very early fallen into his<lb break="yes"/>hands. Can I fail to remark how great an influence must<lb break="yes"/>have been exercised on M. Arago&#x2019;s mind, during the three<lb break="yes"/>years employed by him in geodesical operations, by the<lb break="yes"/>aspect of Nature, fertile in the plains, wild and often grand<lb break="yes"/>on the summits of the mountains; by the colour of the agi-<lb break="no"/>tated waters of the ocean; by the varying height of the<lb break="yes"/>clouds; by the mirage over the arid shores, and in the strata<lb break="yes"/>of the atmosphere in which the night signals appeared to<lb break="yes"/>be multiplied, and to be alternately elevated and depressed;<lb break="yes"/>and generally by the life passed in the open air, beneficial in<lb break="yes"/>so many respects; in enlarging his sphere of thought, and<lb break="yes"/>stimulating his imagination, and exciting his curiosity,<lb break="yes"/>amidst the continual perturbations occurring in the, never-<lb break="no"/>theless, so regular, succession of phenomena? A traveller<lb break="yes"/>whose life is devoted to science, if susceptible to the im-<lb break="no"/>pressions of grandeur in the scenes of Nature, brings back<lb break="yes"/>from distant and adventurous rambles not only a treasure<lb break="yes"/>of recollections, but what is still far more precious, &#x2014; a dis-<lb break="no"/>position to enlarge the horizon of his contemplations, and<lb break="yes"/>to consider a great number of objects at once, and in their<lb break="yes"/>mutual relations. M. Arago had a marked preference for<lb break="yes"/>all the phenomena of meteorological optics; he was espe-<lb break="no"/>cially fond of investigating the laws which regulate the<lb break="yes"/>perpetual variations of the colour of the sea, the intensity<lb break="yes"/>of reflected light on the surface of clouds, and the play of<lb break="yes"/>atmospheric refractions.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If I might here permit myself to enter into some details,<lb break="yes"/>I would recall how greatly the young astronomer had been<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">a 3</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="xxii" facs="#f0006"/> struck by the facility with which, when seated on a mountain<lb break="yes"/>cliff descending abruptly to the water, his eye could penetrate<lb break="yes"/>to the bottom of the sea and discern its rugged inequalities.<lb break="yes"/>This simple observation led him at a subsequent period into<lb break="yes"/>highly interesting discussions concerning the ratio of the light<lb break="yes"/>reflected at an acute angle from the surface of the water to<lb break="yes"/>that which comes from the bottom of the water; it also led<lb break="yes"/>him to the ingenious idea of suggesting, for the discovery of<lb break="yes"/>shoals or rocks under water, the use of a plate of tourmaline,<lb break="yes"/>cut parallel to the axis of double refraction, and placed before<lb break="yes"/>the pupil of the eye in such a position as to eliminate the rays<lb break="yes"/>reflected from the surface of the water under an angle of<lb break="yes"/>37°, and consequently, completely polarised. As said by<lb break="yes"/>himself in the instructions drawn up for the voyage of cir-<lb break="no"/>cumnavigation of the Bonite, this was an attempt to intro-<lb break="no"/>duce polarisation into the art of navigation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The number and variety of M. Arago&#x2019;s investigations,<lb break="yes" />directed equally to terrestrial and celestial physics, will<lb break="yes" />render an account of his life, when it shall be attempted, a<lb break="yes" />very difficult task. In all these we find the same penetra-<lb break="no" />ting spirit, the same ardour in scientific advance, and at the<lb break="yes" />same time the same temperate reserve in the formation of<lb break="yes" />conjectures. It has been said elsewhere, and justly, that M.<lb break="yes" />Arago had derived from his thorough study of mathematics,<lb break="yes"/>that strictness of method, and security of view, which he<lb break="yes"/>brought both to his own experimental researches and to the<lb break="yes"/>appreciation of those made by his contemporaries. The public<lb break="yes"/>believe that generally speaking they have a right to feel a<lb break="yes"/>little mistrustful as to the solidity of researches by the same<lb break="yes"/>author on a considerable variety of subjects; the pre-<lb break="no"/>sumptuous expression of &#x201C;universal knowledge,&#x201D; is highly<lb break="yes" />dangerous, besides being always misapplied. Bacon, Newton,<lb break="yes" />Leibnitz, and Cuvier, possessed very varied, but assuredly<lb break="yes"/>not universal, knowledge. By the extent and variety of his<lb break="yes" />knowledge, M. Arago takes a place by the side of the most<lb break="yes" />eminent men of whom science can boast.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="xxiii" facs="#f0007"/>
                <p>In order to place in a true light the merit of men who<lb break="yes"/>have left behind them a bright track to mark their passage<lb break="yes"/>amongst us, we should fix our attention first on the most<lb break="yes"/>salient points in what has been effected by them. The great<lb break="yes"/>discoveries of M. Arago belong to the years 1811, 1820,<lb break="yes"/>and 1821. They relate to optics, to phenomena in physical<lb break="yes"/>astronomy, to electricity in motion, and to the development<lb break="yes"/>of magnetism by rotation. To indicate them more specifi-<lb break="no"/>cally, they are, &#x2014; 1st, the discovery of <hi rendition="#i">coloured</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">chromatic<lb break="yes"/>polarisation;</hi> 2udly, the precise observation of the <hi rendition="#i">displace-<lb break="no"/>ment of the fringes,</hi> caused by the encounter of two luminous<lb break="yes"/>rays, one of which passes through a transparent plate, as<lb break="yes"/>glass, for example, &#x2014; a phenomenon which indicates a dimi-<lb break="no"/>nution of velocity, or a retardation while in progress, and is<lb break="yes"/>in direct opposition to the emission theory; 3rdly, the first<lb break="yes"/>observation of the property of attracting iron filings possessed<lb break="yes"/>by the wire which conducts electricity in Oersted&#x2019;s experi-<lb break="no"/>ment, otherwise called the reophore of the pile; the happy<lb break="yes"/>idea of causing the electric current to pass in a <hi rendition="#i">helix</hi> round a<lb break="yes"/>needle, and to <hi rendition="#i">magnetise</hi> it as well by the discharge of a<lb break="yes"/>Leyden jar as by a voltaic pile; and, 4thly, <hi rendition="#i">rotation<lb break="yes"/>magnetism.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The discovery of chromatic polarisation led M. Arago to<lb break="yes"/>invent the polariscope, a photometer, the cyanometer, and<lb break="yes"/>apparatus of various kinds used in studying different optical<lb break="yes"/>phenomena. It was by experiments on chromatic polarisation<lb break="yes"/>that previously to 1826 M. Arago showed by physical evidence<lb break="yes"/>that the light of the sun proceeds, not from an incandescent<lb break="yes"/>solid or liquid mass, but from a gaseous envelope. Having<lb break="yes"/>found the means of distinguishing direct from reflected light,<lb break="yes"/>it was possible to ascertain that in the light which proceeds<lb break="yes"/>from the tails of comets a portion is polarised, and that that<lb break="yes"/>light must therefore necessarily be supposed to be, in part at<lb break="yes"/>least, borrowed. Chromatic polarisation also furnished M.<lb break="yes"/>Arago with a means of recognising that the diffused light of<lb break="yes"/>the atmosphere is in part polarised by reflection, and that by<lb break="yes"/>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">a 4</fw>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="xxiv" facs="#f0008"/> successively examining the atmospheric strata at different<lb break="yes"/>heights and in different azimuths there is discovered a <hi rendition="#i">neutral<lb break="yes"/>point</hi> in regard to polarisation, situated in the sun&#x2019;s vertical<lb break="yes"/>plane, and about 30° above the point opposite to that luminary.<lb break="yes"/>This point, which is called neutral, because there is no sensible<lb break="yes" />polarisation at it, differs from the two other &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i" >neutral points</hi>&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>of Babinet and Brewster, which were discovered later.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In this fine series of optical investigations I have stil<lb break="yes"/>to speak of two subjects which have been in a very great<lb break="yes"/>degree elucidated by Arago and his constant friend Fresnel,<lb break="yes"/>himself a master and discoverer in several departments of<lb break="yes"/>optics; they are subjects whose importance cannot be denied,<lb break="yes"/>since they touch on the great phenomena of <hi rendition="#i">interference</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">diffraction.</hi> The first of these is the <hi rendition="#i">scintillation of stars,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>a phenomenon which the illustrious Thomas Young, to whom<lb break="yes"/>we owe the fundamental laws of the interferences of light,<lb break="yes"/>had thought inexplicable. The scintillation is always accom-<lb break="no"/>panied by a change of colour, and of the intensity of the<lb break="yes"/>light. The luminous rays from the stars, after having<lb break="yes"/>traversed an atmosphere in which there are always strata<lb break="yes"/>differing in temperature, density, and humidity, and, con-<lb break="no"/>sequently, in refracting power, re-unite to form an image,<lb break="yes"/>vibrate in accord or disaccord, and either reinforce or destroy<lb break="yes"/>each other by interference. I take pride in recalling that<lb break="yes"/>extracts from this fine theory of scintillation were published,<lb break="yes"/>for the first time, in 1814, in the fourth book of my<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Voyage aux Régions Equinoxiales du Nouveau Continent.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>The memoir itself, which is full of curious historical<lb break="yes"/>researches, is one of the principal ornaments of the collec-<lb break="no"/>tion of the works of my illustrious friend. Other extracts<lb break="yes"/>relating to the same subject, but taken from more recent<lb break="yes"/>manuscripts, belonging to the year 1847, have been inserted<lb break="yes"/>in the astronomical part of my work entitled &#x201C;Cosmos.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The <hi rendition="#i">Interference</hi> of light, respecting which, Grimaldi (of<lb break="yes"/>Bologna) had already obtained some vague glimpses about<lb break="yes"/>@e second half of the 17th century, has given occasion to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="xxv" facs="#f0009"/> the enunciation of a fundamental truth, which has already<lb break="yes"/>been often proclaimed, viz., &#x201C;That under certain conditions<lb break="yes"/>light added to light produces darkness.&#x201D; No doubt there<lb break="yes"/>is inscribed in these few words the victory of the undu-<lb break="no"/>latory over the emission theory; but this victory could not<lb break="yes"/>be regarded as assured and complete until supported by<lb break="yes"/>simple experiments which could not be rejected. As I have<lb break="yes"/>already said, M. Arago had discovered, in 1818, the re-<lb break="no"/>markable effect produced in the phenomena of interferences<lb break="yes"/>by a very thin plate, placed in the path of one of the<lb break="yes"/>two interfering rays. There then occurs a <hi rendition="#i">displacement of<lb break="yes"/>the fringes,</hi> and a retardation in the light, which moves<lb break="yes"/>more slowly through a denser substance. &#x201C;The property<lb break="yes"/>of two rays of light to destroy each other by interference<lb break="yes"/>being once established,&#x201D; says M. Arago, in alluding to other<lb break="yes" />experiments made by him conjointly with Fresnel, &#x201C;is it not<lb break="yes"/>yet far more extraordinary that we should be able at plea-<lb break="no"/>sure to take from them that property, and that one ray should<lb break="yes"/>lose it for the moment only, while another, on the contrary,<lb break="yes"/>should be deprived of it for ever after?&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>When Mr. Wheatstone, in his fine experiments on the<lb break="yes"/>duration of the electric spark (1835), had succeeded in using<lb break="yes"/>with great success his ingenious rotatory apparatus, M. Arago<lb break="yes"/>immediately perceived the possibility, by applying the same<lb break="yes"/>principle of rotation, of measuring, by angular deviations, the<lb break="yes"/>difference of the velocity of light in a liquid and in air. He<lb break="yes"/>gave an account of the experiment which he proposed to make<lb break="yes"/>to the Institute towards the end of the year 1838. Aided by<lb break="yes"/>an experienced and skilful artist, (the younger Breguet,) he<lb break="yes"/>succeeded, after many changes in the apparatus, in realising<lb break="yes"/>his project. In the course of the trials for this purpose,<lb break="yes"/>M. Breguet had succeeded in causing an axis to turn eight<lb break="yes"/>thousand times in a second, when relieved of the weight of<lb break="yes"/>the mirror which it carried. At last, in 1850, all was ready,<lb break="yes"/>and the apparatus, with its various improvements, could be<lb break="yes"/>made to work; but the great and sad alteration which<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="xxvi" facs="#f0010"/> M. Arago&#x2019;s sight had, almost suddenly, undergone, took<lb break="yes"/>from him the hope of himself engaging in the observations.<lb break="yes"/>In a note presented to the Institute, on the 29th of April,<lb break="yes"/>1850, he announced this, saying, with a noble simplicity,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;My pretensions must be limited to having propounded<lb break="yes"/>the problem, and publicly proposed certain means for its<lb break="yes"/>resolution. In the present state of my eyes, I can only ac-<lb break="no"/>company with my best wishes the experimentalists who<lb break="yes"/>shall be willing to follow up my ideas, and add a fresh proof<lb break="yes"/>in favour of the undulatory theory to those which I have<lb break="yes"/>deduced from a phenomenon of interference, too well known<lb break="yes"/>to physicists for it to be needful that I should recall it here.&#x201D;<lb break="yes"/>M. Arago had the satisfaction of seeing his wishes fulfilled.<lb break="yes"/>Two experimenters, equally distinguished by their talent and<lb break="yes"/>by the delicacy of their observation, M. Foucault, to whom<lb break="yes"/>we owe the physical demonstration, by means of the pen-<lb break="no"/>dulum, of the earth&#x2019;s rotation, and M. Fizeau, who has de-<lb break="no"/>termined by an ingenious method the velocity of light in the<lb break="yes"/>atmosphere, succeeded, after adding some further improve-<lb break="no"/>ments to the means proposed by M. Arago, in resolving<lb break="yes"/>the question, in the sense which is subversive of the emission<lb break="yes"/>theory. MM. Foucault and Fizeau presented the results<lb break="yes"/>of their labours to the Academy of Sciences, the former<lb break="yes"/>in May, 1850, and the latter in September, 1851.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>If I have dwelt at some length on the principal researches<lb break="yes"/>of M. Arago on light, it has been because it was the subject<lb break="yes"/>to which he devoted himself with greater perseverance than<lb break="yes"/>to any other, for an interval of more than forty years. His<lb break="yes"/>discoveries in electricity and magnetism, however important<lb break="yes"/>they may be in themselves, only occupied him, compara-<lb break="no"/>tively speaking, transiently. The attraction exercised on iron<lb break="yes"/>filings by the reophore wire joining the two poles of the<lb break="yes"/>Voltaic pile, and the magnetisation effected by the employ-<lb break="no"/>ment of a wire coiled as a helix, either continuously or with<lb break="yes"/>interruptions and changes of direction, had been observed by<lb break="yes"/>M. Arago previous to the admirable labours of Ampere, and<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="xxvii" facs="#f0011"/> these observations had already given a lively impetus to elec-<lb break="no"/>tro-magnetic researches.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Rotation-Magnetism</hi> was discovered by M. Arago during<lb break="yes"/>a visit which he made to England, together with myself, for<lb break="yes"/>the purpose of comparing the length of the pendulum con-<lb break="no"/>jointly with M. Biot. The results of our observations were<lb break="yes"/>not so satisfactory as we could have desired; but M. Arago,<lb break="yes"/>while engaged with me on the slope of Greenwich Hill, in<lb break="yes"/>determining the magnetic intensity, by the number of vi-<lb break="no"/>brations performed in a given time by a dipping needle,<lb break="yes"/>made the important remark, which was <hi rendition="#i" >exclusively his own,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>that a magnetic needle which has been set in motion, comes<lb break="yes"/>to rest sooner when placed in proximity to other substances,<lb break="yes"/>metallic or non-metallic, than when at a distance from them.<lb break="yes"/>From this first remark, rendered fruitful by ingenious com-<lb break="no"/>binations, he was led in 1825 to explain the phenomena pro-<lb break="no"/>duced by the rotation of disks acting on needles at rest, as<lb break="yes"/>well as the influence which water, ice, and glass exercise<lb break="yes"/>on magnetic needles. The excitement of magnetism by<lb break="yes"/>motion became a subject of warm discussions between Nobili,<lb break="yes"/>Antinori, Seebeck, Barlow, Sir John Herschel, Babbage,<lb break="yes"/>and Baumgartner, which lasted for six years, or until 1831,<lb break="yes"/>when the brilliant discovery of Faraday linked all the phe-<lb break="no"/>nomena of magnetism by rotation to the fruitful principles<lb break="yes"/>of <hi rendition="#i">induced currents.</hi> Such is the character of the onward<lb break="yes"/>progress of the sciences at those periods, unhappily too<lb break="yes"/>short, in which they advance with a rapid step, in which<lb break="yes"/>ideas tend towards increased generalisation, and the minds<lb break="yes"/>of the students of nature are gradually rising towards a<lb break="yes"/>higher order of conceptions.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>In tracing the present sketch of the more important of<lb break="yes"/>M. Arago&#x2019;s labours, and of the influence which they have<lb break="yes" />exercised, I have availed myself, in addition to my own re-<lb break="no" />collections, of those of two men devoted to his memory:<lb break="yes"/>M. Auguste de La Rive, the celebrated Genevese professor,<lb break="yes"/>and M. Barral, a chemist and physicist of rare merit, hold-<lb break="no"/>
                    <pb n="xxviii" facs="#f0012"/> ing an official station in the instruction given at the Ecole<lb break="yes"/>Polytechnique, of which establishment I preserve a per-<lb break="no"/>sonally grateful recollection from having long worked there<lb break="yes"/>under the direction of M. Gay-Lussac.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>After the general view above given, I have still to enter<lb break="yes"/>into some details respecting the distribution of the materials<lb break="yes"/>of which M. Arago&#x2019;s collected works will consist. But I<lb break="yes"/>must first premise that it will be difficult to follow any very<lb break="yes" />determinate order, so close are the links which unite the<lb break="yes" />different sciences, and which new discoveries are multiplying<lb break="yes" />daily, and so uncertain are the limits which divide them.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I also find myself constrained to increased indefiniteness,<lb break="yes"/>from the circumstances of my being at a distance from<lb break="yes"/>France (which was long to me, as it were, a second father-<lb break="no"/>land), and of not having M. Arago&#x2019;s manuscripts before me.<lb break="yes"/>I divide the labours of my illustrious friend generally into<lb break="yes"/>six groups.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>1st. <hi rendition="#i">Literary and Biographical Part.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I believe I am a just exponent of the public voice, amidst<lb break="yes" />all the dissimilarities of opinion, when I extol in M. Arago&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Eloges Académiques,&#x201D; the critical care given by him to<lb break="yes"/>inquiry into the facts, the impartiality of his judgments,<lb break="yes"/>the lucid clearness of his scientific expositions, and a fervour<lb break="yes"/>which increases in proportion to the elevation of the subject.<lb break="yes"/>The same qualities distinguish the different discourses which<lb break="yes"/>were pronounced by him in the political assemblies, where<lb break="yes"/>from the nobleness and purity of his convictions, he occu-<lb break="no"/>pied so eminent a place, and the reports which were drawn<lb break="yes"/>up by him for the purpose of causing due honour to be paid<lb break="yes"/>to science in the persons of some celebrated inventors.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>In order that the merits of the men whose life and labours<lb break="yes"/>he proposes to trace and to characterise may be justly ap-<lb break="no" />preciated, M. Arago generally begins with a sketch of the<lb break="yes" />state of knowledge at the period when their career com-<lb break="no" />menced. He brought to this work no less patience than<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="xxix" facs="#f0013"/> ardour; and in consequence his éloges are of high impor-<lb break="no"/>tance for the history of science, and particularly for<lb break="yes"/>the history of great discoveries. Profound convictions, ac-<lb break="no"/>quired by long and arduous researches, have sometimes<lb break="yes"/>rendered his judgments severe, and have caused him to be<lb break="yes"/>exposed to unjust criticisms. The discovery of the decom-<lb break="no"/>position of water, for instance, and the invention of the<lb break="yes"/>high-pressure steam engine which has so powerfully seconded<lb break="yes"/>the dominion of man over nature, are facts in regard to<lb break="yes"/>which, as in regard to many others also, sentiments of<lb break="yes"/>nationality are not the only cause of the divergence of opinion<lb break="yes"/>existing among scientific men.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>A zealous defender of the claims of intellect, M. Arago,<lb break="yes"/>in his éloges, often leads us to feel how much elevation of<lb break="yes" />moral character dignifies and ennobles mental labours. In<lb break="yes" />his expositions of the principles of science, on which he knew<lb break="yes"/>well how to shed an admirable and persuasive clearness,<lb break="yes"/>the style of the orator becomes the more expressive, the<lb break="yes"/>greater the simplicity and precision which it offers; in such<lb break="yes"/>passages he attains what Buffon denominated <hi rendition="#i">la vérité du<lb break="yes"/>style.</hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>2nd. <hi rendition="#i">Part relating to Astronomy and Celestial Physics.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Operations for the measurement of the French are of the<lb break="yes" />meridian in its most southern part, executed conjointly with<lb break="yes"/>M. Biot.&#x2014;Figure of the earth.&#x2014;Investigations relating to<lb break="yes"/>the precise determination of the diameters of the planets.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>New ocular micrometer, and new prismatic telescope different<lb break="yes"/>from that of Rochon. &#x2014; Summer and winter solstices; vernal<lb break="yes"/>and autumnal equinoxes; declinations of southern and cir-<lb break="no"/>cumpolar stars; absolute position of the pole star in 1813;<lb break="yes"/>latitude of Paris; parallax of 61 Cygni (conjointly with M.<lb break="yes"/>Mathieu). &#x2014; Geodesical operations made on the coasts of<lb break="yes"/>France and of England, conjointly with M. Mathieu and with<lb break="yes"/>English men of science, for determining the difference of lon-<lb break="no"/>gitude between Greenwich and Paris. &#x2014; Researches on the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="xxx" facs="#f0014"/> declination of some stars of the first and second magnitudes,<lb break="yes"/>made conjointly with MM. Mathieu and Humboldt. &#x2014; Photo-<lb break="no"/>metric researches on the comparative intensity of the light of<lb break="yes"/>different heavenly bodies, and of the light proceeding from<lb break="yes"/>the margin and from the centre of the sun&#x2019;s disc. &#x2014; Intensity<lb break="yes"/>of the light in different parts of the moon.&#x2014;Variability of<lb break="yes"/>the ashy-coloured light of the moon&#x2019;s disc.&#x2014;Polar regions<lb break="yes"/>of the planet Mars.&#x2014;Bands or &#x201C;belts&#x201D; of Jupiter and<lb break="yes"/>Saturn.&#x2014;Light of Jupiter&#x2019;s satellites compared to that of<lb break="yes"/>the central planet.&#x2014;Physical constitution of the sun and of<lb break="yes"/>its different envelopes.&#x2014;Light emanating from the gaseous<lb break="yes"/>parts of the sun.&#x2014;Singular phenomena presented by total<lb break="yes"/>eclipses of the sun.&#x2014;Reddish protuberances showing them-<lb break="no"/>selves on the contour of the moon during a total eclipse of<lb break="yes"/>the sun.&#x2014;Rays of polarised light in the light of comets.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Cause of the scintillation of stars.&#x2014;Tables of refraction.&#x2014;<lb break="yes" />Irradiation.&#x2014;Effect of telescopes on the visibility of stars<lb break="yes"/>during daylight.&#x2014;Considerations respecting the diffused<lb break="yes"/>light of the atmosphere.&#x2014;Velocity of light proceeding from<lb break="yes"/>the stars towards which the earth is moving, and from the<lb break="yes"/>stars from which she is receding.&#x2014;Velocity of transmission<lb break="yes"/>of rays of different colours.&#x2014;Means furnished by the phases<lb break="yes"/>of Algol for measuring the velocity of transmission of the<lb break="yes"/>rays of light.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The &#x201C;Popular Astronomy,&#x201D; which contains the exposi-<lb break="no"/>tion of the different courses of public lectures delivered by M.<lb break="yes"/>Arago, from 1812 to 1845, in the magnificent theatre of the<lb break="yes"/>Observatory, and which were attended by all classes of<lb break="yes"/>society with the most lively interest, will be the principal or-<lb break="no"/>nament of this second part of his works. In reading the<lb break="yes"/>treatise entitled &#x201C;Popular Astronomy,&#x201D; many pleasing and,<lb break="yes"/>at the same time melancholy recollections will be awakened<lb break="yes"/>in the minds of those who had the good fortune of being<lb break="yes"/>present at the lectures given by M. Arago, and of admiring<lb break="yes"/>the manner of their delivery &#x2014; so simple, so persuasive, so<lb break="yes" />engaging, and awakening so much regard for the speaker.</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="xxxi" facs="#f0015"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>III. <hi rendition="#i">Optical Part.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Difference in the nature of the light emanating from<lb break="yes" />incandescent bodies, solid or gaseous. &#x2014; Means of distin-<lb break="no"/>guishing by the polariscope polarised from ordinary light.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Constant relation between the proportion of polarised light<lb break="yes"/>existing in the transmitted or refracted pencil and that<lb break="yes"/>which exists in the reflected pencil.&#x2014;M. Arago also found,<lb break="yes"/>in conjunction with M. Fresnel, that polarised rays do not<lb break="yes"/>exercise any mutual influence when their planes of polar-<lb break="no"/>isation are perpendicular to each other, and that consequently<lb break="yes"/>they cannot in such case produce any fringes, although all the<lb break="yes" />conditions required for the appearance of that phenomenon,<lb break="yes" />in other cases, shall have been scrupulously fulfilled.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Treatise on photometry, founded on the theory of undu-<lb break="no"/>lations, (an investigation at once experimental and theoretical,<lb break="yes"/>great part of which was contained in seven memoirs pre-<lb break="no"/>sented to the Academy of Sciences in 1850). &#x2014;Refraction<lb break="yes"/>of luminous rays in different gases and under different<lb break="yes"/>angles. &#x2014; Memoir on the possibility of determining the<lb break="yes"/>refracting powers of bodies from their chemical composition.<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014; Investigations on the affinity of bodies for light, made<lb break="yes"/>conjointly with M. Biot.&#x2014;Chromatic polarisation; its varied<lb break="yes" />applicability in celestial and terrestrial physics.&#x2014;Circular<lb break="yes"/>(rotatory) polarisation, or phenomena of colorisation, dis-<lb break="no"/>covered as early as 1811 by M. Arago, in plates of quartz,<lb break="yes"/>cut perpendicularly to the axis of the crystal; (the white<lb break="yes"/>ray which traverses presents the most vivid colours when<lb break="yes"/>looked at through a doubly refracting prism).&#x2014;Reflected<lb break="yes"/>and transmitted coloured rings.&#x2014;Application of double re-<lb break="no"/>fraction to photometry.&#x2014;Formation of photometric tables,<lb break="yes"/>showing the quantities of light reflected and transmitted by a<lb break="yes"/>plate of glass, for inclinations comprised between 4° and 26°,<lb break="yes"/>and continued up to perpendicular incidence by a particular<lb break="yes" />process.&#x2014;Estimation of the loss of light which takes place<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="xxxii" facs="#f0016"/> by reflection at the surface of metals, and demonstration of<lb break="yes"/>the important fact that there is no loss of light in total or<lb break="yes"/>entire reflection.&#x2014;The law of Malus, called the <hi rendition="#i">law of the<lb break="yes"/>cosine,</hi> on the division of polarised light,&#x201C; which was at first<lb break="yes"/>only an empirical mode of representing appearances,&#x201D; was<lb break="yes"/>demonstrated experimentally by M. Arago, for the case in<lb break="yes"/>which the polarised pencil traverses either a doubly refract-<lb break="no"/>ing prism or a tourmaline cut parallel to its axis. (The<lb break="yes"/>polarimeter of M. Arago, employed in these kinds of ex-<lb break="no"/>periment, was so delicate that it indicated unequivocally the<lb break="yes"/>presence of an eightieth part of polarised light in a pencil of<lb break="yes"/>rays. In all these experiments relating to photometry, the<lb break="yes"/>experiments and calculations were made by MM. Laugier and<lb break="yes"/>Petit under the direction of M. Arago.)&#x2014;Demonstration of<lb break="yes"/>the possibility of constructing an interferential barometer,<lb break="yes"/>thermometer, and refractor.&#x2014;Views respecting the measure-<lb break="no"/>ment of mountains by the polariscope, and of the height of<lb break="yes"/>clouds by the aid of a graduated polarimeter.</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>IV. <hi rendition="#i">Electro-magnetical Part.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Discovery of the property of attracting iron filings pos-<lb break="no" />sessed by the reophore, or current-bearing wire joining the<lb break="yes" />poles of the pile. &#x2014; Magnetisation of a needle by means of<lb break="yes"/>the passage of the electric current in a helix; consecutive<lb break="yes"/>points resulting therefrom.&#x2014;Rotation-magnetism, by which<lb break="yes"/>it was made certain that all bodies are susceptible of<lb break="yes"/>acquiring magnetism, a fact already divined by William<lb break="yes"/>Gilbert, and rendered probable by the ingenious experiments<lb break="yes"/>of Coulomb.&#x2014;Observations of the horary variation of the<lb break="yes" />magnetic declination at Paris from 1818; secular change<lb break="yes"/>of the same phenomenon.&#x2014;Discussion respecting the move-<lb break="no" />ment from east to west, of the nodes or points of inter-<lb break="no" />section of the magnetic with the geographic equator.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Perturbations, occasioned by the influence of polar auroras,<lb break="yes"/>in the march of the horary variations of the magnetic decli-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="xxxiii" facs="#f0017"/> nation at places where the polar aurora is not visible.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Simultaneity of perturbations of the declination (magnetic<lb break="yes"/>storms), proved by corresponding observations at Paris and<lb break="yes"/>Kasan, at Paris and Berlin, at Paris, Berlin, and the mines<lb break="yes"/>of Freiberg in Saxony.&#x2014;Observation of the deflection by<lb break="yes"/>the approach of a magnet, of the jet of light which unites<lb break="yes"/>the two charcoal points of the conductor in a closed electric<lb break="yes" />current; analogies which this experiment presents to the<lb break="yes" />phenomena of the aurora borealis.&#x2014;Discovery in 1827<lb break="yes" />of the horary variation of the magnetic inclination and force.</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>V. <hi rendition="#i">Part relating to Meteorology and the General<lb break="yes"/>Principles of Atmospheric Physics.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Determination of the specific weight of atmospheric air,<lb break="yes"/>made conjointly with M. Biot. &#x2014; Experiments made with<lb break="yes"/>M. Dulong, for the purpose of establishing that Mariotte&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>law undergoes no essential variation up to the pressure of<lb break="yes"/>twenty-seven atmospheres, and much beyond.&#x2014;Dangerous<lb break="yes"/>experiments made with the same physicist (M. Dulong),<lb break="yes"/>on the elastic force of steam at very high temperatures.<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014; Table of the elastic force of steam, and corresponding<lb break="yes"/>temperatures.&#x2014;Formation of halos, and polarised light<lb break="yes"/>which halos reflect.&#x2014; Cyanometer. &#x2014; Optical researches on<lb break="yes"/>the causes of the colour of the water of the sea and of<lb break="yes"/>rivers. &#x2014; Cold produced by evaporation. &#x2014; Researches on<lb break="yes"/>the quantity of rain falling at different heights and at<lb break="yes"/>different places. &#x2014; Explanation of the injurious effects which<lb break="yes" />have been attributed to the moon under the name of the<lb break="yes" />&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">lune rousse.</hi>&#x201D; &#x2014; A very extensive memoir on thunder,<lb break="yes"/>and different kinds of lightning, enlarged by numerous<lb break="yes"/>additions dictated by M. Arago, during his last illness,<lb break="yes"/>to a learned and devoted secretary, M. Goujon, a young<lb break="yes"/>astronomer attached to the Paris Observatory, who in the<lb break="yes"/>same manner wrote the &#x201C;Astronomie Populaire&#x201D; to the dic-<lb break="no"/>
                        <fw type="sig" place="bottom">b</fw>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="xxxiv" facs="#f0018"/> tation of his illustrious master. &#x2014; Experiments on the<lb break="yes"/>velocity of sound, made in 1822 between Montlhéry and<lb break="yes"/>Villejuif, conjointly with Messrs. Gay-Lussac, Bouvard,<lb break="yes"/>Prony, Mathieu, and Humboldt, assisted by the artillery of<lb break="yes"/>the Garde Royale.</p>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>VI. <hi rendition="#i">Part relating to Physical Geography.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Level of seas. &#x2014; Thermometric state of the globe. &#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Temperature of the surface of the sea in different latitudes,<lb break="yes"/>and of the sea water in successive strata down to the greatest<lb break="yes"/>depths. &#x2014; Currents of warm and cold water. &#x2014; The waters<lb break="yes"/>of the ocean compared to the atmosphere above them in<lb break="yes"/>respect to temperature. &#x2014; Colour of the sky and of clouds<lb break="yes"/>at different heights above the horizon. &#x2014; Neutral point of<lb break="yes"/>polarisation in the atmosphere. &#x2014; Use of a plate of tour-<lb break="no"/>maline cut parallel to the faces of the prism, for seeing<lb break="yes"/>shoals and the bottom of the sea. &#x2014; Temperature of the<lb break="yes"/>air at the North Pole.&#x2014; Mean temperature of the interior<lb break="yes"/>of the earth, at depths accessible to man; (observations made<lb break="yes" />on the temperature of wells, bored to different depths, have<lb break="yes"/>conducted to the law of the increment of heat in descending<lb break="yes"/>below the surface of the earth).</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Such is the outline, &#x2014; very incomplete, notwithstanding the<lb break="yes"/>vast treasures which it contains, &#x2014; of the labours of M.<lb break="yes"/>Arago. They have raised him to the rank of one among<lb break="yes"/>the most eminent men of the nineteenth century. His name<lb break="yes"/>will be honoured wherever respect for services rendered to<lb break="yes"/>science, a just sentiment of the dignity of man and the<lb break="yes"/>independence of thought, and the love of public liberty<lb break="yes"/>are preserved. But it is not alone the authority of a mighty<lb break="yes"/>intellect which has given to M. Arago the popularity which<lb break="yes"/>
                        <pb n="xxxv" facs="#f0019"/> he enjoyed: the conscientious zeal which failed not when<lb break="yes"/>death approached, the desperate efforts to fulfil up to the<lb break="yes"/>last moment the most minute duties, have contributed to the<lb break="yes"/>honour in which his name is held. Nor should the charm<lb break="yes"/>of his diction, the amenity of his habits and manners, and<lb break="yes"/>the kindliness of his character be forgotten. Capable of<lb break="yes"/>the most tender devotion, the vivacity of his ardent mind<lb break="yes"/>and disposition always tempered by its natural sweetness and<lb break="yes"/>kindness, M. Arago enjoyed, in the midst of an intelligent<lb break="yes"/>and affectionate family, the peaceful happiness of domestic<lb break="yes"/>life. In the surviving circle of those most dear to him<lb break="yes"/>M. Arago found all that a touching assiduity, the exercise of<lb break="yes"/>intelligent foresight, and the most tender and inventive zeal<lb break="yes"/>could offer to soothe and alleviate during the slow exhaustion<lb break="yes"/>of his strength. He died surrounded by his sons, &#x2014; a sister,<lb break="yes"/>Madame Mathieu, worthy of the tender affection of such a<lb break="yes"/>brother, &#x2014; and a niece, Madame Laugier, who gave to him<lb break="yes"/>the most unremitting and devoted care, and who, at the last<lb break="yes" />moment, showed no less fortitude in grief than she had done<lb break="yes" />nobleness in her entire and touching self-devotion.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>At a distance from M. Arago&#x2019;s bed of suffering, I could<lb break="yes" />only testify from afar my deep affliction. Even the certainty<lb break="yes"/>of the near approach of this loss could not lessen its<lb break="yes"/>bitterness. As a last homage to the memory of him who<lb break="yes"/>has been so recently taken from amongst us, I subjoin here<lb break="yes"/>a few lines which have been already published elsewhere:&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;That which characterised this man of unique mould was<lb break="yes"/>not alone the powerful genius which originates new ideas,<lb break="yes"/>and renders fruitful those already attained, or that rare luci-<lb break="no"/>dity which can describe recently discerned and complicated<lb break="yes"/>departments of discovery as clearly as if they had been the<lb break="yes"/>long acquired possessions of human intelligence; it was also<lb break="yes"/>the engaging combination of the force and elevation of an im-<lb break="no"/>passioned character with the affectionate sweetness of a more<lb break="yes"/>gentle one. I am proud of thinking that, by my tender devo-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb n="xxxvi" facs="#f0020"/> tion, and by the constant admiration to which I have given<lb break="yes"/>expression in all my works, I have belonged to him for<lb break="yes"/>forty-four years, and that my name will sometimes be pro-<lb break="no"/>nounced by the side of his great name.&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <closer>
                        <salute>
                            <hi rendition="#et">ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT.</hi>
                        </salute>
                    </closer>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <dateline>
                        <hi rendition="#et">Potsdam, November, 1853.</hi>
                    </dateline>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 