<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Fragment of a letter of Baron Alexander Humboldt to Mr. Albert Berg</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:18</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VII.71</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1854-Auszug_aus_einem-2</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1854-Auszug_aus_einem-1.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1854-Auszug_aus_einem-2.xml" type="self"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Fragment of a letter of Baron Alexander Humboldt to Mr. Albert Berg</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1854</date>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: Albert Berg, &lt;i&gt;Physiognomy of Tropical Vegetation in South America. A Series of Views Illustrating the Primeval Forests on the River Magdalena and in the Andes of New Granada&lt;/i&gt;, London: Paul and Dominic Colnaghi and Co. 1854, S. [I]–II.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung; Schmuck: Kapitälchen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="i" facs="#f0001" /><lb/><div n="1"><head>FRAGMENT OF A LETTER<lb/><hi rendition="#k">of</hi><lb/>BARON ALEXANDER HUMBOLDT TO MR. ALBERT BERG.</head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">If</hi> in the noble creations of painting our imagination delights to find animated pictures of exotic scenery, this<lb/>enjoyment is by no means exclusively confined to the majestic in the forms or in the richness and wild<lb/>luxuriance of the soil which such pictures may present, but is at the same time reflected in our understanding.<lb/>It reminds us of the intimate relation between the distribution of forms and the influences of climate depending<lb/>on the altitude of the plateaux, as also on the latitude. It is this relation which, by presenting to us the<lb/>wonders and peculiar characteristics of the vegetation, renders that, which at first seemed only picturesque,<lb/>both instructive and suggestive in the field of Physical Geography.</p><lb/><p>Before I enter, my dear Sir, upon the charm spread over the delightful pages which you have brought<lb/>from the tropical regions of South America, I have thought it right to determine the point of view from which<lb/>I consider the publication of the drawings you were kind enough to present to me, both as useful and desirable<lb/>in a high degree. These happy conceptions, displaying at once fine talents and the inspiration of a deep love<lb/>of nature, will possess an interest all the greater, inasmuch as they refer to countries which had not yet been<lb/>visited by distinguished artists. Speaking generally, it is only within the last few years that any persons have<lb/>devoted themselves with much interest to the representation of the great forms of the equatorial zone, and their<lb/>varied groupings under their real <hi rendition="#i">physiognomical</hi> aspect. Your work is quite worthy of appearing at the side of<lb/>those of your illustrious predecessors.</p><lb/><p>Having lived for several years with my excellent friend M. Bonpland on the declivity of the great Cordillera<lb/>de los Andes, and in the very same countries which you have visited, I must bear testimony to the admirable truth<lb/>with which you have succeeded in representing not only the interior of the virgin forests, but also that alpine<lb/>vegetation of the Cordilleras which offers an entirely different character. You have not contented yourself<lb/>with seizing the type of the greater productions of the vegetable world by placing them in the foreground, but<lb/>you have also represented their individuality and that curious interlacing of the roots above the soil, of which<lb/>the forests of our temperate zone offer no example. The drawings of the passage of the Cordillera in the<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Paramo de Quindiù</hi> which you are going to publish, will give great interest to your work. The breadth of<lb/>the chain interrupted by valleys and ravines is so considerable, that not wishing to be carried in a little chair<lb/>of Bamboo reeds on the backs of the natives, I required twenty-four days for my journey from the small town<lb/>of Ibagué to that of Cartago. I have found the highest point of this route, that of the division of the waters,<lb/>to be at an elevation of 1798 toises (10788 Par. feet) above the level of the South Sea. It is the <hi rendition="#i">Garita del<lb/>Paramo</hi> where we have encamped in a portable hut made of the large leaves of the Marantace&#x00E6;, and is almost<lb/>600 feet higher than the summit of Etna. In a much more southerly passage of the Cordilleras, at the<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Paramo del Assuay</hi> (S. Lat. 2°<formula notation="TeX">\frac{3}{4}</formula>) between the towns of Alausì and Cuen&#x00E7;a, I have found the highest point of the<lb/>route at the <hi rendition="#i">Ladera de Cadlud</hi> at an elevation of 2428 toises (14568 Par. feet), which is nearly the height of<lb/>the summit of Mont Blanc. The Paramo de Quindiù presents the very extraordinary phenomenon of a group<lb/>of Palm-trees which may be classed amongst the <hi rendition="#i">alpine plants</hi>. To this group belongs the <hi rendition="#i">Wax-palm</hi><lb/>(<hi rendition="#i">Ceroxylon Andicola</hi>), the <hi rendition="#i">Palmito del Azufral</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">Oreodoxa frigida</hi>) and the <hi rendition="#i">Can&#x0303;a de la Vibora</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">Kunthia<lb/>montana</hi>). Whilst the family of the Palm-trees generally only vegetates in the tropics in a zone where the<lb/>mean temperature of the air is from 22° to 24° of the centigrade thermometer, and is not found on the declivity<lb/>of the Cordillera at a greater elevation than 2000 or 2500 feet, the alpine Palm-trees which we have just<lb/>mentioned are first found at Quindiù (with a northern latitude of 4°26&#x2032; to 4°34&#x2032;) at an elevation of 6000 feet<lb/>with a superior limit of 9000 feet. This is a region which in this zone is still 5400 feet from the inferior<lb/>limit of perpetual snow, and in which, according to my observations, the thermometer often falls in the night<lb/>to 4°, 8 and to 6 above the freezing point. To you, my dear Sir, belongs the great merit of having been the<lb/>first to represent the physiognomical traits of the Wax-palm, whose majestic and slender form, according to the<lb/>stems which I ordered to be cut down, attains a height of 160 to 180 feet. The drawings in which you have<lb/>represented these Palm-trees are the most graceful ornament of your work.</p><lb/><p>The association of the Wax-palm with the Conifer&#x00E6; (the yewtree-leaved <hi rendition="#i">Podocarpus</hi>) and the Oaks<lb/>(<hi rendition="#i">Quercus Granadensis</hi>, similar to our northern Oaks) forms as remarkable a contrast as the mixture of Palm-trees<lb/><pb n="ii" facs="#f0002" />
with Pines (<hi rendition="#i">Pinus occidentalis</hi>) and with the <hi rendition="#i">Mahogany</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">Swietenia Mahagoni</hi>) of the warmer regions of the<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Isla de Pinos</hi> in the south of Cuba, and in the <hi rendition="#i">Pinal</hi> of the <hi rendition="#i">Cayo de Moya</hi> in the north of Cuba, which<lb/>Christopher Columbus already mentions &#x2018;with astonishment&#x2019; in his Journal of Navigation of November 1492.<lb/>Types which we call northern, supposing them to belong exclusively to cold and temperate regions, appear<lb/>again with the same <hi rendition="#i">facies</hi>, but in very different species, in the tropical regions of America and the Indian<lb/>Archipelago. It is this circumstance which occasioned me to say in one of my earliest works, that the<lb/>inhabitants of the equator, where the climates follow each other on the plateaux as on different stories, have the<lb/>privilege of contemplating at the same time all the stars which glisten in the vault of heaven, and almost all the<lb/>forms of vegetable life.</p><lb/><p>The view of the volcano of <hi rendition="#i">Tolima</hi>, which may be enjoyed from several points of the eastern side<lb/>of Quindiù, has supplied the subject of one of your most picturesque sketches in Plate III. The volcano,<lb/>which is of a very regular shape, and like the <hi rendition="#i">Cayambé de Quito,</hi> rises in the form of a truncated cone, forms<lb/>the background of the landscape; while in the foreground, the soil is perceived to be encumbered with a most<lb/>luxuriant growth of the tree-fern, the Heliconia and Passiflores, which climb to the top of the trees. It is a<lb/>great advantage of your collection, that, through the care of an excellent botanist, Dr. Klotzsch, my friend and<lb/>colleague at the Academy of Berlin, you have been able to add to your drawings the botanical names of a great<lb/>number of species, and this with the greatest accuracy. As this learned man is Director of the great collection<lb/>of the Herbarium, he has been able to consult the reports of M. Bonpland and myself, in which we have<lb/>indicated the localities, as also the descriptions given by M. Kunth, in our &#x2018;<hi rendition="#i">Nova Genera et Species Plantarum.</hi>&#x2019;<lb/>In your beautiful drawing, the vast snowy masses appear in the horizon through a clearing in the forest. They<lb/>stand out against the azure of the tropical sky at an apparent but illusive proximity. A formidable eruption of<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">volcano of Tolima</hi> took place on the 12th March, 1595, and devastated the entire province of Mariquita,<lb/>since which time it seemed almost extinguished. A celebrated chemist, M. Boussingault, accompanied by<lb/>M. Goudot, the botanist, ascended it to the height of 13,240 feet, which is very near to the region of perpetual<lb/>snow, in order to examine the composition of the vapours emanating from the clefts of <hi rendition="#i">trachytic</hi> rock, which has<lb/>itself emerged from the bosom of a formation of <hi rendition="#i">micaceous and amphibolic schist</hi>. Recently the volcano has<lb/>again been in activity. It deserved a place in your work and in my views of the Cordilleras, all the more, as it<lb/>seems to me to be the loftiest summit of the whole northern hemisphere of the New Continent. I made a<lb/>trigonometrical measurement of the Tolima in the valley of the Carvajal, on the west of Ibagué, and found it<lb/>384 feet higher than the Popocatepetl, the great volcano of Mexico.</p><lb/><p>Descending with you, my dear Sir, from the heights of the Cordilleras, to the lower regions of the valley of<lb/>the Magdalena, I take much pleasure in bearing the same testimony to the truth with which you have seized its<lb/>character. Having passed fifty-six dull days in navigating this great river, I had sufficient time to become<lb/>acquainted with the distribution of its vegetation. The affectionate interest which I take in yourself, induces<lb/>me to advise you to leave to your interesting drawings, so excellently drawn upon stone, that character of<lb/>sketches which they have had in their original state. All later additions to objects of which we received happy<lb/>inspirations, take off a little from the spirit of the drawing. I do not mean to say that the technical perfection<lb/>of a drawing carefully finished on the spot, may not add to the effect and to the truth of the character of the<lb/>landscape; but a traveller in his rapid progress through places difficult of access, is very seldom in a position to<lb/>finish his sketches at leisure. The travels in a beautiful part of the East, which you were so happy as to make<lb/>before your journey to New Granada, have fortunately prepared you to seize with talent in different zones the<lb/>aspect of the forms which are the real elements of the beauty of a landscape.</p><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#i">Potsdam, May</hi> 1853.</hi></dateline></div><lb/></body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
