<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-01-05" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Baron Humboldt And American Affairs.</hi>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">To the Editor of The N.Y. Tribune.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Sir</hi>: Baron von Humboldt called my attention a<lb break="yes"/>day or two since to a paragraph copied from some<lb break="yes" />other paper into <hi rendition="#k">The Semi-Weekly Tribune</hi> of May<lb break="yes"/>12, headed &#x201C;A Huge Pile of Serpents,&#x201D; and begin-<lb break="no"/>ning thus: &#x201C;Baron Humboldt says: In the savan-<lb break="no"/>&#x201C;nahs of Izacubo, Guiana, I saw the most wonderful<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;and terrible spectacle that can be seen,&#x201D; &amp;c. He<lb break="yes"/>smiled at the idea of this story being attributed to<lb break="yes"/>him, for he never was in the country mentioned, and<lb break="yes"/>certainly could never have given such a description<lb break="yes"/>of a sight which he never saw anywhere. He spoke<lb break="yes" />of this paragraph however, not on account of any im-<lb break="no"/>portance he attached to it or its correction, but as af-<lb break="no"/>fording him an opportunity of mentioning a fact in<lb break="yes"/>relation to himself personally, which he requested me<lb break="yes"/>to make known through the columns of <hi rendition="#k">The Tribune</hi>.<lb break="yes"/>
                </p>
                <p>For some twelve or fourteen years, he says, he has<lb break="yes"/>been annoyed by the use of his name by various per-<lb break="no"/>sons in America, especially in Central and South<lb break="yes"/>America, who have, as supposed connections of his,<lb break="yes"/>enjoyed and in some cases abused the confidence of<lb break="yes"/>generous persons who wished and thought to do him<lb break="yes"/>honor. His brother left no children, he himself never<lb break="yes"/>married, and he is alone the last of his race. There is<lb break="yes"/>no person living who can claim anything as a connec-<lb break="no"/>tion of his. That there may be other persons in the<lb break="yes"/>world by the name of Humboldt he of course does not<lb break="yes"/>deny, but the probability is that many pretended dis-<lb break="no"/>coveries in science, which have been promulgated by<lb break="yes"/>people calling themselves by that name, have only<lb break="yes"/>been the offspring of a desire to swindle and humbug<lb break="yes"/>in a more secure and effectual manner. I think, but<lb break="yes"/>am not sure, that in this conncetion he spoke of a<lb break="yes"/>ridiculous story of some Humboldt or other having<lb break="yes"/>five hundred negroes placed in his hands to be ex-<lb break="no"/>perimented on in innoculating for the yellow fever.</p>
                <p>The long letters which occasionally reach him from<lb break="yes"/>America and the West Indies from people who have,<lb break="yes"/>as they suppose, cherished members of his family in<lb break="yes"/>illness, or otherwise founded a claim upon his notice<lb break="yes"/>or friendship, are a serious annoyance, though the sci-<lb break="no"/>entific absurdities published in the papers under the<lb break="yes"/>sanction of his name partake more of the ludicrous.<lb break="yes"/>
                </p>
                <p>This noble and venerable man, though now some<lb break="yes"/>years beyond four score, still retains a lively interest<lb break="yes"/>in the progress of our country. To every American<lb break="yes"/>whom he meets he speaks of his friends, Jefferson and<lb break="yes"/>Gallatin, and laments the change on the question of<lb break="yes"/>Slavery which has come over our Government since<lb break="yes"/>their day. He speaks of Webster&#x2019;s last days with ex-<lb break="yes"/>pressions of the sincerest and deepest regret; nor does<lb break="yes"/>he omit any opportunity to impress upon the minds of<lb break="yes"/>Americans the deep moral degradation in which the<lb break="yes"/>United States as a nation has plunged itself within the<lb break="yes"/>last few years. Though an intimate friend of the<lb break="yes" />King, it is said (of course <hi rendition="#i">he</hi> says nothing of this) that<lb break="yes"/>the subject of politics and political affairs is never<lb break="yes"/>spoken of between them. From the interest with<lb break="yes"/>which he watches the development and progress of<lb break="yes" />the Republican idea in America it would seem that<lb break="yes"/>politics must indeed be banished from among the sub-<lb break="no"/>jects which he can discuss with Frederick William.<lb break="yes"/>At his request I showed him on the map the bound-<lb break="no"/>aries of the new Territories, Kansas and Nebraska&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>his map, though recent, dating back beyond the<lb break="yes"/>Douglas and Pierce outrage.<lb break="yes"/>
                </p>
                <p>It is very gratifiying to our national pride to hear<lb break="yes"/>his praises of some of our authors, Prescott being, in<lb break="yes"/>his opinion, one of the finest, if not the finest, historian<lb break="yes"/>now living and writing in the English language. He has<lb break="yes"/>several times expressed his wish that he could know<lb break="yes"/>that man. Of Prescott&#x2019;s works I think he likes best<lb break="yes"/>the &#x201C;Ferdinand and Isabella.&#x201D; As to the &#x201C;Conquest of<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Mexico,&#x201D; could the distinguished author have traveled<lb break="yes"/>to Mexico and viewed with his own eyes the scenes<lb break="yes"/>he describes, so as to have, in addition to the elegance<lb break="yes"/>of his style and extreme accuracy, added the charm<lb break="yes"/>of description of scenes he personally knew, Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt seems to think the book would have been per-<lb break="no" />fect. It is natural that he should feel something of a<lb break="yes"/>want of this kind in a work upon Mexico, but I do<lb break="yes"/>not see how a reader who has not the personal recol-<lb break="no"/>lections of the Baron can feel this want.<lb break="yes"/>
                </p>
                <p>Parts of Owen&#x2019;s great report upon the Lake Supe-<lb break="yes"/>rior region have pleased him much. I was surprised<lb break="yes"/>that Whitney&#x2019;s new work on the Mineral Resources<lb break="yes"/>of the United States had not reached his notice, for<lb break="yes"/>the great chemist, Rose, had made it the subject of<lb break="yes"/>several papers before the Geographical Society; but<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt seldom goes out to such meetings now.<lb break="yes"/>
                </p>
                <p>The following passages from a note written soon<lb break="yes"/>after reading in the <hi rendition="#k">The Tribune</hi> the account of the<lb break="yes" />opening of the Panama Railroad, I think may be<lb break="yes"/>translated for your paper without any impropriety, as<lb break="yes"/>a breach of the sanctity of private correspondence:</p>
                <p>&#x201C;Le chemin de fer de Panama a été proposé par<lb break="yes"/>moi, dès l&#x2019;Année 1805, avec le projét beaucoup plus<lb break="yes"/>utile et tres executable du canal oceanique du Capica<lb break="yes"/><choice><sic>a</sic><corr type="editorial">à</corr></choice> l&#x2019;Atrato.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;Les tristes debats sur la propagation du systeme de<lb break="yes" />l&#x2019;esclavage ont hereusement offert l&#x2019;occasion à<lb break="yes" />quelques ames nobles de prononcer des paroles con-<lb break="no"/>solantes. Il ne s&#x2019;agit pas de demander à la fois l&#x2019;abo-<lb break="no"/>lition de l&#x2019;esclavage, mais d&#x2019;amener peu à peu des<lb break="yes" />adoucissements dans la legislation actuelle par ne plus<lb break="yes"/>vendre l&#x2019;enfant à la mamelle. La pretention du Pres-<lb break="no"/>ident dans la lettre à M. Soulé de se croire en droit<lb break="yes"/>de conquerer l&#x2019;ile de Cuba lorsque un etat voisin fait<lb break="yes"/>mine de rendre sa legislation plus humaine, m&#x2019;a paru<lb break="yes"/>des plus sauvages.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>I give the following transversion of these para-<lb break="yes"/>graphs:</p>
                <p>&#x201C;The Panama Railroad was proposed by me as<lb break="yes"/>early as 1805, with the imposing project, which would<lb break="yes"/>be far more useful and quite as practicable, of an<lb break="yes"/>interoceanic Canal between Capica and Atrato.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;The sad debates which have taken place on the<lb break="yes"/>extension of the system of Slavery have happily<lb break="yes"/>offered an opportunity to a few noble souls to speak<lb break="yes"/>words of consolation. There is no need of demand-<lb break="no"/>ing immediately the abolition of Slavery, but of grad-<lb break="no"/>ually introducing mitigations into the present legisla-<lb break="no"/>tion, so that the babe may no longer be sold from the<lb break="yes"/>breast. The claim of the President in his letter to Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Soulé, that believed he had a right to conquer the<lb break="yes"/>Island of Cuba when a neighboring State untertook<lb break="yes"/>to render its legislation more humane, appears to me<lb break="yes"/>to be a most barbarous one.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Tastes may differ, but I would rather have the<lb break="yes"/>honor of the approbation expressed in these lines of<lb break="yes"/>the noble course pursued by Seward, Sumner and<lb break="yes"/>Chase than the title of President, which Pierce wears,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">so</hi> obtained! The approval of Humboldt is worth<lb break="yes"/>that of all the men-stealers and women-sellers from<lb break="yes"/>the Potomac to the boundary of Mexico.<lb break="yes"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#et">Your obedient servant,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#right">AN AMERICAN IN GERMANY.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Berlin, Prussia, June</hi> 10, 1855.
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 