<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="16" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">On certain Appearances connected with the Zodiacal Light.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>By Baron Humboldt.<note place="foot" n="*">Monatsbericht der Kön. Preuss. Akademie der Wissenschaften, Juli, 1855.</note>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In Gould&#x2019;s valuable American <hi rendition="#i">Astronomical Journal</hi> (No.<lb break="yes"/>lxxxiv., May 26, 1855), there appears a letter from the Rev. Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Jones, chaplain of the frigate Mississippi, containing, as the result<lb break="yes"/>of his observations of the Zodiacal Light in the seas of China and<lb break="yes"/>Japan, the conjecture of a second radiating ring of light having a<lb break="yes"/>relation to the moon. This conjecture is founded upon the <hi rendition="#i">extra-<lb break="no"/>ordinary spectacle of the Zodiacal Light simultaneously observed<lb break="yes"/>at both east and west horizons from eleven to one o&#x2019;clock,</hi> during<lb break="yes"/>several days in succession. As I observed something analogous<lb break="yes"/>fifty-two years ago in the Southern Ocean during the voyage of<lb break="yes"/>forty days from Callao, in Peru, to the port of Acapulco in Mexico,<lb break="yes"/>and have given only a very brief account of it in the astronomical<lb break="yes"/>part of my <hi rendition="#i">Cosmos,</hi> it may not be uninteresting to the members of<lb break="yes"/>the Academy if I laid before them an extract from my French<lb break="yes"/>Journal, written at sea, relating to this phenomenon, which hitherto<lb break="yes"/>has not formed the subject of any detailed remarks. The Zodiacal<lb break="yes"/>Light, and the difficult question whether we ought to attribute to<lb break="yes"/>a physical cause existing beyond our atmosphere the remarkable<lb break="yes"/>variations of light which it undergoes, while in tropical nights the<lb break="yes"/>smallest stars exhibit the same brightness to the naked eye, were<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="17" facs="#f0002"/> subjects which engaged my attention during a period of five years<lb break="yes"/>upon great heights among the Cordilleras, in the extensive plains<lb break="yes"/>or Llanos, at sea, and on both sides of the equator, as will be seen<lb break="yes"/>by reference to my partly published correspondence with Olbers<lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">Cosmos,</hi> vol. i. p. 412.) From my ship-journal I extract the<lb break="yes"/>following observations, extending from the 14th to the 19th of<lb break="yes"/>March, 1803, between north latitude 12° 9&#x2032; and 15° 20&#x2032;, and<lb break="yes"/>chronometrical longitude 104° 27&#x2032; and 105° 46&#x2032; west of Paris.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;On the 17th and 18th of March the Zodiacal Light, the base<lb break="yes" />of which appeared to rest upon the sun, shone with a brightness<lb break="yes" />which I had never seen on any former occasion of the approach<lb break="yes" />of the vernal equinox. The luminous pyramid terminated be-<lb break="no" />tween <hi rendition="#i">Aldebaran</hi> and the <hi rendition="#i" >Pleiades</hi> at an apparent altitude of<lb break="yes"/>39° 5&#x2032; measured above the sea-horizon, which was still sufficiently<lb break="yes" />visible. The vertex was somewhat inclined towards the north;<lb break="yes" />and the direction of the brightest part appeared by the compass to<lb break="yes"/>be west-north-west. What has struck me most during this<lb break="yes"/>voyage, is the great regularity with which, during five or six<lb break="yes"/>nights in succession, the brightness of the Zodiacal Light progres-<lb break="no"/>sively increased and diminished. Its existence was hardly dis-<lb break="no"/>cernible during the first three-quarters of an hour after sunset,<lb break="yes"/>although the darkness was sufficiently great to render visible the<lb break="yes"/>stars of the fourth and fifth magnitude; but after 7<hi rendition="#sup">h</hi> 15<hi rendition="#sup">m</hi> the lumi-<lb break="no"/>nous spindle appeared at once in all its beauty. Its colour was<lb break="yes"/>not white, like that of the milky way, but a reddish yellow, as<lb break="yes"/>Dominique Cassini assures us he had seen it in Europe. Very<lb break="yes"/>small clouds, situated accidentally towards the horizon, reflected<lb break="yes"/>upon the reddish ground a lively blue light. One would almost<lb break="yes"/>suppose he saw a second sunset in the west. About ten o&#x2019;clock<lb break="yes"/>the light entirely disappeared; at midnight I perceived only a<lb break="yes"/>feeble trace of it, although the celestial vault still exhibited the<lb break="yes"/>same degree of transparency. <hi rendition="#i">While the light was very bright in<lb break="yes"/>the west, we constantly perceived in the east</hi> (<hi rendition="#i">and this is beyond<lb break="yes"/>doubt a very striking phenomenon</hi>) <hi rendition="#i">a whitish light, which was<lb break="yes"/>also of a pyramidal form. The latter augmented the brightness<lb break="yes"/>of the sky in a very striking manner. Even the sailors were de-<lb break="no" />lighted with this double light in the west and the east; and I am<lb break="yes"/>inclined to think that this white light in the east was the reflexion<lb break="yes"/>of the real Zodiacal Light at setting. Both also disappeared at the<lb break="yes"/>same time.</hi> Analogous reflexions frequently present themselves in<lb break="yes"/>our climates at sunset, but I should never have imagined that the<lb break="yes"/>brightness of the zodiacal light could be sufficiently strong to<lb break="yes"/>repeat itself by the simple reflexion of the rays. All these lumi-<lb break="no"/>nous appearances were almost the same from the 14th to the 19th<lb break="yes"/>of March. We did not see the Zodiacal Light on the 20th and<lb break="yes"/>21st of March, <hi rendition="#i">although the nights were beautiful in the highest<lb break="yes"/>degree.</hi>&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>These are the words of my ship-journal, containing my obser-<lb break="no" />vations, and also the thoughts which they suggested at the time to<lb break="yes"/>my mind. It was in reference to what I had written down in an<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="18" facs="#f0003"/> unpublished ship-journal on the occasion of a voyage in the<lb break="yes"/>Southern Ocean, about the beginning of the present century, that,<lb break="yes"/>five years previous to the publication of the interesting observa-<lb break="no"/>tions of the Rev. Mr. George Jones, I made the following state-<lb break="no"/>ment in the astronomical part of <hi rendition="#i">Cosmos:</hi>&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;On the whole the variations of the Zodiacal Light appear to<lb break="yes"/>me to depend upon variations inherent in the phenomenon, upon<lb break="yes"/>the greater or less intensity of the luminous processes going on in<lb break="yes"/>the ring. This is proved by my observations in the Southern<lb break="yes"/>Ocean, which indicated an opposite light in the heavens similar to<lb break="yes"/>that seen at sunset.&#x201D; (<hi rendition="#i">Cosmos,</hi> vol. iii. p. 589.)</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I may remark further that I have been surprised at the in-<lb break="no"/>creased brightness of the Zodiacal Light upon ascending to great<lb break="yes" />altitudes. This was observable upon the lofty peaks of the<lb break="yes" />Cordilleras 10,000 or 12,000 feet high; also in Mexico, in Jan-<lb break="no" />uary 1804, at altitudes of only 7000 feet; and from the Cloister<lb break="yes"/>of Mount Cenis, where I remained with Gay Lussac several<lb break="yes"/>nights (in March 1805) at an altitude of 6350 feet, for the purpose<lb break="yes"/>of determining the intensity of the magnetic force during very<lb break="yes"/>intense cold, and ascertaining the quantity of oxygen contained in<lb break="yes"/>the atmosphere. It was, consequently, seen both in tropical and in<lb break="yes"/>temperate latitudes. But the variations in the brightness of the<lb break="yes"/>phenomenon cannot, according to my experience, be accounted for<lb break="yes"/>solely by the constitution of our atmosphere. There remains much<lb break="yes"/>still to be observed relative to this subject.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The following is a copy of the letter to which Baron Humboldt<lb break="yes" />refers:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#c">(<hi rendition="#i">From the Rev. George Jones, U.S.N. to the Editor of the Astronomical<lb break="yes"/>Journal, Cambridge, U.S.</hi>)</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In my recent cruise in the U.S. steam-frigate Mississippi,<lb break="yes" />chiefly in the China and Japan seas, but taking us also around the<lb break="yes"/>globe, I had excellent opportunities for observation of the Zodiacal<lb break="yes"/>Light. This light, you know, appears to the best advantage within<lb break="yes"/>the tropics, where it stretches upward to a great elevation, and is<lb break="yes"/>a remarkable object; but it is also very desirable to observe it in<lb break="yes"/>high latitudes; and in this also I was favoured, as our voyaging<lb break="yes"/>extended from 41° north to 53° south latitude; and in some in-<lb break="no"/>stances our transitions, for weeks together, were very rapid, thus<lb break="yes"/>giving me opportunities for observing whether any parallax could<lb break="yes"/>be made or not.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;I was also fortunate enough to be twice near the latitude of<lb break="yes"/>23° 28&#x2032; north, when the sun was at the opposite solstice, in which<lb break="yes"/>position the observer has the ecliptic, at midnight, at right angles<lb break="yes"/>with his horizon, and bearing east and west. Whether the latter<lb break="yes"/>circumstance affected the result or not I cannot say; but I then<lb break="yes"/>had the extraordinary spectacle of the Zodiacal Light, simul-<lb break="no"/>taneously at both east and west horizons, from 11 to 1 o&#x2019;clock, for<lb break="yes"/>several nights in succession.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;In the first part of our cruise my observations were of a<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="19" facs="#f0004"/> desultory character; but I soon began to see the necessity of great<lb break="yes"/>precision, and accordingly constructed star-charts from a celestial<lb break="yes"/>globe (a small but excellent one) that happened to be on board,<lb break="yes"/>which charts I afterwards had cut in wood at Canton; and thus I<lb break="yes"/>was furnished with materials for accurately recording all the<lb break="yes"/>changes of this phenomenon, not only in successive nights, but<lb break="yes"/>also in the successive hours of the same night. My rule was, to<lb break="yes"/>draw on my charts the boundaries of the Zodiacal Light as ex-<lb break="no"/>hibited among the stars, with such annotations as the case re-<lb break="no"/>quired; then, again, do the same after an interval of an hour or<lb break="yes"/>half-hour; and so to continue, generally as long as the boundaries<lb break="yes"/>could be made out reliably; then, if the morning admitted it, to<lb break="yes"/>resume observations at the earliest possible hour, and so to proceed<lb break="yes"/>until the dawn. I have thus, in many instances, observations for<lb break="yes"/>every hour of the night.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;At an early period I began to query whether the moon, when<lb break="yes" />near its full, might not give a Zodiacal Light: and at last, when I<lb break="yes"/>had gained more experience in observing, and in the peculiar cha-<lb break="no"/>racter of this light, I was able to get, at different periods, fourteen<lb break="yes"/>reliable observations of what I think must be considered a Zodi-<lb break="no"/>acal Light produced by the moon. I have also two records of a<lb break="yes"/>distinct Zodiacal Light produced by the joint action of the sun and<lb break="yes"/>moon, <hi rendition="#i">i. e.</hi> at the hour when the moon, then near its first quar-<lb break="no"/>tering, was about 65° above the western horizon; the reflexion<lb break="yes"/>from the combined light of the sun and moon being sufficient to<lb break="yes"/>overpower the moonlight proper, and thus to produce a decided<lb break="yes"/>stream of light in the sky within the Zodiacal-Light boundaries.<lb break="yes"/>The latter of these observations was the more remarkable, inas-<lb break="no"/>much as the moon was then <hi rendition="#i">without</hi> the boundary of this joint<lb break="yes"/>reflected light.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;You will excuse my prolixity in stating these varieties of<lb break="yes" />observation, for the conclusion from all the data in my possession<lb break="yes"/>is a startling one. It seems to me that these data can be explained<lb break="yes"/>only by the supposition of a nebulous ring with the earth for its<lb break="yes"/>centre, and lying within the orbit of the moon. This conclusion<lb break="yes"/>seems to evolve itself, &#x2014; 1st, from the simultaneous midnight east<lb break="yes"/>and west observations, which preclude the possibility of a ring<lb break="yes"/>around the sun <hi rendition="#i">within</hi> the earth&#x2019;s orbit; 2dly, from the great<lb break="yes"/>hourly lateral changes (often semi-hourly) in the boundaries of the<lb break="yes"/>Light, caused by the observer&#x2019;s change of place, in that time, as<lb break="yes"/>regards the ecliptic or axis of the Zodiacal Light, which lateral<lb break="yes"/>change in the Light is too great to allow of our considering it at a<lb break="yes"/>distance of 170,000,000 of miles, as its lower end would be, near<lb break="yes"/>dawn, if it is a ring around the sun and beyond the earth&#x2019;s orbit;<lb break="yes"/>and 3dly, from the moon&#x2019;s Zodiacal Light, if real, which I think it<lb break="yes"/>is. That it is a ring, the unbroken continuity of my observations<lb break="yes" />satisfactorily determines. For more than two years, I never failed<lb break="yes"/>to see this Light, evening and morning, when the moon and clouds<lb break="yes"/>did not interfere; and, except one evening, I have continuous<lb break="yes"/>records of this kind.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="20" facs="#f0005"/>
                <p>&#x201C;I could get no parallax; but. on the contrary, as we went<lb break="yes" />south, the boundaries of the Zodiacal Light changed with us to<lb break="yes" />the south among the stars; and so, <hi rendition="#i">vice vers&#x00E2;,</hi> towards the north,<lb break="yes"/>caused, doubtless, by the ring&#x2019;s presenting new portions of its wide<lb break="yes"/>reflecting surface to the sun&#x2019;s light.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">George Jones,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Chaplain U.S. Navy.&#x201D;</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Brooklyn, May</hi> 17, 1855.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 