<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>

<pb n="385" facs="#f0001" />

<dateline><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Berlin, February 3, 1855.</hi></dateline><lb/><p>&#x201C;My Dear and Illustrious Friend: It is now a great number of years since you have been so<lb/>kind as to enrich with your generous contributions the most important institutions&#x2014;the Admiralty,<lb/>the Academy, the Schools of Navigation, and the Libraries&#x2014;of my country. Your immense labours<lb/>on currents and soundings, and the direction of winds at different seasons and in different latitudes,<lb/>have exercised the most beneficent influence on the commerce of nations, by shortening, in a sur-<lb/>prising manner, the passages by sea, and augmenting the security of navigation both in the Atlan-<lb/>tic and the South Sea. The result has been the opening of new paths to navigators, who have<lb/>been penetrated by the correctness of your views, and an increase of the facilities previously deriv-<lb/>ed from the application of steam and the more frequent use of chronometers and of lunar distances.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;My Sovereign, the King of Prussia, sensible of the eminent merit of your laborious
                undertaking,<lb/>and interested in the noble efforts now making by the Government of
                the United States for the<lb/>advancement of the Sciences which are so closely
                allied with the development of the common pros-<lb/>perity, desires to give to M.
                the Lieut. Maury, Superintendent of the National Observatory at<lb/>Washington, a
                mark of his gratitude, by presenting him, through the hands of our Minister,
                M.<lb/>De Geroit (my excellent friend), the medal designed as a reward for
                distinguished works of science.<lb/>Sensible, also, of the affection with which you
                have honoured me for so long a period, the King<lb/>has deemed that he would be
                doing you a further pleasure by adding another medal, that which<lb/>his Majesty had
                struck upon the publication of Cosmos.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;I pray you to accept, my dear and illustrious friend, the renewed assurance of my high and<lb/>most affectionate consideration.</p><lb/><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Your very humble and most devoted servant,<lb/>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#g">THE BARON AL DE HUMBOLDT.</hi>&#x201D;</hi></salute></closer><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
