<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>

<pb n="1" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#b">HUMBOLDT AND AGASSIZ.</hi></head><p>Professor Agassiz may be considered as the<lb/>pupil of the illustrious Humboldt, and his
                    destin-<lb/>ed successor in the realm of natural science.<lb/>For many years
                    there has been a strong and af-<lb/>fectionate connection between them; and if
                    we<lb/>remember right, Agassiz, in early life, was in-<lb/>debted for kindly and
                    opportune assistance in his<lb/>investigations to the generosity of his
                    great<lb/>friend. On the part of each of these men, there<lb/>has always been
                    the most cordial and thorough<lb/>appreciation of the merits of the other.</p><lb/><p>The labors of Agassiz are recognized in the<lb/>Kosmos of Humboldt, in terms which show
                    the<lb/>high estimation placed upon them by the first of<lb/>living
                    philosophers; and Agassiz has never fail-<lb/>ed to express the affectionate
                    veneration which he<lb/>cherishes for the genius, attainments and
                    char-<lb/>acter of the mighty master. The pursuits of<lb/>Agassiz, in this
                    country, have been watched by his<lb/>venerable friend with unceasing interest
                    and hear-<lb/>ty sympathy. Humboldt is now eighty-seven<lb/>years old, but his
                    faculties are still unimpaired,<lb/>and his labors as zealously prosecuted as
                    ever.<lb/>Three years ago we had the pleasure of a conver-<lb/>sation with this
                    extraordinary man. The vivac-<lb/>ity of his manner, and the rapidity of his
                    utter-<lb/>ance betrayed no tokens of age. The liveliness<lb/>of his interest,
                    in all that was passing in the<lb/>world, the richness of his knowledge, and the
                    fine<lb/>humanity that breathed in all he said, made the<lb/>hours passed in his
                    society a memorable episode<lb/>in life.</p><lb/><p>We have lately read a letter written by a dis-<lb/>tinguished literary gentleman, who knew
                    Hum-<lb/>boldt many years ago, and has recently renewed<lb/>his intercourse with
                    him. Time, it appears, has<lb/>had some effect upon his person; but his eye
                    is<lb/>still bright and quick, and he talks even faster<lb/>and more richly than
                    he ever did. His benevo-<lb/>lence and desire to serve everybody seem to
                    in-<lb/>crease with his years. His attentions to his<lb/>friends are incessant;
                    he writes notes, accompa-<lb/>nies them to the studios of artists, points out
                    the<lb/>objects which deserve to be seen; tells them what<lb/>to do, just as
                    John <choice>
                        <sic>Keyon</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Kenyon</corr>
                    </choice>&#x2014;the most genial of<lb/>men&#x2014;does to the stranger in
                    London. He re-<lb/>ceives about four thousand letters a year, and<lb/>answers
                    more than half of them with his own<lb/>hands; he dines daily with the King,
                    sitting from<lb/>three o&#x2019;clock till about six, and sups with him<lb/>at
                    nine. He holds the office of Chamberlain, and<lb/>contrary to the wishes of the
                    King, performs all<lb/>its duties in his turn, standing in the
                    ante-cham-<lb/>ber from six to eight hours a day, many days in<lb/>the year,
                    refusing the indulgence of a chair.<lb/>He rises about seven every morning,
                    looks over<lb/>his letters, breakfasts, answers notes, receives
                    vis-<lb/>itors&#x2014;dines, as already mentioned, with the<lb/>King, returns
                    home and takes a short nap, writes<lb/>letters until supper, and goes to work
                    about half-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>past ten at night, working on till three
                    o&#x2019;clock in<lb/>the morning, and sometimes later, attempting
                    no<lb/>continuous scientific labor, except during these<lb/>hours, when his
                    friends are asleep. &#x201C;And this<lb/>man,&#x201D; adds our friend,
                    &#x201C;will be eighty-seven<lb/>years old on the 14th of this present month
                    (Sep-<lb/>tember); and while, on the one hand, if you were<lb/>to ask the
                    well-dressed people you meet in the<lb/>streets or on the railroad, who is the
                    greatest man<lb/>in Prussia, they would answer unanimously&#x2014;<lb/>Humboldt,
                    I verily believe that, on the other<lb/>hand, nobody who is in the habit of
                    seeing him,<lb/>will doubt that his kindness of heart is more re-<lb/>markable
                    than his genius, philosophy and vast<lb/>knowledge. It is reputation worth
                    having.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>Such is the impression this great and good<lb/>man makes on intelligent travellers.&#x2014;<hi
                        rendition="#i">Boston<lb/>Daily Adv.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
