<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-11-30" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>DUDLEY OBSERVATORY.<lb break="yes"/>&#x201E;From the Albany Argus, Jan. 11.&#x201C;</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A very large assemblage of the friends and patrons<lb break="yes"/>of science met at the hospitable mansion of Mrs.<lb break="yes"/>Dudley, on Friday evening last, to welcome the dis-<lb break="no"/>tinguished astronomer, Dr. B. A. Gould, who has<lb break="yes"/>returned from Europe. The object of his visit was<lb break="yes"/>to procure instruments for the Dudley Observatory,<lb break="yes"/>and to visit and inspect the principal observatories<lb break="yes"/>of England and the Continent. He was received<lb break="yes" />with great kindness and cordiality by the most dis-<lb break="no"/>tinguished astronomers and men of science, who<lb break="yes"/>everywhere manifested a lively interest in the efforts<lb break="yes"/>now making in this city for the advancement of as-<lb break="no"/>tronomical science. He was commissioned to order<lb break="yes"/>a Heliometer, a Meridian Circle, a Transit Instru-<lb break="no"/>ment, and Clock. The three last are to be completed<lb break="yes"/>and delivered in this country by the 1st of August<lb break="yes"/>next, and are to have modifications, additions and<lb break="yes"/>improvements which will render them superior to any<lb break="yes"/>hitherto constructed.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The construction of the heliometer has been con-<lb break="no"/>fided, we are happy to state, to our countrymen,<lb break="yes"/>Messrs. Spencer &#x0026; Eaton, of our own State, who are<lb break="yes"/>about removing their establishment to this city, hav-<lb break="no"/>ing made arrangements for erecting extensive work-<lb break="no"/>shops and for the construction of every description of<lb break="yes"/>astronomical instruments.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Governor Seymour read to the company a long and<lb break="yes"/>interesting letter from Mr. Airey, the Astronomer<lb break="yes"/>Royal of Great Britain, to Mrs. Dudley; and Judge<lb break="yes"/>Parker another from Baron Humboldt, which we are<lb break="yes"/>permitted to give to the public:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <dateline>
                        <hi rendition="#et">
                            <hi rendition="#k">Potsdam,</hi> Nov. 14th, 1855.</hi>
                    </dateline>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#i">To Dr. B. A. Gould</hi>;</salute>
                    <p>&#x2014;The necessity in which I<lb break="yes"/>have found myself of returning to Potsdam has de-<lb break="no"/>prived me, my dear Dr. Gould, of the pleasure of ex-<lb break="no"/>pressing to you how much your last sojourn at Ber-<lb break="no"/>lin has revived the sentiments of affection and high<lb break="yes"/>estimation that we have felt towards you for a long<lb break="yes"/>time. I have wished to address you these few words<lb break="yes"/>of adieu before you return to your native country,<lb break="yes"/>where, from year to year, scientific effort is achiev-<lb break="no"/>ing so much that is worthy of admiration. That<lb break="yes"/>which impresses itself most strongly upon the Eu-<lb break="no"/>ropean mind is that by the side of those who devote<lb break="yes"/>themselves to the culture of the sciences are found<lb break="yes"/>such examples of eminent patriotism and noble liber-<lb break="no"/>ality.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>How could we fail to point out to public gratitude<lb break="yes"/>the generosity of Mrs. Dudley, of Albany, who has<lb break="yes"/>contributed so liberally to the erection of a noble ob-<lb break="no"/>servatory for astronomy, and who has endowed it<lb break="yes"/>with a grand heliometer. Attached as I am by my<lb break="yes"/>feeble efforts in astronomical geography to the study<lb break="yes"/>of the science which you cultivate with so much suc-<lb break="no"/>cess, I beg of you, my dear sir, to offer to that esti-<lb break="no"/>mable lady the homage of my sentiments of grati-<lb break="no"/>tude, and assure her how much I applaud the happy<lb break="yes"/>idea of attaching the name and memory of the bene-<lb break="no"/>factress to an institution for the progress of the sci-<lb break="no"/>ences.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>My health, since your departure, has not been so<lb break="yes"/>good, without, however, interfering with my duties.<lb break="yes"/>Please accept yourself my affectionate regards, and<lb break="yes"/>transmit them to our mutual friends, Dr. Bache and<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Peters.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>What a happiness was the return of Dr. Kane, af-<lb break="no"/>ter so many sufferings and noble achievements?</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <closer>
                        <salute>
                            <hi rendition="#et">
                                <hi rendition="#k">Alexander Humboldt.</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </salute>
                    </closer>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 