<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#b">HUMBOLDT AND AGASSIZ.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <head>The following communication, we presume,<lb break="yes"/>by the signature, from Professor Felton, is of<lb break="yes"/>the deepest interest. We find it in the Boston<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Daily Advertiser:</hi>
                    </head>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Professor Agassiz may be considered as the<lb break="yes"/>pupil of the illustrious Humboldt, and his des-<lb break="no"/>tined successor in the realm of natural science.<lb break="yes"/>For many years, there has been a strong and<lb break="yes"/>affectionate connection between them; and if<lb break="yes"/>we remember right, Agassiz, in early life, was<lb break="yes"/>indebted for kindly and opportune assistance<lb break="yes" />in his investigations to the generosity of his<lb break="yes"/>great friend. On the part of each of these men,<lb break="yes"/>there has always been the most cordial and<lb break="yes"/>thorough appreciation of the merits of the other.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The labors of Agassiz are recognized in the<lb break="yes"/>Kosmos of Humboldt, in terms which show the<lb break="yes"/>high estimation placed upon them by the first<lb break="yes"/>of living philosophers; and Agassiz has never<lb break="yes"/>failed to express the affectionate veneration<lb break="yes"/>which he cherishes for the genius, attainments,<lb break="yes"/>and character, of the mighty master. The pur-<lb break="no" />suits of Agassiz in this country have been<lb break="yes"/>watched by his venerable friend with unceas-<lb break="no"/>ing interest and hearty sympathy. Humboldt<lb break="yes"/>is now eighty-seven years old, but his faculti@<lb break="yes"/>are still unimpaired, and his labors as zealously<lb break="yes"/>prosecuted as ever. Three years ago, we had<lb break="yes"/>the pleasure of a conversation with this extra-<lb break="no"/>ordinary man. The vivacity of his manner,<lb break="yes" />and the rapidity of his utterance, betrayed no<lb break="yes"/>tokens of age. The liveliness of his interest<lb break="yes"/>in all that was passing in the world, the rich-<lb break="no"/>ness of his knowledge, and the fine humanity<lb break="yes"/>that breathed in all he said, made the hours<lb break="yes"/>passed in his society a memorable episode in life.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We have lately read a letter written by a dis-<lb break="no"/>tinguished literary gentleman, who knew Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt many years ago, and has recently renew-<lb break="no"/>ed his intercourse with him. Time, it appears,<lb break="yes"/>has had some effect upon his person; but his<lb break="yes"/>eye is still bright and quick, and he talks even<lb break="yes"/>faster and more richly than he ever did. His<lb break="yes" />benevolence and desire to serve everybody<lb break="yes"/>seem to increase with his years. His attentions<lb break="yes"/>to his friends are incessant; he writes notes,<lb break="yes"/>accompanies them to the studios of artists,<lb break="yes"/>points out the objects which deserve to be seen,<lb break="yes"/>tells them what to do, just as John Kenyon&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>the most genial of men&#x2014;does to the stranger<lb break="yes"/>in London. He receives about four thousand<lb break="yes"/>letters a year, and answers more than half of<lb break="yes"/>them with his own hand; he dines daily with<lb break="yes" />the King, sitting from three o&#x2019;clock till about<lb break="yes" />six, and sups with him at nine. He holds the<lb break="yes"/>office of Chamberlain; and, contrary to the<lb break="yes"/>wishes of the King, performs all its duties in<lb break="yes"/>his turn, standing in the ante-chamber from<lb break="yes"/>six to eight hours a day, many day@ in the year,<lb break="yes"/>refusing the indulgence of a chair. He rises<lb break="yes"/>about seven every morning, looks over his let-<lb break="no"/>ters, breakfasts, answers notes, receives visit-<lb break="no"/>ers&#x2014;dines, as already mentioned, with the<lb break="yes"/>King&#x2014;returns home, and takes a short nap,<lb break="yes"/>writes letters until supper, and goes to work<lb break="yes"/>about half past ten at night, working on till<lb break="yes"/>three o&#x2019;clock in the morning, and sometimes<lb break="yes"/>later, attempting no continuous scientific labor,<lb break="yes"/>except during these hours, when his friends are<lb break="yes"/>asleep. &#x201C;And this man,&#x201D; adds our friend,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;will be eighty-seven years old on the 14th of<lb break="yes"/>this present month, (September;) and while,<lb break="yes" />on the one hand, if you were to ask the well-<lb break="no"/>dressed people you meet in the streets or on<lb break="yes"/>the railroad, who is the greatest man in Prus-<lb break="no"/>sia, they would answer unanimously&#x2014;Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt. I verily believe that, on the other hand,<lb break="yes"/>nobody who is in the habit of seeing him will<lb break="yes"/>doubt that his kindness of heart is more re-<lb break="no"/>markable than his genius, philosophy, and vast<lb break="yes"/>knowledge. It is reputation worth having.&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Such is the impression this great and good<lb break="yes"/>man makes on intelligent travellers.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>We have given the above little sketch by<lb break="yes"/>way of introduction to an extract from a letter<lb break="yes"/>of his to Professor Agassiz, which, at the ex-<lb break="no"/>press desire of Humboldt, we translate and<lb break="yes"/>publish. It is on a subject of general scientific<lb break="yes"/>interest; and as the time for the publication<lb break="yes"/>of the first volume of the great work of Agas-<lb break="no"/>siz draws near, it will not be uninteresting to<lb break="yes"/>the subscribers and to the public, to know the<lb break="yes"/>feelings with which so illustrious a philosopher<lb break="yes"/>regards it. The extract is as follows. It is<lb break="yes" />dated Berlin, September 1, 18@:</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The visit of our distinguished and excellent<lb break="yes"/>friend, Mr. George Ticknor, to this city, where<lb break="yes"/>he resided in his youth, and where he left so<lb break="yes"/>many honorable remembrances, has made<lb break="yes"/>known to me a fact, which has greatly troubled<lb break="yes"/>me. I learn that by an unfortunate occurrence<lb break="yes"/>of circumstances, undoubtedly accidental, you,<lb break="yes"/>my dear Agassia, have never received the letter<lb break="yes"/>of mine, which expressed very strongly the joy<lb break="yes"/>I have shared with all the sincere lover@ of<lb break="yes" />science, on the subject of your beantiful and<lb break="yes"/>important enterprise, the Contributions to the<lb break="yes"/>Natural History of the United States.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Doubtless you must have been surprised by<lb break="yes"/>my long silence, considering the ties of inti-<lb break="no"/>mato affection which have bound us together<lb break="yes"/>since your first residence in Paris, as well as<lb break="yes"/>the high admiration I have never ceased to<lb break="yes"/>entertain for the great and solid labors, for<lb break="yes"/>which we are indebted to your sagacious genius<lb break="yes"/>and your incomparable intellectual energy. In-<lb break="no"/>terested, like you, in the progress made in that<lb break="yes"/>part of the world, where the cultivation of the<lb break="yes"/>sciences is making such rapid strides, I approve,<lb break="yes"/>above all the generality of conceptions, where<lb break="yes"/>is the basis of the plan you have traced out.<lb break="yes"/>I admire that long series of physiological in-<lb break="no"/>vestigations, commencing with the embryology<lb break="yes" />of organisms, called simple and inferior, and<lb break="yes"/>ascending by degrees to the organisms which<lb break="yes"/>are more complicated. I admire that constant<lb break="yes"/>attention to the comparison of the types belong-<lb break="no"/>ing to the present condition of our planet, and<lb break="yes"/>the types found only in a fossil state, and which<lb break="yes"/>abound in the immense @ between the shores<lb break="yes" />opposite to Europe and Northern Asia.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The generous interest displayed in the Uni-<lb break="no"/>ted States, when your vast enterprise was an-<lb break="no"/>nounced, my excellent friend, has given a very<lb break="yes"/>flattering proof of the ever-increasing intellect-<lb break="no"/>ual interest, and of the honorable confidence<lb break="yes"/>manifested for talent and a noble character. I<lb break="yes"/>am charged by the King, who feels the impor-<lb break="no"/>tan@ of your former labors, and retains for<lb break="yes" />you the affectionate esteem which he showed<lb break="yes"/>for you, personally, when he saw you among<lb break="yes"/>your collections, to place his name at the head<lb break="yes"/>of the list of your numerous subscribers. He<lb break="yes"/>hopes that an excursion across the <hi rendition="#i">Atlantic<lb break="yes"/>Va@y</hi> may some day conduct you, who have<lb break="yes"/>boldly sealed the lofty summits of the Alps, to<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">historic hill</hi> of Sans Sou@. I have it much<lb break="yes"/>at heart that you should allow an extract of<lb break="yes"/>this not very legible letter to be published,<lb break="yes"/>since it contains the sincere proof of the lively<lb break="yes"/>satis@ction with which I have welcomed your<lb break="yes" />great and useful enterprise.&#x201D; <hi rendition="#et">F.</hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 