<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">[The Darien Canal]</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:21</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VII.112</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1856-The_Darien_Canal-5</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1856-The_Darien_Canal-1-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-The_Darien_Canal-2.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-The_Darien_Canal-3.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-The_Darien_Canal-4.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-The_Darien_Canal-5.xml" type="self"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">[The Darien Canal]</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1859</date>
          <pubPlace>New York City, New York</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: Frederick M. Kelley, &lt;i&gt;The Union of the Oceans by Ship-Canal without Locks, via the Atrato Valley&lt;/i&gt;, New York: Harper &amp;amp; Brothers 1859, S. 88–89.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="88" facs="#f0001"/>
            <lb/>
            <opener><dateline><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Berlin, January 27, 1856.</hi></dateline>
            <lb/>
            <salute><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Frederick M. Kelley,
                    Esq.</hi></hi>
            <lb/>
            &#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Sir,</hi></salute></opener>
            <p>&#x2014;It is with the deepest satisfaction that I made myself acquainted,<lb/>during
                your short stay in Berlin, with the sound and extensive series of<lb/>measurements
                and levels which, by your direction, have been executed<lb/>since the beginning of
                January, 1855, upon the course of the great Rio<lb/>Atrato and its affluents on the
                West, by an able engineer, Mr. William Ken-<lb/>nish. This survey and those
                previously undertaken by your orders, and to<lb/>which my learned friend, Mr.
                Alexander Bache, Superintendent of the Coast<lb/>Survey of the United States, had
                already drawn my attention, are so much<lb/>the more deserving of regard, since you
                purpose to have examined with the<lb/>same precision the pass from the port of
                Cupica to the Rio Na&#x00EE;pi (Napipi),<lb/>and the points situated above the mouth
                of the Truando, which are all very<lb/>important in the solution of the vast problem
                of an oceanic canal.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>&#x201C;The great number of charts and sections on a large scale in your
                pos-<lb/>session furnish all the elements necessary for judging of the possibility
                of<lb/>establishing a communication between the two oceans by the mouths of
                the<lb/>Atrato, the Rio Truando, and a canal leading to the Pacific Ocean.
                It<lb/>was on account of his not having made so thorough an examination of
                the<lb/>mountainous country between the Gulf of San Miguel and Caledonia
                Bay<lb/>that Mr. Lionel Gisborne&#x2019;s plan of 1852 could not be carried out. The
                ig-<lb/>norance he was in as to the localities, and the absence of measurements
                of<lb/>altitude, led to the unfortunate issue of the courageous expedition of
                Lieu-<lb/>tenant Isaac Strain.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>&#x201C;The great object to be attained is, in my opinion, a canal which
                would<lb/>unite the two oceans without locks and without tunnels. When the
                plans<lb/>and sections can be placed before the public, a free and open discussion
                will<lb/>elucidate the advantages and disadvantages of each locality, and the
                execu-<lb/>tion of this important work, which interests the civilized nations of the
                two<lb/>continents, will be intrusted to engineers who have successfully
                distinguish-<lb/>ed themselves in similar enterprises. The Junction Company will
                find sub-<lb/>scribers among those governments and citizens who, yielding to a noble
                im-<lb/>pulse, will take pride in the idea of having contributed toward the
                execution<lb/>of a work worthy of the intellectual progress of the nineteenth
                century.<lb/>More than fifty years ago I earnestly expressed the same opinion, and
                I<lb/>have incessantly labored in the propagation of those geographical
                views,<lb/>which tend to prove the practicability of establishing commercial
                communi-<lb/>cations, either by canals (with or without either stop-gates or locks)
                or by<lb/>means of railroads uniting opposite coasts and rivers flowing in
                contrary<lb/>directions.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>&#x201C;I was the means of obtaining through General Bolivar the exact geo-<lb/>desic
                survey of the Isthmus of Panama; and I was the first, from informa-<lb/>tion found
                in the Archives of the Viceroyalty of Mexico, to lay down in<lb/>my Mexican Atlas
                the course of the two rivers, the Huasacualco and the<lb/><pb n="89" facs="#f0002"/>
                Chimalapa. I pointed out the proximity of the almost unknown port of<lb/>Cupica to
                the sources of the Rio Na&#x00EE;pi, and to the waters of the Atrato, and<lb/>also
                the existence, with which Europe was unacquainted, of a very small<lb/>navigable
                canal &#x2018;excavated&#x2019; in 1788, under the superintendence of a
                monk,<lb/>the Priest of Novita, by the Indians of his parish, in order to unite the
                wa-<lb/>ters of the Rio de la Raspadura, an affluent of the Rio de Quito
                (Quibdo),<lb/>to the waters of the Rio de San Juan de Chirambira.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>&#x201C;I think nothing more dangerous to the extension of commerce and to<lb/>the
                freedom of international relations than to inspire an aversion to all fu-<lb/>ture
                investigation by an absolute and imperious declaration that all hope of<lb/>an
                oceanic canal must now be abandoned. I expressly described in
                my<lb/>&#x2018;Political Essay on New Spain&#x2019; (compare vol. i., p. 202-248,
                with vol. ii.,<lb/>p. 95-145, 2d edition) the immense work of cutting through the
                mountains<lb/>an open channel for the Desague Huehuetoca, which was executed by
                the<lb/>Spanish government at the beginning of the seventeenth century, and
                I<lb/>have too much faith in the powerful means afforded by the present state
                of<lb/>civilization to be yet discouraged.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>&#x201C;The important communications for which I am indebted to the courtesy<lb/>of
                Colonel Augustus Codazzi and to the exceeding kindness of M. Pastor<lb/>Ospina,
                Minister of the Interior at Bogota, have made me fully aware that<lb/>the line from
                Cupica to the Rio Na&#x00EE;pi presents a series of elevations; in di-<lb/>recting
                this passage to be leveled you will, therefore, be rendering a farther<lb/>service
                to geography. Captain Robert Fitzroy, R.N., whose name is justly<lb/>renowned among
                navigators, in his &#x2018;Memoir on the Isthmus of Central<lb/>America,&#x2019;
                says: &#x2018;Of all the comparatively well-known routes, it has been<lb/>shown that
                the Atrato and Cupica line seems the most suitable for a canal,<lb/>and the Panama
                route for a railway. The officer who recently surveyed<lb/>Cupica (Lieutenant Wood,
                R.N.) states, with respect to the land between it<lb/>and the Na&#x00EE;pi, that he
                set out one morning from Cupica at eight o&#x2019;clock,<lb/>walked with native
                guides to the Na&#x00EE;pi, bathed in the stream, and reached<lb/>his ship (the
                Pandora) at noon.&#x2019; The most elevated ground was, in his<lb/>judgment, 300-400
                feet.&#x2014;Journal of the Royal Geographical Society, vol.<lb/>xx., 1850, part
                ii., p. 178.</p>
            <lb/>
            <closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Receive, my dear sir,
                        etc.,</hi></salute><lb/><signed><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;(Signed), <hi rendition="#k">Alexander von
                        Humboldt.</hi>&#x201D;</hi></signed></closer>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>

    </text>
</TEI>
