<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="477" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#b">HUMBOLDT AND AGASSIZ.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We claim Pref. Agasiz as an American <hi rendition="#i">savan.</hi> If there were no oth-<lb break="no"/>er title for that claim, we have his baptism in the alluvium of the North<lb break="yes"/>American Continent, rolled down by the floods of the Father of Waters,<lb break="yes"/>which many or our readers will remember, on the occasion of his visit<lb break="yes"/>here three years since, when he so pertinaciously pursued the gar-fish<lb break="yes"/>and the alligator through the mud of our lakes and bayous. But the vast<lb break="yes"/>light which he has poured upon the scientific world by his labors, not<lb break="yes"/>only upon the land, but upon the coral homes of the ocean of this conti-<lb break="no" />nent, entitle him eminently to that name, and the great work upon the<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Natural History of the United States,&#x201D; which he is now preparing for<lb break="yes"/>publication, will be but another evidence of its truth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Prof. Agassiz may be considered as the pupil of the illustrious Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt, and his destined successor in the realms of science, adding thus<lb break="yes"/>another proof of the westward march of empire. For many years there<lb break="yes"/>has been a strong and affectionate connection between them, and it has<lb break="yes"/>been stated that in early life Agassiz was indebted for kindly and oppor-<lb break="no"/>tune assistance to the generosity of his great friend. The labors of Agas-<lb break="no"/>siz are recognized in the &#x201C;Cosmos&#x201D; of Humboldt in terms that show the<lb break="yes"/>high estimation placed upon them by the first of living philosophers; and<lb break="yes"/>Agassiz has never failed to express the veneration which he cherishes<lb break="yes"/>for the genius and attainment of the mighty master. The pursuits of<lb break="yes"/>Agassiz in this country have been watched with unceasing interest and<lb break="yes"/>hearty sympathy. The following letter, dated Berlin, Sept. 1, of this<lb break="yes"/>year, which was published in the Boston &#x201C;Advertiser,&#x201D; is an evidence<lb break="yes"/>of this, and was made public, as will be seen, at the express desire of<lb break="yes"/>Baron Humboldt:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The visit of our distinguished and excellent friend, Mr. Geo. Ticknor,<lb break="yes"/>to this city, where he lelt so many honorable remembrances, has made<lb break="yes"/>known to me a fact, which has greatly troubled me. I learn that, by<lb break="yes"/>an unfortunate concurrence of circumstances, undoubtedly accidental,<lb break="yes"/>you, my dear Agassiz, have never received the letter of mine, which ex-<lb break="no"/>pressed very strongly the joy I have shared with all the sincere lovers of<lb break="yes"/>science, on the subject of your beautiful and important enterprise, the<lb break="yes" />&#x201C;Contributions to the Natural History of the United States.&#x201D; Doubtless,<lb break="yes"/>you must have been surprised by my long silence, considering the ties of<lb break="yes"/>intimate affection which have bound us together since your first residence<lb break="yes"/>in Paris, as well as the high admiration I have never ceased to entertain<lb break="yes"/>for the great and solid labors, for which we are indebted to your saga-<lb break="no"/>cious genius and your incomparable intellectual energy. Interested, like<lb break="yes"/>you, in the progress made in that of the world, where&#x2019; the cultivation of<lb break="yes"/>the sciences is making such rapid strides, I approve, above all, the gene-<lb break="no"/>rality of conceptions, which is the basis of the plan you have traced out.<lb break="yes"/>I admire that long series of physiological investigations, commencing<lb break="yes"/>with the embryology of organisms called simple and inferior, and as-<lb break="no"/>cending by degrees to the organisms which are more complicated; I ad-<lb break="no"/>mire that constant attention to the comparison of the types belonging to<lb break="yes"/>the present condition of our planet, and the types found only in a fossil<lb break="yes"/>state, and which abound in the immense area between the shores oppo-<lb break="no"/>site to Europe and Northern Asia. The generous interest diplayed in the<lb break="yes"/>United States, when your vast enterprise was announced, my excellent<lb break="yes"/>friend, has given a very flattering proof of the ever increasing intellectual<lb break="yes"/>interest, and of the honorable confidence manifested for talent and a no-<lb break="no" />ble character. I am charged by the King, who feels the importance of<lb break="yes"/>your former labors, and retains for you the affectionate esteem which he<lb break="yes"/>showed for you personally, when he saw you among your collections, to<lb break="yes"/>place his name at the head of the list of your numerous subscribers. He<lb break="yes"/>hopes that an excursion across the Atlantic Valley may some day conduct<lb break="yes"/>you, who have boldly scaled the lofty summits of the Alps, to the histo-<lb break="no"/>ric hill of Sans Souci. I have it much at heart that you should allow an<lb break="yes"/>extract of this not very legible letter to be published, since it contains the<lb break="yes"/>sincere proof of the lively satisfaction with which I have welcomed your<lb break="yes"/>great and useful enterprise. <hi rendition="#et" >N. O. Picayune.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 