<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="4" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">MRS. IDA PFEIFFER.</hi></head><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<p>Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer, the celebrated lady traveller, who<lb/>went twice round the world, is now again in London, on<lb/>her way to Madagascar, into the interior of which she<lb/>wishes to penetrate and explore. Her most recent travels<lb/>extended over Germany, but she does not find in the<lb/>civilised parts of the world the same interest as in the less<lb/>cultivated regions. There, in the bosom of nature, un-<lb/>disturbed by the presence of man, she delights most.</p><lb/><p>On this her last visit to the European continent, some of<lb/>the most distinguished men came forward unsolicited to<lb/>do her honour. In Berlin and Amsterdam, the Society of<lb/>Natural History conferred upon her their respective<lb/>diplomas, and elected her an honorary member. The King<lb/>of Prussia graciously invited her to his residence at<lb/>Potsdam, and presented her with the golden medal of the<lb/>Humboldt order for arts and sciences. The greatest living<lb/>naturalist and philosopher, Alexander von Humboldt,<lb/>exhibited in her favour the warmest friendship and<lb/>admiration. As a token of the affectionate interest he<lb/>took in her welfare, he presented her on parting with an<lb/>autograph letter, of which the following is a literal<lb/>translation:&#x2014;</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;All those who, in different regions of the earth, pre-<lb/>serve a remembrance of my name
                    and affection for my<lb/>works, I earnestly beg to receive, with friendly
                    interest,<lb/>and to aid with their counsels, the bearer of these
                    lines,<lb/>Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer, celebrated not only for the noble con-<lb/>stancy
                    that, amidst so many dangers and privations, led<lb/>her twice round the globe,
                    but above all, for the amiable<lb/>simplicity and modesty pervading her works,
                    the truthful-<lb/>ness and philanthropy of her judgment, as well as
                    the<lb/>independence and at the same time the delicacy of her<lb/>sentiments.
                    Enjoying the confidence and friendship of this<lb/>respectable lady, I blame her
                    for though I cannot refrain from<lb/>admiring, that indomitable energy of
                    character which she<lb/>displayed wherever called&#x2014;I should say, impelled
                    by an<lb/>unconquerable passion of exploring nature and the habits<lb/>of the
                    various human races. As the oldest living traveller,<lb/>I feel a desire to
                    offer to Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer this slender<lb/>proof of my high and respectful
                    esteem. (Signed) <hi rendition="#k">Alex<lb/>ander Humboldt.</hi> Potsdam City
                    Castle, June 8, 1856.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer might justly to be proud of so very<lb/>flattering a testimony from one of the
                    most eminent men<lb/>living; but her modesty is equal to her good sense,
                    tact,<lb/>patience, perseverance, power of endurance, and simple<lb/>habits.</p><lb/><p>A special Providence seems to have watched over this<lb/>extraordinary woman. She has been
                    preserved amid un-<lb/>told dangers and perils of sea and land. That a
                    delicate<lb/>woman, unarmed, unknown and poor, with no prestige
                    of<lb/>aristocratic descent, without the magic of an ample<lb/>exchequer, should
                    twice have girded the world,<lb/>unharmed and unscathed, and accomplish, unaided
                    and<lb/>single, what the most reckless man who scaled the bloody<lb/>heights of
                    the Alma might have shrunk from appalled,<lb/>seems almost incredible. Is this
                    not an abundant testi-<lb/>mony, then, that deadly weapons are absolutely
                    unneces-<lb/>sary for protection? And may not nations learn from this<lb/>fact,
                    tested under every longitude and latitude of the earth,<lb/>that if they were to
                    confide in the protecting power of Pro-<lb/>vidence, and not in gunpowder, there
                    would be an end<lb/>of maintaining standing armies and men trained to the
                    use<lb/>of arms, which, perhaps, more than any other cause,<lb/>provoke wars and
                    bloody conflicts amongst mankind?</p><lb/><p>An irresistible impulse impels this wonderful lady to<lb/>wander over God&#x2019;s vast and
                    beautiful world, and to visit<lb/>the great variety of races of men. Not the
                    least wonder-<lb/>ful part of her adventures is the way in which she
                    commu-<lb/>nicates with the various peoples, some of whom she found<lb/>in the
                    least developed stage of nature. For she is assisted<lb/>by an extraordinary
                    power of expressing her wants and<lb/>thoughts by mimicry&#x2014;a kind of
                    natural language of<lb/>universal interpretation.</p><lb/><p>It might be imagined that, in order to perform such<lb/>stupendous travels, Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer must be in possession<lb/>of a large fortune, whereas her only pecuniary resources<lb/>are vested in the produce of her literary works. When in<lb/>this way a modest sum has accumulated in the bands of<lb/>her publishers, she again sets out to visit some unexplored<lb/>part of the world, to return when her means are exhausted</p><lb/><p>Several editions of her works, translated into the En-<lb/>glish language, have found extensive public favour in<lb/>England and America. Her last travel round the world,<lb/>by far the most interesting of her literary productions, has<lb/>been edited by Messrs. Orme and Longmans.</p><lb/><p>She is now waiting to meet with a suitable vessel to<lb/>carry her to the Cape of Good Hope or to
                    the Mauritius,<lb/>and thence to Madagascar. May her wishes be
                    fulfilled,<lb/>and may the same good fortune, which hitherto accom-<lb/>panied
                    her, follow her in her future travels, and in due<lb/>time procure us again the
                    pleasure of another of her very<lb/>interesting and instructive descriptions of
                    foreign countries<lb/>and peoples.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
