<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="15" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head>MADAME IDA PFEIFFER.</head><lb/><p>This clever and courageous lady, who has run all round<lb/>the globe more than once, for her own and the public en-<lb/>tertainment, is now in London, and is immediately going<lb/>to Madagascar. She has lately received much honour<lb/>among Continental <hi rendition="#i">savans</hi>. The natural history societies<lb/>of Berlin and Amsterdam elected her as an honorary<lb/>member. She was invited by the King of Prussia to<lb/>Potsdam, presented with the Humboldt gold medal of arts<lb/>and sciences, and with a token of esteem not less gratify-<lb/>ing, a letter, of which we give a translation, from Alex-<lb/>ander von Humboldt himself:&#x2014;</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;All those who, in different regions of the earth pre-<lb/>serve a remembrance of my name
                    and affection for my<lb/>works, I ardently beg to receive with friendly
                    interest<lb/>and to aid with their counsels the bearer of these lines.<lb/>Mrs.
                    Ida Pfeiffer, who is celebrated not only for the noble<lb/>constancy that,
                    amidst so many dangers and privations,<lb/>has led her twice round the globe,
                    but above all for the<lb/>amiable simplicity and modesty which pervade her
                    works,<lb/>for her truthfulness and philanthropy, for the correctness<lb/>of her
                    judgments, as well as for the independence, and at<lb/>the same time the
                    delicacy of her sentiments. Enjoying<lb/>the confidence and friendship of this
                    estimable lady, I<lb/>only blame her&#x2014;though I cannot refrain from
    admiring<lb/><choice><sic>t</sic><corr type="editorial"> </corr></choice>&#x2014;for that indomitable energy of character which she<lb/>has
                    displayed, wherever she has been called, or, I should<lb/>rather say, has been
                    impelled, by an unconquerable pas-<lb/>sion for exploring nature and the habits
                    of the various<lb/>human races. As the oldest living traveller, I felt a
                    desire<lb/>to offer to Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer this slender proof of my high<lb/>and
                    respectful esteem.</p><lb/><closer><salute>(Signed) &#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt</hi>.</salute></closer><lb/><dateline>Potsdam, June 8, 1856.&#x201D;</dateline></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
