<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="826" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The Franklin Expedition.</hi>
                </head>
                <p>&#x2014;On Tuesday evening a meeting was<lb break="yes"/>held at the London Mechanies&#x2019; Institution for the purpose of discussing<lb break="yes"/>the desirability of instituting a further search for traces of Sir John<lb break="yes"/>Franklin and his comrades. Dr King moved the first resolution,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;That the efforts hitherto made to discover traces of the Franklin<lb break="yes"/>expedition having been wholly unsuccessful, a future search is im-<lb break="no"/>peratively required.&#x201D; Dr King explained at some length his project<lb break="yes"/>for a combined expedition by sea and land to the mouth of the Great<lb break="yes"/>Fish River, and expressed his conviction that if such an undertaking<lb break="yes"/>were confided to himself and Lieut. Bedford Pim, they would bring<lb break="yes"/>to light some positive evidence of the fate of Franklin and his com-<lb break="no" />panions. Dr King, in conclusion, read a letter from Baron Von<lb break="yes" />Humboldt to Lieut. Pim, of which the following is an extract: &#x201C;How<lb break="yes"/>could you for an instant doubt the satisfaction with which here in<lb break="yes"/>Germany we receive the intelligence, though somewhat vague, of a<lb break="yes"/>memorial presented to Lord Palmerston, endorsed by so many<lb break="yes"/>illustrious names, announcing the hope of a new expedition directed<lb break="yes"/>towards a point already determined upon. You should have seen the<lb break="yes"/>lively and affecting interest excited both at Court and in the public<lb break="yes"/>mind by your noble and courageous Siberian undertakings. After so<lb break="yes"/>many generous sacrifices made by two nations of the same race already<lb break="yes"/>in possession of objects pertaining to the shipwrecked mariners, and<lb break="yes"/>having reduced the results to such narrow limits, how can you avoid<lb break="yes"/>a last perilous effort (great undertakings are ever somewhat hazardous)<lb break="yes"/>for the solution of this sad enigma? Geography and the physical<lb break="yes" />knowledge of our globe have been advanced by what has been already<lb break="yes"/>gained; but there is a moral end to be attained, and in this under-<lb break="no"/>taking there is a sentimental interest excited by the consanguinity of<lb break="yes"/>those you seek to rescue, ascending to a source above all science&#x2014;an<lb break="yes"/>interest which should be cherished in the breast of a nation&#x2014;a senti-<lb break="no"/>ment at once ennobling and consolatory. P.S. What can you<lb break="yes"/>anticipate from my support? You will smile at my &#x2018;moral end,&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;at the &#x2018;sentiment I would nourish in the breast of the people,&#x2019;&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>at my German sensibility; but I have still force enough to defend<lb break="yes"/>myself, and you are at liberty to use these few lines in any way you<lb break="yes"/>may find useful.&#x201D; Lieut. Pim seconded the resolution, and detailed the<lb break="yes"/>route by which he proposed to reach Dr King. Difficulties, no doubt,<lb break="yes" />would have to be encountered; but long experience in the Polar Seas<lb break="yes"/>had considerably lessened the danger of the search; and his own<lb break="yes"/>opinion was that it was only necessary to approach the Esquimaux<lb break="yes"/>with a little circumspection, to extract from them the striking story<lb break="yes"/>of our countrymen&#x2019;s suffering, and to induce them to tell at what<lb break="yes"/>village the survivors would be found. The resolution was carried<lb break="yes"/>unanimously; and after a short discussion a motion was carried<lb break="yes"/>approving of the plan suggested.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 