<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><p><hi rendition="#k">Humboldt and the Americans</hi>.&#x2014;Baron von Hum-<lb/>boldt has caused the following article to be inserted in<lb/>the Berlin<hi rendition="#i">Spenersche Zeitung</hi>:&#x2014;&#x201C;Under the title of<lb/>&#x2018;Essai Politique sur l&#x2019;Isle de Cuba,&#x2019; published in Paris in<lb/>1826, I collected together all that the large edition of<lb/>my &#x2018;Voyage aux Région Equinoxiales du Nou-<lb/>veau Continent&#x2019; contained upon the state of agri-<lb/>culture and slavery in the Antilles. There ap-<lb/>peared at the same time an English and a<lb/>Spanish translation of this work, the latter<lb/>entitled &#x2018;Ensayo Politico sobre la Isla de Cuba,&#x2019;<lb/>neither of which omitted any of the frank and open<lb/>remarks which feelings of humanity had inspired. But<lb/>there appears just now, strangely enough, translated<lb/>from the Spanish translation, and not from the<lb/>French original, and published by Derby and Jack-<lb/>son in New York, an octavo volume of 400 pages,<lb/>under the title of &#x2018;The Island of Cuba,&#x2019; by<lb/>Alexander Humboldt; with notes and a preliminary<lb/>essay, by J. S. Thrasher. The translator, who<lb/>has lived a long time on that beautiful island,<lb/>has enriched my work by more recent data on the<lb/>subject of the numerical standing of the population,<lb/>of the cultivation of the soil, and the state of trade,<lb/>and, generally speaking, exhibited a charitable mode-<lb/>ration in his discussion of conflicting opinions. I owe it,<lb/>however, to a moral feeling, that is now as lively in me<lb/>as it was in 1826, publicly to complain that in a work<lb/>which bears my name the entire seventh chapter of<lb/>the Spanish translation, with which my<hi rendition="#i">essai poli-<lb/>tique</hi> ended, has been arbitrarily emitted. To this<lb/>very portion of my work I attach greater importance<lb/>than to any astronomical observations, experiments of<lb/>magnetic intensity, or statistical statements. &#x2018;J&#x2019;ai<lb/>examiné avec franchise (I here repeat the words which<lb/>I used 30 years ago) ce qui concerne l&#x2019;organisation des<lb/>sociétés humaines dans les colonies, l&#x2019;inegale répar-<lb/>tition des droits et des jouissances de la vie, les<lb/>dangers mena&#x00E7;ants que la sagesse des législateurs et<lb/>la modération des hommes libres peuvent éloigner,<lb/>quelleque soit la forme des gouvernements. Il<lb/>appertient au voyageur qui a vu de près ce qui tour-<lb/>mente et degrade la nature humaine de faire parvenir<lb/>les plaintes de l&#x2019;infortune à ceux qui ont le devoir de les<lb/>soulager. J'ai rappelé dans cet exposé combien l'anci-<lb/>enne législation Espagnolle de l&#x2019;esclavage est moins in-<lb/>humaine et moins atroce que celle des Etats à esclaves<lb/>dans l&#x2019;Amérique continentale au nord et au sud de l&#x2019;equa-<lb/>teur.&#x2019; A steady advocate as I am for the most unfet-<lb/>tered expression of opinion in speech or in writing.<lb/>I should never have thought of complaining if I had<lb/>been attacked on account of my statements; but I<lb/>do think I am entitled to demand that in the free<lb/>States of the continent of America people should be al-<lb/>lowed to read what has been permitted to circulate<lb/>from the first year of its appearance in a Spanish<lb/>translation.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt</hi>. Berlin,<lb/>July, 1856.&#x201D;</p></div>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
