<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-11-30" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
               <p><hi rendition="#k">Humboldt and Agassiz.</hi> The Daily Ad-<lb/>
                   vertiser publishes a letter from Alexander Von<lb/>
                   Humboldt, in which he pays a high tribute to<lb/>
                   the energy and learning of Prof. Agassiz. It<lb/>
                   bears witness to the friendly relations subsisting<lb/>
                   between the two great lights in the modern sci-<lb/>
                   ence of natural histroy, and to the interest felt<lb/>
                   by Humboldt in the success of Agassiz&#x2019;s magnif-<lb/>
                   icient work, now preparing for publication here.<lb/>
                   The correspondent of the Advertiser, (Prof. Fel-<lb/>
                   ton we presume,) furnishes an interesting sketch<lb/>
                   of Humboldt, by way of introducing his letter to<lb/>
                   Prof. Agassiz. We quote the following para-<lb/>
                   graphs therefrom:
               </p>
                <p>Humboldt is now eighty-seven years old, but<lb/>
                    his faculties are still unimpaired, and his labors<lb/>
                    as zealously prosecuted as ever. Three years<lb/>
                    ago we had the pleasure of a conversation with<lb/>
                    this extraordinary man. The vivacity of his<lb/>
                    manner, and the rapidity of his utterance be-<lb/>
                    trayed no tokens of age. The liveliness of his<lb/>
                    interest, in all that was passing in the world,<lb/>
                    the richness of his knowledge, and the fine hu-<lb/>
                    manity that breathed in all he said, made the<lb/>
                    hours passed in his society a memorable episode<lb/>
                    in life.</p>
                <p>At the express desire of Humboldt, the corre-<lb/>
                    spondent of the Advertiser translates and pub-<lb/>
                    lishes his letter to Prog. Agassiz. We copy the<lb/>
                opening paragraph:</p>
                <p>The visit of our distinguished and excellent<lb/>
                    friend, Mr George Ticknor, to this city, where he<lb/>
                    resided in his youth, and where he left so many<lb/>
                    honorable remembrances, has made known to<lb/>
                    me a fact, which has greatly troubled me. I learn<lb/>
                    that by an unfortunate concurrence of circum-<lb/>
                    stances, undoubtedly accidental, you, my dear<lb/>
                    Agassiz, have never received the letter of mine,<lb/>
                    which expressed very strongly the joy I have<lb/>
                    shared with all the sincere lovers of science, on<lb/>
                    the subject of your beautiful and important en-<lb/>
                    terprise, the <hi rendition="#i">Contributions to the Natural History<lb/>
                    of the United States</hi>. Doubtless you must have<lb/>
                    been surprised by my long silence, considering<lb/>
                    the ties of intimate affection which have bound<lb/>
                    us together since your first residence in Paris, as<lb/>
                    well as the high admiration I have never ceased<lb/>
                    to entertain for the great and solid labors, for<lb/>
                    which we are indebted to your sagacious genius,<lb/>
                    and your incomparable intellectual energy.</p>
                <p>We have lately read a letter written by a dis-<lb/>
                    tinguished literary gentleman, who knew Hum-<lb/>
                    boldt many years ago, and has recently renewed<lb/>
                    his intercourse with him. Time, it appears, has<lb/>
                    had some effect upon his person; but his eye is<lb/>
                    still bright and quick, and he talks even faster<lb/>
                    and more richly than he ever did. His benevo-<lb/>
                    lence and desire to serve everybody seem to in-<lb/>
                    crease with his years. His attentions to his<lb/>
                    friends are incessant; he writes notes, accompa-<lb/>
                    nies them to the studios of artists, points out the<lb/>
                    objects which deserve to be seen, tells them what<lb/>
                    to do, just as John Kenyon&#x2014;the most genial of<lb/>
                    men.&#x2014;does to the stranger in London. He re-<lb/>
                    ceives about four thousand lettres a year and<lb/>
                    answers more than half of them with his own<lb/>
                    hand; he dines daily with the King, sitting from<lb/>
                    three o&#x2019;clock till about six, and sups with him at<lb/>
                nine.</p>
                <p>He holds the coffee or Chamberlain, and con-<lb/>
                    trary to the wishes of the King, performs all its<lb/>
                    duties in his turn, standing in the ante chamber<lb/>
                    from six to eight hours a day, many days in the<lb/>
                    year, refusing the indulgence of a chair. He ri-<lb/>
                    ses about seven every morning, looks over his<lb/>
                    letters, breakfasts, answers notes, receives visit-<lb/>
                    ors&#x2014;dines, as already mentioned, with the King,<lb/>
                    returns home and takes a short nap, writes let-<lb/>
                    ters until supper, and goes to work about half-<lb/>
                    past ten at night, working on till three o'clock in<lb/>
                    the morning, and sometimes later, attempting no<lb/>
                    continuous scientific labor, except during these<lb/>
                    hours, when his friends are asleep.</p>
                <p>The letter concludes in these words:</p>
                <p>The generous interest displayed in the United<lb/>
                    States, when your vast enterprise was announced,<lb/>
                    my excellent friend, has given a very flattering<lb/>
                    proof of the ever increasing intellectual interest,<lb/>
                    and of the honorable confidence manifested for<lb/>
                    talent and a noble character. I am charged by<lb/>
                    the King, who feels the importance of your for-<lb/>
                    mer labors, and retains for you the affectionate<lb/>
                    esteem which he showed for you personally,<lb/>
                    when he saw you among your collections, to<lb/>
                    place his name at the head of the list of your nu-<lb/>
                    merous subscribers. He hopes that an excursion<lb/>
                    across the Atlantic Valley may some day conduct<lb/>
                    you who have boldly scaled the lofty summits of<lb/>
                    the Alps, to the <hi rendition="#i">historic hill</hi> of Sans Souci. I<lb/>
                    have it much at heart that you should allow an<lb/>
                    extract of this not very legible letter to be pub-<lb/>
                    lished, since it contains the sincere proof of the<lb/>
                    lively satisfaction with which I have welcomed<lb/>
                    your great and useful enterprise.</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 