<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#b">Another example of &#x201C;Freedom of the<lb/>
                    Press&#x201D; in America&#x2014;Mutilation of<lb/>
                    Humboldt&#x2019;s Works.</hi></head>
                <lb/>
                <p>The following letter from the venerable philo-<lb/>
                    sopher <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi> explains itself :&#x2014;
                </p>
                <lb/>
                <p>&#x201C;Under the title of <hi rendition="#i">Essai Politique sur l&#x2019;Isle de Cuba</hi>,<lb/>
                    published in Paris in 1826, I collected together all that<lb/>
                    the large edition of my <hi rendition="#i">Voyage aux Regions Equinoxiales<lb/>
                        du Nouveau Continent</hi> contained the state of agri-<lb/>
                    culture and Slavery in the Antilles. There appeared at<lb/>
                    the same time an English and a Spanish translation of<lb/>
                    this work, the latter entitled <hi rendition="#i">Ensayo Politico sobre la<lb/>
                        Isla de Cuba</hi>, neither of whom omitted any of the frank<lb/>
                    and open remarks which feelings of humanity had in-<lb/>
                    spired. But there appears just now, strangely enough,<lb/>
                    translated from the Spanish translation, and not from<lb/>
                    the French original, an octavo volume of 400 pages un-<lb/>
                    der the title of <hi rendition="#i">The Island of Cuba</hi>, by Alexander Hum-<lb/>
                    boldt; with notes and a preliminary essay by Mr. J. S.<lb/>
                    Thrasher. The translator, who has lived a long time on<lb/>
                    that beautiful island has enriched my work by more re-<lb/>
                    cent <hi rendition="#i">data</hi> on the subject of the numerical standing of the<lb/>
                    population, of the cultivation of the soil, and the state of<lb/>
                    trade, and, generally speaking, exhibited a charitable<lb/>
                    moderation in his discussion of conflicting opinions.<lb/>
                    I owe it, however, to a moral feeling, that is now as<lb/>
                    lively in me as it was in 1826, publicly to complain that<lb/>
                    in a work which bears my name, the entire seventh<lb/>
                    chapter of the Spanish translation, with which my <hi rendition="#i">essai<lb/>
                        politique</hi> ended, has been arbitrarily omitted. To this<lb/>
                    very portion of my work I attach greater importance<lb/>
                    than to any astronomical observations, experiments of<lb/>
                    magnetic intensity, or statistical statements. I have ex-<lb/>
                    plained with frankness (I here repeat the words I used<lb/>
                    thirty years ago) whatever concerns the organization of<lb/>
                    human society in the colonies, the unequal distribution of<lb/>
                    the @@ and enjoyments of life, and the impending<lb/>
                    dangers which the wisdom of legislators and the moder-<lb/>
                    ation in @@ @@ avert, whatever may be the form of<lb/>
                    government.</p>
                <p>It is the duty of the traveller who has been an eye-<lb/>
                    witness of all that torments and degrades human nature<lb/>
                    to cause the complaints of the unfortunate to react,<lb/>
                    those whose duty it is to relieve them. I have repeated<lb/>
                    in this @@ the fact that the ancient legislation of<lb/>
                    Spain on the subject of slavery is less inhuman and atro-<lb/>
                    cious than that of the Slave States on the American con-<lb/>
                tinent, north or south of the equator.</p>
                <p>A steady advocate as I am for the most unfettered ex-<lb/>
                    pression of opinion in speech or in writing, I should<lb/>
                    never have thought of complaining if I had been attack-<lb/>
                    ed on account of my statements; but I do think I am<lb/>
                    entitled to demand that in the Free States of the conti-<lb/>
                    nent of America, people should be allowed to read what<lb/>
                    has been permitted to circulate from the first year of its<lb/>
                    appearance in a Spanish translation.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#right">ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT.</hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
                <dateline><hi rendition="#k">Berlin</hi>, July, 1856.</dateline>
                <lb/>
                </div>
                <div>
                <p>It is hardly creditable to what an extent Slave-<lb/>
                    holding intolerance exercises censorship over<lb/>
                    the American press. This is but one instance<lb/>
                out of a thousand. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi> fares as <hi rendition="#k">Cowper</hi>,<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Milton</hi> and <hi rendition="#k">Jefferson</hi> have fared before him.<lb/>
                    Even from children&#x2019;s School Books, Readers and<lb/>
                    Geographies, every paragraph rellecting against<lb/>
                    the peculiar institution of the South is carefully<lb/>
                    expunged. Our Government journals are muz-<lb/>
                    zled. Our Magazines are silenced. The Pulpit<lb/>
                    is forbidden to speak.
                </p>
                <p>Nor is &#x201C;expurgation&#x201D; the only means taken<lb/>
                    for the suppression of opinion. We look on<lb/>
                    without remonstrance while one Mob destroys a<lb/>
                    Printing Press in Lawrence as a &#x201C;nuisance ;&#x201D;<lb/>
                    another drives booksellers from Mobile for sell-<lb/>
                    ing anti-slavery books, and another arrests and<lb/>
                    condemns to ten years imprisonment the Cler-<lb/>
                    gymen and Lawyers of Kansas for daring to<lb/>
                    &#x201C;write, print or speak,&#x201D; against Slavery!</p>
                <p>Yet we have a Party among us professing a<lb/>
                    horror of such intolerance&#x2014;a party whose<lb/>
                    Fillmores and Brookses weep diurnal tears<lb/>
                    over the persecution of Galileo, and the atroci-<lb/>
                    ties of the Inquisition, three hundred years ago,<lb/>
                    three thousand miles away! But for the Gali-<lb/>
                    leos here under their eyes they have no sympa-<lb/>
                    thy, and for the Inquisition here at their doors,<lb/>
                no remonstrance!</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 