<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="28" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">humboldt&#x2019;&#x017F; prote&#x017F;t.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>J. S. Thrasher, having printed an old book of<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt&#x2019;s about Cuba, expurgating it of his<lb break="yes"/>decided aversion to slavery, the old philosopher<lb break="yes"/>has published the following protest, in which he<lb break="yes"/>spurns, with deserved scorn, the base attempt to<lb break="yes"/>make him a party to that literary cowardice of<lb break="yes" />our day, which fails to speak its honest senti-<lb break="no"/>ments on slavery. &#x201C;Humboldt,&#x201D; says a corres-<lb break="no"/>pondent of the <hi rendition="#i">Evening Post,</hi> &#x201C;is no fanatic, but<lb break="yes"/>upon the question of property in human blood<lb break="yes" />his Germanic love of justice glows with a depth<lb break="yes"/>which he never conceals. I learn from a person<lb break="yes"/>who is frequently in his society, that he looks<lb break="yes"/>upon the attempts now making in the United<lb break="yes"/>States to take slavery to the Pacific, through the<lb break="yes"/>free western prairies, and across the Rocky Moun-<lb break="no" />tains, with an utter abhorrence. &#x2018;To attempt to<lb break="yes" />introduce, in 1856, slavery where it does not now<lb break="yes"/>exist, Humboldt regards as a great crime,&#x2019; said<lb break="yes"/>my informant.&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">A. S. Standard.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Under the title of <hi rendition="#i">Essai Politique sur l&#x2019; Isle<lb break="yes"/>de Cuba,</hi> published in Paris in 1826, I collected<lb break="yes"/>together all that the large edition of my <hi rendition="#i">Voyage<lb break="yes"/>aux Regiones Equinoxiales du Nouveau Conti-<lb break="no"/>nent</hi> contained upon the state of agriculture and<lb break="yes"/>slavery in the Antilles. There appeared at the<lb break="yes"/>same time an English and a Spanish translation<lb break="yes" />of this work, the latter entitled <hi rendition="#i">Ensayo Politico<lb break="yes"/>sobre la Isla de Cuba,</hi> neither of which omitted<lb break="yes"/>any of the frank and open remarks which feelings<lb break="yes" />of humanity had inspired. But there appears<lb break="yes"/>just now, strangely enough, translated from the<lb break="yes"/>Spanish translation, and not from the French<lb break="yes"/>original, and published by Derby and Jackson,<lb break="yes"/>in New York, an octavo volume of 400 pages,<lb break="yes"/>under the title of <hi rendition="#i">The Island of Cuba,</hi> by<lb break="yes"/>Alexander Humboldt; with notes and a prelimi-<lb break="no"/>nary essay by J. S. Thrasher. The translator,<lb break="yes" />who has lived a long time on that beautiful island,<lb break="yes"/>has enriched my work by more recent <hi rendition="#i">data</hi> on<lb break="yes" />the subject of the numerical standing of the<lb break="yes"/>population, of the cultivation of the soil, and the<lb break="yes"/>state of trade, and, generally speaking, exhibited<lb break="yes"/>a charitable moderation in his discussion of con-<lb break="no"/>flicting opinions. I owe it, however, to a moral<lb break="yes"/>feeling, that is now as lively in me as it was in<lb break="yes"/>1826, publicly to complain that, in a work which<lb break="yes" />bears my name, the entire seventh chapter of the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> Spanish translation, with which my <hi rendition="#i">essai poli-<lb break="no"/>tique</hi> ended, has been arbitrarily omitted. To<lb break="yes"/>this very portion of my work, I attach greater<lb break="yes" />importance than to any astronomical observations,<lb break="yes"/>experiments of magnetic intensity, or statistical<lb break="yes"/>statements. I have examined with frankness (I<lb break="yes"/>here repeat the words I used thirty years ago)<lb break="yes"/>whatever concerns the organization of human<lb break="yes"/>society in the colonies, the unequal distinction of<lb break="yes"/>the rights and enjoyments of life, and the im-<lb break="no" />pending dangers which the wisdom of legislators<lb break="yes"/>and the moderation of freemen can avert, what-<lb break="no"/>ever may be the form of government.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It is the duty of the traveller who has been an<lb break="yes"/>eye-witness of all that torments and degrades hu-<lb break="no"/>man nature, to cause the complaints of the un-<lb break="no"/>fortunate to reach those whose duty it is to relieve<lb break="yes"/>them. I have repeated in this treatise the fact,<lb break="yes"/>that the ancient legislation of Spain on the sub-<lb break="no" />ject of slavery is less inhuman and atrocious than<lb break="yes"/>that of the slave States on the American conti-<lb break="no"/>nent, north or south of the equator.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A steady advocate as I am for the most unfet-<lb break="no"/>tered expression of opinion in speech or in<lb break="yes"/>writing, I should never have thought of com-<lb break="no"/>plaining if I had been attacked on account of my<lb break="yes"/>statements; but I do think I am entitled to de-<lb break="no" />mand that, in the free States of the continent of<lb break="yes"/>America, people should be allowed to read what<lb break="yes"/>has been permitted to circulate from the first<lb break="yes"/>year of its appearance in a Spanish translation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#et">
                            <hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <dateline>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Berlin, July,</hi> 1856.</dateline>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 