<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="2" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">MADAME IDA PFEIFFER.</hi></head><lb/><p>This clever and courageous lady, who has run<lb/>all round the globe more than once, for her own
                    and<lb/>the public entertainment, is now in London, and is imme-<lb/>diately
                    going to Madagascar. She has lately received much<lb/>honour among Continental
                        <hi rendition="#i">savans.</hi> The natural history so-<lb/>cieties of
                    Berlin and Amsterdam elected her as an honorary<lb/>member. She was invited by
                    the King of Prussia to Pots-<lb/>dam, presented with the Humboldt gold medal of
                    arts and<lb/>sciences, and with a token of esteem not less gratifying,
                    a<lb/>letter, of which we give a translation, from Alexander von<lb/>Humboldt
                    himself:</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;All those who, in different regions of the earth preserve<lb/>a remembrance of my name
                    and affection for my works, I<lb/>ardently beg to receive with friendly interest
                    and to aid<lb/>with their counsels the bearer of these lines. Mrs.
                    Ida<lb/>Pfeiffer, who is celebrated not only for the noble constancy<lb/>that,
                    amidst so many dangers and privations, has led her<lb/>twice round the globe,
                    but above all for the amiable sim-<lb/>plicity and modesty which pervade her
                    works, for her<lb/>truthfulness and philanthropy, for the correctness of
                    her<lb/>judgments, as well as for the independence, and at the same<lb/>time the
                    delicacy of her sentiments. Enjoying the confi-<lb/>dence and friendship of this
                    estimable lady, I only blame<lb/>her&#x2014;though I cannot refrain from
                    admiring it&#x2014;for that in-<lb/>domitable energy of character which she has
                    displayed,<lb/>wherever she has been called, or, I should rather say,
                    has<lb/>been impelled, by an unconquerable passion for exploring<lb/>nature and
                    the habits of the various human races. As the<lb/>oldest living traveller, I
                    felt a desire to offer to Mrs. Ida<lb/>Pfeiffer this slender proof of my high
                    and respectful esteem.</p><lb/><closer><salute>(Signed) &#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt</hi>.</salute></closer><lb/><dateline>&#x201C;Potsdam, June 8, 1856.&#x201D;</dateline></div><lb/><lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
