<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="2" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">MRS. IDA PFEIFFER.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer,</hi> the celebrated lady traveller, who<lb break="yes"/>went twice round the world, is now again in London,<lb break="yes"/>on her way to Madagascar, into the interior of which<lb break="yes"/>she wishes to penetrate and explore. Her most @<lb break="yes" />cent travels extended over Germany, but she does not<lb break="yes"/>find in the civilised parts of the world the same in-<lb break="no"/>terest as in the less cultivated regions. There, in the<lb break="yes"/>bosom of nature, undisturbed by the presence of man,<lb break="yes"/>she delights most.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>On this her last visit to the European continent,<lb break="yes"/>some of the most distinguished men came forward un-<lb break="no"/>solicited to do her honour. In Berlin and Amster-<lb break="no"/>dam, the Society of Natural History conferred upon<lb break="yes"/>her their respective diplomas, and elected her an<lb break="yes"/>honorary member. The King of Prussia graciously<lb break="yes"/>invited her to his residence at Potsdam, and presented<lb break="yes"/>her with the golden medal of the Humboldt order for<lb break="yes"/>arts and sciences. The greatest living naturalist and<lb break="yes"/>philosopher, Alexander von Humboldt, exhibited in<lb break="yes"/>her favour the warmest friendship and admiration.<lb break="yes"/>As a token of the affectionate interest he took in her<lb break="yes"/>welfare, he presented her on parting with an autograph<lb break="yes"/>letter, of which the following is a literal translation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <div n="2" type="letter">
                            <p>&#x201C;All those who, in different regions of the ea@<lb break="yes" />preserve a remembrance of my name and affection for<lb break="yes" />my works, I earnestly beg to receive, with friendly<lb break="yes" />interest, and to aid with their counsels, the bearer of<lb break="yes"/>these lines, Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer, celebrated not only for<lb break="yes"/>the noble constancy that, amidst so many dangers and<lb break="yes"/>privations, led her twice round the globe, but a@<lb break="yes"/>all, for the amiable simplicity and modesty pervading<lb break="yes"/>her works, the truthfulness and philanthropy of her<lb break="yes"/>judgment, as well as the independence and at the<lb break="yes"/>same time the delicacy of her sentiments. Enj@<lb break="yes"/>the confidence and friendship of this respectable lady.<lb break="yes"/>I blame and admire at once that indomitable en@<lb break="yes"/>of character which she displayed wherever called&#x2014;I<lb break="yes"/>should say, impelled by, an unconquerable passion of<lb break="yes"/>exploring nature and the habits of the various hu@<lb break="yes"/>races. As the oldest living traveller, I feel a desire @<lb break="yes"/>offer to Mrs Ida Pfeiffer this slender proof of @<lb break="yes"/>high and respectful esteem. (Signed)</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rendition="#k">Alexande@<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt.</hi>
                                </signed>
                                <dateline>Potsdam City Castle, June 8, 18@.&#x201D;</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer might justly be proud of so @<lb break="yes"/>flattering a testimony from one of the most eminent<lb break="yes"/>men living; but her modesty is equal to her good sense,<lb break="yes"/>fact, patience, perseverance, power of endurance, and<lb break="yes"/>simple habits.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>A special Providence seems to have watched over<lb break="yes"/>this extraordinary woman. She has been preserved<lb break="yes"/>amid untold dangers and perils of sea and land. That<lb break="yes"/>a delicate woman, unarmed, unknown and poor, with<lb break="yes"/>no prestige of aristocratic descent, without the mag@<lb break="yes"/>of an ample exchequer, should twice have girded the<lb break="yes"/>globe, unarmed and unscathed, and accomplish, @<lb break="yes"/>aided and single, what the most reckless man who<lb break="yes" />scaled the bloody heights of the Alma might have<lb break="yes"/>shrunk from appalled, seems almost incredible. Is<lb break="yes"/>this not an abundant testimony, then, that deadly<lb break="yes"/>weapons are absolutely unnecessary for protection?<lb break="yes"/>And may not nations learn from this fact, tested under<lb break="yes"/>every longitude and latitude of the earth, that if they<lb break="yes"/>were to confide in the protecting power of Providence,<lb break="yes"/>and not in gunpowder, there would be an end of main-<lb break="no"/>taining standing armies and men trained to the use<lb break="yes"/>of arms, which, perhaps, more than any other cause,<lb break="yes"/>provoke wars and bloody conflicts amongst mankind@</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>An irresistible impulse impels this wonderful lady<lb break="yes"/>to wander over God&#x2019;s vast and beautiful world, and to<lb break="yes"/>visit the great variety of races of men. Not the least<lb break="yes"/>wonderful part of her adventures is the way in which<lb break="yes"/>she communicates wtih the various people, some of<lb break="yes"/>whom she found in the least developed stage of natu@e.<lb break="yes"/>In this she is assisted by an extraordinary power of<lb break="yes"/>expressing her wants and thoughts by mimicry&#x2014;a kind<lb break="yes"/>of natural language of universal interpretation.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>It might be imagined that, in order to perform such<lb break="yes"/>stupendous travels, Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer must be in po@<lb break="yes"/>session of a large fortune, whereas her only pecuniary<lb break="yes"/>resources are vested in the produce of her literary<lb break="yes"/>works. When in this way a modest sum has accumu-<lb break="no"/>lated in the hands of her publishers, she again sets<lb break="yes"/>out to visit some unexplored part of the world, to re-<lb break="no"/>turn when her means are exhausted. Several editions<lb break="yes"/>of her works, translated into the English language,<lb break="yes"/>have found extensive public favour in England and<lb break="yes"/>America. Her last travel round the world, by far the<lb break="yes"/>most interesting of her literary productions, has been<lb break="yes"/>edited by Messrs. Longmans and Green. She is now<lb break="yes" />waiting to meet with a suitable vessel to carry her to<lb break="yes"/>the Cape of Good Hope or to the Mauritius, and<lb break="yes"/>thence to Madagascar. May her wishes be fulfilled,<lb break="yes"/>and may the same good fortune, which hitherto acco@<lb break="yes"/>panied her, follow her in her future travels, and in due<lb break="yes"/>time procure us again the pleasure of another of her<lb break="yes"/>very interesting and instructive descriptions of foreign<lb break="yes"/>countries and peoples.&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i" >London Star.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 