<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Humboldt on Spiritual Rappings.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;It was<lb/>recently rumored that the celebrated Baron <hi rendition="#k"
                        >Hum-<lb/>boldt</hi> was taking an interest in spirit-rappings,<lb/>table
                    turnings, &amp;c.; and accordingly a friend, one<lb/>Dr. Jobard, wrote a letter
    to the venerable sa-<lb/>vant, on the subject. Here is the reply:</p><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Berlin</hi>, April 2, 1856.</hi></dateline><lb/>
    </div>
    <div><p>&#x201C;Dear Sir: You wrote, as always, a most<lb/>amiable letter, but I am unable to discuss the<lb/>simple possibility of different kinds of mineral,<lb/>vegetable, animal, voluntary and involuntary<lb/>celebral electricism. I had always the weakness<lb/>of having a dread of the spiritualism of pine<lb/>deals and of <choice><sic>psychrographic</sic><corr type="editorial">psychographic</corr></choice> mysticism. You<lb/>augment my dread by the ghost of an ephemeral<lb/>rational being, which is to get understanding by<lb/>the thoughts of the men surrounding the instru-<lb/>ment, (the mediums around the table.) You<lb/>know that Geoffroy de St. Hilaire believed he<lb/>had in Egypt, had a transpiration of oxydated<lb/>thoughts; and you, dear Doctor, will perhaps<lb/>find that my skepticism is the result of my lazi-<lb/>ness. I submit to this rebuke, but I am convinc-<lb/>ed that the regret which I feel in knowing that<lb/>you have gone astray on such a dark pathway<lb/>will not diminish the friendship which you have<lb/>allowed me to enjoy for so long. I trust that<lb/>you will excuse me.</p><lb/><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT.&#x201D;</hi><lb/><lb/></salute></closer></div>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
