<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="69" facs="#f0001" /><lb/><div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">Letter of</hi> <hi rendition="#k">Baron von Humboldt</hi> <hi rendition="#i">to</hi> Mr. <hi rendition="#k">Frederick M. Kelley.</hi><lb/>(<hi rendition="#i">Translation.</hi>)</head><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#et">Berlin, 27th January, 1856.</hi></dateline><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">It</hi> is with the most lively satisfaction that I have taken notice, during<lb/>your too short visit to Berlin, of the great and solid operations which<lb/>you have caused to be executed since the beginning of January, 1855,<lb/>by Mr. William Kennish, a skilful engineer, in surveying and levelling<lb/>the course of the great river Atrato and its affluents from the W.<lb/>My learned friend Mr. Alexander Bache, superintendent of the coast<lb/>survey of the United States, had already drawn my attention to the<lb/>previous investigations which you had caused to be made; and these<lb/>researches are the more deserving of regard in consequence of your<lb/>proposal to extend the investigation, with equal precision, to the<lb/>passage between Port Cupica and the river Napipi, as well as to<lb/>other points situated above the confluence of the Truando&#x2014;positions<lb/>of great importance in the solution of the vast problem of an oceanic<lb/>canal.</p><lb/><p>The great number of maps and sections on large scales, which you<lb/>possess, furnish all the necessary elements for judging of the possibility<lb/>of communication through the mouths of the Atrato, the Truando, and<lb/>a canal leading from the latter to the South Sea. It is owing to such<lb/>a complete examination not having been effected of the mountainous<lb/>country between the Gulf of San Miguel and Caledonia Bay, that<lb/>Mr. Lionel Gisborne&#x2019;s project in 1852 has not been executed. Igno-<lb/><pb n="70" facs="#f0002" />
rance of the locality, with the want of hypsometrical measurements,<lb/>led to the sad results of Lieut. Strain&#x2019;s courageous expedition.</p><lb/><p>The great object to be accomplished is, in my opinion, a canal<lb/>uniting the two oceans <hi rendition="#i">without locks or tunnels.</hi> When the plans and<lb/>sections can be submitted to the public, a free and open discussion will<lb/>elicit the advantages and disadvantages of each locality; and the<lb/>execution of this important work, which interests the civilised nations<lb/>of the two continents, should be entrusted to engineers who have suc-<lb/>cessfully constructed similar works. The Junction Company will find<lb/>supporters among those governments and citizens, who, yielding to noble<lb/>feelings, will take pride in the idea of having contributed to a work<lb/>worthy of the progress of intellect in the 19th century. This opinion I<lb/>have expressed with warmth for more than fifty years. I have laboured,<lb/>without ceasing, to disseminate the geographical views which tend<lb/>to prove the possibility of commercial communications, whether by<lb/>canals, with or without locks, either simple or coupled with inclines;<lb/>or by means of railroads, uniting coasts or rivers having an opposite<lb/>course.</p><lb/><p>Through General Bolivar, I obtained the exact geodetic levelling of<lb/>the Isthmus of Panama. I was the first to make known, in my Mexican<lb/>Atlas, the course of the two rivers Huasacoalco and Chimalapa, accord-<lb/>ing to documents found in the archives of the viceroyalty of Mexico.<lb/>I indicated the proximity of the almost unknown port of Cupica to the<lb/>sources of the Napipi and the waters of the Atrato, as well as the exist-<lb/>ence, ignored in Europe, of a canal of very small dimensions, con-<lb/>structed in 1788, under the directions of a monk, curate of Novita, by<lb/>the Indians of his parish, for connecting the waters of the Raspadura,<lb/>an affluent of the Quito, with the waters of the San Juan de Chiram-<lb/>bira. I think there is nothing more likely to obstruct the extension of<lb/>commerce and the freedom of international relations, than to create a<lb/>distaste for any further investigation, by declaring, in an absolute and<lb/>imperative manner, that all hope of an oceanic canal ought now to be<lb/>abandoned.</p><lb/><p>I have described already in my &#x2018;Essai Politique de la Nouvelle<lb/>Espagne&#x2019; <note place="foot" n="*"><hi rendition="#i">See</hi> the last edition, vol. i., pages 202-248, and vol. ii., pages 95-145.</note> the immense operation of cutting through mountains the<lb/>open canal, called the Desague of Huehuetoca, which was executed<lb/>by the Spanish government at the commencement of the 17th century;<lb/>and I have now too much faith in the power of the resources offered by<lb/>modern civilisation, to be discouraged.</p><lb/><p>I am indebted to Colonel Codazzi, and to the affectionate kindness of<lb/>the Minister of the
                    Interior at Bogota, M. Pastor Ospina, for im-<lb/>portant communications which
                    remind me that the route from Cupica<lb/><pb n="71" facs="#f0003"/> to the river
                    Napipi presents successive elevations; and it would be<lb/>an additional service
                    to geography, if you would cause this route to be<lb/>levelled.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
