<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Humboldt and Agassiz</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:21</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VII.107</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-06-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-06-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Humboldt and Agassiz</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1856</date>
          <pubPlace>New York City, New York</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;American Publishers’ Circular and Literary Gazette&lt;/i&gt; 2:43 (25. Oktober 1856), S. 653.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p>Antiqua</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>

<pb n="653" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Humboldt and Agassiz.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;Professor Agassiz may be considered as the pupil<lb/>of the illustrious Humboldt, and his destined successor in the realm of natural<lb/>science. For many years there has been a strong and affectionate connection<lb/>between them; and if we remember right, Agassiz, in early life, was in-<lb/>debted for kindly and opportune assistance in his investigations to the gen-<lb/>erosity of his great friend. On the part of each of these men, there has<lb/>always been the most cordial and thorough appreciation of the merits of the<lb/>other.</p><lb/><p>The labors of Agassiz are recognized in the Kosmos of Humboldt, in terms<lb/>which show the high estimation placed upon them by the first of living phi-<lb/>losophers; and Agassiz has never failed to express the affectionate veneration<lb/>which he cherishes for the genius, attainments and character of the mighty<lb/>master. The pursuits of Agassiz, in this country, have been watched by his<lb/>venerable friend with unceasing interest and hearty sympathy. Humboldt<lb/>is now eighty-seven years old, but his faculties are still unimpaired, and his<lb/>labors as zealously prosecuted as ever. Three years ago we had the plea-<lb/>sure of a conversation with this extraordinary man. The vivacity of his<lb/>manner, and the rapidity of his utterance betrayed no tokens of age. The<lb/><cb/>
liveliness of his interest, in all that was passing in the world, the richness of<lb/>his knowledge, and the fine humanity that breathed in all he said, made the<lb/>hours passed in his society a memorable episode in life.</p><lb/><p>We have lately read a letter written by a distinguished literary gentle-<lb/>man, who knew
                    Humboldt many years ago, and has recently renewed his<lb/>intercourse with him.
                    Time, it appears, has had some effect upon his per-<lb/>son; but his eye is
                    still bright and quick, and he talks even faster and more<lb/>richly than he
                    ever did. His benevolence and desire to serve everybody<lb/>seem to increase
                    with his years. His attentions to his friends are incessant;<lb/>he writes
                    notes, accompanies them to the studios of artists, points out the<lb/>objects
                    which deserve to be seen, tells them what to do, just as John
                    Kenyon<lb/>&#x2014;the most genial of men&#x2014;does to the stranger in London.
                    He receives<lb/>about four thousand letters a year and answers more than half of
                    them with<lb/>his own hand; he dines daily with the King, sitting from three
                    o&#x2019;clock till<lb/>about six, and sups with him at nine. He holds the
                    office of Chamberlain,<lb/>and contrary to the wishes of the King, performs all
                    its duties in his turn,<lb/>standing in the ante-chamber from six to eight hours
                    a day, many days in<lb/>the year, refusing the indulgence of a chair. He rises
                    about seven every<lb/>morning, looks over his letters, breakfasts, answers
                    notes, receives visitors&#x2014;<lb/>dines, as already mentioned, with the King,
                    returns home and takes a short<lb/>nap, writes letters until supper, and goes to
                    work about half past ten at night,<lb/>working on till three o&#x2019;clock in
                    the morning, and sometimes later, attempt-<lb/>ing no continuous scientific
                    labor, except during these hours, when his friends<lb/>are asleep. &#x201C;And
                    this man,&#x201D; adds our friend, &#x201C;will be eighty-seven years<lb/>old on
                    the 14th of this present month (September)&#x2014;and while, on the
                    one<lb/>hand, if you were to ask the well-dressed people you meet in the streets
                    or<lb/>on the railroad, who is the greatest man in Prussia, they would
                    answer<lb/>unanimously&#x2014;Humboldt, I verily believe that, on the other
                    hand, nobody<lb/>who is in the habit of seeing him will doubt that his kindness
                    of heart is more<lb/>remarkable than his genius, philosophy and vast knowledge.
                    It is reputation<lb/>worth having.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>Such is the impression this great and good man makes on intelligent<lb/>travellers.</p><lb/><p>We have given the above little sketch by way of introduction to an ex-<lb/>tract from a letter of his to Professor Agassiz which, at the express desire<lb/>of Humboldt, we translate and publish. It is on a subject of general scien-<lb/>tific interest; and as the time for the publication of the first volume of the<lb/>great work of Agassiz draws near, it will not be uninteresting to the sub-<lb/>scribers and to the public, to know the feelings with which so illustrious a<lb/>philosopher regards it. The extract is as follows. It is dated Berlin, Sep-<lb/>tember 1, 1856:</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;The visit of our distinguished and excellent friend, Mr. George Ticknor,<lb/>to this
                    city, where he resided in his youth, and where he left so many hon-<lb/>orable
                    remembrances, has made known to me a fact, which has greatly<lb/>troubled me. I
                    learn that by an unfortunate occurrence of circumstances,<lb/>undoubtedly
                    accidental, you, my dear Agassiz, have never received the letter<lb/>of mine,
                    which expressed very strongly the joy I have shared with all the<lb/>sincere
                    lovers of science, on the subject of your beautiful and important
                    enter-<lb/>prise, the Contributions to the Natural History of the United States.
                    Doubt-<lb/>less you must have been surprised by my long silence, considering the
                    ties of<lb/>intimate affection which have bound us together since your first
                    residence<lb/>in Paris, as well as the high admiration I have never ceased to
                    entertain for<lb/>the great and solid labors, for which we are indebted to your
                    sagacious<lb/>genius, and your incomparable intellectual energy. Interested,
                    like you, in<lb/>the progress made in that part of the world, where the
                    cultivation of the<lb/>sciences is making such rapid strides, I approve above
                    all, the generality of<lb/>conceptions, where is the basis of the plan you have
                    traced out. I admire<lb/>that long series of physiological investigations,
                    commencing with the embry-<lb/>ology of organisms called simple and inferior,
                    and ascending by degrees to<lb/>the organisms which are more complicated; I
                    admire that constant attention<lb/>to the comparison of the types belonging to
                    the present condition of our<lb/>planet, and the types found only in a fossil
                    state, and which abounds in the<lb/>immense area between the shores opposite to
                    Europe and Northern Asia.<lb/>The generous interest displayed in the United
                    States, when your vast enter-<lb/>prise was announced, my excellent friend, has
                    given a very flattering proof of<lb/>the ever increasing intellectual interest,
                    and of the honorable confidence<lb/>manifested for talent and a noble character.
                    I am charged by the King, who<lb/>feels the importance of your former labors,
                    and retains for you the affection-<lb/>ate esteem which he showed for you
                    personally, when he saw you among<lb/>your collections, to place his name at the
                    head of the list of your numerous<lb/>subscribers. He hopes that an excursion
                    across the <hi rendition="#i">Atlantic Valley</hi> may<lb/>some day conduct you,
                    who have boldly scaled the lofty summits of the Alps,<lb/>to the <hi
                        rendition="#i">historic hill</hi> of Sans Souci. I have it much at heart
                    that you should<lb/>allow an extract of this not very legible letter to be
                    published, since it con-<lb/>cerns the sincere proof of the lively satisfaction
                    with which I have welcomed<lb/>your great and useful
                        enterprise.&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">Boston Daily
                    Advertiser.</hi></p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
