<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="3" facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1">
   <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
    <head><hi rendition="#i">MRS. IDA PFEIFFER.</hi></head><lb/>
        <p>Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer, the celebrated lady traveller, who<lb/>
            went twice round the world, is now again in London, on<lb/>
            her way to Madagascar, into the interior of which she<lb/>
            wishes to penetrate and explore. Her most recent travels<lb/>
            extended over Germany, but she does not find in the<lb/>
            civilised parts of the world the same interest as in the less<lb/>
            cultivated regions. There, in the bosom of nature, un-<lb/>
            disturbed by the presence of man, she delights most.</p>
    <p>On this her last visit to the European continent, some<lb/>
        of the most distinguished men came forward unsolicited<lb/>
        to do her honour. In Berlin and Amsterdam, the<lb/>
        Society of Natural History conferred upon her their re-<lb/>
        spective diplomas, and elected her an honorary member.<lb/>
        The King of Prussia graciously invited her to his resi-<lb/>
        dence at Potsdam, and presented her with the golden<lb/>
        medal of the Humboldt order for arts and sciences. The<lb/>
        greatest living naturalist and philosopher, Alexander von<lb/>
        Humboldt, exhibited in her favour the warmest friendship<lb/>
        and admiration. As a token of the affectionate interest<lb/>
        he took in her welfare, he presented her on parting with<lb/>
        an autograph letter, of which the following is a literal<lb/>
        translation:&#x2014;</p>
    <p>&#x201C;All those who, in different regions of the earth, pre-<lb/>
        serve a remembrance of my name and affection for my<lb/>
        works, I earnestly beg to receive, with friendly interest,<lb/>
        and to aid with their counsels, the bearer of these lines,<lb/>
        Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer, celebrated not only for the noble con-<lb/>
        stancy that, amidst so many dangers and privations, led<lb/>
        her twice round the globe, but above all, for the amiable<lb/>
        simplicity and modesty pervading her works, the truthful-<lb/>
        ness and philanthropy of her judgment, as well as the<lb/>
        independence and at the same time the delicacy of her<lb/>
        sentiments. Enjoying the confidence and friendship of<lb/>
        this respectable lady, I blame her for though I cannot<lb/>
        refrain from admiring, that indomitable energy of charac-<lb/>
        ter which she displayed wherever called&#x2014;I should say,<lb/>
        impelled by an unconquerable passion of exploring na-<lb/>
        ture and the habits of the various human races. As the<lb/>
        oldest living traveller, I feel a desire to offer to Mrs. Ida<lb/>
        Pfeiffer this slender proof of my high and respectful<lb/>
        esteem. (Signed) <hi rendition="#k">Alexander Humboldt</hi>. Potsdam<lb/>
        City Castle, June 9, 1856.&#x201D;</p>
    <lb/>
    <p>Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer might justly to be proud of so very<lb/>
        flattering a testimony from one of the most eminent men<lb/>
        living; but her modesty is equal to her good sense, tact,<lb/>
        patience, perseverance, power of endurance, and simple<lb/>
        habits.</p>
    <p>A special Providence seems to have watched over this<lb/>
        extraordinary woman. She has been preserved amid un-<lb/>
        told dangers and perils of sea and land. That a delicate<lb/>
        woman, unarmed, unknown and poor, with no prestige of<lb/>
        aristocratic descent, without the magic of an ample ex-<lb/>
        chequer, should twice have girded the world, unharmed<lb/>
        and unscathed, and accomplish, unaided and single, what<lb/>
        the most reckless man who scaled the bloody heights of<lb/>
        the Alma might have shrunk from appalled, seems almost<lb/>
        incredible. Is this not an abundant testimony, then, that<lb/>
        deadly weapons are absolutely unnecessary for protection?<lb/>
        And may not nations learn from this fact, tested under<lb/>
        every longitude and latitude of the earth, that if they<lb/>
        were to confide in the protecting power of Providence, and<lb/>
        not in gunpowder, there would be an end of maintaining<lb/>
        standing armies and men trained to the use of arms, which<lb/>
        perhaps, more than any other cause, provoke wars and<lb/>
        bloody conflicts amongst mankind?</p>
    <p>An irresistible impulse impels this wonderful lady to<lb/>
        wander over God&#x2019;s vast and beautiful world, and to visit<lb/>
        the great variety of races of men. Not the least wonder-<lb/>
        ful part of her adventures is the way in which she com-<lb/>
        municates with the various peoples, some of whom she<lb/>
        found in the least developed stage of nature. For she is<lb/>
        assisted by an extraordinary power of expressing her wants<lb/>
        and thoughts by mimicry&#x2014;a kind of natural language<lb/>
        of universal interpretation.</p>
    <p>It might be imagined that, in order to perform such<lb/>
        stupendous travels, Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer must be in posses-<lb/>
        sion of a large fortune, whereas her only pecuniary re-<lb/>
        sources are vested in the produce of her literary works.<lb/>
        When in this way a modest sum has accumulated in the<lb/>
        hands of her publishers, she again sets out to visit some<lb/>
        unexplored part of the world, to return when her means<lb/>
        are exhausted.</p>
    <p>Several editions of her works, translated into the Eng-<lb/>
        lish language, have found extensive public favour in<lb/>
        England and America. Her last travel round the world,<lb/>
        by far the most interesting of her literary productions,<lb/>
        has been edited by Messrs. Orme and Longmans.</p>
    <p>She is now waiting to meet with a suitable vessel to<lb/>
        carry her to the Cape of Good Hope or to the Mauritius,<lb/>
        and thence to Madagascar. May her wishes be fulfilled,<lb/>
        and may the same good fortune, which hitherto accom-<lb/>
        panied her, follow her in her future travels, and in due<lb/>
        time procure us again the pleasure of another of her very<lb/>
        interesting and instructive descriptions of foreign countries<lb/>
        and peoples.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
