<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Humboldt and Agassiz.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb/>
                <div n="2">
                    <p>The following communication, we presume by<lb/>
                        the signature, from Professor Felton, is of the<lb/>
                        deepest interest. We find it in the Boston <hi rendition="#i">Daily<lb/>
                            Advertiser:</hi></p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>Professor Agassiz may be considered as the<lb/>
                        pupil of the illustrious Humboldt, and his des-<lb/>
                        tined successor in the realm of natural science.<lb/>
                        For many years there has been a strong and af-<lb/>
                        fectionate connection between them; and if we<lb/>
                        remember right, Agassiz, in early life, was in-<lb/>
                        debted for kindly and opportune assistance in<lb/>
                        his investigations to the generosity of his great<lb/>
                        friend. On the part of each of these men, there<lb/>
                        has always been the most cordial and thorough<lb/>
                        appreciation of the merits of the other.</p>
                    <p>The labors of Agassiz are recognised in the<lb/>
                        Kosmos of Humboldt, in terms which show the<lb/>
                        high estimation placed upon them by the first of<lb/>
                        living philosophers; and Agassiz has never<lb/>
                        failed to express the affectionate veneration<lb/>
                        which he cherishes for the genius, attainments<lb/>
                        and character of the mighty master. The pur-<lb/>
                        suits of Agassiz in this country have been<lb/>
                        watched by his venerable friend with unceasing<lb/>
                        interest and hearty sympathy. Humboldt is<lb/>
                        now eighty-seven years old, but his faculties are<lb/>
                        still unimpaired, and his labors as zealously<lb/>
                        prosecuted as ever. Three years ago we had the<lb/>
                        pleasure of a conversation with this extraordi-<lb/>
                        nary man. The vivacity of his manner, and the<lb/>
                        rapidity of his utterance betrayed no tokens of<lb/>
                        age. The liveliness of his interest, in all that<lb/>
                        was passing in the world, the richness of his<lb/>
                        knowledge, and the fine humanity that breathed<lb/>
                        in all he said, made the hours passed in his so-<lb/>
                        ciety a memorable episode in life.</p>
                    <p>We have lately read a letter written by a dis-<lb/>
                        tinguished literary gentleman, who knew Hum-<lb/>
                        boldt many years ago, and has recently renewed<lb/>
                        his intercourse with them. Time, it appears,<lb/>
                        has had some effect upon his person; but his eye<lb/>
                        is still bright and quick, and he talks even fas-<lb/>
                        ter and more richly than he ever did. His be-<lb/>
                        nevolence and desire to serve everybody seem to<lb/>
                        increase with his years. His attentions to his<lb/>
                        friends are incessant; he writes notes, accompa-<lb/>
                        nies them to the studios of artists, points out the<lb/>
                        objects which deserve to be seen, tells them what<lb/>
                        to do, just as John Kenyon&#x2014;the most genial of<lb/>
                        men&#x2014;does to the stranger in London. He re-<lb/>
                        ceives about four thousand letters a year and<lb/>
                        answers more than half of them with his own<lb/>
                        hand; he dines daily with the King, sitting from<lb/>
                        three o&#x2019;clock till about six, and sups with him<lb/>
                        at nine. He holds the office of Chamberlain, and<lb/>
                        contrary to the wishes of the King, performs all<lb/>
                        its duties in his turn, standing in the antecham-<lb/>
                        ber from six to eight hours a day, many days in<lb/>
                        the year, refusing the indulgence of a chair. He<lb/>
                        rises about seven every morning, looks over his<lb/>
                        letters, breakfasts, answers notes, receives visi-<lb/>
                        tors&#x2014;dines, as already mentioned, with the<lb/>
                        King, returns home and takes a short nap,<lb/>
                        writes letters until supper, and goes to work<lb/>
                        about half past ten at night, working on till<lb/>
                        three o&#x2019;clock in the morning, and sometimes<lb/>
                        later, attempting no continuous scientific labor,<lb/>
                        except during these hours, when his friends are<lb/>
                        asleep. &#x201C;And this man;&#x201D; adds our friend, &#x201C;will<lb/>
                        be eighty seven years old on the 14th of this<lb/>
                        present month (September)&#x2014;and while, on the<lb/>
                        one hand, if you were to ask the well dressed<lb/>
                        people you meet in the streets or on the railroad,<lb/>
                        who is the greatest man in Prussia, they would<lb/>
                        answer unanimously&#x2014;Humboldt. I verily be-<lb/>
                        lieve that, on the other hand, nobody who is in<lb/>
                        the hand; nobody who is in the habit of seeing<lb/>
                        him will doubt that his kindness of heart is<lb/>
                        more remarkable than his genius, philosophy<lb/>
                        and vast knowledge. It is reputation worth<lb/>
                        having.&#x201D;</p>
                    <p>Such is the impression this great and good<lb/>
                        man makes on intelligent travellers.</p>
                    <p>We have given the above little sketch by way<lb/>
                        of introduction to an extract from a letter of his<lb/>
                        to Professor Agassiz, which, at the express de-<lb/>
                        sire of Humboldt, we translate and publish. It<lb/>
                        is on a subject of general scientific interest; and<lb/>
                        as the time for the publication of the first vol-<lb/>
                        ume of the great work of Agassiz draws near, it<lb/>
                        will not be uninteresting to the subscribers and<lb/>
                        to the public, to know the feelings with which<lb/>
                        so illustrious a philosopher regards it. The ex-<lb/>
                        tract is as follows. It is dated Berlin, Septem-<lb/>
                        ber 1, 1856:</p>
                    <p>The visit of our distinguished and excellent<lb/>
                        friend, Mr. George Ticknor, to this city, where<lb/>
                        he resided in his youth, and where he left so<lb/>
                        many honorable remembrances, has made known<lb/>
                        to me a fact, which has greatly troubled me. I<lb/>
                        learn that by an unfortunate occurrence of cir-<lb/>
                        cumstances, undoubtedly accidental, you, my<lb/>
                        dear Agassiz, have never recovered the letter of<lb/>
                        mine, which expressed very strongly the joy I<lb/>
                        have shared with all the sincere lovers of science,<lb/>
                        on the subject of your beantiful and important<lb/>
                        enterprise, the contributions to the Natural His-<lb/>
                        tory of the United States. Doubtless you must<lb/>
                        have been surprised by my long silence, con-<lb/>
                        sidering the ties of intimate affection which have<lb/>
                        bound us together since your first residence in<lb/>
                        Paris, as well as the high admiration I have<lb/>
                        never ceased to entertain for the great and solid<lb/>
                        labors, for which we are indebted to your sagaci-<lb/>
                        ous genius, and your incomparable intellectual<lb/>
                        energy. Interested, like you, in the progress<lb/>
                        made in that part of the world, where the culti-<lb/>
                        vation of the sciences is making such rapid<lb/>
                        strides, I approve above all, the generality of con-<lb/>
                        ceptions, where is the basis of the plan you have<lb/>
                        traced out. I admire that long series of physio-<lb/>
                        logical investigations, commencing with the em-<lb/>
                        bryology of organisms called simple and inferior,<lb/>
                        and ascending by degrees to the organisms which<lb/>
                        are more complicated; I admire that constant at-<lb/>
                        tention to the comparison of the types belonging<lb/>
                        to the present condition of our planet, and the<lb/>
                        types found only in a fossil state, and which<lb/>
                        abounds in the immense area between the shores<lb/>
                        opposite to Europe and Northern Asia. The<lb/>
                        generous interest displayed in the United States,<lb/>
                        when your vast enterprise was announced, my<lb/>
                        excellent friend, has given a very flattering proof<lb/>
                        of the ever increasing intellectual interest, and<lb/>
                        of the honorable confidence manifested for talent<lb/>
                        and a noble character. I am charged by the<lb/>
                        King, who feels the importance of your former<lb/>
                        labors, and retains for you the affectionate esteem<lb/>
                        which he showed for you personally, when he<lb/>
                        saw you among your collections, to place his<lb/>
                        name at the head of the list of your numerous<lb/>
                        subscribers. He hopes that an excursion across<lb/>
                        the <hi rendition="#i">Atlantic Valley</hi> may some day conduct you,<lb/>
                        who have boldly sealed the lofty summits of the<lb/>
                        Alps, to the <hi rendition="#i">historic hill</hi> of Sans Souci. I have<lb/>
                        it much at heart that you should allow an extract<lb/>
                        of this not very legible letter to be published,<lb/>
                        since it contains the sincere proof of the lively<lb/>
                        satisfaction with which I have welcomed your<lb/>
                        great and useful enterprise.&#x201D; <hi rendition="#right">F.</hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 