<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<floatingText>
    <body><p>From the Jamestown Journal.<lb/></p></body>
</floatingText>
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#b">A High Testimony to Worth</hi></head><lb/><p>It is doubtless known to most of our citi-<lb/>zens that for a few years past, Prof.
                    Lorin<lb/>Blodget, formerly of this County, has been<lb/>engaged in prosecuting
                    important scientific<lb/>labors in Washington: but we presume few<lb/>of them
                    have been acquainted with the<lb/>difficulties he has encountered, nor the
                    high<lb/>position, in spite of them, to which he has<lb/>attained. When Prof. B.
                    went to Washin-<lb/>gton, five or six years since, he was entrusted<lb/>with the <choice>
                        <sic>Meetorological</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">Meteorological</corr>
                    </choice> Department in the<lb/>Smithsonian Institute. At that time,
                    the<lb/>results of meteorological observations taken<lb/>at the several military
                    posts during more<lb/>than a quarter of a century, and at other<lb/>points by
                    State direction and reported to the<lb/>institute, were a mere mass of rubbish,
                    un-<lb/>compiled unclassified, and, for all purposes of<lb/>practical use
                    worthless. He completed the<lb/>labor of systemizing them: and after
                    having<lb/>thus brought order out of confusion, and<lb/><choice>
                        <sic>preparded</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">prepared</corr>
                    </choice> a valuable work upon American<lb/>climatology, the first contribution
                    of the kind<lb/>in the country, certain aristocratic old fogies<lb/>connected
                    with the Institution, who had<lb/>made their places mere sinecures,
                    attempted<lb/>to rob him of the fruits of his hard-earned<lb/>honors. He
                    resisted their pretensions, fought<lb/>them single-handed, and whatever he
                    has<lb/>since accomplished, has been in the face of a<lb/>persecution that knew
                    no honor nor merey.<lb/>He has, however, published his work, and<lb/>now has the
                    proud satisfaction of receiving<lb/>from Baron Von Humboldt the
                    following<lb/>tribute to the value of his labor. The com-<lb/>pliment is the
                    more marked, because, from<lb/>his great age and demands upon his time<lb/>the
                    Baron rarely indites such epistles himself<lb/>and this one, delivered to Prof.
                    Blodget by<lb/>the Prussian Minister in person, is all of it<lb/>in
                    Humboldt&#x2019;s own hand writing:</p><lb/><p>Lorin Blodget, Esq., Washington.</p><lb/><p>Sir: I am very sensible of the honor<lb/>you have done me in communicating your<lb/>important work on the Distribusion of<lb/>Heat over the vast area of the United<lb/>States.</p><lb/><p>When I returned from my Expedition to<lb/>the North of Asia, near the close of 1829, I<lb/>proposed to the Academy of St. Petersburgh<lb/>to establish Meteorological Observations at<lb/>Moscow, Pekin, Archangel, and in the Cau-<lb/>casus; and referred at length to what had<lb/>been done in your noble country since 1822<lb/>under care of Messrs. Lovell and Lawson<lb/>at a large number of military posts near its<lb/>extreme limits.</p><lb/><p>The work to which you have devoted<lb/>yourself with so much care and intelligence,<lb/>is a most meritorious one&#x2014;the graphic<lb/>representation of Climates by the isothermal<lb/>lines. For it I beg you to accept the expres-<lb/>sion of my lively gratitude.</p><lb/><p>As it is possible that you may not have re-<lb/>ceived a very recent memoir by M. Dove,<lb/>my fellow member of the Academy of Ber-<lb/>lin, 1 take the liberty to offer it to you. The<lb/>memoir is printed in the Journal of the Geo-<lb/>graphical Society of Berlin, for June, 1866<lb/>and you will find in it many points for further<lb/>comparison.</p><lb/><p>I renew, my dear sir, the assurance of the<lb/>high consideration with which I have the<lb/>honor to be</p><closer><salute>Yours very obedient<lb/>And very humble Servant,<lb/>A. V. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt</hi>.</salute></closer></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
