<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">HUMBOLDT&#x2019;S PROTEST.</hi></head><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<p>[J. S. Thrasher, the American Fillibuster, having printed an old<lb/>book of Humboldt&#x2019;s about Cuba, expurgating it of his decided aver-<lb/>sion to slavery, the old philosopher has published the following pro-<lb/>test, in which he spurns, with deserved scorn, the base attempt to<lb/>make him a party to that literary cowardice of our day which fails<lb/>to speak its honest sentiments on slavery. &#x201C;Humboldt,&#x201D; says a<lb/>correspendent of the <hi rendition="#i">Evening Post,</hi> &#x201C;is no fanatic, but upon the<lb/>question of property in human blood his Germanic love of justice<lb/>glows with a depth which he never conceals. I learn from a person<lb/>who is frequently in his society that he looks upon the attempts<lb/>now making in the United States to take slavery to the Pacific through<lb/>the free Western prairies, and across the Rocky Mountains, with an<lb/>utter abhorrence. &#x2018;To attempt to introduce, in 1856, slavery where<lb/>it does not now exist, Humboldt regards as a great crime,&#x2019; said my<lb/>informant.&#x201D;]</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">Under</hi> the title of <hi rendition="#i">Essai Politique sur l&#x2019; Isle
                        de Cuba,</hi><lb/>published in Paris in 1826, I collected together all
                    that<lb/>the large edition of my <hi rendition="#i">Voyage aux Régions
                        Equinoxiales<lb/>du Nouveau Continent</hi> contained upon the state of
                    agri-<lb/>culture and slavery in the Antilles. There appeared at<lb/>the same
                    time an English and a Spanish translation of<lb/>this work, the latter entitled
                        <hi rendition="#i">Ensayo Politico sobre la Isla<lb/>de Cuba</hi>, neither
                    of which omitted any of the frank and<lb/>open remarks which feelings of
                    humanity had inspired.<lb/>But there appears just now, strangely enough,
                    translated<lb/>from the Spanish translation, and not from the
                    French<lb/>original, and published by Derby and Jackson, in New<lb/>York, an
                    octavo volume of 400 pages, under the title of<lb/><hi rendition="#i">The Island
                        of Cuba</hi>, by Alexander Humboldt; with<lb/>notes and a preliminary essay
                    by J. S. Thrasher. The<lb/>translator, who has lived a long time on that
                    beautiful<lb/>island, has enriched my work by more recent <hi rendition="#i"
                        >data</hi> on the<lb/>subject of the numerical standing of the population,
                    of<lb/>the cultivation of the soil, and the state of trade, and,<lb/>generally
                    speaking, exhibited a charitable moderation in<lb/>his discussion of conflicting
                    opinions. I owe it, however,<lb/>to a moral feeling, that is now as lively in me
                    as it was<lb/>in 1826, publicly to complain that in a work which bears<lb/>my
                    name the entire seventh chapter of the Spanish trans-<lb/>lation, with which my
                        <hi rendition="#i">essai politique</hi> ended, has been<lb/>arbitrarily
                    omitted. To this very portion of my work I<lb/>attach greater importance than to
                    any astronomical ob-<lb/>servations, experiments of magnetic intensity, or
                    statisti-<lb/>cal statements. I have examined with frankness (I here<lb/>repeat
                    the words I used thirty years ago) whatever con-<lb/>cerns the organization of
                    human society in the colonies,<lb/>the unequal distinction of the rights and
                    enjoyments of<lb/>life, and the impending dangers which the wisdom of
                    legis-<lb/>lators and the moderation of freemen can avert, whatever<lb/>may be
                    the form of government.</p><lb/><p>It is the duty of the traveller who has been an eye-<lb/>witness of all that torments and degrades human nature<lb/>to cause the complaints of the unfortunate to reach those<lb/>whose duty it is to relieve them. I have repeated in this<lb/>treatise the fact that the ancient legislation of Spain on<lb/>the subject of slavery is less inhuman and atrocious than<lb/>that of the slave States on the American continent, north<lb/>or south of the equator.</p><lb/><p>A steady advocate as I am for the most unfettered ex-<lb/>pression of opinion in speech or in writing, I should never<lb/>have thought of complaining if I had been attacked on<lb/>account of my statements; but I do think I am entitled<lb/>to demand that in the free States of the continent of<lb/>America people should be allowed to read what has been<lb/>permitted to circulate from the first year of its appear-<lb/>ance in a Spanish translation.</p><lb/><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute></closer><lb/><dateline>Berlin, July, 1856.</dateline></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
