<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#b">Alexander Von Humboldt.</hi></hi></head><p>The extraordinary activity with which Alexander<lb/>Von Humboldt is gifted continues to manifest it-<lb/>self in intellectual labors which at his age are little<lb/>less than miraculous. A recent letter from him to<lb/>Hardinger, of Vienna, appears in a late number of<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">K&#x0153;lnische Zeitung</hi>, and from which we trans-<lb/>late the following:</p>
        <p>&#x201C;All my collections of chrystals made in Ameri-<lb/>ca and Siberia were carefully gone over lately and<lb/>experimented upon by Rose and Rammelsberg,<lb/>and many new things have been discovered relative<lb/>to the component parts of <hi rendition="#i">trachytes</hi>, (a variety of<lb/>lava,) and their family dissemination. The differ-<lb/>ent families of this mineral are often found precise-<lb/>ly alike in the most remotely distant regions,<lb/>while again we find marked differences in an over-<lb/>lying strata. Thirty four sheets of the last part of<lb/>my Kosmos are already printed. I hope to con-<lb/>clude the work with this year, and trust that it will<lb/>not escape your attention.&#x201D;</p>
        <p>There can be no question that the appearance of<lb/>a new volume of Kosmos will excite not a little at-<lb/>tention in the scientific world. When we remem-<lb/>ber that this is the work of one well nigh a cente-<lb/>narian, and that we have during the past year pub-<lb/>lished more than one extract from his letters, indi-<lb/>cating the most genial flow of spirits, the most un-<lb/>tiring industry, and all the enthusiasm for science<lb/>which could be expected in the youngest devotee,<lb/>we cannot but admit that a strong confirmation is<lb/>added by the instance of Von Humboldt to the<lb/>theories of those philosophers who maintain that<lb/>intellectual pursuits, when born out by easy circum-<lb/>stances, far from wearing life away, actually extend<lb/>its term.</p></div><lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
