<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
    <div n="1">
        <p><hi rendition="#k">Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer&#x2014;Letter from Hum-<lb/>
            boldt.</hi> Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer, the celebrated lady<lb/>
            traveller, who went twice round the world, is<lb/>
            now again in London, on her way to Madagas-<lb/>
            car, into the interior of which she wishes to pen-<lb/>
            etrate and explore. Her most recent travels ex-<lb/>
            tended over Germany, but she does not find in<lb/>
            the civilized parts of the world the same interest<lb/>
            as in the less cultivated regions. There, in the<lb/>
            bosom of nature, undisturbed by the presence of<lb/>
            man, she delights most.</p>
        <p>On this her last visit to the European conti-<lb/>
            nent, some of the most distinguished men came<lb/>
            forward unsolicited to do her honor. In Berlin<lb/>
            and Amsterdam, the Society of Natural History,<lb/>
            conferred upon her their respective diplomas,<lb/>
            and elected her an honorary member. The King<lb/>
            of Prussia graciously invited her to his residence<lb/>
            at Potsdam, and presented her with the golden<lb/>
            medal of the Humboldt order for arts and sciences.<lb/>
            The greatest living naturalist and philosopher,<lb/>
            Alexander von Humboldt, exhibited in her favor<lb/>
            the warmest friendship and admiration. As a<lb/>
            token of the affectionate interest he took in her<lb/>
            welfare, he presented her, on parting, with an<lb/>
            autograph letter, of which the following is a lit-<lb/>
            eral translation.</p>
        <p>&#x201C;All those who, in different regions of the<lb/>
            earth, preserve a remembrance of my name and<lb/>
            affection for my works, I earnestly beg to receive,<lb/>
            with friendly interest, and to aid with their coun-<lb/>
            sels, the bearer of these lines, Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer,<lb/>
            celebrated not only for the noble constancy that,<lb/>
            amidst so many dangers and privations, led her<lb/>
            twice round the globe, but above all, for the ami-<lb/>
            able simplicity and modesty pervading her works,<lb/>
            the truthfulness and philanthropy of her judg-<lb/>
            ment, as well as the independence, and at the<lb/>
            same time the delicacy of her sentiments. En-<lb/>
            joying the confidence and friendship of this re-<lb/>
            spectable lady, I blame her for, though I cannot<lb/>
            refrain from admiring, that indomitable energy<lb/>
            of character which she displayed wherever called<lb/>
            &#x2014;I should say, impelled by an unconquerable<lb/>
            passion of exploring nature and the habits of the<lb/>
            various human races. As the oldest living trav-<lb/>
            eller, I feel a desire to offer to Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer<lb/>
            this slender proof of my high and respectful es-<lb/>
            teem. <hi rendition="#et">Alexander Humboldt.</hi>
            &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Potsdam City, Castle, June</hi> 8, 1856&#x201D;</p>
        <p>Mrs. Ida Pfeiffer might justly to be proud of<lb/>
            so very flattering a testimony from one of the<lb/>
            most eminent men living; but her modesty is<lb/>
            equal to her good sense, tact, patience, persever-<lb/>
            ance, power of endurance and simple habits.<lb/>
        London Morning Star.</p>
    </div>
    <lb/>
</body>
    <back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
