<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-06-04" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-11-30" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="xi" facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#et">
                    <hi rendition="#i">&#x201C;Berlin, June</hi> 18, 1855.</hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#et">&#x2018;My dear Friend and &#x2019;Travelling Companion,&#x2019;<note place="foot" n="*">A playful allusion to my academical name, &#x201C;Bonpland.&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">B. S.</hi>
                    </note>
                </hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;Your kind letter of the 13th instant has been a source of great<lb break="yes"/>pleasure to me. I received it the moment of my return from<lb break="yes"/>Potsdam, early this morning, there being no postal delivery on a<lb break="yes"/>Sunday at Berlin. As there is only an hour left until the depar-<lb break="no"/>ture of the mail-train, and as you are pleased to long for a speedy<lb break="yes"/>answer, I must unfortunately be very brief in expressing my high<lb break="yes"/>sense of gratitude for the honour you intend to confer upon me.<lb break="yes"/>A dedication from you, dear Seemann, cannot but be extremely<lb break="yes"/>agreeable and flattering, and I gladly accept your favour, but on<lb break="yes"/>the express condition that you will simply call me your friend,<lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="xii" facs="#f0002"/> and avoid every species of titulation, which is quite contrary to<lb break="yes"/>my way of thinking. ... Your Work will, I am convinced, go<lb break="yes"/>through several editions; it begins in a jovial strain, but never<lb break="yes"/>oversteps, according to my opinion, the boundaries of good taste;<lb break="yes"/>it may be called popular, because, without supposing the reader<lb break="yes"/>to be possessed of any great botanical knowledge, it supplies him<lb break="yes"/>with an agreeable literary recreation. The &#x2018;low connections&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>(p. 12) with the plebeian Grasses have not proved a serious disad-<lb break="no"/>vantage to your patrician, aristocratic Palms. ... I have read<lb break="yes"/>line for line of the sheets you sent, and as a proof thereof note<lb break="yes"/>two unfortunate misprints, which I discovered at page 33 and 34.<lb break="yes"/>The first is <hi rendition="#i">Moricheles,</hi> instead of <hi rendition="#i">Morichales.</hi> The terminations<lb break="yes" />indicative of forests (<hi rendition="#i">Waldendigungen</hi>) form themselves in Spanish<lb break="yes"/>always in &#x2018;al&#x2019; or &#x2018;ar;&#x2019; thus, Pino, Pinal or Pinar (Pine-forest);<lb break="yes"/>Olivo, Olivar (Olive-forest); Roble, Robledar (Oak-forest). The<lb break="yes"/>second misprint is <hi rendition="#i">Cauca</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Erenato,</hi> instead of <hi rendition="#i">Caura</hi> and<lb break="yes"/>
                <hi rendition="#i">Erevato.</hi> Of the Caura, which flows into the Erevato, I have<lb break="yes"/>published a special chart. Caura, again, is a tributary of the<lb break="yes"/>Orinoco, whilst Cauca is a tributary of the Magdalena. You<lb break="yes"/>will perceive from this that I have carefully perused your in-<lb break="no"/>structive pages. The description of the great Palm-house at<lb break="yes"/>Kew, and especially the paragraphs which immediately succeed<lb break="yes"/>that, have pleased me very much indeed. Pray do not omit to<lb break="yes"/>mention the surprise travellers experience when beholding for the<lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="xiii" facs="#f0003"/> first time European forms (<hi rendition="#i" >Pinus</hi> for instance) growing together<lb break="yes"/>with tropical ones (Palms, etc.) in the same forest, as is the case<lb break="yes"/>at Chilpanzingo, on the western declivity of the Mexican table-<lb break="no"/>land, or in that, on account of its mahogany, frequented Isle of<lb break="yes"/>Pines, south of Cuba. Peter Martyr (Angheria) states on the<lb break="yes"/>authority of one of Columbus&#x2019;s letters that <hi rendition="#i">Pineta</hi> and <hi rendition="#i" >Palmite</hi>
                <lb break="yes"/>grew there together. The Conquistadores noticed a coniferous<lb break="yes"/>plant with fruit resembling Olives (<hi rendition="#i">parezen azeytunos del Azarate<lb break="yes"/>de Sevilla</hi>), which I take to be a species of the genus <hi rendition="#i">Podocarpus.</hi>
                <lb break="yes"/>As your Work will be much read, you must not forget to dwell<lb break="yes"/>upon the <hi rendition="#i">oppositum</hi> of the numerous littoral plants,&#x2014;the little-<lb break="maybe"/>known, small group of mountainous or alpine Palms (<hi rendition="#i">Ceroxylon<lb break="yes"/>Andicola, Oreodoxa frigida,</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Kunthia montana</hi>). <hi rendition="#i" >Ceroxylon<lb break="yes"/>Andicola</hi> I found in the cordillera of the Pass of Quindiu, be-<lb break="no"/>tween Ibague and Cartago, not lower on the declivity than<lb break="yes"/>7930, not higher than 9700 English feet (you could say be-<lb break="no"/>tween 7900 and 9700 feet), in company of Podocarpus-trees and<lb break="yes"/>
                <hi rendition="#i">Quercus Granatensis.</hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <closer>
                <salute>
                    <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;I am, etc.,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt.</hi>&#x201D;</hi>
                </salute>
            </closer>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 