<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>

<pb n="526" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Letter from Humboldt.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;Some persons reported the author of Cosmos to<lb/>be a believer in the mysteries of table moving, because he had approved of the<lb/>theory of the electricity of the nerves, started by Du Boys Reymonds. Dr.<lb/>Jobard thereupon wrote to Humboldt, to ascertain his opinion about spiritualism,<lb/>and received the following answer:</p><lb/><dateline>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Berlin</hi>, April 2d, 1856.</dateline>
                    </div>
                    <div><p>&#x2014;You have written to me, my dear sir, as you always<lb/>do, a most amiable letter, but I
                    am not able to give you my opinion upon the<lb/>possibility of the existence of
                    the various kinds of mineral, vegetable, animal,<lb/>direct or indirect cerebral
                    electricity. I have a holy horror of all kinds of pine<lb/>wood spiritualism and
                    psychographic mysticisms. You increase my horror by<lb/>the ghost of that
                    ephemeric being of reason, which is to receive intelligence<lb/>from the
                    thoughts of those persons who surround the table. You know that<lb/>Geoffrey
                    Saint Hilaire pretends to have sweat the oxyde of thought while in<lb/>Egypt,
                    and you, my dear friend, will say, that my incredulity is the simple
                    con-<lb/>sequence of my laziness. I submit willingly to this reproach, for I am
                    convinced<lb/>that the friendship, which you always extended to me, will not be
                    diminished if<lb/>I can be instrumental in leading you out of the obscure path
                    of error. I rely<lb/>on your forgiveness.</p><closer><salute>A. V. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi>&#x201D;</salute></closer></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
