<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#b">Baron Von Humboldt&#x2019;s Political Essay
                        on<lb/>Cuba&#x2014;Letter from the Author on the omis-<lb/>sion of a Chapter
                        by the Translator.</hi></head>
                <lb/>
                <p>Baron <hi rendition="#k">von Humboldt</hi> has caused the fol-<lb/>lowing article
                    to be inserted in the <hi rendition="#i">Spenersche Zei-<lb/>tung:</hi></p>
                <lb/>
                <p>&#x201C;Under the title of <hi rendition="#i">Essai Politique sur l&#x2019;Isle
                        de<lb/>Cuba,</hi> published in Paris in 1826, I collected together<lb/>all
                    that the large edition of my <hi rendition="#i">Voyage aux
                        Régions<lb/>Equinoxiales du Nouveau Continent</hi> contained upon<lb/>the
                    state of Agriculture and Slavery in the Antilles.<lb/>There appeared at the same
                    time an English and a<lb/>Spanish translation of this work, the latter
                        entitled<lb/><hi rendition="#i">Ensayo Politico sobre la Isla de Cuba,</hi>
                    neither of which<lb/>omitted any of the frank and open remarks
                    which<lb/>feelings of humanity had inspired. But there ap-<lb/>pears just now,
                    strangely enough, translated from<lb/>the Spanish translation, and not from the
                    French<lb/>original, and published by <hi rendition="#k">Derby &amp;
                        Jackson</hi> in New-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>York, an octavo volume of 400
                    pages under the title<lb/>of <hi rendition="#i">The Island of Cuba,</hi> by <hi
                        rendition="#k">Alexander Humboldt;</hi><lb/>with notes and a preliminary
                    essay, by J. S. <hi rendition="#k">Thrash-<lb/>er.</hi> The translator, who has
                    lived a long time on<lb/>that beautitul island, has enriched my work<lb/>by more
                    recent <hi rendition="#i">data</hi> on the subject of the nu-<lb/>merical
                    standing of the population, of the cultiva-<lb/>tion of the soil, and the state
                    of trade, and, gene-<lb/>rally speaking, exhibited a charitable
                    moderation<lb/>in his discussion of conflicting opinions. I owe it,<lb/>however,
                    to a moral feeling, that is now as lively in<lb/>me as it was in 1826, publicly
                    to complain that in a<lb/>work which bears my name the entire seventh
                    chap-<lb/>ter of the Spanish translation, with which my <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Essai<lb/>Politique</hi> ended, has been arbitrarily omitted. To
                    this<lb/>very portion of my work I attach greater importance<lb/>than to any
                    astronomical observations, experiments<lb/>of magnetic intensity, or statistical
                    statements.<lb/>&#x2018;J&#x2019;ai examiné avec franchise (I here repeat
                    the<lb/>words which I used 30 years ago) ce qui
                    concerne<lb/>l&#x2019;organisation des sociétés humaines dans les
                    colo-<lb/>nies, l&#x2019;inégale répartition des droits et des jouis-<lb/>sances
                    de la vie, les dangers mena&#x00E7;ants que la sagesse<lb/>des législateurs et
                    la modération des bommes libres<lb/>peuvent éloigner, quelleque soit la forme
                    des Gouv-<lb/>ernements. Il appartient au voyageur qui a vu de<lb/>près ce qui
                    tourmente et dégrade la nature humaine<lb/>de faire parvenir les plaintes de
                    l&#x2019;infortune à ceux<lb/>qui ont le devoir de les soulager. J&#x2019;ai
                    rappelé dans<lb/>cet exposé combien l&#x2019;ancienne législation
                    Espag-<lb/>nolle de l&#x2019;esclavage est moins inhumaine et moins<lb/>atroce
                    que celle des Etats à esclaves dans l&#x2019;Amérique<lb/>continentale au nord
                    et au sud de l&#x2019;équateur.&#x2019; A<lb/>steady advocate as I am for the
                    most unfettered ex-<lb/>pression of opinion in speech or in writing. I
                    should<lb/>never have thought of complaining if I had been at-<lb/>tacked on
                    account of my statements; but I do<lb/>think I am entitled to demand that in the
                    Free<lb/>States of the continent of America, people should be<lb/>allowed to
                    read what has been permitted to circu-<lb/>late from the first year of its
                    appearance in a Span-<lb/>ish transtation</p>
                <lb/>
                <closer><signed><hi rendition="#et">ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT.</hi></signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <dateline><hi rendition="#k">Berlin,</hi> July,
                    1856.&#x201D;</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>

    </text>
</TEI>
