<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#b">Mr. Thrasher&#x2019;s Book on Cuba.</hi></head>
                <lb/>
                <p>The very valuable and instructive book on<lb/>
                    Cuba, which was published in New York last<lb/>
                    season, by our fellow-citizen, Mr. John S.<lb/>
                    Thrasher, has been recently made the theme<lb/>
                    of discussion, by a complaint made in Europe<lb/>
                    by Baron Humboldt, that Mr, Thrasher omit-<lb/>
                    ted a material chapter in the work translated,<lb/>
                    of which the Baron is the author. We pub-<lb/>
                    lish below the article in which Humboldt<lb/>
                    makes this criticism, and the reply which Mr.<lb/>
                    Thrasher has put forth in New York. Mr.<lb/>
                    Thrasher explains that he published every<lb/>
                    thing from Humboldt contained in the vo-<lb/>
                    lume, which had reference to the subject of<lb/>
                    Cuba, up to the point at which Mr. Thrasher&#x2019;s<lb/>
                    personal inquiries and investigations com-<lb/>
                    menced. There is no ground for imputing<lb/>
                any mutilation or suppression.</p>
                <p>While on the subject, we may say that the<lb/>
                    book of Mr. Thrasher is one of very great in-<lb/>
                    terest, very full of important and carefully<lb/>
                    prepared information on the state, progress,<lb/>
                    and prospects of Cuba&#x2014;social, political and<lb/>
                    material&#x2014;and the most complete exposition of<lb/>
                    the whole of the &#x201C;Cuban question&#x201D; which has<lb/>
                    yet been published in this country, and ought<lb/>
                to be universally read.</p>
                <p>The card of Humboldt, which follows, pays<lb/>
                    a high tribute to the literary and statistical<lb/>
                    merits of the book, which has such substan-<lb/>
                tial claims to American study.</p>
                <p>The following is the article of Baron Hum-<lb/>
                    boldt, which he caused to be inserted in the<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Spenersche Zeitung:</hi>
                </p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Under the title of &#x201C;Essai Politique sur l&#x2019;Isle de<lb/>
                    Cuba,&#x201D; published in Paris in 1826, I collected to-<lb/>
                    gether all that the large edition of my &#x201C;Voyage aux<lb/>
                    Régions Equinoxiales du Nouveau Continent&#x201D; con-<lb/>
                    tained upon the state of agriculture and slavery in<lb/>
                    the Antilles. There appeared at the same time an<lb/>
                    English and a Spanish translation of this work, the<lb/>
                    latter entitled &#x201C;Ensayo Politico sobre la Isla de Cu-<lb/>
                    ba,&#x201D; neither of which omitted any of the frank and<lb/>
                    open remarks which feelings of humanity had in-<lb/>
                    spired. But there appears just now, strangely<lb/>
                    enough, translated from the Spanish translation, and<lb/>
                    not from the French original, and published by Derby<lb/>
                    &amp; Jackson in New York, an octavo volume of 400<lb/>
                    pages, under the title of &#x201C;The Island of Cuba,&#x201D; by<lb/>
                    Alexander Humboldt; with notes and a preliminary<lb/>
                    essay, by J. S. Thrasher. The translator, who has<lb/>
                    lived a long time on that beautiful island, has enriched<lb/>
                    my work by more recent <hi rendition="#i">data</hi> on the subject of the<lb/>
                    numerical standing of the population, of the cultiva-<lb/>
                    tion of the soil, and the state of trade, and, gene-<lb/>
                    rally speaking, exhibited a charitable moderation in<lb/>
                    his discussion of conflicting opinions. I owe it, how-<lb/>
                    ever, to a moral feeling, that is now as lively in me as<lb/>
                    it was in 1826, publicly to complain that in a work<lb/>
                    which bears my name, the entire seventh chapter<lb/>
                    of the Spanish translation, with which my &#x201C;Es-<lb/>
                    sai Politique&#x201D; ended, has been arbitrarily omitted.<lb/>
                    To this very portion of my work I attach greater<lb/>
                    importance than to any astronomical observations,<lb/>
                    experiments of magnetic intensity, or statistical<lb/>
                    statements. &#x201C;J&#x2019;ai examiné avec franchise (I here<lb/>
                    repeat the words which I used thirty years ago) ce<lb/>
                    qui concerne l&#x2019;organisation des sociétés humaines<lb/>
                    dans les colonies, l&#x2019;inégale répartition des droits et<lb/>
                    des jouissances de la vie, les dangers mena&#x00E7;ants que<lb/>
                    la sagesse des législateurs et la modération des<lb/>
                    hommes libres peuvent éloigner, quelleque soit la<lb/>
                    forme des Gouvernements. Il appertient au voya-<lb/>
                    geur qui a vu de près ce qui tourmente et degrade la<lb/>
                    nature humaine de faire parvenir les plaintes de l&#x2019;in-<lb/>
                    fortune à ceux qui ont le devoir de les soulager. J&#x2019;ai<lb/>
                    rappelé dans cet exposé combien l'ancienne législa-<lb/>
                    tion Espagnolle de l&#x2019;esclavage est moins inhumaine<lb/>
                    et moins atroce que celle des Etats à esclaves dans<lb/>
                    l&#x2019;Amérique continentale au nord et au sud de l&#x2019;équa-<lb/>
                    teur.&#x201D; A steady advocate as I am for the most un-<lb/>
                    fettered expression of opinion in speech or in writ-<lb/>
                    ing, I should never have thought of complaining if I<lb/>
                    had been attacked on account of my statements; but<lb/>
                    I do think I am entitled to demand that in the free<lb/>
                    States of the continent of America, people should be<lb/>
                    allowed to read what has been permitted to circulate<lb/>
                    from the first year of its appearance in a Spanish<lb/>
                    translation.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#right"><hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt</hi>.</hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
                <dateline><hi rendition="#i">Berlin</hi>, July, 1856.</dateline>
            </div>
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
            <div>
                <p>Mr. Thrasher&#x2019;s reply is as follows:</p><lb/>
                <p>To the Editor of the Herald:</p><lb/></div>
            <div>
                    <dateline><hi rendition="#right"><hi rendition="#k">New York</hi>, <hi rendition="#i">August</hi> 13, 1856.</hi></dateline><lb/></div>
            <div><p><hi rendition="#i">Dear Sir</hi>&#x2014;I have noticed in your journal an article<lb/>
                    which has been published by Baron Humboldt in the<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Spenersche Zeitung</hi>, in relation to my translation of<lb/>
                    his essay on the Island of Cuba, published by Derby<lb/>
                    &amp; Jackson. As your readers may be led to infer that<lb/>
                    I have willfully mutilated a work of that great writer,<lb/>
                    I request that you will publish the following explana-<lb/>
                tion.</p>
                <p>Being destrous of placing in the hands of Ameri-<lb/>
                    can readers such information in relation to the Island<lb/>
                    of Cuba as my studies had enabled me to obtain, I<lb/>
                    made the translation referred to, as being the best<lb/>
                    work I had ever seen on the subject. In under-<lb/>
                    taking this labor I was not aware that any English<lb/>
                    version of the work had ever been made, and I<lb/>
                    used the Spanish edition for text simply because,<lb/>
                    being ignorant of the French language, I could<lb/>
                not translate the essay from that tongue.</p>
                <p>As it was written thirty years ago, during which<lb/>
                    time the material development of Cuba had been<lb/>
                    very great, a continuation of Baron Humboldt&#x2019;s re-<lb/>
                    marks became necessary, in order to bring the sub-<lb/>
                    ject matter up to the present time, and this labor I<lb/>
                    have inserted in notes. In carrying out the design<lb/>
                    of a work on Cuba, I deemed that I could not take<lb/>
                    up the subject at a more appropriate point than that<lb/>
                where the illustrious author had left it in 1825.</p>
                <p>The chapter complained of as being omitted is a<lb/>
                    distinct essay &#x201C;On Slavery,&#x201D; and is so entitled in the<lb/>
                    volume where it is published. Cuba is only inciden-<lb/>
                    tally alluded to in it, while it begins with this express<lb/>
                    declaration: &#x201C;I here close the @@, or Political<lb/>
                    Essay on Cuba, in which I have presented the state<lb/>
                    of this important Spanish possession as it at present<lb/>
                    exists.&#x201D; Baron Humboldt&#x2019;s complaint is not that I<lb/>
                    have mutilated his essay on Cuba, but that I have not<lb/>
                    published all the matter contained in the volume from<lb/>
                    which I have translated his work on that important<lb/>
                    island. I would add that so one entertains a higher<lb/>
                    or more sincere regard than I do for the great and<lb/>
                venerable name of Alexander von Humboldt.</p>
                <p>I would ask those journals that may have alluded<lb/>
                    to or published the article in question to publish also<lb/>
                    this letter. Very respectfully, yours,<lb/></p>
                <closer>
                    <salute><hi rendition="#right">J. S. <hi rendition="#k">Thrasher</hi>.</hi></salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 