<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Humboldt and Agassiz</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:21</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VII.107</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-01-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-01-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1856-Humboldt_and_Agassiz-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Humboldt and Agassiz</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1856</date>
          <pubPlace>Boston, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;Boston Daily Advertiser&lt;/i&gt; 88:88/13206 (14. Oktober 1856), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <relatedItem type="reprint">
            <bibl>in: "Blätter der Erinnerung an A.v.H, Gesammelt von ***", Berlin 1860, S. 19 ff. und in: "Das Humboldt-Buch" AvH, Eine Darstellung seines Lebens und wissenschaftlichen Wirkens .... dem Andenken des unsterblichen Groß-Meisters ... gewidmet von Dr. W.F.A. Zimmermann". Berlin III 1859, S. 58 ff. (mit geringen Abweichungen in der Interpunktion) [Zimmermann ist angeblich ein Pseudonym für C.G.W. Vollmer]</bibl>
          </relatedItem>
        </notesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung, Schriftgradverkleinerung.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="2" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt and Agassiz.&#x2014;</hi>
                </head>
                <p>We take great<lb break="yes"/>pleasure in laying before our readers and<lb break="yes"/>commending to their particular attention the<lb break="yes" />subjoined paper, which has been prepared by<lb break="yes"/>a friend for insertion in our columns. It bears<lb break="yes"/>witness to the friendly relations subsisting be-<lb break="no"/>tween the two great lights in the modern<lb break="yes"/>science of natural history, and to the interest<lb break="yes"/>felt by Humboldt in the success of Agassiz&#x2019;s<lb break="yes"/>magnificent work, now preparing for publica-<lb break="no" />tion here:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#et">[For the Boston Daily Advertiser.]</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Professor Agassiz may be considered as the pupil<lb break="yes"/>of the illustrious Humboldt, and his destined succes-<lb break="no"/>sor in the realm of natural science. For many years<lb break="yes"/>there has been a strong and affectionate connection<lb break="yes"/>between them; and if we remember right, Agassiz<lb break="yes"/>in early life, was indebted for kindly and opportune<lb break="yes"/>assistance in his investigations to the generosity of<lb break="yes"/>his great friend. On the part of each of these men,<lb break="yes"/>there has always been the most cordial and thorough<lb break="yes"/>appreciation of the merits of the other. The labors<lb break="yes"/>of Agassiz are recognized in the Kosmos of Hum-<lb break="no" />boldt, in terms which show the high estimation<lb break="yes"/>placed upon them by the first of living philosophers;<lb break="yes"/>and Agassiz has never failed to express the affection-<lb break="no"/>ate veneration which he cherishes for the genius, at-<lb break="no"/>tainments and character of the mighty master. The<lb break="yes"/>pursuits of Agassiz in this country, have been watched<lb break="yes"/>by his venerable friend with unceasing interest and<lb break="yes"/>hearty sympathy. Humboldt is now eighty-seven<lb break="yes"/>years old, but his faculties are still unimpaired, and<lb break="yes"/>his labors as zealously prosecuted as ever. Three<lb break="yes"/>years ago we had the pleasure of a conversation with<lb break="yes"/>this extraordinary man. The vivacity of his manner,<lb break="yes"/>and the rapidity of his utterance betrayed no tokens<lb break="yes"/>of age. The liveliness of his interest, in all that was<lb break="yes"/>passing in the world, the richness of his knowledge,<lb break="yes"/>and the fine humanity that breathed in all he said,<lb break="yes"/>made the hours passed in his society a memorable<lb break="yes" />episode in life. We have lately read a letter writ-<lb break="no"/>ten by a distinguished literary gentleman, who knew<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt many years ago, and has recently renewed<lb break="yes"/>his intercourse with him. Time, it appears, has had<lb break="yes"/>some effect upon his person; but his eye is still<lb break="yes"/>bright and quick, and he talks even faster and more<lb break="yes"/>richly than he ever did. His benevolence and desire<lb break="yes"/>to serve everybody seem to increase with his years.<lb break="yes"/>His attentions to his friends are incessant; he<lb break="yes" />writes notes, accompanies them to the studios<lb break="yes"/>of artists, points out the objects which deserve to be<lb break="yes"/>seen, tells them what to do, just as John Kenyon&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>the most genial of men&#x2014;does to the stranger in<lb break="yes"/>London. He receives about four thousand letters a<lb break="yes"/>year and answers more than half of them with his<lb break="yes"/>own hand; he dines daily with the King, sitting<lb break="yes"/>from three o&#x2019;clock till about six, and sups with him<lb break="yes"/>at nine. He holds the office of Chamberlain, and<lb break="yes" />contrary to the wishes of the King, performs all its<lb break="yes"/>duties in his turn, standing in the ante-chamber<lb break="yes"/>from six to eight hours a day, many days in the<lb break="yes"/>year, refusing the indulgence of a chair. He rises<lb break="yes"/>about seven every morning, looks over his letters,<lb break="yes"/>breakfasts, answers notes, receives visitors&#x2014;dines,<lb break="yes"/>as already mentioned, with the King, returns home<lb break="yes"/>and takes a short nap, writes letters until supper,<lb break="yes"/>and goes to work about half past ten at night, work-<lb break="no"/>ing on till three o&#x2019;clock in the morning, and some-<lb break="no"/>times later, attempting no continuous scientific la-<lb break="no"/>bor, except during these hours, when his friends<lb break="yes" />are asleep. &#x201C;And this man,&#x201D; adds our friend,<lb break="yes" />&#x201C;will be 87 years old on the 14th of this present<lb break="yes"/>month (September):&#x2014;and while, on the one hand,<lb break="yes"/>if you were to ask the well dressed people you meet<lb break="yes"/>in the streets or on the railroad, who is the greatest<lb break="yes"/>man in Prussia, they would answer uanimously&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt.&#x2014;I verily believe, that on the other hand,<lb break="yes"/>nobody who is in the habit of seeing him will doubt<lb break="yes"/>that his kindness of heart is more remarkable than<lb break="yes"/>his genius, philosophy and vast knowledge. It is<lb break="yes" />reputation worth having.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Such is the impression this great and good man<lb break="yes"/>makes on intelligent travellers.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We have given the above little sketch by way of<lb break="yes"/>introduction to an extract from a letter of his, to<lb break="yes"/>Professor Agassiz, which, at the express desire of<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt, we translate and publish. It is on a subject<lb break="yes"/>of general scientific interest; and as the time for the<lb break="yes"/>publication of the first volume of the great work of<lb break="yes"/>Agassiz draws near, it will not be uninteresting to the<lb break="yes"/>subscribers and to the public, to know the feelings<lb break="yes"/>with which so illustrious a philosopher regards it.<lb break="yes"/>The extract is as follows. It is dated Berlin, Sept.<lb break="yes"/>1, 1856:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The visit of our distinguished and excellent<lb break="yes"/>friend, Mr. George Ticknor, to this city, where he<lb break="yes"/>resided in his youth, and where he left so many<lb break="yes"/>honorable remembrances, has made known to me a<lb break="yes"/>fact, which has greatly troubled me. I learn that<lb break="yes"/>by an unfortunate concurrence of circumstances,<lb break="yes" />undoubtedly accidental, you, my dear Agassiz, have<lb break="yes"/>never received the letter of mine, which expressed<lb break="yes"/>very strongly the joy I have shared with all the<lb break="yes"/>sincere lovers of science, on the subject of your<lb break="yes"/>beautiful and important enterprise, the <hi rendition="#i">Contribu-<lb break="no"/>tions to the Natural History of the United States.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Doubtless you must have been surprised by my long<lb break="yes"/>silence, considering the ties of intimate affection<lb break="yes"/>which have bound us together since your first resi-<lb break="no"/>dence in Paris, as well as the high admiration I have<lb break="yes"/>never ceased to entertain for the great and solid<lb break="yes"/>labors, for which we are indebted to your sagacious<lb break="yes"/>genius, and your incomparable intellectual energy.<lb break="yes"/>Interested, like you, in the progress made in that<lb break="yes"/>part of the world, where the cultivation of the scien-<lb break="no"/>ces is making such rapid strides, I approve above<lb break="yes" />all, the generality of conceptions, which is the basis<lb break="yes"/>of the plan you have traced out. I admire that<lb break="yes"/>long series of physiological investigations, com-<lb break="no"/>mencing with the embryology of organisms <hi rendition="#i">called</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>simple and inferior, and ascending by degrees to the<lb break="yes"/>organisms which are more complicated; I admire<lb break="yes" />that constant attention to the comparison of the<lb break="yes"/>types belonging to the present condition of our planet,<lb break="yes"/>and the types found only in a fossil state, and which<lb break="yes"/>abound in the immense area between the shores oppo-<lb break="no"/>site to Europe and Northern Asia. The generous inter-<lb break="no"/>est displayed in the United States, when your vast en-<lb break="no"/>terprise was announced, my excellent friend, has<lb break="yes"/>given a very flattering proof of the ever increasing<lb break="yes"/>intellectual interest, and of the honorable confidence<lb break="yes"/>manifested for talent and a noble character. I am<lb break="yes"/>charged by the King, who feels the importance of<lb break="yes" />your former labors, and retains for you the affection-<lb break="no"/>ate esteem which he showed for you personally,<lb break="yes"/>when he saw you among your collections, to place<lb break="yes"/>his name at the head of the list of your numerous<lb break="yes"/>subscribers. He hopes that an excursion across the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Atlantic Valley</hi> may some day conduct you, who<lb break="yes"/>have boldly scaled the lofty summits of the Alps, to<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i">historic hill</hi> of Sans Souci. I have it much at<lb break="yes"/>heart that you should allow an extract of this not<lb break="yes"/>very legible letter to be published, since it contains<lb break="yes"/>the sincere proof of the lively satisfaction with which<lb break="yes"/>I have welcomed your great and useful enterprise. &#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 