<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-03" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="2" facs="#f0001"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Humboldt and Agassiz.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We claim Prof. Agassiz as an American sa-<lb break="no"/>van. If there were no other title for that<lb break="yes"/>claim, we have his baptism in the alluvium of<lb break="yes"/>the North American Continent, rolled down<lb break="yes" />by the floods of the Father of Waters, which<lb break="yes"/>many of our readers will remember, on the<lb break="yes"/>occasion of his visit here three years since,<lb break="yes"/>when he so pertinaciously pursued the gar<lb break="yes"/>fish and the alligator through the mud of our<lb break="yes" />lakes and bayons. But the vast light which<lb break="yes"/>he has poured upon the scientific world by his<lb break="yes"/>labors, not only on the land, but upon the<lb break="yes"/>coral homes of the ocean of this continent,<lb break="yes"/>entitle him eminently to that name, and the<lb break="yes" />great work upon the &#x201C;Natural History of the<lb break="yes"/>United States,&#x201D; which he is now preparing for<lb break="yes"/>publication, will be but another evidence of<lb break="yes"/>its truth.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Prof. Agassiz may be considered as the pu-<lb break="no"/>pil of the illustrious Humboldt, and his des-<lb break="no"/>tined successor in the realms of science, add-<lb break="no"/>ing thus another proof of the westward march<lb break="yes" />of empire. For many years there has been a<lb break="yes"/>strong and affectionate connection between<lb break="yes"/>them, and it has been stated that in early life<lb break="yes"/>Agassiz was indebted for kindly and oppor-<lb break="no"/>tune assistance to the generoeity of his great<lb break="yes" />friend. The labors of Agassiz are recognized<lb break="yes"/>in the Cosmos of Humboldt in torms that<lb break="yes"/>show the high estimation placed upon them by<lb break="yes"/>the first of living philosophers; and Agassiz<lb break="yes"/>has never falled to express the veneration<lb break="yes" />which he cherishes for the genius and attain-<lb break="no"/>ments of the mighty master. The pursuits of<lb break="yes"/>Agassiz in this country have been watched<lb break="yes"/>with uncensing interest and hearty sympathy.<lb break="yes"/>The following letter, dated Berlin, Sept. 1, of<lb break="yes" />this year, which was published in the Boston<lb break="yes"/>Advertiser, is an evldence of this, and was<lb break="yes"/>made public, as will be seen, at the express<lb break="yes"/>desire of Baron Humboldt:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>The visit of our distinguished and excellent<lb break="yes"/>friend, Mr. George Ticknor, to this city, where<lb break="yes"/>he resided in his youth, and where he left no<lb break="yes"/>many honorable remembrances, has made<lb break="yes" />known to me a fact, which has greatly troubled<lb break="yes"/>me. I learn that, by an unfortunate concur-<lb break="no"/>rence of circumstances, undoubtedly acci-<lb break="no"/>dental, you, my dear Agassiz, have never re-<lb break="no"/>ceived the letter of mine, which expressed<lb break="yes"/>very strongly the joy I have shared with all<lb break="yes"/>the sincere lovers of science, on the subject<lb break="yes"/>of your beautiful and important enterprise,<lb break="yes"/>the &#x201C;Contributions to the Natural History of<lb break="yes"/>the United States.&#x201D; Doubtless you must have<lb break="yes"/>been surprised by my long silence, consider-<lb break="no"/>ing the ties of intimate affection which have<lb break="yes"/>bound us together since your first residence<lb break="yes"/>in Paris, as well as the high admiration I have<lb break="yes"/>never ceased to entertain for the great and<lb break="yes"/>solid labors, for which we are indebted to<lb break="yes"/>your sagacious genius, and your incompara-<lb break="no"/>ble intellectual energy. Interested, like you,<lb break="yes"/>in the progress made in that of the world,<lb break="yes"/>where the cultivation of the sciences is making<lb break="yes"/>such rapid strides, I approve above all, the<lb break="yes" />generality of conceptions, which is the basis<lb break="yes"/>of the plan you have traced out. I admire<lb break="yes"/>that long series of physiological investiga-<lb break="no"/>tions, commencing with the embryology of<lb break="yes"/>organisms called simple and inferior, and as-<lb break="no" />cending by dogrees to the organisms which<lb break="yes"/>are more complicated. I admire that con-<lb break="no"/>stant attention to the comparison of the types<lb break="yes"/>belonging to the present condition of our<lb break="yes"/>planet, and the types found only in a fossil<lb break="yes" />state, and which abound in the immense area<lb break="yes"/>between the shores opposite to Europe and<lb break="yes"/>Northern Asia. The generous interest dis-<lb break="no"/>played in the United States, when your vast<lb break="yes"/>enterprise was announced, my excellent<lb break="yes"/>friend, has given a very flattering proof of<lb break="yes"/>the ever increasing intellectual interest, and<lb break="yes"/>of the honorable confidence manifested for<lb break="yes"/>talent and a noble character. I am charged<lb break="yes"/>by the King, who feels the importance of your<lb break="yes" />former labors, and retains for you the affec-<lb break="no"/>tionate esteem which he showed for you per-<lb break="no"/>sonally, when he saw you among your collec-<lb break="no"/>tions, to place his name at the head of the list<lb break="yes"/>of your numerous subscribers. He hopes<lb break="yes"/>that an excursion across the Atlantic Valley<lb break="yes"/>may some day conduct you, who have boldly<lb break="yes"/>scaled the lofty summits of the Alps, to the<lb break="yes"/>historic hill of Sans Souci. I have it much at<lb break="yes" />heart that you should allow an extract of this<lb break="yes"/>not very legible letter to be published, since<lb break="yes"/>it contains the sincere proof of the lively sat-<lb break="no"/>isfaction with which I have welcomed your<lb break="yes"/>great and useful enterprise.</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 