<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-06-04" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-01-10" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>An Original Letter from Humboldt&#x2014;Handsome<lb break="yes"/>Compliment to an American Officer.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Correspondence of the Pennsylvania Inquirer ]</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Washington</hi>, Feb. 7, 1857.&#x2014;In the absence<lb break="yes"/>of anything particularly interesting or impor-<lb break="no"/>tant in the political world, you and you read-<lb break="no"/>ers will, I know, be delighted with the treasure<lb break="yes"/>I send you in the shape of an original letter<lb break="yes"/>from the venerable and generated Humboldt.<lb break="yes"/>It has never before been published, and I am<lb break="yes"/>happy to be the medium, through the columns<lb break="yes"/>of the <hi rendition="#i">Inquirer</hi>, of first communicating it to<lb break="yes"/>the world. It was with considerable difficulty<lb break="yes"/>that I obtained it, owing to the extreme person-<lb break="no"/>al modesty of its recipient, but I was favored<lb break="yes"/>with a translation in the hands of the House<lb break="yes"/>Committee on Engraving, and send it to you<lb break="yes"/>entire, both because it is a magnificent compli-<lb break="yes"/>ment to a most excellent and deserving man<lb break="yes"/>whose noble services have been ill-requitted by<lb break="yes"/>his Government, and because it contains pas-<lb break="no"/>sages relative to its author which will be of<lb break="yes"/>general interest everywhere. The autograph<lb break="yes"/>manuscript is extremely interesting and char-<lb break="no"/>acteristic, and will doubtless be cherished by<lb break="yes"/>its presend possessor as a sort of heirloom.<lb break="yes"/>If pride were ever justifiable, he certainly is<lb break="yes"/>entitled to indulge in it after receiving such a<lb break="yes"/>testimonial from such a source. The following<lb break="yes"/>is a litteral translation of the letter.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;I need words to express to you how much I<lb break="yes"/>have been touched by the noble token of re-<lb break="no"/>membrance you have sent me&#x2014;the admirable<lb break="yes"/>volumes you have published on Chili and the<lb break="yes"/>magnificent Cordilleras bordering it. In one<lb break="yes"/>respect your work marks an epoch, for, at the<lb break="yes"/>time of Bougeur and La Condamine, science<lb break="yes"/>was less advanced, and instruments and methods<lb break="yes"/>less perfected. You have enriched at the same<lb break="yes"/>time Astronomy, Geography, Geology, and, to<lb break="yes"/>some extent, descriptive Natural History. A<lb break="yes"/>work which has been brought out in so splen-<lb break="no"/>did a manner, well merits the title of a &#x201C;Na-<lb break="no"/>val Astronomical Expedition of the United<lb break="yes"/>States.&#x201D; After you, it honors the Government<lb break="yes"/>which undertook and fostered it.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;I have read it at night page by page, and<lb break="yes"/>always with increasing interest; and, although<lb break="yes"/>your generous present reached me at the most<lb break="yes"/>disturbed period of my life, when my health is<lb break="yes"/>no little suffering, I have been able to enjoy it<lb break="yes"/>and express to you my admiration for a work<lb break="yes"/>greatly superior to every thing published upon<lb break="yes"/>South America since the time of Bouguer and<lb break="yes"/>La Condamine. Varied in its delineations,<lb break="yes"/>rich in celestial, magnetical, geographical, and<lb break="yes"/>historical facts, for it all I need a leisure which<lb break="yes"/>is not accorded to me. I should limit myself<lb break="yes"/>to profit by your observations, and, offering to<lb break="yes"/>you from them the most cordial expressions of<lb break="yes"/>gratitude, I hope to live long enough to see the<lb break="yes"/>next volume.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Tell me, will it contain the extensive astro-<lb break="no"/>nomical observations for the parallax&#x2014;the im-<lb break="no"/>mediate object of your important expedition&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>your magnetical observations (the intensity<lb break="yes"/>greatly interests me, from my own investiga-<lb break="no"/>tions in Peru long ago)&#x2014;the review of the<lb break="yes"/>Southern heavens; and your report on the bril-<lb break="no"/>liancy of Eta Argus, which you saw as lumi-<lb break="no"/>nous as Canopus?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Although I have passed a portion of my<lb break="yes"/>life in measuring them, I do not regard the<lb break="yes"/>phenomenon of the absolute height of moun-<lb break="no"/>tains as one of great moment; yet, when called<lb break="yes"/>upon to answer the question, &#x2018;Which is the<lb break="yes"/>highest mountain of America?&#x2019; I should be<lb break="yes"/>able to give the numbers that are believed to be<lb break="yes"/>the most exact. Is the highest mountain, then,<lb break="yes"/>Aconcagua, Sahama, or your Tupungato, in<lb break="yes"/>latitude 33 deg. 22 min S.? In the table on<lb break="yes"/>page 13, you state it to be 22,458 feet, and on<lb break="yes"/>the map from the survey of M. Pissis, oppo-<lb break="no"/>site page 48, only 22,016 feet. Which of these<lb break="yes"/>numbers seems to you the most probable? The<lb break="yes"/>trigonometrical measures seem equally depend-<lb break="no"/>ent on barometrical valuations of the base.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Do you consider the result for Aconcagua<lb break="yes"/>by M. Pissis, 22,301 feet, as more reliable than<lb break="yes"/>than that given us by Fitzroy, who made it<lb break="yes"/>21,766 Paris feet? though, according to the<lb break="yes"/>correction by Pentland we should have 22,431<lb break="yes"/>Paris feet. Kellet found Aconcagua to have a<lb break="yes"/>height of 21,567 Parisian, or 23,004 English<lb break="yes"/>feet. To which of these determinations do you<lb break="yes"/>give preference?</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Chimborazo should also be re-measured.<lb break="yes"/>From my observations made at Riobamba-Nuevo,<lb break="yes"/>I believe its elevation to be 20,100 Paris feet.<lb break="yes"/>Kunchingunga is 4,406 <hi rendition="#i">toises</hi> The brothers<lb break="yes"/>Schlagintwert have been on the slopes of Ibi-<lb break="maybe"/>Gamen in Thibet, and found Siberian shells at<lb break="yes"/>an elevation of 20,886 French feet!</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Accept, respected friend, my kind regards.</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rendition="#et3">&#x201C;A. V. HUMBOLDT.</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <dateline>
                        <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Berlin</hi>, 8th September, 1856.&#x201D;</hi>
                    </dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>