<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-04" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#b">Letter from Humboldt.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb/>
                <p>The following is a literal translation of a letter from<lb/>Humboldt to Lieut. J. M. Gilliss, at Washington,<lb/>author of the work on Chili, recently published by<lb/>order of Congress. The letter bearn date&#x2014;</p>
                <dateline>Berlin,<lb/>Sept. 8, 1856:&#x2014;</dateline>
                <lb/>
                <p>I need words to express to you how much I have<lb/>been touched by the noble token of remembrance you<lb/>have sent me&#x2014;the admirable volumes you have pub-<lb/>lished on Chili and the magnificent Cordilleras bor-<lb/>dering it. In one respect your work marks an epoch,<lb/>for, at the time of Bouguer and La Condamine, sci-<lb/>ence was less advanced, and instruments and methods<lb/>less perfected. You have enriched, at the same time,<lb/>Astronomy, Geography, Geology, and, to some extent,<lb/>descriptive Natural History. A work which has<lb/>been brought out in so splendid a manner, well mer-<lb/>its the title of a &#x201C;Naval Astronomical Expedition of<lb/>the United States.&#x201D; After you, it honors the Gov-<lb/>ernment which undertook and fostered it.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>I have read it at night, page by page, and always<lb/>with increasing interest; and, although your gener-<lb/>ous present reached me at the most disturbed period<lb/>of my life, when my health is no little suffering, I<lb/>have been able to enjoy it and express to you my ad-<lb/>miration for a work greatly superior to every thing<lb/>published upon South America since the time of Bou-<lb/>guer and La Condamine. Varied in its delineations,<lb/>rich in celestial, magnetical, geographical, and histori-<lb/>cal facts, for it all I need a leisure which is not accord-<lb/>ed to me. I should limit myself to profit by your<lb/>observations, and, offering to you for them the most<lb/>cordial expressions of gratitude, I hope to live long<lb/>enough to see the next volume.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Tell me, will it contain the extensive astronomical<lb/>observations for the parallax&#x2014;the immediate object<lb/>of your important expedition&#x2014;your magnetical ob-<lb/>servations (the intensity greatly interests me from my<lb/>own investigations in Peru long ago)&#x2014;the review of<lb/>the Southern heavens; and your report on the bril-<lb/>liancy of Eta Argus, which you saw as luminous as<lb/>Canopus?</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Although I have passed a portion of my life in<lb/>measuring them, I do not regard the phenomenon of<lb/>the absolute height of mountains as one of great mo-<lb/>ment; yet, when called upon to answer the question,<lb/>Which is the highest mountain of America? I should<lb/>be able to give the numbers that are believed to<lb/>be the most exact. Is the highest mountain, then,<lb/>Aconcagua, Sahama, or your Tupungato, in latitude<lb/>33° 22&#x2032; S.? In the table on page 13 you state it to be<lb/>22,458 feet, and on the map from the survey of M.<lb/>Pissis opposite page 48, only 22,016 feet. Which of<lb/>these numbers seems to you the most probable? The<lb/>trigonometrical measures seem equally dependent on<lb/>barometrical valuations of the base.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Do you consider the result for Aconcagua by M.<lb/>Pissis, 22,301 feet, as more reliable than that given<lb/>us by Fitzroy, who made it 21,767 Paris feet? though,<lb/>according to the correction by Pentland we should<lb/>have 22,431 Paris feet. Kellet found Aconcagua to<lb/>have a height of 21,564 Parisian or 23,004 English<lb/>feet. To which of these determinations do you give<lb/>preference?</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Chimborazo also should be re-measured. From<lb/>my observations made at Riobamba-Nuevo, I believe<lb/>its elevation to be 20,100 Paris feet. Kunchingunga<lb/>is 4406 <hi rendition="#i">toises.</hi> The brothers Schlagintwert have been<lb/>on the slopes of Ibi-Gamen in Thibet, and found Si-<lb/>berian shells at an elevation of 20,886 French feet!</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Accept, respected friend, my kind regards,</p>
                <lb/>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#et">A. <hi rendition="#k">Von<choice><sic>.</sic><corr type="editorial"></corr></choice> Humboldt.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>