<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-04" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="xi" facs="#f0001" />
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#g">PREFACE</hi>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#c">BY</hi>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#g">ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Relations</hi> of reciprocal good will, and a certain simi-<lb/>larity of endeavour in important and serious under-<lb/>takings, could alone have induced me to overcome the<lb/>objection I have always felt &#x2014; perhaps without suf-<lb/>ficient reason &#x2014; to introductory prefaces by any other<lb/>hand but that of the author.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>During the whole course of my life I have written<lb/>such prefaces only four times; namely, for the French<lb/>translation of the Voyage to the North Cape of our<lb/>great geologist, Leopold von Buch; for the English<lb/>narrative of Sir Robert Schomburgh&#x2019;s dangerous enter-<lb/>prise of five years&#x2019; duration, undertaken to connect the<lb/>coasts of Guiana, at Essequibo, astronomically with the<lb/>eastern point of the Upper Orinoco, which I had<lb/>reached from the west; thirdly, for the original edition<lb/>of the complete works of my ever-memorable friend,<lb/>Fran&#x00E7;ois Arago; and lastly, for the Travels in the<lb/>
                    <pb n="xii" facs="#f0002" /> East Indies and Thibet of the late amiable and lamented<lb/>Prince Waldemar of Prussia.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In the present instance I have voluntarily under-<lb/>taken the task, from esteem for the untiring energy<lb/>and activity manifested by the author in an important<lb/>undertaking, as well as for the modest integrity of his<lb/>vigorous and honourable character, and the remark-<lb/>able artistic talent which he has developed, almost<lb/>wholly by the study of Nature.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The present volumes make no pretension to the cha-<lb/>racter of a scientific work, although they contain much<lb/>valuable information on the physical geography of the<lb/>regions investigated &#x2014; sometimes from the author&#x2019;s own<lb/>observation, sometimes communicated by other members<lb/>of the party specially skilled in those departments.<lb/>Mr. Möllhausen was appointed to accompany, as topo-<lb/>grapher and draughtsman, the Expedition sent by the<lb/>Government of the United States to determine the<lb/>direction of a line of railroad from the coasts of the<lb/>Pacific; and he here offers the diary which he kept as<lb/>a kind of commentary on his pictorial sketches of the<lb/>country and the people, and in which he has reflected<lb/>back, with the freshness with which they were received,<lb/>his impressions of life and Nature.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>When a traveller&#x2019;s descriptions are the result of<lb/>accurate and conscientious observation, and especially<lb/>when they concern the condition of natives standing<lb/>at various grades of uncivilised life, they must always<lb/>interest the student of humanity. A melancholy ex-<lb/>
                    <pb n="xiii" facs="#f0003" /> perience has taught us that, in almost all climates,<lb/>the vicinity of European or North American settlers<lb/>has always tended to the destruction of the uncivi-<lb/>lised races. Crowded together within narrow limits,<lb/>and where the near contact affords opportunity for<lb/>plunder, often sinking into a lower moral state than<lb/>they occupied before, they gradually waste away in<lb/>unequal conflicts. If, at the commencement of the<lb/>Empire of the Incas of Peru, in the Cordilleras of Quito,<lb/>and the elevated plains of New Granada (the ancient<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Cundinamarca</hi>), and in the Mexican Anahuac, south of<lb/>the 28th parallel, the ancient population has main-<lb/>tained itself, and at some points even considerably<lb/>increased, the cause must be sought in the fact that,<lb/>many hundred years before the Spanish conquest, the<lb/>population consisted of peaceful agricultural tribes.<lb/>The report concerning the ethnography, and of the<lb/>physical and moral condition of the scarce, copper-<lb/>coloured, or rather brown-red, natives of the regions<lb/>between the Missouri and the Rocky Mountains, is<lb/>interesting in a twofold point of view, either with<lb/>reference to generalisations concerning the sometimes<lb/>progressive and sometimes stationary character of<lb/>civilisation, or to particular local and historical cir-<lb/>cumstances. In general views of the manifold grades<lb/>of intelligence manifested by those whom we so<lb/>vaguely, and often so improperly, denominate savages,<lb/>the <hi rendition="#i">Indios bravos,</hi> the imagination is carried beyond the<lb/>narrow limits of the present to a mysterious past, in<lb/>
                    <pb n="xiv" facs="#f0004" /> which the greater part of the human race &#x2014; of those<lb/>who have now attained to so high a point of civilisa-<lb/>tion, art, and science &#x2014; lived in the same rude condition.<lb/>How often have such thoughts occurred to me during a<lb/>river navigation of fifteen hundred miles in the wilder-<lb/>nesses of the Orinoco, south of the cataracts of the<lb/>Atures, on the Atabapo-Cassiquiare and Rio Negro.<lb/>But even in the savage state you are struck occasionally<lb/>by signs of spontaneously awakening intellectual power<lb/>in the knowledge of several languages, by which the<lb/>intercourse between neighbouring tribes is so much<lb/>facilitated &#x2014; in the anticipation of a future existence of<lb/>joy or sorrow, and in traditions that boldly rise to the<lb/>origin of the human race, and its abode.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The hordes which occupy the country between New<lb/>Mexico and the river Gila specially attract our atten-<lb/>tion, because they are scattered about the line of march<lb/>along which, in the period from the sixth to the twelfth<lb/>centuries, the various nations known as Tolteks, Chi-<lb/>chimekis, Nahuatlakes, and Aztecs proceeded when they<lb/>traversed and partly peopled southern tropical Mexico.<lb/>Memorials remain of the architectural and industrial<lb/>skill of these nations, who had evidently attained to a<lb/>high degree of culture. The various <hi rendition="#i">stations</hi> or<lb/>abiding places of the Aztecs on the river Gila, and at<lb/>several points south-south-east of it, can still be pointed<lb/>out by means of historical paintings and ancient tra-<lb/>ditions. They are laid down in my Mexican atlas. And<lb/>the large, many-storied, family houses (<hi rendition="#i">casas grandes</hi>)<lb/>
                    <pb n="xv" facs="#f0005" /> seen in 1846 by the engineer, Lieutenant W. Abert,<lb/>and subsequently by Möllhausen, &#x2014; houses which are<lb/>entered by means of ladders, drawn up at night, &#x2014; offer<lb/>analogies to the mode of building in use among some of<lb/>those tribes.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The gigantic sculptures and religious and historical<lb/>paintings left by the Tolteks or Aztecs, who built<lb/>pyramids, and kept the record of cycles of years, show<lb/>a striking agreement in their representations of the<lb/>human form and face, the physiognomical character of<lb/>which, especially in the structure of the forehead, and<lb/>of the very large and prominent aquiline nose, differs<lb/>much from that of the present many millions of agri-<lb/>cultural native inhabitants of Mexico, Guatemala, and<lb/>Nicaragua; and the solution of the problem discussed<lb/>by the acute Catlin, whether these forms, and the phy-<lb/>siognomical structure can still be found among the<lb/>northern tribes, &#x2014; not merely in individuals, but races,<lb/>and where, &#x2014; becomes of great ethnographical import-<lb/>ance.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In the case of the American migration of nations<lb/>from north to south (as in that of the Asiatic nations<lb/>from east to west), to which the attack of the <hi rendition="#i">Huingnu</hi>
                    <lb/>on the fair <hi rendition="#i">Yueti</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Usün</hi> gave the earliest impulse,<lb/>might not single tribes have remained behind northward<lb/>of the Gila, as others in the Caucasus of the Pontic<lb/>isthmus. All the conjectures connected with the bold<lb/>hypothesis concerning the sources of a certain amount<lb/>of civilisation evident in the original seats of the wan-<lb/>
                    <pb n="xvi" facs="#f0006" /> dering nations (Huehuetlapallan, Aztlan, and Quivira),<lb/>have hitherto fallen into the abyss of historic myths.<lb/>Want of faith in the possibility of finding a satisfactory<lb/>solution of the problem, in the absence of more suf-<lb/>ficient materials for judgment, must, nevertheless, not<lb/>be allowed to lessen our diligence, or set limits to our<lb/>inquiries. The question concerning the remains of<lb/>these wandering nations of the north will find much<lb/>satisfaction in Catlin&#x2019;s oil pictures (preserved in the<lb/>Berlin Museum), as well as in Möllhausen&#x2019;s drawings.<lb/>It has also given rise to a valuable work in the philo-<lb/>logical field, in which the traces of the Aztec idiom<lb/>(<hi rendition="#i">Nahuatl</hi>) are followed along the western side of North<lb/>America. Professor Buschmann, my talented friend of<lb/>many years&#x2019; standing, has therein confirmed some<lb/>opinions that I expressed on the subject half a century<lb/>ago; and in works undertaken in conjunction with my<lb/>brother, Wilhelm von Humboldt, has turned his pro-<lb/>found knowledge of the ancient Aztec language to<lb/>historical account.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>In addition to the historical and ethnological interest<lb/>connected with a part of the earth so little known, and<lb/>the exact description of which is the object of the fol-<lb/>lowing pages, its political importance, with relation to<lb/>the commerce of the world and its cultivation, which<lb/>must stand in immediate connection with that com-<lb/>merce, becomes a no less suggestive subject of reflection.<lb/>The rich Atlantic States on the Ohio and Mississippi<lb/>find themselves compelled, by the course of events, to<lb/>
                    <pb n="xvii" facs="#f0007" /> seek the best route to the newly acquired countries on<lb/>the Pacific coast, which have now been received into<lb/>the mighty American Union. These countries are<lb/>richer than the sea-board lying opposite to Europe in<lb/>safe and beautiful harbours, in timber for ship building,<lb/>and in the mineral productions most in demand. This<lb/>new territory, so long under the strict, though peaceful,<lb/>rule of the monks, and engaged only in the productive<lb/>chase of the sea-otter, is now, with all its physical ad-<lb/>vantages, in the hands of a restlessly active, enter-<lb/>prising and intelligent population, destined to play an<lb/>important part in the commerce with China and Japan,<lb/>as well as in the slowly rising trade of East Siberia.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>At the time of the second discovery of America by<lb/>Columbus, there were found along the western part of<lb/>the new continent, from the Mexican Anahuac to Chili,<lb/>regular, social, and political institutions, widely dif-<lb/>fused a common form of religious worship, monumental<lb/>sculptures, great architectural works, temples, pyra-<lb/>mids, palaces, and fortifications. The far more exten-<lb/>sive and flatter eastern region, though covered with a<lb/>perfect net-work of rivers, was inhabited only by savage<lb/>tribes, isolated, and scarcely capable of any co-opera-<lb/>tion even for a warlike undertaking, and maintaining<lb/>themselves only by hunting and fishing. This singular<lb/>contrast between civilisation and uncivilisation, thus<lb/>geographically marked out, began to disappear when<lb/>the great oceanic valley was crossed from the most<lb/>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">
                        <hi rendition="#k">vol I.</hi> a</fw>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="xviii" facs="#f0008" /> northern and the most southern part of Europe, at<lb/>periods separated by an interval of five hundred years.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The first Scandinavian island settlement, originated<lb/>by Leif, the son of Erik the Red, was feeble and tran-<lb/>sitory, and in a moral sense fruitless; it remained<lb/>without effect on the condition of the natives, although<lb/>the American coasts of the frigid and temperate zones,<lb/>from the seventy-third degree (namely, from the small<lb/>group of &#x201C;Women&#x2019;s Islands&#x201D; in West Greenland) to<lb/>the forty-first, were visited by bold Christian naviga-<lb/>tors. It was not till the second discovery of America<lb/>by Christopher Columbus, a discovery that took place<lb/>within the torrid zone, that the one half of the earth<lb/>began to be really revealed to the other, and the old<lb/>promise of the astronomer and physician Toscanelli &#x2014;<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">buscar el levante por el poniente,</hi> to find the golden East,<lb/>by sailing to the west &#x2014; became fulfilled. If we go back<lb/>in imagination to those ages of the world in which the<lb/>civilised nations who dwell round the basin of the Medi-<lb/>terranean saw its gates opened to them by the founding<lb/>of Tartessus, and the important, though erroneous,<lb/>voyage of Colaus of Samos, we shall recognise the same<lb/>impulse to move from east to west which carried the<lb/>Atlantic navigators across the vast ocean. The historical<lb/>events, in which a great part of the human race appears<lb/>animated by a similar tendency, lead to great results,<lb/>slowly, indeed, and gradually, but so much the more<lb/>certainly, developing themselves according to eternal<lb/>laws, like those which reign in organic nature.</p>
                <lb/>
                <pb n="xix" facs="#f0009" />
                <p>Although the Pacific was first seen seven years after<lb/>the death of Columbus, by Vasco Nun&#x0303;ez de Balboa, from<lb/>the summit of the Sierra de Quarequa, on the Isthmus<lb/>of Panama, and a few days afterwards navigated in<lb/>a canoe by Alonzo Martin de Don Benito, Columbus<lb/>had obtained precise information of its existence eleven<lb/>years before, in the year 1502, during his fourth<lb/>voyage, the one in which he most displayed the vigour<lb/>of his genius. He gained the information at Puerto de<lb/>Retrete, on the east coast of Veragua, and he points<lb/>out, in his <hi rendition="#i">carta rarissima</hi> of the 7th of July, 1503, in<lb/>the letter wherein he so poetically describes his mag-<lb/>nificent dreams in the clearest manner, the two opposite<lb/>lying oceans, or, as his son says in the biography of his<lb/>father, the contraction (<hi rendition="#i">estrecho</hi>) of the continent at<lb/>that part. The ocean, whose existence had been<lb/>revealed to him by the natives of the country, must<lb/>lead, he thought, to the gold Chersonesus of Ptolemy,<lb/>and the East Asiatic land of Spices; whither, some day,<lb/>North American fleets, built in San Francisco, will sail<lb/>under the guidance of the chronometer. The distance,<lb/>in a straight line, from the Atlantic coast to that of<lb/>San Francisco, in California, is about 2200 miles, and<lb/>there is a kind of pleasure in looking back to the small<lb/>beginnings of our knowledge of the Pacific, to all that<lb/>even Columbus could know of it on his death-bed, at a<lb/>time when such gigantic projects are entertained of<lb/>railways and oceanic canals through the Narpi and<lb/>Cupica; through the Atrato and the Rio Truando; the<lb/>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">a 2</fw>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="xx" facs="#f0010" /> Huasacualco and the Chimalapa; through the Rio San<lb/>Juan and Lake Nicaragua. That great Columbus, half<lb/>forgotten, as I have elsewhere shown, even by his con-<lb/>temporaries, died (at Valladolid, 20th of May, 1506) in<lb/>the firm belief, shared also by Amerigo Vespucci until<lb/>his death at Seville (Feb. 22nd, 1522), that they had<lb/>discovered only the coasts of the continent of Asia,<lb/>and no new part of the world. Columbus considered<lb/>the sea that washes the western part of Veragua so<lb/>near the gold Chersonesus, that he compares the rela-<lb/>tive positions of the province of Ciguare, in West<lb/>Veragua, and Puerto Retrete (<hi rendition="#i">Puerto Escrivanos</hi>), to<lb/>those of Venice and Pisa, or from Tortosa, at the<lb/>mouth of the Ebro, to Fuenterabia on the Bidassoa, in<lb/>Biscay; and he reckoned from Ciguare to the Ganges<lb/>(<hi rendition="#i">Gangues</hi>) only nine days&#x2019; journey. It appears to me<lb/>worthy of consideration, too, that at the present day<lb/>the gold fields (<hi rendition="#i">las minas de la Aurea</hi>), which the <hi rendition="#i">carta<lb/>ravissima</hi> of Columbus points out as lying in the most<lb/>eastern part of Asia, are really to be found on the<lb/>western side of the new continent.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>To give a descriptive survey of the contrast between<lb/>the former and the present time, and the great benefit<lb/>which an intelligent investigation of the <hi rendition="#i">terra incognita</hi>
                    <lb/>of the far West, within the territory of the United<lb/>States, will afford to our geographical knowledge for<lb/>many years to come, has been the chief purpose of this<lb/>preface. It remains for me, in conclusion, to fulfil the<lb/>agreeable duty of reminding the reader that the author<lb/>
                    <pb n="xxi" facs="#f0011" /> of the following narrative of a Journey from the Missis-<lb/>sippi and Arkansas to the shores of the Pacific, had the<lb/>advantage, in a former journey to the Nebraska river, of<lb/>familiarising himself with the life of the Indian tribes<lb/>by a long stay among them. He is the son of a<lb/>Prussian artillery officer, and at twenty-four years of<lb/>age left the service and his country, with the most<lb/>honourable testimonials from his superior officers, to<lb/>proceed to the western part of the United States. He<lb/>was independent and alone, but irresistibly urged<lb/>onwards, as is most frequently the case with active and<lb/>energetic characters, by a thirst for the aspect of wild,<lb/>free nature, and vast untrodden regions. When near<lb/>the banks of the Mississippi he happened to hear of the<lb/>proposed grand and promising scientific Expedition of<lb/>H. R. H. Duke Paul William of Wurtemberg to the<lb/>Rocky Mountains. He asked permission to join it,<lb/>which was accorded in the most gratifying manner, and<lb/>the Expedition proceeded without accident as far as<lb/>Fort Laramie, on the Flat River, but there the un-<lb/>practicable character of the ground, a terrible and<lb/>general affection of the eyes from a fall of snow, the<lb/>repeated attacks of the Indians, and the deaths of a<lb/>great number of horses, indispensable for the journey,<lb/>compelled the duke for the time to give up his inten-<lb/>tion. Having been separated from the party, M. Möll-<lb/>hausen joined a passing band of Ottoe Indians, who<lb/>provided him with a horse; after which he turned<lb/>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">a 3</fw>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="xxii" facs="#f0012" /> northwards to Bellevue, at that time the seat of an<lb/>agency and dep&#x00F4;t of the fur company. After a resi-<lb/>dence of three months among the Omahas, during<lb/>which he was an active associate of their hunting<lb/>parties, he embarked on board a steamer going down<lb/>the Mississippi, and had the pleasure of again meeting<lb/>Duke Paul of Wurtemberg, accompanying him in<lb/>several excursions, and assisting him in adding to his<lb/>important geological collection. In 1852 he embarked<lb/>at New Orleans for Europe, having been commissioned<lb/>by M. Angelrodt, the estimable Prussian consul at<lb/>St. Louis, at the mouth of the Missouri, to take charge<lb/>of a number of interesting animals, destined for the<lb/>Berlin Zoological Gardens.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>With increased knowledge, and improved artistic<lb/>culture, although with very limited resources, M. Möll-<lb/>hausen had taken the bold resolution of making another<lb/>journey to the West of the United States, and through<lb/>the intervention of my old and valued friend, Professor<lb/>Lichtenstein, I became acquainted with the enterprising<lb/>young traveller. Although now, perhaps, the oldest<lb/>traveller of the age, I remembered too well the enthusi-<lb/>astic feelings of my early life not to be interested in a<lb/>young man of such congenial tastes, and who had been<lb/>so warmly recommended to me; and the kindness of a<lb/>monarch, who has always so gladly extended his pro-<lb/>tection to rising talent, permitted M. Möllhausen to lay<lb/>before him in person his remarkably clear and accurate<lb/>
                    <pb n="xxiii" facs="#f0013" /> Sketches of Indian Life. The increasing favour with<lb/>which my labours and exertions have been regarded in<lb/>the United States, and the generous sacrifices made by<lb/>many of the particular governments there for the<lb/>encouragement of intellectual progress, especially in all<lb/>departments of astronomical and geographical science,<lb/>and of natural history, led me to hope that recommenda-<lb/>tions from me, joined to those of my dear friend the Prus-<lb/>sian ambassador, M. von Gerolt, would, on his return to<lb/>the United States, have some weight with the authori-<lb/>ties and with the admirable Smithsonian institution;<lb/>and my hopes were speedily fulfilled. M. Möllhausen<lb/>has himself, in the commencement of his narrative,<lb/>mentioned his appointment as topographical draughts-<lb/>man<note place="foot" n="*">M. Möllhausen frequently speaks of himself as the &#x201C;German<lb/>
                        <hi rendition="#i">Naturalist</hi>&#x201D; of the Expedition, and appears to have acted also in that<lb/>capacity.</note> in the very completely equipped Expedition under<lb/>Lieutenant Whipple.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Notwithstanding the fatigue inseparable from a land<lb/>journey of eleven months&#x2019; duration, the traveller several<lb/>times sent papers, two of which were of remarkable<lb/>interest, to the Geographical Society of Berlin. One<lb/>related to the manners and physical conformation of<lb/>some little known Indian tribes on the great Colorado<lb/>and in the neighbouring mountains &#x2014; Mohaves, Cut-<lb/>chanas, and Cosninos; the other to the so-called petri-<lb/>fied forest, between the &#x201C;Old Town&#x201D; (Pueblo de Zun&#x0303;i),<lb/>and the Little Colorado. This remarkable phenomenon,<lb/>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">a 4</fw>
                    <lb/>
                    <pb n="xxiv" facs="#f0014" /> in which <hi rendition="#i">conifer&#x0153;</hi> were found united with tree ferns,<lb/>was also examined by M. Marcou, the geologist of the<lb/>Expedition, now professor at the Federal Polytechnic<lb/>School of Zurich, and it has been described in his<lb/>extremely instructive work, entitled &#x201C;General Oro-<lb/>graphy of Canada and the United States.&#x201D; The<lb/>following narrative of travel has been enriched by some<lb/>scientific notes from the learned works of Professor<lb/>Marcou, now printed.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The purpose of the Expedition under Lieutenant<lb/>Whipple was happily attained on the 23rd of March,<lb/>1854, by its arrival on the Pacific coast, at the sea-port<lb/>of San Pedro, to the north of the Californian mission of<lb/>San Diego. The return was by a rapid journey across<lb/>the Isthmus of Panama to New York; and after an<lb/>absence of a year and five months, M. Möllhausen<lb/>returned to Berlin with his collections, and a great<lb/>number of interesting pictorial studies from nature in<lb/>the Far West, which met with the most encouraging<lb/>approval from his sovereign. His Majesty has since<lb/>been graciously pleased to take the young traveller into<lb/>his own service, by appointing him to be the keeper of<lb/>the libraries in the castles of Potsdam and the environs.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>His fresh and animated descriptions of wild nature<lb/>in all the manifold variety of her forms, of the uncivi-<lb/>lised state of the native tribes, and of the habits of<lb/>various species of animals, evince a keen sensibility<lb/>that naturally finds adequate expression in language.<lb/>
                    <pb n="xxv" facs="#f0015" /> What Baldwin Möllhausen has learned of Nature<lb/>through so many vicissitudes and privations, though<lb/>with many compensatory pleasures, has not been lost<lb/>to his intellectual culture; as Schiller says, with<lb/>beautiful simplicity, &#x201C;Man himself grows with his<lb/>aims.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Berlin.</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>