<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>

<pb n="152" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">Baron Humboldt.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;Among other marks of<lb/>respect and sympathy offered to Baron Hum-<lb/>boldt, at his last birthday, was a fine as-<lb/>sortment of China objects from Herr Moritz<lb/>Fischer, the proprietor of the porcelain manu-<lb/>factory at Herend, near Veszprim. The German<lb/>journals publish the answer of the veteran of natural<lb/>science to this amiable offering,&#x2014;a letter written<lb/>in the good-natured gossiping way peculiar to<lb/>Humboldt, and which has, besides, a special in-<lb/>terest on account of the autobiographical notices<lb/>it contains. It runs thus:&#x2014;&#x201C;The Art-loving and<lb/>Art-knowing Baron von Koller (son of the Baron<lb/>von Koller, in Bohemia, whose splendid collection<lb/>of Etruscan vases I was commissioned by the late<lb/>King of Prussia to buy,) was eye-witness of the<lb/>great pleasure your fine birthday present has<lb/>afforded to me. Since then it has been the admi-<lb/>ration of many who have come to my house. The<lb/>amiable way in which you, dear sir, have known<lb/>to give these fine productions of Art and industry,<lb/>has added materially to the satisfaction I had in<lb/>accepting them. To call to mind why these<lb/>objects have a peculiar charm for me, I give myself<lb/>the pleasure of stating that, when twenty-two<lb/>years old, I was employed, together with the great<lb/>Klaproth, at the Royal Porcelain Manufactory at<lb/>Berlin, that I made many experiments at the so-<lb/>called rolling of the China clay; and that, on my<lb/>Siberian expedition, (undertaken in 1829 for the<lb/>Emperor Nicholas), while penetrating into Khuni-<lb/>Macka-Hug towards Lake Dsaisau, in Chinese<lb/>Dsungaria, I had the joy to find a layer of pure<lb/>porcelain clay in a valley of the Chinese province<lb/>of Shee, north-east of the Mandshourian town of<lb/>Tschugutschang. My old friendship with Alex-<lb/>ander Brongniart, director of Sèvres, and with<lb/>Stanislas Julien, the translator of the Chinese<lb/>works on porcelain manufacture, has led me to<lb/>understand the importance of the universally ac-<lb/>knowledged interest for your productions. In rilievo-<lb/>work, in the delicacy of shape, the colouring and<lb/>taste of the imitated antique painting, I never saw<lb/>anything equally perfect to what you produce in<lb/>your great establishment. Cups, plates, net-like<lb/>perforation of vase, all is equally deceptive to the<lb/>eye, and my gratitude is as sincere as the respect<lb/>which is highly due to the noble and happy promo-<lb/>ter of &#x00E6;sthetical industry.&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
