<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="717" facs="#f0001" />
<cb/>
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#b">AMIE BONPLAND&#x2014;THE NATURALIST.</hi></head><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">The</hi> death of this person has been recently<lb/>announced. Some of our older inhabitants<lb/>well remember the interest that was felt in<lb/>his travels and captivity in Paraguay, about<lb/>forty years ago. The following account of<lb/>him, which is taken from a letter from Berlin,<lb/>Prussia, published in the <hi rendition="#i">Boston Journal</hi>,<lb/>will, with Humboldt&#x2019;s letter accompanying it,<lb/>be read with interest: &#x2014;</p><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Berlin,</hi> July 16, 1858.</hi></dateline><lb/>
    </div>
    <div><p>&#x201C;Within a few days, letters have been re-<lb/>ceived in Berlin from Montevideo, bringing<lb/>painful rumor that Amie Bonpland, the<lb/>celebrated botanist, the beloved friend and<lb/>fellow-traveller of Alexander Von Humboldt,<lb/>is no more. Should this rumor be con-<lb/>firmed, and there is little occasion to ques-<lb/>tion its truth, Bonpland will have passed<lb/>away, after an eventful life of unremitted toil<lb/>and research in the realm of natural science,<lb/>at the ripe age of eighty-five; he was still<lb/>engaged, up to a short period previous to<lb/>the time of his reported death, in arduous<lb/>agricultural and botanical pursuits. The sor-<lb/>row which this rumor has diffused throughout<lb/>Europe, is but the natural regret which all<lb/>men feel when a noble spirit departs from<lb/>among them, and bears no resemblance to<lb/>the grief awakened when a man of promise<lb/>is cut down in the fullness of strength and<lb/>expectation, to disappoint the hopes of the<lb/>world. He had done work enough for one<lb/>lifetime, and leaving mankind a noble legacy<lb/>of scientific results, has passed away to higher<lb/>spheres of labor. &#x201C;Well done!&#x201D; is the<lb/>signet stamp upon the record of his days.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;I have obtained from a gentleman of this<lb/>city, who has access to private sources of in-<lb/>formation, and especially to the correspond-<lb/>ence between Humboldt and Bonpland, an<lb/>interesting sketch of the life of the great<lb/>botanist. To insert the whole of it here<lb/>would swell my letter far beyond the pre-<lb/>scribed limits, and I must content myself<lb/>with such brief references to certain portions<lb/>of his eventful history as will serve to illus-<lb/>trate the touching letter which Humboldt<lb/>dedicates to the memory of his lifelong<lb/>friend.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;The intimacy of these two illustrious men<lb/>began during Humboldt&#x2019;s visit to
                    Paris in<lb/>May, 1798, shortly after Napoleon had sailed<lb/>from Toulon upon
                    his disastrous expedition<lb/>to Egypt. Bonpland was about four years<lb/>his
                    junior, finely cultivated in his profession,<lb/>ardent in temperament, and in
                    him the<lb/>maturer German found a man after his own<lb/>heart. The grand result
                    of this fortunate<lb/>acquaintance, was the journey they performed<lb/>together,
                    during the years 1799&#x2014;1804,<lb/>through the American tropics, a
                    journey<lb/><cb/> which has furnished material, besides the<lb/>more immediate
                    scientific results, for some of<lb/>the most magnificent descriptive passages
                    of<lb/>the Cosmos. Humboldt&#x2019;s letters bear fre-<lb/>quent witness to the
                    disinterested affection<lb/>and devotion of his fellow traveller, who
                    in<lb/>more than one dangerous adventure displayed<lb/>that greatest of all
                    love, which is willing to<lb/>sacrifice life itself for its friend. In health
                    and<lb/>sickness, in every privation, in every pleasure<lb/>incident to their
                    long wanderings, the two<lb/>friends were inseparable, and the lonely
                    forests<lb/>of the Amazon and the Orinoco, the intimacy<lb/>which began in the
                    gay capital of France<lb/>ripened into friendship, which after half
                    a<lb/>century receives its first interruption by the<lb/>death of Bonpland.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;On his return to Europe, Bonpland was<lb/>introduced to Josephine, and by her favor ob-<lb/>tained the office of Superintendent of the<lb/>royal gardens at Malmaison and Navarre.<lb/>Here, in the sunshine of imperial favor, he<lb/>passed the happiest and palmiest days of his<lb/>life. But it was in darker days, when the<lb/>divorced Empress could no longer distribute<lb/>royal patronage, that the true nobleness of<lb/>his character appeared. He remained the<lb/>faithful friend of his fallen benefactress, and<lb/>to him she confided her most secret sorrows.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;After Josephine&#x2019;s death, Bonpland, find-<lb/>ing no place of repose in Europe, emigrated<lb/>in 1816 to Buenos Ayres, taking with him a<lb/>large number of fruit trees and a variety of<lb/>other natural productions. He was there<lb/>received with due honor, and soon afterward<lb/>received the appointment of Professor of<lb/>Natural History. His restless temperament<lb/>soon incited him to undertake a journey<lb/>through the interior of the continent, a jour-<lb/>ney fraught with unhappy consequences to<lb/>himself and to science. For in passing<lb/>through a portion of territory claimed by the<lb/>Argentine Confederacy, he unfortunately in-<lb/>curred the jealousy of the Dictator, Dr.<lb/>Francia, by whom he was seized in the most<lb/>dastardly manner and thrown in confinement.<lb/>True greatness always rises above misfortune,<lb/>and Bonpland, denied a hearing by his perse-<lb/>cutor, confined to a small plantation, dressed<lb/>in the clothing of a slave, and compelled to<lb/>perform menial labor for his daily bread, nobly<lb/>resigned himself to his destiny, and endeav-<lb/>ored to make the best of it. He was always<lb/>ready to give assistence to the sick, and by<lb/>his gentle benevolence won the hearts of all<lb/>who knew him. Nor was his scientific ardor<lb/>suffered meanwhile to lie dormant. He made<lb/>large additions to his collection of plants,<lb/>and occupied himself a portion of the time in<lb/>the distillation of brandy from honey. Not-<lb/>withstanding the intercession of Alexander<lb/>V. Humboldt and the remonstrances of<lb/>France and England, he remained a captive<lb/><pb n="718" facs="#f0002" />
<cb/>
for nearly ten years. In 1831 he was released<lb/>without the formality of a trial, and sent away<lb/>from the country which had so long been his<lb/>prison.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Refusing the most pressing invitations to<lb/>return to Europe, Bonpland lived until<lb/>recently upon his estate in the village of San<lb/>Borgia. Conforming in almost every thing,<lb/>except his ardor in the scientific pursuits, to<lb/>the habits of the natives, he married an In-<lb/>dian woman, and in the midst of the most<lb/>enchanting region in the new world built him-<lb/>self a quiet and happy home. Here, sur-<lb/>rounded by an affectionate family, revered by<lb/>every one, and at perfect liberty, he conceived<lb/>and carried into execution many schemes for<lb/>the advancement of agriculture, besides add-<lb/>ing continually to his immense collection of<lb/>plants.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;But neither the charms of a simple life,<lb/>nor the engrossing nature of his pursuits,<lb/>could wholly wean his heart from the old as-<lb/>sociations. Though firmly resolved to live<lb/>and die upon his own estate in the new world,<lb/>he long cherished the hope of a flying visit<lb/>to the old. He desired, with all the ardor of<lb/>a life-long friendship, to see Humboldt once<lb/>more, that he might talk over &#x2018;old times&#x2019;<lb/>with him. How deeply this feeling was<lb/>shared by his illustrious friend, I need not<lb/>say. For many years they have maintained<lb/>a constant correspondence, and though separ-<lb/>ated thousands of miles, each has felt a cer-<lb/>tain society in the life of the other. The<lb/>senior by about four years, Humboldt fondly<lb/>hoped that he might not survive the last, the<lb/>most faithful, the noblest and best beloved of<lb/>all the friends of his long life. Yet so it<lb/>must be. It is the destiny of this venerable<lb/>man to follow all his friends to the grave, and<lb/>to remain himself the sole representative of<lb/>the times of his youth. One after another,<lb/>within a few years, the great men who started<lb/>with him and kept pace with him, have gone<lb/>to their rest and their final fame, and now<lb/>Bonpland has left him. How deeply he feels<lb/>this fresh bereavement, the following letter<lb/>affords touching evidence. It was written for<lb/>publication in the German papers, but I have<lb/>learned, from a private source, that the vener-<lb/>able man desires its circulation in the journals<lb/>of the United States, as a mark of respect<lb/>and esteem both for Bonpland and his<lb/>American friends&#x2019;:&#x2014;</p><lb/><div n="2"><head><hi rendition="#k">humboldt&#x2019;s letter.</hi></head><lb/><p>&#x201C;Conscious of the deep sympathy of numer-<lb/>ous friends in the sorrow occasioned by the<lb/>wide-spread report of the death of my dear,<lb/>noble friend and fellow-traveller, Bonpland, I<lb/>consider it my duty to give at least a brief<lb/>notice of this event, for the particulars of<lb/>which I am indebted to the kind services of<lb/><cb/>
    Dr. Lallemant, author of an important paper<lb/>on the diseases of Europeans in the tropics.<lb/>This talented gentleman, after leaving the<lb/>Austrian royal expedition in the frigate<lb/>Novara, in February of this year, for the pur-<lb/>pose of doing a kindness to myself, made the<lb/>journey from Rio Janeiro to Rio Grande, and<lb/>thence by way of Porto Alegro through the<lb/>former Jesuit Mission to San Borgia, under<lb/>the erroneous impression that Bonpland, who<lb/>had gone there in 1831, was still resident at<lb/>that place. I have received two letters from<lb/>Dr. Lallemant, one dated at San Borgia on<lb/>the 10th of April, the other written from the<lb/>village of Umguaiana, after he had visited<lb/>Bonpland at Santa Anna. An extended ab-<lb/>stract of these letters having been sent to the<lb/>editor of the widely-read and interesting<lb/>botanical journal, the Bonplandia, in Han-<lb/>over, the following briefer extracts may here<lb/>suffice:</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;&#x2018;In San Borgia,&#x2019; writes Dr. Lallemant,<lb/>&#x2018;I lived with an intimate friend of Bonpland,<lb/>the Vicar Gray, with whom I visited the<lb/>garden of the botanist, so long cultivated with<lb/>care, but now lying waste and desolate. It<lb/>was near the close of the year 1857 that the<lb/>Vicar last received letters from Bonpland,<lb/>since when intelligence had come of his<lb/>severe illness. Letters of inquiry still re-<lb/>mained unanswered, and notwithstanding the<lb/>short distance between the places, the people<lb/>of San Borgia were uncertain whether I<lb/>should find your fellow-traveller yet in the<lb/>land of the living. In 1853 Bonpland had<lb/>left San Borgia and taken up his residence<lb/>upon his larger plantation of Santa Anna,<lb/>where he had long occupied himself in the<lb/>cultivation of orange trees. The residence of<lb/>the aged scholar in the Estancia of Santa<lb/>Anna, consists of two large buildings, merely<lb/>clay walls bound together by bamboo sticks,<lb/>and a few beams, and thatched with straw.<lb/>These buildings have doors, but no windows,<lb/>the light being admitted through the chinks<lb/>between the bamboo sticks. Despite the deep<lb/>furrows which an eventful life had engraven<lb/>in the beloved countenance, his eye had not<lb/>grown dim nor lost any of its full-thoughted<lb/>vivacity. But lively conversation, though<lb/>started by himself, appeared to weary him<lb/>much, and he suffered severely from a chronic<lb/>affection of the bladder. The privations he<lb/>had so strangely imposed upon himself are<lb/>by no means in consequence of poverty, or of<lb/>any necessity for abstinence, but of long cus-<lb/>tom, great self-control, and characteristic in-<lb/>dividuality. The government of Corrientes<lb/>has presented to him an estate valued at 10,-<lb break="no"/>000 Spanish piastres, and he enjoys a French<lb/>pension of 3000 francs a year. He has never<lb/>made the practice of medicine a source of<lb/>pecuniary profit to himself. Though univer-<lb/><pb n="719" facs="#f0003" />
<cb/>
sally revered, he loves the solitude, and espe-<lb/>cially avoids all persons who might offer him<lb/>assistance or advice. His scientific ardor has<lb/>not yet abated, and his collections and manu-<lb/>scripts are deposited in Corrientes, where he<lb/>has founded a national Museum.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;&#x2018;On the following morning I found him<lb/>visibly worse, and sinking away. The night<lb/>had been a painful one. I pressed him to<lb/>tell me whether I might not, in some way, be<lb/>of service to him. But I fared no better than<lb/>his other friends&#x2014;he would accept of no<lb/>assistance. How gladly would I have per-<lb/>suaded him to return once more to civilized<lb/>society! But I, too, felt with him that his<lb/>time was passed. He belongs to the first<lb/>half of the nineteenth century, not to the<lb/>second. I think that your friend himself was<lb/>moved when I took his wasted hands in mine<lb/>with the pressure of farewell. For three<lb/>months now his attendants have remarked<lb/>his failing strength, and perhaps the old man<lb/>had the same foreboding as myself, at parting,<lb/>that I might be the last ambassador of Eu-<lb/>ropean lineage who should penetrate the<lb/>depths of the wilderness to offer him regard,<lb/>love and thanks, in the name of that science<lb/>which owes so much to his labors. I mounted<lb/>my horse, and rode northward through the<lb/>evergreen plains. No path showed my way,<lb/>no guide disturbed me; I was alone with my<lb/>sorrowful thoughts over the departing Bonp-<lb/>land.&#x2019;</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Yet how cheerful the last letter I received<lb/>from Bonpland, bearing date the 7th of
                        June,<lb/>1857! &#x2018;I myself,&#x2019; he writes, &#x2018;shall bring
                        all<lb/><cb/> my collections and manuscripts to Paris, and<lb/>deposit them
                        in the Museum. My journey to<lb/>France will be exceedingly short. I shall
                        re-<lb/>turn to my Santa Anna, where I lead a quiet<lb/>and happy life. Here
                        shall I die, and my<lb/>sepulchre and my grave shall be underneath<lb/>the
                        shadow of the many trees I have planted.<lb/>Oh how happy were I, my dear
                        Humboldt,<lb/>could we meet once more, and recall our<lb/>common
                        experiences! On the 28th of August<lb/>next I shall be eighty-four years
                        old, and am<lb/>yet four years younger than you. A man<lb/>lately died in
                        this vicinity who had attained<lb/>the age of one hundred and seven. What
                        a<lb/>prospect for two travellers who have already<lb/>stepped beyond the
                        eightieth year!&#x2019;</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;The cheerful, almost life-desiring tone of<lb/>this letter, contrasts strangely with the melan-<lb/>choly representations of Dr. Lallemant. Ac-<lb/>cording to Herr v. Tschudi the report was<lb/>credited in Montevideo on the 29th of May,<lb/>that Bonpland had died at San Borgia, the<lb/>date of his death uncertain. Yet Dr. Lalle-<lb/>mant had spoken with him on the 18th of<lb/>April in Santa Anna, and on May 19 the<lb/>report of his death was discredited at Porto<lb/>Allegro. Thus there yet remains ground for<lb/>hope that the younger is not to be first called<lb/>away. Such remoteness often stretches un-<lb/>certainty to a painful duration; such the<lb/>solicitude felt for Edward Vogel in Central<lb/>Africa, and for Adolphus Schlagintweit in<lb/>Central Asia&#x2014;the sorrowfully missed!</p><lb/><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Alexander V. Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute></closer><lb/><dateline>&#x201C;Berlin, July 12, 1858.&#x201D;</dateline></div></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
