<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">[Letter to George Ticknor]</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:25</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VII.179</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-01-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">primary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-01-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-21-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-22-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-23-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">[Letter to George Ticknor]</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1858</date>
          <pubPlace>Boston, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;Boston Daily Courier&lt;/i&gt; 68:136 (9. Juni 1858), S. [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <p>We have the pleasure of laying before our readers<lb break="yes"/>the translation of a letter addressed by the illustri-<lb break="no"/>ous Alexander Von Humboldt to our townsman,<lb break="yes"/>Mr. Ticknor. It will be perceived that the publi-<lb break="no"/>cation is in conformity with the request of the<lb break="yes"/>writer. Indeed, the privilege of a purely personal<lb break="yes"/>communication is denied to such world-wide and<lb break="yes" />long-maintained celebrity as that of Humboldt;<lb break="yes"/>every thing that he writes belongs to mankind. He<lb break="yes"/>now presents to our astonishment and admiration<lb break="yes"/>the spectacle of a man of the highest order of intel-<lb break="no"/>lect, at the advanced age of eighty-nine, in the full<lb break="yes"/>possession of all his powers, and busily engaged in<lb break="yes"/>the completion of a work of the vastest scope and<lb break="yes"/>the most profound scientific generalizations. We<lb break="yes" />do not know where to look, at least in modern times,<lb break="yes"/>for any parallel case. The nearest approaches to it<lb break="yes"/>are those of Serjeant Maynard, who was discharging<lb break="yes"/>at eighty-eight, with vigor and ability, the duties<lb break="yes"/>of Lord High Commissioner, and of Titian, &#x201C;the<lb break="yes"/>gay, smiling old man,&#x201D; as Coleridge calls him,<lb break="yes"/>who at eighty-nine, and for ten years more, was<lb break="yes"/>painting pictures hardly inferior to those of his<lb break="yes"/>prime. But here is one of the greatest of men,<lb break="yes" />arrived at an age at which ordinary men become<lb break="yes"/>objects of interest and reverence, and with not a<lb break="yes"/>spot of decay upon the full-orbed glory of his setting<lb break="yes"/>sun! It is good for us to be living at a time when<lb break="yes"/>we can witness such a spectacle.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Humboldt, in spite of his infinite avocations and of<lb break="yes"/>his vast correspondence with whatever is most distin-<lb break="no"/>guished in the whole circle of the globe, perseveres<lb break="yes"/>in the habits of his long life, and never, on any oc-<lb break="no"/>casion, employs another to write for him. What is<lb break="yes"/>perhaps quite as remarkable, there are no more<lb break="yes"/>signs of age in his manuscript than there are in his<lb break="yes"/>style and his thoughts. The original letter, of which<lb break="yes"/>the following is a translation, is in a hand differing<lb break="yes"/>in no perceptible particular from manuscripts writ-<lb break="no"/>ten by him forty years ago. He is enabled to go<lb break="yes" />through his immense labors by his habits of regular<lb break="yes"/>industry, and by the fortunate peculiarity of his<lb break="yes"/>constitution, which enables him to live with compa-<lb break="no"/>ratively little sleep. Most of his hard work is done<lb break="yes"/>at night, when others are at rest.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Humboldt has had the wisdom to keep his per-<lb break="no"/>sonal attachments in constant repair; and now en-<lb break="no"/>joys the devoted regard of men who are the<choice>
                        <sic> the</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial"/>
                    </choice>
                    <lb break="yes"/>grand-children of his contemporaries, with whom he<lb break="yes"/>began life. And he has never allowed his intellectual<lb break="yes"/>eminence or his age to emancipate him from the<lb break="yes" />discharge of the common duties and small courte-<lb break="no"/>sies of life: he is a man full of thoughtful and ob-<lb break="no"/>servant kindness&#x2014;wearing his honors with a grace-<lb break="no"/>ful gentleness that establishes ties of sympathy be-<lb break="no"/>tween him and men who can be naught to him in-<lb break="no"/>tellectually; and thus he receives from the commu-<lb break="no"/>nity around him an affectionate reverence which his<lb break="yes"/>genius and learning alone could not have secured.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <salute>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">To George Ticknor, Esq.:</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;My Dear and Excellent Friend:</salute>
                    <p>&#x2014;Bonds of friendship which<lb break="yes"/>have their origin so far back in my family, and the affection felt<lb break="yes"/>for you by my brother William von Humboldt, when you lived<lb break="yes"/>in Germany, as a young man, seem to impose on me the very<lb break="yes"/>pleasant duty of giving you some sign of life&#x2014;that is to say, a<lb break="yes" />renewed proof of my attachment to you and my interest in your<lb break="yes"/>country, and a brief account of my labors.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;My physical strength declines, but it declines slowly. My<lb break="yes"/>steps are more uncertain in their direction, owing to a feebleness<lb break="yes"/>(a relaxing) of the ligaments of the knees; but I can remain<lb break="yes"/>standing for an hour, without being fatigued. I continue to work<lb break="yes"/>chiefly at night, being unrelentingly persecuted by my corres-<lb break="no"/>pondence, which increases the more as one becomes an object of<lb break="yes"/>public curiosity. What is called literary celebrity is especially<lb break="yes" />the result of a long endurance of life, (une longue patience de<lb break="yes"/>vivre.) This kind of eminence increases, therefore, in proportion<lb break="yes"/>as imbecility becomes more manifest. I am never really ill, but<lb break="yes"/>often incommoded, as is to be expected at the age of eighty-nine.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Since we were only two persons in the American expedition,<lb break="yes"/>(the unfortunate Carlos de Montufar,<note place="foot" n="*">Carlos de Montufar was a young man passionately attach-<lb break="no"/>ed to science, and accompanied Humboldt and Bonpland from<lb break="yes"/>Quito, where they arrived in January, 1802, through all their<lb break="yes"/>travels in Peru and Mexico, till their embarkation at Vera<lb break="yes"/>Cruz in the spring of 1804.</note> son of the Marquis de<lb break="yes"/>Selvalegra, of Quito, fell a victim to his love for the liberty of his<lb break="yes"/>country), it is somewhat remarkable that we should both have<lb break="yes"/>reached so advanced an age. Bonpland, still much occupied<lb break="yes"/>with scientific labors, even cherishing the hope of visiting Eu-<lb break="no"/>rope again, and of bringing in person back to Paris his rich and<lb break="yes"/>beautiful collections in botany and geology, is eighty-five years<lb break="yes"/>old, and enjoys greater strength than I do.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;I have just published in Germany the 4th volume of Cosmos,<lb break="yes"/>and they are now printing the 5th volume, which completes<lb break="yes"/>that work so imprudently begun and so favorably received by<lb break="yes"/>the public. General Sabine writes me that the English transla-<lb break="no"/>tion is finished and will appear immediately. The same news<lb break="yes"/>comes to me from France, from M. Galuzzi, who has been pass-<lb break="no"/>ing the winter in the south, at Cannes.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The great and beautiful work of Agassiz (the first two vol-<lb break="no"/>
                        <pb facs="#f0002"/> umes) reached me only a few days since. It will produce a<lb break="yes"/>great effect by the breadth of its general views and by the ex-<lb break="no"/>treme sagacity of its special embryological observations. I<lb break="yes"/>never believed that this illustrious man, who is no less a man<lb break="yes"/>of a constant and beautiful nature, would accept the offers nobly<lb break="yes"/>made him in Paris. I was sure that gratitude would bind<lb break="yes"/>him to a new country where he finds a field so immense for his<lb break="yes"/>researches and great means of assistance. I hope he may be<lb break="yes"/>inclined, together with his great anatomical and physiological<lb break="yes"/>labors among the inferior organisms, to give us also the specific<lb break="yes"/>icthyology of the numerous basins of the &#x201C;Far West,&#x201D; beginning<lb break="yes" />with the <hi rendition="#i">Holy</hi> Empire of the Mormons.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Science has lately met with an immense loss here by the<lb break="yes"/>unexpected death of the greatest anatomist of our century,&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Prof. Johann Müller.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Johann Müller, who died a few months ago, was only 57<lb break="yes"/>years old.</note> This loss is as great for science, as was<lb break="yes"/>for art the death of the immortal sculptor, Rauch.<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Rauch, who died last autumn, was above eighty, and<lb break="yes"/>seemed, until shortly before his death, destined to many years<lb break="yes"/>of health. When Humboldt kept his 87th birthday, the 14th<lb break="yes"/>September, 1856, with his niece, the admirable Madame de<lb break="yes"/>Bülow, at Tegel the favorite residence of her father and of his<lb break="yes"/>brother William, he desired to have only one other person of<lb break="yes"/>the party, and that was Rauch, undoubtedly then the first of<lb break="yes" />living sculptors. It is most agreeable to know that a fine bust<lb break="yes"/>of Humboldt by Rauch is either already in the collection of a<lb break="yes"/>gentleman at Washington, or will soon be there.</note> The uni-<lb break="no"/>versality of his zoological knowledge in the inferior <choice><sic>organiza-<lb break="no"/>tions.</sic><corr type="editorial">organiza-<lb break="no"/>tions</corr></choice> placed Johann Müller near Cuvier, having a great pre-<lb break="no"/>eminence in the delicacy of his anatomical and physiological<lb break="yes"/>work. He made long and painful voyages at his own expense<lb break="yes"/>on the shores of the Mediterranean and in the Northern Seas.<lb break="yes"/>It is scarcely two years since he came near perishing by ship-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>wreck on the coast of Norway. He sustained himself by swim-<lb break="no"/>ming for more than half an hour, and considered himself quite<lb break="yes"/>lost when he was wonderfully rescued. I lose in him a friend<lb break="yes"/>who was very dear to me. He was a man of great talent, and<lb break="yes"/>at the same time of a noble character. He was admirable for the<lb break="yes" />elevation and independence of his opinions. By making enor-<lb break="no" />mous sacrifices he was able to form a choice library, not only<lb break="yes"/>of anatomy, physiology and zoology, but one that extended<lb break="yes"/>over all the physical sciences. It consists of more than three<lb break="yes"/>thousand volumes, well bound, and of as many more volumes<lb break="yes"/>containing dissertations, so difficult to collect. Mr. Müller<lb break="yes"/>spent nearly 800 thalers a year [600 dollars] for binding alone.<lb break="yes"/>It would be sad to see a collection dispersed and broken up,<lb break="yes"/>which was made with so much care. Since duplicates are<lb break="yes"/>dreaded in Europe, I cannot help fearing lest this fine collection<lb break="yes"/>should cross the great Atlantic <hi rendition="#i">river.</hi> I have almost the air of<lb break="yes"/>exciting your appetite when I thus present myself before you<lb break="yes"/>as a citizen of the world, while the <hi rendition="#i">Church</hi> journal of Vienna<lb break="yes"/>calls me, in capital letters, a naturalist assassin of souls,<lb break="yes" />&#x2018;Seelen-mörder.&#x2019;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Accept, I beg you, my dear and respected friend, the renewal<lb break="yes"/>of the high and affectionate consideration which, for so many<lb break="yes"/>years, I have given to your talents and to your character.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <closer>
                        <salute>
                            <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;A. v. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </salute>
                    </closer>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <dateline>&#x201C;Berlin, 9 May. 1858.&#x201D;</dateline>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>&#x201C;Since so many benevolent persons, colored as well as white, in<lb break="yes"/>the United States, take an interest in me, it would be agreeable<lb break="yes"/>to me, my dear friend, if this letter, translated into English by<lb break="yes"/>you, could be <hi rendition="#i">printed,</hi> without omitting what relates to our<lb break="yes"/>mutual friendship. If you think it necessary you can add that<lb break="yes"/>I have myself begged of you this publication, because I leave<lb break="yes"/>unanswered so many letters that are addressed to me.&#x201D;</p>
                    </postscript>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 
