<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-05" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="3" facs="#f0001"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>The following letter written to George Ticknor,<lb break="yes"/>Esq., of Boston, by
                Baron Humboldt, will be<lb break="yes"/>found to possess much interest</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <floatingText>
                <body>
                    <div n="2" type="letter">
                        <opener>
                            <salute>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">To George Ticknor, Esq,:</hi>
                            </salute>
                        </opener>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>&#x201C;My Dear and Excellent Friend: Bonds of<lb break="yes"/>friendship
                            which have their origin so far back in<lb break="yes"/>my family and the
                            affection felt for you by my<lb break="yes"/>brother William Von
                            Humboldt, when you lived<lb break="yes"/>in Germany, as a young man seem
                            to impose<lb break="yes"/>on me the very pleasant duty of giving you
                                some<lb break="yes"/>sign of life&#x2014;that is to say, a renewed
                            proof of<lb break="yes"/>my attachment to you and my interest in your<lb
                                break="yes"/>country, and a brief account of my labors.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>&#x201C;My physical strength declines, but it declines<lb break="yes"
                            />slowly. My steps are more uncertain in their di-<lb break="no"
                            />rection, owing to a feebleness (a relaxing) of the<lb break="yes"
                            />ligaments of the knees; but I can remain stand-<lb break="no"/>ing for
                            an hour, without being fatigued. I con-<lb break="no"/>tinue to work
                            chiefly at night, being unrelent-<lb break="no"/>ingly persecuted by my
                            correspondence, which<lb break="yes"/> increases the more as one becomes
                            an object of <lb break="yes"/>public curiosity. What is called literary
                                celebrity<lb break="yes"/> is especially the result of a long
                            endurance of life,<lb break="yes"/>(<hi rendition="#i">une longue
                                patience de vivre</hi>). This kind of emi-<lb break="no"/>nence
                            increases, therefore, in proportion as imbe-<lb break="no"/>cility
                            becomes more manifest. I am never really<lb break="yes"/>ill, but often
                            incommoded, as is to be expected at<lb break="yes"/>the age of
                            eighty-nine.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>&#x201C;Since we were only two persons in the Ameri-<lb break="no"/>can
                            expedition, (the unfortunate Carlos de Mon-<lb break="no"/>tufar, son of
                            the Marquis de Selvalegra, of Quito,<lb break="yes"/>fell a victim to
                            his love for the liberty of his coun-<lb break="no"/>try), it is
                            somewhat remarkable that we should<lb break="yes"/>both have reached so
                            advanced an age. Bonpland,<lb break="yes"/>still much occupied with
                            scientific labors, even<lb break="yes"/>cherishing the hope of visiting
                            Europe again, and<lb break="yes"/>bringing in person back to Paris his
                            rich and beauti-<lb break="no"/>ful collections in botany and geology,
                            is eighty-five<lb break="yes"/>years old, and enjoys greater strength
                            than I do.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>&#x201C;I have just published in Germany the 4th vol-<lb break="no"/>ume
                            of Cosmos, and they are now printing the<lb break="yes"/>5th volume,
                            which completes that work so impru-<lb break="no"/>dently begun and so
                            favorably received by the<lb break="yes"/>public. General Sabine writes
                            me that the English<lb break="yes"/>translation is finished and will
                            appear immediately.<lb break="yes"/>The same news comes to me from
                            France, from<lb break="yes"/>M. Galuzzi, who has been passing the Winter
                            in <lb break="yes"/>the south, at Cannes.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>&#x201C;The great and beautiful work of Agassiz (the<lb break="yes"
                            />first two volumes) reached me only a few days<lb break="yes"/>since.
                            It will produce a great effect by the breadth<lb break="yes"/>of its
                            general views and by the extreme sagacity of<lb break="yes"/>its special
                            embryological observations. I never<lb break="yes"/>believed that this
                            illustrious man, who is no less a<lb break="yes"/>man of constant and
                            beautiful nature, would ac-<lb break="no"/>cept the offers nobly made
                            him in Paris. I was<lb break="yes"/>sure that gratitude would bind him
                            to a new<lb break="yes"/>country, where he finds a field so immense<lb
                                break="yes"/>for his researches and great means of assistance.<lb
                                break="yes"/>I hope he may be inclined, together with his great<lb
                                break="yes"/>anatomical and physiological labors among the<lb
                                break="yes"/>inferior organisms, to give us also the specific<lb
                                break="yes"/>icthyology of the numerous basins of the &#x201C;Far<lb
                                break="yes"/>West,&#x201D; beginning with the Holy Empire of the<lb
                                break="yes"/>Mormons.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p>&#x201C;Science has lately met with an immense loss<lb break="yes"/>here
                            by the unexpected death of the greatest<lb break="yes"/>anatomist of our
                            country&#x2014;Prof. Johann Mueller<lb break="yes"/>This loss is as
                            great for science as was for art the<lb break="yes"/>death of the
                            immortal sculptor, Rauch. The<lb break="yes"/>universality of his
                            zoological knowledge in the<lb break="yes"/>inferior organizations
                            placed Johann Mueller near<lb break="yes"/>Cuvier, having a great
                            pre-emmence in the deli-<lb break="no"/>cacy of his anatomical and
                            physiological work.<lb break="yes"/>He made long and painful vovages at
                            his own<lb break="yes"/>expense on the shores of the Mediterranean
                                and<lb break="yes"/>in the Northern Seas. It is scarcely two
                                years<lb break="yes"/>since he came near perishing by ship-wreck
                                on<lb break="yes"/>the coast of Norway. He sustained himself by<lb
                                break="yes"/>swimming for more than half an hour, and con-<lb
                                break="no"/>sidered himself quite lost when he was wonder-<lb
                                break="no"/>fully rescued. I lose in him a friend who was<lb
                                break="yes"/>very dear to me. He was a man of great talent,<lb
                                break="yes"/>and at the same time of a noble character. He<lb
                                break="yes"/>was admirable for the elevation and independence<lb
                                break="yes"/>of his opinions. By making enormous sacrifices<lb
                                break="yes"/>he was able to form a choice library, not only<lb
                                break="yes"/>of anatomy, physiology and zoology, but one<lb
                                break="yes"/>that extended over all the physical sciences. It<lb
                                break="yes"/>consists of more than three thousand volumes,<lb
                                break="yes"/>well bound, and of as many more volumes con-<lb
                                break="no"/>taining dissertations, so difficult to collect. Mr.<lb
                                break="yes"/>Mueller spent nearly 800 thalers a year ($600) for<lb
                                break="yes"/>binding alone. It would be sad to see a collection<lb
                                break="yes"/>dispersed and broken up, which was made with<lb
                                break="yes"/>much care. Since duplicates are dreaded in Europe,<lb
                                break="yes"/>I cannot help fearing <choice><sic>least</sic><corr
                                    type="editorial">lest</corr></choice> this fine collection<lb
                                break="yes"/>should cross the great Atlantic <hi rendition="#i"
                                >river</hi>. I have<lb break="yes"/>almost the air of exciting your
                            appetite when<lb break="yes"/>thus I present myself before you as a
                            citizen of<lb break="yes"/>the world, while the <hi rendition="#i"
                                >Church</hi> journal of Vienna<lb break="yes"/>calls me in capital
                            letters, a natural assassin of<lb break="yes"/>souls, a
                                &#x2018;Selenmorder.&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/></p>
                        <p>&#x201C;Accept, I beg you, my dear and respected<lb break="yes"/>friend,
                            the renewal of the high and affectionate<lb break="yes"/>consideration
                            which for so many years I have<lb break="yes"/>given to your talents and
                            to your character.<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;A. V. HUMBOLDT.</p>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline>&#x201C;Berlin, 9th May, 1858.&#x201D;</dateline>
                            <salute> </salute>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </floatingText>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;Since so many benevolent persons, colored as<lb break="yes"/>well as white,
                in the United States, take an inter-<lb break="no"/>est in me, it would be agreeable
                to me, my dear<lb break="yes"/>friend, if this letter, translated into English by<lb
                    break="yes"/>you, could be printed, without omitting what re-<lb break="no"
                />lates to our mutual friendship. If you think it<lb break="yes"/>necessary you can
                add that I have myself beg-<lb break="no"/>ged of you this publication, because I
                leave un-<lb break="no"/>answered so many letters that are addressed to<lb
                    break="yes"/>me.&#x201D;</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 