<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
    <p>[Foreign Correspondence of The Journal.]</p>
            <p><hi rendition="#b">Letter from Berlin, Prussia.</hi></p>
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">Rumored Death of Amie Bonpland, the Botanist&#x2014;Letter<lb/>from
                        Alexander V. Humboldt.</hi>
                </head>
    <timeline><hi rendition="#k">Berlin,</hi> July 16, 1858.</timeline>
    <p><hi rendition="#i">To the Editor of The Boston Journal:</hi></p>
<p>Within a few days, letters have been received in Berlin from Montevideo,
                    bringing painful rumor that Amie Bonpland, the celebrated botanist, the
                    beloved friend and fellow-traveller of Alexander Von Humboldt, is no
                    more. Should this rumor be confirmed, and there is little occasion to
                    question its truth, Bonpland will have passed away, after an eventful
                    life of unremitted toil and research in the realm of natural science, at
                    the ripe age of eighty-five; he was still engaged, up to a short period
                    previous to the time of his reported death, in arduous agricultural and
                    botanical pursuits. The sorrow which this rumor has diffused
                    throughout Europe, is but the natural regret which all men feel when a
                    noble spirit departs from among them, and bears no resemblance to the
                    grief awakened when a man of promise is cut down in the fullness of strength
                    and expectation, to disappoint the hopes of the world. He had done work
                    enough for one lifetime, and leaving mankind a noble legacy of
                    scientific results, has passed away to higher spheres of labor. &#x201C;Well
                    done!&#x201D; is the signet stamp upon the record of his days.</p>
                <p>I have obtained from a gentleman of this city, who has access to private
                    sources of information, and especially to the correspondence between
                    Humboldt and Bonpland, an interesting sketch of the life of the
                    great botanist. To insert the whole of it here would swell my letter far
                    beyond the prescribed limits, and I must content myself with such
                    brief references to certain portions of his eventful history as will serve
                    to illustrate the touching letter which Humboldt dedicates to the
                    memory of his lifelong friend.</p>
                 
                <p>The intimacy of these two illustrious men began during Humboldt&#x2019;s
                    visit to Paris in May, 1798, shortly after Napoleon had sailed from
                    Toulon upon his disastrous expedition to Egypt. Bonpland was about four
                    years his junior, finely cultivated in his profession, ardent in
                    temperament, and in him the maturer German found a man after his
                    own heart. The grand result of this fortunate acquaintance, was the
                    journey they performed together, during the years
                    1799&#x2014;1804, through the American tropics, a journey which has
                    furnished material, besides the more immediate scientific results, for some
                    of the most magnificent descriptive passages of the Cosmos.
                    Humboldt&#x2019;s letters bear frequent witness to the disinterested
                    affection and devotion of his fellow traveller, who in more than one
                    dangerous adventure displayed that greatest of all love, which is willing
                    to sacrifice life itself for its friend. In health and sickness, in
                    every privation, in every pleasure incident to their long wanderings, the
                    two friends were inseparable, and the lonely forests of the Amazon and
                    the Orinoco, the intimacy which began in the gay capital of
                    France ripened into friendship, which after half a century receives its
                    first interruption by the death of Bonpland.</p>
                 
                <p>On his return to Europe, Bonpland was introduced to Josephine, and by her
                    favor obtained the office of Superintendent of the royal gardens at
                    Malmaison and Navarre. Here, in the sunshine of imperial favor,
                    he passed the happiest and palmiest days of his life. But it was in
                    darker days, when the divorced Empress could no longer distribute royal
                    patronage, that the true nobleness of his character appeared. He remained
                    the faithful friend of his fallen benefactress, and to him she confided
                    her most secret sorrows.</p>
                 
                <p>After Josephine&#x2019;s death, Bonpland, finding no place of repose in
                    Europe, emigrated in 1816 to Buenos Ayres, taking with him a large
                    number of fruit trees and a variety of other natural productions. He was
                    there received with due honor, and soon afterward received the
                    appointment of Professor of Natural History. His restless
                    temperament soon incited him to undertake a journey through the interior
                    of the continent, a journey fraught with unhappy consequences
                    to himself and to science. For in passing through a portion of territory
                    claimed by the Argentine Confederacy, he unfortunately incurred the
                    jealousy of the Dictator, Dr. Francia, by whom he was seized in the
                    most dastardly manner and thrown in confinement. True greatness always
                    rises above misfortune, and Bonpland, denied a hearing by his
                    persecutor, confined to a small plantation, dressed in the clothing of
                    a slave, and compelled to perform menial labor for his daily bread,
                    nobly resigned himself to his destiny, and endeavored to make the best
                    of it. He was always ready to give assistence to the sick, and by his
                    gentle benevolence won the hearts of all who knew him. Nor was his
                    scientific ardor suffered meanwhile to lie dormant. He made large
                    additions to his collection of plants, and occupied himself a portion of the
                    time in the distillation of brandy from honey. Notwithstanding the
                    intercession of Alexander V. Humboldt and the remonstrances of France
                    and England, he remained a captive for nearly ten years. In 1831 he was
                    released without the formality of a trial, and sent away from the
                    country which had so long been his prison.</p>
                 
                <p>Refusing the most pressing invitations to return to Europe, Bonpland lived
                    until recently upon his estate in the village of San Borgia. Conforming
                    in almost every thing, except his ardor in the scientific pursuits,
                    to the habits of the natives, he married an Indian woman, and in the
                    midst of the most enchanting region in the new world built himself a
                    quiet and happy home. Here, surrounded by an affectionate family, revered
                    by every one, and at perfect liberty, he conceived and carried into
                    execution many schemes for the advancement of agriculture, besides
                    adding continually to his immense collection of plants.</p>
                 
                <p>But neither the charms of a simple life, nor the engrossing nature of his
                    pursuits, could wholly wean his heart from the old associations.
                    Though firmly resolved to live and die upon his own estate in the new
                    world, he long cherished the hope of a flying visit to the old. He
                    desired, with all the ardor of a life-long friendship, to see Humboldt
                    once more, that he might talk over &#x2018;old times&#x2019; with him.
                    How deeply this feeling was shared by his illustrious friend, I need
                    not say. For many years they have maintained a constant correspondence,
                    and though separated thousands of miles, each has felt a certain
                    society in the life of the other. The senior by about four years, Humboldt
                    fondly hoped that he might not survive the last, the most faithful, the
                    noblest and best beloved of all the friends of his long life. Yet so
                    it must be. It is the destiny of this venerable man to follow all his
                    friends to the grave, and to remain himself the sole representative
                    of the times of his youth. One after another, within a few years, the
                    great men who started with him and kept pace with him, have gone to
                    their rest and their final fame, and now Bonpland has left him. How deeply
                    he feels this fresh bereavement, the following letter affords touching
                    evidence. It was written for publication in the German papers, but I
                    have learned, from a private source, that the venerable man desires
                    its circulation in the journals of the United States, as a mark of
                    respect and esteem both for Bonpland and his &#x201C;American
                    friends&#x201D;:</p> <div n="2">
                    <head><hi rendition="#k">humboldt&#x2019;s letter.</hi></head>
                    <p>Conscious of the deep sympathy of numerous friends in the sorrow occasioned
                        by the wide-spread report of the death of my dear, noble friend and
                        fellow-traveler, Bonpland, I consider it my duty to give at least a brief
                        notice of this event, for the particulars of which I am indebted to the kind
                        services of Dr. Lallemant, author of an important paper on the diseases of
                        Europeans in the tropies. This talented gentleman, after leaving the
                        Austrian Royal Expedition in the frigate Novara, in February of this year,
                        for the purpose of doing a kindness to myself, made the journey from Rio
                        Janeiro to Rio Grande, and thence by way of Porto Alegro through the former
                        Jesuit Mission to San Borgia, under the erroneous impression that Bonpland,
                        who had gone there in 1831, was still resident at that place. I have
                        received two letters from Dr. Lallemant, one dated at San Borgia on the 10th
                        of April, the other written from the village of Umguaiana, after he had
                        visited Bonpland at Santa Ana. An extended abstract of these letters having
                        been sent to the editor of the widely-read and interesting botanical
                        jonrnal, the <hi rendition="#i">Bonplandia,</hi> in Hanover, the following
                        briefer extracts may here suffice.</p>
                    <p>&#x201C;In San Borgia,&#x201D; writes Dr. Lallemant, I lived with an intimate
                        friend of Bonpland, the Vicar Gray, with whom I visited the garden of the
                        botanist, so long cultivated with care, but now lying waste and desolate. It
                        was near the close of the year 1857 that the Vicar last received letters
                        from Bonpland, since when intelligence had come of his severe illness.
                        Letters of inquiry still remained unanswered, and notwithstanding the short
                        distance between the places, the people of San Borgia were uncertain whether
                        I should find your fellow travellers yet in the land of the living. In 1853
                        Bonpland had left San Borgia and taken up his residence upon his larger
                        plantation of Santa Ana, where he had long occupied himself in the
                        cultivation of orange trees. The residence of the aged scholar in the
                        Estancia of Santa Ana, consists of two large buildings, mere clay walls,
                        bound together by bamboo sticks and a few beams, and thatched with straw.
                        These buildings have doors, but no windows, the light being admitted through
                        the chinks between the bamboo sticks. Despite the deep furrows which an
                        eventful life had engraven in the beloved countenance, his eye had not grown
                        dim nor lost any of its full-thoughted vivacity. But lively conversation,
                        though started by himself, appeared to weary him much, and he suffered
                        severely from a chronic affection of the bladder. The privations he had so
                        strangely imposed upon himself are by no means in consequence of poverty, or
                        of any necessity for abstinence, but of long custom, great self-control, and
                        characteristic individuality. The Government of Corrientes has presented to
                        him an estate valued at 10,000 Spanish piasters, and he enjoys a French
                        pension of 3,000 francs a year. He has never made the practice of medicine a
                        source of pecuniary profit to himself. Though universally revered, he loves
                        the solitude, and especially avoids all persons who might offer him
                        assistance or advice. His scientific ardor has not yet abated, and his
                        collections and manuscripts are deposited in Corrientes, where he has
                        founded a national museum.</p>
                    <p>On the following morning I found him visibly worse, and sinking away. The
                        night had been a painful one. I pressed him to tell me whether I might not,
                        in some way, be of service to him. But I fared no better than his other
                        friends&#x2014;he would accept of no assistence. How gladly would I have
                        persuaded him to return once more to civilized society! But I, too, felt
                        with him that his time was past. He belongs to the first half of the
                        nineteenth century, not to the second. I think that your friend himself was
                        moved when I took his wasted hands in mine with the pressure
                        of farewell. For three months now his attendants have remarked his
                        failing strength, and perhaps the old man had the same foreboding as myself at
                        parting, that I might be the last ambassador of European lineage who should penetrate the depths of the
                        wilderness to offer him regard, love and thanks, in the name of that science
                        which owes so much to his labors. I mounted my horse and rode northward
                        through the evergreen plains. No path showed my way, no guide disturbed me;
                        I was alone with my sorrowful thoughts over the departed Bonpland.</p>
                    <p>Yet how cheerful the last latter I received from Bonpland, bearing date the
                        7th of June, 1857! &#x2018;I myself,&#x2019; he writes, &#x2018;shall bring
                        all my collections and manuscripts to Paris, and deposit them in the Museum.
                        My journey to France will be exceedingly short. I shall return to my Santa
                        Ana, where I lead a quiet and happy life. Here shall I die, and my sepulchre
                        and my grave shall be underneath the shadow of the many trees I have
                        planted. Oh, how happy were I, my dear Humboldt, could we meet once more,
                        and recall our common experiences! On the 28th of August next I shall be
                        eighty-four years old, and am yet four years younger than you. A man lately
                        died in this vicinity who had attained the age of one hundred and seven.
                        What a prospect for two travelers who have already stepped beyond the
                        eightieth year!&#x201D;</p>
                    <p>The cheerful, almost life-desiring tone of this letter, contrasts strangely
                        with the melancholy representations of Dr. Lallemant. According to Herr v.
                        Tschudi the report was credited in Montevideo on the 29th of May, that
                        Bonpland had died at Borgia, the date of his death uncertain. Yet Dr.
                        Lallemant had spoken with him on the 18th of April in Santa Ana, and on May
                        10 the report of his death was discredited at Porto Allegro. Thus there yet
                        remains ground for hope that the younger is not to be first called away.
                        Such remoteness often stretches uncertainty to a painful
                        dura-<lb/><cb/>tion; such the solicitude felt for Edward Vogel
                        in<lb/>Central Africa, and for Adolphus Schlagintwait in<lb/>Central
                        Asia&#x2014;the sorrowfully missed!</p>
                    <closer>
                        <salute><hi rendition="#et">ALEXANDER V. HUMBOLDT.</hi></salute>
                    </closer>
                        <dateline>Berlin, July 12, 1858.</dateline>    
                        <p>It is a touching and noble sight&#x2014;that of the
                        &#x201C;old<lb/>master of science,&#x201D; as ther Germans delight to call
                        him,<lb/>turning with calm resignation from the graves of his<lb/>dearest
                        friends, and quietly addressing himself once<lb/>more to the great work of
                        his life, from which nothing<lb/>is suffered to divert his mind. He is still
                        hale and<lb/>full of vigor, loves the society of congenial friends,<lb/>and
                        is especially pleased to receive visitors from Amer-<lb/>ica. No other man
                        of science ever won such a hold<lb/>upon the heart of mankind, and though
                        all the world<lb/>will sympathize with him in his present
                        bereavement,<lb/>there is no one but will rejoice that he is still
                        allowed<lb/>to remain among us, the noblest man that lives.<lb/></p>
                        <closer><hi rendition="#right">S. S. C.</hi></closer>
                    
                    </div>
                </div> </body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
