<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-04" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="112" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Aimé Bonpland.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <dateline>
                    <hi rendition="#et">Berlin, 12th July, 1858.</hi>
                </dateline>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">Aware</hi> of the deep sympathy felt for me by<lb break="yes" />many of my friends, in my great distress at the<lb break="yes"/>death of my beloved, noble friend and travelling<lb break="yes"/>companion, Bonpland, I have considered it my<lb break="yes"/>duty to publish at any rate a short preliminary<lb break="yes"/>communication on the subject, for which I am<lb break="yes"/>indebted to the friendly zeal of Dr. Lallemant<lb break="yes" />(author of an important work on the diseases of<lb break="yes"/>Europeans in tropical climates). This accomplished<lb break="yes"/>man, thinking thereby to give me pleasure, after<lb break="yes"/>leaving the Imperial Austrian Expedition on board<lb break="yes"/>the frigate Novara, undertook a journey in February<lb break="yes"/>last from Rio Janeiro to Rio Grande, and from<lb break="yes" />thence, by Porto Alegre and the former Jesuit<lb break="yes"/>Missions, to San Borja, where he erroneously sup-<lb break="no"/>posed that Bonpland was still residing, as he had<lb break="yes"/>since the year 1831. I am in possession of two<lb break="yes"/>letters of Dr. Lallemant: one from San Borja,<lb break="yes"/>on the Uruguay, dated the 10th of April; another,<lb break="yes"/>written from the Villa de Uruguaiana, on the<lb break="yes" />19th of April 1858, after having conversed with<lb break="yes"/>Bonpland at Santa Anna:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Whilst at San Borja,&#x201D; writes Dr. Lallemant,<lb break="yes" />&#x201C;I resided with an intimate friend of Bonpland,<lb break="yes"/>the vicar Gay, in whose company I visited the<lb break="yes"/>formerly well-kept garden of the botanist, but<lb break="yes"/>which is now desolate and overgrown. M. Gay<lb break="yes"/>had received the last letter from Bonpland towards<lb break="yes"/>the end of the year 1857. Subsequently news was<lb break="yes" />received of his serious illness. Letters written<lb break="yes"/>with a view to learn the state of his health re-<lb break="no"/>mained unanswered, and in spite of the short<lb break="yes"/>distance it was still uncertain at San Borja whether<lb break="yes"/>I should find your travelling companion alive.<lb break="yes"/>Bonpland had left San Borja in the year 1853, to<lb break="yes" />reside on his larger estate at Santa Anna, where<lb break="yes"/>he long occupied himself in cultivating orange-trees<lb break="yes"/>of his own planting. The residence of the old man<lb break="yes"/>of science (in the Estancia of Santa Anna) con-<lb break="no"/>sists of two large cottages, the mud walls of which<lb break="yes"/>are secured by bamboo poles and a few beams on<lb break="yes"/>the thatch. Both cottages have doors, but no<lb break="yes" />windows, as the light is admitted by the crevices<lb break="yes"/>between the bamboo supports of the wall. I was<lb break="yes"/>received in a hearty and friendly manner. In spite<lb break="yes"/>of the deep lines which a stirring life had imprinted<lb break="yes"/>upon the beloved countenance, the eye was still<lb break="yes"/>piercing, clear, and full of expression. Spirited<lb break="yes"/>conversation, commenced by himself, seemed to<lb break="yes" />weary him much, and he suffered much from<lb break="yes"/>chronic rheumatism of the bladder. The privations<lb break="yes"/>which he so wonderfully imposes on himself are not<lb break="yes"/>in consequence of want or necessary retrenchment,<lb break="yes"/>but rather of long habit, great self-command, and<lb break="yes"/>characteristic individuality. The Government of<lb break="yes"/>Corrientes has presented him with an estate worth<lb break="yes"/>10,000 Spanish piastres,&#x2014;he also enjoys a pension<lb break="yes"/>of 3,000 francs per annum from the French Govern-<lb break="no" />ment. He has always practised as a physician,<lb break="yes"/>with the most perfect disinterestedness. He is<lb break="yes"/>universally respected,&#x2014;greatly prefers, however,<lb break="yes"/>solitude, and especially avoids those who come to<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> him for advice and assistance. His scientific zeal<lb break="yes"/>remains unabated; his collections and manuscripts<lb break="yes"/>are deposited at Corrientes, where he has founded<lb break="yes"/>a national museum. On the following morning I<lb break="yes"/>found him considerably weaker. The night had<lb break="yes"/>been a painful one. I earnestly entreated him to<lb break="yes"/>tell me if I could in any way be of service to him,<lb break="yes"/>but it was with me as with all his friends,&#x2014;&#x2018;he<lb break="yes"/>was in no need of assistance.&#x2019; I took leave of him<lb break="yes"/>with a sorrowful heart. How gladly would I have<lb break="yes"/>prevailed on him to return to the civilized world!<lb break="yes"/>But I felt with him, that his time was past. He<lb break="yes" />belongs to the first period of the nineteenth cen-<lb break="no"/>tury, not to the second. It appeared to me that<lb break="yes"/>your friend was himself affected when I took both<lb break="yes"/>his wrinkled hands in mine to bid him adieu.<lb break="yes"/>Those who surround him have found his powers<lb break="yes"/>failing him much during the last three months.<lb break="yes" />Perhaps the old man experienced the same feelings<lb break="yes"/>at parting as myself, who would probably be the<lb break="yes"/>last messenger of European birth sent to him from<lb break="yes"/>afar off into this wilderness, to express to him in<lb break="yes"/>the name of Science all the reverence, love, and<lb break="yes"/>thankfulness which is due to him. I mounted my<lb break="yes" />horse and gallopped in a northern direction, across<lb break="yes"/>the green plains. No path directed me; I was<lb break="yes"/>disturbed by no guide; I was alone, with my<lb break="yes"/>mournful thoughts on Bonpland sinking into the<lb break="yes"/>grave.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>How happy was the last letter which I received<lb break="yes"/>from Bonpland, from Corrientes, dated the 7th of<lb break="yes"/>June, 1857:&#x2014;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;J&#x2019;irai,&#x201D; said he, &#x201C;porter mes collections et mes<lb break="yes"/>manuscrits moi-m&#x00EA;me à Paris, pour les déposer au<lb break="yes"/>Muséum. Mon voyage en France ne sera que très<lb break="yes" />court; je retournerai à mon S. Ana, où je passe<lb break="yes"/>une vie tranquille et heureuse. C&#x2019;est là que je<lb break="yes"/>veux mourir, et où mon tombeau se trouvera à<lb break="yes"/>l&#x2019;ombre des arbres nombreux que j&#x2019;ai plantés. Que<lb break="yes"/>je serais heureux, cher Humboldt, de te revoir<lb break="yes"/>encore une fois et de renouveler nos souvenirs<lb break="yes"/>communs. Le mois d&#x2019;ao&#x00FB;t prochain, le 28, je com-<lb break="no"/>pléterai ma 84ème année, et j&#x2019;ai trois (4) ans de<lb break="yes"/>moins que toi. Il vient de mourir dans cette<lb break="yes"/>province un homme de 107 ans. Quelle perspective<lb break="yes" />pour deux voyageurs qui ont passé leur 80ème<lb break="yes" />année!&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>This joyous letter, almost expressing a longing<lb break="yes"/>for life, contrasts wonderfully with the mournful<lb break="yes"/>description of Dr. Lallemant&#x2019;s visit. In Monte<lb break="yes"/>Video (according to Mr. von Tschudi) it was be-<lb break="no"/>lieved that Bonpland had died at San Borja, on<lb break="yes"/>the 29th of May, but without further particulars.<lb break="yes"/>On the 18th of April Lallemant conversed with<lb break="yes" />him at Santa Anna. On the 19th of May his<lb break="yes"/>death was denied at Porto Alegre. There is,<lb break="yes"/>therefore, still hope that the younger of the two<lb break="yes"/>has not been the first summoned away. At such<lb break="yes"/>great distances uncertainty is often unfortunately<lb break="yes"/>long continued, as evidence the anxiety on account<lb break="yes"/>of Edward Vogel in Central Africa and Adolph<lb break="yes" />Schlagintweit in Central Asia.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#et">
                            <hi rendition="#k">Alexander v. Humboldt.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 