<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#b">Baron Humboldt on American Slavery.</hi></head><lb/><p>This world-renowned man of science and of<lb/>the age, in a letter to the traveler Froebel
                    under<lb/>date of Berlin, <date>Jan. 11, 1858</date>, thus bears
                    his<lb/>strong testimony against American Slavery&#x2014;<lb/>He writes:</p><lb/><p>Your next volume on the political future of<lb/>America, would I, almost the original
                    Adam,<lb/>gladly live to see. Continue to brand the shame-<lb/>ful devotion to
                    Slavery, the treacherous impor-<lb/>tation of negroes, under the pretense of
                    their<lb/>becoming free&#x2014;a means to stimulate the hunt-<lb/>ing of negroes
                    in the interior of Africa. What<lb/>atrocities have been witnessed by one who
                                        has<lb/>had the misfortune to live from <choice><sic>1780</sic><corr type="editorial">1789</corr></choice> to 1858.<lb/>My book against
                    Slavery (Political Essay on<lb/>the Island of Cuba) is not prohibited in
                    Mad-<lb/>rid, but cannot be purchased in the United<lb/>States, which you call
                    &#x201C;The Republic of dis-<lb/>tinguished people,&#x201D; except with the
                    omission of<lb/>everything that relates to the sufferings of our<lb/>colored
                    fellow-men, who, according to my po-<lb/>litical views, are entitled to the
                    enjoyment of<lb/>the same freedom with ourselves. Add to this<lb/>the anathema
                    on other races of men, forgetting<lb/>that the most ancient cultivation of
                    humanity,<lb/>before that of the white Hellenic race in Assy-<lb/>ria, in
                    Babylon, in the valley of the Nile, in<lb/>Iran, in China, was the work of
                    colored men,<lb/>though not woolly haired.</p><lb/><p>I still work hard, mostly in the night, because<lb/>I am unmercifully tormented with a constantly<lb/>increasing correspondence, for the most part, of<lb/>not the slightest interest. I live joyless in my<lb/>89th year, because of the much for which I have<lb/>ardently striven from my early youth, so little<lb/>has been accomplished.</p></div><lb/><lb/>
</body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
