<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-04" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="2" facs="#f0001" />
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>FORSTER AND HUMBOLDT&#x2014;ANOTHER LET-<lb/>TER FROM THE AUTHOR OF COSMOS.</head>
                <dateline>
                    <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Berlin,</hi> July 28, 1858.</hi>
                </dateline>
                <lb/>
                <p>&#x201C;How shall I, honored sir, thank you warmly<lb/>enough for having followed the friendly advice<lb/>given you by the noble and liberal Grand Duke in<lb/>Wilhelmsthal! You have furnished an admirable,<lb/>vigorously written, physiognomically accurate and<lb/>impartial biography of my departed friend. You<lb/>have employed me for two long nights, for I have<lb/>read page for page of your excellent work. It has<lb/>caused me to experience many happy and many sad<lb/>emotions. For thirty years I have had leisure only<lb/>at night. I have spent half a century&#x2014;no matter<lb/>whither a restless, wandering life has led me&#x2014;in<lb/>telling myself and others how much I owed to my<lb/>teacher and friend, George Forster, in generalizing<lb/>my views of nature, and in strengthening and de-<lb/>veloping that which had begun to dawn within me<lb/>before that happy intimacy took place.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>&#x201C;In these nights, disposed to sadness, as my<lb/>strength is now rapidly failing, I have been vividly<lb/>reminded of the singular similarities and contrasts<lb/>exhibited in all the relations of George Forster&#x2019;s<lb/>and my own life. A like direction of political<lb/>opinions&#x2014;mine not derived from Forster, but ante-<lb/>dating his&#x2014;the first view of the ocean by the side<lb/>of the circumnavigator, at a time when I little<lb/>hoped that twelve years later I, too, would be on<lb/>the waters of the South Seas; my sojourn in Lon-<lb/>don at the time when [Captain] Cook&#x2019;s widow was<lb/>yet living, and when Sir Joseph Banks took a liking<lb/>to me; in my Siberian expedition I came upon the<lb/>banks of the Samara, whence the eldest Forster<lb/>sent to Linn&#x00E6;us, at Upsala, a specimen of the wild<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">waijer</hi>(<hi rendition="#i">?</hi>); Reinhold Forster, accompanied by the<lb/>lad George, having visited the spot in 1765, four<lb/>years before I was born, which I reached in 1825;<lb/>under the Czar Alexander I was invited by Count<lb/>Rumanzoff, in 1812, to a great <choice><sic>scientiffc</sic><corr type="editorial">scientific</corr></choice> expedition<lb/>through the interior of Asia, as George Forster,<lb/>under the Empress Catharine, had been invited to<lb/>join the scientific voyage round the world by Com-<lb/>modore Mulowsky;&#x2014;a like bitter disappointment;<lb/>both expeditions were frustrated by wars with the<lb/>French and Turks.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>&#x201C;How your valued gift has stirred up within me<lb/>old memories! Your whole Sixth Book is mas-<lb/>terly&#x2014;but fills me with sadness; this is espe-<lb/>cially the case with the 8th, 9th and 10th lines<lb/>from the bottom of page 251&#x2014;and yet they were<lb/>welcome!</p>
                <lb/>
                <closer>
                    <salute>&#x201C;With the renewed expression of my heartfelt<lb/>thanks and friendly esteem, I remain,<lb/>
                        <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Your obedient A. V. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
                <lb/>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>&#x201C;I am personally very thankful to you for having<lb/>so warmly and amiably mentioned my unyielding<lb/>and faithful attachment to and admiration for<lb/>George Forster, at a time when you could not have<lb/>known that your work would fall into my hands.&#x2014;<lb/>I do not fear that you will, from the fourth volume<lb/>of my &#x2018;Kosmos,&#x2019; judge me to be a mere believer<lb/>in the &#x2018;change of matter,&#x2019; like Moleschott, (page<lb/>18 of your preface,) for one can believe in the<lb/>ever-varying fettering and unfettering of matter,<lb/>without, on that account, doubting the existence<lb/>of the higher, spiritual essence in the animal or-<lb/>ganization.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The George Forster, of whose biography Hum-<lb/>boldt speaks with so much warmth, was born at<lb/>Nassenhuten, near Dantsic, in 1754. His father was<lb/>John Reinhold Forster, Prussian Privy Councillor<lb/>and Professor of Natural History (Zoology) at the<lb/>University of Halle. He was a descendant of the<lb/>Lords Forester of Scotland, who had taken refuge<lb/>in Polish Prussia. In 1772 George accompanied<lb/>his father on Captain Cook&#x2019;s second exploring ex-<lb/>pedition&#x2014;the father having been appointed Natu-<lb/>ralist to the expedition, and both father and son<lb/>being masters of the English language. George<lb/>subsequently became the historian of the expedi-<lb/>tion. In 1792 George Forster, then first librarian<lb/>of the Elector of Mayence, embraced with fervor<lb/>the cause of the French revolutionists, and was sent<lb/>as deputy from Mayence to the Convention at Paris.<lb/>He was in Paris when the city of Mayence was re-<lb/>captured by Prussia, which involved the confisca-<lb/>tion of all his property, including his books and<lb/>manuscripts.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Forster, now a ruined man, separated from his<lb/>wife, and determined to leave Europe and proceed<lb/>to the Indies. With this end in view he com-<lb/>menced the study of the Oriental languages. His<lb/>exertions and his sufferings, however, were too<lb/>great, and he died in Paris in 1794. His labors in<lb/>both the literary and scientific departments of<lb/>knowledge were immense, inferior only to those of<lb/>his father, who, whether as a zoologist, botanist,<lb/>historian or linguist&#x2014;he spoke and wrote seven-<lb/>teen modern and dead languages&#x2014;had few superi-<lb/>ors in the seventeenth century.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>An enterprising American publisher, we doubt<lb/>not, would find his account in a translation of<lb/>&#x201C;George Forster&#x2019;s Life at Home and Abroad.&#x201D;&#x2014;<hi rendition="#i">N.<lb/>Y. Evening Post.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>