<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-05" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="342" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <cb/>
            <p>The following letter from Humboldt is chiefly<lb break="yes"/>remarkable as being the
                production of a man<lb break="yes"/>in his 89th year. <hi rendition="#i">The Boston
                    Courier</hi> re-<lb break="no"/>marks:</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>&#x201C;There are no more signs of age in this manu-<lb break="no"/>script than there
                are in his style and his<lb break="yes"/>thoughts. The original letter, of which the
                    fol-<lb break="no"/>lowing is a translation, is in a hand differing in<lb
                    break="yes"/>no perceptible particular from manuscripts writ-<lb break="no"/>ten
                by him forty years ago. He is enabled to<lb break="yes"/>go through his immense
                labors by his habits of<lb break="yes"/>regular industry, and by the fortunate
                    peculiari-<lb break="no"/>ty of his constitution, which enables him to live<lb
                    break="yes"/>with comparatively little sleep. Most of his<lb break="yes"/>hard
                work is done at night when others are at<lb break="yes"/>rest.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>Humboldt has had the wisdom to keep his<lb break="yes"/>personal attachments in
                constant repair, and now<lb break="yes"/>enjoys the devoted regard of men who are
                    grand-<lb break="no"/>children of his cotemporaries, with whom he<lb break="yes"
                />began life. And he has never allowed his in-<lb break="no"/>tellectual eminence or
                his age to emancipate<lb break="yes"/>him from the discharge of the common duties<lb
                    break="yes"/>and small courtesies of life; he is a man full of<lb break="yes"
                />thoughtful and observant kindness&#x2014;wearing his<lb break="yes"/>honors with a
                graceful gentleness that establishes<lb break="yes"/>ties of sympathy between him
                and men who can<lb break="yes"/>be naught to him intellectually; and thus he<lb
                    break="yes"/>receives from the community around him an af-<lb break="no"
                />fectionate reverence which his genius and learn-<lb break="no"/>ing alone could
                not have secured.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="2">
                <opener>
                    <salute>&#x201C;To <hi rendition="#k">George Ticknor,</hi> Esq,:<lb break="yes"
                            />&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">My dear and Excellent Friend:</hi>
                    </salute>
                </opener>
                <p>Bonds of<lb break="yes"/>friendship, which have their origin so far back<lb
                        break="yes"/>as my family, and the affection felt for you by<lb break="yes"
                    />my brother William von Humboldt, when you<lb break="yes"/>lived in Germany, as
                    a young man, seem to im-<lb break="no"/>pose on me the very pleasant duty of
                    giving you<lb break="yes"/>some sign of life&#x2014;that is to say, renewed
                        proof<lb break="yes"/>of my attachment to you and my interest in your<lb
                        break="yes"/>country, and a brief account of my labors.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;My physical strength declines, but it de-<lb break="no"/>clines slowly.
                    My steps are more uncertain in<lb break="yes"/>their direction, owing to a
                    feebleness (a relax-<lb break="no"/>ing) of the ligaments of the knees; but I
                        can<lb break="yes"/>remain standing for an hour without being<lb break="yes"
                    />fatigued. I continue work chiefly at night, being<lb break="yes"
                    />unrelentingly persecuted by my correspondence,<lb break="yes"/>which increases
                    the more as one becomes an ob-<lb break="no"/>ject of public curiosity. What is
                    called literary<lb break="yes"/>celebrity is especially the result of long
                        endur-<lb break="no"/>ance of life, (une longue patience de vivre).<lb
                        break="yes"/>This kind of eminence increases, therefore, in<lb break="yes"
                    />proportion as imbecility becomes more manifest.<lb break="yes"/>I am never
                    really ill, but often incommoded, as<lb break="yes"/>is to be expected at the
                    age of eighty-nine.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Since we were only two persons in the<lb break="yes"/>American expedition
                    (the unfortunate Carlos de<lb break="yes"/>Montufar, son of the Marquis de
                    Selvalegra of<lb break="yes"/>Quito, fell a victim to his love for the liberty
                        of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <pb n="343" facs="#f0002"/>
                    <cb/> his country), it is somewhat remarkable that we<lb break="yes"/>should
                    both have reached so advanced an age.<lb break="yes"/>Bonpland, still much
                    occupied with scientific<lb break="yes"/>labors, even cherishing the hope of
                        visiting<lb break="yes"/>Europe again, and of bringing in person back to<lb
                        break="yes"/>Paris his rich and beautiful collections in botany<lb
                        break="yes"/>and geology, is 85 years old, and enjoys greater<lb break="yes"
                    />strength than I do.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;I have just published in Germany the 4th<lb break="yes"/>volume of
                    Cosmos, and they are now printing<lb break="yes"/>the 5th volume, which
                    completes that work so<lb break="yes"/>imprudently begun and so favorably
                    received by<lb break="yes"/>the public. Gen. Sabine writes me that the<lb
                        break="yes"/>English translation is finished and will appear<lb break="yes"
                    />immediately. The same news comes to me from<lb break="yes"/>France, from M.
                    Galuzzi, who has been passing<lb break="yes"/>the Winter in the South, at
                    Cannes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The great and beautiful work of Agassiz<lb break="yes"/>(the first two
                    volumes) reached me only a few<lb break="yes"/>days since. It will produce a
                    great effect by the<lb break="yes"/>breadth of its general views and by the
                        extreme<lb break="yes"/>sagacity of its special embryological
                        observations.<lb break="yes"/>I never believed that this illustrious man,
                        who<lb break="yes"/>is no less a man of a constant and beautiful<lb
                        break="yes"/>nature, would accept the offers nobly made him<lb break="yes"
                    />in Paris. I was sure that gratitude would bind<lb break="yes"/>him to a new
                    country where he finds a field so<lb break="yes"/>immense for his researches and
                    great means of<lb break="yes"/>assistance. I hope he may be inclined,
                        together<lb break="yes"/>with his great anatomical and physiological la-<lb
                        break="no"/>bors among the inferior organisms, to give us<lb break="yes"
                    />also the specific icthyology of the numerous<lb break="yes"/>basins of the
                    &#x2018;Far West,&#x2019; beginning with the<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Holy</hi> Empire of the Mormons.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Science has lately met with an immense loss<lb break="yes"/>here by the
                    unexpected death of the greatest<lb break="yes"/>anatomist of our country, Prof.
                    Johann Müller.<lb break="yes"/>This loss is as great for science, as was for
                        art<lb break="yes"/>the death of the immortal sculptor Rauch.<lb break="yes"
                    />The universality of his zoological knowledge in<lb break="yes"/>the inferior
                    organizations placed Johann Müller<lb break="yes"/>near Cuvier, having a great
                            <choice><sic>pre eminence</sic><corr type="editorial"
                            >pre-eminence</corr></choice> in the<lb break="yes"/>delicacy of his
                    anatomical and physiological work.<lb break="yes"/>He made long and painful
                    voyages, at his own<lb break="yes"/>expense, on the shores of the Mediterranean
                        and<lb break="yes"/>in the Northern Seas. It is scarcely two years<lb
                        break="yes"/>since he came near perishing by shipwreck on<lb break="yes"
                    />the coast of Norway. He sustained himself by<lb break="yes"/>swimming for more
                    than half an hour, and con-<lb break="no"/>sidered himself quite lost, when he
                    was wonder-<lb break="no"/>fully rescued. I lose in him a friend who was<lb
                        break="yes"/>very dear to me. He was a man of great talent,<lb break="yes"
                    />and at the same time of a noble character. He<lb break="yes"/>was admirable
                    for the elevation and independence<lb break="yes"/>of his opinions. By making
                    enormous sacrifices<lb break="yes"/>he was able to form a choice library, not
                    only of<lb break="yes"/>anatomy, physiology and zoology, but one that<lb
                        break="yes"/>extended over all the physical sciences. It con-<lb break="no"
                    />sists of more than three <choice><sic>thoussnd</sic><corr type="editorial"
                            >thousand</corr></choice> volumes, well<lb break="yes"/>bound, and of as
                    many more volumes containing<lb break="yes"/>dissertations, so difficult to
                    collect. Mr. Muller<lb break="yes"/>spent nearly 800 thalers a year [600
                    dollars] for<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> binding alone. It would be sad to see a col-<lb break="no"/>lection
                    dispersed and broken up, which was<lb break="yes"/>made with so much care. Since
                    duplicates are<lb break="yes"/>dreaded in Europe, I cannot help fearing lest<lb
                        break="yes"/>this fine collection should cross the great Atlantic<lb
                        break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">river.</hi> I have almost the air of
                            <choice><sic>exiciting</sic><corr type="editorial"
                        >exciting</corr></choice> your<lb break="yes"/>appetite when I thus present
                    myself before you<lb break="yes"/>as a citizen of the world, while the <hi
                        rendition="#i">Church</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Journal of Vienna calls me, in capital letters, a<lb
                        break="yes"/>naturalist assassin of souls,
                    &#x2018;Seelen-morder.&#x2019;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Accept, I beg you, my dear and respected<lb break="yes"/>friend, the renewal of
                    the high and affectionate<lb break="yes"/>consideration which, for so many
                    years, I have<lb break="yes"/>given to your talents and to your character.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#et">A. V. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </salute>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <dateline>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Berlin,</hi> 9 <hi rendition="#i">May,</hi>
                        1858.&#x201D;</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="2">
                <p>&#x201C;Since so many benevolent persons, colored,<lb break="yes"/>as well as
                    white, in the United States, take an<lb break="yes"/>interest in me, it would be
                    agreeable to me, my<lb break="yes"/>dear friend, if this letter, translated into
                        English<lb break="yes"/>by you, could be <hi rendition="#i">printed,</hi>
                    without omitting what<lb break="yes"/>relates to our mutual friendship. If you
                        think<lb break="yes"/>it necessary you can add that I have myself<lb
                        break="yes"/>begged of you this publication, because I leave<lb break="yes"
                    />unanswered so many letters that are addressed<lb break="yes"/>to
                    me.&#x201D;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 