<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <teiHeader> <fileDesc> <titleStmt> <title>DUMMYHEADER</title> </titleStmt> <publicationStmt> <p></p> </publicationStmt> <sourceDesc> <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p> </sourceDesc> </fileDesc> </teiHeader> <text><front></front><body> <pb facs="#f0001" /> <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">A LETTER FROM HUMBOLDT.</hi></head><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/> <p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">From the Boston Courier.</hi></hi></p><lb break="yes"/><p>We have the pleasure of laying before our readers<lb break="yes"/>the translation of a letter addressed by the illustrious<lb break="yes"/>Alexander Von Humboldt to our townsman, Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Ticknor. It will be perceived that the publication is<lb break="yes"/>in conformity with the request of the writer. Indeed,<lb break="yes"/>the privilege of a purely personal communication is<lb break="yes"/>denied to such world-wide and long maintained ce-<lb break="no"/>lebrity as that of Humboldt; everything that he<lb break="yes"/>writes belongs to mankind. He now presents to our<lb break="yes"/>astonishment and admiration the spectacle of a man<lb break="yes"/>of the highest order of intellect, at the advanced age<lb break="yes"/>of 89, in the full possession of all his powers, and<lb break="yes"/>busily engaged in the completion of a work of the<lb break="yes"/>vastest scope and the most <choice><sic>profouud</sic><corr type="editorial">profound</corr></choice> scientific gener-<lb break="no"/>alizations. We do not know where to look, at least<lb break="yes"/>in modern times, for any parallel case. The nearest<lb break="yes"/>approaches to it are those of Serjeant Maynard, who<lb break="yes"/>was discharging at 88, with vigor and ability, the du-<lb break="no"/>ties of Lord High Commissioner, and of Titian, &#x201C;the<lb break="yes"/>gay, smiling old man,&#x201D; as Coleridge calls him, who at<lb break="yes"/>89, and for ten years more, was painting pictures<lb break="yes"/>hardly inferior to those of his prime. But here is<lb break="yes"/>one of the greatest of men, arrived at an age at<lb break="yes"/>which ordinary men become objects of interest and<lb break="yes"/>reverence, and with not a spot of decay upon the full-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>orbed glory of his setting sun! It is good for us to<lb break="yes"/>be living at a time when we can witness such a<lb break="yes"/>spectacle.</p><lb break="yes"/><p>Humboldt, in spite of his infinite avocations and of<lb break="yes"/>his vast correspondence with whatever is most distin-<lb break="no"/>guished in the whole circle of the globe, perseveres in<lb break="yes"/>the habits of his long life, and never, on any occasion,<lb break="yes"/>employs another to write for him. What is, perhaps,<lb break="yes"/>quite as remarkable, there are no more signs of age in<lb break="yes"/>his manuscript than there are in his style and his<lb break="yes"/>thoughts. The original letter, of which the following<lb break="yes"/>as a translation, is in a hand differing in no perceptible<lb break="yes"/>particular from manuscripts written by him forty<lb break="yes"/>years ago. He is enabled to go through his immense<lb break="yes"/>labors by his habits of regular industry, and by the<lb break="yes"/>fortunate peculiarity of his constitution, which ena-<lb break="no"/>bles him to live with comparatively little sleep. Most<lb break="yes"/>of his hard work is done at night when others are at<lb break="yes"/>rest.</p><lb break="yes"/><p>Humboldt has had the wisdom to keep his personal<lb break="yes"/>attachments in constant repair, and now enjoys the<lb break="yes"/>devoted regard of men who are the grand-children of<lb break="yes"/>his cotempararies, with whom he began life. And he<lb break="yes"/>has never allowed his intellectual eminence or his age<lb break="yes"/>to emancipate him from the discharge of the common<lb break="yes"/>duties and small courtesies of life; he is a man full of<lb break="yes"/>thoughtful and observant kindness&#x2014;wearing his honors<lb break="yes"/>with a graceful gentleness that establishes ties of<lb break="yes"/>sympathy between him and men who can be naught<lb break="yes"/>to him intellectually; and thus he receives from the<lb break="yes"/>community around him an affectionate reverence<lb break="yes"/>which his genius and learning alone could not have<lb break="yes"/>secured.</p><lb break="yes"/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb break="yes"/><div n="2">
                    <salute>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">To George Ticknor,</hi> esq.:<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;<hi
                            rendition="#k">My Dear and Excellent Friend:</hi></salute>
                    <p>Bonds of<lb break="yes"/>friendship which have their origin so far back as my<lb break="yes"/>family,
                        and the affection felt for you by my brother<lb break="yes"/>William von Humboldt, when
                        you lived in Germany,<lb break="yes"/>as a young man, seem to impose on me the very<lb
                            break="yes"/>pleasant duty of giving you some sign of life—that
                        is<lb break="yes"/>to say, a renewed proof of my attachment to you and<lb break="yes"/>my interest
                        in your country, and a brief account of my<lb break="yes"/>labors.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;My physical strength declines, but it declines<lb break="yes"/>slowly. My steps
                        are more uncertain in their direc-<lb break="no"/>tion, owing to a
                        feebleness (a relaxing) of the liga-<lb break="no"/>ments of the knees; but
                        I can remain standing for an<lb break="yes"/>hour, without being fatigued. I continue to
                        work chiefly<lb break="yes"/>at night, being unrelentingly persecuted by my corres-<lb
                            break="no"/>pondence, which increases the more as one becomes
                        an<lb break="yes"/>object of public curiosity. What is called literary<lb break="yes"/>celebrity is
                        especially the result of a long endurance of<lb break="yes"/>life, (une longue patience
                        de vivre). This kind of emi-<lb break="no"/>nence increases, therefore, in
                        proportion as imbecility<lb break="yes"/>becomes more manifest. I am never really ill,
                        but <lb break="yes"/>often incommoded, as is to be expected at the age
                        of<lb break="yes"/>eighty-nine. </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Since we were only two persons in the American<lb break="yes"/>expedition, (the
                        unfortunate Carlos de Montufar,<note place="foot" n="*">Carlos de Montufar
                            was a young man passionately attached to<lb break="yes"/>science, and accompanied
                            Humboldt and Bonpland from Quito,<lb break="yes"/>where they arrived in January,
                            1802, through all their travels in<lb break="yes"/>Peru and Mexico, till their
                            embarkation at Vera Cruz in the Spring<lb break="yes"/>of 1804. </note> son<lb break="yes"/>of
                        the Marquis de Selvalegra, of Quito, fell a victim to<lb break="yes"/>his love for the
                        liberty of his country), it is somewhat<lb break="yes"/>remarkable that we should both
                        have reached so ad-<lb break="no"/>vanced an age. Bonpland, still much occupied
                        with<lb break="yes"/>scientific labors, even cherishing the hope of visiting<lb break="yes"/>Europe
                        again, and of bringing in person back to Paris<lb break="yes"/>his rich and beautiful
                        collections in botany and geolo-<lb break="no"/>gy, is 85 years old, and enjoys greater
                        strength than I<lb break="yes"/>do. </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;I have just published in Germany the 4th volume<lb break="yes"/>of Cosmos, and
                        they are now printing the 5th volume,<lb break="yes"/>which completes that work so
                        imprudently begun and<lb break="yes"/>so favorably received by the public. Gen.
                        Sabine<lb break="yes"/>writes me that the English translation is finished and<lb break="yes"/>will
                        appear immediately. The same news comes to<lb break="yes"/>me from France, from M.
                        Galuzzi, who has been pass-<lb break="no"/>ing the Winter in the South, at
                        Cannes. </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The great and beautiful work of Agassiz (the first<lb break="yes"/>two volumes)
                        reached me only a few days since. It<lb break="yes"/>will produce a great effect by the
                        breadth of its gen-<lb break="no"/>eral views and by the extreme sagacity of its
                        special<lb break="yes"/>embryological observations. I never believed that<lb break="yes"/>this
                        illustrious man, who is no less a man of a con-<lb break="no"/>stant and beautiful
                        nature, would accept the offers<lb break="yes"/>nobly made him in Paris. I was sure that
                        gratitude<lb break="yes"/>would bind him to a new country where he finds a<lb break="yes"/>field so
                        immense for his researches and great means of<lb break="yes"/>assistance. I hope he may
                        be inclined, together with<lb break="yes"/>his great anatomical and physiological labors
                        among<lb break="yes"/>the inferior organisms, to give us also the specific<lb
                            break="yes"/>icthyology of the numerous basins of the &#x2018;Far
                        West,&#x2019;<lb break="yes"/>beginning with the <hi rendition="#i">Holy</hi> Empire of
                        the Mormons. </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Science has lately met with an immense loss here<lb break="yes"/>by the
                        unexpected death of the greatest anatomist of<lb break="yes"/>our century,—Prof. Johann
                        Müller. <note place="foot" n="†">Johann Müller, who died a few months ago,
                            was only 57<lb break="yes"/>years old. </note> This loss is as<lb break="yes"/>great
                        for science, as was for art the death of the im-<lb break="no"/>mortal sculptor, Rauch.
                            <note place="foot" n="‡">Rauch, who died last Autumn, was above eighty,
                            and seemed,<lb break="yes"/>until shortly before his death, destined to many years
                            of health.<lb break="yes"/>When Humboldt kept his 87th birthday, the 14th
                            September,<lb break="yes"/>1856, with his niece, the admirable Madame Bülow, at
                            Tegel, the<lb break="yes"/>favorite residence of her father and of his brother
                            William, he<lb break="yes"/>desired to have only one other person of the party, and
                            that was<lb break="yes"/>Rauch, undoubtedly then the first of living sculptors. It
                            is most<lb break="yes"/>agreeable to know that a fine bust of Humboldt by Rauch
                            is<lb break="yes"/>either already in the collection of a gentleman at Washington,
                            or<lb break="yes"/>will soon be there. </note> The universality of
                        his<lb break="yes"/>zoological knowledge in the inferior organizations<lb break="yes"/>placed Johann
                        Müller near Cuvier, having a great pre-<lb break="no"/>eminence in the
                        delicacy of his anatomical and physio-<lb break="no"/>logical work. He made long and
                        painful voyages at<lb break="yes"/>his own expense on the shores of the
                        Mediterranean<lb break="yes"/>and in the Northern Seas. It is scarcely two
                        years<lb break="yes"/>since he came near perishing by shipwreck on the<lb break="yes"/>coast of
                        Norway. He sustained himself by swimming<lb break="yes"/>for more than half an hour, and
                        considered himself<lb break="yes"/>quite lost when he was wonderfully rescued. I lose
                        in<lb break="yes"/>him a friend who was very dear to me. He was a<lb break="yes"/>man of great
                        talent, and at the same time of a noble<lb break="yes"/>character. He was admirable for
                        the elevation and<lb break="yes"/>independence of his opinions. By making
                        enormous<lb break="yes"/>sacrifices he was able to form a choice library, not only<lb
                            break="yes"/>of anatomy, physiology and zoology, but one that
                        ex-<lb break="no"/>tended over all the physical sciences. It consists of<lb break="yes"/>more than
                        three thousand volumes, well bound, and<lb break="yes"/>of as many more volumes
                        containing dissertations, so<lb break="yes"/>difficult to collect. Mr. Müller spent
                        nearly 800 thalers<lb break="yes"/>a year [600 dollars] for binding alone. It would
                        be<lb break="yes"/>sad to see a collection dispersed and broken up, which<lb break="yes"/>was made
                        with so much care. Since duplicates are<lb break="yes"/>dreaded in Europe, I
                        cannot help fearing lest this fine<lb break="yes"/>collection should cross the great
                        Atlantic <hi rendition="#i">river.</hi> I<lb break="yes"/>have almost the air of
                        exciting your appetite when I<lb break="yes"/>thus present myself before you as a
                        citizen of the<lb break="yes"/>world, while the <hi rendition="#i">Church</hi> journal
                        of Vienna calls me,<lb break="yes"/>in capital letters, a naturalist assassin of
                            souls,<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;Seelen-mörder.&#x2019;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Accept, I beg you, my dear and respected friend,<lb break="yes"/>the renewal of
                        the high and affectionate consideration<lb break="yes"/>which, for so many years, I have
                        given to your talents<lb break="yes"/>and to your character. </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <closer>
                        <salute>
                            <hi rendition="#et"> &#x201C;A. v. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </salute>
                    </closer>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <dateline>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Berlin,</hi> 9 May,
                        1858.&#x201D;</dateline>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <postscript>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <p> &#x201C;Since so many benevolent persons, colored as well<lb break="yes"/>as white,
                            in the United States, take an interest in me,<lb break="yes"/>it would be agreeable
                            to me, my dear friend, if this<lb break="yes"/>letter, translated into English by
                            you, could be <hi rendition="#i">print-<lb break="no"/>ed,</hi> without omitting
                            what relates to our mutual friend-<lb break="no"/>ship. If you think it necessary
                            you can add that I<lb break="yes"/>have myself begged of you this publication,
                            because<lb break="yes"/>I leave unanswered so many letters that are addressed<lb break="yes"/>to
                            me.&#x201D; </p>
                    </postscript>
                </div> </div><lb break="yes"/></body><back></back> </text> </TEI>