<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-04" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="192" facs="#f0001" />
            <cb/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>BARON HUMBOLDT ON AMERICAN<lb/>SLAVERY.</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rendition="#k">The</hi> following highly-interesting extract is<lb/>taken from a recent number of the <hi rendition="#i">New-<lb/>York Tribune.</hi> It is from a private letter,<lb/>addressed by the venerable philosopher to his<lb/>friend, Mr. Julius Froebel, an author of<lb/>distinction. The Baron&#x2019;s testimony against<lb/>Slavery adds one more to &#x201C;the host of<lb/>witnesses&#x201D; who have raised their voice in<lb/>condemnation of this iniquity. The editor<lb/>of the <hi rendition="#i">Tribune</hi> publishes it with the Baron&#x2019;s<lb/>consent.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>&#x201C;Accept, my dear Froebel, if only in a few<lb/>lines, my most cordial thanks for your kind letter<lb/>and for the gift of an able work on your personal<lb/>experience in America, in which you have sub-<lb/>
                    <cb/> mitted all classes of society to such a sagacious<lb/>comparison. You are here warmly cherished<lb/>in the memory of all who are acquainted with<lb/>your distinguished scientific attainments, the<lb/>nobleness of your character, and the peculiar<lb/>features of your mind. I have boasted of your<lb/>enduring friendship with me in the new volume<lb/>of <hi rendition="#i">Kosmos,</hi> p. 541. I closed this volume just as<lb/>I received the first part of your travels and<lb/>researches, which had already often been described<lb/>to me by friends, and especially by Varnhagen<lb/>von Ense. I trust I shall not lose your favour<lb/>on account of my differing from you in regard to<lb/>the connection between the North Mexican high-<lb/>lands and the Rocky Mountains. Our con-<lb/>troversy, as you will find when you read<lb/>attentively (pp. 431&#x2014;440), is almost entirely one<lb/>of words. I make a distinction between a broad,<lb/>continuous elevation, and the disconnected chain<lb/>rising above it, often steeply and like battlements.<lb/>The word mountain is very indefinite. In spite<lb/>of my heretical disposition, however, your ninth<lb/>chapter (pp. 504&#x2014;518) gives me a great deal of<lb/>instruction. You have explained many points<lb/>which were only hinted at in the &#x201C;Remarks&#x201D;<lb/>(<hi rendition="#i">Contributions to Phys. Geog., Smithson. Inst.</hi>)<lb/>But there are other things which come nearer<lb/>my heart than those elevations. Your next<lb/>volume on the political future of America would<lb/>I, almost the original Adam, gladly live to see.<lb/>Continue to brand the shameful devotion to<lb/>slavery, the treacherous importation of negroes,<lb/>under the pretence of their becoming free&#x2014;a<lb/>means to stimulate the hunting of negroes in the<lb/>interior of Africa. What atrocities have been<lb/>witnessed by one who has had the misfortune to<lb/>live from 1789 to 1858. My book against Slavery<lb/>(<hi rendition="#i">Political Essay on the Island of Cuba</hi>) is not<lb/>prohibited in Madrid, but cannot be purchased in<lb/>the United States, which you call &#x201E;The Repub-<lb/>lic of distinguished people,&#x201D; except with the<lb/>omission of every thing that relates to the suffer-<lb/>ings of our coloured fellow-men, who, according<lb/>to my political views, are entitled to the enjoy-<lb/>ment of the same freedom with ourselves. Add<lb/>to this, the anathema on other races of men,<lb/>forgetting that the most ancient cultivation of<lb/>humanity, before that of the white Hellenic race<lb/>in Assyria, in Babylon, in the valley of the Nile,<lb/>in Iran, in China, was the work of coloured men,<lb/>though not woolly-haired.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>&#x201C;I still work hard, mostly in the night,<lb/>because I am unmercifully tormented with a<lb/>constantly increasing correspondence, for the<lb/>most part of not the slightest interest. I live<lb/>joyless in my 89th year, because, of the much for<lb/>which I have ardently striven from my early<lb/>youth so little has been accomplished.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>&#x201C;With renewed expressions of the friendship<lb/>of many years, which political events have never<lb/>troubled, <hi rendition="#et">I am ever your illegible</hi>
                </p>
                <lb/>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#et">
                            <hi rendition="#k">Al. Humboldt.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
                <lb/>
                <dateline>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Berlin, January</hi> 11, 1858.</dateline>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>