<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-05" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="206" facs="#f0001"/>
            <cb/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#et">From The Boston Courier.</hi>
            </p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>
                <hi rendition="#k">We</hi> have the pleasure of laying before our<lb break="yes"
                />readers the translation of a letter addressed<lb break="yes"/>by the illustrious
                Alexander Von Humboldt<lb break="yes"/>to our townsman, Mr. Ticknor. It will be<lb
                    break="yes"/>perceived that the publication is in confor-<lb break="no"/>mity
                with the request of the writer. Indeed,<lb break="yes"/>the privilege of a purely
                personal communi-<lb break="no"/>cation is denied to such world-wide and long-<lb
                    break="hyph-yes"/>maintained celebrity as that of Humboldt;<lb break="yes"
                />every thing that he writes belongs to man-<lb break="no"/>kind. He now presents to
                our astonishment<lb break="yes"/>and admiration the spectacle of a man of the<lb
                    break="yes"/>highest order of intellect, at the advanced<lb break="yes"/>age of
                eighty-nine, in the full possession of<lb break="yes"/>all his powers, and busily
                engaged in the<lb break="yes"/>completion of a work of the vastest scope<lb
                    break="yes"/>and the most profound scientific generaliza-<lb break="no"/>tions.
                We do not know where to look, at<lb break="yes"/>least in modern times, for any
                parallel case.<lb break="yes"/>The nearest approaches to it are those of<lb
                    break="yes"/>Serjeant Maynard, who was discharging at<lb break="yes"
                />eighty-eight, with vigor and ability, the du-<lb break="no"/>ties of Lord High
                Commissioner, and of<lb break="yes"/>Titian, &#x201C;the gay, smiling old
                man,&#x201D; as Col-<lb break="no"/>eridge calls him, who at eighty-nine, and for<lb
                    break="yes"/>ten years more, was painting pictures hardly<lb break="yes"
                />inferior to those of his prime. But here is<lb break="yes"/>one of the greatest of
                men, arrived at an<lb break="yes"/>age at which ordinary men become objects<lb
                    break="yes"/>of interest and reverence, and with not a<lb break="yes"/>spot of
                decay upon the full-orbed glory of<lb break="yes"/>his setting sun! It is good for
                us to be liv-<lb break="no"/>ing at a time when we can witness such a<lb break="yes"
                />spectacle.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>Humboldt, in spite of his infinite avoca-<lb break="no"/>tions and of his vast
                correspondence with<lb break="yes"/>whatever is most distinguished in the whole<lb
                    break="yes"/>circle of the globe, perseveres in the habits<lb break="yes"/>of
                his long life, and never, on any occasion,<lb break="yes"/>employs another to write
                for him. What is<lb break="yes"/>perhaps quite as remarkable, there are no<lb
                    break="yes"/>more signs of age in his manuscript than<lb break="yes"/>there are
                in his style and his thoughts. The<lb break="yes"/>original letter, of which the
                following is a<lb break="yes"/>translation, is in a hand differing in no per-<lb
                    break="no"/>ceptible particular from manuscripts written<lb break="yes"/>by him
                forty years ago. He is enabled to go<lb break="yes"/>through his immense labors by
                his habits of<lb break="yes"/>regular industry, and by the fortunate pe-<lb
                    break="no"/>culiarity of his constitution, which enables<lb break="yes"/>him to
                live with comparatively little sleep.<lb break="yes"/>Most of his hard work is done
                at night, when<lb break="yes"/>others are at rest.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <p>Humboldt has had the wisdom to keep his<lb break="yes"/>personal attachments in
                constant repair; and<lb break="yes"/>now enjoys the devoted regard of men who<lb
                    break="yes"/>are the grand-children of his contemporaries,<lb break="yes"/>with
                whom he began life. And he has never<lb break="yes"/>allowed his intellectual
                eminence or his age<lb break="yes"/>to emancipate him from the discharge of the<lb
                    break="yes"/>common duties and small courtesies of life:<lb break="yes"/>
                <cb/> he is a man full of thoughtful and observant<lb break="yes"
                />kindness&#x2014;wearing his honors with a grace-<lb break="no"/>ful gentleness
                that establishes ties of sympa-<lb break="no"/>thy between him and men who can be
                    naught<lb break="yes"/>to him intellectually; and thus he receives<lb
                    break="yes"/>from the community around him an affection-<lb break="no"/>ate
                reverence which his genius and learning<lb break="yes"/>alone could not have
                secured.</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="2">
                <opener>
                    <salute>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">To George Ticknor, Esq.,</hi> Author of
                            the<lb break="yes"/>
                        <hi rendition="#c">History of Spanish Literature.</hi>
                    </salute>
                </opener>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;My Dear and Excellent Friend:&#x2014;Bonds<lb break="yes"/>of friendship
                    which have their origin so far<lb break="yes"/>back in my family as the
                    affection felt for<lb break="yes"/>you by my brother William von Humboldt,<lb
                        break="yes"/>when you lived in Germany, as a young man,<lb break="yes"/>seem
                    to impose on me the very pleasant duty<lb break="yes"/>of giving you some sign
                    of life&#x2014;that is to<lb break="yes"/>say, a renewed proof of my attachment
                        to<lb break="yes"/>you and my interest in your country, and a<lb break="yes"
                    />brief account of my labors.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;My physical strength declines, but it de-<lb break="no"/>clines slowly.
                    My steps are more uncertain<lb break="yes"/>in their direction, owing to a
                    feebleness (a<lb break="yes"/>relaxing) of the ligaments of the knees; but<lb
                        break="yes"/>I can remain standing for an hour, without<lb break="yes"
                    />being fatigued. I continue to work chiefly at<lb break="yes"/>night, being
                    unrelentingly persecuted by my<lb break="yes"/>correspondence, which increases
                    the more as<lb break="yes"/>one becomes an object of public curiosity.<lb
                        break="yes"/>What is called literary celebrity is especially<lb break="yes"
                    />the result of a long endurance of life, (une<lb break="yes"/>longue patience
                    de vivre). This kind of emi-<lb break="no"/>nence increases, therefore, in
                    proportion as<lb break="yes"/>imbecility becomes more manifest. I am<lb
                        break="yes"/>never really ill, but often incommoded, as<lb break="yes"/>is
                    to be expected at the age of eighty-nine.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Since we were only two persons in the<lb break="yes"/>American
                    expedition, (the unfortunate Carlos<lb break="yes"/>de Montufar,<note
                        place="foot" n="*">Carlos de Montufar was a young man pas-<lb break="no"
                        />sionately attached to science, and accompanied<lb break="yes"/>Humboldt
                        and Bonpland from Quito, where they<lb break="yes"/>arrived in January,
                        1802, through all their travels<lb break="yes"/>in Peru and Mexico, till
                        their embarkation at<lb break="yes"/>Vera Cruz in the spring of 1804.</note>
                    son of the Marquis de Sel-<lb break="no"/>valegra, of Quito, fell a victim to
                    his love for<lb break="yes"/>the liberty of his country), it is somewhat<lb
                        break="yes"/>remarkable that we should both have reached<lb break="yes"/>so
                    advanced an age. Bonpland, still much<lb break="yes"/>occupied with scientific
                    labors, even cherish-<lb break="no"/>ing the hope of visiting Europe again,
                        and<lb break="yes"/>of bringing in person back to Paris his rich<lb
                        break="yes"/>and beautiful collections in botany and geolo-<lb break="no"
                    />gy, is eighty-five years old, and enjoys greater<lb break="yes"/>strength than
                    I do.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <pb n="207" facs="#f0002"/>
                <cb/>
                <p>&#x201C;I have just published in Germany the<lb break="yes"/>4th volume of
                    Cosmos, and they are now<lb break="yes"/>printing the 5th volume, which
                        completes<lb break="yes"/>that work so imprudently begun and so fa-<lb
                        break="no"/>vorably received by the public. General<lb break="yes"/>Sabine
                    writes me that the English translation<lb break="yes"/>is finished and will
                    appear immediately. The<lb break="yes"/>same news comes to me from France,
                        from<lb break="yes"/>M. Galuzzi, who has been passing the winter<lb
                        break="yes"/>in the south, at Cannes.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;The great and beautiful work of Agassiz<lb break="yes"/>(the first two
                    volumes) reached me only a<lb break="yes"/>few days since. It will produce a
                    great effect<lb break="yes"/>by the breadth of its general views and by<lb
                        break="yes"/>the extreme sagacity of its special embryo-<lb break="no"
                    />logical observations. I never believed that<lb break="yes"/>this illustrious
                    man, who is no less a man of<lb break="yes"/>a constant and beautiful nature,
                    would accept<lb break="yes"/>the offers nobly made him in Paris. I was<lb
                        break="yes"/>sure that gratitude would bind him to a new<lb break="yes"
                    />country where he finds a field so immense<lb break="yes"/>for his researches
                    and great means of assist-<lb break="no"/>ance. I hope he may be inclined,
                        together<lb break="yes"/>with his great anatomical and physiological<lb
                        break="yes"/>labors among the inferior organisms, to give<lb break="yes"/>us
                    also the specific icthyology of the numer-<lb break="no"/>ous basins of the
                    &#x2018;Far West,&#x2019; beginning with<lb break="yes"/>the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Holy</hi> Empire of the Mormons.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Science has lately met with an immense<lb break="yes"/>loss here by the
                    unexpected death of the<lb break="yes"/>greatest anatomist of our century,
                    &#x2014; Prof.<lb break="yes"/>Johann Müller.<note place="foot" n="*">Johann
                        Müller, who died a few months ago,<lb break="yes"/>was only 57 years
                        old.</note> This loss is as great for<lb break="yes"/>science, as was for
                    art the death of the immor-<lb break="no"/>tal sculptor Rauch.<note place="foot"
                        n="&#x2020;">Rauch, who died last autumn, was above<lb break="yes"/>eighty,
                        and seemed, until shortly before his death,<lb break="yes"/>destined to many
                        years of health. When Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt kept his 87th birthday, the
                        14th September,<lb break="yes"/>1856, with his niece, the admirable Madame
                            de<lb break="yes"/>Bülow, at Tegel the favorite residence of her<lb
                            break="yes"/>father and of his brother William, he desired to<lb
                            break="yes"/>have only one other person of the party, and that<lb
                            break="yes"/>was Rauch, undoubtedly then the first of living<lb
                            break="yes"/>sculptors. It is most agreeable to know that a<lb
                            break="yes"/>fine bust of Humboldt by Rauch is either already<lb
                            break="yes"/>in the collection of a gentleman at Washington,<lb
                            break="yes"/>or will soon be there.</note> The universality of his<lb
                        break="yes"/>zöological knowledge in the inferior organiza-<lb break="no"
                    />tions, placed Johann Müller near Cuvier,<lb break="yes"/>having a great
                    pre-eminence in the delicacy<lb break="yes"/>of his anatomical and physiological
                        work.<lb break="yes"/>
                    <cb/> He made long and painful voyages at his<lb break="yes"/>own expense on the
                    shores of the Mediterra-<lb break="no"/>nean and in the Northern Seas. It is<lb
                        break="yes"/>scarcely two years since he came near per-<lb break="no"
                    />ishing by shipwreck on the coast of Norway.<lb break="yes"/>He sustained
                    himself by swimming for more<lb break="yes"/>than half an hour, and considered
                        himself<lb break="yes"/>quite lost when he was wonderfully rescued.<lb
                        break="yes"/>I lose in him a friend who was very dear to<lb break="yes"/>me.
                    He was a man of great talent and at<lb break="yes"/>the same time of a noble
                    character. He was<lb break="yes"/>admirable for the elevation and
                        independence<lb break="yes"/>of his opinions. By making enormous sac-<lb
                        break="no"/>rifices he was able to form a choice library,<lb break="yes"
                    />not only of anatomy, physiology and zöology,<lb break="yes"/>but one that
                    extended over all the physical<lb break="yes"/><choice><sic>sciencies</sic><corr type="editorial">sciences</corr></choice>. It consists of more
                    than three<lb break="yes"/>thousand volumes, well bound, and of as<lb
                        break="yes"/>many more volumes containing dissertations,<lb break="yes"/>so
                    difficult to collect. Mr. Müller spent<lb break="yes"/>nearly 800 thalers a year
                    [600 dollars] for<lb break="yes"/>binding alone. It would be sad to see a
                        col-<lb break="no"/>lection dispersed and broken up, which was<lb
                        break="yes"/>made with so much care. Since duplicates<lb break="yes"/>are
                    dreaded in Europe, I cannot help fearing<lb break="yes"/>lest this fine
                    collection should cross the great<lb break="yes"/>Atlantic <hi rendition="#i"
                        >river.</hi> I have almost the air of ex-<lb break="no"/>citing your
                    appetite when I thus present my-<lb break="no"/>self before you as a citizen of
                    the world,<lb break="yes"/>while the <hi rendition="#i">Church</hi> journal of
                    Vienna calls me,<lb break="yes"/>in capital letters, a naturalist assassin of
                        souls<lb break="yes"/>&#x2018;Seelen-mörder.&#x2019;</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x201C;Accept, I beg you, my dear and respected<lb break="yes"/>friend, the
                    renewal of the high and affection-<lb break="no"/>ate consideration which, for
                    so many years, I<lb break="yes"/>have given to your talents and to your char-<lb
                        break="no"/>acter.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;A. <hi rendition="#k">v. Humboldt.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <dateline>&#x201C;Berlin, 9 May, 1858.&#x201D;</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="2">
                <p>&#x201C;Since so many benevolent persons, col-<lb break="no"/>ored as well as
                    white, in the United States,<lb break="yes"/>take an interest in me, it would be
                        agreeable<lb break="yes"/>to me, my dear friend, if this letter trans-<lb
                        break="no"/>lated into English by you, could be <hi rendition="#i"
                        >printed,</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>without omitting what relates to our mutual<lb break="yes"
                    />friendship. If you think it necessary you<lb break="yes"/>can add that I have
                    myself begged of you<lb break="yes"/>this publication, because I leave
                        unanswered<lb break="yes"/>so many letters that are addressed to
                    me.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 