<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">A letter from Humboldt on the death of Bonpland</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:24</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VII.159</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-11-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-01.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-05.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-11-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">A letter from Humboldt on the death of Bonpland</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1858</date>
          <pubPlace>New York City, New York</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;New-York Daily Tribune&lt;/i&gt; 18:5394 (5. August 1858), S. 3.</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">A LETTER FROM HUMBOLDT ON THE<lb/>DEATH OF BONPLAND.</hi></head><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<p>The Berlin correspondent of <hi rendition="#i">The Boston Journal</hi><lb/>sends the following
                    letter of Alexander von Humboldt,<lb/>on the recent death of Bonpland, his
                    junior by about<lb/>four years. Humboldt hoped he might not survive<lb/>the
                    warmest friend of his early years, but it seems to<lb/>be the destiny of this
                    venerable man to follow all his<lb/>friends to the grave, and to remain himself
                    the sole<lb/>representative of the times of his youth.</p><lb/><div n="2"><head><hi rendition="#k">humboldt&#x2019;s letter.</hi></head><lb/><p>Conscious of the deep sympathy of numerous friends<lb/>in the sorrow occasioned by the
                        wide-spread report of<lb/>the death of my dear, noble friend and
                        fellow-trav-<lb/>eler, Bonpland, I consider it my duty to give at
                        least<lb/>a brief notice of this event, for the particulars of<lb/>which I
                        am indebted to the kind services of Dr. Lalle-<lb/>mant, author of an
                        important paper on the diseases<lb/>of Europeans in the tropics. This
                        talented gentle-<lb/>man, after leaving the Austrian Royal Expedition
                        in<lb/>the frigate Novara, in February of this year, for the<lb/>purpose of
                        doing a kindness to myself, made the<lb/>journey from Rio Janeiro to Rio
                        Grande, and thence<lb/>by way of Porto Alegro through the former
                        Jesuit<lb/>Mission to San Borgia, under the erroneous impres-<lb/>sion that
                        Bonpland, who had gone there in 1831, was<lb/>still resident at that place.
                        I have received two letters<lb/>from Dr. Lallemant, one dated at San Borgia
                        on the<lb/>10th of April, the other written from the village
                        of<lb/>Umguaiana, after he had visited Bonpland at Santa<lb/>Ana. An
                        extended abstract of these letters having<lb/>been sent to the editor of the
                        widely-read and inter-<lb/>esting botanical jonrnal, the <hi rendition="#i"
                            >Bonplandia,</hi> in Hanover,<lb/>the following briefer extracts may
                        here suffice.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;In San Borgia,&#x201D; writes Dr. Lallemant, &#x201C;I lived<lb/>with an intimate friend
                        of Bonpland, the Vicar Gray,<lb/>with whom I visited the garden of the
                        botanist, so<lb/>long cultivated with care, but now lying waste
                        and<lb/>desolate. It was near the close of the year 1857 that<lb/>the Vicar
                        last received letters from Bonpland, since<lb/>when intelligence had come of
                        his severe illness.<lb/>Letters of inquiry still remained unanswered,
                        and<lb/>notwithstanding the short distance between the<lb/>places, the
                        people of San Borgia were uncertain<lb/>whether I should find your fellow
                        travellers yet in<lb/>the land of the living. In 1853 Bonpland had
                        left<lb/>San Borgia and taken up his residence upon his<lb/>larger
                        plantation of Santa Ana, where he had long<lb/>occupied himself in the
                        cultivation of orange trees.<lb/>The residence of the aged scholar in the
                        Estancia<lb/>of Santa Ana, consists of two large buildings,<lb/>mere clay
                        walls, bound together by bamboo sticks<lb/>and a few beams, and thatched
                        with straw. These<lb/>buildings have doors, but no windows, the light
                        being<lb/>admitted through the chinks between the bam-<lb/>boo sticks.
                        Despite the deep furrows which an event-<lb/>ful life had engraven in the
                        beloved countenance, his<lb/>eye had not grown dim nor lost any of its
                            full-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>thoughted vivacity. But lively conversation, though<lb/>started by
                        himself, appeared to weary him much, and<lb/>he suffered severely from a
                        chronic affection of the<lb/>bladder. The privations he had so strangely
                        im-<lb/>posed upon himself are by no means in consequence<lb/>of poverty, or
                        of any necessity for abstinence, but of<lb/>long custom, great self-control,
                        and characteristic in-<lb/>dividuality. The Government of Corrientes has
                        pre-<lb/>sented to him an estate valued at 10,000 Spanish pias-<lb/>ters,
                        and he enjoys a French pension of 3,000 francs<lb/>a year. He has never made
                        the practice of medi-<lb/>cine a source of pecuniary profit to himself.
                        Though<lb/>universally revered, he loves the solitude, and espe-<lb/>cially
                        avoids all persons who might offer him assist-<lb/>ance or advice. His
                        scientific ardor has not yet<lb/>abated, and his collections and manuscripts
                        are depos-<lb/>ited in Corrientes, where he has founded a
                            national<lb/>museum.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;On the following morning I found him visibly<lb/>worse, and sinking away. The night had
                        been a<lb/>painful one. I pressed him to tell me whether I<lb/>might not, in
                        some way, be of service to him. But<lb/>I fared no better than his other
                        friends&#x2014;he would ac-<lb/>cept of no assistence. How gladly would I
                        have per-<lb/>suaded him to return once more to civilized society!<lb/>But
                        I, too, felt with him that his time was past. He<lb/>belongs to the first
                        half of the nineteenth century,<lb/>not to the second. I think that your
                        friend himself<lb/>was moved when I took his wasted hands in mine
                        with<lb/>the <choice>
                            <sic>preseure</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">pressure</corr>
                        </choice> of farewell. For three months now his<lb/>attendants have remarked
                        his failing <choice>
                            <sic>strengtb</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">strength</corr>
                        </choice>, and<lb/>perhaps the old man had the same foreboding as
                        my-<lb/>self at parting, that I might be the last <choice>
                            <sic>embassador</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">ambassador</corr>
                        </choice> of<lb/>European lineage who should penetrate the depths of<lb/>the
                        wilderness to offer him regard, love and thanks, in<lb/>the name of that
                        science which owes so much to his<lb/>labors. I mounted my horse and rode
                        northward<lb/>through the evergreen plains. No path showed my<lb/>way, no
                                guide disturbed me; I was alone with my <choice><sic>sor<lb/>rowful</sic><corr type="editorial">sor-<lb break="no"/>rowful</corr></choice> thoughts over the
                        departed Bonpland.</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Yet how cheerful the last latter I received from<lb/>Bonpland, bearing date the 7th of June, 1857! &#x2018;I<lb/>myself,&#x2019; he writes, &#x2018;shall bring all my collections and<lb/>&#x2018;manuscripts to Paris, and deposit them in the Muse-<lb/>&#x2018;um. My journey to France will be exceedingly short.<lb/>&#x2018;I shall return to my Santa Ana, where I lead a quiet<lb/>&#x2018;and happy life. Here shall I die, and my sepulchre<lb/>&#x2018;and my grave shall be underneath the shadow of the<lb/>&#x2018;many trees I have planted. Oh, how happy were I,<lb/>&#x2018;my dear Humboldt, could we meet once more, and<lb/>&#x2018;recall our common experiences! On the 28th of<lb/>&#x2018;August next I shall be eighty-four years old, and am<lb/>&#x2018;yet four years younger than you. A man lately died<lb/>&#x2018;in this vicinity who had attained the age of one hun-<lb/>&#x2018;dred and seven. What a prospect for two travelers<lb/>&#x2018;who have already stepped beyond the eightieth<lb/>&#x2018;year!&#x2019;&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>The cheering, almost life-desiring tone of this letter,<lb/>contrasts strangely with the
                        melancholy representa-<lb/>tions of Dr. Lallemant. According to Herr v.
                        Tschudi<lb/>the report was credited in Montevideo on the 29th of<lb/>May,
                        that Bonpland had died at Borgia, the date of<lb/>his death uncertain. Yet
                        Dr. Lallemant had spoken<lb/>with him on the 18th of April in Santa Ana, and
                        on<lb/>May 10 the report of his death was discredited at<lb/>Porto Allegro.
                        Thus there yet remains ground for<lb/>hope that the younger is not to be
                        first called away.<lb/>Such remoteness often stretches uncertainty to a
                        pain-<lb/>ful duration; such the solicitude felt for Edward Vogel<lb/>in
                        Central Africa, and for Adolphus Schlagintwait in<lb/>Central
                        Asia&#x2014;the sorrowfully missed!</p><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#i">Berlin,</hi> July 12, 1858.</dateline><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">ALEXANDER V. HUMBOLDT.</hi></salute></closer></div></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
