<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-05" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#b">Alexander Von Humboldt.</hi></head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <opener>
                        <dateline>
                            <hi rendition="#et">
                                <hi rendition="#k">Berlin,</hi> May 9, 1858.</hi>
                        </dateline>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <salute>
                            <hi rendition="#k">My Dear and Excellent Friend</hi>
                        </salute>
                    </opener>
                    <p>&#x2014; Bonds of friendship,<lb break="yes"/>which have their origin so far
                        back in my family, and the<lb break="yes"/>affection felt for you by my
                        brother William Von Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt, when you lived in Germany, as
                        a young man, seem<lb break="yes"/>to impose on me the very pleasant duty of
                        giving you<lb break="yes"/>some sign of life&#x2014;that is to say, a
                        renewed proof of my<lb break="yes"/>attachment to you and my interest in
                        your country, and a<lb break="yes"/>brief account of my labors.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>My physical strength declines, but it declines slowly.<lb break="yes"/>My
                        steps are more uncertain in their direction, owing to a<lb break="yes"
                        />feebleness (a relaxing) of the ligaments of the knees; but<lb break="yes"
                        />I can remain standing for an hour without being fatigued.<lb break="yes"
                        />I continue to work chiefly at night, being unrelentingly<lb break="yes"
                        />persecuted by my correspondence, which increases the<lb break="yes"/>more
                        as one becomes an object of public curiosity. What<lb break="yes"/>is called
                        literary celebrity is especially the result of a<lb break="yes"/>long
                        endurance of life, (<hi rendition="#i">une longue patience de vivre.</hi>)
                            This<lb break="yes"/>kind of eminence increases, therefore, in
                        proportion as im-<lb break="no"/>becility becomes more manifest. I am never
                        really ill, but<lb break="yes"/>often incommoded, as is to be expected at
                        the age of<lb break="yes"/>eighty-nine.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Since we were only two persons in the American expe-<lb break="no"/>dition
                        (the unfortunate Carlos de Montufar,<note place="foot" n="*">Carlos de
                            Montufar was a young man passionately attach-<lb break="no"/>ed to
                            science, and accompanied Humboldt and Bonpland from<lb break="yes"
                            />Quito, where they arrived in January, 1802, through all their<lb
                                break="yes"/>travels in Peru and Mexico, till their embarkation at
                                Vera<lb break="yes"/>Cruz in the spring of 1804.</note> son of
                            the<lb break="yes"/>Marquis de Selvalegra, of Quito, fell a victim to
                        his love<lb break="yes"/>for the liberty of his country), it is somewhat
                            remarkable<lb break="yes"/>that we should both have reached so advanced
                        an age.<lb break="yes"/>Bonpland, still much occupied with scientific
                        labors, even<lb break="yes"/>cherishing the hope of visiting Europe again,
                        and of<lb break="yes"/>bringing in person back to Paris his rich and
                            beautiful<lb break="yes"/>collections in botany and geology, is
                        eighty-five years old,<lb break="yes"/>and enjoys greater strength than I
                        do.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>I have just published in Germany the fourth volume of<lb break="yes"
                        />&#x201C;Cosmos,&#x201D; and they are now printing the fifth volume,<lb
                            break="yes"/>which completes that work so imprudently begun and so<lb
                            break="yes"/>favorably received by the public. General Sabine writes<lb
                            break="yes"/>me that the English translation is finished and will
                            appear<lb break="yes"/>immediately. The same news comes to me from
                            France,<lb break="yes"/>from M. Galuzzi, who has been passing the winter
                        in the<lb break="yes"/>south, at Cannes.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>The great and beautiful work of Agassiz (the first two<lb break="yes"
                        />volumes) reached me only a few days since. It will<lb break="yes"/>produce
                        a great effect by the breadth of its general<lb break="yes"/>views and by
                        the extreme sagacity of its special em-<lb break="no"/>bryological
                        observations. I never believed that this illus-<lb break="no"/>trious man,
                        who is no less a man of a constant and<lb break="yes"/>beautiful nature,
                        would accept the offers nobly made him<lb break="yes"/>in Paris. I was sure
                        that gratitude would bind him to a<lb break="yes"/>new country, where he
                        finds a field so immense for his<lb break="yes"/>researches and great means
                        of assistance. I hope he may<lb break="yes"/>be inclined, together with his
                        great anatomical and physi-<lb break="no"/>olgical labors among the inferior
                        organisms, to give us<lb break="yes"/>also the specific icthyology of the
                        numerous basins of the<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Far West,&#x201D; beginning
                        with the holy empire of the Mor-<lb break="no"/>mons.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Science has lately met with an immense loss here by<lb break="yes"/>the
                        unexpected death of the greatest anatomist of our cen-<lb break="no"/>tury,
                        Professor Johann Muller.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Johann Muller, who
                            died a few months ago, was only 57<lb break="yes"/>yeara old.</note>
                        This loss is as great for<lb break="yes"/>science, as was for art the death
                        of the immortal sculptor,<lb break="yes"/>Rauch.<note place="foot"
                            n="&#x2021;">Rauch, who died last autumn, was above eighty, and<lb
                                break="yes"/>seemed, until shortly before his death, destined to
                            many years<lb break="yes"/>of health. When Humboldt kept his 87th
                            birthday, the 14th of<lb break="yes"/>September, 1856, with his niece,
                            the admirable Madame de<lb break="yes"/>Bulow, at Tegel, the favorite
                            residence of her father and of<lb break="yes"/>his brother William, he
                            desired to have only one other person<lb break="yes"/>of the party, and
                            that was Rauch, undoubtedly then the first<lb break="yes"/>of living
                            sculptors. It is most agreeable to know that a fine<lb break="yes"/>bust
                            of Humboldt by Rauch is either already in the <choice><sic>colllec-<lb break="no"
                            />tion</sic><corr type="editorial">collec-<lb break="no"
                            />tion</corr></choice> of a gentlemen at Washington, or will soon be there.</note> The
                        universality of his zoological knowledge in<lb break="yes"/>the interior
                        organizations, placed Johann Muller near<lb break="yes"/>Cuvier, having a
                        great pre-eminence in the delicacy of his<lb break="yes"/>anatomical and
                        physiological work. He made long and<lb break="yes"/>painful voyages at his
                        own expense on the shores of the<lb break="yes"/>Mediterranean and in the
                        Northern seas. It is scarcely two<lb break="yes"/>years since he came near
                        perishing by shipwreck on the<lb break="yes"/>coast of Norway. He sustained
                        himself by swimming for<lb break="yes"/>more than half an hour, and
                        considered himself quite<lb break="yes"/>lost when he was wonderfully
                        rescued. I lose in him a<lb break="yes"/>friend who was very dear to me. He
                        was a man of<lb break="yes"/>great talent, and at the same time of a noble
                            character.<lb break="yes"/>He was admirable for the elevation and
                            independence<lb break="yes"/>of his opinions. By making enormous
                        sacrifices he was<lb break="yes"/>able to form a choice library, not only of
                        anatomy, phy-<lb break="no"/>siology and zoology, but one that extended over
                            all<lb break="yes"/>the physical sciences. It consists of more than
                            three<lb break="yes"/>thousand volumes, well bound, and of as many
                            more<lb break="yes"/>volumes containing dissertations so difficult to
                        collect. Mr.<lb break="yes"/>Muller spent nearly eight hundred thalers a
                        year ($600)<lb break="yes"/>for binding alone. It would be sad to see a
                        collection dis-<lb break="no"/>persed and broken up, which was made with so
                            much<lb break="yes"/>care. Since duplicates are dreaded in Europe, I
                            cannot<lb break="yes"/>help fearing lest this fine collection should
                        cross the great<lb break="yes"/>Atlantic river. I have almost the air of
                        exciting your<lb break="yes"/>appetite when I thus present myself before you
                        as a citi-<lb break="no"/>zen of the world, while the church journal of
                        Vienna calls<lb break="yes"/>me, in capital letters, a naturalist assassin
                        of souls,<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Seelen-morder.&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Accept, I beg you, my dear and respected friend, the<lb break="yes"/>renewal of the high and affectionate consideration which,<lb break="yes"/>for so many years, I have given to your talents and to<lb break="yes"/>your character.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rendition="#et">A. V. HUMBOLDT.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <p>
                        <hi rendition="#k">To George Ticknor, Esq.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>Since so many benevolent persons, colored as well as<lb break="yes"/>white,
                        in the United States, take an interest in me, it<lb break="yes"/>would be
                        agreeable to me, my dear friend, if this letter,<lb break="yes"/>translated
                        into English by you, could be printed, without<lb break="yes"/>omitting what
                        relates to our mutual friendship. If you<lb break="yes"/>think it necessary
                        you can add that I have myself begged<lb break="yes"/>of you this
                        publication, because I leave unanswered so<lb break="yes"/>many letters that
                        are addressed to me.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 