<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">Interesting Letter from Humboldt. His Old Age – The Fifth Volume of Cosmos – Reminiscences of his Contemporaries</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:25</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VII.179</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-23-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-01-neu.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-05-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-12-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-18-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-19-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-20-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-21-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-22-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-xxx_Letter_to_Ticknor-23-neu.xml" type="self"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">Interesting Letter from Humboldt. His Old Age – The Fifth Volume of Cosmos – Reminiscences of his Contemporaries</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="1"/>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1858</date>
          <pubPlace>Boston, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;Boston Investigator&lt;/i&gt; 18 (25. August 1858), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung, Kapitälchen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="#f0001"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <byline>From the Boston Courier.</byline>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <head>Interesting Letter from Humboldt.</head><lb break="yes"/>
                <p><hi rendition="#i">His Old Age&#x2014;The Fifth Volume of Cosmos&#x2014;Reminiscen-<lb break="no"/>ces of his Contemporaries.</hi></p>
                
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>We have the pleasure of laying before our readers<lb break="yes"/>the translation of a letter addressed by the illustrious<lb break="yes"/>Alexander Von Humboldt to our townsman, Mr. Tick-<lb break="no"/>nor. Humboldt now presents, to our astonishment and<lb break="yes"/>admiration, the spectacle of a man of the highest order<lb break="yes"/>of intellect, at the advanced age of eighty-nine, in the<lb break="yes"/>full possession of all his powers, and busily engaged in<lb break="yes"/>the completion of a work of the vastest scope and the<lb break="yes"/>most profound scientific generalizations. We do not<lb break="yes"/>know where to look, at least in modern times, for any<lb break="yes"/>parallel case. The nearest approaches to it are those<lb break="yes"/>of Sergeant Maynard, who was discharging at eighty-<lb break="hyph-yes"/>eight, with vigor and ability, the duties of Lord High<lb break="yes"/>Commissioner, and of Titian, &#x201C;the gay, smiling old<lb break="yes"/>man,&#x201D; as Coleridge calls him, who, at eighty-nine, and<lb break="yes"/>for ten years more, was painting pictures hardly inferi-<lb break="no"/>or to those of his prime.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Humboldt, in spite of his infinite avocations and of<lb break="yes"/>his vast correspondence with whatever is most distin-<lb break="no"/>guished in the whole circle of the globe, perseveres<lb break="yes"/>in the habits of his long life, and never, on any occa-<lb break="no"/>sion, employs any one to write for him. What is per-<lb break="no"/>haps quite as remarkable, there are no more signs of<lb break="yes"/>age in his manuscript than there was in his style and<lb break="yes"/>thoughts. The original letter, of which the following<lb break="yes"/>is a translation, is in a hand differing in no perceptible<lb break="yes"/>particular from manuscripts written by him forty years<lb break="yes"/>ago. He is enabled to go through his immense labors<lb break="yes"/>by his habits of regular industry, and by the fortunate<lb break="yes"/>peculiarity of his constitution, which enables him to<lb break="yes"/>live with comparatively little sleep. Most of his hard<lb break="yes"/>work is done at night, when others are at rest.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <p>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">To George Ticknor, Esq.</hi>:&#x2014;My dear and excel-<lb break="no"/>lent friend: Bonds of friendship which have their ori-<lb break="no"/>gin so far back in my family, and the affection felt for<lb break="yes"/>you by my brother William von Humboldt, when you<lb break="yes"/>lived in Germany, as a young man, seem to impose on<lb break="yes"/>me the very pleasant duty of giving you some sign of<lb break="yes"/>life&#x2014;that is to say, a renewed proof of my attachment<lb break="yes"/>to you and my interest in your country, and a brief ac-<lb break="no"/>count of my labors.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;My physical strength declines, but it declines slow-<lb break="no" />ly. My steps are more uncertain in their direction,<lb break="yes"/>owing to a feebleness (a relaxing) of the ligaments of<lb break="yes"/>the knees; but I can remain standing for an hour, with-<lb break="no"/>out being fatigued. I continue to work chiefly at night,<lb break="yes"/>being unrelentingly persecuted by my correspondence,<lb break="yes"/>which increases the more as one becomes an object of<lb break="yes"/>public curiosity. What is called literary celebrity is<lb break="yes"/>especially the result of a long endurance of life, (<hi rendition="#i">une<lb break="yes"/>longue patience de vivre.</hi>) This kind of eminence in-<lb break="no"/>creases, therefore, in proportion as imbecility becomes<lb break="yes"/>more manifest. I am never really ill, but often incom-<lb break="no"/>moded, as is to be expected at the age of eighty-nine.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Since we were only two persons in the American<lb break="yes" />expedition, (the unfortunate Carlos de Montufar, son<lb break="yes"/>of the Marquis de Selvalegra, of Quito, fell a victim<lb break="yes"/>to his love for the liberty of his country,) it is some-<lb break="no"/>what remarkable that we should both have reached so<lb break="yes"/>advanced an age. Bonpland, still much occupied with<lb break="yes"/>scientific labors, even cherishing the hope of visiting<lb break="yes"/>Europe again, and of bringing in person back to Paris<lb break="yes"/>his rich and beautiful collections in botany and geolo-<lb break="no"/>gy, is eighty-five years old, and enjoys greater strength<lb break="yes"/>than I do.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;I have just published in Germany the 4th volume<lb break="yes"/>of Cosmos, and they are now printing the 5th volume,<lb break="yes"/>which completes that work so imprudently begun and<lb break="yes"/>so favorably received by the public. General Sabine<lb break="yes"/>writes me that the English translation is finished and<lb break="yes"/>will appear immediately. The same news comes to<lb break="yes"/>me from France, from M. Galuzzi, who has been pass-<lb break="no"/>ing the winter in the south, at Cannes.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;The great and beautiful work of Agassiz (the first<lb break="yes" />two volumes) reached me only a few days since. It<lb break="yes"/>will produce a great effect by the breadth of its gener-<lb break="no"/>al views, and by the extreme sagacity of its special<lb break="yes"/>embryological observations. I never believed that this<lb break="yes"/>illustrious man, who is no less a man of a constant and<lb break="yes"/>beautiful nature, would accept the offers nobly made<lb break="yes"/>him in Paris. I was sure that gratitude would bind<lb break="yes"/>him to a new country where he finds a field so im-<lb break="no"/>mense for his researches, and great means of assist-<lb break="no"/>ance. I hope he may be inclined, together with his<lb break="yes"/>great anatomical and physiological labors among the<lb break="yes"/>inferior organisms, to give us also the specific icthyolo-<lb break="no"/>gy of the numerous basins of the &#x2018;Far West,&#x2019; begin-<lb break="no"/>ning with the <hi rendition="#i" >Holy</hi> Empire of the Mormons.</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Science has lately met with an immense loss here<lb break="yes"/>by the unexpected death of the greatest anatomist of<lb break="yes"/>our century&#x2014;Prof. Johann Muller. This loss is as<lb break="yes"/>great for science, as was for art the death of the im-<lb break="no"/>mortal sculptor, Rauch. The universality of his zoolog-<lb break="no"/>ical knowledge of the inferior organizations, placed<lb break="yes"/>Johann Muller near Cuvier, having a great pre-emi-<lb break="no"/>nence in the delicacy of his anatomical and physiolog-<lb break="no"/>ical work. He made long and painful voyages at his<lb break="yes"/>own expense on the shores of the Mediterranean and<lb break="yes"/>in the Northern seas. It is scarcely two years since he<lb break="yes"/>came near perishing by shipwreck on the coast of Nor-<lb break="no"/>way. He sustained himself by swimming for more<lb break="yes"/>than half an hour, and considered himself quite lost<lb break="yes"/>when he was wonderfully rescued. I lose in him a<lb break="yes"/>friend who was very dear to me. He was a man of<lb break="yes"/>great talent, and at the same time of a noble charac-<lb break="no"/>ter. He was admirable for the elevation and independ-<lb break="no"/>ence of his opinions. By making enormous sacrifices<lb break="yes"/>he was able to form a choice library, not only of anato-<lb break="no"/>my, physiology, and zoology, but one that extended<lb break="yes"/>over all the physical sciences. It consists of more than<lb break="yes"/>three thousand volumes, well bound, and of as many<lb break="yes"/>more volumes containing dissertations, so difficult to<lb break="yes"/>collect. Mr. Muller spent nearly 800 thalers a year<lb break="yes"/>($600) for binding alone. It would be sad to see a col-<lb break="no"/>lection dispersed and broken up, which was made with<lb break="yes"/>so much care. Since duplicates are dreaded in Europe,<lb break="yes"/>I cannot help fearing lest this fine collection should<lb break="yes"/>cross the great Atlantic <hi rendition="#i">river.</hi> I have almost the air<lb break="yes"/>of exciting you appetite when I thus present myself<lb break="yes"/>before you as a citizen of the world, while the <hi rendition="#i">Church</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>journal of Vienna calls me, in capital letters, a natural-<lb break="no"/>ist assassin of souls, &#x2018;Seelenmorder.&#x2019;</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p>&#x201C;Accept, I beg you, my dear and respected friend,<lb break="yes"/>the renewal of the high and affectionate consideration<lb break="yes"/>which, for so many years, I have given to your talents<lb break="yes"/>and to your character.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <salute>
                            <hi rendition="#et">A. V. HUMBOLDT.</hi>
                        </salute>
                        <lb break="yes"/>
                        <dateline>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Berlin, May</hi> 9, 1858.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <p>&#x201C;Since so many benevolent persons, colored as well<lb break="yes"/>as
                        white, in the United States, take an interest in me,<lb break="yes"/>it
                        would be agreeable to me, my dear friend, if this<lb break="yes"/>letter,
                        translated into English by you, could be <hi rendition="#i">printed,</hi>
                        <lb break="yes"/>without omitting what relates to our mutual friendship.<lb
                            break="yes"/>If you think it necessary you can add, that I have my-<lb
                            break="no"/>self begged of you this publication, because I leave<lb
                            break="yes"/>unanswered so many letters that are addressed to
                        me.&#x201D;</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 