<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-04" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#c">AIME BONPLAND.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb/>
                <dateline><hi rendition="#k">Berlin, 12th July, 1858.</hi></dateline>
                <p>&#x2014;Aware of the deep sympathy<lb/>
                    felt for me by many of my friends, in my great distress at<lb/>
                    the death of my beloved, noble friend and travelling com-<lb/>
                    panion, Bonpland, I have considered it my duty to publish<lb/>
                    at any rate a short preliminary communication on the sub-<lb/>
                    ject, for which I am indebted to the friendly zeal of Dr.<lb/>
                    Lallemant (author of an important work on the diseases of<lb/>
                    Europeans in tropical climates). This accomplished man<lb/>
                    thinking thereby to give me pleasure after leaving the Im-<lb/>
                    perial Austrian Expedition on board the frigate Novara,<lb/>
                    undertook a journey in February last from Rio Janeiro to<lb/>
                    Rio Grande, and from thence by Porto Alegre and the former<lb/>
                    Jesuit Missions, to San Borja, where he erroneously supposed<lb/>
                    that Bonpland was still residing, as he had since the year<lb/>
                    1831. I am in possession of two letters of Dr. Lallemant,<lb/>
                    one from San Borja, on the Uruguay, dated the 10th of<lb/>
                    April&#x2014;another written from the Villa de Uruguaiana, on the<lb/>
                    19th of April 1858, after having conversed with Bonpland at<lb/>
                    Santa Anna:&#x2014;
                </p>
                <p>&#x2018;Whilst at San Borja,&#x2019; writes Dr. Lallemant, &#x2018;I resided<lb/>
                    with an intimate friend of Bonpland, the vicar Gay, in whose<lb/>
                    company I visited the formerly well-kept garden of the<lb/>
                    botanist, but which is now desolate and overgrown. M. Gay<lb/>
                    had received the last letter from Bonpland towards the end<lb/>
                    of the year 1857. Subsequently news was received of his<lb/>
                    serious illness. Letters written with a view to learn the<lb/>
                    state of his health remained unanswered, and in spite of the<lb/>
                    short distance it was still uncertain at San Borja whether I<lb/>
                    should find your travelling companion alive. Bonpland had<lb/>
                    left San Borja in the year 1853, to reside on his larger estate<lb/>
                    at Santa Anna, where he long occupied himself in cultivat-<lb/>
                    ing orange trees of his own planting. The residence of the old<lb/>
                    man of science (in the Estancia of Santa Anna) consists of<lb/>
                    two large cottages, the mud walls of which are secured by<lb/>
                    bamboo poles and a few beams on the thatch. Both cottages<lb/>
                    have doors, but no windows, as the light is admitted by the<lb/>
                    crevices between the bamboo supports of the wall. I was<lb/>
                    received in a hearty and friendly manner. In spite<lb/>
                    of the deep lines which a stirring life had im-<lb/>
                    printed upon the beloved countenance, the eye was<lb/>
                    still piercing, clear, and full of expression. Spirited<lb/>
                    conversation, commenced by himself, seemed to weary him<lb/>
                    much, and he suffered much from chronic rheumatism of the<lb/>
                    bladder. The privations which he so wonderfully imposes on<lb/>
                    himself are not in consequence of want or necessary retrench-<lb/>
                    ment, but rather of long habit, great self-command, and indi-<lb/>
                    viduality. The government of Corrientes has presented him<lb/>
                    with an estate worth 10,000 Spanish piastres : he also enjoys<lb/>
                    a pension of 3000 francs per annum from the French<lb/>
                    government. He has always practised as a physician<lb/>
                    with the most perfect disinterestedness. He is uni-<lb/>
                    versally respected&#x2014;greatly prefers, however, solitude, and<lb/>
                    especially avoids those who come to him for advice and<lb/>
                    assistance. His scientific zeal remains unabated; his collec-<lb/>
                    tions and manuscripts are deposited at Corrientes, where he<lb/>
                    has founded a national museum. On the following morning<lb/>
                    I found him considerably weaker. The night had been a<lb/>
                    painful one. I earnestly entreated him to tell me if I could<lb/>
                    in any way be of service to him, but it was with me as with<lb/>
                    all his friends&#x2014;&#x2018; he was in no need of assistance.&#x2019; I took<lb/>
                    leave of him with a sorrowful heart. How gladly would I<lb/>
                    have persuaded him to return to the civilized world! But I<lb/>
                    felt with him, that his time was past. He belongs to the first<lb/>
                    period of the nineteenth century, not to the second. It ap-<lb/>
                    peared to me that your friend was himself affected when I<lb/>
                    took both his wrinkled hands in mine to bid him adieu.<lb/>
                    Those who surround him have found his powers failing him<lb/>
                    much during the last three months. Perhaps the old man<lb/>
                    experienced the same feelings at parting as myself, who<lb/>
                    would probably be the last messenger of European birth sent<lb/>
                    to him from afar off into this wilderness, to express to him<lb/>
                    in the name of Science all the reverence love, and thankful-<lb/>
                    ness which is due to him. I mounted my horse and gallopped<lb/>
                    in a northern direction across the green plains. No path<lb/>
                    directed me; I was disturbed by no guide; I was alone, with<lb/>
                    my mournful thoughts on Bonpland sinking into the grave.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>How happy was the last letter which I received from Bon-<lb/>
                    pland, from Corrientes, dated the 7th of June, 1857 :&#x2014;</p>
                <p>&#x201C;J&#x2019;irai,&#x201D; said he, &#x201C;porter mes collections et mes manuscrits<lb/>
                    moi-meme a Paris, pour les deposer au Museum. Mon voyage<lb/>
                    en France ne sera que tres court; je retournerai a mon S. Ana,<lb/>
                    ou je passe une vie tranquille et heureuse. C&#x2019;est la que je<lb/>
                    veux mourir, et ou mon tombeau se trouvera a l&#x2019;ombre des<lb/>
                    arbres nombreux que j&#x2019;ai plantes. Que je serais heureux,<lb/>
                    cher Humboldt, de te revoir encore une fois et de renouveler<lb/>
                    nos souvenirs communs. Le mois d&#x2019;aout prochain, le 28, je<lb/>
                    completerai ma 84eme annee, et j&#x2019;ai trois (4) ans de moins que<lb/>
                    toi. Il vient de mourir dans cette province un homme de<lb/>
                    107 ans. Quelle perspective pour deux voyageurs qui ont<lb/>
                    passe leur 80eme annee!&#x201D;</p>
                <p>This joyous letter, almost expressing a longing for life, con-<lb/>
                    trasts wonderfully with the mournful description of Dr. Lal-<lb/>
                    lemant&#x2019;s visit. In Monte Video (according to Mr. von<lb/>
                    Tschudi) it was believed that Bonpland had died at San Borja<lb/>
                    on the 29th of May, but without further particulars. On the<lb/>
                    18th of April Lallemant conversed with him at Santa Anna.<lb/>
                    On the 19th of May his death was denied at Porto Alegre.<lb/>
                    There is, therefore, still hope that the younger of the two has<lb/>
                    not been the first summoned away. At such great distances<lb/>
                    uncertainty is often unfortunately long continued, as evidence<lb/>
                    the anxiety on account of Edward Vogel in Central Africa and<lb/>
                    Adolph Schlagintweit in Central Asia.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#right">
                            <hi rendition="#k">Alexander V. Humboldt.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 