<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-04" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#c">AIME BONPLAND.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb/>
                <dateline><hi rendition="#k">Berlin, 12th July, 1858.</hi></dateline>
                    <p>&#x2014;Aware of the deep<lb/>
                    sympathy felt for me by many of my friends, in<lb/>
                    my great distress at the death of my beloved, noble<lb/>
                    friend and travelling companion, Bonpland, I have<lb/>
                    considered it my duty to publish at any rate a short<lb/>
                    preliminary communication on the subject, for<lb/>
                    which I am indebted to the friendly zeal of Dr.<lb/>
                    Lallemant (author of an important work on the<lb/>
                    diseases of Europeans in tropical climates). This<lb/>
                    accomplished man, thinking thereby to give me<lb/>
                    pleasure, after leaving the Imperial Austrian Ex-<lb/>
                    pedition on board the frigate Novara, undertook a<lb/>
                    journey in February last from Rio Janeiro to Rio<lb/>
                    Grande, and from thence by Porto Alegre and the<lb/>
                    former Jesuit Missions, to San Borja, where he<lb/>
                    erroneously supposed that Bonpland was still re-<lb/>
                    siding, as he had since the year 1831. I am in pos-<lb/>
                    session of two letters of Dr. Lallemant: one from<lb/>
                    San Borja, on the Uruguay, dated the 10th of April<lb/>
                    &#x2014; another written from the Villa de Uruguaiana,<lb/>
                    on the 19th of April, 1858, after having conversed<lb/>
                    with Bonpland at Santa Anna :&#x2014;</p>
                <p>&#x2018;Whilst at San Borja,&#x2019; writes Dr. Lallemant, &#x2018;I<lb/>
                    resided with an intimate friend of Bonpland, the<lb/>
                    vicar Gay, in whose company I visited the formerly<lb/>
                    well kept garden of the botanist, but which is now<lb/>
                    desolate and overgrown. M. Gay had received the<lb/>
                    last letter from Bonpland towards the end of the<lb/>
                    year 1857. Subsequently news was received of his<lb/>
                    serious illness. Letters written with a view to learn<lb/>
                    the state of his health remained unanswered, and<lb/>
                    in spite of the short distance it was still uncertain<lb/>
                    at San Borja whether I should find your travelling<lb/>
                    companion alive. Bonpland had left San Borja in<lb/>
                    the year 1853, to reside on his larger estate at Santa<lb/>
                    Anna, where he long occupied himself in cultivating<lb/>
                    orange trees of his own planting. The residence<lb/>
                    of the old man of science (in the Estancia of Santa<lb/>
                    Anna) consists of two large cottages, the mud walls<lb/>
                    of which are secured by bamboo poles and a few<lb/>
                    beams on the thatch. Both cottages have doors, but<lb/>
                    no windows, as the light is admitted by the crevices<lb/>
                    between the bamboo supports of the wall. I was re-<lb/>
                    ceived in a hearty and friendly manner. In spite<lb/>
                    of the deep lines which a stirring life had<lb/>
                    imprinted upon the beloved countenance, the eye was<lb/>
                    still piercing, clear, and full of expression. Spirited<lb/>
                    conversation, commenced by himself, seemed to<lb/>
                    weary him much, and he suffered much from chronic<lb/>
                    rheumatism of the bladder. The privations which he<lb/>
                    so wonderfully imposes on himself are not in conse-<lb/>
                    quence of want or necessary retrenchment, but<lb/>
                    rather of long habit, great self-command, and indi-<lb/>
                    viduality. The government of Corrientes has pre-<lb/>
                    sented him with an estate worth 10,000 Spanish<lb/>
                    piastres; he also enjoys a pension of 3,000 francs<lb/>
                    per annum from the French government. He has<lb/>
                    always practised as a physician, with the most perfect<lb/>
                    disinterestedness. He is universally respected&#x2014;<lb/>
                    greatly prefers, however, solitude, and especially<lb/>
                    avoids those who come to him for advice and assis-<lb/>
                    tance. His scientific zeal remains unabated; his<lb/>
                    collections and manuscripts are deposited at Cor-<lb/>
                    rientes, where he has founded a national museum.<lb/>
                    On the following morning I found him considerably<lb/>
                    weaker. The night had been a painful one. I ear-<lb/>
                    nestly entreated him to tell me if I could in any way<lb/>
                    be of service to him, but it was with me as with all his<lb/>
                    friends&#x2014;&#x2018;he was in no need of assistance.&#x2019; I took<lb/>
                    leave of him with a sorrowful heart. How gladly<lb/>
                    would I have persuaded on him to return to the civi-<lb/>
                    lised world! But I felt with him, that his time<lb/>
                    was past. He belongs to the first period of the<lb/>
                    nineteenth century, not to the second. It appeared<lb/>
                    to me that your friend was himself affected when<lb/>
                    I took both his wrinkled hands in mine to bid<lb/>
                    him adieu. Those who surround him have found<lb/>
                    his powers failing him much during the last three<lb/>
                    months. Perhaps the old man experienced the<lb/>
                    same feelings at parting as myself, who would<lb/>
                    probably be the last messenger of European birth<lb/>
                    sent to him from afar off into this wilderness, to<lb/>
                    express to him in the name of Science all the re-<lb/>
                    verence, love, and thankfulness which is due to<lb/>
                    him. I mounted my horse and gallopped in a<lb/>
                    northern direction across the green plains. No<lb/>
                    path directed me; I was disturbed by no guide; I<lb/>
                    was alone, with my mournful thoughts on Bonpland<lb/>
                    sinking into the grave.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>How happy was the last letter which I received<lb/>
                    from Bonpland, from Corrientes, dated the 7th of<lb/>
                    June, 1857.</p>
                <p>&#x201C;J&#x2019;irai,&#x201D; said he, &#x201C;porter mes collections et mes<lb/>
                    manuscrits moi-meme a Paris, pour les deposer au<lb/>
                    Museum. Mon voyage en France ne sera que tres<lb/>
                    court; je retournerai a mon S. Ana, ou je passe une<lb/>
                    vie tranquille et heureuse. C&#x2019;est la que je veux<lb/>
                    mourir, et où mon tombeau se trouvera a l&#x2019;ombre<lb/>
                    des arbres nombreux que j&#x2019;ai plantes. Que je serais<lb/>
                    heureux, cher Humboldt, de te revoir encore une<lb/>
                    fois et de renouveler nos souvenirs communs. Le<lb/>
                    mois d&#x2019;aout prochain, le 28, je completerai ma 84eme<lb/>
                    annee, et j&#x2019;ai trois (4) ans de moins que toin. Il<lb/>
                    vient de mourir dans cette province un homme de<lb/>
                    107 ans. Quelle perspective pour deux voyageurs<lb/>
                    qui ont passe leur 80eme annee!&#x201D;</p>
                <p>This joyous letter, expressing a longing for life,<lb/>
                    contrasts wonderfully with the mournful description<lb/>
                    of Dr. Lallemant&#x2019;s visit. In Monte Video (accord-<lb/>
                    ing to Mr. von Tschudi) it was believed that Bon-<lb/>
                    pland had died at San Borja on the 29th of May, but<lb/>
                    without further particulars. On the 18th of April Lal-<lb/>
                    lemant conversed with him at Santa Anna. On the<lb/>
                    19th of May his death was denied at Porto Alegre.<lb/>
                    There is, therefore, still hope that the younger of the<lb/>
                    two has not been the first summoned away. At<lb/>
                    such great distances uncertainty is often unfortunately<lb/>
                    long continued, as evidence the anxiety on account<lb/>
                    of Edward Vogel in Central Africa and Adolph<lb/>
                    Schlagintweit in Central Asia.</p>
                <lb/>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#right">
                            <hi rendition="#k">Alexander V. Humboldt.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 