<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p></p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text><front></front><body>
        <pb n="2" facs="#f0001" />
        
        <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Humboldt and American Slavery.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;The fol-<lb/>lowing, from a letter, addressed lately by Alexander von<lb/>Humboldt to
                    Julius Froebel, a German author of some dis-<lb/>tinction, and formerly a member
                    of the Parliament at<lb/>Frankfort, may not be without interest to some of
                    our<lb/>readers, partly from the question of slavery it alludes to,<lb/>and
                    partly from the noble image it exhibits of the undy-<lb/>ing earnestness of
                    purpose in that &#x201C;old man eloquent:&#x201D;&#x2014;<lb/>&#x201C;I should
                    like to live long enough yet to see your book<lb/><hi rendition="#i">On the
                        Political State of America,</hi> with which you are en-<lb/>gaged. May you
                    continue to brand that shameful leaning<lb/>to slavery, and that imposture about
                    introducing negroes<lb/>who are said to become free, and which is a means
                    to<lb/>encourage those negro hunts in the interior of Africa.<lb/>What horrors
                    one is obliged to witness, if one has the mis-<lb/>fortune of living from <choice>
                        <sic>1767</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">1789</corr>
                    </choice> to 1858. My book against<lb/>slavery has not been prohibited in
                    Madrid, yet in the<lb/>United States which you call &#x2018;the republic of
                    gentlemen,&#x2019;<lb/>it could only become saleable by the omission of all
                    that<lb/>concerns the sufferings of coloured people who, according<lb/>to my
                    political views, are fellow-men entitled to enjoy any<lb/>amount of freedom. I
                    lead an industrious life, chiefly at<lb/>night, being much worried by an ever
                    increasing and<lb/>mostly uninteresting correspondence. I exist
                    joylessly,<lb/>in my 89th year, since of so many things towards which I<lb/>have
                    striven ever since my early youth and with ever equal<lb/>warmth, so very little
                    has been fulfilled.&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>
        
    </text>
</TEI>