<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="3" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#b">Baron Humboldt on American Slavery.</hi><lb/><milestone
                        unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/> A PRIVATE LETTER TO MR. JULIUS
                        FROEBEL.<lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/></head>
                <p>Accept, my dear Froebel, if only a few<lb/>lines, my most cordial thanks for your
                    kind<lb/>letter and for the gift of an able work on<lb/>your personal
                    exporiences in America, in<lb/>which you have submited all classes
                    of<lb/>society to such a sagacious comparison. You<lb/>are here warmly cherished
                    in the memory<lb/>of all who are acquainted with your disting-<lb/>uished
                    scientific attainments, the nobleness<lb/>of your character, and the peculiar
                    features<lb/>of your mind. I have boasted of your en-<lb/>during friendship with
                    me in the new volume<lb/>of <hi rendition="#i">Kosmos,</hi> p. 541. I closed
                    this volume<lb/>just as I received the last part of your<lb/>travels and
                    researches, which had already<lb/>often been directed to me by friends,
                    and<lb/>aspecially by Varnhagen von Ense. I trust<lb/>I shall not <choice>
                        <sic>loose</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">lose</corr>
                    </choice> your favor on account of<lb/>my differing from you in regard to the
                    con-<lb/>nexion between the North Mexican high-<lb/>lands and the Rocky
                    Mountains. Our<lb/>controversy, as you will find when you<lb/>read attentively,
                    (p. 431&#x2014;440,) is almost<lb/>entirely one of words. I make a
                    distinction<lb/>butween a broad and continuous elevation,<lb/>and the
                    disconnceted chain rising above it,<lb/>often steeply and like battlements.
                    The<lb/>word mountain is very indefinite. In spite<lb/>of my heretical
                    disposition, however, your<lb/>ninth chapter, (p.501&#x2014;518,) gives me a
                    great<lb/>deal of instruction. You have explained<lb/>many points which were
                    only hinted at in<lb/>the &#x201C;Remarks.&#x201D; (Contribution to
                    Phys.<lb/>Geog., Smithson. Inst.)</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>But there are other things which come<lb/>nearer my heart than those elevations.
                    Your<lb/>next volume on the political future of Amer-<lb/>ica, would I, almost
                    the original Adam,<lb/>gladly live to see. Continue to brand the<lb/>shameful
                    devotion to slavery, the treacher-<lb/>ous importation of negroes, under the
                    pretence<lb/>of their becoming free&#x2014;a means to stimulate<lb/>the hunting
                    of negroes in the interior of<lb/>Africa. What atrocities have been
                    witness-<lb/>ed by one who has had the misfortune to<lb/>live from 1789 to 1858!
                    My book against<lb/>slavery (Political Essay on the Island of<lb/>Cuba) is not
                    prohibited in Madrid, but can-<lb/>not be purchased in the United States,
                    which<lb/>you call &#x201C;the republic of distinguished<lb/>people,&#x201D;
                    except with the omission of every-<lb/>thing that relates to the sufferings of
                    our<lb/>colored fellow-men, who according to my<lb/>political views, are
                    entitled to the enjoyment<lb/>of the same freedom with ourselves. Add<lb/>to
                    this, the anahema on other races of men,<lb/>forgetting that the most ancient
                    cultivation<lb/>of humanity, before that of the white Hel-<lb/>lenic race, in
                    Assyria, in Babylon, in the<lb/>valley of the Nile, in Iran, in China,
                    was<lb/>the work of colored men, though not woolly<lb/>haired.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>I still work hard, mostly in the night,<lb/>herause I am unmercifully tormented
                    with<lb/>a constantly increasing correspondence, for<lb/>the most part, of not
                    the slightest interest.<lb/>I live joyless in my 89th year, because of<lb/>the
                    much for which I have ardently striven<lb/>from my earliest youth, so little has
                    been<lb/>accomplished.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>With expressions of the friend-<lb/>ship of many years, which political
                    events<lb/>have never troubled,</p>
                <lb/>
                <closer>
                    <salute><hi rendition="#et">I am ever your illegible,<lb/><hi rendition="#k">Al.
                                Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute>
                </closer>
                <lb/>
                <dateline>Berlin, January 11, 1858.</dateline>
                <lb/>
</div>
    <div>
                <p><hi rendition="#i">New York Tribune.</hi></p>
            </div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
