<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
           
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#k">Humboldt and American Slavery.</hi></head>
                <p>&#x2014;The <choice>
                        <sic>follow <lb break="no"/>ing</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">follow-<lb break="no"/>ing</corr>
                    </choice>, from a letter addressed lately by Alexander von<lb/>Humboldt to Julius
                    Froebel, a German author of some dis-<lb/>tinction, and formerly a member of the
                    Parliament at<lb/>Frankfort, may not be without interest to some of
                    our<lb/>readers, partly from the question of slavery it alludes to,
                    and<lb/>partly from the noble image it exhibits of the undying ear-<lb/>nestness
                    of purpose in that &#x201C;old man eloquent:&#x201D;&#x2014;&#x201C;I
                    should<lb/>like to live long enough yet to see your book &#x2018;On the
                    Poli-<lb/>tical State of America,&#x2019; with which you are engaged.
                    May<lb/>you continue to brand that shameful leaning to slavery, and<lb/>that
                    imposture about introducing negroes who are said to<lb/>become free, and which
                    is a means to encourage those negro<lb/>hunts in the interior of Africa. What
                    horrors one is obliged<lb/>to witness, if one has the misfortune of living from <choice>
                        <sic>1767</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">1789</corr>
                    </choice> to<lb/>1858. My book against slavery has not been prohibited<lb/>in
                    Madrid, yet in the United States, which you call &#x2018;the<lb/>republic of
                    gentlemen,&#x2019; it could only become saleable by the<lb/>omission of all that
                    concerns the sufferings of coloured people<lb/>who, according to my political
                    views, are follow-men entitled<lb/>to enjoy any amount of freedom. I lead an
                    industrious life,<lb/>chiefly at night, being much worried by an
                    ever-increasing<lb/>and mostly uninteresting correspondence. I exist
                    joylessly,<lb/>in my 89th year, since of so many things towards which I<lb/>have
                    striven ever since my early youth, and with ever equal<lb/>warmth, so very
                    little has been fulfilled.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <back/>

    </text>
</TEI>
