<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/124004377">
                        <surname>Eibach</surname>
                        <forename>Joachim</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Nehrlich</surname>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1.2.0" when="2019-06-04" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
            </change>
            <change n="1.1.0" when="2018-11-30" who="#wernicke_nd">Validation. <note type="remarkRevision">Vorbereitung der Druckvorlage durch wernicke_nd abgeschlossen.</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="4" facs="#f0001" />
            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#i">BARON HUMBOLDT ON AMERICAN<lb break="yes"/>SLAVERY.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/>
                    <lb break="yes"/> A <hi rendition="#g">PRIVATE LETTER TO MR. JULIUS FROEBEL.</hi>
                    <lb break="yes"/>Communicated to <hi rendition="#k">The Tribune</hi> with Humboldt&#x2019;s content.</head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>Accept, my dear Froebel, if only in a few lines, my<lb break="yes"/>most cordial thanks for your kind letter and for the<lb break="yes"/>gift of an able work on your personal experiences in<lb break="yes"/>America, in which you have submitted all classes of<lb break="yes"/>society to such a sagacious comparison. You are<lb break="yes"/>here warmly cherished in the memory of all who are<lb break="yes"/>acquainted with your distinguished scientific attain-<lb break="yes"/>ments, the nobleness of your character, and the pe-<lb break="no"/>culiar features of your mind. I have boasted of your<lb break="yes"/>enduring friendship with me in the new volume of<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Kosmos,</hi> p. 541. I closed this volume just as I re-<lb break="no"/>ceived the first part of your travels and researches,<lb break="yes"/>which had already often been described to me by<lb break="yes"/>friends, and especially by Varnhagen von Ease. I<lb break="yes"/>trust I shall not lose your favor on account of my dif-<lb break="no"/>fering from you in regard to the connexion between the<lb break="yes"/>North Mexican highlands and the Rocky Mountains<lb break="yes"/>Our controversy, as you will find when you read at-<lb break="no"/>tentively (pp. 431-440), is almost entirely one of words<lb break="yes"/>I make a distinction between a broad, continuous ele-<lb break="no"/>vation, and the disconnected chain rising above it,<lb break="yes"/>often steeply and like battlements. The word moun-<lb break="no"/>tain is very indefinite. In spite of my heretical dispo-<lb break="no"/>sition, however, your ninth chapter, (pp. 504-518)<lb break="yes"/>gives me a great deal of instruction. You have ex-<lb break="no"/>plained many points which were only hinted at in the<lb break="yes"/>&#x201C;Remarks&#x201D; (Contributions to Phys. Geog., Smithson<lb break="yes"/>Inst). But there are other things which come nearer<lb break="yes"/>my heart than those elevations. Your next volume on<lb break="yes"/>the political future of Americs, would I, almost the<lb break="yes"/>original Adam, gladly live to see. Continue to brand the<lb break="yes"/>shameful devotion to Slavery, the treacherous importa-<lb break="no"/>tion of negroes, under the pretense of their becoming free<lb break="yes"/>&#x2014;a means to stimulate the hunting of negroes in the in<lb break="yes"/>terior of Africa. What atrocities have been witnessed<lb break="yes"/>by one who has had the misfortune to live from 1789<lb break="yes"/>to 1858. My book against Slavery (Political Essay on<lb break="yes"/>the Island of Cuba) is not prohibited in Madrid, but<lb break="yes"/>cannot be purchased in the United States, which you<lb break="yes"/>call &#x201C;The Republic of distinguished people,&#x201D; except<lb break="yes"/>with the omission of everything that relates to the suf-<lb break="no"/>ferings of our colored fellow-men, who, according to<lb break="yes"/>my political views, are entitled to the enjoyment of<lb break="yes"/>the same freedom with ourselves. Add to this, the<lb break="yes"/>anathema on other races of men, forgetting that the<lb break="yes"/>most ancient cultivation of humanity, before that of the<lb break="yes"/>white Hellenic race in Assytia, in Babylon, in the va-<lb break="no"/>ley of the Nile, in Iran, in China, was the work of<lb break="yes"/>colored men, though not woolly haired.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>I still work hard, mostly in the night, because I am<lb break="yes"/>unmercifully tormented with a constantly increasing<lb break="yes"/>correspondence, for the most part, of not the alightest<lb break="yes"/>interest. I live joyless in my 89th year, because of the<lb break="yes"/>much for which I have ardently striven from my early<lb break="yes"/>youth, so little has been accomplished.</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>With renewed expressions of the friendship of many<lb break="yes"/>years, which political evants have never troubled,<lb break="yes"/>
                    <hi rendition="#c">I am ever your illegible</hi>
                </p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <dateline>
                    <hi rendition="#i">Berlin,</hi> January 11, 1858.</dateline>
                <closer>
                    <salute>
                        <hi rendition="#et">AL HUMBOLDT</hi>
                    </salute>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>