<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#b">Baron Humboldt on American Slavery.</hi><lb/>[A private
                    Letter to Mr. Julius Froebel.]</head>
                <lb/>
                <p>Accept, my dear Froebel, if only a few lines,<lb/>my most cordial thanks for your
                    kind letter<lb/>and for the gift of an able work on your per-<lb/>sonal
                    experiences in America, in which you<lb/>have submitted all classes of society
                    to such a<lb/>sagacious comparison. You are here warmly<lb/>cherished in the
                    memory of all who are ac-<lb/>quainted with your distinguished
                    scientific<lb/>attainments, the nobleness of your character,<lb/>and the
                    peculiar features of your mind. I<lb/>have boasted of your enduring friendship
                    with<lb/>me in the new volume of <hi rendition="#i">Kosmos</hi>, p. 541.
                    I<lb/>closed this volume just as I received the first<lb/>part of your travels
                    and researches, which<lb/>had already often been directed to me by<lb/>friends,
                    and especially by Varnhagen von<lb/>Ense. I trust I shall not lose your favor
                    on<lb/>account <choice>
                        <sic>af</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">of</corr>
                    </choice> my differing from you in regard<lb/>to the connexion between North
                    Mexican<lb/>highlands and the Rocky Mountains. Our<lb/>controversy, as you will
                    find when you read<lb/>attentively, (pp. 431&#x2014;440,) is almost
                    entirely<lb/>one of words. I make a distinction between<lb/>a broad and
                    continuous elevation, and the dis-<lb/>connected chain rising above it, often
                    steeply<lb/>and like battlements. The word mountain<lb/>is very indefinite. In
                    spite of my heretical<lb/>disposition, however, your ninth chapter,<lb/>(pp.
                    504&#x2014;513), gives me a great deal of in-<lb/>struction. You have explained
                    many points<lb/>which were only hinted at in the
                    &#x201C;Remarks&#x201D;<lb/>(Contributions to Phys. Geog., Smithson,<lb/>Inst.)
                    But there are other things which come<lb/>nearer my heart than those elevations.
                    Your<lb/>next volume on the political future of Ame-<lb/>rica, would I, almost
                    the original Adam,<lb/>gladly live to see. Continue to brand the<lb/>shameful
                    devotion to slavery, the treacherous<lb/>importation of negroes, under the
                    pretence of<lb/><cb/>their becoming free&#x2014;a means to stimulate<lb/>the
                    hunting of negroes in the interior of Af-<lb/>rica. What atrocities have been
                    witnessed<lb/>by one who has the misfortune to live from<lb/>1789 to 1858! My
                    book against slavery (Po-<lb/>litical Essay on the Island of Cuba) is
                    not<lb/>prohibited in Madrid, but cannot be purchas-<lb/>ed in the United
                    States, which you call &#x201C;the<lb/>republic of distinguished people,&#x201D;
                    except with<lb/>the omission of everything that relates to the<lb/>sufferings of
                    our colored fellow-men, <choice>
                        <sic>who,<lb break="yes"/>who,</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">who,<lb break="yes"/></corr>
                    </choice> according to my political views, are<lb/>entitled to the enjoyment of
                    the same freedom<lb/>with ourselves. Add to this, the anathema<lb/>on other
                    races of men, forgetting that the<lb/>most ancient cultivation of humanity,
                    before<lb/>that of the white Hellenic race, in Assyria, in<lb/>Babylon, in the
                    valley of the Nile, in Iran<choice>
                        <sic>.</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">,</corr>
                    </choice><lb/>in China, was the work of colored men, tho&#x2019;<lb/>not woolly
                    haired.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>I still work hard, mostly in the night, be-<lb/>cause I am unmercifully tormented
                    with a<lb/>constantly increasing correspondence, for the<lb/>most part, of not
                    the slightest interest. I live<lb/>joyless in my 89th year, because of the
                    much<lb/>for which I have ardently striven from my<lb/>early youth, so little
                    has been accomplished</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>With renewed expressions of the friendship<lb/>of many years, which political
                    events have<lb/>never troubled,</p>
                <lb/>
                <closer>
                    <salute><hi rendition="#et">I am ever your illegible,<lb/><hi rendition="#k">Al.
                                Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute>
                </closer>
                <lb/>
                <dateline>Berlin, Jan. 11, &#x2019;58.</dateline>
                <lb/>
</div>
    <div>
                <p>[<hi rendition="#i">N. Y. Tribune.</hi></p>
            </div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
