<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title type="main">A Letter from Humboldt on the Death of Bonpland</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
          <surname>Humboldt</surname>
          <forename>Alexander</forename>
          <nameLink>von</nameLink>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <editor>
        <persName>Oliver Lubrich</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <note>Gesamtherausgeber</note>
      </editor>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
      <funder>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</funder>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Yvonne Wübben</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 1, Texte 1789–1799</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Rex Clark</persName>
        <persName>Sarah Bärtschi</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 2, Texte 1800–1809</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jobst Welge</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 3, Texte 1810–1819</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 4, Texte 1820–1829</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Bernhard Metz</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 5, Texte 1830–1839</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Jutta Müller-Tamm</persName>
        <persName>Michael Strobl</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 6, Texte 1840–1849</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Joachim Eibach</persName>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <resp>Herausgeber Band 7, Texte 1850–1859</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Apparatband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Johannes Görbert</persName>
        <resp>Redakteur Forschungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Corinna Fiedler</persName>
        <resp>Redakteurin Übersetzungsband</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Michael Hagner</persName>
        <persName>Eberhard Knobloch</persName>
        <persName>Alexander Košenina</persName>
        <persName>Hinrich C. Seeba</persName>
        <resp>Beirat</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Thomas Nehrlich</persName>
        <persName>Luca Querciagrossa</persName>
        <persName>Norbert D. Wernicke</persName>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>XML-Kodierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Frank Wiegand</persName>
        <resp>Programmierung</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
        <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
        <orgName role="edition">Alexander von Humboldt: Sämtliche Schriften (Aufsätze, Artikel, Essays). Berner Ausgabe digital</orgName>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3012 Bern</addrLine>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </address>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
      <date type="publication">2021-08-25T18:09:24</date>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.de">
          <p>Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).</p>
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno>
        <idno type="print">VII.159</idno>
        <idno type="basename">1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-12-neu</idno>
        <idno type="type">secondary</idno>
      </idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <notesStmt>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-01.xml" type="primary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-02-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-03-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-04-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-05.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-06-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-07-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-08-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-09-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-10-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-11-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-12-neu.xml" type="self"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-13-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-14-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-15-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-16-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
      <relatedItem target="1858-Neueste_Nachrichten_ueber-17-neu.xml" type="secondary"/>
    </notesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblFull>
        <titleStmt>
          <title type="main">A Letter from Humboldt on the Death of Bonpland</title>
          <author>
            <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
              <surname>Humboldt</surname>
              <forename>Alexander</forename>
              <nameLink>von</nameLink>
            </persName>
          </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher/>
          <date type="publication">1858</date>
          <pubPlace>New York City, New York</pubPlace>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <title type="full">in: &lt;i&gt;National Anti-Slavery Standard&lt;/i&gt; 19:3/949 (14. August 1858), [o. S.].</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </biblFull>
      <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
          <repository>unknown</repository>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
          <typeDesc>
            <p n="simple">Antiqua</p>
            <p n="full">Antiqua; Spaltensatz; Auszeichnung: Kursivierung, Kapitälchen.</p>
          </typeDesc>
        </physDesc>
      </msDesc>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">Englisch</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#i">A LETTER FROM HUMBOLDT ON THE DEATH<lb/>OF BONPLAND.</hi></head><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
    <p><hi rendition="#k">The</hi> Berlin correspondent of the Boston <hi rendition="#i">Journal</hi> sends<lb/>the following letter of Alexander Von Humboldt, on the<lb/>recent death of Bonpland. His senior by about four<lb/>years, Humboldt hoped he might not survive the warm-<lb/>est friend of his early years, but it seems to be the destiny<lb/>of this venerable man to follow all his friends to the grave,<lb/>and to remain himself the sole representative of the times<lb/>of his youth.</p><lb/><div n="2">
                    <head><hi rendition="#k">humboldt&#x2019;s letter.</hi></head>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>Conscious of the deep sympathy of numerous friends in<lb/>the sorrow
                        occasioned by the wide-spread report of the<lb/>death of my dear, noble
                        friend and fellow-traveller, Bon-<lb/>pland, I consider it my duty to give
                        at least a brief notice<lb/>of this event, for the particulars of which I am
                        indebted<lb/>to the kind services of Dr. Lallemant, author of an
                        im-<lb/>portant paper on the diseases of Europeans in the tropics.<lb/>This
                        talented gentleman, after leaving the Austrian royal<lb/>expedition in the
                        frigate Novara, in February of this<lb/>year, for the purpose of doing a
                        kindness to myself, made<lb/>the journey from Rio Janeiro to Rio Grande, and
                        thence<lb/>by way of Porto Alegro through the former Jesuit Mis-<lb/>sion to
                        San Borgia, under the erroneous impression that<lb/>Bonpland, who had gone
                        there in 1831, was still resident<lb/>at that place. I have received two
                        letters from Dr. Lal-<lb/>lemant, one dated at San Borgia on the 10th of
                        April,<lb/>the other written from the village of Umguaiana, after he<lb/>had
                        visited Bonpland at Santa Ana. An extended<lb/>abstract of these letters
                        having been sent to the editor of<lb/>the widely-read and interesting
                        botanical journal, <hi rendition="#i">The<lb/>Bonplandia,</hi> in Hanover,
                        the following briefer extracts<lb/>may here suffice.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>&#x201C;In San Borgia,&#x201D; writes Dr. Lallement, &#x201C;I lived
                        with<lb/>an intimate friend of Bonpland, the Vicar Gray, with<lb/>whom I
                        visited the garden of the botanist, so long culti-<lb/>vated with care, but
                        now lying waste and desolate. It<lb/>was near the close of the year 1857
                        that the Vicar last<lb/>received letters from Bonpland, since when
                        intelligence<lb/>had come of his severe illness. Letters of inquiry
                        still<lb/>remained unanswered, and, notwithstanding the short dis-<lb/>tance
                        between the places, the people of San Borgia were<lb/>uncertain whether I
                        should find <choice>
                            <sic>you</sic>
                            <corr type="editorial">your</corr>
                        </choice> fellow-travellers yet<lb/>in the land of the living. In 1853
                        Bonpland had left San<lb/>Borgia and taken up his residence upon his larger
                        plan-<lb/>tation of Santa Ana, where he had long occupied himself<lb/>in the
                        cultivation of orange trees. The residence of the<lb/>aged scholar in the
                        Estancia of Santa Ana consists of<lb/>two large buildings, mere clay walls
                        bound together by<lb/>bamboo sticks, and a few beams, and thatched with
                        straw.<lb/>These buildings have doors, but no windows, the light<lb/>being
                        admitted through the chinks between the bamboo<lb/>sticks. Despite the deep
                        furrows which an eventful life<lb/>had engraven in the beloved countenance,
                        his eye had not<lb/>grown dim nor lost any of its full-thoughted
                        vivacity.<lb/>But lively conversation, though started by
                        himself,<lb/>appeared to weary him much, and he suffered severely<lb/>from a
                        chronic affection of the bladder. The privations<lb/>he had so strangely
                        imposed upon himself are by no means<lb/>in consequence of poverty, or of
                        any necessity for absti-<lb/>nence, but of long custom, great self-control,
                        and charac-<lb/>teristic individuality. The government of Corrientes
                        has<lb/>presented to him an estate valued at 10,000 Spanish<lb/>piasters,
                        and he enjoys a French pension of 3,000 francs<lb/>a year. He has never made
                        the practice of medicine a<lb/>source of pecuniary profit to himself. Though
                        universally<lb/>revered, he loves the solitude, and especially avoids
                        all<lb/>persons who might offer him assistance or advice. His<lb/>scientific
                        ardor has not yet abated, and his collections<lb/>and manuscripts are
                        deposited in Corrientes, where he<lb/>has founded a national museum.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>&#x201C;On the following morning I found him visibly worse,<lb/>and sinking
                        away. The night had been a painful one. I<lb/>pressed him to tell me whether
                        I might not, in some way,<lb/>be of service to him. But I fared no better
                        than his<lb/>other friends&#x2014;he would accept of no assistance.
                        How<lb/>gladly would I have persuaded him to return once more<lb/>to
                        civilized society! But I, too, felt with him that his<lb/>time was past. He
                        belongs to the first half of the nine-<lb/>teenth century, not to the
                        second. I think that your<lb/>friend himself was moved when I took his
                        wasted hands<lb/>in mine with the pressure of farewell. For three
                        months<lb/>now his attendants have remarked his failing strength,<lb/>and
                        perhaps the old man had the same forboding as my-<lb/>self at parting, that
                        I might be the last ambassador of<lb/>European lineage who should penetrate
                        the depths of the<lb/>wilderness to offer him regard, love and thanks, in
                        the<lb/>name of that science which owes so much to his labors.<lb/>I mounted
                        my horse and rode northward through the<lb/>evergreen plains. No path showed
                        my way, no guide<lb/>disturbed me; I was alone with my sorrowful
                        thoughts<lb/>over the departing Bonpland.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>Yet how cheerful the last letter I received from Bon-<lb/>pland, bearing date
                        the 7th of June, 1857! &#x201C;I myself,&#x201D;<lb/>he writes,
                        &#x201C;shall bring all my collections and manu-<lb/>scripts to Paris, and
                        deposit them in the Museum. My<lb/>journey to France will be exceedingly
                        short. I shall re-<lb/>turn to my Santa Ana, where I lead a quiet and
                        happy<lb/>life. Here shall I die, and my sepulchre and my grave<lb/>shall be
                        underneath the shadow of the many trees I have<lb/>planted. Oh, how happy
                        were I, my dear Humboldt,<lb/>could we meet once more, and recall our common
                        expe-<lb/>riences! On the 28th of August next I shall be eighty-<lb
                            break="hyph-yes"/><lb/>four years old, and am yet four years younger
                        than you.<lb/>A man lately died in this vicinity who had attained
                        the<lb/>age of one hundred and seven. What a prospect for two<lb/>travellers
                        who have already stepped beyond the eightieth<lb/>year!&#x201D;</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>The cheering, almost life-desiring tone of this letter<lb/>contrasts
                        strangely with the melancholy representations<lb/>of Dr. Lallemant.
                        According to Herr von Tschudi the<lb/>report was credited in Montevideo on
                        the 29th of May,<lb/>that Bonpland had died at Borgia, the date of his
                        death<lb/>uncertain. Yet Dr. Lallemant had spoken with him on<lb/>the 18th
                        of April in Santa Ana, and on May 10 the re-<lb/>port of his death was
                        discredited at Porto Allegro. Thus<lb/>there yet remains ground for hope
                        that the younger is not<lb/>to be first called away. Such remoteness often
                        stretches<lb/>uncertainty to a painful duration; such the
                        solicitude<lb/>felt for Edward Vogel in Central Africa, and for
                        Adol-<lb/>phus Schlagintweit in Central Asia&#x2014;the
                        sorrowfully<lb/>missed!</p>
                    <closer>
                        <salute><hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#k">Alexander V.
                                Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute>
                    </closer>
                    <lb/>
                    <dateline>Berlin, July 12, 1858.</dateline>
                </div></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
