<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#b">Letter from Humboldt.</hi></head><lb/><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/><lb/>
<p>We copy from the Boston Courier the follow-<lb/>ing interesting letter from one of the men most<lb/>venerable in this or in any age, for learning,<lb/>Alexander von Humboldt, addressed to our dis-<lb/>tinguished townsman, George Ticknor, Esq.<lb/>He is now at the great age of eighty-nine.<lb/>&#x201C;Humboldt,&#x201D; says the Courier, &#x201C;perseveres in<lb/>the habits of his long life, and never, on any<lb/>occasion, employs another to write for him.<lb/>What is perhaps quite as remarkable, there are<lb/>no more signs of age in his manuscript than there<lb/>are in his style and his thoughts. The original<lb/>letter, of which the following is a translation, is<lb/>in a hand differing in no perceptible particular<lb/>from manuscripts written by him forty years<lb/>ago. He is enabled to go through his immense<lb/>labors by his habits of regular industry, and by<lb/>the fortunate peculiarity of his constitution,<lb/>which enables him to live with comparatively<lb/>little sleep. Most of his hard work is done at<lb/>night, when others are at rest.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p><hi rendition="#k">To George Ticknor, Esq.:</hi></p><lb/><p>My dear and excellent friend&#x2014;Bonds of friend-<lb/>ship which have their origin so far back in my family,<lb/>and the affection felt for you by my brother William<lb/>von Humboldt, when you lived in Germany, as a<lb/>young man, seem to impose on me the very pleas-<lb/>ant duty of giving you some sign of life&#x2014;that is to<lb/>say, a renewed proof of my attachment to you and<lb/>my interest in your country, and a brief account of<lb/>my labors.</p><lb/><p>My physical strength declines, but it declines slowly.<lb/>My steps are more uncertain in their
                    direction, owing<lb/>to a feebleness (a relaxing) of the ligaments of
                    the<lb/>knees; but I can remain standing for an hour with-<lb/>out being
                    fatigued. I continue to work chiefly at<lb/>night, being unrelentingly
                    persecuted by my corres-<lb/>pondence, which increases the more as one
                    becomes<lb/>an object of public curiosity. What is called literary<lb/>celebrity
                    is especially the result of a long endurance<lb/>of life, (une longue patience
                    de vivre.) This kind of<lb/>eminence increases, therefore, in proportion as
                    im-<lb/>becility becomes more manifest. I am never really<lb/>ill, but often
                    incommoded, as is to be expected at the<lb/>age of eighty-nine.</p><lb/><p>Since we were only two persons in the American<lb/>expedition, (the unfortunate Carlos de Montufar,<note place="foot" n="*">Carlos de Montufar was a young man passionately at-<lb/>tached to science, and accompanied Humboldt and Bon-<lb/>pland from Quito, where they arrived in January, 1802,<lb/>through all their travels in Peru and Mexico, till their em-<lb/>barkation at Vera Cruz in the spring of 1804.</note><lb/>son of the Marquis de Selvalegra, of Quito, fell a<lb/>victim to his love for the liberty of his country), it is<lb/>somewhat remarkable that we should both have<lb/>reached so advanced an age. Bonpland, still much<lb/>occupied with scientific labors, even cherishing the<lb/>hope of visiting Europe again, and of bringing in<lb/>person back to Paris his rich and beautiful collections<lb/>in botany and geology, is eighty-five years old, and<lb/>enjoys greater strength than I do.</p><lb/><p>I have just published in Germany the 4th volume<lb/>of Cosmos, and they are now printing the 5th
                    vol-<lb/>ume, which completes that work so imprudently be-<lb/>gun and so
                    favorably received by the public. Gen.<lb/>Sabine writes me that the English
                    translation is fin-<lb/>ished and will appear immediately. The same
                    news<lb/>comes to me from France, from M. Galuzzi, who has<lb/>been passing the
                    winter in the south, at Cannes.</p><lb/><p>The great and beautiful work of Agassiz (the first<lb/>two volumes) reached me only a few days since. It<lb/>will produce a great effect by the breadth of its gen-<lb/>eral views and by the extreme sagacity of its special<lb/>embryological observations. I never believed that<lb/>this illustrious man, who is no less a man of a con-<lb/>stant and beautiful nature, would accept the offers<lb/>nobly made him in Paris. I was sure that gratitude<lb/>would bind him to a new country where he finds a<lb/>field so immense for his researches and great means<lb/>of assistance. I hope he may be inclined, together<lb/>with his great anatomical and physiological labors<lb/>among the inferior organisms, to give us also the spe-<lb/>cific icthyology of the numerous basins of the &#x201C;Far<lb/>West,&#x201D; beginning with the <hi rendition="#i">holy</hi> empire of the Mor-<lb/>mons.</p><lb/><p>Science has lately met with an immense loss here by<lb/>the unexpected death of the greatest anatomist of our<lb/>country,&#x2014;Prof. Johann Müller.<note place="foot" n="&#x2020;">Johann Muller, who died a few months ago, was only 57<lb/>years old.</note> This loss is as great<lb/>for science, as was for art the death of the immortal<lb/>sculptor, Rauch.<note place="foot" n="&#x2021;">Rauch, who died last autumn, was above eighty, and<lb/>seemed, until shortly before his death, destined to many<lb/>years of health. When Humboldt kept his 87th birthday,<lb/>the 14th September, 1856, with his niece, the admirable<lb/>Madame de Bulow, at Tegel, the favorite residence of her<lb/>father and of his brother William, he desired to have only<lb/>one other person of the party, and that was Rauch, un-<lb/>doubtedly then the first of living sculptors. It is most<lb/>agreeable to know that a fine bust of Humboldt by Rauch<lb/>is either already in the collection of a gentleman at Wash-<lb/>ington, or will soon be there.</note> The universality of his zoological<lb/>knowledge in the inferior organizations, placed Jo-<lb/>hann Müller near Cuvier, having a great preëminence<lb/>in the delicacy of his anatomical and physiological<lb/>work. He made long and painful voyages at his own<lb/>expense on the shores of the Mediterranean and in<lb/>the northern seas. It is scarcely two years since he<lb/>came near perishing by shipwreck on the coast of<lb/>Norway. He sustained himself by swimming for<lb/>more than half an hour, and considered himself quite<lb/>lost when he was wonderfully rescued. I lose in him<lb/>a friend who was very dear to me. He was a man of<lb/>great talent, and at the same time of a noble charac-<lb/>ter. He was admirable for the elevation and inde-<lb/>pendence of his opinions. By making enormous sac-<lb/>rifices he was able to form a choice library, not only<lb/>of anatomy, physiology and zoology, but one that ex-<lb/>tended over all the physical sciences. It consists of<lb/>more than three thousand volumes, well bound, and<lb/>of as many more volumes containing dissertations, so<lb/>difficult to collect. Mr Müller spent nearly 800 tha-<lb/>lers a year (600 dollars) for binding alone. It would<lb/>be sad to see a collection dispersed and broken up,<lb/>which was made with so much care. Since duplicates<lb/>are dreaded in Europe, I cannot help fearing lest this<lb/>fine collection should cross the great Atlantic <hi rendition="#i">river.</hi><lb/>I have almost the air of exciting your appetite when<lb/>I thus present myself before you as a citizen of the<lb/>world, while the <hi rendition="#i">church</hi> journal of Vienna calls me,<lb/>in capital letters, a naturalist assassin of souls, &#x201C;Seel-<lb/>en-mörder.&#x201D;</p><lb/><p>Accept, I beg you, my dear and respected triend,<lb/>the renewal of the high and affectionate consideration<lb/>which, for so many years, I have given to your talents<lb/>and to your character.</p><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">A. v. <hi rendition="#k">Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute></closer><lb/><dateline>Berlin, 9 May, 1858.</dateline><lb/>
    </div>
    <div><p>Since so many benevolent persons, colored as well<lb/>as white, in the United States, take an
                    interest in<lb/>me, it would be agreeable to me, my dear friend, if<lb/>this
                    letter, translated into English by you, could be<lb/><hi rendition="#i"
                        >printed,</hi> without omitting what relates to our mutual<lb/>friendship.
                    If you think it necessary, you can add<lb/>that I have myself begged of you this
                    publication,<lb/>because I leave unanswered so many letters that
                    are<lb/>addressed to me.</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
