<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb n="2" facs="#f0001" />

    <div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Humboldt and American Slavery.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;The<lb/>following, from a letter, addressed lately by Alexander<lb/>von Humboldt to
                    Julius Froebel, a German author of<lb/>some distinction, and formerly a member
                    of the Parlia-<lb/>ment at Frankfort, may not be without interest to some<lb/>of
                    our readers, partly from the question of slavery it<lb/>alludes to, and partly
                    from the noble image it exhi-<lb/>bits of the undying earnestness of purpose in
                    that<lb/>&#x201C;old man eloquent&#x201D;: &#x2014; &#x201C;I should like to
                    live<lb/>long enough yet to see your book &#x2018;On the Poli-<lb/>tical State
                    of America,&#x201D; with which you are engaged.<lb/>May you continue to brand
                    that shameful leaning to sla-<lb/>very, and that imposture about introducing
                    negroes who<lb/>are said to become free, and which is a means to
                    encourage<lb/>those negro hunts in the interior of Africa. What hor-<lb/>rors
                    one is obliged to witness, if one has the misfortune<lb/>of living from <choice>
                        <sic>1767</sic>
                        <corr type="editorial">1789</corr>
                    </choice> to 1858. My book against slavery has not<lb/>been prohibited in
                    Madrid, yet in the United States which<lb/>you call &#x2018;the republic of
                    gentlemen,&#x2019; it could only become<lb/>saleable by the omission of all that
                    concerns the sufferings of<lb/>coloured people who, according to my political
                    views, are<lb/>fellow-men entitled to enjoy any amount of freedom.<lb/>I lead an
                    industrious life, chiefly at night, being much<lb/>worried by an ever increasing
                    and mostly uninteresting<lb/>correspondence. I exist joylessly, in my
                    eighty-ninth<lb/>year, since of so many things towards which I have<lb/>striven
                    ever since my early youth and with ever equal<lb/>warmth, so very little has
                    been fulfilled.&#x201D;</p></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
