<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>

<pb n="433" facs="#f0001" />

<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">Humboldt in Hebrew.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;A curious Hebrew pub-<lb/>lication has just issued from the Berlin press, a
                    bio-<lb/>graphy of Alexander von Humboldt, written in the<lb/>ancient tongue of
                    Moses, and destined to extend<lb/>the knowledge of the life and scientific
                    labors of this<lb/>celebrated man in the wide circle of the Russo-Polish<lb/>and
                    Asiatic Jews. The full title is, &#x201C;<hi rendition="#i">Alexander
                        von<lb/>Humboldt:</hi> a Biographical Sketch. Dedicated to<lb/>the Nestor of
                    Wisdom on his 88th birthday. By<lb/>S. Slominski.&#x201D; The author is a
                    Russian Israelite,<lb/>who some years ago invented a very clever
                    calculat-<lb/>ing machine, and drew upon himself, at that time,<lb/>by his
                    mathematical knowledge, the attention of the<lb/>celebrated astronomers Herren
                    Bessel and Jacoby,<lb/>of Konigsberg. These gave him letters of
                    recom-<lb/>mendation to Alexander von Humboldt, in Berlin,<lb/>who, with his
                    accustomed benevolence, effectually<lb/>assisted the poor Jewish scholar. The
                    first half,<lb/>consisting of 100 pages of strong, correct, and flow-<lb/>ing
                    Hebrew, is devoted to the life and general re-<lb/>view of Humboldt&#x2019;s
                    works; whilst the second forms<lb/>a sketch of the <hi rendition="#i"
                        >Kosmos,</hi> and in which the author<lb/>speaks of the double stars, and of
                    earthly magnet-<lb/>ism, of volcanoes, and of the South-American Flora,<lb/>in
                    such a way as to lead one to imagine that it<lb/>would be impossible to find
                    expressions worthy of<lb/>clothing the &#x201C;ideas of this great Western
                    sage.&#x201D;<lb/>The author, who had transmitted the manuscript of<lb/>his work
                    to Humboldt as a tribute of homage on his<lb/>88th birthday, received from him
                    the following cha-<lb/>racteristic reply:</p><lb/><p>&#x201C;Honored Herr Slominski: I owe you a thou-<lb/>sand apologies for so long delaying my thanks for<lb/>the honor you have been pleased to confer upon<lb/>me. The unquiet condition in which I live, in this<lb/>age of social and political excitement, can scarcely<lb/>plead my excuse. A recommendation from two re-<lb/>nowned, and to me personally so dear friends as<lb/>Bessel and Jacoby, leaves a lasting impression. A<lb/>stranger, alas! to Hebrew literature, but from my<lb/>earliest youth intimately connected with the noblest<lb/>of your co-religionists, and a warm and persevering<lb/>advocate for their numerous and unjustly withheld<lb/>rights, I am not indifferent to the honor you have<lb/>conferred upon me. The testimony of a learned<lb/>Oriental linguist, the celebrated and highly learned<lb/>Dr. Michael Sacks, (one of the Rabbis of the Berlin<lb/>Jewish congregation,) leads me to prize still more<lb/>highly this distinction. It is almost a comfort to him<lb/>who is the object of the praises not to be acquainted<lb/>with the original language. After next Tuesday I<lb/>shall again reside during a few weeks in Berlin, and<lb/>at that time, if you, Herr Slominski, have not yet<lb/>returned to Warsaw, I shall be pleased to see you<lb/>daily in Berlin between one and two o&#x2019;clock, and<lb/>personally renew the expressions of my high esteem<lb/>for your noble, prompt, and learned efforts.</p><lb/><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et">&#x201C;Yours, with high esteem,<lb/>&#x201C;<hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt.</hi>&#x201D;</hi></salute></closer></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
