<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/basisformat.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">DUMMYHEADER</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="https://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                        <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <editor corresp="#avh_in_bern">
                    <persName>
                        <surname/>
                        <forename/>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt xml:id="baertschi_s">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bärtschi</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">Verantwortliche Textkonstitution</note>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="wernicke_nd">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wernicke</surname>
                        <forename>Norbert D.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <orgName ref="http://www.humboldt.unibe.ch"/>
                    <resp>
                        <note type="remarkResponsibility">XML Bearbeiter</note>
                        <ref target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1014897157"/>
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Vollständige digitalisierte Ausgabe.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher xml:id="avh_in_bern">
                    <orgName role="hostingInstitution">Universität Bern</orgName>
                    <orgName role="project">Alexander von Humboldt in Bern</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Institut für Germanistik, Universität Bern, Länggassstrasse 49, 3000 Bern 9</addrLine>
                        <country>Switzerland</country>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bern</pubPlace>
                <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">
                        <p>Dieses Werk ist gemeinfrei.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>
                    <idno type="DTAID">[ID innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="DTADirName">[Verzeichnisname innerhalb des DTA-Korpus]</idno>
                    <idno type="URN">[URN der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLWeb">[URL der DTA-Onlinepublikation des Werkes]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLXML">[URL zum XML/TEI-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLHTML">[URL zum HTML-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLText">[URL zum Text-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLCAB">[URL zum Download der CAB-Fassung der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="URLTCF">[URL zum TCF-Download der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                    <idno type="PIDCMDI">[Handle-PID zum CMDI-Metadatensatz der DTA-Publikation]</idno>
                </idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>[Kurztitel]</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">[Titel des Originalartikels]</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">
                                <surname>Humboldt</surname>
                                <forename>Alexander</forename>
                                <nameLink>von</nameLink>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition n="1"/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>
                            <name>[Verlag/Druckerei]</name>
                        </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Publikationsort]</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">[Publikationsdatum]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">[Zeitschriftenname]</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">[Bandnummer]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pages">[Seitenangabe]</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <physDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <p>[Fraktur/Antiqua und weitere typographische Angaben]</p>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change n="1.1.0" when="2019-06-05" who="#wernicke_nd">Format. <note type="remarkRevision">Umformatierung als Vorbereitung zur Onlineausgabe.</note>
                </change>
                <change n="1.0.0" when="0001-01-01" who="#avh_in_bern">Text constitution. <note type="remarkRevision">Bereitstellung der ersten vollständigen Textfassung anhand der Transkriptionen.</note>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Verfahren der Texterfassung: manuell (doppelt erfasst).</p>
            <p>Bogensignaturen: gekennzeichnet; Druckfehler: dokumentiert; fremdsprachliches Material: keine Angabe; Geminations-/Abkürzungsstriche: keine Angabe; Hervorhebungen (Antiqua, Sperrschrift, Kursive etc.): wie Vorlage; i/j in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; I/J in Fraktur: wie Vorlage; Kolumnentitel: gekennzeichnet; Kustoden: gekennzeichnet; langes s (ſ): wie Vorlage; Normalisierungen: keine; rundes r (&amp;#xa75b;): keine Angabe; Seitenumbrüche markiert: ja; Silbentrennung: wie Vorlage; u/v bzw. U/V: wie Vorlage; Vokale mit übergest. e: wie Vorlage; Vollständigkeit: vollständig erfasst; Zeichensetzung: wie Vorlage; Zeilenumbrüche markiert: ja; </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="deu">Deutsch</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="506" facs="#f0001"/>
            <p>A correspondent of the <hi rendition="#i">Daily Telegraph</hi> states that<lb break="yes"/>a curious Hebrew publication has just issued from the<lb break="yes"/>Berlin press, a biography of Alexander von Hum-<lb break="no" />boldt, writen in the ancient tongue of Moses, and<lb break="yes"/>destined to extend the knowledge of the life and<lb break="yes"/>scientific labours of this celebrated man in the wide<lb break="yes"/>circle of the Russo-Polish and Asiatic Jews. The<lb break="yes"/>full title is &#x201C;Alexander von Humboldt: a Bio-<lb break="no"/>graphical Sketch. Dedicated to the Nestor of Wis-<lb break="no"/>dom on his 88th birthday. By S. Slominski.&#x201D; The<lb break="yes"/>author is a Russian Israelite, who some years ago<lb break="yes"/>invented a very clever calculating machine, and<lb break="yes"/>drew upon himself, at that time, by his mathematical<lb break="yes"/>knowledge, the attention of the celebrated astrono-<lb break="no"/>mers Herren Bessel and Jacoby, of Königsberg.<lb break="yes"/>These gave him letters of recommendation to Alex-<lb break="no" />ander von Humboldt, in Berlin, who, with his ac-<lb break="no"/>customed benevolence, effectually assisted the poor<lb break="yes"/>Jewish scholar. The latter by this means had an<lb break="yes"/>opportunity of making himself more fully acquainted<lb break="yes"/>with the works of his patron, and thus arose within<lb break="yes"/>him the wish (as he expresses it in his preface) to com-<lb break="no"/>municate to his Hebrew co-religionists in Sclavonian<lb break="yes"/>and Eastern lands the progress of those branches of<lb break="yes" />science so intimately connected with the life of Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt, and desiring at the same time to erect a memo-<lb break="no"/>rial (as the Hebrew title expresses it) to the justice<lb break="yes"/>and sympathy which the latter has constantly mani-<lb break="no"/>fested towards Judaism and the Jews. The first half,<lb break="yes"/>consisting of 100 pages of strong, correct, and flowing<lb break="yes"/>Hebrew, is devoted to the life and general review<lb break="yes" />of Humboldt&#x2019;s works; whilst the second forms<lb break="yes"/>a sketch of the &#x201C;Kosmos,&#x201D; and in which the<lb break="yes"/>author speaks of the double stars, and of earthly<lb break="yes"/>magnetism, of volcanoes, and of the South American<lb break="yes"/>Flora, in such a way as to lead one to imagine that<lb break="yes"/>it would be impossible to find expressions worthy of<lb break="yes"/>clothing the &#x201C;ideas of this great Western sage.&#x201D; The<lb break="yes"/>author, who had transmitted the manuscript of his<lb break="yes"/>work to Humboldt as a tribute of homage on his<lb break="yes"/>88th birthday, received from him the following cha-<lb break="no"/>racteristic reply:</p>
            <lb break="yes"/>
            <div n="2">
                <opener>
                    <salute>Honoured Herr Slominski</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>&#x2014;I owe you a thousand apolo-<lb break="no"/>logies for so long delaying my thanks for the honour you<lb break="yes"/>have been pleased to confer upon me. The unquiet con-<lb break="no"/>dition in which I live, in this age of social and political<lb break="yes"/>excitement, can scarcely plead my excuse. A recommenda-<lb break="no"/>tion from two renowned, and to me personally so dear<lb break="yes"/>friends as Bessel and Jacoby, leaves a lasting impression.<lb break="yes"/>A stranger, alas! to Hebrew literature, but from my earliest<lb break="yes"/>youth intimately connected with the noblest of your co-<lb break="no"/>religionists, and a warm and persevering advocate for their<lb break="yes"/>numerous and unjustly withheld rights, I am not indif-<lb break="no"/>ferent to the honour you have conferred upon me. The<lb break="yes"/>testimony of a learned oriental linguist, the celebrated and<lb break="yes"/>highly learned Dr. Michael Sacks (one of the Rabbis of<lb break="yes"/>the Berlin Jewish congregation), leads me to prize still<lb break="yes"/>more highly this distinction. It is almost a comfort to<lb break="yes"/>him who is the object of the praises not to be acquainted<lb break="yes"/>with the original language. After next Tuesday I shall<lb break="yes"/>again reside during a few weeks in Berlin, and at that time,<lb break="yes"/>if you, Herr Slominski, have not yet returned to Warsaw, I<lb break="yes"/>shall be pleased to see you daily in Berlin between one and<lb break="yes"/>two o&#x2019;clock, and personally renew the expressions of my<lb break="yes"/>high esteem for your noble, prompt, and learned efforts.&#x2014;<lb break="yes"/>Yours, with high esteem,</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rendition="#et">
                            <hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI> 