<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="2" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div>
            <p>&#x261E;The Berlin papers received by the City of<lb/>Baltimore, contain the
                following very curious and<lb/>characteristic card from <hi rendition="#k">Baron
                    Humboldt:</hi></p>
                <dateline><hi rendition="#et">Berlin, March 15,
                    1859.</hi></dateline><lb/>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>&#x201C;Suffering beneath the pressure of a still
                increas-<lb/>ing correspondence, amounting to between sixteen<lb/>hundred and two
                thousand communications per<lb/>annum, and embracing letters, printed
                pamphlets<lb/>on matters with which I am wholly unacquainted,<lb/>manuscripts
                concerning which my opinion is desir-<lb/>ed, projects for emigration and
                colonizing, the send-<lb/>ing of models, machines and natural curiosities,
                re-<lb/>quests of contributions and collections of auto-<lb/>graphs, offers to take
                charge of my domestic con-<lb/>cerns, to cheer and enliven me, &amp;c., &amp;c., I
                must<lb/>again publicly urge all persons having my welfare<lb/>at heart to exert
                their influence in my behalf, that<lb/>individuals in both continents may no longer
                busy <lb/>themselves with my person and make of my house<lb/>an intelligence office;
                and that I be allowed, in the<lb/>declining state of my physical and mental
                powers,<lb/>to enjoy some rest and leisure to attend to my du-<lb/>ties. May this
                cry for relief, which I utter with<lb/>much reluctance and after reflection, not
                meet an<lb/>unfriendly interpretation!<lb/><hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#k"
                    >&#x201C;Alexander Von Humboldt.&#x201D;</hi></hi></p>
            <lb/>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back/>
        
    </text>
</TEI>
