<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">A Letter from Humboldt, Praying Re-<lb/>lease From the Letter Writers.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;The<lb/>venerable Humboldt thus appeals for mercy<lb/>to a class which was never yet
                    known to<lb/>spare either sex or age:</p><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#k">Berlin,</hi> March 15, 1859.</hi></dateline><lb/>
                    </div>
                    <div><p>Suffering beneath the pressure of a still<lb/>increasing correspondence, amounting to<lb/>between
                    sixteen hundred and two thousand<lb/>communications per annum, and
                    embrac-<lb/>ing letters, printed pamphlets on matters<lb/>which I am wholly
                    unacquainted, manu-<lb/>scripts concerning which my opinion is de-<lb/>sired,
                    projects for emigration and coloniz-<lb/>ing, the sending of models, machines
                    and<lb/>natural curiosities, request of contributions<lb/>to collections of
                    autographs, efforts to take<lb/>charge of my domestic concerns, to cheer<lb/>and
                    enliven me, &#x0026;c., &#x0026;c., I must again<lb/>publicly urge all persons
                    having my wel-<lb/>fare at heart to exert their influence in my<lb/>behalf, that
                    individuals on both continents<lb/>may no longer busy themselves with
                    my<lb/>person and make of my house an intelli-<lb/>gence office; and that I be
                    allowed, in the<lb/>declining state of my physical and mental<lb/>powers, to
                    enjoy some rest and leisure to<lb/>attend to my duties. May this cry for
                    re-<lb/>lief, which I utter with much reluctance<lb/>and after reflection, not
                    meet an unfriend-<lb/>ly interpretation!</p><lb/><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#k">Alexander von Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute></closer></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
