<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat_ohne_header.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <pb n="8" facs="#f0001"/>
            <div n="1">
                <head>
                    <hi rendition="#k">A Cry of Distress from Alexander Hum-<lb break="no"/>boldt.</hi>
                </head>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <p>&#x2014;Berlin papers that came by the City of<lb break="yes"/>Baltimore, contain
                    the following card from<lb break="yes"/>Alexander Humboldt:</p>
                <lb break="yes"/>
                <div n="2">
                    <dateline>
                        <hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#k">Berlin,</hi> March 15, 1859.</hi>
                    </dateline>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <p> Suffering beneath the pressure of a still in-<lb break="no"/> creasing
                        correspondence, amounting to between<lb break="yes"/> sixteen hundred and
                        two thousand communica-<lb break="no"/> tions per annum, and embracing
                        letters, printed<lb break="yes"/> pamphlets on matters with which I am
                            wholly<lb break="yes"/> unacquainted, manuscripts concerning which<lb
                            break="yes"/> my opinion is desired, projects for emigration<lb
                            break="yes"/> and colonising, the sending of models, machines<lb
                            break="yes"/> and natural curiosities, requests of contribu-<lb
                            break="no"/> tions to collections of autographs, offers to take<lb
                            break="yes"/> charge of my domestic concerns, to cheers and<lb
                            break="yes"/> enliven me, &#x0026;c., &#x0026;c., I must again publicly
                            urge<lb break="yes"/> all persons having my welfare at heart to exert<lb
                            break="yes"/> their influence in my behalf, that individuals in<lb
                            break="yes"/> both continents may no longer busy themselves<lb
                            break="yes"/> with my person and make of my house an intel-<lb
                            break="no"/> ligence office; and that I be allowed, in the de-<lb
                            break="no"/> clining state of my physical and mental powers,<lb
                            break="yes"/> to enjoy some rest and leisure to attend to my<lb
                            break="yes"/> duties. May this cry for relief, which I utter<lb
                            break="yes"/> with much reluctance and after reflection, not<lb
                            break="yes"/> meet an unfriendly interpretation!</p>
                    <lb break="yes"/>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rendition="#et">
                                <hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von Humboldt.</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
            </div>
            <lb break="yes"/>
        </body>
        <back/>

    </text>
</TEI>
