<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>DUMMYHEADER</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p></p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>DUMMYHEADER zur Validitätsprüfung</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><front></front><body>
<pb facs="#f0001" />
<div n="1"><head><hi rendition="#k">A Cry of Distress from Alexander Hum-<lb/>boldt.</hi></head><p>&#x2014;Berlin papers received by the City of<lb/>Baltimore contain the following card from Alex-<lb/>ander Humboldt:</p><lb/><dateline><hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#k">Berlin,</hi> March 15, 1859.</hi></dateline><lb/>
                </div>
                <div><p>Suffering beneath the pressure of a still in-<lb/>creasing correspondence, amounting to
                    between<lb/>sixteen hundred and two thousand communica-<lb/>tions per annum, and
                    embracing letters, printed<lb/>pamphlets on matters with which I am
                    wholly<lb/>unacquainted, manuscripts concerning which my<lb/>opinion is desired,
    <choice><sic>projeets</sic><corr type="editorial">projects</corr></choice> for emigration and<lb/>colonizing, the sending of models, machines
                    and<lb/>natural curiosities, requests of contributions to<lb/>collections of
    autographs, offers to take charge<lb/>of my domestic <choice><sic>concers</sic><corr type="editorial">concerns</corr></choice>, to cheer and
                    enliven me,<lb/>&#x0026;c., &#x0026;c., I must again publicly urge all
                    persons<lb/>having my welfare at heart to exert their influ-<lb/>ence in my
                    behalf, that individuals in both con-<lb/>tinents may no longer busy themselves
                    with my<lb/>person and make of my house an intelligence of-<lb/>fice; and that I
                    be allowed, in the declining state<lb/>of my physical powers, to enjoy some rest
                    and<lb/>leisure to attend to my duties. May this cry for<lb/>relief, which I
                    utter with reluctance and after<lb/>much reflection, not meet and unfriendly
                    inter-<lb/>pretation.</p><closer><salute><hi rendition="#et"><hi rendition="#k">Alexander Von Humboldt.</hi></hi></salute></closer></div><lb/></body><back></back>

</text>
</TEI>
